<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE Debate SYSTEM "../Debate.dtd"[]>
<Debate DocTitle="Seanad Debate" Day="Thu" Date="29" Month="Nov" Year="1984" Vol="106" No="4" DateIrish="Déardaoin, 29 Samhain 1984" DateEnglish="Thursday, 29 November 1984" House="S" CommitteeEng="" CommitteeIr="" SubNameEng="" cnum="375">
  <MainHeading Type="Prelude" LHead="" RHead="">
    <Title>
    </Title>
    <P>
      <Col N="375" /> Chuaigh an Cathaoirleach i gceannas ar 10.30 a.m.</P>
    <P Just="Center">
      <i>Paidir.</i>
    </P>
    <P Just="Center">
      <i>Prayer.</i>
    </P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Business" RHead="of Seanad">
    <Title>Business of Seanad.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickJReynolds" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I have notice from Senator Alexis FitzGerald that, on the motion for the Adjournment of the House today, he proposes to raise the following matter:</P>
      <P>The serious public concern arising from primitive lead polluting industries and other emissions from industrial processes and commercial or domestic installations in Dublin city.</P>
      <P>I regard the matter as suitable for discussion on the Adjournment, and it will be taken at the conclusion of business.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Order of" RHead="Business">
    <Title>Order of Business.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDooge" hpid="Professor Dooge Professor Dooge">
      <NameTxt>Professor Dooge</NameTxt>
      <P>When it was decided to meet for a second day this week it was in order to deal with certain non-urgent motions that were before us.  It now transpires that there are three matters of urgency before the Seanad which it is hoped can be cleared today.  It is proposed to take items Nos. 1 to 5 and possibly item No. 6, though it is most unlikely to be reached, and I understand the members of the Marriage Breakdown Committee wish that item No. 13 to be taken today.  If so, I will not object to its inclusion in the Order of Business.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="376" /> In regard to item No. 1, this is an urgent matter.  It is the question of the protection of back wages of employees when a firm becomes insolvent.  I want to say &mdash; and I am sure I speak on behalf of all Members here &mdash; that if it is urgent today it has been urgent for some time. I believe both parties in Dáil Éireann have treated this House with scant respect in the manner in which they have given themselves as much leisure as they like in regard to this matter and then despatched it for cursory examination by this House.  The Bill was circulated on 21 May last.  My information is that the initial delay was largely attributable to the Minister and his Department and that these were the initial delays.  That was compounded, when the Minister was ready to go ahead, by the fact that there was a change in spokesman in the chief Opposition Party.  There was further delay because the new spokesman wished to have time to settle into his brief.  When ultimately it was becoming clear that this was legislation that should be enacted without delay the Dáil still took its time. The Dáil took two separate weeks in order to discuss the Committee Stage of this Bill before passing it over to us.</P>
    <P>I resent this House being treated in this manner, but I do not think we should allow this to blind us to the fact that this is an urgent measure.  If, in fact, by delaying this Bill we could make the Members of Dáil Éireann suffer then there might be some point in delaying it. But by delaying this Bill all we can do is make certain unfortunate people faced with redundancy through the insolvency of their firms suffer and I do not think we should do so.</P>
    <P>My suggestion is that we should take the Second Stage of this Bill immediately but that we should then proceed to deal with Nos. 3 and 4 which we commenced yesterday and perhaps then take item No. 13 and that we should return to item No. 1 at 3 o'clock to take Committee Stage. This will give a couple of hours for consideration of the Second Stage debate and the preparation of amendments.  It is hoped to complete all Stages by the normal Adjournment time of 5 o'clock <Col N="377" /> and then take the Early Signature Motion.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MickLanigan" hpid="Mr. Lanigan Mr. Lanigan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lanigan</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not think we should get involved in any role playing here this morning.  The continuation of the argument that has been very well put by Senator Dooge would not do any good to this House but I want to say that we concur completely with his assessment of the Dáil's part in the delaying of this Bill. Even though we do not agree that any Bill should be taken or forced to be taken on a particular day, because of the very serious implications of this Bill, we will go along with what has been suggested by the Leader of the House.  The intention is that the Second Stage will be taken, presumably until lunch time&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDooge" hpid="Professor Dooge Professor Dooge">
      <NameTxt>Professor Dooge</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes, we should have a break from 1 o'clock to 2 o'clock.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryRobinson" hpid="Mrs. Robinson Mrs. Robinson">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Robinson</NameTxt>
      <P>I feel it necessary to correct a possible impression that might have been drawn from what the Leader of the House said in relation to the motion proposing to extend the time for the Committee on Marriage Breakdown to complete its work.  He used the expression that members of the Committee on Marriage Breakdown wished to have this motion taken.  I want to assure the House that many members of the Committee on Marriage Breakdown profoundly wish that we did not have to have this motion taken.  Perhaps when the motion is taken we can explain the difficult circumstances in which we find ourselves.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDooge" hpid="Professor Dooge Professor Dooge">
      <NameTxt>Professor Dooge</NameTxt>
      <P>I just want to thank Senator Lanigan for his support and for his forbearance.  It is always much more difficult for an Opposition to agree to take all stages of a Bill in one day than for the Government, for they get their way much more quickly.  I am grateful to him for the attitude he has taken in regard to the Bill.</P>
      <P>Order of Business agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Protection of Employees (Employers'" RHead="Insolvency) Bill, 1984: Second Stage">
    <Title>Protection of Employees (Employers' Insolvency) Bill, 1984: Second Stage.</Title>
    <P>
      <Col N="378" /> Question proposed: &ldquo;That the Bill be now read a Second Time.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="RuairiQuinn" hpid="Minister for Labour (Mr. Quinn) Ruairí Quinn">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Labour (Mr. Quinn)</NameTxt>
      <P>May I begin by expressing my appreciation to this House for the co-operation they have extended to me in relation to putting through, in a way that I know is not terribly acceptable in the normal course of events, a piece of legislation of this nature or indeed any form of legislation. I do want to put on the record of the House my personal appreciation and I hope, in effect, the appreciation of all of the workers who will benefit from this legislation when it becomes law and when it comes into operation.</P>
      <P>This legislation is being introduced for the purpose of implementing an EC directive but also in the interests of social justice for workers who lose their employment and are left without due rights because of their employers' insolvency.</P>
      <P>Ever since it became publicly known that this legislation was being prepared, I have been receiving very many letters and representations from, and on behalf of, workers whose employers have become insolvent.  These individual representations have underlined for me the extent of the loss being suffered by the workers affected by employers' insolvency and of the difficulties and hardship caused for them and their families.  To be made redundant and have to face unemployment for any reason is a traumatic experience, but to be left without wages for the final weeks of employment and other due entitlements as well makes the situation even more intolerable.  Even in cases where some assets are available for part-payment of workers' entitlements, under existing legislation, because of the operation of the legal processes involved, these payments can be delayed for months or years until bankruptcy or liquidation proceedings can be finalised.  It is the purpose of this legislation to provide that workers' entitlements are paid in full and are paid quickly.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>A view sometimes heard implies that <Col N="379" /> worker protection legislation can itself be in large measure responsible for closures, insolvencies and unemployment.  I wish to express my total disagreement with this view.  Nor do I accept that the body of worker protection legislation which has been built up in recent years should now be jettisoned because of general economic and employment difficulties. On the contrary, it is in such difficult times that such legislation is most needed.  That is not to say, however, that the legislation in this area should not be closely looked at and reviewed.  It has developed over the years in an <i>ad hoc</i> fashion and experience of its operation has shown that in various aspects it needs to be improved.  The work of reviewing all worker protection legislation is an extensive task but I intend to have this undertaken as expeditiously as possible given the resources available to my Department.  The purpose of these reviews will be to look not only at the individual statutes but also at the overall implications of the whole <i>corpus</i> of worker legislation to see what changes can be made to make the law more effective and fairer for employers, for workers and in the general public interest.</P>
    <P>The measures proposed in this Bill are particularly necessary in current economic conditions in which, unfortunately, many businesses have ceased to function, many because of insolvency.  But even in an improved economic situation this type of legislation will be needed as some companies will continue to get into financial difficulties leaving their workers not only without jobs but also without their wages and other entitlements.</P>
    <P>The Members of the House will be aware of the existence of an EC directive which contains measures to protect workers in insolvency situations.  This Bill will give effect to the requirements of that directive and in a number of respects goes beyond these requirements.  Among the payments to be covered are wages, arrears of statutory minimum wages, holiday pay, payments on foot of company sick pay schemes and entitlements arising under various worker protection <Col N="380" /> legislation as well as unpaid contributions to company pension schemes.  Workers have been entitled to claim for the benefits set out in the EC directive as from 22 October 1983 and I am providing in the Bill for the payment of claims relating to pay in insolvency cases arising on or after that date.  Strong representations have been made to me seeking to have an earlier implementation date but this is not feasible for a number of reasons.  As with all worker protection legislation, it is unfortunately the case that regardless of what implementing date is chosen some workers will lose out.  In this case, the most objective date which can be chosen is 22 October 1983, the date on which the EC directive came into force.</P>
    <P>Detailed provisions are set in section 1 to cover the various types of insolvency situations which can arise.  This section also outlines the criteria to be used to determine when an employer will be regarded as being insolvent.  As the date of the insolvency will be of vital importance for the calculation of amounts due, the Bill specifies, in section 4, the date on which an employer will be regarded as having become insolvent.  Section 4 will also enable me to specify by regulations the circumstances in which employers who are of a class or description specified in the regulations are to be taken to have become insolvent.  This provision will enable me to cover situations which might arise where no formal winding up or bankruptcy proceedings are initiated.</P>
    <P>The EC directive to which I referred requires the setting up of a fund &mdash; referred to in the directive as a Guarantee Institution &mdash; which will guarantee the payment of employees' outstanding claims relating to pay and this requirement will be met by the proposed extension of the existing Redundancy Fund.  In my view, this is the simplest and most satisfactory way of doing so.  The extended fund will be called the Redundancy and Employers' Insolvency Fund and this retitling is provided for in section 2 of the Bill.</P>
    <P>The Redundancy Fund is financed by <Col N="381" /> way of contributions from employers, including the Government in their role as employers, and this will continue to be the case with the extended fund.  Because of the already high level of expenditure from the fund in respect of redundancy payments, it was necessary to raise the employers' contribution rate in this year's budget.  The increase in the redundancy contribution from .01 per cent to .4 per cent contains an element of .02 per cent to cover anticipated expenditure arising from the measures provided for in this Bill.  This .02 per cent element of the contribution should guarantee an income of approximately £1 million in a full year. It is difficult to predict what the likely level of expenditure will be but the best estimates which we have been able to make suggest that an income of this level should be sufficient.</P>
    <P>I have power under the Redundancy Payments Acts to alter the level of contribution should this be necessary.  While some information is available as to the number of companies which are the subject of formal insolvency proceedings during particular periods, little information is available in regard to the number of employees involved or the extent and nature of their claims.  Account must also be taken of the informal type of insolvency situations about which figures are not available.  Given that workers are unlikely to be in a position or willing to continue to work for long periods without remuneration, I consider that in the majority of cases, claims in respect of ordinary pay should not be substantial. The experience in the United Kingdom, where a similar fund has been in operation since 1976, has been that the major items of expenditure for the fund are minimum notice and holiday pay and I expect that the situation will be somewhat similar here.  The average period in the UK was approximately for two weeks of arrears of pay.</P>
    <P>Section 3 provides that the Bill will apply to those in employment which is insurable for all benefits under the Social Welfare Acts.  The effect of this will be that the benefits provided for in the Bill will be available to those who are covered <Col N="382" /> by the Redundancy Payments Acts.  At present these Acts apply only to persons who work 20 hours or more a week for the same employer, although employers pay contributions to the Redundancy Fund in respect of people who work 18 hours a week and over.  18 hours is also the general limit for eligibility under the Social Welfare Acts.</P>
    <P>When the EC directive was being drawn up, it was foreseen that the position of those who were outside the social insurance system could give rise to difficulties in the context of the Guarantee Institution from which payments would be made.  For this reason the directive provides for the exclusion in the case of this country of persons who work for fewer than 18 hours per week for one or more employers and who do not derive their basic means of subsistence from the pay for this work.</P>
    <P>Arising from the changing employment patterns and the growth in part-time working and jobsharing in this country and throughout the EC the question of part-time workers <i>vis-à-vis</i> worker protection legislation in general is being examined.  Senators may be aware of the discussions that are in progress on a draft EC directive to cover a whole area of part-time working.</P>
    <P>The basic approach in this Bill has been to cover employees whose employers pay a contribution to the Redundancy Fund on their behalf.  I am, however, taking power in section 11 to enable me to extend the protection being provided to cover other categories of employees should I consider this to be desirable at a later stage.  I have also provided in the Bill, in sections 12 and 13, for the reduction of the thresholds operated in a number of other pieces of worker protection legislation to 18 hours.  These changes involve a reduction from 20 hours in the case of the Redundancy Payments Acts and from 21 hours in the Minimum Notice and Terms of Employment Act, 1973 and the Unfair Dismissals Act, 1977.  These changes will bring about a desirable harmonisation in the eligibility thresholds for protection under the various Acts and are also in line with <Col N="383" /> present trends in European Community labour practice.</P>
    <P>I already referred to the fact that section 4 will give me power to deal with situations where no formal insolvency proceedings have been initiated.  The Bill envisages a major role for receivers, liquidators and similar officers who are referred to as &ldquo;relevant officers&rdquo;, in cases where formal insolvencies have occurred. It is necessary for me to have power to appoint a person to perform corresponding functions in situations in which formal insolvency proceedings have not been instituted but where workers are still left without their due payments, for example where employers have gone away or merely ceased trading and effectively insolvent.  The same power may be needed in exceptional cases of formal insolvencies where, for example, a liquidator has withdrawn or failed to discharge his or her obligations under the Bill. The power is contained in section 5.</P>
    <P>The duties envisaged for relevant officers under the Bill mainly involve arranging for the completion of various forms and certifying that amounts claimed are due and remain unpaid.  The various forms to be used are referred to in the Bill as prescribed forms and will be set out in regulations to be made under section 16 when the Bill has been enacted.</P>
    <P>Sections 6 and 7 outline the payments which will be made from the fund.  While the EC directive refers specifically to outstanding claims relating to pay, it allows member states freedom to adopt their own definition of this term.  I am providing in the Bill for the payment of claims in respect of the following: wages, arrears of statutory minimum wages, holiday pay, payments on foot of company sick pay schemes, entitlements under the Minimum Notice and Terms of Employment Act, 1973, and Anti-Discrimination (Pay) Act, 1974, the Employment Equality Act, 1977, the Unfair Dismissals Act, 1977, civil court awards in respect of wages, sick pay, holiday pay or unfair dismissal and also outstanding contributions to company pension schemes.  A <Col N="384" /> limit of eight weeks will operate in the case of wages, holiday pay and amounts due under company sick pay schemes. This is fully in line with the terms of the EC directive.  The directive also allows member states the option of setting a ceiling on the weekly amounts which will be paid.</P>
    <P>As the measures provided for in the Bill are related, in many ways, to the provisions of the Redundancy Payments Acts, I propose to limit the amount of payments, where these are related to wages, to the amount provided for in the Redundancy Payments Acts.  At present this limit is £211.54 a week.  The existence of this limit will not affect lower-paid workers.  I will, of course, be keeping the limit under review &mdash; the Bill gives me power to revise it and also to vary the period of weeks in respect of which payments will be made.  A limit of 12 months' contributions will operate in respect of unpaid contributions to company pension schemes.  As far as workers' contributions are concerned, payment will be made only in respect of amounts deducted from pay but not actually paid into the scheme. The payments which I am providing for in the Bill go further than the requirements of the EC directive in a number of areas &mdash; for example, payments relating to company sick pay schemes, unfair dismissals and pension contributions.</P>
    <P>In addition to providing for the protection of workers' claims relating to pay, the EC directive also imposes an obligation on member states to ensure that the necessary measures are taken to protect workers interests under company pension schemes.  Because of the wide variety of pension arrangements which operate, it was apparent when the directive was being discussed that movement in this area would take some considerable time. The directive does not require that pensions be paid from the Guarantee Institution and it also provides that the institution need not be liable for outstanding contributions to company pension schemes.  I am very concerned that workers' interests under company pension schemes be protected but I have also to take account of the possible cost <Col N="385" /> implications of any measures which I introduce.  In this Bill, I am providing for the payment from the fund of outstanding contributions whether payable by an employer on his own behalf or where deductions have been made for a worker's pay but not paid into the scheme, subject to a limit of 12 months contributions in each case.</P>
    <P>I have given very detailed consideration to the whole question of company pension schemes and in particular to the best means of protecting employees' entitlements under such schemes.  I am satisfied that the best way to proceed is in the context of the proposals for a national income-related pension scheme which are at present under consideration by my colleague, the Minister for Social Welfare.  It is only prudent to have the position examined in full rather than making some hasty provision in this Bill which could have very wide reaching cost consequences for the Redundancy Fund, and which might not afford full protection for workers' rights.  The overall security of company pension schemes is one of the matters which will be considered in connection with the proposals for a national scheme.</P>
    <P>The Bill provides in section 9 that persons who have applied for payments in respect of wages, sick pay, holiday pay or arrears of pension contributions may, within a period of six weeks beginning on the day on which the decision on the application was communicated to them, or if that is not reasonably practicable, within such further period as the Employment Appeals Tribunal considers reasonable, present a complaint to the tribunal that no payment has been made or that any payment made was less than the amount which should have been paid. This appeals procedure will not extend to entitlements under the Minimum Notice and Terms of Employment Act, the Unfair Dismissals Act, the Anti-Discrimination (Pay) Act, the Employment Equality Act, court awards, or in respect of arrears of statutory minimum wages under the Industrial Relations Acts.</P>
    <P>In relation to the pension schemes area <Col N="386" /> there has been some debate in recent weeks because of the unfortunate circumstances that arose in respect of a particular company in the midlands.  I hope we will be in a position to move quickly to ensure that workers who have pension schemes in their companies make sure that the trustees who represent their interests are properly informed and indeed that they have a say in the appointment of such trustees because of the difficulties that have arisen in those cases.</P>
    <P>The question of pensions is much broader and much larger than the measures we are dealing with in this legislation. The thrust of the legislation is to ensure that workers who are entitled to payments out of the proceeds of a company in respect of wages they have already earned &mdash; which is money that is needed for day-to-day purposes &mdash; do not have to wait in line with the other creditors for that essential form of income but can be paid as quickly as is administratively practicable from a fund that would be funded entirely by the employers contribution and that they can take their money from that fund in the normal way.  Then I, as Minister for Labour, would step into their shoes in the queue and would wait for the liquidator to wind up the company and if there were sufficient assets available to cover, in whole or in part, the wages that were the legal due of the worker in the first place, those wages would come back into the fund to pay other workers who might be affected.</P>
    <P>The essence of the entire Bill is to avoid what is manifestly an injustice where workers who have earned wages but who have not been able to collect them have to wait in some cases over a year before they can get basic income.  This fund will avoid that injustice and will avoid it in the most efficient, effective administrative system that seems appropriate to us.</P>
    <Speaker pid="BrianJHillery" hpid="Professor Hillery Professor Hillery">
      <NameTxt>Professor Hillery</NameTxt>
      <P>I readily acknowledge the urgency of this Bill but I join with the Leader of the House in deploring the scant treatment that we are permitted to give it today.  There is no way we <Col N="387" /> can give it the detailed treatment that it deserves.</P>
      <P>Now that the Minister for Labour is here &mdash; a former Member of this House &mdash; I hope he will use his influence where possible to ensure that in future we will have the amount of time we deserve to discuss Bills.</P>
      <P>I welcome this Bill which protects wages and other matters where employers become insolvent.  The sudden unemployment caused by insolvencies causes trauma among the people affected and their families and valuable skills gained over a lifetime can be lost.  The Bill represents a modest further step in worker protection.  My remarks will be of a general nature and some of the subsequent speakers on this side of the House will pinpoint specifics as they have affected enterprises in their own constituencies.</P>
      <P>I would like to indicate three areas where the State can help in the case of potential insolvencies.  First of all, by ensuring prompt collection of PAYE and PRSI by the Revenue Commissioners.  I will develop that point later.  Secondly, by ensuring adequate controls by Government Departments over State-sponsored bodies and, thirdly, by the correction of an anomaly in the social welfare regulations which cropped up recently in the discussion on the Ombudsman Bill.  One often hears about the power of trade unions and how they protect their members rights.  It is true that trade unions have come a long way since the &ldquo;Strumpet City&rdquo; days, but the vulnerability of employees even if unionised is all too evident in insolvencies and liquidations. Many companies have gone to the wall in the private sector especially in the recent past but the liquidation of Irish Shipping &mdash; up to 1982 a profit-making State company &mdash; has highlighted in a dramatic way the vulnerability of employees in the public sector.  Many employees in Irish Shipping have up to 30 years' service and I was glad to hear the Minister imply that he is looking into that case and the rights they will have.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>As regards Irish Shipping the statutory redundancy entitlements on the face of <Col N="388" /> it are abysmally small when compared with the lifetime of employment that has been invested by the workers in that company. Incidentally &mdash; this is only a passing reference &mdash; I remain to be convinced that liquidation was the correct decision in that case. As a member of the Joint Committee on State-Sponsored Bodies I feel that there were other options, especially a more realistic renegotiation of the chartering arrangements.  I hope that the presence of the shipowners in Dublin at the present time will serve as a means to pull something out of the fire.</P>
    <P>Employers normally wish to keep their companies in business.  We do have fly-by-nights but, generally speaking, employers are as interested as their employees in keeping their enterprises going.  But they can fail, for a variety of reasons, including bad management. Prevention is better than cure.  Unpaid taxes, like PAYE and PRSI, can serve as a very significant warning signal that companies are in financial difficulties.  A few weeks ago when discussing the report of the Joint Committee on State-Sponsored Bodies and the State-owned hotel group, OIE, the Minister indicated, in response to a suggestion I made, that the social welfare regulations would be examined with a view to changing them so that employees would be entitled to know if the taxes already deducted from their pay had been paid over to the Revenue Commissioners.  The significance of that point is that if such a change were implemented it would establish whether companies had complied with their legal obligations in paying over the taxes to the Revenue Commissioners.  That in turn would act as an indicator of their financial health.</P>
    <P>On the question of social welfare regulations, recently we were discussing an amendment Bill in respect of the office of the Ombudsman.  This arose out of something that the Ombudsman himself highlighted in the course of his work where a serious anomaly in the contributory old age pension scheme has become a source of complaint to him.  Perhaps it is worth recapitulating what Mr. Mills <Col N="389" /> said.  His view was that old age pensioners had found that on reaching the age of 66 they had not the required average stamps each year to meet the social welfare regulations. Changes in these regulations, as we know, between 1953 and 1974 meant, in effect, that contributors who had paid more social welfare contributions are being treated less favourably than those who had paid fewer contributions over a shorter period.  I realise this is not a functional matter for the Minister for Labour but I would take this opportunity to ask him to use his influence with his Cabinet colleagues, the Ministers for Social Welfare and Finance, to correct this inequity.  This is one way the State can help in protecting workers' rights in respect of the delicate area of pensions.</P>
    <P>Some companies go into liquidation or become insolvent because the management do not take effective action soon enough.  As I have said, the non-payment of taxes almost invariably is a warning sign.  It certainly was a warning sign in the case of OIE, as the Minister is aware, where there was £2 million unpaid taxes. If remedial action had been taken early enough the State, and therefore the taxpayer, would have had to pay less.  Therefore, prompt collection by the Revenue Commissioners can actually assist companies to face up to their difficulties on time.  I was a member of an earlier Joint Committee on State-Sponsored Bodies which reported on Fóir Teoranta in 1981. In the course of evidence Fóir Teoranta told the committee that:</P>
    <P>The fact is that we continue to receive requests for assistance at very short notice.  The reason for this would seem to be psychological.  Many businesses experiencing financial difficulty will go to endless trouble to conceal their plight from creditors, bankers and financial advisers in the expectation that things will come right.  The result very often is that irreparable damage has taken place before we become aware of the company's problems.</P>
    <P>Employees can, and have suffered through insolvencies and liquidations because quick remedial action has not been forthcoming from management. <Col N="390" /> This raises the question, of course, of disclosure of information to employees which itself is an area to which the Minister is devoting attention.  In that context I was glad to hear him refer to the examination of trustees and the degree of information that would be supplied to employees in respect of pension schemes, because that is one of the main criticisms we have of this Bill.</P>
    <P>If employees were told the score about their companies, they would be in a position to respond to save their companies and in so doing to save their jobs.  At least they would get the opportunity to &ldquo;have a go&rdquo; to remedy the situation. Furthermore, there is a lot of untapped expertise in workforces which, especially in times of difficulty could be used to prevent insolvencies.  In that context, I was on a radio programme recently discussing Irish Shipping.  One of the employees of Irish Shipping was on the same programme.  He specifically made the point to me that there is a pool of expertise in Irish Shipping which was untapped and, if you like, unasked for, by the management in that organisation. Irish Shipping is not unique in this respect.</P>
    <Speaker pid="RuairiQuinn" hpid="Mr. Quinn Mr. Quinn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Quinn</NameTxt>
      <P>If we had worker directors on the board of Irish Shipping it might have been an interesting alternative scenario to the one that has developed tragically.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BrianJHillery" hpid="Professor Hillery Professor Hillery">
      <NameTxt>Professor Hillery</NameTxt>
      <P>I agree, and in that context perhaps the Minister when replying might indicate when he is going to extend the list of designated bodies.  I know it is the Minister's intention to add certain bodies, but I look forward to our debate on that when it comes because it will afford an opportunity to review the experience of worker directors to date and perhaps to make suggestions for the improvement of that scheme.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>As far as State companies are concerned the liquidation of Irish Shipping has raised a number of important issues. Here again the State can help.  While the primary reason for the liquidation of Irish Shipping was a serious error of judgment by management, the case raised the ever-present problem of control of State-sponsored <Col N="391" /> bodies.  These bodies should be allowed control over their day-to-day affairs.  I would be the first to defend that right.  I worked for seven years in State-sponsored bodies before I joined the staff of UCD and I am all for day-to-day control by the bodies themselves.  But when it comes to substantial policy decisions, and in particular to substantial investment decisions, then I suggest it is a prerequisite that departmental approval be forthcoming.  That approval was not sought in the case of the Russell Court Hotel in Belfast &mdash; which is an OIE hotel. The Department were not informed. Also, the approval as we now know, was not sought in the case of Irish Shipping.</P>
    <P>The Minister for Communications said recently that the days of the free ride are over for State-sponsored bodies.  In so far as the bottomless pit syndrome infected the minds of the managements and boards of these organisations, I am glad that that is so.  The State-sponsored bodies sector will never be the same again after the liquidation of Irish Shipping. Some benefits may well accrue from this. But I put it to the Minister, and through him to his Ministerial colleagues, that a thorough review of the control mechanisms in State-sponsored bodies should be carried out as a matter of urgency so that a traumatic and damaging event such as the liquidation of Irish Shipping could be avoided in the case of other troubled State-sponsored bodies.</P>
    <P>Clearly there is a need for a thorough review and change of the control relationship in relation to substantial policy and investment decisions.  The onus is on the Government to get their side of the House in order in that regard.  Equally, of course, individual Ministers have the responsibility to ensure that the boards fully meet their trustee responsibilities. If these boards do not perform as they are expected to perform, they should be fired.</P>
    <P>As matters stand, the Bill will take effect from 22 October 1983.  However, the year 1983 was a particularly black <Col N="392" /> year for insolvencies.  We are again pleading with the Minister to make the effective date that of the final winding-up rather than the date the receiver or liquidator was appointed.  There are companies which went into liquidation or receivership during 1983 and prior to 1983 but the winding-up has not yet taken place.  In these cases, we would urge that the effective date should be the actual date of winding-up.  Admittedly, this would cost money.  The money has to be found somewhere as is also admitted. However, given that the Redundancy Fund as revealed by the Minister in the Dáil, is in a healthy condition, at a figure of £12 million, we feel that the renamed fund could bear the additional cost to cover more than those who will be covered from 22 October 1983.  Many of the people who would benefit under our proposal are still unemployed and suffering a lot of hardship.  Any additional State protection they can get will be welcomed. We intend to press this matter on Committee Stage.  It is not a question of seeking an open-ended retrospective period but rather to make the Bill effective for the exceptionally black year of 1983.</P>
    <P>In the other House the Minister calculated that the cost of covering employees affected for the ten months period from 1 January 1983 up to October 1983 would mean an additional £800,000 to £850,000. I know it is a question of judgment and of costs, but I suggest that against the background of hardship of these unemployed and the fact that the Minister as of now at any rate intends to apply this Bill from the latest possible date under the European Community Directive, namely 22 October 1983, an additional cost of less than £1 million can be borne by a healthy Redundancy Fund of £12 million.</P>
    <P>One of the most disturbing features of insolvencies occurs where former employees not alone lose their entitlement under contributory pension schemes but in some cases do not even get their contributions refunded.  I know the Minister is alert to this problem, and he has indicated his thinking up to this moment.  It is clearly very unfair that they <Col N="393" /> should lose their pension rights on the one hand and for those who are not already on pension to lose their contributions as well as losing their eventual pensions. It is traumatic enought to lose one's job but to lose one's pension entitlement on top of that is even worse.  We have a duty to defend people in the 60-plus category who are made redundant before they reach pensionable age and in particular those who are already pensioners who lose their pensions in insolvencies. Again, there is clearly expenditure involved, and money has come from some quarter, and I know that this is a predictable line that the Minister will take and it is understandable.  However, the generalised talk by the Minister about a national income pension related scheme at some future date is entirely inadequate in the present circumstances.  There is, of course, provision in the Bill which fulfils the minimum requirement in the European Community Directive for the payments from the fund of unpaid pension contributions for a period of 12 months. This is a step in the right direction, but it goes nowhere near the type of protection that is required.  Again, we will be pursuing the issue of pension schemes and pension entitlements at Committee Stage.</P>
    <P>A Chathaoirligh, we hope to raise a number of points at Committee Stage, but I am happy to join in the welcome for this Bill.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JimHiggins" hpid="Mr. J. Higgins Mr. J. Higgins">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J. Higgins</NameTxt>
      <P>I also would like to stitch into the record my general welcome for the principle of the Bill.  It is a good Bill.  It is a protective measure, and one of the immediate benefits I see from the point of view of the workers is that hopefully at last it will end the situation that where insolvency does arise you have the degrading and demeaning exercise of employees who have just been paid, hawking their cheques around from Billy to Jack in order to have them cashed, on top of the trauma of the knowledge that their jobs are gone.  I welcome the measure because of the protection that it affords workers who become redundant when companies go into liquidation, and <Col N="394" /> it is a measure not before its time, as has been acknowledged from all sides of the House and by the Minister, particularly coming in the wake of a litany of very well-publicised debacles and liquidations, insolvencies, etc.  As the Minister said in his speech, too often companies just disappear overnight.  Too often companies have gone into liquidation and are continuing to go into liquidation, where there are no assets or insufficient assets to meet the requirements and demands therefrom.  Too often in the past &mdash; and in the past employees were the important people in this type of exercise &mdash; people have had to take their place in the pecking order and very often have had to wait for a period of a year before they got their entitlements.</P>
      <P>It is a comprehensive measure.  It is a very thorough measure.  As the Minister said, it covers all possible contingencies such as wages, holiday pay, sick pay, minimum notice, etc.  The Bill is also extremely welcome in that it clarifies insolvency, when exactly the date of insolvency occurs and what is meant precisely by insolvency.  Very often, as the Minister said in his Second Stage speech, there is no formal winding-up process, and the Bill covers this.  The funding and operation of the Bill are based on the Redundancy and Employers' Insolvency Fund of £12 million.  The fund is contributed to totally by the employers.</P>
      <P>There has been some criticism that the Bill applies only to employees who work 18 hours or more.  I think it is a particularly fair norm.  It is a fair average particularly when one takes into consideration that it is the average which applies for a social welfare entitlement and that it effectively effects a reduction on the pervious 20 hour norm.  The maximum amount of £211.54 per week is fair and equitable by any standards.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The operative date of the Bill, 22 October 1983, has been criticised in the other House and in this House.  In the other House, as in this House, there has been a case made for winding-ups which have not in fact concluded in 1983 or as of now to be included but from the Minister's viewpoint I think the safest and fairest <Col N="395" /> way is to adhere as closely as possible to the dates and specifics set down in EC Directive 89-87.  Pensions, again, are covered partially.  We all share the apprehensions of Senator Hillery in this regard.  We do welcome the Minister's assurance that his colleague, the Minister for Health and Social Welfare, Deputy Desmond, is working on an integrated income-related pension scheme and pension fund and pension plan.  We look forward hopefully to the early rather than the later introduction of this.  The measure therefore is to be welcomed.  It should certainly eliminate the panic which invariably ensues in the case of such insolvencies. It does give quite a substantial degree of protection, and one aspect in particular that I welcome is that the Minister keeps unto himself the necessary flexibility to adjust and upgrade and revise the limits and the guidelines from time to time.  I therefore wish again to record my endorsement of the measure.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MartinODonoghue" hpid="Dr. O'Donoghue Dr. O'Donoghue">
      <NameTxt>Dr. O'Donoghue</NameTxt>
      <P>I would like to make a brief contribution, if I may.  I do not wish to cover the ground that has already been dealt with.  I, too, welcome the Bill. It is right that we should try to adapt legislation to our changing circumstances, and this whole area of the legal position of workers who find themselves suddenly without a job through insolvency undoubtedly creates not only many problems and anomalies but also genuine hardship, especially for lower-paid workers. It is right that we should be setting out to try to deal with that situation.  I cannot resist making, if I may, the sort of political point that whatever about the other merits of the date, 22 October, at least to me it seems appropriate in the sense that it is the date of the EC Directive and as far as I can judge, the only reason why we are getting the legislation now is because there is an EC Directive. I wonder how long we might have had to wait if there had not been the EC Directive.  Would we have to wait another one year, five years, ten years? We are being appropriate and being honest in saying in fact that the EC have, if you like, twisted our arm in order to <Col N="396" /> bring about this measure to deal with the situation.  It is right that we should recognise this because at times, when we become more and more accustomed to the criticisms of the EC and to long debates and so forth about the ways in which national interests are fought out in the EC context, it is no harm to remind ourselves that the Community has also been a very positive force for much good. Many of the measures and many of the laws, some of which are even touched on elsewhere in the Minister's speech, and many of the changes in the labour area had their origins in various EC proposals and directives.  It is no harm to recognise that fact.  That is one of the points I wish to stitch into the record, that we should try to see in a more balanced way the activities associated with our membership of the EC.</P>
      <P>Coming closer to home, I must say I am also glad to see a measure of this kind coming in if only because it will get rid of some of the very ill-informed comments which are made when any liquidation does arise.  I will refrain from going into situations but I am sure many people read comments in one of our leading newspapers in the last week or so on the Irish Shipping liquidation and deploring the circumstances in which some of the crews found themselves.  We all recognise the hardship which is caused there and it is right that we should now be getting new legislation which can deal with that type of situation but what was wrong was to read editorials in leading newspapers inviting people to break the law.  That is what they were suggesting &mdash; why did the company not, in its dying hours, make arrangements to pay people, for instance, to pay the shipyard in France who were carrying out repairs, apparently not realising that had they done so, they could all be up on charges of fraud under the existing company law.</P>
      <P>Whether or not we like the laws that exist we have to recognise that laws, when they are there have to be operated. The correct approach is to change laws which we feel are no longer appropriate to the circumstances.  That is the essential point I wanted to make.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="397" /> The Minister's speech touches on another aspect of the general question of how and where we need reform of the law, namely the problems created through inadequate supervision or management of pension funds, perhaps by trustees who are not sufficiently familiar either with the legal situations of companies or with their current trading circumstances. The sooner we can press on with reforms in that area the better.</P>
    <P>That reference to pension funds involves another Department, the Department of Social Welfare.  If we get on to the kind of reform which the Minister has spoken of and the type of reform I have mentioned because of the provisions of the prevailing company law you will have to bring in a third Department, the Department of Industry, Trade, Commerce and Tourism, because that is the Department dealing with company legislation. I shudder at the prospect of three Departments trying to get together with their respective legal advisers or representatives to come up with a comprehensive package.</P>
    <P>I do not wish to advocate delay but I wish to suggest that any reforms proposed should now try to get us a modern, up to date set of legal provisions which will deal with the activities of companies.  It is important to remind ourselves that the entity which we work with so freely and which we accept, the limited company, the company that has its various activities and obligations specified by legal framework, is a comparatively modern invention. It is not much more than 100 years old.  It was devised to suit what was regarded as the appropriate circumstances of the mid-19th century.  It has been reformed or updated on a number of occasions &mdash; I think it was three times this century &mdash; but I do not think many people would suggest that, in their present form, the laws covering the operations of companies in this country really reflect contemporary circumstances. If there is to be a package of reform, please try to make it suitably comprehensive.  Let us not have bits coming from Social Welfare to try to deal with pensions, bits coming from Labour <Col N="398" /> to try to deal with specific redundancy problems and bits coming from Industry, Trade, Commerce and Tourism to try to deal with some of the other points.</P>
    <P>There is another aspect regarding why we might need this kind of comprehensive reform, and that is while we are rightly concerned with the hardships caused to employees who suddenly find themselves deprived not only of their jobs but even of their payments, we should not lose sight of the problems caused for the other creditors of firms.  Many of the policies not only of Government but of Opposition parties speak of encouraging and, by various incentives, set out to encourage enterprise.  You set out to encourage people to start up businesses to provide employment for others. Ask yourself what of the situation of many of the small firms who supply goods and services to another firm which suddenly goes into liquidation?  They find themselves in just as bad a position as the worker without a job.  In fact, in many instances they find themselves in a worse position because nobody is going to pass a law which says they are entitled to X number of weeks wages or they are entitled to have their pension contributions paid for 12 months.  In fact, they will not have any pension contributions and, worse still, depending on whether it is a small business and on what kind of awareness they had of their legal obligations, they might find themselves losing a lot of their personal assets, even their family home, because they may have used that as security to finance what they regarded as a basically sound, viable business, which is now going to become insolvent through the failure of another company with which they were trading.</P>
    <P>We talk about enterprise and we encourage it with one set of measures and then, through the way in which our current legal system operates in other areas, we are saying to people, &ldquo;You would be really a damn fool to set out starting a business of your own because you will end up in a far worse situation: there will be no protection in insolvency; there will be no redundancy payments; there will be no coverage for your pension <Col N="399" /> or other things&rdquo;.  If we are trying to run programmes like enterprise development programmes we ought to try to fit them into whatever type of reformed package we wish to operate to reflect our policies and our values as we enter the closing years of the 20th century.  Reform, I hope, will be comprehensive.  Meanwhile, we cannot wait for that comprehensive package and I welcome the fact that, thanks to the activities of the EC, we are getting a specific proposal to deal with one specific area of hardship.</P>
    <Speaker pid="StephenMcGonagle" hpid="Mr. McGonagle Mr. McGonagle">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGonagle</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not intend to speak at any great length about this matter.  I will try to be brief.  What has been said has been said very appropriately. I welcome the Bill.  I welcome the clear statement made by the Minister.  I noted his compassionate reference:</P>
      <P>To be made redundant and have to face unemployment for any reason is a very traumatic experience, but to be left without wages for the final weeks of employment and other due entitlements as well makes the situation even more intolerable.</P>
      <P>To me that is a key sentence.  I have had the experience on two or three occasions in my working life of having no job.  I know what it means.  When I was presented from time to time with workers who were without work &mdash; even those not in an insolvency situation &mdash; I, as their trade union representative, found this an unnerving experience, working without such legislation.  It bites deep into one's bones to look at the faces, the strain, the anxiety, the feelings of despair, especially if the breadwinner is involved.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>This is the sympathetic motivation behind such legislation.  Senator O'Donoghue has stolen some of my thunder about the European Directive.  This legislation has come out of Europe.  There is no doubt about that, but it is unfortunate that we have had to wait for it until the middle of the last quarter of the 20th century.  It is a pity we did not look at the British involvement in 1976 because the lack of this sort of legislation is one of <Col N="400" /> the gaps in worker protection legislation. It is a very serious matter to people like myself who are very close to the problems, but for those who are not close to it, it does not matter very much.  There was this kind of face of capitalism at work of not bothering very much about these situations.  This is being corrected and I commend the Minister for acting swiftly.</P>
    <P>I also have words of praise for the Members of this House in their attitude this morning on the Order of Business as to how we would go about getting this urgent matter through as quickly as possible. I cannot forget the discussions I had both in Geneva and in this country when the ILO representatives came to our ICTU conferences.  This kind of legislation was always discussed with the ILO. It is not without significance that the ILO head office where I have been several times is in Geneva, in the middle of Europe.  We will benefit in many ways from the pressures exerted by the continental trade unions as well as by the British and Irish trade unions on the ILO and in that way, on the whole European Community.  I am in no doubt that these are some of the progressive measures we will enjoy in the arena of worker protective legislation.  I am glad the Minister has made the clear statement that legislation in this area has developed over the years in an <i>ad hoc</i> fashion and that experience of its operation has shown that in various aspects it needs to be improved.  He went on to say that the work of reviewing all worker protection legislation is an extensive task and that he intends to have this task undertaken as expeditiously as possible given the resources available to the Department. The Minister is to be commended for having stated so clearly what his intentions are.</P>
    <P>I shall conclude by referring to the closing words of the Minister.  The Bill will go a considerable way towards easing this hardship, the hardship of facing the reality of redundancy, and the possibility of no wages or other moneys that may be due in an insolvency situation.  The Bill represents a very significant desirable <Col N="401" /> addition to our code of worker protection legislation.  I commend it to the House. The Minister has asked for unanimous adoption of the Bill.  I agree with him on that.  There should be no controversy about this Bill.  It is all right that there be some minor criticism but there should be no deep controversy.  It is a non-controversial Bill and it is necessary and vital in the area of worker protective legislation.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelSmith" hpid="Mr. Smith Mr. Smith">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Smith</NameTxt>
      <P>I should like to welcome this Bill, which establishes a fund from employers' PRSI contributions in order that workers who lose their jobs because of insolvency may be reimbursed for their wages, salaries, holiday pay, sick pay or whatever benefits they may be entitled to.  We on this side of the House are not trying to be in any way political about this Bill.  The Minister is probably one of the few members of the present Cabinet who still has an attitude of compassion, and all we would try to do here is to enhance his reputation by doing a little more in a few places.  The last couple of years have thrown up a lot of very disturbing situations.  Individuals have suffered the trauma of not just losing their jobs but also of finding, having contributed substantially to pensions and in other ways, that there were no funds available to assist them.  We have tended always to leave over to other legislation provisions that should be included in the legislation of the day.  When a Minister is asked about a certain provision being included, the reply often is that the matter is one for other legislation.  While these statements were made genuinely at the time, the result has been that various measures have not been implemented and that when we get the opportunity of a Bill like this we are inclined to use it to the maximum extent to cover the disturbing features affecting individuals and companies throughout the country.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The argument is usually advanced as to where the money is to come from for the implementation of new provisions. That will always be a difficult question. We contribute enormous sums to maintaining security along an artificial Border even though we come up against the <Col N="402" /> intransigence of others who have a greater responsibility but who will not move.  I read in yesterday's paper that the Minister for Justice said it is not the responsibility of the banks to contribute towards the cost of security, of transferring funds from one bank to another since they are not accountable for terrorism. They obviously are not, but they certainly should operate their systems in a way which would reduce the load on the State in the provision of this type of security.</P>
    <P>There have been instances of companies closing down overnight and owing sums of up to £2 million in PRSI, income tax and so on to the Revenue Commissioners. Those of us who are very small employers would find ourselves receiving letters every couple of weeks from the Revenue Commissioners about one or two employees if we happened to be in arrears from time to time.  It is incredible to find that some individual companies over the years can build up to a stage where such huge sums are due and leave ordinary workers not alone not having the knowledge that this is happening but in such a vulnerable position when a company collapses.</P>
    <P>There is the added factor that we have failed to introduce the legislation of the Fourth Directive as it relates to company law with the result that we still have fly-by-night operators, unscrupulous individuals setting up companies, becoming insolvent and not just starting up in other businesses but restarting in the same line in which they became insolvent previously. When the ordinary people of the country look at all this and ask why we cannot find sufficient scope to cover the areas we would like to see covered in this legislation, they are not given answers.  It seems from looking right across the board at what is happening that there is a lot which could be done to improve matters if we could get more co-operation not only here at home but from the British Government as well.</P>
    <P>Existing laws under the Companies and Bankruptcy Acts, give priority to worker claims but unfortunately what is written down in law is not capable of being put into effect if the individual company have <Col N="403" /> not sufficient resources to meet these legal requirements.  The Minister might indicate when the legislation for the updating of company law will be introduced. That legislation is long overdue, and it will have its own bearing and effect on the necessity for the use of this legislation.</P>
    <P>I referred in my initial remarks to individuals who would want to see this legislation cover very particular needs.  It is always very difficult to introduce legislation on the basis of catering for individual circumstances.  There was the case in the other House for Kilrush Ceramics.  We had in our own constituency the Castle Brand trauma.  The town of Nenagh which depended for over 50 years on this industry was rocked by the news of its going into liquidation.  That was followed shortly afterwards by the tragic news that whereas there was £190,000 contributed to the workers' pension fund by the workers, that fund in effect had been reduced to £76,000.  Other speakers have tried to indicate the trauma and loss this is to individual employees, many of whom have given almost a lifetime of service to the company and who were moving towards their retirement years having made their own contribution, not only in terms of finance but also through their skills and efforts to give this company an international reputation which was second to none.  Not only has a considerable proportion of the pension fund disappeared but the very fact of that difficulty being there is a stumbling block towards negotiations to get new interests involved in restoring the company and providing worth-while employment in an industry which I believe can and should be viable.  Obviously we are trying to persuade the Minister in some way to try to cater for this and other similar situations.  It may be difficult in this legislation to do it but perhaps he could go some of the way, either by indicating the way in which that situation could be catered for in other legislation or by including it here.  We are not standing hard and fast as to how it should be dealt with so long as it is dealt with.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="404" /> The urgency of this Bill has already been referred to.  I would therefore like to ask the Minister, assuming that he gets all Stages today, if that means that an attempt will be made to have payments that are outstanding made by Christmas, or does it mean that it will take somewhat longer to get the necessary procedures into action?  I would ask him if it is technically possible to ensure that these payments are made prior to Christmas.</P>
    <P>I would conclude by generally welcoming the provisions of the Bill.  We had really no great argument against its general principles.  What we would like to see happening is the extension and widening of the ambit to cover individual traumatic situations which have happened in the past couple of years, and also some indication from the Minister as to whether this Bill or impending legislation could solve these problems for us, in which event our opposition to individual sections of this Bill would obviously be reduced.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JohnHarte" hpid="Mr. Harte Mr. Harte">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Harte</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not intend delaying the House.  I agree with Senator McGonagle that the Bill is non-controversial in the sense that it protects and is designed to protect the employees' interest.  Whether we serve in advice clinics or elsewhere we encounter far too many problems relating to holiday pay, minimum notice and so on.  There are also the many problems created for workers in respect of the limited conditions applying to receiverships.</P>
      <P>The Bill has to be welcomed from the point of view of the reduction in the weekly threshold.  This also presented some difficulties to trade union officials down through the years.  It is very good to see being regularised a situation where a lot of controversy has existed.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I did not hear the Minister's speech but I am a little concerned about what happens where no formal winding up or bankruptcy proceedings are initiated. Will employees in such situations have the same lien on the funds as a creditor who could put the company into receivership would have?  What is the situation in regard to the resources left over?  Will the fund be able to cope with situations <Col N="405" /> of that nature in the sense of its being adequate to cover the broad spectrum where events of this nature occur?</P>
    <P>It is right to say, even though this is not a recruiting forum, that in the present economic conditions where there will be more redundancies it is not only timely to bring this type of legislation forward but it is very commendable that the date of the EC Council directive is being taken as the date for the retroactive function of the Bill.  Despite that, it should be borne in mind that people, though they know what the law is about now, still have great difficulty when a company is put into receivership.  The Bill expresses in a much more effective way than heretofore where legal rights lie.  Therefore, they can act with more certainty.  However, in cases where there are workers who are not always in a strong position &mdash; unorganised workers &mdash; there will be the problem that they do not know where to go, who to see or what to say, despite the fact that the law is quite clear.  In those circumstances people would be well advised to get themselves into trade unions who are experienced in dealing with these situations.</P>
    <P>It is a shattering experience for somebody to be told suddenly that the person who had the power of debenture is the person with the power to put a company into receivership and that then there is little that can be done except follow the law.  Where there is no guide to follow the law, despite the comprehensive nature of the Bill, it is very essential and very wise for workers to get themselves into an organised position where they can be more effective when following the procedures in the Bill.</P>
    <P>The appointment of a receiver is a most serious development.  It would be encouraging to know that if we were to introduce company law that would give some protection in the event of companies being put into receivership.  Senator Smith has made this point.  There are other areas, too, but I do not want to go into too much detail on company law that will have a bearing on protecting rather <Col N="406" /> than on compensating people in companies in receivership.</P>
    <P>The Bill does not change the question of the secured creditor.  He will still be the person who will put the company into liquidation.  The Bill itself will provide the necessary protection in the sense of compensation but there is some company law needed to give some protection to people who find themselves in receivership situations as a result of the cowboy activities of certain people.  As Senator Smith rightly says, such people possibly come back into business under another guise or in fact even into the same type of business.</P>
    <P>Therefore, if we set out to ensure that people are compensated, we must also provide for some sort of protective element so that there is a reduction in the number of people finding themselves in these situations.  That can be done by way of legislation.  We cannot do everything by way of legislation but we can take effective measures in many areas, and in this particular area such measures are very necessary.</P>
    <P>I welcome the Bill and I compliment the Minister on the time and effort he has put into it.  It has been a very good and comprehensive effort.</P>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFallon" hpid="Mr. Fallon Mr. Fallon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Fallon</NameTxt>
      <P>As has been said by previous speakers, to lose one's job can indeed be a very traumatic experience not just for the individual but for the family as a unit.  Indeed it has happened many times that whole neighbourhoods have lost their jobs because there has been a tendency in many areas for entire communities to work in certain industries. The whole experience of job losses in such circumstances can be traumatic and can have great social implications for both the individual families and the communities as a whole.  No amount of compensation, no Government Bill, no payment of any kind will make up for such loss.  Obviously compensation will be a help, and this is what this Bill is all about &mdash; to soften the blow, as it were.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The Bill is designed to protect employees' interests in regard to pay in the event of their employer becoming insolvent.  The Bill is positively a further <Col N="407" /> benefit in the area of worker protection, but certainly no worker can say that his job is safe.</P>
    <P>As Senator Hillery has pointed out, Irish Shipping were trading profitably in 1982.  We know the plight of that company today.  Neither in the public area nor in the private area can anyone sit on his laurels and expect to have a safe job for the rest of his life.  It just is not that way any more, regrettably.  The Bill has become necessary as a result of an EC directive, but I wonder if that directive was appropriate in some ways to Ireland. From the point of view of our record being so bad, perhaps the Bill could be amended in some way.  I understand that Senator Hillery will be suggesting some amendments.  For instance, we could do with an element of retrospection in this Bill.  We can go back as far as 1980 but a compromise seems to be reasonable rather than a starting date of October 1983.  Why not have it start from January 1983?</P>
    <P>In my own town I have witnessed some of the trauma I referred to.  We are very pleased in the Athlone area that we have done reasonably well despite the very severe financial and economic recession. As the Minister is aware, in the past few months 67 employees of Gentex have been laid off twice.  The liquidator was called in.  Gentex has not just been an ordinary company.  For Athlone and for Athlone people it has been a way of life, but this situation has now ceased.  The liquidator was called in, no redundancies were paid and the union in question, the FWUI of which the Minister is a member, took up the case and appealed it to the Employment Appeals Tribunal.  They in turn sat in Athlone and they allowed the appeal.  The Department of Labour subsequently paid out redundancies of varying amounts and all of which were gratefully received and very useful indeed.  It was only right, legally and morally, that the money should have been paid.</P>
    <P>These people, too, will become beneficiaries within the terms of this Bill.  I do not know the exact amounts they will <Col N="408" /> receive but I sincerely hope it will be sufficient and that it will add further to the comfort of their lives.  How long will the 67 people I have referred to have to wait for their money?  So far as we are concerned on this side of the House we are only too anxious to facilitate the passage of the Bill.  My colleagues and I are very keen to do so that the money can be paid out.  I believe and hope that the Minister can co-operate with the unions or with the employees in question and ensure that payment is made before Christmas.  My hope is that as a result of a speedy passage for the Bill here today, the Minister can act Santa Claus and bring finance to these people before the Christmas holidays.</P>
    <Speaker pid="TrasHonan" hpid="Mrs. Honan Mrs. Honan">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Honan</NameTxt>
      <P>I welcome this Bill.  I understand the sadness that the workers and their families have suffered.  The need for the Bill is quite clear.  The Minister stated this morning:</P>
      <P>Strong representations have been made to me seeking to have an early implementation date, but this is not feasible for a number of reasons.  As with all other protection legislation, it is unfortunately the case that regardless of what implementing date is chosen some workers will lose out.  In this case the most objective date which can be chosen is 22 October 1983, the date of the implementing of the EC directive.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>That directive has been in existence, I understand, since 1983.  So I repeat here this morning my support for the representations and speeches and requests that Deputy Brendan Daly made in the other House.  I ask you this morning to change that date from 22 October, 1983 to 1 January, 1983 or, indeed, even to 1 April, 1983 because I am specifically talking about the effects that would have on 90 workers in west Clare.  He spoke at length and he made some representation on it, and, indeed, it was a pity that the other Clare Deputies did not follow what they said when it came to voting later in the day on that issue.  I hope that one or other of the Clare Senators will do so later <Col N="409" /> on when amendments come before the House.  As a former Minister for Labour, Deputy Daly knew what he was talking about.  So he knows it is possible.</P>
    <P>I support the glowing tributes that Senator Smith paid to the Minister this morning, providing we get action this evening from him.  In the Kilrush Pottery factory we are talking about £25,000 minimum notice holiday pay money.  The Minister might not know but I am well aware that he made commitments to these workers when he was in Clare campaigning in the EC elections for his Munster colleague on the Sunday of the Fleadh Nua.  He met some of the workers on that day and they came away believing that he was going to look after them in some way.  I hope the Minister will keep the promise made to them.  I do not know in what way the Minister gave the promise to them, but he certainly gave them the impression that he would help them.  I do not know the time of day when the promise was made.  That might have some bearing on how much the promise meant.  If I do not intend standing for Clare I still think I should at least look after the Kilrush workers in west Clare for Deputy Daly's sake.  When Senator Hillery puts this amendment here this evening I would ask the Minister to accept it and to bring back the date to 1 January 1983 or to 1 April, 1983 so as to cover workers who have been caught. There are a few of the last supporters of Labour in that group.  So, the Minister should do some thinking during lunch time and he might give in here when he did not give in in the other House.  We are more gracious in the way we ask for things here, so the Minister might remember those people and back date the Bill even at this late stage.</P>
    <Speaker pid="RuairiQuinn" hpid="Minister for Labour (Mr. Quinn) Ruairí Quinn">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Labour (Mr. Quinn)</NameTxt>
      <P>May I first of all thank the Senators for the contributions and for the generous support that they have given to this measure? A number of specific items have been raised and I will try in sequence to deal with them.  First of all, I compliment Senator Hillery for the range of his contribution <Col N="410" /> and for setting this measure within the framework of the need to look at work protection legislation generally.  I know that on Committee Stage we will deal with a number of points that are relevant to his contribution, but with respect to the tragedy of Irish Shipping can I just say that attempts to re-negotiate the charter arrangements were extensively undertaken before the decision that the Government finally took was made.  In fact, efforts were made over the course of an entire year.  I share the view that if there had been worker representation on the board of Irish Shipping in line with the representation that there is in other companies, particularly Aer Lingus which got into difficult circumstances as well and managed with the co-operation of its work force to turn around its operations in a very successful manner, perhaps a similar possibility could have been developed and extended in Irish Shipping. In response to the question as to when I propose to bring in the legislation to extend the worker participation legislation, we are currently in discussions with the parliamentary draftsmen, and it would be my intention and expectation that it would be circulated and taken in the next session.</P>
      <P>I share the view and will convey it to the Minister for Finance about the tardiness of the Revenue Commissioners in not collecting money at a regular time and fairly promptly, because this allows what would otherwise be a very effective early warning system to go without the opportunity of availing of it plus the fact that the cash flow implications are inherent in this as well.</P>
      <P>I would like to thank Senator Higgins for his welcome support for the Bill and for his encouragement in having it enacted as quickly as possible.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Senator McDonald's contribution, as has been the case on previous occasions, was particularly incisive in relation to the balance between the need to reform company law in general and to maintain some level of compensation balance between the extension of workers' rights on the one hand and the extension of the rights for creditors <i>vis-à-vis</i> small companies. <Col N="411" /> We are in effect doing two things in this Bill.  We are protecting the rights of workers in one sense by means of a fund which will be funded by the employers. In so doing we are also giving the workers <i>de facto</i> a preferential position compared with that of small creditors many of whom go into subsequential bankruptcy following on the insolvency of a major company.</P>
    <P>The reform of company law which was raised by a number of Senators is something that we will deal with, particularly the fly-by-night company director that has frequently enough been seen.  They are not by any means the normal kind of company director that is the experience of our mixed economy, but they have existed and they can still legally exist where they can close down on a Monday and open on a Tuesday and essentially trade in the same area.  I should tell the House that the Cabinet are currently reviewing a substantial memorandum on the reform of company law which will make some provision for the Fourth Directive, referred to by Senator Smith, and which will give the House and, indeed, the other House a substantial amount of legislative work to do.  As Senator O'Donoghue said company law has only been reformed once or twice in this century and in fact it is only about 100 years old.  There is a lot of technical legislative work in which the expertise of this House will be called upon to help the Government and the Civil Service in getting the right kind of company law that is appropriate for the last 16 years of this century and hopefully will take us into the first 25 years of the next century.</P>
    <P>In that context, he raised the question of pensions and, indeed, other Senators raised the question of pensions and why it was that we were not addressing ourselves to the problem of pension fund contributions and the continuation of pension payments after a company goes into insolvency.  The answer is that it is a complex area and, in particular, the fund contributions for this measure would come exclusively from the employer.  I do not think that anybody is seriously <Col N="412" /> suggesting that pensions and the receipt of pensions should come from a fund that is not contributed to by both the workers and the employers.  The consequences of trying to extend this fund into the ongoing pension payment until the termination of life or whatever the conditional pension might be out of a fund that was exclusively funded from the employers would seem to me to be inequitable.  It would also have an enormous cost implication on the size of the employer contribution that would be required in the fund.</P>
    <P>The other point made by Senator O'Donoghue was in connection with the EC and the &ldquo;Godfather&rdquo; role the EC is having not just in relation to this legislation but also in relation to other legislation.</P>
    <P>We have referred to the role of the EC in all of this and we have taken the date on which the directive became a legal obligation upon the member states as the commencement date for this legislation. I will return to that later.  It points out the very positive social contribution in some areas of social legislation that the EC has been able to provide within our society.</P>
    <P>Senator McGonagle's political and trade union experience underscores the need for having this kind of measure.  On the one hand, when a company goes into insolvency the trading companies who are affected by that insolvency are not exclusively affected by it.  Presumably they would have other customers and presumably they are in a position where if they are trading profitably they can carry on until such time as the liquidator can make arrangements to come to a settlement on outstanding moneys due to them.  That is not so in the case of workers who are exclusively working for that company and who have allowed an average of two to three weeks of arrears of back money, wages and salaries, to try to assist the company in the first instance to continue. They find that their money, essential income, is stopped and they have little or no prospect of receiving it.  The trauma of that reality on top of the tragedy of losing their jobs is frightening. Senator Fallon referred to it.  Legislation <Col N="413" /> is long overdue and it is to the shame of our political society that we have not introduced this legislation much sooner than we are proposing to do today.</P>
    <P>Senator Smith raised the question of the role of the Revenue Commissioners in a vein similar to that in which Senator Hillery spoke, and he talked about the cost in administering the scheme and the difficulties we have currently with our nearest political neighbour in relation to policing the boundaries of a state which generates problems for security in our own State.  I would be very much in sympathy with the sentiments that he expressed in that regard, and I hope that the ongoing discussions that will take place between our two countries will attempt to resolve that problem and reduce the disproportionate burden of cost that the citizens of this State have to carry to provide security for a problem that is not of our making.</P>
    <P>Senator Smith turned to the tragedy in relation to his own town and constituency of Nenagh and the position in relation to Castle Brand.  It is very clear that the workers who contributed over the 50 years to the pension fund there or whenever the pension fund was instituted, should have been better protected.  There are many pension fund schemes in operation which were set up at a time when the employer class or the capitalist class in this country had a very patronising attitude to workers and felt that they either could not be trusted or that they were not capable of acting as trustees in their own pension fund.  That is patently nonsense and would be seen as such by all Members of this House in 1984.  Therefore I propose to take steps to ensure that the trustees of such pension funds are representative of both participants in the pension fund.  I would go further and support the point raised by Senator Harte that pension fund contributors in a particular company should avail of the trade union movement to provide trustees if they do not want to do it themselves or do not want to be so directly involved. The trade union movement has both the position and the expertise to ensure that the kind of tragedy that has happened in <Col N="414" /> the Castle Brand pension fund could be avoided.</P>
    <P>Senator Harte also referred to the need to reform and impose company law, and raised the position of an employee whose company did not go to formal liquidation or insolvency but which simply, so to speak, disappeared in the night.  We can take this up at some length on Committee Stage if the House so wishes.  In that instance where there is not a formal liquidation, where there is not somebody to whom the workers or the workers' representative can present their claim or their case, I have taken power within the Bill for the Minister for Labour to step in.  Where a company disappears, if the workers arrive on a Monday and find that the plant, the factory or the shop is closed and that the worker is non-protectable, the procedures would be as follows: the workers or their representative can come to the Department of Labour and make a formal complaint or claim and I will appoint a relevant officer with powers similar to those of the relevant officer who would be the liquidator in a formal liquidation to make the normal investigations and if satisfied that the workers have a bona fide claim in respect of lost wages, then they would be paid accordingly.  This is part of the problem with regard to the question of cost.  When we confer this right retrospectively to 22 October 1983 we have a reasonable estimation, although with very inadequate statistics, of the formal liquidations and the formal insolvencies that have taken place but we have no estimation whatever of the informal ones.  We have attempted to make provision in the fund to cover what we reckon would be a reasonable estimate of what the demand would be on the one hand and quite frankly, to minimise the level of contribution that the employers would have to make on the other.  It is frequently referred to in the House and in public affairs generally that one of the difficulties that employers are currently experiencing in the Irish environment where trading conditions are difficult is the level of public taxation that they have to carry and specifically in <Col N="415" /> relation to employment, employers have on numerous occasions referred to the high level of employment cost that their PRSI contribution represents.  They have referred to the PRSI contribution as a tax on employment.  For every worker who is paid £100 PRSI, £120 has to be found, £12 extra of which comes from the employer's contribution.  It does represent a charge albeit a much smaller charge than employers in other EC countries have to pay.  It is a claim being made by employers and those who would argue that we should make this fund retrospective to various dates for various reasons that we should have regard to the difficulties that employers have in recruiting staff or maintaining staff or increasing the workforce and to the fact that we are trying to balance one consideration against the other.</P>
    <P>On the question of Athlone &mdash; Senator Fallon raised the point of the prospect of trying to get quick and effective payment as soon as possible and the point was raised by other Senators also &mdash; it is our intention if this Bill is enacted to move as quickly as we can to make payments. The regulations are in draft form and the claim forms are in draft form and will be available within a week or so.  Subject to the necessary information being correct and all the detail being complied with, it would be my intention to give a direction that where possible and feasible payments will be made as soon as possible. If that enables payment to be made from the Department and from the fund before Christmas I will be very happy.</P>
    <P>I have avoided making any reference to the Leas-Chathaoirleach's contribution until the last because it warrants a certain kind of riposte that is in the same tone and quality as her own contribution. I had the temerity to visit Clare without her permission during June.</P>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I would invite the Minister.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RuairiQuinn" hpid="Mr. Quinn Mr. Quinn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Quinn</NameTxt>
      <P>I realised as I left the outskirts of Limerick that I was heading into very difficult and dangerous country, and <Col N="416" /> it was confirmed when I saw at the far end of the town of Ennis the statue of someone who on occasion the Leas-Chathaoirleach has made reference to.  I was glad to see that the spectacles had been returned.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I have no regrets ever for referring to him.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RuairiQuinn" hpid="Mr. Quinn Mr. Quinn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Quinn</NameTxt>
      <P>When I saw his august presence I felt that your resounding presence that emanates and fills this Chamber on many occasions was everywhere.  I did not stay late into the night.  The meeting I had was in the middle of the day.  The undertaking I gave to the Kilrush Pottery workers whom I met &mdash; and you are well informed, as I would expect, in that part of the world &mdash; was that I would do everything possible to try to meet what was a reasonable claim on their behalf.  We have looked at the situation and I was festooned and besieged with representations from Deputy Madeline Taylor-Quinn and from Deputy Donal Carey and from the Transport and General Workers Union representatives in Clare. Quite frankly, and I say this with some reluctance, we are not in a position to accede to either of the two options that the Fianna Fáil Party in the other House gave us in relation to the retrospection date.  Indeed, Deputy Brendan Daly was particularly vociferous in trying to press this point.  The reason why we are not in a position is that the fund is not as flaithiúlach as would appear.  The claims on it this year are going to be enormous. It may very well be that we will have to look at the possibility of increasing the level of employer contribution.</P>
      <P>I am very conscious of the critical balance that many companies are currently in in terms of their trading position. Therefore, it is with great reluctance that I request the Government and the Minister for Finance to add to the cost of employment.  This has to be seen in objective terms as a cost to employment.  For that reason we are not in a position to go back further than the date of 22 October 1983.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I would point out to Senator Honan <Col N="417" /> that her constituency colleague, Deputy Daly, was in the Department of Labour during the time when this directive was passed by the EC and then it was on the order book, so to speak, of work to be done.  The Government from 1977 through until 1981 &mdash; it had no difficulties in terms of its parliamentary majority &mdash; negotiated that directive because the directive was agreed upon on 22 October 1980 and member states were given three years within which to bring forward the legislation and after which the legal date from which they were liable was 22 October. Therefore, one can draw the conclusion that if the concern that Deputy Daly has expressed so vociferously over the last few days in the other House had been applied effectively in the Department of Labour when he was in Mespil Road, then the workers in Kilrush Potteries would not be in the unfortunate position that they are in today.  But that is of little consolation to those people or to any other workers who find themselves in that situation.  Our statistics are not sufficiently adequate to enable us to make the date retrospective from that point. Regrettably, I cannot accede to the request.</P>
    <P>In conclusion, I thank Senators for their contributions and confirm what I said in my opening speech on Second Stage, that all the legislation we have in the worker protection area needs to be looked at and reviewed in the context of seeing whether it provides adequate and effective protection and if it enables the economy on which workers are dependent for their livelihood to function and prosper.  It is my desire and my intention to have such a comprehensive review with one clear understanding that in bringing forward any changes or reforms that will be necessary &mdash; it is quite clear that changes and reforms will be necessary &mdash; we do not throw out the baby with the bath water, that we do not unlearn the lessons of history, so to speak, in terms of the way in which these measures have been painfully put onto the Statute Book.  I thank the House for its co-operation.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="418" /> Question put and agreed to.</P>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Next Stage?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDooge" hpid="Professor Dooge Professor Dooge">
      <NameTxt>Professor Dooge</NameTxt>
      <P>It is proposed in accordance with our decision this morning to take Committee Stage at 3 p.m. today.</P>
      <P>Committee Stage ordered for 3 p.m.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Ombudsman Act (First Schedule) (Amendment)" RHead="Order, 1984: Motion (Resumed)">
    <Title>Ombudsman Act (First Schedule) (Amendment) Order, 1984: Motion (Resumed).</Title>
    <P>Debate resumed on the following motion:</P>
    <P>That Seanad Éireann approves the following Order in draft:&mdash;</P>
    <P>Ombudsman Act (First Schedule) (Amendment) Order, 1984</P>
    <P>a copy of which Order in draft was laid before the House on 23 November, 1984.</P>
    <P Just="Right">&mdash;(Senator Dooge).</P>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>May I remind Senators that this motion is being discussed with item No. 4?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnBoland" hpid="Minister for the Public Service (Mr. Boland) John Boland">
      <NameTxt>Minister for the Public Service (Mr. Boland)</NameTxt>
      <P>I would like to thank the Seanad for the warm welcome which they gave to the order before the House in relation to the extension of the Ombudsman's remit.  Senator Hillery, in particular, inquired about the proposed additional staffing that might be necessary for the office of the Ombudsman in connection with the extension of his remit to the four areas: local authorities, health boards, An Post and An Bord Telecom.  It is intended that there would be an additional three senior investigators and 12 investigator staff together with back-up clerical staff appointed for each of the areas; broadly speaking, one senior investigator and four investigators for each of the areas of the local authorities, the health boards and telecommunications. <Col N="419" /> When one bears in mind that the present staff comprises one senior investigator and four investigators in relation to the Civil Service, I think the Seanad will agree that the staff provision should be more than adequate to meet the demands being placed upon the office through the extension of the remit.</P>
      <P>Senator Hillery also raised a matter which was adverted to during the passage of legislation here some weeks ago as to whether questions of personnel matters involving civil servants ought to be subject to investigation by the Ombudsman.  This area is specifically excluded at present.  Whilst the case has been made to me on a number of occasions about the possibility of the Ombudsman investigating this area, I remain still to be convinced of the necessity for it.  At the time the legislation was going through the then Minister of State did not favour this idea.  I should mention that in the last year there has been a very detailed procedure agreed with the staff interests regarding the steps that are to be taken when a civil servant finds himself or herself in dispute on a particular matter with their employer.  That is a very detailed procedure and leaves open to the individual recourse to quite a series of steps.</P>
      <P>The other potential objection to the concept of the Ombudsman investigating areas such as this is that the Ombudsman might well become a personnel grievance officer in so far as civil servants are concerned and that might not be the best image for the Ombudsman to have.  However, I still have a relatively open mind on this issue.  And if in the future it appears there is gain to be had in extending the Ombudsman's remit into this particular area, then certainly I would be prepared to consider it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I agree with Senator Ferris regarding the emphasis which he placed on the need for courtesy to be shown by public bodies and their staffs towards their customer who, is, in effect, the general public. The difficulty is that very often with a bureaucracy when a service is being delivered the emphasis is placed upon <Col N="420" /> efficient delivery of the service.  I am not always sure, because so many of the public sector bodies are operating in a monopoly situation, whether the treatment of the general public and the courtesy extended to them and the amount of information given to them is commensurate with the way in which a private sector body operating in a free market and trading against competitors would always operate.  I would hope that the extension of the Ombudsman's remit to the areas concerned would also serve to help to remind staff employed in public bodies of the overriding need not only to carry out their duties to the public efficiently but to ensure that when they come in contact with the public, whether personally at public counters or through telephone conversations or in correspondence, the extension of courtesy and the imparting of information should be one of the overriding factors in their attitudes towards the general public.</P>
    <P>I would hope that the level of complaints which have been experienced by a number of the Members of the House in relation to the general attitude shown to the individual subscriber, for instance, in the case of the telephone service, may be an area that would be given particular additional attention by the authorities operating that service and that that aspect will be one which will also receive the attention of the Ombudsman.</P>
    <P>There seems to be a belief that the majority of the complaints which the Ombudsman may have to deal with in relation to An Bord Telecom will have to do with the question of subscriber accounts.  There are very many other areas where public representatives regularly receive complaints from the public both in relation to the length of delay on the part of potential subscribers in having telephones provided for them and the lack of real information given to them as to when they might realistically hope to have telephone service provided to them and indeed difficulties experienced by the general public in having service restored following breakdown.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="421" /> While there has been considerable progress made in the telephone network in recent years through an enormous capital investment on the part of the customer, the general public, the taxpayer, that has not always been matched by a realistic imparting of information to persons awaiting service and to people who contact the service with a genuine complaint. Regrettably, as Senator Ferris mentioned, some public representatives on a committee of the House have experienced from time to time over the last year an attitude from An Bord Telecom which perhaps was adopted because of the great pressures upon them to catch up with service being required but which is not designed to improve the general image of the service in the minds of the public. I would like to urge all of those who are engaged in the public service in dealing with the general public to remember that the public is the customer and is the person who is paying the bill and in many instances not only paying the bill but paying the overall operational costs through their general taxation and that the customer is entitled to basic courtesy as well as efficiency.  I hope there will be particular attention paid to that area.</P>
    <P>The examples which the Senator gave in relation to the health area and the exclusions in connection with clinical judgment, of possible delays in the provision of community care services, are clearly examples which would be, under the proposed order, within the remit of the Ombudsman to attend to.  The question of delay in the provision of service is clearly one which the Ombudsman within his remit is entitled to investigate and is quite exclusive from the clinical judgment which might be exercised when eventually the case comes to be examined. This question of clinical judgment has been exempted from the remit of Ombudsmen in, as far as I know, all of the countries where an Ombudsman operates.  It is only right that that should be so.  The other question of delays in the provision of medical services is clearly an administrative one and will be within <Col N="422" /> the power of the Ombudsman to investigate.</P>
    <P>Senator Killilea made a number of points which were more of general interest than relating specifically to the question of the extension of the Ombudsman's remit.  Perhaps he did not really expect a detailed reply from me to them.  He may have been making them more for the edification of the House or as points of general interest.  I appreciate his experience as an office holder in the former Department of Posts and Telegraphs. Despite the remarks which he made regarding the operation of that Department, he did say that there was, during his time there, a rapid response to complaints made by members of the public. I am not sure that everybody would be in agreement that that was the situation.  I can recall, particularly during that period and other periods, having to wait for as long as six, eight, nine months to receive a reply to legitimate representations made to that Department.  Many of my constituents and, I know, the constituents of other public representatives, found themselves in a similar situation. It is galling for a potential subscriber who is looking for service to be without that service over a period of time and to find that he is unable to elicit accurate information as to when he might reasonably hope to get that service.  It is particularly galling to people who are invited to pay their connection fee, which is now quite a sizeable amount of money and having paid that connection fee, to be still left for quite a length of time without service. One would hope that the improved methods of operation of Bord Telecom, together with the extension of the remit of the Ombudsman into this area, will help to bring about a greater dissemination of information to the subscriber and potential subscribers.</P>
    <P>I can only say, in relation to the Senator's remarks, that it must be a great consolation to be able to announce categorically that there is absolutely nothing wrong with the administration of a large public body of which he happens to be a member.  It is a very wide and proud claim and I am sure the Senator believes <Col N="423" /> it absolutely.  I have no reason to disagree with him except to say that in any large organisation, whether in the public or private sector, there will always be an element of customer dissatisfaction and whether that dissatisfaction is reasonable and legitimate or otherwise it is reasonable, if the organisation happens to be a State one, that the State should provide an apparatus such as the Ombudsman's office to which the person who has a perceived grievance can refer that grievance and where an impartial adjudicator such as the Ombudsman can then decide as to the legitimacy or otherwise of the grievance.  As I said in my introductory remarks, the Ombudsman should act both on behalf of those who work within the bureaucracy and on behalf of the general public.  I think when the Ombudsman's first report comes before the House it will be ascertained that his findings will have concluded that in many of the cases of complaint the bureaucracy acted both fairly and impartially and there were not real grounds for the complaint. It is as well that that should be so, so that there can be a yardstick whereby complaints that may be unfairly made against public bodies can be adjudicated on and where an impartial adjudicator such as the Ombudsman can come to a decision and make that clear.</P>
    <P>I appreciate particularly the remarks of Senator McGonagle who, as the House knows, is a former Ombudsman in Northern Ireland.  He made a number of points which were of great validity including the fact that the Ombudsman should neither do the job of the courts nor the job of the trade unions.  In that respect I was reminded of the remarks of Senator Hillery regarding the question of personnel difficulties, complaints or grievances within the Civil Service.  Senator McGonagle's remarks are worthy of attention by people who have a concern in this area and I would refer Senator Hillery to them.  The office of Ombudsman is designed to act on complaints about malpractice or delay in administration on behalf of the general public.  There are other <Col N="424" /> organisations whose functions include that of ensuring the adequate representation of their individual members.</P>
    <P>The Senator concluded by saying that this extension of the remit was essentially an extension of democracy.  I am glad that was the note on which the debate concluded last evening, because I do believe that both the establishment of the office of Ombudsman and the progressive extension of his remit into further areas of the public service is an extention of democracy itself and is an important safeguard for the continuation of democracy. In that respect I welcome the remarks of the Senators who contributed yesterday and their welcome to the concept of the extension of the remit.  I would hope that at some stage during 1985 the House will have the opportunity, and I am sure it will find it an interesting one, to consider the first annual report of the Ombudsman's office in relation to his activities during 1984.  I look forward to having the further helpful contributions of Members of the Seanad on that occasion.</P>
    <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Joint Committee on Commercial" RHead="State-Sponsored Bodies: Motion">
    <Title>Joint Committee on Commercial State-Sponsored Bodies: Motion.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDooge" hpid="Professor Dooge Professor Dooge">
      <NameTxt>Professor Dooge</NameTxt>
      <P>I move:</P>
      <P>That Seanad Éireann takes note of the decision of the Minister for the Public Service, after consultation with the Joint Committee on Commercial State-Sponsored Bodies, and with the agreement of the Minister for Finance, to include Bord Telecom Éireann and An Post in the schedule of bodies which the Joint Committee may examine in accordance with its Orders of Reference.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Business" RHead="of Seanad">
    <Title>Business of Seanad.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDooge" hpid="Professor Dooge Professor Dooge">
      <NameTxt>Professor Dooge</NameTxt>
      <P>It is now 12.45 p.m. Rather than break up the debate, the Seanad might wish to adjourn now until 2 o'clock.  On the other hand, if Senators <Col N="425" /> feel we are going to say a lot about item No. 13 and a lot on Committee Stage they may prefer to restrict themselves to an hour.  It is a matter for the House to decide.</P>
      <P>
        <i>Sitting suspended at 12.45 p.m. and resumed at 2 p.m.</i>
      </P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Joint Committee on Marriage Breakdown:" RHead="Motion">
    <Title>Joint Committee on Marriage Breakdown: Motion.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="KatherineBulbulia" hpid="Mrs. Bulbulia Mrs. Bulbulia">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Bulbulia</NameTxt>
      <P>I move:</P>
      <P>That the period for reporting back of the Joint Committee on Marriage Breakdown be extended to the 19th February, 1985.</P>
      <P>It is with no sense of pleasure that I seek this extension and have my name to this motion.  It has been found necessary by the members of the Marriage Committee to seek an extension due to the magnitude of the task in hand.  As you will know &mdash; to remind Senators &mdash; this Joint Committee were established by a motion in the Dáil on 7 July 1983 and in the Seanad on 12 July 1983.  Since that time members have been working extremely hard and conscientiously in order to complete their deliberations.  Advertisements were placed in daily newspapers seeking submissions, and such is the volume of public interest in the work of this committee that some 700 submissions came flooding in.  Members were obliged to study these carefully and draw conclusions from them.  In order to allow a process of consultation some 24 groupings who had made written submissions were invited in to meet the committee and to give oral submissions in order to further elaborate on the points that they had made and in order to allow themselves to be questioned by members of the committee as to various details within their submissions.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>As a result of all of this, of course, the committee have acquired a body of information which is probably unique in Irish society, and this has provided source material which will be incorporated in <Col N="426" /> its report.  We had initial difficulties in staffing, and these difficulties were experienced by all committees in the House.  This led to a request for an extension which we made on the 28 June, and we looked at that stage for an extension until December.  We did so in good faith because at that time we sincerely believed that we could have had our work completed by that date.  I would like to assure Members that it certainly seems very clear to me and indeed to most members of the committee that this is the very last time we shall have a motion before this House seeking an extension of our time, and we do so with the greatest reluctance. We really did have a choice whether we should bring before you a report which was hastily compiled and hastily considered or whether we should extend our time and make sure that what we brought before both Houses was a worth-while, carefully considered and well-researched document with all the i's dotted and the t's crossed.</P>
    <P>We have at this stage a final draft report.  We have commenced examining it and consulting for the final time with all of those who we feel can give us any last-minute help and advice which we would need on it.  So, it is with confidence that I say that this will be the final time we will come before the House seeking an extension, and I would ask the House to grant this to us in order that we can bring the best possible document for consideration, because it goes without saying that the problem of marital breakdown is one which is affecting a great number of people in Irish society.  Very many people are looking to this committee for a well considered, well-thought-out report which shows a grasp of the complexity of the situation being suffered by individuals and which will bring forth realistic observations and &mdash; if I may use the word &mdash; recommendations as to what courses of action should flow on its findings.  Thank you.</P>
    <Speaker pid="CharlesBMcDonald" hpid="Mr. McDonald Mr. McDonald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McDonald</NameTxt>
      <P>I would just like to second the motion in the hope that the <Col N="427" /> House will agree to it and wish the committee success in the very important task that they have before them.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Business" RHead="of Seanad">
    <Title>Business of Seanad.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDooge" hpid="Professor Dooge Professor Dooge">
      <NameTxt>Professor Dooge</NameTxt>
      <P>I think Senators have been overcome by the haste in which the last matter has been dealt with.  I can assure the House that we do have a speaker on No. 5 and if we take our ease for a few minutes the debate will proceed. I do not know how many speakers are offering.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="CharlesBMcDonald" hpid="Mr. McDonald Mr. McDonald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McDonald</NameTxt>
      <P>Could I ask the Leader of the House if item No. 6 will be reached this afternoon?  I thought we would have had half a day to deal with that today.  It would be very appropriate seeing that it is just before the summit meeting, when the House could consider the most important points especially relating to the enlargement and the accession of Portugal and Spain.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Report of the Joint Committee on the Secondary" RHead="Legislation of the EC: Motion (Resumed)">
    <Title>Report of the Joint Committee on the Secondary Legislation of the EC: Motion (Resumed).</Title>
    <P>Debate resumed on the following motion:</P>
    <P>That Seanad Éireann pursuant to the Order of the Seanad of 13th September 1984 takes note of the Report of the Joint Committee on the Secondary Legislation of the European Communities on Proposals relating to equality of Opportunity (including Parental and Family Leave) which was laid before the Seanad on 17th October 1984 and which contains a request for a debate thereon.</P>
    <P Just="Right">&mdash;(Senator Robinson).</P>
    <Speaker pid="JackFitzsimons" hpid="Mr. Fitzsimons Mr. Fitzsimons">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Fitzsimons</NameTxt>
      <P>Could I say that it is appropriate that Motion No. 5 dealing with the reports on proposals relating to equality of opportunity should be on the <Col N="428" /> Order Paper at this time when we also have on the Order Paper a motion that Seanad Éireann takes note of the Joint Committee on Women's Rights Interim Report dealing with education.</P>
      <P>As a member of that committee I have a particular interest in looking forward to the debate on the latter motion.  There can be no doubt in anybody's mind about the extreme discrimination against women in every sphere.  I spoke about this at greater length last time that we were dealing with the motion on EC developments.  Some people may not realise that the rate of progress in rectifying this injustice is unacceptably slow.  In spite of legislation but possibly because this discrimination has been so long and deeply rooted in our society, movement to redress the problem is proving unacceptably sluggish.  Against that background reports such as this must receive an unqualified welcome.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>We have a wealth of information and reports from the EC on women's rights. In the European File No. 484 for February 1984 it goes into this in great detail and points out that in the European Community 52 per cent of women aged between 14-59 have a job or are looking for work.  The proportion is increasing under the double pressure of women's desire for independence and their need to boost the family income.  Out of a total working population estimated at 118 million, women account for about 44 million. Of these 69 per cent work in services, 25 per cent in industry and 6 per cent in agriculture.  Women are also to be found among Europe's unemployed. There are more women out of work than men in proportion to their share of the total workforce.  Women make up 41 per cent of Europe's jobless.  They are often the victims of the fact that their training is no longer suited to present-day economic needs.  The recession has also made women's jobs more vulnerable.  Unemployment has indirectly had a negative effect on the rights of women.  At the same time women occupy 90 per cent of Europe's part-time jobs.  Such jobs <Col N="429" /> frequently carry the same benefits as fulltime work.  They rarely lead to promotion or a more responsible job.</P>
    <P>The unemployment of women raises other problems which cannot be illustrated in figures.  Equality in education and training, equal pay and equal social security rights are objectives set by society, but in many cases there is still a wide gulf between principle and practice. We have a wealth of information on this problem in the area of discrimination against women.  I would like to quote three very short paragraphs from &ldquo;The Situation of Women in Europe&rdquo; which was published in May of this year.  I will quote from the foreword by Piet Danker. It states:</P>
    <P>It is no coincidence that the term &ldquo;equal treatment&rdquo; should recur so frequently; although the legal texts establish it as a general principle, in reality there is discrimination between men and women, and this cannot be tolerated by anyone, let alone a democratic institution such as Parliament.  Women have an inviolable right to play a full part in the life of society in all its forms, and can no longer be denied the means of doing so.  Although some progress has been made, women, when they are not trapped in their role as mothers find it difficult to rise to positions of responsibility in working life.  The few exceptions do not invalidate this rule, which is borne out by experience.  We can no longer permit differences in the treatment of working women and men, and it is the responsibility of the Community to ensure that the laws adopted on the basis of Community directives are observed.  Yet, at the same time, it must also ensure that, once the legal provisions have entered into force, indirect and insidious forms of discrimination do not deprive them of all effect.</P>
    <P>Action at the sources is needed to attempt to free our society from this regrettable discrimination: education and vocational training have a vital role to play here, while the advent of new technologies could also open up new <Col N="430" /> opportunities.  A great effort should be made to capitalise on them.</P>
    <P>Parliament has not confined its activities to making requests, it has also been instrumental in securing the necessary budgetary funds.  It will need to continue along this road.</P>
    <P>The report points out that the female unemployment rate in Ireland, unlike most of the other member states of the European Communities, is lower than for males.  Unfortunately the trends in registered unemployment here shows that female unemployment is rising, although the Industrial Development Authority, AnCO, the Youth Employment Agency and the National Manpower Service, according to the report, play an active part in seeking fair and just female participation in the employment area.  I believe there is a greater injustice than simple arithmetical equity in numbers. The type of work is most important. The joint report on Women's Rights at paragraph 10.2 stated:</P>
    <P>Since the early years of the present century the number of women teachers in primary schools has increased steadily with the result that today there are more women than men working in this area, where once men were numerically stronger.  The situation is unlikely to change in the foreseeable future because of the imbalance at entry to the Colleges of Education, where females now constitute over 70 per cent of the student population.  However, the predominance of women teachers, 15,500 (75 per cent) to 5,100 (25 per cent) is not reflected in the figures for posts of responsibility, with 53 per cent of principalships being held by men and 47 per cent by women.  A system in which 25 per cent of the work force holds more than half of the principalships illustrates the extent to which inequality between the sexes is entrenched in the teaching profession.  While the representation of women in the lesser posts of responsibility, i.e. Vice-Principal, Grade A and Grade B posts is more equitable, even in these grades, <Col N="431" /> male teachers, having regard to their overall numbers, hold a disproportionate number of the posts, i.e. 18 per cent, 33 per cent and 27 per cent respectively.</P>
    <P>I suspect that this denial of opportunity applies to every sphere of activity.  There is no doubt that the Joint Committee on the Secondary Legislation of the European Communities is firmly committed to removal of all obstacles which hinder the principles of equal pay for work of equal value and equal opportunities in all areas for men and women.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JimHiggins" hpid="Mr. J. Higgins Mr. J. Higgins">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J. Higgins</NameTxt>
      <P>The first thing I would like to do is to pay tribute to and compliment Senator Robinson for the vast quantity of work and the vast quantity of thought that has gone into the compilation of this very substantial and very worthwhile report and documents.  As regards the Council resolution on action to combat unemployment among women, one must agree with the approach recommended, that is of affording women access to the whole of the labour market and the taking of specific measures linked to the inherent characteristics of the unemployment of women.  Statistics have already been referred to recently on the other side of the House by Senator Fitzsimons.  It is true that although the female unemployment rate in Ireland is lower than that of males and runs counter to the general pattern within the EC, the disturbing feature is that the situation is getting worse and that the pattern is changing.  The two years 1982 to 1984 showed female unemployment increasing by 54 per cent as against 40.9 per cent for men.  The female share of unemployment total also increased.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The report draws attention to the substantial shift of female employment away from agriculture.  This has been, by various factors, considerably accelerated. Here I would like to take issue with two relatively recent decisions.  One is the cutting out altogether of the farm home advisory service; the other is the <Col N="432" /> closing of the rural home economic colleges, one of which is in my own county, County Mayo.  I am sorry that the Department of Education and ACOT and the Minister have seen fit to go along with this proposal.  It is a retrograde step. The colleges particularly did invaluable work in training housewives for life on the land in rural Ireland.  I have grave reservations about the decision.  I know that one of the reasons given for the decision was that the curriculum was alleged to have a too-high home economics content.  I personally do not think that the curriculum content as regards home economics was too great.  Even if it were I think every possible opportunity should have been availed of to try to modify or to amend or to readjust or to change the curriculum rather than close the colleges.</P>
    <P>At the time the decision was taken we were given assurances that the colleges would be replaced by something substantial and something worthwhile and something that was alleged to be more meaningful.  We are still awaiting for the emergence of this replacement facility. Until such time as there is a replacement facility there remains a void or a vacuum or certainly a gaping hole to be filled in relation to education for women in rural Ireland, particularly taking into account their desire to go back on the land or to be a partner in a farming enterprise. Furthermore, I believe that in relation to the previous point that I made &mdash; that is the phasing out of the farm home advisory service &mdash; another look should be had at this area.</P>
    <P>The report highlights a number of very stark statistics that have to be taken into consideration.  For example, the school-leavers survey of May 1983 regarding the 1981-1982 school-leavers showed that the highest proportion of young women were working in the service and clerical occupations and by contrast that most young men were working in the skilled and semiskilled or manual occupations.  In 1981, the service sector accounted for 75 per cent of all female employment, compared with 63 per cent in 1961.  Again, in 1981, 97,200 females were employed as clerical workers in comparison with 35,900 <Col N="433" /> males.  Forty-one thousand four hundred males were employed in administrative and management occupations by comparison, again, with 6,400 females.  We can see very clearly there a very definite pattern in relation to skills or particular areas of occupation.</P>
    <P>Because of the preponderance of women in the clerical and service areas new office technology and automation offer a considerable threat to the position of women.  It is from such a background as this that the report analyses the roles of various agencies, what they have achieved so far, what their aims and their targets are and what their training programmes are likely to be for the future. For example, AnCO's positive training programme and its return to work programme has been analysed and scrutinised very thoroughly and the deficiencies in relation to those particular agencies have been highlighted.  It is noted, for example, that girls currently outnumber boys on the youth training and work experience programme.  Again, there is such a high secretarial content in such programmes that this statistic is quite credible and quite believable.</P>
    <P>The Minister for Labour has charged the Youth Employment Agency with overall responsibility for ensuring that youth programmes provide adequate opportunities for young people of both sexes.  Unfortunately, however, the vast majority of youth employment schemes, which do excellent work, apart altogether from the facilities they provide for people in getting them into a pattern of work, of helping them to co-operate and team up projects with colleagues and in teaching them skills &mdash; and in my county alone there is something like £300,000 of projects ongoing &mdash; are of a manual nature and thereby girls are by and large automatically precluded from them although they have the option of participating should they so desire.</P>
    <P>One of the fears I have about the special employment programme whereby 10,000 people who are on unemployment <Col N="434" /> assistance can now be employed for two-and-a-half days per week for a wage of £70 without prejudice to any other earnings they may accrue for the other five days is that these jobs will be largely male-orientated or will have a large manual content so that when the figures emerge at the end of the year the vast bulk of the 10,000 people who will be taken off the dole queue and gainfully employed in the scheme, will be male.</P>
    <P>I welcome the conclusion of the Joint Committee that equal opportunities should be vigorously promoted particularly in the public sector as well as the private sector.  We should look to the public sector to provide the headlines and the guidelines in this respect.  Particularly I welcome the consideration by the Minister for Labour that a general policy framework be adopted for the public sector organisations.  The lead will have to come within the Civil Service, within the semi-State bodies, within the health boards.  The provision of basic prerequisites such as the provision of child care facilities is an essential part of such a framework.  Job-sharing is another concept to which we have paid lip service for a number of years, but by and large there is very, very little evidence of it on the ground.</P>
    <P>Women's educational prospects are largely conditioned by their educational preparation.  Here we look forward with some considerable optimism and with a degree of anticipation to the emergence of the findings of the Curriculum and Examinations Board.  Educational conditioning has by and large relegated women psychologically to the role of being an employee or to being seen both by herself psychologically and by outside agencies as an appendage of her husband.</P>
    <P>This in particular emerges in relation to another area of discrimination against women, and that is the difficulty for females in getting financial accommodation. Generally, irrespective of the amount of security they have <i>per se</i> or in partnership with their husbands or spouses, the husbands are still looked upon by the financial institutions as being better risk ventures than the wives.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="435" /> The report mentioned on page 23 that the reduction of working time for everyone could be a factor in remedying or certainly reducing unemployment.  A factor that I referred to previously in my contribution on the national plan, <i>Building on Reality</i>&mdash; I expressed disappointment on that occasion that this was not even referred to in this plan &mdash; is early retirement.  If this country is providing a stable livelihood or a living for people from the ages on average between 20 and 60 years of age &mdash; I am not saying it owes very little to these people &mdash; I believe these people themselves would be more than prepared to enjoy well-earned superannuation and retirement and that they could gainfully be given the money that is now being given to the 25-year-olds as dole, by way of retirement or pension benefit, and thereby create something in the region of 10,000 jobs in the public sector.  It is something that I will be pressing for.  It certainly will be in line with the EC thinking in general, and it is one of the allegations that has been made in this House today in relation to the insolvency figures.  By and large, we tend to be behind the rest of Europe: we tend to wait until such time as the directives are upon us and act in response to such directives.  It is something which is well worth-while pursuing from an equity viewpoint as regards creating jobs for young people and also from the point of equity and fair play to the people that are at the top end of the salary scale, the people who are 60-plus years of age.</P>
    <P>It is unfortunate that the industries which are most vulnerable such as the textile industry, clothing industry, leather industry, the ones that have gone to the wall most readily, are the ones that have the highest component or the highest element of female employment. I welcome the report and the recommendations within it, and I sincerely hope that the next time we sit down to monitor the report and discuss it progress will be reported under the various headings.</P>
    <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Business" RHead="of Seanad">
    <Title>Business of Seanad.</Title>
    <Col N="436" />
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I would like to remind the Senators that items Nos. 7 and 8 are being taken with item No. 6. There is no Senator in possession.  We will now take item No. 6 and with it items Nos. 7 and 8.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDooge" hpid="Professor Dooge Professor Dooge">
      <NameTxt>Professor Dooge</NameTxt>
      <P>I made some remarks this morning on the Order of Business in regard to the manner in which this House is treated by the Dáil.  When I see how this House has conducted itself from the lunch time interval one can hardly blame the Dáil for paying such scant respect, because the Seanad itself is treating itself with very scant respect.  Senators knew what the Order of Business was this morning.  Senator knew that items Nos. 13, 5 and 6 were to be taken and yet we have found the Chair in the position in which when item No. 13 had been disposed of, of looking around in bewilderment as no Senator offered.  Again, we have the position that Senator Higgins finished his contribution.  Some Senators will come around complaining that they did not get an opportunity to speak and yet when there was the opportunity to speak they were not here in the House. This is a matter for very, very serious regret and I feel, having made remarks about the way in which we had been treated with scant respect by the way in which certain business had been transmitted to us, it is only fair that I should be similarly critical of ourselves.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Developments in the European" RHead="Communities: Motion (Resumed)">
    <Title>Developments in the European Communities: Motion (Resumed).</Title>
    <P>Debate resumed on the following motion:</P>
    <P>That Seanad Éireann takes note of developments in the European Communities since January 1984.</P>
    <P Just="Right">&mdash;(Senator Ferris).</P>
    <Speaker pid="CharlesBMcDonald" hpid="Mr. McDonald Mr. McDonald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McDonald</NameTxt>
      <P>The period to which the motion relates is not one that will go down in the annuals of European history as having been of any tremendous importance.  There has been an amount <Col N="437" /> of difficulty and stagnation in the past 11 months.  Perhaps this indicates that there has been a greater upsurge of nationalism to a point among the Governments of the Ten.  This is regrettable.  Many true blue Europeans are looking with a certain amount of hope to the new SPARK Committee which is under the chairmanship of our distinguished colleague, Senator Dooge.  While I consider that the work entrusted to that committee has not made tremendous headlines except perhaps for some side issues, I pin my hopes on the committee being able to reintroduce into the Community the kind of spirit and the kind of prespective that enthused and fired the founding fathers to embark on this great ideal of a united Europe where countries and nations would talk out their differences and would plan the future together in harmony and co-operation.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I wish Senator Dooge every success and I hope that the work of his committee will give a very clear verdict and will map out what needs to be achieved and what needs to be done in order to bring back into the Community the kind of momentum that was there 25 years ago when the Community was starting off.  That is the important task.  Up to a few years ago the meeting of Heads of State was a sort of bastard affair in that it had not got a foundation in the Treaty itself.  It would have been better of if it had been left illegitimate for the simple reason that in the vast number of summits they clearly demonstrated their inability to rise over their own narrow-minded national interests. That is where we fail as a civilised Community.  We in Europe would like to preach to the rest of the world about how to run their business, whether we are talking to the Indians, the Africans or the people of the Carribean or wherever. Yet we cannot sink our differences at home.  We cannot appreciate the difficulties between one member state and another.  One of the major points on the agenda, I presume, in the coming week in Dublin Castle will be the enlargement of the Community yet again.  I look forward to the enlargement of the Community not so much from an economic point <Col N="438" /> of view but from a political and peace aspect.</P>
    <P>During the seventies both in Spain and Portugal were rescued back into the democratic systems.  Sometimes one thinks that democracy has lost its usefulness because people, at least in this country, find it more difficult to accept the democratic process from an administration point of view.  They do not wish to contribute extra taxes and yet they do not wish to lose any services they had grown accustomed to.  While everybody pays lip service to running the country as it should be run, it is very hard to accept the realities.  It is much the same in the Community.</P>
    <P>Some weeks ago I was shocked at the attitude of at least one Spanish trawler captain to our Naval Service.  We are not a warring nation.  We have not got a Navy <i>per se</i> but we have a naval section in our Defence Forces who have given valiant and distinguish service to this country since the State was founded.  It is unacceptable that any Spanish fishing captain should attempt to ram one of our few fishery patrol vessels and expect to get away with it.  If I were the Minister for Defence, and I suppose many would say thank God I am not, anyone who would offer any resistance to a fishery protection vessel would be blasted out of the sea.  I would say to the Taoiseach and to the Ministers who will be involved in negotiations for the next five or six weeks that the difficult problems surrounding Spain's entry to the Community must be settled and that we must have guarantees that the Spanish people will abide by them before anything is signed.  The way the Greek entry was negotiated was not the ideal but all the people involved should be able to learn from history.  I would not want to see that repeated again because it is unacceptable that we should expect any section of our population to suffer inordinately just to accommodate a new entry into the Community.  What we are talking about so far as Spain is concerned is our fishing industry.</P>
    <P>The species of fish that we have in our national waters in the main represent a species that are quota controlled and <Col N="439" /> quotas have been allocated.  If we bring in Spain, which we are told has a fishing fleet which is on a par with, or even greater than the combined fishing fleets of the Community of Ten, where are the quotas to come from?  It is unreasonable to expect that our population and our fishermen in particular should be left under a cloud.  It is of paramount importance to the Minister for Foreign Affairs and the Taoiseach that they should be left under no misapprehension in this regard.  There must be an agreement that is acceptable to this country and to the various sectoral interests before anything is signed.  We should not allow the situation to develop where Spain can be allowed into the Community on 1 January 1986 while leaving a number of difficult cases to be negotiated.</P>
    <P>On the question of the Portuguese entry I believe that it is a completely different case.  I would welcome the entry of Portugal to the Community as we welcomed that country into the democratic process after a prolonged period of dictatorship. In the short few years that they have had democracy a number of free elections have taken place and have been successful. One of the problems which does not directly affect us is on the question of sugar.  Portugal have a long standing arrangement with a number of their former colonies in Africa whereby they import a considerable tonnage of raw sugar.  This is refined in Portugal.  While that would appear to be outside the sugar quota system at present most people would agree that since the former colonies from part of the ACP there should be a special derogation provided for them. I would hope that our country would support that.  However, I do not wish to be misunderstood.  This year our sugar best farmers have been changed over to a quota system.  They found themselves in the summer, due to the fine weather, producing tonnage in excess of the quota they contracted for and having to feed the excess to cattle.  The Sugar Company are only offering £5 a tonne for it.  That is outlandish.  In the Government's programme, <i>Building on Reality</i>, the farmers <Col N="440" /> are being asked to pay a farm tax in order to stimulate production in an agricultural economy where every crop that is common to this country is being over-produced.</P>
    <P>I wonder what An Foras Talúntais and ACOT are talking about when they say that farmers should be penalised for not producing more.  I was horrified when at an Agricultural Science Association function Dr. Brendan Kearney made a speech on those lines.  It is something that is tied up in the Community.  While we have a very well developed Common Agricultural Policy we have not got long term policies or long term prospects in any field.  We are to enlarge the Community to 12.  We are taking in two countries a percentage of whose GNP would be agricultural based and we have not got agreement in the Community on adequate budgetary arrangements not only to accommodate the new member states but to meet the ordinary bills and running expenses of the present membership of the Community.  This is where the Heads of State do a tremendous disservice to the concept of a united Europe.</P>
    <P>It would be better if those various knotty problems were left to the Council of Ministers and not have a glamorous fall-back, namely the Heads of State or Governments.  I should like the SPARK committee to look at the institutions and their evolvement to see if it is worth while having these glamorous and spectacular meetings of Heads of Government.  We have not had a successful summit since 1975, one where there was tangible work and where there were decisions taken that have been implemented.  We cannot put the clock back.  We must find a way of making the Community work in order to bring the realisation and the visions of the people who set it up, but we are losing ground.  The enlargement of the Community is very important to everyone in this country, because it will have an effect on the economic and budget side and also on the living conditions of everyone in this State.</P>
    <P>Portugal is a food importing country. Two-thirds of their food is imported but presently it is imported on the world <Col N="441" /> market mainly from the US at prices which are much lower than the floor prices under the Common Agricultural Policy.  Looking at the figures for the Portugese budget it will be extremely difficult for them to pay the traiffs if they are to import all their requirements from within the Community or else pay the tariffs on the imports from the third world countries.  That has to be resolved, and it will be resolved if there is goodwill and if the wealthier countries are prepared, as they undertook to do when they signed the Treaty of Accession, to work towards a society where the wealthier regions would support the less developed and the poorer regions.</P>
    <P>For the past couple of months the lead story has been the famine situation in Ethiopia and in other African countries. It is important to mention this in the context of activities in the European Community.  The Community's allocation from the budget to development in third world countries, of which there must be 70 at present between Africa and the Carribean, is almost £4,000 million. That is a sizeable contribution.  One would hope that it would be all used to great advantage.</P>
    <P>I must compliment the Irish people in the way they responded to the plight of the starving millions of people in Africa. Most of the countries have defence allocations amounting to almost 30 per cent of their GNP.  Some of those underdeveloped countries do not seem to have a great interest in nourishing and looking after the ordinary welfare of their citizens.</P>
    <P>The only country in Africa that has any semblance of a social service is the Republic of South Africa, which often gets a belt in this House.  I would hope that the Community Committee for Development and Aid would examine the possibility of expediting development programmes as much as possible in the next few years to see if we can more or less short circuit the trend which is becoming apparent in many African countries where they are incapable of generating the food necessary to feed their population.  As a Christian country <Col N="442" /> we must be concerned with that problem. My own view is that the governmental agencies do not do enough in trying to co-operate with the non-governmental agencies.</P>
    <P>There are many fine voluntary agencies but perhaps with more co-operation between them and the mission people more could be achieved more quickly.  It might be very helpful, for instance, if the ordinary volunteers were financed to put in the infrastructures necessary and even to have Irish parishes adopt comparable areas in some of the African countries and to put in some of the necessary irrigation and perhaps set them up with food-producing co-ops.  I think that is possible, Many of our missionaries have done that on a shoestring.  If we could have people more readily identify the problems and bring them closer to the people it could be of greater benefit and perhaps bring greater momentum to the problem.</P>
    <P>I am sure everybody will recognise the tremendous input that the Irish Presidency has made in the past five months. The Taoiseach and his Ministers have worked extremely hard.  In a short time they have got a momentum into the Social Affairs Commission and into the progress that has been made in agriculture, through the problems are exceptionally difficult.</P>
    <P>I take this opportunity of wishing our out-going Commissioner, Mr. Richard Burke, success.  During his years with the Community he has, by his work, his input and his understanding of the system and of the role of the Community, carried out his duties in a manner that has brought great credit and honour to our own country. I wish his successor, Mr. Sutherland every success also.  I hope that at the end of his term he will report a big improvement in the cohension of the Community. I hope also that in the next few months we will succeed in getting agreement on the enlargement of the Community.  It is important that we have a united Europe and one that is prosperous.  The only hope of doing that is under the umbrella of the EC.  With the various Governments working together we should be able to achieve spectacular success, if we have <Col N="443" /> from the leaders of the Community countries the kind of unselfish input that the founding fathers dreamed of and in their own way set the pace 27 or 28 years ago.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JackFitzsimons" hpid="Mr. Fitzsimons Mr. Fitzsimons">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Fitzsimons</NameTxt>
      <P>I, too, welcome the comprehensive report which the Minister gave to the House.  There are many aspects of it with which we could deal and many aspects with which I am in agreement with other Senators.  The area of greatest concern is unemployment.  I, too, am very disappointed that so little has been done in this area.  Unemployment and housing are two of our greatest problems.  I suggested on a previous occasion that in some imaginative way something could be done to solve both these problems by engaging the unemployed in the housing area.  Something in general could be done by introducing shorter working hours or by a combination of all these factors.  Because of our high unemployment figures, something along these lines will have to be done in the very near future.</P>
      <P>We do not have any formal report to cover this period.  The last report which I have on file is the 23rd Report which was issued in January 1983.  As I said previously there is no scarcity of documentation on all the activities.</P>
      <P>In my contribution of 4 July 1984 I covered most of the areas with which I was concerned so there is no point in going over those areas again.  I mentioned at that time that we were awaiting reports of the planning regions towards development strategy to the year 2004.</P>
      <P>Debate adjourned.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Protection of Employees (Employers' Insolvency)" RHead="Bill, 1984: Committee and Final Stages">
    <Title>Protection of Employees (Employers' Insolvency) Bill, 1984: Committee and Final Stages.</Title>
    <P>Sections 1 to 5, inclusive, agreed to.</P>
    <P Just="Center">SECTION 6.</P>
    <Speaker pid="BrianJHillery" hpid="Professor Hillery Professor Hillery">
      <NameTxt>Professor Hillery</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 1:</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>In page 6, subsection (1), lines 29 <Col N="444" /> and 30, to delete paragraph (b) and substitute the following:</P>
    <P>&ldquo;(b) the date on which the employer became insolvent was not earlier than the 1st day of January, 1983, and&rdquo;.</P>
    <P>As I indicated on Second Stage we specifically wish to return to the question of retrospection.  The year 1983 was a particularly black one for insolvencies. It is our hope that the Minister will go some way towards meeting us in order to cater for the grave number of redundancies and the consequential losses of jobs that occurred in that year.  Essentially we are pressing for retrospection to 1 January 1983.  The Minister has indicated that the redundancy fund stands at more than £12 million.  He has indicated further that the additional cost to meet our amendment is estimated to be £800,000 to £850,000.  We feel that the fund could bear this additional cost and in so doing relieve the hardship of many people who are now in the ranks of the long term unemployed.  Since the proposed date of implementation of the Bill, that is 22 October 1983, is later than in other European Economic Community countries could the Minister not make this concession and backdate it to January 1983, Could I make the additional point that the Kilrush Pottery is of course, a particularly deserving case.</P>
    <P>As I understand it there were special circumstances there.  The employees were led to believe that they were getting early holidays.  They did not realise they had lost their jobs until the plant failed to reopen &mdash; a major lack of communication problem, obviously.  True, a worker directive would have helped in that situation. There is the point, however, that the State was represented on the board by a director of Fóir Teoranta and they still were misled in this situation.  I am not saying that he has a specific responsibility to inform the employees but there was a State presence on the board none-the less and perhaps that should have led to somewhat more enlightenment than at times we can expect from boards of directors.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="445" /> The case involved genuine hardship for many who have not since been reemployed as in so many insolvencies.  The amount involved in the case of Kilrush is relatively small, especially if the Minister accepts the compromise put forward by Senator Honan this morning of 1 April 1983.</P>
    <P>To recap, my general point is that we believe there is a case for retrospection to 1 January in any case, given the scale of the amount and the size of the Redundancy Fund and the fact that we are the last country in the EC to implement this directive, as I understand it.  Finally then, I want to make the specific point about Kilrush that, of course, it is in west Clare, where I was born and reared.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelSmith" hpid="Mr. Smith Mr. Smith">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Smith</NameTxt>
      <P>I would like to support Senator Hillery on this amendment.  The reason we are having this Bill at all is because of the hardships which were referred to on Second Stage and in the Dáil which are imposed on individuals when there are insolvencies of the kind that have been referred to.  It is very rare that we have proposals for amending legislation which would cover almost a full year and is estimated by the Minister to cost about £1 million.  It is unlikely that with a similar expenditure under any other Bill the Minister would be able to ease, in so many individual cases, the hardship that we are referring to.  The amounts paid individually would be small but collectively over the country would assist immeasurably in the situation.  In the course of the debate either in the Dáil or in this House this morning the Minister mentioned that he does not know precisely the extent of all the liquidations and similar situations in the country.  It seems extraordinary.  I am not saying we do not have detailed information.  We must have information on practically all of these, particularly a year or two later.  What kind of data processing do we have that the Minister can be in a position to tell the House that he does not know the extent of the liabilities and therefore cannot accept an amendment which <Col N="446" /> cannot be costed?  Most people would not accept that argument.</P>
      <P>It seems to us that the information required must be fairly readily available at this stage.  The amount of expenditure is not great and we feel that the Minister should accede to our request.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RuairiQuinn" hpid="Minister for Labour (Mr. Quinn) Ruairí Quinn">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Labour (Mr. Quinn)</NameTxt>
      <P>I would very much like to be in a position to move off the point of the date of 22 October 1983 but I find that I cannot, despite the very persuading arguments put forward by Senators Hillery and Smith and indeed, by the Leas-Chathaoirleach, on Second Stage.  Let me take up the last point made by Senator Smith in relation to statistics.  We are now in one sense, fortunately in the position where both our respective parties, Coalition on the one side comprised of two parties and Fianna Fáil both majority and minority administrations, have had sufficient recent experience of Government, in which we cannot really afford to throw stones at each other in relation to the quality of administration.  That said, the reality is that our statistics and our stattistical data base, to use the phrase that Senator Smith chose earlier is, frankly, in the area of labour and labour-related law woefully inadequate.  If I can refer to Senator Hillery in his professional capacity as some one who has a detailed technical and academic knowledge of this area, he would be the first to agree that there are whole areas that are of critical importance to Irish industrial and labour relations both in a sort of justice sense and economic sense, where the statistical data which we have is very inadequate.  This prevents us from either targeting in specific policy measures to cope with the particular problems on the one hand or alternatively, being able to say we can afford to take on a course of action because we can quantity the cost.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>This has nothing at all to do with Kilrush Pottery <i>per se</i> and I do not want it to be seen in any way as a refusal by the Minister or, indeed, by the Department or by the Government because I take total responsibility for the line I am taking.  This is not a vindictive refusal <Col N="447" /> by me to grant retrospective rights to wronged workers in Kilrush.  I take the point that Senator Hillery made.  It is precisely because we would have to extend the general right back to a particular retrospective date, whether it is 1 April or 1 January or whatever, but designed effectively within the Opposition's amendment to bring on board Kilrush, because that is quite clearly and quite understandably a concern that the representatives from Clare have and a concern that has been very stridently and strenuously argued.  We do not know, in extending that general right, what the ongoing complications cost, to be more precise, might be.</P>
    <P>Senator Smith said that he found it extraordinary that we did not know the number of insolvencies there were in our society.  The answer is we do not.  We have a reasonably good picture, probably to the accuracy level of about 90 per cent, of the number of companies that go into liquidation or receivership because they are court cases and there is a court decision consequent on them.  But not all the decisions of the courts are accurately transmitted at a level of accuracy that we would like.  Let us assume an accuracy rate of 90 to 100 per cent &mdash; I would not think it would be 100 per cent &mdash; that does not include companies that simply cease to trade, the companies that disappear in the night, so to speak, and in turn that does not include companies who in real terms are not companies at all but simply employers.  Take in agricultural Ireland the number of one to one employer-employee relations where, in fact, moneys might be outstanding that have not been paid.  This Bill when it becomes law will extend its solvency rights to every worker, not just those who work for companies but those who work for employers in whatever legal framework that employer was acting.</P>
    <P>Regrettably, a Leas-Chathaoirligh, the line we have taken has been to be cautious in the extreme because for every lack of caution, as it were, that we express to cover a rate of potential load on the fund we increase the employer's contribution. <Col N="448" /> I referred to the PRSI cost on Second Stage.  I am not arguing against the PRSI system.  It is basically a very sound system.  In many respects it is infinitely better than the flat-rate stamp contribution that it susperseded.  But an employer can argue and, indeed, employers write to the Community, because I hear this argument at the Council of Ministers in the EC where in fact, employer contributions are much higher than the 12 per cent that they are here, that it is contradictory for the politicians within the Community, both the left and the right of the political divide, to be saying that unemployment is the major issue confronting the Community where unemployment throughout the EC has doubled from 6,500,000 to 13,000,000 in the space of two-and-a-half years.</P>
    <P>That is the number one issue that concerns the very fabric of our society on the one hand and at the same time to be taking actions or enacting laws or passing statutes that have been the direct and immediate consequence of increasing the cost of hiring labour, as a net additional cost to the wages that have to be paid in a free collective bargaining system in the context of relations between employer and labourer.  They are the two constraining balancing factors: a lack of accuracy of statistics on the one hand which imples a certain degree of caution in the provision of the amount of money that should be made available, combined with a realisation that many employers, particularly employers who are in traditional industries which are labour intensive relatively speaking, find that their products are now subject to competition from products coming from Third World countries.</P>
    <P>A classic example in the Irish economy would be shoes, a very labour intensive industry by comparison with pharmaceuticals for example, which are subject to direct import competition from Third World countries, Poland, which has very low wages, or Far East countries and so on.  These employers and sectors of industry who traditionally have held, relatively speaking, large levels of employment are the very ones who are <Col N="449" /> most affected by any marginal change in their labour cost bill.  For that reason and having regard to the consensus of concern in relation to employment levels I am particularly sensitive to going back to Cabinet and looking for an increase in the contribution to the redundancy fund.</P>
    <P>The House is aware that this matter has been referred to at Second Stage and is obviously aware of the consultation within the Fianna Fáil Party.  We have had a fairly extensive discussion in the other House.  I am not presupposing that what was said in the other House should automatically be taken on board here. We start <i>de novo</i> in this House.  But the House is aware that there has been considerable discussion on this overall matter.</P>
    <P>One of the things that emerged during the debate in the other House and was referred to here was the relative size of the fund and the fact that it was substantially in credit to the tune of £12.5 million and, therefore, implicitly, that there should not be any great difficulty.  I do have to say that the level of redundancies, tragically, is still at an unacceptably high level.  The demand on the fund will be substantial.  That is not a soft £12.5 million sitting on the shelf that is not likely to have demands made upon it and therefore is capable of being picked up.  If the ratio is £1 million for the last year, approximately £850,000, based on our best estimates, for the ten months back to 1 January, that fund is used not just for that but for redundancy payments proper.  It is our considered judgment, cautious as we need to be, that the fund will just about cover the anticipated demands likely to be made on it over the next year or so, in the light of the figures that are known and published.</P>
    <P>I am making a comprehensive response because I really want to cover all the arguments in relation to it.  I recognise the justice of the case in general terms but you could say about all protective worker legislation that it has come too late for some individual workers.  Unfair dismissals came too late for those who were unfairly dismissed prior to the <Col N="450" /> enactment of the legislation.  Equal pay came far too late for the generations of Irish women who were exploited by unequal pay much as we would have like retrospectively to make payments to women who had been exploited over the years.  Equally, the elimination of the marriage bar in the Civil Service came too late for the women who were forced out of the Civil Service because they chose to get married like all of their male counterparts who had the right to stay on in the Civil Service.  Nobody suggested seriously at the time that all of the female Civil Servants who were forced out of the Civil Service on marriage would have the right of re-entry.  It would be nice to be able to correct the wrongs of history.  We are fortunate that the EC has forced this island to catch up with the rest of Europe in the pace of history which has been dictated, in social matters at least by more advanced and more progressive countries than our own, tragically, has been.</P>
    <P>Regrettably &mdash; I say so in that one &mdash; for the reasons I have enumerated, and I will summarise them &mdash; this is not a reflection on the Civil Service but a reflection on our collective periods of office &mdash; not having accurate statistics to calculate the full cost or to know the full extent, combined with a desire to minimise the cost of employment to the employer if we want to maintain the existing levels of employment and encourage employers to take on more people where they are currently in employment, coupled with the fact that a precedent in this area opens the door for retrospection in other areas, the consequences of which are just beyond our capacity to respond to at this stage in time.</P>
    <Speaker pid="BrianJHillery" hpid="Professor Hillery Professor Hillery">
      <NameTxt>Professor Hillery</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister has made a comprehensive reply.  I have to agree with him about the unsatisfactory situation regarding statistical material.  I take his point that in many fields, including industrial relations, policy decisions are being made without the necessary, the essential benefit of accurate statistical <Col N="451" /> information.  Could I add in that context, wearing my professional hat, that I appreciate the support of the Department of Labour for the research programme that we are actively pursuing? We look forward to that support in the future.  Interestingly enough, it is precisely in this area of statistical information on strikes and strike activities that we have devoted most of our efforts in the recent past and on which several research papers have already been published and a book will be published in due course.</P>
      <P>Given the inaccuracy or the relative uncertainty about the figures, it is logically follows that the Minister is only &ldquo;guesstimating&rdquo; as to what the number of redundancies will be and what the demands will be on the redundancy fund.  The same type of informed guess work applies to those who will qualify under this Bill. In other words, the Minister cannot say categorically now that the demand on that fund will be £1 million because of the uncertainty of his statistical information.</P>
      <P>I stressed that I have a particular interest in Kilrush and the Minister acknowledged that.  I appreciate his acknowledgment of that fact.  If the demands on the fund under this legislation are somewhat less than are anticipated at this time, would the Minister then review the question of retrospection of the fund and in particular the question of retrospection in the case of the Kilrush Potteries?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The Minister has touched upon a very important point about labour costs and the PRSI component of those costs, which has increased considerably in recent years.  I have a lot of contacts in the course of my professional work in the university with middle to senior managers who are in important decision making positions, as well as other contacts that I have in the employer field.  Almost invariably they refer to the growing PRSI burden as an anti-employment tax.  Fair enough, I can see that increased energy cost is an anti-employment tax, and a whole range of other costs.  The point I would make in relation to PRSI is that it, more than the cost of energy, is within the <Col N="452" /> Government's control.  To that extent reduction in the PRSI levels which are really vital for the maintenance of jobs and the creation of further jobs and the maintenance of incentive to go into business and to create jobs is so important that it is linked obviously with the whole taxation system.</P>
    <P>I do not want to broaden this discussion into reform of the taxation system but the fact remains that PRSI is a tax on employment.  We are now taxed to such a point that incentive is being killed and I think jobs are actually being lost.  For that reason I found it bitterly disappointing that in the recently published economic plan the findings of the Commission on Taxation were really dismissed in one sentence, saying that it was not feasible to implement them.  There are numerous well-considered ideas in the reports of the Commission on Taxation.  They deserve the closest possible attention as a means to maintaining jobs and to creating further jobs among other things.  If the lack of reform of taxation including PRSI, is due to administrative inertia or reluctance, that reason is not good enough because the political will should prevail in the interests of people and their jobs and in the interests of the community as a whole.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelSmith" hpid="Mr. Smith Mr. Smith">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Smith</NameTxt>
      <P>The first thing I want to do is to assure the Minister that we have no intention of keeping him here until Christmas Day on the Committee Stage of the Bill.  He did not appear to be a little worried about that.  At the same time I should remind him that the fact that something is debated for a long time in the Dáil is not necessary proof that we should not have a look at it here.  There is no greater example of that than the way the Lower House met some of the amendments which we put to the Criminal Justice Bill, which the Minister will appreciate they had for a lot longer than we had this one.  That being said, I take the point that it is very important to create a balance between employers' contributions as a proportion of overall taxation on them and the question of providing a proper climate and incentive <Col N="453" /> for additional employment.  We tend to exaggerate taxation.  I am not saying that it is not a very significant component but I would like to see a proper relationship between employer and worker.  There are many examples in the industrial field of what a company is able to do where the proper relationship exists between management and worker and where there is proper understanding of both their roles.  Even in times of adversity and in times when it is very difficult to create opportunities, some employers have been able to expand employment.</P>
      <P>The Minister's point is valid but does he think the position is helped by the kind of suspicion that is created between employee and employer when the person who has made a genuine contribution all his lifetime in terms of skill and monetary contributions is left in the lurch, as referred to on Second Stage?  A very definite contribution towards easing that kind of suspicion would be embodied in the comparatively inexpensive amendment, as far as the Minister is concerned, that we have put forward.  It looks as if on this occasion we are not going to be able to change our minds.  I would like to put it across in this way: in the case of workers who have been hurt in the way that many thousands of them have been in the past 12 months how are they going to view a new employer, an innocent employer in the future when they can point to that traumatic experience which had such a detrimental effect on them and their families?  There is a combination. There is not only the tax situation.  There is a question of removing these doubts, some of them historical, some of them true and some of them false.  It is in that total combination that we would like to be of assistance.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RuairiQuinn" hpid="Mr. Quinn Mr. Quinn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Quinn</NameTxt>
      <P>My thanks to the Senators for their contributions.  There is an axiom in relation to legislation that it really is very difficult to make any of it retrospective, certainly in relation to criminal law. You cannot have retrospective legislation <Col N="454" /> for self-evident reasons.  There are constraints in relation to this Bill that have to be balanced against the equity and justice involved.  We have made the Bill as retrospective as we think is possible and we have taken the date, 22 October 1983 which will cover a large number of the people who are affected.</P>
      <P>I welcome the contribution that the section in UCD have made towards developing our knowledge of research and I am confident that in the coming years we will be able to enter into a new arrangement with UCD to look at areas of research that are of immediate concern to the law-making process and to the Department of Labour.  I have to say, and I do not say it easily, that I really am not in a position to accept the amendments put forward by the Fianna Fáil Party on this matter having regard to the points that were made in this House during the course of the morning and this afternoon.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BrianJHillery" hpid="Professor Hillery Professor Hillery">
      <NameTxt>Professor Hillery</NameTxt>
      <P>Perhaps the Minister did mean that to be his final word on it but I just want to raise the issue again, just in case it slipped his mind, as to whether in the light of reviewing demands on the Redundancy Fund, and on that portion of it which will be payable under this Bill, if it was in a healthier condition or greater than is now anticipated, would the Minister be in a position to review it at that time for retrospection purposes?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RuairiQuinn" hpid="Mr. Quinn Mr. Quinn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Quinn</NameTxt>
      <P>I would be more than happy to do that.  I have set out the constraints that prevent me from accepting the amendment now but if those constraints were deemed to be far more cautious than necessary and if extra statistics emerge that enable us to put an accurate figure on the facts involved and we were in a position to respond without disrupting the equilibrium that we were talking about earlier on I would certainly give a formal undertaking to the Seanad to review it in the light of any subsequent legislative changes that might be needed.</P>
      <P>Amendment, by leave, withdrawn.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="455" />
    <Speaker pid="BrianJHillery" hpid="Professor Hillery Professor Hillery">
      <NameTxt>Professor Hillery</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 2:</P>
      <P>In page 8, subsection (2) (a), between lines 3 and 4, to insert the following:</P>
      <P>&ldquo;(xii)  entitlements arising in the event of a person losing his ongoing pension payments owing to his employer becoming insolvent&rdquo;.</P>
      <P>The point I want to refer to here is pensions and this received a fair amount of treatment this morning.  I indicated in the course of my Second Stage contribution that I would be returning to it on Committee Stage.  As I said earlier today, I find the reference to the possibility of a national income pension related scheme rather vague.  Certainly it in no way meets the urgency of present problems.  Perhaps I could ask the Minister if he is in a position to give any kind of indication as to when, as a result of the discussions which we are led to understand are active under the aegis of the Department of Social Welfare in this regard, progress of a substantial nature will be made in the completion of this scheme?</P>
      <P>Just to reiterate on a few of the points I made this morning, job losses are compounded by the loss of pension rights and contributions and both together make, of course, for a devastating combination. The most vulnerable people are those who have just turned 60 or those who have already retired and are depending on their former company's pension for income.  These people in an insolvency situation are left without pension or without a refund of their pension contributions at a time when they can do virtually nothing to remedy their financial situation.  Nobody can join a pension scheme if he is 63 years or over.</P>
      <P>I recognise that there is a cost involved in meeting the type of amendment we have moved.  The national income pension related scheme is no answer to the immediate problems and I would just conclude for the moment by asking the Minister again if he could give us a progress report on what is happening in relation to this proposed scheme.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="456" />
    <Speaker pid="RuairiQuinn" hpid="Mr. Quinn Mr. Quinn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Quinn</NameTxt>
      <P>I have done some work on that since this House discussed the matter and when the debate started.  The original thinking on a national income related pension scheme which exists in a number of other EC countries was published during the period when Frank Cluskey was Parliamentary Secretary for Social Welfare and was the effective Minister for Social Welfare in that Department, the Tánaiste at that time, Brendan Corish, being effectively Minister for Health.  The work that they did, which emerged in a Green Paper, was subsequently consolidated and expanded upon by Deputy Haughey, when he was Minister for Health and Social Welfare.</P>
      <P>In 1976 and 1978 two substantial documents were published which provided a framework in which a national income related pension would be contemplated. If I may use a political analogy, we are talking about a confederal system of pension funding rather than a unitary State system, because you have the base level of the State non-contributory pension scheme, to which everybody is entitled. Then you have a category of people who are entitled to a contributory pension if they have the stamps.  Senator Hillery referred to the anomaly that has emerged in the representations made to the Ombudsman for that category or group of people who are, in fact, fixed in time. The problem will not continue after 1987 &mdash; because they are a legacy from the past.  I have made personal representations to the Minister for Health and Social Welfare to have that anomaly removed provided we can cost it again and know what it is.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I have described the two kinds of State pensions that we have, the flat non-contributory and the contributory.  That is at one end of the scale.  At the other end of the scale you have the best positioned people pensionwise, the public service and the public sector pensioners who have an index linked or inflation linked pension which is not effectively funded in full by their contributions and for which there is no separate, independent pension fund.  All of the civil service pensions and the local authority pensions are paid out <Col N="457" /> of current account receipts, which is probably the most inefficient and economically wasteful way of providing for pensions.  They are very costly relative to the dependency ratio that we have in our society.  In between that you have large established companies.  Guinness would be the prototype of them.  There are other large private companies of more modern vintage like Cement Roadstone and others who have substantial pension schemes of one kind or another.</P>
    <P>The thinking, as I understand it, is that the guaranteed flat floor level of the non-contributory pension would become the basic building block unit to which people could add elements of company pensions or could make additional contributions. The norm is that you would get two-thirds of your average salary for the last five years of your working life and that that, somehow or other, would be index linked to take you through, on average, the ten years or so that people live after the age 65.  You have the floor of the State pension scheme plus whatever company pension you have had contributed to plus the possibility of being able to contribute extra stamps if you wanted to make provision for an additional pension.  Work and consultation has gone on with the pension institutions here, the largest of which is the Irish Pensions Trust which organises most of the pensions in Irish industry or certainly acts as a consultant. The thinking is that people would have the possibility in a manner similar to the way in which, although not exactly the same, people can take out insurance cover within the VHI.  You have a choice of deciding what level of cover or what level of comfort and what level of financial provision you want to make for yourself and you contribute accordingly within a range but that range provides a basic floor below which you are definitely going to get treatment.  You do not have to be in the VHI.  There is a national scheme that falls in below that.</P>
    <P>Designing something like that and getting it to integrate with existing contributions and getting credit for existing contributions is apparently where the technical difficulty is.  The cost of pensions <Col N="458" /> is something that is now a considerable worry.  I would say that for those of us who will be involved in political life over the next ten years, and certainly who will be involved in political life by the year 2000, the way in which the balance of payments and foreign borrowing has dominated political concerns today the major political economic problem facing our society will undoubtedly be the pensions crisis which is going to confront this country and indeed every other country in the EC within a period of 15 to 16 years.  You can simply take the level of people who are currently in the public service, take their age and extrapolate it to a pensionable period and make an assumption about their life expectancy. There is a downstream commitment of payment that the working population, which will be a declining or a static working population if all of the objectives, as distinct from political projections, are to be taken into account.  That is going to be an enormous task facing us as a political society.  We have an obligation to meet and answer it.</P>
    <P>I have read a number of articles on this and I have talked to a number of pension consultants about it.  It is an enormously complex, difficult area and its complexity and the fear about the downstream effects of it has brought a certain degree of reluctance to the people who are attempting to design a national income related pension scheme.  We had discussions in Cabinet on the matter when the national plan was being formulated and I am aware that the Minister for Health and Social Welfare is particularly committed to it.  What is not decided is the level.  There are two outstanding issues essentially, assuming that people can top up their contributions beyond a certain floor level.  This would also provide for the self-employed who are excluded entirely from the present system, other than for the non-contributory pension.</P>
    <P>There are two outstanding issues.  The first is what percentage of average economic income should the pension represent &mdash; should it be two-thirds of the average over three years or five years and what kind of provision can you and <Col N="459" /> should you make for indexation?  There are in our society categories of people who have the misfortune to have grown old on fixed pensions at a time of high inflation.  They have become increasingly impoverished with every month.  The most devastating sight is people whose standard of living and standard of expectation has actually gone down perceptively in their lifetime at a time when they really should not have to worry, the age of 69 through to 85.  There are widows and people who are very vulnerable in that regard.</P>
    <P>I do not want to turn this Committee Stage into an extended discussion on pensions but the question was raised in a general sense and in a very constructive spirit.  We are going to try to deal with it. We have the capacity to deal with it, but there are new factors on the horizon that, quite frankly, frighten people about the implications of a national income related pension, and therefore it has to be looked at very carefully.</P>
    <P>This amendment has been useful in focusing attention on the rights of workers who lose their pension entitlements. This House will recognise that it is not equitable or reasonable to think that a fund that is contributed to exclusively by employers &mdash; and it is my commitment to equity and justice rather than my commitment to employers that enables me to make this particular argument &mdash; a fund that is exclusively funded by employers should not be used as the source for maintaining a pension fund <i>in perpetua</i> for people who might live for 15, 20 or 30 years after the insolvency of a particular firm.  Everybody in the pension field recognises that pensions must combine a joint contribution element on both sides.</P>
    <P>I want to stress that this fund, the name of which has been changed from the redundancy fund to the redundancy and insolvent employers' fund, is a fund that is exclusively funded by employers.  The effect of the Fianna Fáil amendment, in equity terms, would be to oblige employers exclusively to fund pensions without reference to any kind of employee contributions. I do not think it is on equitable <Col N="460" /> terms.  In addition to that, there is the cost of it.  In the United Kingdom the average arrears they have been dealing with are two weeks of pay plus holiday money and some sick pay etc. up to a maximum of £211.  If for argument sake we call that four weeks at the maximum and it becomes £800 odd, call it £1,000 in round terms &mdash; that is the once-off commitment payment &mdash; and we scaled the contributions at a level to meet that kind of maximum payment, the cost of meeting a pension at the average industrial wage which is £7,500 or £8,000 at two-thirds of that level or one-third of that level for a period of ten years &mdash; you are talking about something that is running from a maximum contribution of £1,000 and I am using figurative figures so to speak, could over a period of ten years, extend to £40,000 if you accept that £4,000 would be the kind of pension that somebody on £7,500 might get and that they would on average be continuing on for ten years after their period of retirement.</P>
    <P>That is the relative scale of the problem if you accept it on the basis upon which I rested my figures.  For that reason it simply is not possible to contemplate that this fund could be utilised to maintain ongoing commitments.  It should come out of a broader fund.  In Germany, for example, companies are required &mdash; in, for example, the metal industry sector or in the construction industry sector &mdash; to be participants in that industry's pension fund.  If an individual company defaults, indeed it works somewhat similarly in the CIF pension fund at the moment, that industry as a sub-unit of the total economy picks up the tabs for defaulters within its own industry and continues on the main contribution.</P>
    <P>In the construction industry here, because the nature of the contracting business is such that companies frequently have a much shorter life span than an established manufacturing company, that necessity is clearly more evident. In Germany, in manufacturing industry you have a fund contributed by both the employers and the employees in a particular subsector and if one company <Col N="461" /> goes into insolvency then the ongoing pension entitlement is picked up by the rest of that group in the association. Something along that model is the route we are going to have to travel in relation to insolvency pensions.</P>
    <P>I apologise for going on at such length. I do appreciate the concern the Opposition have and the legitimacy of the argument which we will have to address, and we are going to have to do it and we are committed to doing it.  It is for the Opposition to ensure that we meet that commitment within the framework of the national plan.</P>
    <P>Senator Hillery raised the point that the most vulnerable person would be somebody who is on the age of 60 and about to retire and who suddenly finds that the pension commitment has gone because of insolvency.  That is obviously the case in Castle Brand which is going to be a point of particular anguish. Let us consider the case of a properly run pension fund, as distinct from the current account system that some companies have, administered by an insurance company or by somebody like the Irish Pensions Trust and of somebody who needed 35 years' contributions or whatever is the minimum threshold and who was making contributions to their employer for that fund.  However, the employer, as appears to have been the case in Castle Brand, was effectively misappropriating or misusing that fund or using the contributions for a reason other than that intended, as has been the case with PRSI and VAT where companies in difficulty have been using that cash as a form of working capital.  If workers have had money deducted from their salary as a contribution to a pension fund and that money has not been paid into the pension fund then this fund will back date and validate contributions for the previous 12 months.  That will protect those who might otherwise not have qualified for either a full pension or a substantial pension.  That is as far, quite frankly, as we can go.  We looked at the possibility of extending the cover beyond 12 months but the lack of statistics prevented <Col N="462" /> us from going much further.  The only thing we have been able to say is: &ldquo;We will cover and indemnify pension contributions for 12 months that were deducted from the employee but were not paid into the fund.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>I have given a reasonably comprehensive reply to the pension fund issue, which was the issue raised by Senator Hillery in general terms.  The commitment is there. I intend that it should be met and I expect the Opposition will remind us if we do not meet it and constantly keep us on our toes to do so.  It is in all our interests. There is the future problem that confronts all of us and will probably confront the kids in the gallery more in real terms than it will many of the people in this Chamber.  It is the major political problem on the economic agenda facing this country.  We are going to have to devise the most efficient and smartest way of dealing with it.  In the context of insolvency we have gone as far as we can.</P>
    <Speaker pid="BrianJHillery" hpid="Professor Hillery Professor Hillery">
      <NameTxt>Professor Hillery</NameTxt>
      <P>I want to thank the Minister for his comprehensive reply and for focusing in such a detailed way on this increasingly pressing issue of pensions.  I would add, however, that our amendment was in no way intended to convey the view that we saw the additional payments from this fund in respect of pensions as coming from the existing or an increased employer contribution only.  I go along with the Minister that that would be inequitable.  I was at pains to point out that what is inequitable is the taxation system as a whole and that that is in need of urgent reform.  I visualise that reform as actually easing the PRSI impositions on management and worker alike.  I found the Minister's comments about experience elsewhere very interesting. One of the merits of our membership of the European Economic Community is that we are brought into regular contact with experiences in other countries.  The Minister, of course, during this current presidency of the EC is in a particularly advantageous position to view what is going on elsewhere.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I would conclude my comments by <Col N="463" /> making a plea to the Minister that this valuable experience which he is gaining from his interaction with our European partners could be quickly translated into action in Ireland to meet our specific needs.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelSmith" hpid="Mr. Smith Mr. Smith">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Smith</NameTxt>
      <P>This amendment has arisen primarily because of the bitter experience in Castle Brand.  While this Bill as a whole catered for reimbursing workers who lose out on wages and salaries, on holiday pay etc. where a company becomes insolvent, the Minister will have to accept that a far more crucially important area for the workers &mdash; and I am not trying to minimise the effect of insolvency in relation to these payments &mdash; is the area of pensions. It is a fairly sacrosanct area.  People look forward to being able to support themselves and their dependants in their declining years, and to have any major upset in that area in a most traumatic and bitter experience.  This amendment, while it is of a general nature, specifically relates to the tragic situation in Castle Brand where employee contributions over the years had reached the sum of £190,000 but when the company went into liquidation it was discovered that there was only £76,000 in the fund.</P>
      <P>There are 14 or 15 Departments of State and sometimes one would think they were all working against one another and not in tandem.  If I were to establish a new industry in Nenagh and I went to the Minister responsible and the IDA I certainly would be able to get a fairly substantial grant to establish that new industry.  When an industry closes we have adoption grants and we have training grants.  We have a variety of funds to cater for both closure situations and preparation of people for adapting to new employment opportunities.  Very considerable sums of money are expended in that area.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>One of the reasons why we are not going to be able, at least at the present state of negotiations, to get this industry which, as I said this morning, has a long tradition and should have a fairly bright future, one which the workers and the <Col N="464" /> people of Nenagh have been very proud of, back on the road again is that there is an immediate stumbling block.  An incoming interest has a very substantial liability arising from the bad management of the previous management in the factory.</P>
    <P>I am trying to make the point that vast sums of money are spent to encourage people to start up something.  Is there a way, even if it cannot be done under the provisions of this Bill, of getting some commitment to the removal of this stumbling block, so that we could, on the one hand, protect the pension rights of the workers where they have contributed and, on the other, open the door for continuing an industry which to my mind can be viable again in the future?  I would ask the Minister when he is replying to give us some idea of whether there is any other way in which this problem could be approached, because it is a crunch one for the individuals concerned and indeed for the people of Nenagh generally.</P>
    <P>In so far as the pay-related scheme is concerned and the very comprehensive reply which the Minister has given I think the bottom line of what he said is that there are substantial differences of opinion, that it is going to be a difficult road to travel, that it is not certain to be implemented in the near future and that, therefore, we cannot rely on it as a substitute for the particular recommendation in this amendment.  Naturally we will be pressing to see if it can be brought forward, but on the basis on what the Minister has just said I think we cannot hope for that scheme in the immediate future.  In the light of that and my other comments is there another road we can travel, is there some other way in which we can transfer from existing incentives, funds which would assist us in the dilemma in which we are?</P>
    <Speaker pid="RuairiQuinn" hpid="Mr. Quinn Mr. Quinn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Quinn</NameTxt>
      <P>Let me try to reply briefly to the specific question that Senator Smith raised.  He has accurately described my sense of the timetable in relation to a national income related pension.  I think we will see the proposals within the duration of this Government, I am <Col N="465" /> talking about 1987, but as to its effectiveness and its integration I could not be more specific.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Senator Smith raised the question of how we can get over the problem in legal terms to remove the liability that any incoming interest might have in dealing with the receiver in the particular example that he referred to.  I think Senator O'Donoghue pointed out in his Second Stage contribution that effectively in order to do so, as I understand it, and there are people in this House who are better qualified in the technicalities and legalities of company law, but my understanding from the various briefings that I have had, and they are subject to correction is that for the State to selectively redeem in full particular creditors, in this instance pensioners or employers who are entitled to moneys due from the company in addition to what is covered in this fund, we would be breaking the queue of various other creditors, suppliers.  Revenue Commissioners, who have a preferential position, and debenture holders, whether they are banks or some kind of financial institutions.  What would be involved would be a substantial and fundamental change in company law in relation to liquidations and insolvency generally.  You would be making a new category of creditor and that would be the worker/pensioner whom the State would redeem in full which would be the example in Castle Brand and that, for example, the IDA in conjunction with the Department of Labour in assisting Castle Brand in 1985 to get of the ground would come in and specifically redeem the commitments or remove the liabilities in so far as they concern themselves with the pensioners of Castle Brand but would not have any obligation or responsibility for the creditors of any other kind who would be putting in a claim against the receiver and indeed the liquidator.  My understanding, which is subject to correction, is that for the State to do so legally under present company law you would have to have what is called a solvent liquidation in which all creditors and all claims would <Col N="466" /> be me and that therefore the cost would not be feasible.</P>
    <P>There is an argument, and Senator Smith was looking into it, in saying in a sense that workers and pensioners are different and more vulnerable than other kinds of creditors and that anyway creditors can have the benefit, if they are trading profitably of writing off this loss as a tax loss against the State, which in a sense is a form of indirect redemption. These are matters that will be looked at within the framework of the operation of company law.  In this instance we are talking about the rights that derive from liquidation of companies, or a company, or an employer under our company law.  I have nothing further to add to the general points that have been raised.</P>
    <P>Amendment, by leave, withdrawn.</P>
    <P>Section 6 agreed to.</P>
    <P>Sections 7 to 15, inclusive, agreed to.</P>
    <P Just="Center">SECTION 16.</P>
    <Speaker pid="BrianJHillery" hpid="Professor Hillery Professor Hillery">
      <NameTxt>Professor Hillery</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 3:</P>
      <P>In page 16, lines 19 to 25, to delete subsection (5) and substitute the following:</P>
      <P>&ldquo;(5)  Every regulation proposed to be made by the Minister under this Act shall be laid in draft before each House of the Oireachtas and the regulation shall not be made until a resolution approving of the draft has been passed by each such House.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>This amendment was put down because the same amendment was put down in the Dáil and from a very brief reference we got we understood that the Minister would consider it overnight and if he thought Deputy Ahern's line of argument was accurate he would bring in a Ministerial amendment today.  I have looked at the procedural change in the Ombudsman Bill and I think it is not quite what was intended in the amendment in the <Col N="467" /> Dáil.  I would welcome the Minister's clarification on that.</P>
    <Speaker pid="RuairiQuinn" hpid="Mr. Quinn Mr. Quinn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Quinn</NameTxt>
      <P>Deputy Ahern, on behalf of the opposition, proposed an amendment which he felt was in line with a new change that both Houses of the Oireachtas were anxious to introduce and that the Minister for the Public Service had sought to introduce in relation to the Ombudsman Bill.  Essentially there is a traditional provision, and it is a standard section that applies in most of our legislation, that where regulations are to be made under a particular Act the Minister makes those regulations in the relevant Department as empowered by the Act, that they have to be laid before the Houses of the Oireachtas or in some cases before the Dáil but generally before the Houses of the Oireachtas for 21 sitting days.  The sitting days is the critical element, and they cannot become operative until that time.  During the course of any of those sitting days they are effectively on the Order of Business and they could be raised by means of a motion.  What Deputy Ahern was proposing, the centre of which I agreed with entirely, which is why I gave the commitment very freely and very definitely in the House, was to change that procedure whereby the House would be consciously made aware that they were on the Order Paper and that you would not have the provision of 21 sitting days requirement and that time would be set aside in the normal working week where they could be debated or where they could be put through on the nod so to speak, but you would not have the 21 day provision.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>If I am summarising his argument accurately that was the basis on which he put down on behalf of Fianna Fáil the amendment in the Dáil to this Bill.  My response to him was that I accepted the principle of what he was saying and that if it was applicable to this legislation I would incorporate it, accept an amendment. I was not sure and he was not 100 per cent sure himself although he felt fairly definite that it was applicable.  The <Col N="468" /> undertaking I gave was that we would look at it; we could consult with the drafting office and with the relevant legislation he was using as the particular model and if it was the case I would propose the amendment here.  The intention was that we would go back to the Dáil this afternoon on the assumption that the Seanad would clear the Bill here.</P>
    <P>I now understand that what he was proposing was not immediately relevant to what is intended here, and I will read the particular note because it is quite specific:</P>
    <P>In the debate on the Ombudsman (Amendment) Bill what was being discussed were orders to be made by the Government or the Minister for the Public Service and not regulations. Any major changes which the Minister might propose to make in the provisions of the Insolvency Bill must also be done by order under section 11. However, the procedure to be followed in regard to the making of orders under this section is exactly the same as that provided for in the amendment which was to be made relevant by the provisions of the Ombudsman Bill.</P>
    <P>We are doing two things.  This Bill empowers us to make orders and regulations. Deputy Ahern's amendment refers to the possibility of regulations in addition to orders.  It is complex and technical. We have anticipated the provisions of the Ombudsman Bill so the orders &mdash; which are the ones that have to be come before the 21 sitting days, the provision that he was describing, are covered by this.  The regulations are the methods, the prescription, the prescribing of the forms and all those things which do not happen to come before the Dáil anyway. They are not affected by the 21 sitting days provisions.  They can be made as empowered by this Bill.  It is not necessary to improve the Parliamentary procedure. For that reason I have not sought to adopt his amendment or to have it moved here and have it taken in the Dáil.</P>
    <Speaker pid="BrianJHillery" hpid="Professor Hillery Professor Hillery">
      <NameTxt>Professor Hillery</NameTxt>
      <P>I accept that the Minister and his advisers have researched <Col N="469" /> the matter and, based on what he has told me, I am prepared to accept that that is the position.  I thank the Minister for the comprehensive replies he has made today on the various points.  He has not met us as much as we would like, but I referred in the course of my speech to the inadequacy of the time to consider the Bill for Committee Stage today.  I fully join with Senator Dooge in deploring the limited amount of time we have for consideration of the Bill.  Given its urgency we are prepared to support it, but I would ask the Minister to put on the record that as far as he can personally control the pace of legislation within his Department in future that he will do his utmost to ensure that we will have adequate time to consider all Stages rather than the rushed manner in which we had to deal with this important Bill today.</P>
      <P>Amendment, by leave, withdrawn.</P>
      <P>Section 16 agreed to.</P>
      <P>Sections 17 and 18 agreed to.</P>
      <P>Title agreed to.</P>
      <P>Bill reported without amendment, received for final consideration and passed.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RuairiQuinn" hpid="Mr. Quinn Mr. Quinn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Quinn</NameTxt>
      <P>Could I make two observations? I want to thank the House for the consideration it has given this Bill at such short notice.  I am a first parliamentarian and secondly an office-holder.  I expect with a reasonable degree of forecasting accuracy that I am more likely to be longer in my role as a parliamentarian than as an office-holder, so my primary loyalty remains with Parliament and its procedures.  I appreciate that Senators have waived some of their fundamental rights today in granting a quick passage to this Bill.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TrasHonan" hpid="Mrs. Honan Mrs. Honan">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Honan</NameTxt>
      <P>Only for you, Minister.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RuairiQuinn" hpid="Mr. Quinn Mr. Quinn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Quinn</NameTxt>
      <P>I appreciate that, but I anticipated that there would be a degree <Col N="470" /> of consensus in relation to the provisions of the Bill, and therefore I would like to say that it is my intention to bring in and to move in this House first the worker participation legislation.  We can then have a comprehensive discussion on the question of access to information and the relationship between employer and worker.  I believe the House will be in a position to make a substantial contribution which will inform the debate in the other House.</P>
      <P>I would like to acknowledge and pay tribute to the work that has been done in my Department by the legislative section and by the officials here with me today, Mr. Fitzgerald and Mr. Fallon, and to invite the House to contemplate that we frequently pass legislation in both Houses without recognising the amount of work that has to be done in formulating it and particularly in this case where we are trying to comply with an EC directive and get detailed, comparative analyses from other countries.  That takes time and effort and a degree of commitment which was very much evident within my Department.</P>
      <P>The second task is that the Bill has to be administered.  While the work of the Seanad is now over, in one sense the work of the officials in the Department commences in terms of completing the regulations and devising the system and the method of payment and the method of checking that will ensure that the provisions that have been democratically provided for in this Bill will be efficiently carried out.  As politicians, as parliamentarians and as office-holders, we do not pay adequate or sufficient tribute to the people who carry out with great anonymity and self-effacement the task which has the potential in this instance of making a happy Christmas for a lot of people which they would not have had if the Bill was not taken so quickly today.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Protection of Employees (Employers' Insolvency)" RHead="Bill, 1984: Motion for Earlier Signature">
    <Title>Protection of Employees (Employers' Insolvency) Bill, 1984: Motion for Earlier Signature.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDooge" hpid="Professor Dooge Professor Dooge">
      <NameTxt>Professor Dooge</NameTxt>
      <P>I move:</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="471" /> That, pursuant to subsection 2º of section 2 of Article 25 of the Constitution, Seanad Éireann concurs with the Government in a request to the President to sign the Protection of Employees (Employers' Insolvency) Bill, 1984, on a date which is earlier than the fifth day after the date on which the Bill shall have been presented to him.</P>
    <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Developments in the European" RHead="Communities: Motion (Resumed)">
    <Title>Developments in the European Communities: Motion (Resumed).</Title>
    <P>Debate resumed on the following motion:</P>
    <P>That Seanad Éireann takes note of developments in the European Communities since January 1984.</P>
    <P Just="Right">&mdash;(Senator Ferris).</P>
    <Speaker pid="JackFitzsimons" hpid="Mr. Fitzsimons Mr. Fitzsimons">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Fitzsimons</NameTxt>
      <P>We are very grateful to the Minister for his very full report to the House.  The Minister in his speech referred to the solution to what he said was the most intractable problem, that of the British and German contributions to the Community budget.  The UK rebate amounted to £720 million this year and two-thirds remission on its VAT payments from next year onwards.  There are many people who would look on this as an imposed solution rather than an agreed one.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>In congratulating the Members elected to the European Parliament it is necessay to point out that that the turnout for the elections was disappointing.  The turnout in Ireland was 47.6 per cent, which was the second lowest in Europe.  The dubious distinction of the lowest turnout belongs to the United Kingdom at 32 per cent.  With regard to the super-levy, there are very many people who are disappointed with it, particularly with the bungling of figures by the Minister for Agriculture.  There are many people concerned that unfortunately this country <Col N="472" /> will suffer because of this really unforgiveable error.  I referred earlier to the reports of the seven planning regions. They have all held seminars to decide on development strategy to the year 2004.  I repeat that I hope they will be able to accommodate the changes of emphasis from single projects to programmes, which is absolutely essential.</P>
    <P>I would be very interested, as I am sure other Members of this House would be also, in getting reports from all the seminars. I intended to say on the last occasion in July with regard to my native county, Meath, that there is a considerable area in north County Meath which many people in public life have claimed could be included as a disadvantaged area.  I would like to add my voice to theirs.  I am proud of the fertile fields of my native Meath.  But I would point out at this fertile area does not coincide with the borders of the county.  The soil survey, for example, carried out by the Agricultural Institute and other projects by the Department of Agriculture and ACOT, led to the conclusion that there is a large area of land from Moynalty onwards which could probably be included in the disadvantaged area.  I would urge that this be looked at again.</P>
    <P>We have dealt fairly adequately with the aspect of discrimination against women.  There is a large volume of reports from the EC.  In my previous contribution I dealt individually with those.  This will be coming up again next week when we are dealing with the Interim Report by the Joint Committee on Womens' Rights.  As one who took part in the committee, I look forward to making a contribution then on this subject.  I want to say in passing that things have changed very rapidly because women in general will not put up with conditions that obtained many years ago. We used to have a phrase then that the mother's place is in the home.  As we all know now, this is no longer accepted. There is no great reason why this should be so, any more than that the father's place is in the home.  The big problem which we are trying to solve is that women will break out of their traditional <Col N="473" /> roles and that all positions and situations will be open to them.</P>
    <P>Adult education is an area in which I have a special involvement.  It is also an area which could benefit far more from the EC.  I believe that there is no reason why people at any age cannot qualify in different areas.  For example, the man working on the road who retires at 65 years could very well go to university and take out a doctorate.  There is no logical reason why he should not, if the facilities were available for him and people like him.  Adult education is something which had been included in the interim report on education by the Joint Committee.  I have some involvement with adult education in County Meath and a great step forward has been made in recent years. I was one of a number of people involved in teaching a diploma course who visited the UK last year.  We saw there at first hand what was being done by adult education. We visited Waltham Forest.  While I know it would be impossible from one short visit to pick up all the details, it seemed to me that the United Kingdom is benefiting far more from the Social Fund in the area of adult education than we are.  We saw their situation where all subjects were being taught.  There were créche facilities available.  Generally, more funds were being spent than are available in this country.</P>
    <P>In our report of the Joint Committee on Womens' Rights we urged that child-minding facilities would be provided for all housing schemes in the future and for all existing schemes where this is possible. It seems to me that, if this is an area which qualifies under the Social Fund, perhaps it would be possible to have those provisions made through moneys from the fund.  Overall, much more could be done in the area of adult education.  We should qualify for a far greater percentage of the fund than we have been receiving up to now.</P>
    <P>In the area of rehabilitation we could qualify for far more than we are receiving. In my local paper, <i>The Meath Chronicle</i>, a few weeks ago there was an article which suggested that the funds for the coming year would be drastically <Col N="474" /> reduced in the area of rehabilitation because there is some concern that the criteria for qualifications are being very strictly applied from now onwards.  Sheltered employment does not qualify for assistance from the Social Fund.  Ireland and Greece have a very little statutory provision on sheltered employment.  The State did not see the disabled requiring special legislation, so the work was left by and large to voluntary organisations. But the health boards have a statutory duty to look after the disabled.  Since the function of rehabilitation has been taken out of the Social Fund and because the budget has got tight the criteria are being applied strictly from now onwards, and I hope that this does not result in a situation where many of the people who are being looked after at present will be neglected.</P>
    <P>I believe that in this area there are four categories: those people who are in institutional care, and they are well looked after; also the day-care level which is the responsibility of the health boards, and those with an ability to work but whose productivity could not compete on the open market, and, lastly, training for open employment.  It is my belief, and there is not too much information available on this as far as I can understand, that only the last category will qualify for funds from the EC.  I would hate to see a situation where the health boards would suffer because I have visited a number of institutions over the last few years and I saw the work that was being done for the handicapped and for the disabled.  I saw them in situations where they were happy, where they had something to work for and something to look forward to.  I would make a plea that any shortfalls in this area from the Social Fund would be made good by the Government.</P>
    <P>In the area of the environment I did on the last occasion refer to the problem of smog particularly in Dublin.  I see that this has become a subject which is being debated in depth very recently.  An Foras Forbartha have produced a booklet <i>Air Quality in Ireland</i>.  It was published in June this year.  They have been designated <Col N="475" /> by the Minister for the Environment as the National Air Pollution Data Base Centre.  The booklet is well worth studying.  It does also deal with the problem of acid rain, and while in general for the country it points out that there are no problems, it does state on page 10 that &mdash;and I will quote this short paragraph:</P>
    <P>On a regional scale, however, the picture that emerges is somewhat different. In Dublin, in particular, the air quality is now a greater concern than in the past, due to rapid urbanisation coupled with a significant increase in the use of solid fuel within the domestic sector.  The Dublin conurbation is expanding rapidly, and with about a million people already located within an area of about 290 square kilometres it is one of the fastest growing cities in Europe.  Urban growth is also occurring in other centres such as Cork, Limerick, Waterford and Galway, and so the air quality in these areas also warrants attention in the future.</P>
    <P>I would like to see a situation where some positive action will be taken on the lines of the Report on Air Pollution: Conservation and Protection of the Environment by the Joint Committee on Secondary Legislation of the European Communities which was published on 11 April this year.  I am sure the Minister will take the recommendations into consideration.</P>
    <P>With regard to energy I did also deal with that matter on the last occasion.  I dealt with the finances that were available to this country in the quota and non-quota sections.  I believe that Irish participation in EC energy research and development programmes has resulted in financial assistance of approximately IR£7 million in the last ten years.  Ireland has received 1 per cent of the first four-year research and development programme and 2 per cent of the budget allocation for second four-year energy research and development programme. In the demonstration programme Ireland received 1.7 per cent and 3.9 per cent of <Col N="476" /> the total budget allocation for the 1979-83 and 1983 programmes respectively. Altogether 62 research and development projects were funded through direct and indirect actions in the last two four-year programmes and the total value of EC contributions to Irish research and development contracts was IR£1.9 million.</P>
    <P>Though only 17 Irish demonstration projects received funds from the demonstration programmes financial aid for these programmes amounted to almost IR£5 million.  I would like to see something more being done in the domestic area.  We have reasonably good grants for the provision of conservation of buildings and this is mandatory in new buildings. We still have more or less the concept of the open fire where stoves would be far more economical.  I did say before that I believe there was a competition to determine the best type of stove for the fuels that are available in this country, and I would like to see grants or some kind of financial inducements to people to use stoves instead of the open fire.  I would also like to see some grants for the provision of systems of solar heating, direct solar heat, for example glass porches which would make a sizeable contribution in the domestic area.  Perhaps we could allow, for example, in new houses where we have maximum floor areas specified some provision for the addition of solar porches to exceed this limit.  I do not think there would be anything to be lost, and there would be everything to be gained by that provision.  There should be special grants for heating our water supply by the solar method, and indeed some years back it was possible to purchase packages in some of the builders' providers but now these are not available because there was no demand for them.</P>
    <P>I agree with everything that has been said by the other Members with regard to Ethiopia and all the Third World and deprived and developing countries, and I hope that the aid which is being provided will be continued on an on-going basis.</P>
    <P>Fisheries was dealt with before, and we will have this problem to a greater degree with the accession of Spain and Portugal to the Community, and as some <Col N="477" /> Members have pointed out these countries have fleets which are perhaps 20 times greater than ours.  This will pose a problem.  It seems that in an island country such as ours even still we have not availed of our position in respect of fisheries. I am most indebted to Professor Dooge for the very full information he gave in reply to my question on the last occasion.</P>
    <P>We are also further behind in forestry than we should be.  Finally, I welcome the new plan in the Community to fight poverty.  It was reported in the Community report for October-November that the long term and young unemployed, the elderly, single parent families and refugees are among groups identified for priority treatment in the fight against poverty according to a new Commission proposal for specific action on poverty. The proposal aims at a five year programme of action and research among these and other population groups who fall outside the grasp of social protection measures.</P>
    <P>Community action to combat poverty was initiated in 1974 when a social action programme was introduced.  At that time some 30 million people in the Community of Nine were thought to be living on less than half the national average wage of their country.  Since then the growth in the number of one parent families, youth unemployed and refugees has made the situation more severe.  The Commission proposal would help cross-Community action to combat poverty and ease the way to finding solutions.  The schemes envisaged would be based mainly on cooperation action by the member states. The research programme will cost an estimated £25 million.  I welcome this heartily and I hope that we will benefit to a proper extent from this money.</P>
    <Speaker pid="RichardHourigan" hpid="Mr. Hourigan Mr. Hourigan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hourigan</NameTxt>
      <P>This motion encompasses an area so wide that it is very difficult to know precisely the sort of aspect one should lay emphasis on.  There are a number of matters in relation to the EC that are quite striking at present. Since our membership of the EC began in 1972 we have benefited quite substantially <Col N="478" /> from that membership.  In the past 12 years our country has gained very significantly in financial terms.  At the same time certain prices have been paid.  We must not lose sight of that either.</P>
      <P>We are substantially a net beneficiary as a result of our membership of the EC.  On the cost side we have the whole unfortunate unemployment situation which has arisen due to a certain extent to inability on our part to compete with our European partners in many areas. That is very serious.  In any review of this situation we must take into account not alone the economic aspects to which I have referred but also the whole spectrum of the political dimensions.  We must consider also the social implications in every respect.</P>
      <P>On the political aspect, as I have stated in this House before, I am not so sure the Ten can afford to have Spain and Portugal as members.  While politically it is desirable that they should become members, economically I pose the question whether we can afford to have them. This question has been raised by other speakers also.  It is a very important consideration at a time when we have these various surpluses in the areas of milk and other dairy products, of wine and grain and, potentially, in the area of beef.</P>
      <P>On the question of the applications of Spain and Portugal, we must examine very closely and very carefully the implications for us of having these countries in the EC.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>It will be acknowledged and recognised that Spain and Portugal are essentially countries not unlike Ireland.  They are classed as underdeveloped countries and consequently they are areas which would perhaps draw most on the resources that we ourselves get as one of the underdeveloped countries of the Ten.  With the exception of Southern Italy and perhaps Greece we could be classified as the most underdeveloped of the total membership of the EC.  Bringing in other countries with fairly substantial populations is something I would question.  I acknowledge that there are overriding political reasons for the Community being extended but one has to weigh all the <Col N="479" /> arguments against each other.  The question of affording something at a given time should not be forgotten.  In that context it applies to a country which should not have gone along a certain route and yet has done so.  We have bitter experience of this in Ireland.  We pursued certain economic routes and now we are suffering the consequences.  We are in a very serious economic position.</P>
    <P>The EC, I should like to make it clear for the record, has been extremely important to us.  It will even be of greater importance to us in the future.  At the same time we have to make our presence very strongly felt at European level.  We must remember that most of the decisions that affect our economic life and our entire lives are taken not in Dublin but in Brussels.  For that reason our Government at all times must be totally vigilant to ensure that the decisions taken do help us, are decisions in the direction that will give us benefit in various areas.  Too often we forget that we are now part of a greater Europe and that Government decisions are limited in terms of the assistance they can give to us as a nation.</P>
    <P>We are only too familiar with the exclusion, by reason of the rules and regulations of the EEC, <i>vis-à-vis</i> national aids. We are prevented as a country, as are other member countries, from giving certain national aids that would obviously be beneficial to us.  As another Senator remarked today, we are classified and regarded as good Europeans in that we have always obeyed the rules but let us be frank about it: we are in partnership with other persons who at all times do not obey the rules.  Certain countries have strayed away from the absolute rules and have applied their own set of regulations to certain aspects.  In these instances the country concerned is admonished and given a certain amount of time to correct the position.  This goes on almost continuously. It is something we should be wary and mindful of.  I am not in any way suggesting that we ought not comply with the rules and regulations but we should be aware that rules and regulations are <Col N="480" /> not always adhered to by our partners in Europe.</P>
    <P>There remain some issues that are in need of a great deal of tidying up.  We have still to finalise as a Community the whole question of funding and the whole question of own resources.  That is an extremely important point.  We have to tidy up very considerably the whole agricultural policy.  The question of the enlargement of the Community is also very important.  There are many areas related to these and one could talk for a long time about them.</P>
    <P>On the question of the agricultural situation, we are in a unique position in so far as our dependence on agriculture is very much greater than that of our European partners.  If there is any hiccup in the system as far as agriculture is concerned it seriously affects not just our farming community but our entire population.  In this context there is a greater need to establish a better understanding between the urban and rural sections of our society.  We have had examples of the way in which problems in the agricultural area affect our entire economy.  We are in the midst of uncertainty at the moment in regard to the milk producing area of our economy.  Milk production is extremely important for our economy.  A great percentage of our farmers depend directly on it and practically all our farmers depend indirectly on it in so far as they get their livestock from the dairy herd.</P>
    <P>Farmers do not know what the future holds for them.  They are told that the position <i>vis-á-vis</i> milk production will not be made known until about next March. I would urgently say to our Government that we must get clarity of the position long in advance of that.  We have many people who have now produced up to quota level.  They have produced up to a level to which we were allowed to produce in 1984 above the 1983 level and from now on they are to pay a penalty of up to 92p per gallon on any extra milk produced.  If this happens it will create an intolerable situation but what is even more serious is the total lack of clarity <Col N="481" /> with regard to 1985.  This is very damaging. It will undermine our entire economy. There are a number of people who are seriously affected in the whole employment sector by this matter of lack of competitive ability to which I referred earlier.  This is the biggest single social problem facing our country at this time. It is a matter that we cannot easily overcome. Nevertheless every effort is being made by the Government to try to overcome the difficulty of a major unemployment situation.  I am satisfied that the national plan will contribute a great deal towards that.  On its own accord it cannot be seen to provide all the answers but it will go a long way to helping the situation.</P>
    <P>Fisheries has been mentioned and this question has particular relevance in the context of an enlarged European Community. On a general basis there are just a few points I should like to make.  There is the whole question of price fixing and also the question of quotas.  Quotas are fast becoming the order of the day and must be established long in advance of the producing year so far as agriculture is concerned.  We have benefited also from the Regional and Social Funds though not to the extent that we would have wished.  There is an urgent need for our Government to ensure that we get as much clarity, as clear a direction as we can and as soon as we can, in particular in relation to this super-levy which is a very important issue.</P>
    <P>I shall conclude by saying that our Government and in particular our Minister for Agriculture, achieved a great deal earlier this year in getting a 4.6 per cent increase on the 1983 production level. We hope that further progress will be made next year but it is important that the position is clarified at the earliest date possible.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JoachimLoughrey" hpid="Mr. Loughrey Mr. Loughrey">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Loughrey</NameTxt>
      <P>Developments in the Community are relevant to the countries to which they relate.  The biggest single development that has taken place with regard to the area from which I come was the travelling of a delegation of two <Col N="482" /> officials and eight councillors from Donegal to Brussels to put a case for our county.  I do not understand why that event was not mentioned in the national press.  The press can be critical often of public representatives by way of blaming us for wasting money or of not doing our work as public representatives.</P>
      <P>We as members of Donegal County Council went to Brussels on a two-fold mission: first, to educate ourselves in the ways of European affairs and, secondly, to apply what we learned to the specific needs of the county we represent.  The national papers referred to the cost of the trip and mentioned a figure in this context of £16,000.  It has since been shown that the trip cost Donegal County Council less than £6,000.  Telefís Éireann participated in this decrying of our trip by sending cameras to Donegal County Council.  If our national papers and our television service had nothing better to do than to try to suggest that councillors or other public representatives are simply leaving this island to go on junket trips, their concern for the welfare of the citizens of our State is doubtful.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>We went there to educate ourselves on the methods of Europe and to put on record the needs of our county.  I will talk about one or two of those needs.  We have, for instance, in Donegal an area that is badly in need of a water supply, that is, Letterkenny town.  If Letterkenny and the areas surrounding it, as well as the north-west of Donegal are to develop, there must be a proper water supply.  That water supply is available within eight miles of the town in the River Lennon.  One may ask why we cannot bring water from the River Lennon to Letterkenny.  The answer is that the River Lennon is causing grievious and serious flooding in the area through which it flows causing damage to thousands of acres.  It would seem on the surface that to take water from the Lennon would help to alleviate the flooding somewhat, yet that is not the case.  Farmers living along the River Lennon feel that if water is extracted for consumption purposes from the river their hopes of ever having <Col N="483" /> it formally drained will end.  We went to Europe to put this case.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickJReynolds" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>That was the correct place to put the case then.  I am not sure as to how relevant the Senator is now.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoachimLoughrey" hpid="Mr. Loughrey Mr. Loughrey">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Loughrey</NameTxt>
      <P>We went to Europe to put this case specifically to those in Europe in charge of the funds for which we are applying.  We learned there that the Regional Development Fund, as from 1 January this year, was allocated by a different method whereby the base allocation to each member state will be given and the total of those base allocations will be only 88 per cent of the total allocation whereas each member state may surpass that base allocation.  If all of these allocations were taken up they would reach 112 per cent of the allocation. It does not take a mathematician to realise that you cannot take 112 per cent from 100 per cent but some of the member states can take more than their lower quota.  Some of them can exceed the 100 per cent.  This is where I would call on our national representatives to press to ensure that Ireland gets more than its share of the Regional Development Fund.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>If they want to make a case as to where they might spend the money, I will try to help them along those lines by citing the case of the River Lennon and the water supply for Letterkenny town.  These are very important matters.  It is important that they be brought up at European level and that we do not visualise the European scene as something over there as distinct from something to which we belong, to which we in this House are contributing as a nation.  The Community should be about the development of the poorer regions by way of funding from the richer areas.  We on the west coast have felt for some time that the classification of the whole of our country as one area has damaged the west because it is only natural that things will gravitate towards the east coast or towards the cities.  It is imperative therefore that we make a stronger case for the west, for the particular needs of places like Donegal, for the <Col N="484" /> draining of the Lennon.  As urbanisation continues these matters become increasingly important.</P>
    <P>Debate adjourned.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Adjournment Matter. -" RHead="Air Pollution Levels">
    <Title>Adjournment Matter. - Air Pollution Levels.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="AlexisJGFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. FitzGerald Mr. FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>First, I should like to thank you for facilitating me this evening in raising this issue on the Adjournment and in particular I thank Senator de Brún who gave way to this motion on the Adjournment because of its urgency.  His motion, I understand, will be tabled and taken next week.</P>
      <P>I am spokesman for this side of the House on planning.  I wish to speak in particular about a certain industry in Ranelagh which is causing some distress. I would like by way of introduction to say that Ranelagh to most people in this city of Dublin would have been, over the years, a pleasant inner city residential area.  The chief health inspector's report of 1982-83 reveals for the first time that the Ranelagh-Rathmines area of the city along with Ballyfermot and Cabra have exceeded for the first time the sulphur dioxide smoke levels laid down by the EC, an increase by 50 per cent on the 1981-82 winter.  I hope the Minister faces up to the urgent need to introduce gradually smoke free zones in this and other parts of Dublin city, by way of a Clean Air Bill, in order to protect the hundreds of thousands of inner city dwellers, especially those in sub-standard housing who will run the possibility of lower IQ levels and the probability of increased respiratory or bronchial conditions if this is not done urgently.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>What concerns me particularly today is the plight of residents in the Mount Pleasant area of Ranelagh who are affected by a lead polluting industry McGovern's of Prices Lane.  This scrap yard had, over the years, created a nuisance, noise on unloading and loading of vehicles in this narrow laneway.  However, in the last five to six years the activities have mushroomed to an admitted <Col N="485" /> turnover by Mr. Kenneth McGovern recently of £2.9 million.  This punitive operation today burns polythene casing largely supplied by Telecom Éireann, the ESB and Dublin Corporation, in a metal hopper and throws up a very damaging pollutant in the immediate neighbourhood. To demonstrate my point, I will pass a photograph taken by the chief health inspector's office to the Minister which shows in colour the terrible damage this pollutant is causing in the area.</P>
    <P>The chief health inspector has already admitted that dust in the vicinity is contaminated to an alarming degree.  The situation in Ranelagh is still bad despite prosecution under the Atmospheric Pollution Regulations, 1970 &mdash; £25 fine and £25 costs were achieved in court in 1982 &mdash; and there is currently another prosecution in hand by the chief health inspector, and the burning continues.  In a report by the atmospheric pollution unit of February 1984 samples which I will quote are included.  We are told by the chief health inspector that the figures I am about to mention are very high even classifying McGovern's as an industrial source.  To put them in perpective the lead content of surface dust in Dublin is between 20 to 4,380 ppms.  Yet in the four samples that have been taken in the analysis that I am just about to mention, sample one shows 22,777 ppms, sample two, 162,825 ppms, sample three 33,825 ppms, and sample four, 17,595 ppms.  These are of the order of 12 to 15 times the average surface dust problem in the city of Dublin.</P>
    <P>This must be the worst industrial pollution in Ireland although other serious problems exist, for example, the Mining Company of Ireland operation at Ringsend. There does not seem to be any real indication from the Department of the Environment that this industry must be forced to regulate its operation or relocate.</P>
    <P>When is the Minister for the Environment either going to introduce a Bill to deal with this terrifying level of pollution situated directly opposite the home of the <Col N="486" /> Minister of State in his Department and in a heavily built up residential area or amend the Atmospheric Pollution Regulations, 1970 and introduce the necessary registration of industrial processes like this by the chief health inspector?</P>
    <P>There is a need in the mid-eighties to look at other improvements in these regulations such as fan ducts from dry cleaner establishments, factory chimney heights, flues from central heating boilers.  All of these have been brought to my attention by the chief health inspector who, to say the least, with Dublin Corporation has been trying to deal within the limits of regulation and legislation with this kind of problem.</P>
    <P>I cannot stress enough the public concern that exists on this issue.  The Taoiseach, the Minister for Labour and every public representative in this constituency, not least myself because I am living perhaps closer than anybody else, a short distance on one side away from the Minister of State &mdash; we look at it from two different perpectives &mdash; are concerned to see the well-meaning residents locally given some identifiable support.  Nobody would argue that the chief inspector and, Dublin Corporation are not attempting everything to resolve this situation.  They are powerless without the necessary legislative changes that the Minister and the Department of the Environment should now produce.  It cannot be said that the Department have not been given more than adequate time to respond.  The present Minister for the Environment has not been in his post all that long but the Department of the Environment are well aware of the growing concern in relation to these premises over the last five to six years, say, from the time in which it turned from a very typical and traditional scrap yard into something that was taking in batteries and polythene casings and putting them through a burning process, producing lead and lead dust and causing people who are living within 20 feet of this operation fear and dismay.  Their greatest fear and dismay is about whether or not we will get the response we are looking for.  This is an opportunity that should be given to them, an opportunity that should <Col N="487" /> be faced up to.  I hope the Minister in his response can give a detailed timetable and a detailed response as to how he feels this plant can be regulated, whether it requires legislation or not, and that we will get down to doing something positive to clearing this nuisance.</P>
    <Speaker pid="LiamKavanagh" hpid="Minister for the Environment (Mr. Kavanagh) Liam Kavanagh">
      <NameTxt>Minister for the Environment (Mr. Kavanagh)</NameTxt>
      <P>As one who resided in Ranelagh for three years during that period that I spent in Dublin I am sorry to hear that that area has deteriorated since those days in the early sixties.  Certainly, if in my capacity as Minister for the Environment I can be of some assistance, I can assure the Senator that I will be.</P>
      <P>There are some facts I should bring to the notice of the House.  The Dublin conurbation has been expanding rapidly over recent years.  There are about a million people already located within a relatively small area.  Dublin is one of the fastest growing cities in Europe.  An industrial infrastructure has also grown relatively quickly to cater for employment outlets for the population.</P>
      <P>A further phenomenon has been the switch, particularly in the domestic sector, from oil to coal for space heating. This switch made sound economic sense, to the householders involved because of the increased price of oil which resulted from various oil crises in the last decade. However, an inevitable consequence has been a disimprovement in air quality due to emissions of smoke and other polluting substances.  The motorcar, and greater reliance on it than in the past, has also contributed.  Industry, too, is responsible for a share of air pollution.  In Dublin, therefore, air quality is now a greater cause for concern than in the past.  The impact on air quality of the dramatic increase in the use of coal within the domestic sector has been demonstrated in Dublin during the past few winters. Pollutant levels have increased appreciably over those which were observed in the years immediately prior to the switch in fuel use.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>While overall air quality has disimproved some localised small industries have <Col N="488" /> contributed disproportionately to the problem and are a cause for concern to residents in the immediate areas.  Senator FitzGerald has referred to this.  It is a problem which I am very conscious of and to which I will refer later.</P>
    <P>There are many aspects of air pollution and in the time available to me I cannot dwell on them all in detail.  However, I can assure the House that concern about air pollution is not confined to this country. International concern about air pollution is high at present and in my capacity as President of the Environment Council in the EC I will preside next week at a meeting which will consider proposals for the improvement of air quality generally.  One of these is a proposal to eliminate lead from petrol.</P>
    <P>In this connection Senator FitzGerald may be interested to note that the refinery at Whitegate is to make the necessary technical adjustments to enable it to produce petrol with maximum lead content of 1.5 grammes per litre by 1986.  The elimination of lead from petrol will undoubtedly be a significant contributory factor in the reduction of lead levels generally in Dublin.  Lead levels in the capital are being monitored by Dublin Corporation at a number of sites.  The monitoring results obtained were generally in compliance with the 1982 EC directive on air quality standards for lead which stipulates an annual limit of two microgrammes per cubic metre. This monitoring regime will continue.</P>
    <P>In so far as lead in the air is concerned, Dublin Corporation have also investigated ambient lead levels in dust contained in or near schools and industrial premises.  High concentrations were found nearer to off-street lead processing operations one of which is located in Naas in a residential area.  The level found in some of the schools could be due to the presence of old paint containing lead on nearby woodwork or iron railings rather than from traffic.</P>
    <P>While to date we have been able to comply with EC requirements for lead levels in the air, we must not become complacent and action must be taken and continue to be taken against firms, <Col N="489" /> located in residential areas, which are contributing significantly to air pollution activities related to the processing of lead.  I do not intend to name individual firms but I can assure the House that every effort is being made to ensure that this type of air pollution is curtailed.</P>
    <P>Dublin Corporation have powers in the control of atmospheric pollution regulations since 1970 to prosecute offenders. They have used these powers successfully against a particular firm for breaches of the regulations and intend to initiate proceedings against the same firm for further contravention.  The 1970 regulations also provide where contravention of the regulation is likely to continue or to occur again the sanitary authority may notify the occupier of the premises of the works which they consider necessary to be done to end the contravention or prevent its recurrence.  The corporation are considering the applicability of this provision to the firm in question.</P>
    <P>Ideally, however, the answer to air pollution problems caused by these type of firms is to have them re-located in more environmentally suitable surroundings. My Department are also examining the possibility as a short term measure of regulations to provide for a system of local authority specification to ensure that material handled by such firms is stored, processed and disposed of in an environmentally acceptable manner. This is a difficult area and I am not sure yet whether action can be taken but if it can be taken then it will be taken.</P>
    <P>In the long term, however, so far as legislation is concerned I am fully aware that the existing controls in regard to air pollution generally are in need of amendment to take account of the present conditions and EC requirements.  The work of preparing the necessary legislation is at present being undertaken in my Department and it is hoped that the relevant legislation will be brought before <Col N="490" /> this House next year.  As I said earlier, I am concerned with the recurrence of high air pollution levels, particularly smoke. In consultation with the Minister for Energy, efforts are being made to devise energy policies which will make greater use of natural gas at the expense not only of oil but of solid fuels as well, for commercial, industrial and domestic purposes.  The Government have assisted the Dublin Gas Company to the tune of £150 million to develop the use of natural gas throughout the Dublin area.  My Department have approved the provision of a mains supply of natural gas to several new local authority housing schemes in the Dublin area at a cost of approximately £210 per house.  We will continue to consider favourably any proposals by local authorities to provide a mains supply of natural gas to new houses provided the cost of connection is reasonable.</P>
    <P>The environmental impact of converting from oil to natural gas can be quite significant.  For example, if all industries in Dublin use natural gas, emissions of sulphur dioxide in the region could be reduced by as much as 15 per cent.  It is encouraging to note that major commercial users like Guinness, Jacobs, Irish Distillers have opted for natural gas. Extension of the gas grid in Dublin is expected to encompass 15,000 to 60,000 homes by 1988.  This is also very significant.</P>
    <P>There is no easy solution to the alleviation of air pollution.  I can assure the House, however, that all available options are being considered and whatever action is possible will be taken.</P>
    <P>The Seanad adjourned at 5.20 p.m. until 2.30 p.m. on Wednesday, 5 December, 1984.</P>
  </MainHeading>
</Debate>