<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE Debate SYSTEM "../Debate.dtd"[]>
<Debate DocTitle="D&aacute;il Debate" Day="Fri" Date="17" Month="Sep" Year="1920" Vol="F" No="17" DateIrish="" DateEnglish="" House="D" CommitteeEng="" CommitteeIr="" SubNameEng="" cnum="212">
  <MainHeading Type="Prelude" LHead="" RHead="">
    <Title></Title>
<P><Col N="212"/> Dáil Éireann assembled in Private Session at 9.15 a.m. on Friday, 17th September, 1920.  In the absence of the Deputy Speaker, the Chair was taken by E.J. Duggan, Deputy for South Meath.</P>
<P>There were present:&mdash;</P>
<P>THE ACTING-PRESIDENT.<br/>
THE SECRETARY FOR FINANCE.<br/>
THE SECRETARY FOR DEFENCE.<br/>
THE SECRETARY FOR LOCAL GOVERNMENT.<br/>
THE SECRETARY FOR LABOUR.<br/>
THE SECRETARY FOR INDUSTRIES.<br/>
THE ACTING SECRETARY FOR HOME AFFAIRS.<br/>
THE ASSOCIATE SECRETARY FOR FOREIGN AFFAIRS.<br/>
THE DIRECTOR OF TRADE AND COMMERCE.<br/>
THE DIRECTOR OF FISHERIES.<br/>
THE SUBSTITUTE DIRECTOR OF PROPAGANDA.<br/>
THE SUBSTITUTE DIRECTOR OF AGRICULTURE.<br/>
BUCKLEY, D. (Kildare North).<br/>
CLANCY, J.J. (Sligo North).<br/>
COLIVET, M.P. (Limerick City).<br/>
CROWLEY, DR. (Mayo North).<br/>
CROWLEY, J. (Kerry North).<br/>
DOLAN, J.N. (Leitrim).<br/>
DUGGAN, E.J. (Meath South).<br/>
FAHY, F. (Galway South).<br/>
HAYES, J. (Cork West).<br/>
HAYES, DR. R.J. (Limerick East).<br/>
KENT, D. (Cork East).<br/>
LAWLESS, F. (Dublin North).<br/>
LENNON, J. (Carlow).<br/>
LYNCH, F. (Kerry South).<br/>
MACBRIDE, J. (Mayo West).<br/>
MAC DONAGH, J. (Tipperary North).<br/>
MAC ENTEE, J. (Monaghan South).<br/>
MAC GUINNESS, J. (Longford).<br/>
MACGRATH, J. (St. James', Dublin).<br/>
MOLONEY, P.J. (Tipperary South).<br/>
MULCAHY, R.J. (Clontarf).<br/>
O'DOHERTY, J. (Donegal North).<br/>
O'HIGGINS, B. (Clare West).<br/>
O'KEEFFE, P. (Cork North).<br/>
O'MAILLE, P. (Connemara).<br/>
O'MAHONY, J. (Fermanagh South).<br/>
RYAN, DR. J. (Wexford South).<br/>
SEARS, W. (Mayo South).<br/>
SHANAHAN, P. (Harbour, Dublin).<br/>
STAINES, M. (St. Michan's, Dublin).<br/>
SWEENEY, J. (Donegal West).<br/>
SWEETMAN, R.M. (Wexford North).<br/>
WALSH, J.J. (Cork City).<br/>
WARD, P.J. (Donegal South).
</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="ATTENDANCE OF RUAIDHRI" RHead="O CONCHUBHAIR">
    <Title>ATTENDANCE OF RUAIDHRI O CONCHUBHAIR.</Title>
<P>On the motion of the SECRETARY FOR LOCAL GOVERNMENT, leave was given to Ruaidhri O Conchubhair, Secretary to the Local Government Commission, to be present during the Session.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="ACTING PRESIDENT'S OPENING" RHead="STATEMENT. - PARIS">
    <Title>ACTING PRESIDENT'S OPENING STATEMENT. - PARIS.</Title>
<P>The ACTING PRESIDENT, in the course of his address, stated that in view of the short period which had elapsed since last Session there was not very much to report.  The expulsion of Mr. Gavan Duffy from Paris would be dealt with by the Associate Secretary for Foreign Affairs.  Captain Mac White had been in charge of the Embassy since, but Mr. Sean T.O Ceallaigh had now returned.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="ACTING PRESIDENT'S OPENING" RHead="STATEMENT. - BELFAST">
    <Title>ACTING PRESIDENT'S OPENING STATEMENT. - BELFAST.</Title>
<P>The general boycott instituted against Belfast was being stringently felt, especially by the banks.  A general plan of action in regard to the boycott had been decided on at a conference with the representatives of Labour and of Republicans from Belfast.  In order that this plan might be properly carried out it was essential to place a man in charge of operations in Dublin.  This man should be appointed by An Dáil to-day.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="ACTING PRESIDENT'S OPENING" RHead="STATEMENT. - UNIONIST POURPARLERS">
    <Title>ACTING PRESIDENT'S OPENING STATEMENT. - UNIONIST POURPARLERS.</Title>
<P>The only other important matter he had to mention was that some leaders of the Irish Unionist Party recently visited him and asked if peace could not be arranged.  They asked if he would submit proposals from them to Dáil Éireann.  He told them that Dáil Éireann would receive proposals from any body of Irishmen, and would send a courteous reply.  They subsequently <Col N="213"/> submitted a scheme for the establishment of a Commonwealth connected with England.  These proposals were placed before the Ministry, who decided that they contained no basis for a settlement. He suggested that counter proposals be sent to the Unionists, and that they be asked what guarantees they would require from the Republic.  They should be met by the Commission on Organised Opposition to the Republic which was being set up.  He suggested the following terms of reference for the Commission:&mdash;</P><P>&ldquo;To investigate and report on the organised opposition to the Republic amongst certain sections of the Irish people.</P><P>&ldquo;To consider the means by which such opposition can be abated or overcome.</P><P>&ldquo;To consider what steps can be taken to protect and strengthen the Republican population in areas in which the majority is hostile.&rdquo;</P><P>The only names suggested for the Commission so far were those of the Secretary for Finance, the Rev. Dr. Irwin and himself.  It would be for the Dáil to suggest further names.</P><P>As it was very desirable that the business of the Session be concluded as early as possible, he asked the Deputies to try and finish the Agenda by 7 p.m.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="POLITICAL" RHead="PRISONERS">
    <Title>POLITICAL PRISONERS.</Title>
<P>J.J. WALSH (Cork City) moved the suspension of Standing Orders to draw the attention of foreign countries to the sufferings of the Lord Mayor of Cork and the prisoners in Cork Jail, and also to tender to their relatives the sympathy of the Dáil.</P>
<P>This was seconded by P. O MAILLE (Connemara), and the following resolution was unanimously agreed to:&mdash;</P><P>&ldquo;Dáil Éireann, assembled in full session in Dublia, records its appreciation of the loyalty and devotion of the Deputy for Mid-Cork and Chief Magistrate of Cork City To him and to the sufferers in Cork Jail it sends, on behalf of the people of Ireland, assurance of sympathy and admiration.  In that assurance the duly elected representatives of the people of Ireland are confident, all the civilised nations of the world join.&rdquo;</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="MOTIONS DEFERRED FROM PREVIOUS" RHead="SESSION - ALTERATION IN CONSTITUTION">
    <Title>MOTIONS DEFERRED FROM PREVIOUS SESSION - ALTERATION IN CONSTITUTION.</Title>
<P>J.J. WALSH (Cork City) moved, in accordance with notice of motion:&mdash;</P><P>&ldquo;Whereas Mr. de Valera has repeatedly publicly announced in America that the Constitution of the Irish Republic was based on the democratic foundations under lying the Constitution of the United States; and whereas the latter body provides for the consideration of all phases of legislative activity through the medium of Committees whose findings are subject only to the veto of the whole Parliament&mdash; a method already in vogue in County and Borough Councils in Ireland&mdash;and as no such machinery has yet been set up within the Irish Republican Government, with the consequent practically entire exclusion of three-fourths of the people's representatives from effective work on the nation's behalf, we now resolve to bring this Constitution into harmony with the American idea of Committees elected by the whole House, and clothed with similar powers.&rdquo;</P>
<P>He stated that this resolution had already been brought forward twelve months ago and debated at length.  The result was a compromise whereby it was decided that there should be a number of advisory Committees.  These Committees meant little or nothing, their powers were restricted, and they consequently fell through.  Committees similar to those mentioned in the resolution operated in all other Parliaments, and their findings were only subject to the veto of the parent body.  Those Committees would put new life into the Dáil, with much more satisfactory results <Col N="214"/> to the country.  He gave instances in which the assistance of the Committees would have been of service, and said that one man could not possibly do as satisfactory work as if he was supported by a Committee of six or seven men.  The members of the present Committees had no standing, as it rested with the responsible Minister to accept or reject their findings.  In order to get satisfactory work the members of the Dáil should be harnessed to the work of the nation.</P>
<P>J. MACENTEE (Monaghan South), in seconding the motion, said that under the present circumstances there could be no real opposition to the Ministry. Meetings of the Dáil were got through hurriedly, and there could be very little discussion on many important subjects. All decisions should be carefully gone into.  The Dáil should delegate certain functions to the Committees, who should be empowered to take decisions.  These decisions could afterwards be ratified by the Dáil.</P>
<P>F. FAHY (Galway South) said that there would be at least four members required for each Committee of ten Committees, which would mean having forty members almost continuously in Dublin. How could this be arranged?</P>
<P>The SECRETARY FOR FINANCE said the system proposed was not new.  Committees had already been formed under the various Departments.  Every member of the Dáil had been asked what Committees he wished to serve on.  Some attended once or twice.  Only a few attended regularly.  The real difficulty was to get practical assistance from the members.  It was news to him to hear that the members had no redress if they disapproved of the actions of the Ministers. The Dáil had absolute power to remove any Minister.  If any Committee found that its wishes were being disregarded by the Minister the members had the ordinary means of redress, that of raising the matter at the Dáil. If it could be shown that the will of the Dáil was opposed to that of the Minister for the time being, then he could not continue in office.</P>
<P>R. SWEETMAN (Wexford North) said that the advisory Committees fell into abeyance owing to the increased offensive of the enemy.  It would be a very drastic method of procedure to have the findings of the Committees subject only to the veto of the whole Parliament.  It was also very undemocratic to have to dispose of important questions in the few minutes that could be devoted to them under present circumstances.</P>
<P>The ACTING-PRESIDENT pointed out that the motion meant a complete revolution of the Constitution of Dail Eireann.  It meant taking away the responsibility of the Ministers and placing it in the hands of Committees. The suggestion that President de Valera was in favour of this departure was unfounded.  Mr. de Valera was the inspirer of the present Constitution. The Acting-President had a perfectly open mind regarding the Committee system; it might be adopted in normal times, but under present circumstances it would be hopeless to try to function through Committees.</P>
<P>After further discussion EOIN MAC NEILL (Derry City and National University) moved an amendment that the motion be postponed for twelve months.  It was a very revolutionary proposal and he did not believe that the country would approve of it.</P>
<P>M. STAINES (St. Michan's, Dublin) seconded the amendment.</P><P>The amendment was put and carried on a division by 33 votes to 1.</P><P>It was the general opinion of the meeting that there was no reason why the Advisory Committees already in existence should not continue to meet as before.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="MOTIONS DEFERRED FROM PREVIOUS" RHead="SESSION - PROPAGANDA IN ENGLAND">
    <Title>MOTIONS DEFERRED FROM PREVIOUS SESSION - PROPAGANDA IN ENGLAND.</Title>
<P>J.J. WALSH (Cork City) moved:&mdash;</P><P>A motion regarding the initation of a Propaganda campaign on a scale likely to affect the internal harmony of England.  Propaganda was more powerful than weapons.  He explained the nature of his proposals and how he thought they could be financed.</P>
<P>The SECRETARY FOR DEFENCE was entirely in favour of a Propaganda <Col N="215"/> campaign in England.  He was willing to second the motion on the Agenda paper.</P>
<P>After some discussion as to the details of the motion the SECRETARY FOR FINANCE stated that he was absolutely opposed to any person making a proposal the details of which were not carefully thought out.  The Ministry were pursuing the right lines at present. He considered that to accept certain of the proposals outlined by Mr. Walsh would have as disastrous results as if they decided to return to the Westminster Parliament.  The English people broke down the Germans by means of propaganda though the latter were able to spend forty millions more than the Republic could spend.  English morale could not be broken by propaganda.  He was firmly convinced they had no friends in England. Asquith was a worse enemy of Ireland than Lloyd George; Gladstone was a greater enemy than Castlereagh; Thomas was worse than either Carson or Bonar Law; English Labour was just as hostile as English Capital.</P><P>After further discussion the proposer agreed to withdraw the motion.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="REPORTS. - DEPARTMENT" RHead="OF HOME AFFAIRS">
    <Title>REPORTS. - DEPARTMENT OF HOME AFFAIRS.</Title>
<P>The SECRETARY FOR HOME AFFAIRS in the course of an oral report stated that great progress had been made with the establishment of Parish and District Courts.  Much satisfaction had been expressed with their working. The rules of the Courts had been printed and were now ready for circulation. A great bulk of business had sprung up in the matter of Emigration which necessitated a fair amount of expense; a fee of &#x2153; was therefore being charged for each permit. He thought the recommendations for the issuing of permits were being made too freely and he was getting out an instruction to the parties concerned in the matter.  The causes often pleaded by those applying for permits, viz., ill-health, completion of studies and unemployment should henceforth be supported by reliable evidence.  Most of the cases dealt with so far related to persons who had booked their passages before the issue of the Decree.</P><P>He had a motion on the Agenda authorising the ruling out of certain Acts of the British Parliament which were hostile or repugnant on religious or national grounds.</P><P>With regard to the Increase of Rent Decree he did not want to press for its consideration at that Session as it was a very large measure and would require a fair amount of time to consider all its clauses.</P><P>It was thought that the setting up of a National Film Censorship could be undertaken by An Dail.  The latest suggestion was that the Municipal Bodies should be asked to appoint a Central Censor in Dublin.  It would be well to have one recognised authority for the whole country as it sometimes happened that pictures passed in Dublin were not approved of in the country.  He did not, however, intend to introduce legislation on the subject at the present Session.</P>
<P>The SECRETARY FOR LOCAL GOVERNMENT moved, and P. O MAILLE (Connemara) seconded the adoption of the Report.</P>
<P>The SECRETARY FOR HOME AFFAIRS stated in reply to the Deputy for Wexford North that the number of applications for emigration permits dealt with so far exceeded 250.  The rejections did not exceed 50; the reason being that the Registrars, Justices and Volunteer Commandants in the country took it for granted that they ought to pass all applications from persons who had their passages booked before the issue of the Decree.  The warning he was now issuing would cause them to be less ready to-recommend applications.</P><P>The Report was adopted.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="DEPARTMENT OF FOREIGN" RHead="AFFAIRS. - France">
    <Title>DEPARTMENT OF FOREIGN AFFAIRS. - France.</Title>
<P>The ASSOCIATE SECRETARY FOR FOREIGN AFFAIRS (COUNT PLUNKETT) in the course of an oral report stated that much attention had been directed to France <Col N="216"/> owing to recent events there.  The French Government had given Mr. Gavan Duffy his congé and had given him a very short time to leave Paris. They had given no explanation of their action, but they had otherwise treated him with courtesy.  Mr. Duffy had gone to Brussels.  French popular sympathy had been moved by the action of their Government and both the Government and the semi-official press of France realised that a most serious blunder had been committed.  The meaning of it was understood all over Europe.  French prestige had been lowered under English pressure.  Much as they might regret the insult to Mr. Duffy, the Irish Republic had rather gained than lost from a propaganda point of view over this matter.  Mr. Duffy could do very effective work in Brussels.  Captain Mac White whose status in Parisien Commercial circles was high, and who had given service as a soldier of the French Republic had since Mr. Duffy's departure been in charge of Irish Propaganda in Paris. Mr. Sean T.O Ceallaigh had just returned there from Rome.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="DEPARTMENT OF FOREIGN" RHead="AFFAIRS. - Italy">
    <Title>DEPARTMENT OF FOREIGN AFFAIRS. - Italy.</Title>
<P>The Italian Press was very busy with Ireland.  Very effective work was being done by a number of people there who were contributing articles to all the leading papers.  Mr. Hales was in Genoa and was on the alert lest any anti-Irish articles should go unanswered. England's busiest efforts were being concentrated on Rome where they were being foiled.  Asquith went to Rome in 1916 and this year Arthur Balfour went there, but in neither case was the mission a success. The Pope was friendly and prayed for the success of the Irish Cause.  It should be remembered that there was an English Colony resident in Rome who acted as propagandists against the Republic.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="DEPARTMENT OF FOREIGN" RHead="AFFAIRS. - United States">
    <Title>DEPARTMENT OF FOREIGN AFFAIRS. - United States.</Title>
<P>President de Valera's work in the United States was going ahead.  One of the most hopeful facts to be recorded was that Mr. John Devoy had with drawn all statements made against the conduct of the campaign on behalf of the Republic and had stated that there was only one body of Irish opinion in the United States.  This showed that an acute crisis was over.  The news of English brutality and lawlessness in Ireland was now spreading throughout the world.  In regard to the case of Mr. James Larkin, advices received from America showed that when he was up for trial a representative of the Republic attended at the court and did all that was possible in his defence. Since then the Consul in New York had issued a report in Mr. Larkin's case, but it had not yet been received. A letter had, however, been received from him in reference to the case.  It would seem that Mr. Larkin had been treated with great severity.  Advanced Labour in America had taken up the case and the services of Mr. Frank P. Walsh, who was a tower of strength had been secured.  He read the following letter received from Mr. Fawsitt:</P><P Just="Right">&ldquo;Irish Consulate, New York,</P><P Just="Right">&ldquo;12th August, 1920.</P><P>&ldquo;Dear Sirs,</P><P>&ldquo;Supplementing my report to you on the James Larkin case.  Following conversations which we have had with the Hon. Frank P. Walsh of this City, I am glad to report that that gentleman has consented to act as Court Counsel in the Appeal proceedings which it is proposed to take in the New York State Supreme Court on behalf of James Larkin in the event of the Governor of the State declining to grant the free pardon for which he has now been prayed by the Attorney representing Larkin.  (See report of said petition taken from to-day's New York &lsquo;Call,&rsquo; attached herewith).</P><P>&ldquo;I have to add that so far no application has been received at this Consulate either from Mr. Larkin or in his behalf from his Attorney inviting the protection and services of either the Consul or other representative in this country of the Republic of Ireland.</P>
<P>&ldquo;I have to request that you will bring this correspondence and enclosure to the attention of the Minister <Col N="217"/> responsible for Foreign Affairs for his information and guidance and also for that of the Cabinet as a whole.</P><P Just="Right">&ldquo;Yours faithfully,</P><P Just="Right">(Signed), &ldquo;J.L. Fawsitt,</P><P Just="Right">&ldquo;Irish Consul.&rdquo;</P><P>It was not their business to enquire as to whether Mr. Larkin's friends in the State had approached them or not.  Mr. Larkin was one of their fellow-citizens and it was their business to do what they could to protect him.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="DEPARTMENT OF FOREIGN AFFAIRS." RHead="- Most Rev. Dr. Mannix">
    <Title>DEPARTMENT OF FOREIGN AFFAIRS. - Most Rev. Dr. Mannix.</Title>
<P>They were all aware that a Deputation from the Dáil had gone to Liverpool in the expectation that the Most Rev. Dr. Mannix would land there. The Deputation went afterwards to London where they had an interview with the Archbishop, and came away convinced that no one could show more tenacity and vigour in maintaining the position of the Republic than he.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="DEPARTMENT OF FOREIGN" RHead="AFFAIRS. - Russia">
    <Title>DEPARTMENT OF FOREIGN AFFAIRS. - Russia.</Title>
<P>The Russian Government were manifesting the most friendly feelings towards Ireland and were anxious to come to an understanding with the Republic and with Irish Labour.</P>
<P>J. MACDONAGH (Tipperary, North) moved the adoption of the Report.  He suggested that a copy of the letter received from Mr. Fawsitt should be sent to the Dublin Corporation, in order that that body might know what Mr. Larkin's position really was.</P>
<P>J. MACBRIDE (Mayo, West) seconded the motion and said that he considered that a strong protest should be forwarded to the French Government in connection with the expulsion of Mr. Duffy.</P>
<P>D. KENT (Cork East) considered that a protest against the action of the British Government in interfering with Irish Trade by preventing American ships calling at Cobh should be forwarded to the Irish Consul at New York and also to the Acting American Consul at Cobh.</P>
<P>The ASSOCIATE SECRETARY FOR FOREIGN AFFAIRS (COUNT PLUNKETT) suggested that the form the protests should take should be left to the Ministry.  The protest with regard to the expulsion was a matter which required very delicate handling.</P>
<P>The ACTING-PRESIDENT agreed that it was a very delicate matter.  The expulsion had not the sympathy of the French people.  As regards Cobh, their course should be to notify the American Government that it was not the action of the Irish Government that was responsible for the stoppage of the shipping at Cobh, but the action of the British Government.  If these matters were left in the hands of the Ministry they would be better able to deal with them.</P><P>The adoption of the Report was then put and carried.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="DEPARTMENT" RHead="OF FINANCE">
    <Title>DEPARTMENT OF FINANCE.</Title>
<P>The SECRETARY FOR FINANCE presented the Report and amplified certain of the matters contained therein.</P>
<P>D. BUCKLEY (Kildare North) proposed the adoption of the Report, and asked if anything had been done in regard to the issuing of receipt stamps which could be used by Merchants throughout the country.</P>
<P>The SECRETARY FOR FINANCE, in reply, stated that this matter came under the heading of licenses and was being dealt with as such.</P>
<P>The SECRETARY FOR LOCAL GOVERNMENT seconded the motion for the adoption of the Report.</P><P>Reference having been made to the presence in Ireland of a number of the Knights of Columbus, it was decided on the suggestion of the ACTING-PRESIDENT, that Messrs. Dolan, Fitzgerald and Mac Guinness should interview a number of them with a view to securing their co-operation for the Loan work in America.</P>
<P>The SECRETARY FOR FINANCE stated that the money received by him from the Friends of Irish Freedom Fund had been credited to the Self-Determination Fund.  As regards the Collection in Australia Dr. Mannix had put it down at £25,000, but this had been <Col N="218"/> considered a very conservative estimate.</P>
<P>J.J. WALSH (Cork City) raised the question of publicans' licenses, which amounted to £8,000 in Cork City.</P>
<P>The SECRETARY FOR FINANCE stated that this matter would require very careful consideration.</P>
<P>The SECRETARY FOR DEFENCE wanted an assurance that sufficient money would be provided for the establishment of an Import and Export Warehouse. Their Consular Service could not be kept going without such a House.  The Consuls should be appointed as Agents of the Company so that they might be in a position to do effective work.</P><P>The Report was put and adopted.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="DEPARTMENT" RHead="OF LABOUR">
    <Title>DEPARTMENT OF LABOUR.</Title>
<P>The SECRETARY FOR LABOUR read her Report.</P>
<P>EOIN MAC NEILL (Derry City and National University) moved the adoption of the Report, and asked if it were not possible to recover any of the Labour Arbitration Expenses by getting both sides to lodge a fee beforehand.</P>
<P>The SECRETARY FOR LABOUR thought it was not possible to do as suggested in view of the fact that on the formation of the Board an announcement was circulated stating that the services of the Board would be available free of charge.  The British Boards were not demanding fees.</P>
<P>M.P. COLIVET (Limerick City) seconded the motion for the adoption of the Report.  He thought that the parties to the dispute could be got to pay a fee beforehand.</P>
<P>The SECRETARY FOR LABOUR stated that whilst it might be possible to obtain fees in country districts where the whole population were in sympathy with the Republican Movement, it was practically impossible to obtain them in cities and towns.</P>
<P>D. KENT (Cork East) asked if any arrangement could be made with Labour regarding men &ldquo;on the run.&rdquo; He knew of cases where the Transport Workers had refused to allow these men to work as labourers because they were not members of the Union.</P>
<P>The SECRETARY FOR LABOUR promised to take this question up with the Irish Transport Workers' Union.</P><P>The motion for the adoption of the Report was then put and carried.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="DEPARTMENT OF LOCAL" RHead="GOVERNMENT">
    <Title>DEPARTMENT OF LOCAL GOVERNMENT.</Title>
<P>The SECRETARY FOR LOCAL GOVERNMENT submitted the final Report of the Commission on Local Government. Considering the circumstances under which the Enquiry was conducted he thought that the best possible information had been made available.</P><P>The best thanks of the Dáil were due to the Chairman and other members of the Commission and also to the Secretary, for the care and attention shown in submitting the Report.  It had been got together in a very able manner and in a very short space of time.</P><P>If the recommendations of the Commission were adopted a considerable sum of money would be required to set up the Department necessary to take on the work of the British Local Government Board.  He did not think it right or just to ask the local authorities to pay the expenses of this new Department.  Therefore he should ask the Dáil to provide the money.</P><P>He reviewed the principal recommendations made by the Commission, and moved the adoption of these in the following terms:&mdash;</P><P>&ldquo;Recommendations:</P><P>&ldquo;1.  The clean break&mdash;The Local Government Department to function on the lines of the Custom House.</P><P>&ldquo;2.  All Local Bodies to sever connection with Custom House on a date to be fixed, and to recognise thereafter the Local Government Department of An Dáil as the agency to supervise and control these bodies.</P>
<P>&ldquo;3.  In order for the Local Government Department to exercise the <Col N="219"/> duties of controlling and supervising, a staff is necessary as follows:&mdash;</P><P><i>a.</i>  Four Inspectors&mdash;one being a Medical Officer and one Engineer.</P><P><i>b.</i>  Ten Clerks.</P><P><i>c.</i>  Nineteen Auditors.</P><P>&ldquo;4.  Economies to be carried out by Local Bodies on the lines laid down in the report under the following heads:&mdash;</P>
<table pgwide="1">
 <tgroup cols="2">
  <colspec  colname="1" colnum="1" colwidth="40*" align="left"></colspec>
  <colspec  colname="2" colnum="2" colwidth="10*" align="right"></colspec>
  <thead>
<row>
<entry rowsep="1"></entry>
<entry rowsep="1">£</entry></row></thead><tbody><row>
<entry>a.  Withholding Principal and Interest on British Government Loans</entry>
<entry>200,000</entry></row><row>
<entry>b.  Stopping payments made to persons doing work for British Government and expenses incidental thereto</entry>
<entry>20,000</entry></row><row>
<entry>c. Economies on Road Works</entry>
<entry>50,000</entry></row><row>
<entry>d. Venereal Diseases and Child Welfare Schemes</entry>
<entry>25,000</entry></row><row>
<entry>e. Economies by abolition and amalgamation of Workhouses</entry>
<entry>50,000</entry></row><row>
<entry>f. Economies in Asylums by sending home some patients, etc.</entry>
<entry>10,000</entry></row><row>
<entry>g. Tuberculosis&mdash;Economies by reducing number of patients under Hospital treatment and by amalgamation of Hospitals</entry>
<entry>10,000</entry></row><row>
<entry>h. General Economies, i.e., Stationery, Legal Expenses, etc.</entry>
<entry>5,000</entry></row><row>
<entry>Total estimated saving during remainder of Financial year for all Ireland</entry>
<entry>£370,000</entry></row><row>
<entry>Total estimated saving during remainder of current financial year for Republican bodies, say 75 per cent. of above</entry>
<entry>277,500</entry></row><row>
<entry>Estimated deficit (all Ireland) due to withholding. 80 per cent. of Government Grants estimated at £1,600,000, for half year</entry>
<entry>640,000</entry></row><row>
<entry>Approximate saving as indicated</entry>
<entry>370,000</entry></row><row>
<entry>Difference (all Ireland) for half-year</entry>
<entry>£270,000</entry></row><row>
<entry>Assuming Republican bodies to be 75 per cent. of all Ireland and that the finances are affected in like proportion&mdash;the deficit for such bodies would be 75 per cent. of above, i.e.</entry>
<entry>£202,500</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table>
<P>&ldquo;In addition to the foregoing the following is recommended:&mdash;</P><P><i>a.</i>  Pooling of Contracts.</P><P><i>b.</i>  Closing down some Agricultural and Technical Committees.</P><P><i>c.</i>  Labourers' cottages.  Purchase of same by the occupier by annual payments.</P><P><i>d.</i>  National Medical Service.  (Postponed.)</P><P>&ldquo;5.  That the deficit in the accounts of Local Bodies&mdash;after making allowance for the economies set out above&mdash;be met by diverting land annuities and income tax from the British Government to the Dáil Exchequer.</P><P>&ldquo;That Supplementary Orders be issued without delay to Local Bodies covering all recommendations adopted by An Dáil.&rdquo;</P>
<P>P. O MAILLE (Connemara) seconded the motion.</P>
<P>M. STAINES (St. Michan's, Dublin) was of opinion that some of the economies mentioned in the report could not be carried out.</P>
<P>COUNTESS DE MARKIEVICZ (St. Patrick's, Dublin) inquired whether the purchase of labourers' cottages by their occupiers would not result in the planting of a large number of families or uneconomic holdings.</P>
<P>The SECRETARY FOR LOCAL GOVERNMENT explained that at present the cost of repairs, together with the interest on the loans, was greater than the rent received from the cottages.  The Commission thought that the occupiers would be prepared to pay a little <Col N="220"/> more rent and keep their cottages in repair if they were to become the owners of them.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="DEPARTMENT OF LOCAL" RHead="GOVERNMENT. - Economies">
    <Title>DEPARTMENT OF LOCAL GOVERNMENT. - Economies.</Title>
<P>It was here decided to take up the clauses of the memorandum separately, and the SECRETARY FOR LOCAL GOVERNMENT proposed, and M. STAINES (St. Michan's, Dublin) seconded the adoption of Clause 4 of the memorandum down to and including sub-clause (h).</P>
<P>J. MACENTEE (Monaghan South) was in total disagreement with the proposals regarding the reduction of the Child Welfare grants.</P>
<P>Dr. R.J. HAYES (Limerick East) stated that it was the opinion of a Committee of Doctors that the health scheme mentioned in the motion could be dropped for a short period in the present emergency without injury to the national health.</P>
<P>The SECRETARY FOR LOCAL GOVERNMENT explained that the sums raised in rates for those services would be spent on them.  The dropping of the services was only rendered necessary through the refusal of the English Government to fulfil its contracts.</P>
<P>J. MACENTEE (Monaghan South) was of opinion that the people in a position to pay rates should be asked to pay the extra £5,000 necessary to provide meals for Dublin school children.</P>
<P>ART O'CONNOR (Kildare South) enquired whether any arrangements had been made with Labour in the country districts regarding deductions in salaries and wages.</P>
<P>The SECRETARY FOR LOCAL GOVERNMENT stated no arrangements had been made outside Dublin.  This was not recommended by the Commission.</P>
<P>JOSEPH MACGRATH (St. James', Dublin) strongly objected to the proposal to close down the Tuberculosis Hospitals.</P>
<P>The SECRETARY FOR LOCAL GOVERNMENT explained that the economies adopted by the Dublin Corporation were absolutely essential.</P>
<P>J.N. DOLAN (Leitrim) suggested that the financial proposals be first discussed. They could not decide what economies were necessary without first knowing what amount of revenue they might be able to raise by the collection of land annuities, etc., in Ireland.</P>
<P>J. MACDONAGH (Tipperary North) agreed.  The revenue schemes to be discussed might result in a large amount of revenue coming in.  He thought they should declare all their commitments to the British Government absolutely cancelled.</P>
<P>The SECRETARY FOR LOCAL GOVERNMENT could not agree to this suggestion. The advances made to the Local Authorities must appear on the debit side of their books.  It would be adopting a very dangerous principle to decide to wipe them out.</P>
<P>The SECRETARY FOR FINANCE said that the proposal to withhold principal and interest on loans was wrong.  They should be paid to the National Government. If a Commission were set up to work out financial relations between the English Government and themselves the new Government should take over liability for payment of this money.  It was the duty of the Department to put before the public bodies a clear conception of their obligations towards the children of the State.  He had not the slightest doubt that the citizens of Dublin would pay the money necessary to provide meals for the children.  If the Dublin Corporation, circulated and approached every householder in the matter they would get the money.</P>
<P>COUNTESS DE MARKIEVICZ (St. Patrick's, Dublin) stated that she was one of the Committee who originally started the feeding of children in Dublin. If an appeal were issued for this purpose it would be responded to.</P>
<P>J. MACENTEE (Monaghan South) moved:&mdash;</P><P>&ldquo;That all reference to child welfare be deleted from the list of economies recommended.&rdquo;</P><P>The amount required for the supply of meals was infinitesmal.  They should try to make distress less hard.</P>
<P><Col N="221"/> SEAN ETCHINGHAM (Wicklow East) seconded the amendment.  He believed that means of raising the money could be devised.</P>
<P>J.N. DOLAN (Leitrim) supported the amendment, and suggested as an addendum that the Republican Government be asked to provide the money withheld.</P>
<P>The ACTING-PRESIDENT stated that the proposal meant that they take over the English Government's responsibilities. He understood that the Dublin Corporation were applying the same amount of money as usual to these services. Were they going to make the public bodies responsible for the starving children and cloak up what the English Government was doing?</P>
<P>The SECRETARY FOR LOCAL GOVERNMENT did not consider it fair to place the responsibility of providing money withheld on the shoulders of the Republican Government.</P><P>The amendment proposed by the Deputy for South Monaghan was agreed to.</P>
<P>The SECRETARY FOR LOCAL GOVERNMENT suggested that the proposal regarding the withholding of principal and interest on loans should be altered to read:</P><P>&ldquo;Principal and Interest due by Public.  Bodies on foot of English Government Loans to be credited to the Local Taxation Account against Grants due by the English Government and unpaid.&rdquo;</P>
<P>The SECRETARY FOR FINANCE accepted this suggestion.</P><P>The adoption of Clause 4 of the memorandum amended to read as follows was then put and carried:</P><P>&ldquo;Economics to be carried out by Local Bodies on the lines laid down in the Report under the following heads:&mdash;</P>
<table pgwide="1">
 <tgroup cols="2">
  <colspec  colname="1" colnum="1" colwidth="40*" align="center"></colspec>
  <colspec  colname="2" colnum="2" colwidth="10*" align="center"></colspec>
  <tbody>
<row>
<entry>a.  Principal and Interest on British Government Loans to be credited to the Local Taxation Account against Grants due by them and unpaid</entry>
<entry>£200,000</entry></row><row>
<entry>b.  Stopping payments made to persons doing work for British Government and expenses incidental thereto</entry>
<entry>20,000</entry></row><row>
<entry>c.  Economies on Road Works</entry>
<entry>50,000</entry></row><row>
<entry>d.  Venereal Diseases</entry>
<entry>25,000</entry></row><row>
<entry>e.  Economies by abolition and Amalgamation of Workhouses</entry>
<entry>50,000</entry></row><row>
<entry>f.  Economies in Asylums by sending home some patients, etc.</entry>
<entry>10,000</entry></row><row>
<entry>g.  Tuberculosis&mdash;economies by reducing number of patients under Hospital treatment and by amalgamation of Hospitals</entry>
<entry>10,000</entry></row><row>
<entry>h.  General Economies, i.e. Stationery, Legal Expenses, etc.</entry>
<entry>5,000</entry></row><row>
<entry>Total estimated saving during remainder of financial year for all Ireland</entry>
<entry>£370,000&rdquo;</entry></row><row>
<entry></entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="DEPARTMENT OF LOCAL GOVERNMENT. - Break" RHead="with English Local Government Board">
    <Title>DEPARTMENT OF LOCAL GOVERNMENT. - Break with English Local Government Board.</Title>
<P>The Secretary for Local Government then moved the adoption of Clauses 1, 2 and 3, viz.:&mdash;</P><P>1.  &ldquo;The clean break&mdash;The Local Government Department to function on the lines of the Custom House.&rdquo;</P><P>2.  &ldquo;All Local Bodies to sever connection with Custom House on a date to be fixed, and to recognise thereafter the Local Government Department of An Dáil as the agency to supervise and control these bodies.&rdquo;</P><P>3.  &ldquo;In order for the Local Government Department to exercise the duties of controlling and supervising, a staff is necessary, as follows:&mdash;</P><P><i>a.</i>  Four Inspectors&mdash;one being a Medical Officer and one Engineer.</P><P><i>b.</i>  Ten Clerks.</P><P><i>c.</i>  Nineteen Auditors.&rdquo;</P>
<P>Clause No. 3 involved an annual cost of £23,000.  Though the Secretary <Col N="222"/> for Finance had said that the money was not available, he submitted that it was unreasonable to expect a Department like that proposed to function unless provision was made for expenditure.  Due consideration should be given to the estimate submitted. The position he had taken up was justifiable.</P>
<P>FIONAN LYNCH (Kerry South) seconded the motion.</P>
<P>J. MACENTEE (Monaghan South) said that the Local Authorities should be asked to finance the Local Government Department, as its main duty would be to protect the interests of the ratepayers.  The number of those bodies who had already pledged allegiance to Dáil Éireann was 250, and the average contribution from each would amount to only £100.  He moved as an amendment:&mdash;</P><P>&ldquo;That the various Local Authorities who have pledged allegiance to An Dáil be asked to provide the sum required for the financing of the Local Government Department upon whatever basis may be found most equitable.&rdquo;</P>
<P>W. SEARS (Mayo South) seconded the amendment, and suggested that the valuation be taken as the basis in each case.</P>
<P>J.J. CLANCY (Sligo North) said that if they were going to set up a Department of the Dáil it was not for the Local Bodies to finance it.  He thought it would be a bad precedent to ask Local Bodies to pay for a Department which would have to supervise these Local Bodies themselves.</P>
<P>W. SEARS (Mayo South) said that in the procedure of the English Government they made the Public Bodies pay for the audit.  They would be only asking the Public Bodies to contribute to their own supervision.</P>
<P>The SECRETARY FOR LOCAL GOVERNMENT could not accept the amendment. The Local Bodies were sufficiently taxed already.  They would have first of all to provide the sums withheld. That was a big price for their loyalty and a sufficiently severe test without their having to bear an additional tax for the upkeep of the Department which would be responsible for their supervision.  He was satisfied with the figures submitted by the Commission. He thought that the Commission was well qualified for its work, being composed of men who were accustomed to the working of Local Government.  The estimate they had submitted was entitled to respect.  As the sum was very large considering the present state of their finances, he hoped they would be able to come to some agreement about it.</P>
<P>The SECRETARY FOR FINANCE said that nobody would accept the estimate for £23,000 as it stood.  Though the appointment of nineteen Auditors had been recommended, no provision had been made in the statement for the customary audit fees paid by Local Bodies.  If each local Council were to pay an audit fee of even two guineas it would amount to something between £400 and £500.  That sum should have been included in the estimate. In any event the present estimate should only cover the period to the end of December next, and the sum of £5,000 would be sufficient for that period.  The suggestion that the Department be financed by the Local Bodies was wrong from every point of view.  It would make the Department subsidiary to the Local Bodies, any one of which could stop payment at any time, and thereby weaken the control of the Department.</P>
<P>J. MACENTEE (Monaghan South) said that the supervision of Local Bodies was directed towards safeguarding local interests.  He believed that the local ratepayers should relieve the Dáil of the financial burden of this supervision.  They would be well repaid in the check that would be exercised over expenditure.</P><P>The amendment was put, and on a division was lost by 26 votes to 2.</P><P>The original motion was then put and carried.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="DEPARTMENT OF LOCAL GOVERNMENT. -" RHead="Vote for Local Government Department">
    <Title>DEPARTMENT OF LOCAL GOVERNMENT. - Vote for Local Government Department.</Title>
<P><Col N="223"/> On the motion of the SECRETARY FOR LOCAL GOVERNMENT, seconded by M. P. COLIVET (Limerick City), a Vote of £5,000 to cover the expenses of the Local Government Department to 31st December, 1920, was adopted.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="DEPARTMENT OF LOCAL GOVERNMENT." RHead="- Further Economies">
    <Title>DEPARTMENT OF LOCAL GOVERNMENT. - Further Economies.</Title>
<P>The SECRETARY FOR LOCAL GOVERNMENT then moved the adoption of the recommendations for</P><P>(a)  Pooling of Contracts; and</P><P>(b)  Purchase of Labourers' Cottages by occupiers.</P><P>With regard to the Pooling of Contracts there should be a schedule of standard supplies compiled.  The second item aimed at the establishment of a scheme whereby labourers would own their own cottages.  This had the further merit that it would save money to the local Councils.  He did not propose to move the recommendations for closing down Agricultural and Technical Committees at present.  Neither did he propose to deal with the question of a National Medical Service.</P>
<P>The ACTING-PRESIDENT seconded the motion.</P>
<P>J.J. WALSH (Cork City) enquired what machinery would be available for dealing with the pooling of contracts. It would be necessary to establish contract centres in different parts of the country.</P>
<P>J. MACBRIDE (Mayo West) stated that the scheme for the pooling of contracts would be looked on with great suspicion in the country.  It would be regarded as an attempt to favour Dublin trade.</P>
<P>The ACTING-PRESIDENT said that the scheme was one of the original proposals made by Sinn Fein in 1906.  All the Poor Law Boards were then consulted in regard to the matter, and not one of them objected to it.  If the contracts were pooled a great many new industries would be started in the country, as the guaranteeing of large orders was bound to encourage manufactures.</P>
<P>The SECRETARY FOR LOCAL GOVERNMENT said that they had no machinery to enable the Local Authorities to carry out a scheme for the purchase of labourers' cottages unless a Decree was passed for the purpose.  He suggested that they should adopt the motion with that reservation.  A Decree would be brought in afterwards.</P><P>The motion was then put and carried.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="DEPARTMENT OF LOCAL GOVERNMENT." RHead="- Revenue Suggestions">
    <Title>DEPARTMENT OF LOCAL GOVERNMENT. - Revenue Suggestions.</Title>
<P>At the suggestion of the SECRETARY FOR LOCAL GOVERNMENT the proposals in Clause 5 for collection of revenue were referred to the Finance Department for consideration.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="DEPARTMENT OF LOCAL GOVERNMENT." RHead="- Vote of Thanks to Commission">
    <Title>DEPARTMENT OF LOCAL GOVERNMENT. - Vote of Thanks to Commission.</Title>
<P>The SECRETARY FOR LOCAL GOVERNMENT then moved that the best thanks of the Dáil be tendered to the Chairman, members and Secretary of the Commission.</P><P>The motion was put and carried.</P><P>The Chair having been temporarily vacated by the Acting Speaker, it was taken by P.O MAILLE (Connemara).</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="DEPARTMENTS OF INDUSTRIES" RHead="AND TRADE AND COMMERCE">
    <Title>DEPARTMENTS OF INDUSTRIES AND TRADE AND COMMERCE.</Title>
<P>The DIRECTOR OF TRADE AND COMMERCE submitted a joint report from the Departments of Industries and Trade and Commerce.</P>
<P>F. FAHY (Galway South) proposed the adoption of the report.</P>
<P>JOHN O'MAHONY (Fermanagh South) seconded the adoption of the report, and asked for information as to what was being done regarding the establishment of an Import and Export Warehouse.</P>
<P>The DIRECTOR OF TRADE AND COMMERCE said that the matter had been held up owing to the want of money for its establishment.  In reply to the Deputy for Cork East he stated that the financing of small industrial Societies could only be undertaken in very exceptional cases.  He was sure that the Bank would sympathetically consider such cases as were mentioned. A question by the Deputy for <Col N="224"/> St. James', Dublin, was deferred until the Acting-President was present.</P>
<P>J. MACDONAGH (Tipperary North) asked what had been done in regard to the formation of the Economic Council, and if all the parties concerned were willing to take part in it. It was a very urgent matter.  He believed that the restriction of exports would be the most effective means of stabilising labour conditions.  The British Ministry of Labour were trying to keep their hold on the country, and had established a new office for the settling of Labour disputes, one which was partial to Labour and against the Employers.  The assistance of Labour should be obtained in the restricting of exports and the lowering of prices.</P>
<P>The DIRECTOR OF TRADE AND COMMERCE replied that the question of the establishment of the Economic Council would come on later, when he would ask for a vote towards its expenses.</P>
<P>J. MACGRATH (St. James', Dublin) stated that Labour was ready to move in the direction suggested by the Deputy for Tipperary North.</P>
<P>J.J. WALSH (Cork City) congratulated the Director on the wise decisions he had come to on the matter of Irish industries.  All shopkeepers should be notified of those decisions, so that people would not be working in the dark.</P>
<P>M.P. COLIVET (Limerick City) asked if the Department intended to take joint steps with the Department of Local Government regarding the pooling of contracts.</P>
<P>CATHAL BRUGHA (Waterford County) wanted information as regards the activities of the Consuls.</P>
<P>THE DIRECTOR OF TRADE AND COMMERCE stated that the Economic Council could not act if only Labour were a party to its functions.  The farmers should also be induced to take part. All parties should come in on equal terms.  He was acting jointly with the Local Government Department in the matter of the pooling of contracts, and had been present at meetings of the General Council of County Councils and of the Executive of that body. The Consuls were supplying information regarding markets and looking up opportunities for the sale of Irish goods.  They had also a propagandist value.  It was probable that the provision of the extra shipping for the United States Service was largely owing to the activity of Mr. Fawsitt. One of the advantages of an Export House would be that it could arrange contracts in such lines as poplin and boots.  The manufacturers, in the absence of such contracts, did not feel justified in extending their plant.</P>
<P>M.P. COLIVET (Limerick City) said that the extension of the export trade was one of the prime businesses of the Department.</P>
<P>J. MACBRIDE (Mayo West) stated that it was impossible to do an export trade without having a Warehouse.</P><P>The adoption of the Report was put and carried.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="DEPARTMENT OF" RHead="AGRICULTURE">
    <Title>DEPARTMENT OF AGRICULTURE.</Title>
<P>The SUBSTITUTE DIRECTOR OF AGRICULTURE, in the course of an oral Report, stated that as regards land disputes he had nothing in particular to say.  He submitted for the third time proposals for the establishment of a National Land Commission.  These proposals had gone through Committee, and he hoped that they would be accepted.  The proposals had been made as elastic as possible, the idea being to create a good framework, leaving such details as were found necessary to be filled in from time to time.  The general policy regarding ranches, etc., had been laid down in previous legislation.  It would be a mistake to attempt at the moment anything in the shape of a revolutionary policy regarding land.  He had circulated a memo, dealing in detail with Committees of Agriculture and as to how they might function.  When it was remembered that the export trade fostered by those Committees reached a gross total of £64,000,000 last year it would be seen that these Committees could play a <Col N="225"/> very important part in the industrial life of the country.  While recommending the clean cut with the British Department of Agriculture, he was against allowing the Committees of Agriculture to lapse.</P><P>Since the last session he had got into communication with one of the best forestry experts available in the country.  If appointed, his salary and expenses would not exceed £800 or £1,000.  Such a man could save a large amount of money to the country by preventing the cutting of woods prematurely and by instructing the Committees of Agriculture in the matters of afforestation and the establishment of nurseries.  He had succeeded in making his Department self-supporting up to the present, but with the establishment of the Land Commission the expenses would naturally be much greater.</P>
<P>The SECRETARY FOR FINANCE stated that provision had already been made in the estimates for the appointment of an Inspector of Forestry.  He was strongly of opinion that such an appointment should be made.</P>
<P>J. MACGUINNESS (Longford) moved, and F. FAHY (Galway South) seconded, that the Report be adopted.</P>
<P>The SUBSTITUTE DIRECTOR OF AGRICULTURE, in reply to a query, stated that he was convinced that the clean cut with the English Department of Agriculture would be made whether they wished it or not.  He knew that the English Department was very anxious to carry on, but the position of the Committees would be intolerable, inasmuch as they would have to submit to the Department's audit.  He failed to see what difference there was between an audit by the English Department of Agriculture and one by the English Local Government Board.</P>
<P>D. KENT (Cork East) feared that there were land troubles ahead owing to the threatening attitude of Labour. In some instances Labour had threatened to till farms which the occupiers proposed leaving go into grass next year.  He suggested that a Bill be drafted making tillage compulsory on all farms over thirty acres in extent. If next year the English Navy blockaded the Irish coasts they should be able to fall back on their own resources.</P>
<P>The DIRECTOR OF AGRICULTURE, in reply, stated that he would refer the points raised to the Economic Council. The farmers objected to compulsory tillage legislation, as they averred that Labour swallowed up all the profits.</P><P>The adoption of the Report was then put and carried.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="DEPARTMENT OF" RHead="PROPAGANDA">
    <Title>DEPARTMENT OF PROPAGANDA.</Title>
<P>The SUBSTITUTE DIRECTOR OF PROPAGANDA, in the course of his Report, stated that the object of his Department was to enlighten the unenlightened, but he was quite willing to send copies of the &ldquo;Bulletin&rdquo; to the Deputies. As regards Propaganda in England, it was directed towards those who were likely to influence public opinion there.  Propaganda in that country was very urgent, and he was in communication with the Irish Organisations there.  He had already suggested the establishment of a Propaganda Bureau in Geneva, and the importance of such a bureau was being borne home on him more and more every day.  The establishment of the Continental Bureau was largely a question of money.</P><P>Propaganda in the English Colonies was occupying his mind at the moment, and he hoped to be able to get into touch with Australia through the agency of Dr. Mannix.  In this way a new system of warfare might be created against England.  One of his reasons for advocating the establishment of a headquarters in Europe was to co-ordinate the efforts of all those who were friendly to Ireland.</P>
<P>The publicity given to the case of Ireland owing to the treatment of the Lord Mayor of Cork was the largest yet attained.  It was so great that foreign journalists thought that the Irish Government spent millions of money on propaganda in other countries. The only weapons being used <Col N="226"/> were the strength and truth of their cause.  The value of the advent of so many journalists to Ireland lap in the fact that they returned firmly convinced of the iniquity of the British occupation.  Dublin Castle had found it necessary to reorganise its whole propaganda system.  He was of opinion that the Republican propaganda campaign would continue to carry more and more weight outside Ireland.</P>
<P>M. STAINES (St. Michan's, Dublin) moved the adoption of the Report.  He was glad to know that their propaganda rested on truth.</P>
<P>R.J. MULCAHY (Clontarf) seconded the motion.</P>
<P>J. MACDONAGH (Tipperary North) thought that the results achieved by the Self-Determination League in England were negligible as far as Ireland was concerned.  The leaders there seemed to approach all questions with an air of hopelessness.  He believed that the Propaganda Department in England required a complete reorganisation. There was a tremendous number of Irish people in England who would be of great help if they were only got at in the proper manner.</P>
<P>The SUBSTITUTE DIRECTOR OF PROPAGANDA pointed out that the Self-Determination League in England was not a branch of his Department.  He was, however, doing his best to assist the efforts of the League along the right lines.</P>
<P>J. MACENTEE (Monaghan South) suggested that the Director of Propaganda enter into such negotiations as would enable him to utilise the Self-Determination League for conducting propaganda in England.  A special edition of the &ldquo;Bulletin&rdquo; should be printed and circulated there.</P>
<P>The SUBSTITUTE DIRECTOR OF PROPAGANDA having stated that he had already tried to carry out all that had been suggested, it was decided, on the motion of the ACTING-PRESIDENT, that the wishes of the Dáil regarding propaganda in England be conveyed to the Convention of the Self-Determination League which, was to assemble at an early date.</P><P>The motion that the Report be adopted was then put and carried.</P><P>At this point the Deputy for South Meath resumed the Chair.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="DEPARTMENT OF" RHead="FISHERIES">
    <Title>DEPARTMENT OF FISHERIES.</Title>
<P>The DIRECTOR OF FISHERIES, in submitting an oral Report, stated that the Committee which had been appointed at the last meeting to investigate the operations of the West Carbery Co-operative Fishing Society had not yet been able to submit their report.  He suggested that the Committee be reappointed and asked to investigate affairs on the spot.  Father Farragher was inquiring into disputes which had arisen in one or two of the fishing centres.</P>
<P>The SECRETARY FOR LOCAL GOVERNMENT proposed, and J. MACDONAGH (Tipperary North) seconded, the adoption of the Report.</P>
<P>JOHN HAYES (Cork West) said that the affairs of the West Carbery Fishing Society should be inquired into immediately, else the success of the autumn fishing season would be endangered.</P>
<P>JOHN O'MAHONY (Fermanagh South) inquired whether the Director of Fisheries had any control over the Bank advances for Fisheries.</P>
<P>The DIRECTOR OF FISHERIES, in reply, stated that any monies advanced by the Bank for Fishery purposes had first been sanctioned by the Department.</P>
<P>The ACTING-PRESIDENT moved, and J. MACDONAGH (Tipperary North) seconded, the re-appointment of the West Carbery Co-operative Fishing Society Inquiry Committee.</P><P>This was agreed to, and the motion for the adoption of the Report was then put and carried.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="DEPARTMENT" RHead="OF DEFENCE">
    <Title>DEPARTMENT OF DEFENCE.</Title>
<P>The SECRETARY FOR DEFENCE submitted an oral Report, which was adopted on the motion of P. O MAILLE (Connemara), seconded by F. LYNCH (Kerry South).</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="DEPARTMENT" RHead="OF IRISH">
    <Title>DEPARTMENT OF IRISH.</Title>
<P><Col N="227"/> The ASSISTANT MINISTER OF IRISH, in the course of an oral Report in Irish, stated that the scheme drawn up by the Department of Irish was being put into operation.  He hoped to have a full report on the subject for the next Session.  Much help had been given by the Departmental Committee, and he asked the Deputies to give all the assistance in their power.  The scheme of Education had been forwarded to the different Education Bodies, but no replies had been received from either the University or Intermediate Education Authorities. The request of the National Board that the Department interview them was not acceded to.  Whilst good progress was being made, especially in Clare and Cork, it was necessarily slow owing to the prevailing conditions.</P>
<P>ART O'CONNOR (Kildare South) proposed, and BRIAN O'HIGGINS (Clare West) seconded, the adoption of the Report.</P>
<P>P. O MAILLE (Connemara) criticised the appointment of one of the Organisers under the Department.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="RATIFICATION OF ASSISTANT" RHead="MINISTER FOR IRISH">
    <Title>RATIFICATION OF ASSISTANT MINISTER FOR IRISH.</Title>
<P>CATHAL BRUGHA (Waterford County) stated that the Committee exercised all due vigilance in the matter of the appointments. They had necessarily to be guided to a large extent by the views of the local people.  Owing to the inability of the Secretary for Irish to devote sufficient time to the duties of the position, Proinnsias O Fathaigh (Galway, South) had been appointed as Assistant Minister at the same salary as that allowed to Heads of Departments, viz., £400 per annum.  He now formally moved that the Dáil ratify the appointment.</P>
<P>P. O MAILLE (Connemara) seconded the motion.</P><P>The motions for the adoption of the Report and the ratification of the appointment of Proinsias O Fathaigh (Galway, South) as Assistant Minister for Irish were then put and carried.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="ORAL QUESTIONS. - APPOINTMENT" RHead="OF TOWN CLERK IN WATERFORD">
    <Title>ORAL QUESTIONS. - APPOINTMENT OF TOWN CLERK IN WATERFORD.</Title>
<P>J. MACDONAGH (Tipperary, North) to the Secretary for Local Government:&mdash;</P><P>&ldquo;Whether it has come to the knowledge of the Minister of Local Government that an Alderman of the Waterford Corporation immediately on his resignation from the Aldermanship took up the position of Town Clerk?</P><P>&ldquo;Is not this action by the Alderman in question and the members of the Waterford Corporation illegal? Is it not also very undesirable in view of the fact that the Waterford Corporation is composed largely of Republicans; and because the Alderman who was appointed was formerly the Sinn Fein Organiser for Waterford, and as such was responsible for the registration work in Waterford City in the Republican interest?&rdquo;</P><P>He understood that when the Clean Cut with the English Local Government was made that the Dáil took over all the Acts which tended against what might be regarded as corruption. One of those Acts laid it down that a man must have resigned his position as an elected representative at least six months before taking up a paid position under the Council of which he had been a member.</P>
<P>The SECRETARY FOR LOCAL GOVERNMENT stated that he had received no official intimation of the appointment.  He had written to the Mayor of Waterford and had asked him to furnish a report on the matter.  It was a moot point whether the clause governing the ineligibility of members for appointment to salaried positions under their own bodies applied to Borough Councils. He was consulting legal opinion on the matter, and would suspend judgment until then.  The late Town Clerk and his predecessor had been appointed without the position being advertised. The fact that the late Town Clerk, though given every opportunity by the new Corporation to mend his ways, had <Col N="228"/> proved himself utterly inefficient and neglectful of his duties disposed of any sound allegation that the man had been dismissed to make a job.  The members of the Waterford Corporation felt very strongly on the matter.  They had said that the man appointed was the only person who, in their opinion, could efficiently discharge the duties of Town Clerk.  They had stated that if his appointment was not sanctioned their position would become intolerable.  He had been unanimously appointed, and had neither wanted nor convassed for the position.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="ORAL QUESTIONS. - CLERKS OF LOCAL" RHead="BODIES AND THE IRISH LANGUAGE">
    <Title>ORAL QUESTIONS. - CLERKS OF LOCAL BODIES AND THE IRISH LANGUAGE.</Title>
<P>D. KENT (Cork, East) asked the Secretary for Local Government what arrangements should be made where substitutes were rendered necessary owing to the Clerk of a local authority being unable to discharge his duties from ignorance of the Irish language.</P>
<P>The SECRETARY FOR LOCAL GOVERNMENT stated that one similar case had arisen.  The decision was that the Clerk get six months to learn the language, and that the substitute be paid in the meantime by the Council.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="ORAL QUESTIONS. -" RHead="MINISTER FOR INDUSTRIES">
    <Title>ORAL QUESTIONS. - MINISTER FOR INDUSTRIES.</Title>
<P>The ACTING-PRESIDENT, in reply to a question by JOSEPH MACGRATH (St. James', Dublin), stated, that the Secretary for Industries had been away for a considerable time and that the Director of Trade and Commerce was discharging his duties.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="MINISTERIAL MOTIONS. - COMMISSION ON" RHead="ORGANISED OPPOSITION TO THE REPUBLIC">
    <Title>MINISTERIAL MOTIONS. - COMMISSION ON ORGANISED OPPOSITION TO THE REPUBLIC.</Title>
<P><b>Terms of Reference.</b></P>
<P>The ACTING-PRESIDENT moved:&mdash;</P><P>&ldquo;That the following be the terms of reference of the Commission on Organised Opposition to the Republic:&mdash;</P><P>&lsquo;To investigate and report on the organised opposition to the Republic amongst certain sections of the Irish people.</P><P>&lsquo;To consider the means by which such opposition can be abated or overcome.</P><P>&lsquo;To consider what steps can be taken to protect and strengthen the Republican population in areas in which the majority is hostile.&rsquo; &rdquo;</P>
<P>The DIRECTOR OF TRADE AND COMMERCE seconded the motion.</P><P>The motion was put and carried.</P><P>Vote of £400.</P>
<P>The ACTING-PRESIDENT moved:&mdash;</P><P>&ldquo;That a sum of £400 be voted towards the expenses of the Commission on Organised Opposition to the Republic.&rdquo;</P>
<P>The SECRETARY FOR LOCAL GOVERNMENT seconded the motion, which was adopted.</P><P>Membership.</P>
<P>On the motion of the ACTING-PRESIDENT it was agreed that the following persons should be invited to act on the Commission on Organised Opposition to the Republic:&mdash;</P><P>Eoin Mac Neill, Arthur Griffith, M. Collins, Rev. Fr. O'Kieran, Denis Mac Cullough, Rev. Dr. Irwin, Alex Mac Cabe, Erskine Childers, Cathal O Shannon, Thomas Johnston, P. Mac Gilligan, Desmond Fitzgerald, William Sears, Dermot Coffey, Rev. Fr. O Flanagan, P.S. O Hegarty, Owen O Duffy, Sean Mac Entee, J.N. Dolan, Rev. Fr. Mac Shane, Earnan de Blaghd, George Irvine and George Murnaghan.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="MINISTERIAL MOTIONS. -" RHead="LOCUM TENENS FOR DEPUTIES">
    <Title>MINISTERIAL MOTIONS. - LOCUM TENENS FOR DEPUTIES.</Title>
<P>The ACTING-PRESIDENT mentioned the matter of the appointment of Locum Tenens for Deputies which had been referred to the Ministry at the previous session.  The Ministry were of opinion that the Local Sinn Fein Executive should not be empowered to select Locum Tenens for Deputies.  In any case where a Deputy found that such an appointment was necessary he should himself select the Locum Tenens.</P><P>The matter dropped.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="MINISTERIAL MOTIONS. -" RHead="INCREASE OF RENT DECREE">
    <Title>MINISTERIAL MOTIONS. - INCREASE OF RENT DECREE.</Title>
<P><Col N="229"/> The consideration of the proposed Increase of Rent Decree was postponed to the next session.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="MINISTERIAL MOTIONS. - NON-RECOGNITION" RHead="OF HOSTILE LEGISLATION">
    <Title>MINISTERIAL MOTIONS. - NON-RECOGNITION OF HOSTILE LEGISLATION.</Title>
<P>The SECRETARY FOR HOME AFFAIRS moved:&mdash;</P><P>&ldquo;That the Ministry of Home Affairs be empowered to make orders from time to time declaring that any particular Act or Acts of the British Parliament or Orders thereunder or any parts of such Acts or Orders being clearly motived by a religious or political animosity to the Irish people or repugnant to the Republican Government or to Irish ideals, shall not be recognised by the Irish Republic and shall not be applied in the Law Courts of the Republic, and that on making any such order the Ministry may make any consequential orders which may be deemed necessary or expedient.&rdquo;</P>
<P>The SECRETARY FOR LOCAL GOVERNMENT seconded the motion, which was adopted.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="MINISTERIAL MOTIONS. - BILL FOR THE" RHead="PROTECTION OF IRISH INDUSTRIES">
    <Title>MINISTERIAL MOTIONS. - BILL FOR THE PROTECTION OF IRISH INDUSTRIES.</Title>
<P>The DIRECTOR OF TRADE AND COMMERCE moved his Bill for the Protection of Irish Industries, and explained its provisions.</P><P>The following is the proposed</P><P Just="Center">DECREE FOR THE PROTECTION OF IRISH INDUSTRIES.</P><P>WHEREAS it is impossible at the present juncture to establish a customs tariff and impose regular duties upon foreign goods on their entry into Ireland, and in consequence the protection of Irish Industries must take the form chiefly of discrimination by individual citizens in favour of Irish products, WHEREAS for the Dáil to call upon the people of Ireland to buy Irish goods without stipulation as to value, labour conditions, or allegiance of the firms producing them, might lead to the most loyal citizens of the Republic being taxed out of proportion to their means or to their being improperly and need lessly taxed, AND WHEREAS failure on the part of retailers to stock Irish goods would seriously impede the effort of consumers to give a constant preference to Irish manufacture.</P><P>IT IS HEREBY DECREED</P><P>(Schedule of Irish Goods).</P><P>1.  The Department of Trade and Commerce shall compile a schedule of Irish goods which it shall be the duty of citizens of the Irish Republic to purchase, to the exclusion of similar articles of foreign origin.</P><P>2.  The name and address of the maker of every article on the schedule shall be stated.</P><P>3. (1)  No article shall be put upon the schedule unless the Minister for Trade and Commerce on the advice of competent technical and commercial experts is satisfied that its price is not more than 5 per cent. greater than that of any closely similar foreign-made article of equal quality readily procurable in Ireland.</P><P>(2)  The price considered shall be that charged to the consumer, but if the selling price does not allow a reasonable percentage of profit to the retailer, due addition shall be made to such price in deciding whether the article shall be put on the schedule.  It shall not be held that a retailer is in any particular case entitled to the same profit on Irish goods as on competing foreign-made goods, but only to a reasonable profit.</P><P>(3)  Committees representative of various trades shall be set up to advise the Department of Trade and Commerce as to what profits may be regarded as reasonable for the purposes of this section on all classes of goods.</P><P>4.  Any article may be omitted or removed from the schedule:&mdash;</P><P>(a)  If it is produced by sweated labour.</P>
<P><Col N="230"/> (b)  If it is made by a foreign firm in Ireland or by a firm avowedly hostile to the national interests.</P><P>(c)  If its makers do not themselves give reasonable support to Irish Industry.</P><P>(d)  If the supply is insufficient and there does not appear to be a probability of its being immediately increased.</P><P>(e)  If its makers refuse to brand it with their name or a registered mark.</P><P>5.  The schedule shall be re-issued and revised from time to time as the Minister for Trade and Commerce may consider necessary.</P><P>6.  The Minister for Trade and Commerce shall have power, if he thinks proper, to fix a fee to be paid by each manufacturer in respect of each class of article made by him and listed on the schedule.</P><P>(The Stocking of Irish Goods).</P><P>7.  (1)  Every retailer stocking foreign goods of a class which is made in Ireland shall also stock one or more scheduled makes of goods of the same class.</P><P>(2)  Any retailer failing to comply with this section shall be liable to a fine not exceeding £5 in respect of each class of goods which he fails to stock.</P><P>The penalty may be imposed for every day the offence is wilfully continued.</P><P>There shall be no conviction if it be shown that the retailer has taken all reasonable care to procure scheduled goods in good time and sufficient quantity.</P><P>8.  (1)  Every retailer shall display prominently in his shop an accurate list of the Irish goods stocked by him.  The list shall show the name and address of the manufacturer of each article.</P><P>(2)  Any retailer failing to comply with this section shall be liable to a fine of £5 for the first offence and £20 for every subsequent offence.</P><P Just="Center">(Embargo on Shops).</P><P>9.  In the case of any retailer who has been twice convicted for non-compliance with the requirements of this Decree and has refused to pay the fines inflicted on him, the President of a District Court may certify to the Department of Trade and Commerce that such retailer has deliberately refused obedience to this Decree.  The Minister for Trade and Commerce with the concurrence of the President may, thereupon, by proclamation put the shop of such retailer under embargo.</P><P>10.  Any person found trading in a shop under embargo shall be liable to a fine of £1 for each offence.</P><P Just="Center">(Prohibition of Sale of Foreign Goods).</P><P>11.  (1)  When the Minister for Trade and Commerce is satisfied in the case of any particular class of goods that the scheduled makes are produced in sufficient quantity to meet the demand, that there is sufficient variety as to quality and type, and that a monopoly would not thereby be created, he may with the concurrence of the President prohibit retailers from taking into stock any foreign makes of such goods.</P><P>(2)  The penalty for continuing to take into stock prohibited foreign goods shall be, on the first conviction not exceeding £20, and on every subsequent conviction not exceeding £100.</P><P>The penalty may be imposed in respect of each class of goods set out separately in the prohibition, but shall not be imposed twice in respect of the same lot of goods.  A retailer refusing to pay fines imposed under this section may be put under embargo.</P>
<P>12.  The Minister for Trade and Commerce may empower individuals, Sinn Fein Clubs, Industrial Development Associations, or other bodies to institute proceedings under this Decree before District Courts or <Col N="231"/> other Courts authorised by Dáil Eireann.</P>
<P>The SECRETARY FOR LOCAL GOVERNMENT seconded the motion.</P>
<P>JOSEPH MACBRIDE (Mayo, West) looked upon the system of control outlined in the Bill as an abomination. Traders should not be coerced.  Under the proposed Bill foreign firms established in Ireland would be ruled out, with the result that trade could not be carried on.  Clause 4 (d) would result in the wiping out of small manufacturers, who could not turn out sufficient supplies.  It was rather a harsh proceeding to make retailers who failed to supply Irish goods liable to a fine of £5.</P>
<P>R.M. SWEETMAN (Wexford, North) agreed with the Deputy for Mayo, West. He had never come across any scheme giving inducements to retailers to stock Irish goods, and they were now propounding a system of fines for those very people.</P>
<P>J.J. WALSH (Cork City) contended that the retailer would stock whatever there was a demand for.  The Irish public were asleep as regards their duty to support Irish manufacture.  A big campaign in favour of Irish Industries should be organised.</P>
<P>J. MACDONAGH (Tipperary, North), moved as an amendment:&mdash;</P><P>&ldquo;That Clauses 4 (d), 6, 8 (2), 9, 10, 11 (1), and 11 (2) be deleted from the Bill.&rdquo;</P><P>He thought that the remainder of the Bill was very good.  The effect of accepting the Bill <i>in globo</i> would be to restrict trade to such an extent that shopkeepers would be inclined to oppose the whole scheme.</P>
<P>COUNTESS DE MARKIEVICZ (St. Patrick's, Dublin) believed that if customers could not get the goods they required from their local retailers they would procure them by post from London. This Bill by prohibiting the stocking of foreign goods, placed a premium on one of the worst forms of trading, viz., shopping by post.  She admitted on the other hand that there were many retailers who would not stock Irish-made goods unless they were forced to do so.</P>
<P>M. STAINES (St. Michan's, Dublin) suggested that the Bill be postponed to the next Session so that the Members might have a chance of studying it.  The measure was a very important and a very drastic one.  While Clause 4 (d) might adversely affect small manufacturers he knew of large manufacturers in Dublin who would be enabled by its operation to double their staffs.</P>
<P>The DIRECTOR OF TRADE AND COMMERCE expressed his willingness to postpone the Bill to the next Session and confer with interested parties in the meantime.</P>
<P>On the motion of the ACTING-PRESIDENT, seconded by J. MACBRIDE (Mayo, West), the Bill was taken as read the first time.</P>
<P>On the motion of PADRAIG O MAILLE (Connemara), seconded by R.M. SWEETMAN (Wexford, North), the following were appointed a Committee to discuss the Bill, Clause by Clause, and report to the next Session:&mdash;</P><P>Cathal Brugha, Domhnall O Buachalla, Seamus Breathnach, J. MacBride, M.P. Colivet, J. MacGrath, J. MacGuinness, J. O'Mahony, M. Staines, P. O'Keeffe, P.O Maille, Count Plunkett, J. MacDonagh, and J.N. Dolan.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="MINISTERIAL MOTIONS. - BILL FOR THE" RHead="FORMATION OF AN ECONOMIC COUNCIL">
    <Title>MINISTERIAL MOTIONS. - BILL FOR THE FORMATION OF AN ECONOMIC COUNCIL.</Title>
<P>The DIRECTOR OF TRADE AND COMMERCE presented a Bill for the formation of an Economic Council and moved its adoption.  The text of the Bill is as follows:&mdash;</P><P Just="Center">NATIONAL ECONOMIC COUNCIL.</P><P>1.  The National Economic Council shall be established by Dáil Eireann as a Government Board and shall carry out such duties as may from time to time be assigned to it.  The funds necessary for its work shall be provided by vote of the Dáil and its employees shall be servants of the Dáil.</P>
<P><Col N="232"/> 2.  Membership of the Council shall consist of two elements:&mdash;</P><P>(a)  A nominated element comprising representatives of various Departments of the Ministry and experts and others having special knowledge nominated by the Ministry.</P><P>(b)  An elected element comprising duly accredited representatives of various organised economic interests, such as Labour, Agriculture (Farmers' Union, etc.), Co-operation, etc., and representatives of some of the local Public Bodies.</P><P>3.  The duties of the Council shall be:&mdash;</P><P>(a)  To examine and report on all current economic questions referred to it by the Dáil or the Cabinet and generally to advise the Republican Government in regard to economic policy.</P><P>(b)  By providing a common ground for representatives of various economic interests and by promoting negotiations between them to secure agreements and joint action which will safeguard national interests.</P><P>4.  Decisions of the Council on matters not relating to procedure or internal discipline shall be with the consent of the representatives of the interests concerned.  Where agreement cannot be reached majority and minority reports may be submitted to An Dáil.  The Secretary of the Council shall supply the Ministry with copies of the minutes of the Council and its Sub-Committees.</P><P>He also moved that a Vote of £400 be made to cover the expenses of the Council to 31st December, 1920.</P>
<P>J. MACBRIDE (Mayo, West) seconded the motions, which were put and carried.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="MINISTERIAL MOTIONS. -" RHead="ALDERMAN THOMAS KELLY, T.D">
    <Title>MINISTERIAL MOTIONS. - ALDERMAN THOMAS KELLY, T.D.</Title>
<P>The SECRETARY FOR FINANCE moved:</P><P>&ldquo;That an immediate payment of the sum of £250 to Alderman Thomas Kelly, T.D., be authorised.&rdquo;</P><P>He said that the expenses connected with the breakdown in his health as a result of his imprisonment had been very heavy.</P>
<P>M. STAINES (St. Michan's, Dublin) seconded the motion, which was put and carried.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="MINISTERIAL MOTIONS. - LABOUR" RHead="ARBITRATION TRIBUNAL EXPENSES">
    <Title>MINISTERIAL MOTIONS. - LABOUR ARBITRATION TRIBUNAL EXPENSES.</Title>
<P>The SECRETARY FOR LABOUR moved:</P><P>&ldquo;That a sum of £500 be voted towards the expenses of the Labour Arbitration Tribunals.&rdquo;</P>
<P>J.N. DOLAN (Leitrim) seconded the motion, which was put and carried.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="MINISTERIAL MOTIONS. -" RHead="POLICE EMPLOYMENT BUREAU">
    <Title>MINISTERIAL MOTIONS. - POLICE EMPLOYMENT BUREAU.</Title>
<P>The SECRETARY FOR LABOUR moved, and the ACTING-PRESIDENT seconded, the following resolution, which was put and carried:</P><P>&ldquo;That a sum of £350 be voted towards the expenses of the Police Employment Bureau.&rdquo;</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="MINISTERIAL MOTIONS. - BILL FOR" RHead="ESTABLISHMENT OF NATIONAL LAND COMMISSION">
    <Title>MINISTERIAL MOTIONS. - BILL FOR ESTABLISHMENT OF NATIONAL LAND COMMISSION.</Title>
<P>The SUBSTITUTE DIRECTOR OF AGRICULTURE, in moving the adoption of the Bill, stated that the Committee appointed at the last Session had discussed the Bill clause by clause.  The only amendment made consisted of a slight alteration in Clause 2, Section (a).  He had inserted the alteration in order to make it clear that the powers of the Commission were not limited to judicial matters.</P>
<P>J.N. DOLAN (Leitrim) seconded the motion, which was put and carried.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="MINISTERIAL MOTIONS. -" RHead="ENQUIRY INTO ATROCITIES">
    <Title>MINISTERIAL MOTIONS. - ENQUIRY INTO ATROCITIES.</Title>
<P>The ACTING-PRESIDENT read the following extract from that morning's <i>Irish Independent:</i>&mdash;</P>
<P>&ldquo;Reuter's Agency has received a communication from the London Correspondent of the New York <i>Nation</i> which states that the following appeal <Col N="233"/> was recently sent by that paper to a number of prominent Americans:&mdash;</P><P>&lsquo;The struggle between Great Britain and Ireland, which has gone on for many months with an increasing use of armed force by both parties, is widely reported to be accompanied by atrocities planned by the British Government and answered in kind by the Irish people.  One grave result is the rapid growth of anti-British feeling which seriously threatens the unspeakable calamity of war between the United States and Great Britain and endangers the Peace of the world.  In the interests of peace and international friendship, the Editors of the &lsquo;Nation' earnestly invite you to serve as a member of a non-partisan Committee of representative Americans, with power to add to their number, who shall designate a Select Commission, to sit at Washington or elsewhere, for the impartial investigation of atrocities in Ireland, regarding which the British Ambassador and Professor de Valera and others shall be invited to submit evidence.  The proposal does not contemplate any recommendations regarding the future political relations between Great Britain and Ireland.&rsquo;</P><P>&ldquo;It is added that over 80 acceptances have been received from Senators, Congressmen, Mayors, lawyers and others, and it is expected that the Committee will within a fortnight be able to select a small Commission which will sit in Washington early in October.</P><P>&ldquo;The New York Correspondent of the <i>Daily Chronicle</i> (quoted by special arrangement) says Mrs. McSwiney, wife of the Lord Mayor of Cork, will appear before the Committee. The English point of view, he adds, will be fully presented.&rdquo;</P><P>He suggested that every Teachta should collect in his Constituency all the available accounts of burnings, outrages, shootings, and other crimes and transmit the evidence to the Propaganda Department.  The Mayors and Chairmen of Urban Councils should be asked to help in this matter.  He understood that the Mayor of Limerick had already taken action such as that now suggested.</P>
<P>The SUBSTITUTE DIRECTOR OF PROPAGANDA dwelt on the necessity of getting the names and ranks of the perpetrators of the outrages.</P>
<P>The ACTING-SPEAKER advised that persons with legal knowledge should be consulted in the compilation of the statements.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="MINISTERIAL MOTIONS. - WITHDRAWAL OF" RHead="MOTION FROM DEPARTMENT OF DEFENCE">
    <Title>MINISTERIAL MOTIONS. - WITHDRAWAL OF MOTION FROM DEPARTMENT OF DEFENCE.</Title>
<P>The MINISTER FOR DEFENCE stated that he had been informed that it was not necessary for him to move for a specific vote for his Department, as the sum required would come out of the vote made last Session.  He therefore withdrew the motion.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="MINISTERIAL MOTIONS." RHead="- BELFAST BOYCOTT">
    <Title>MINISTERIAL MOTIONS. - BELFAST BOYCOTT.</Title>
<P>The ACTING PRESIDENT stated that it was the desire of those in charge of the Boycott in Belfast that some one resident in Dublin should take charge of the matter in Dublin.  He suggested the name of the Deputy for St. Michan's, Dublin.</P><P>After some discussion Mr. Staines was prevailed upon to undertake this work.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="NON-MINISTERIAL MOTIONS." RHead="- PAYMENTS TO DEPUTIES">
    <Title>NON-MINISTERIAL MOTIONS. - PAYMENTS TO DEPUTIES.</Title>
<P>J.J. WALSH (Cork City) moved:</P><P>&ldquo;That an allowance of £250 per annum be given to each Member of An Dáil not holding an Executive appointment, so that he may be able properly and efficiently to discharge his duties.&rdquo;</P><P>The expenses incurred by the Deputies in connection with their work were very heavy, and this allowance would be in the nature of a Grant to cover those expenses rather than in the nature of a salary.</P>
<P>D. KENT (Cork, East) seconded the motion.</P>
<P><Col N="234"/> J. MACENTEE (Monaghan, South) supported the motion.  It was necessary that the Deputies should in ordinary circumstances give most of their time to the work of the Dáil.</P>
<P>J. MACGUINNESS (Longford) proposed that the question be postponed for twelve months.  Certain individual cases could be considered by the Ministry.</P>
<P>J. MACBRIDE (Mayo, West) seconded the amendment.</P>
<P>CATHAL BRUGHA (Waterford County) was in favour of the creation of a fund to help those Members who had been victimised owing to their position.</P>
<P>J. MACDONAGH (Tipperary, North) suggested that Deputies who incur out-of-pocket expenses in connection with work in their constituencies should be recouped by the Dáil on application.</P><P>After further discussion the amendment with this addition was put and declared carried by 20 votes for to 13 against.</P><P>The amendment thus became a substantive motion.</P>
<P>The SECRETARY FOR FINANCE moved as a further amendment:</P><P>&ldquo;That a Deputies' Expenses' Fund be established, out of which each month, on application, any Member requiring same may be paid one-twelfth of the sum of £250.  The existing regulations regarding claims for expenses for special journeys to remain unaltered.&rdquo;</P>
<P>D. KENT (Cork, East) seconded the amendment.</P>
<P>The ACTING PRESIDENT and J.J. WALSH (Cork City) thought this suggestion would meet the case.</P><P>All the other proposals having been withdrawn in favour of the motion of the Secretary for Finance, it was put and agreed to.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="NON-MINISTERIAL MOTIONS." RHead="- MOTION WITHDRAWN">
    <Title>NON-MINISTERIAL MOTIONS. - MOTION WITHDRAWN.</Title>
<P>The motion regarding the development of the Arigna Coal Area, standing in the name of the Deputy for Leitrim, was by leave of the House withdrawn.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="NON-MINISTERIAL MOTIONS." RHead="- COMMERCIAL INSURANCE">
    <Title>NON-MINISTERIAL MOTIONS. - COMMERCIAL INSURANCE.</Title>
<P>J. MACDONAGH (Tipperary, North) moved:&mdash;</P><P>&ldquo;That Dáil Eireann immediately erects machinery for the purpose of protecting merchants and others with Republican sympathies throughout Ireland against losses caused by Riot, Civil Commotion, and Incendiarism.&rdquo;</P><P>Fabulous sums were at present being paid as premiums in respect of those classes of insurance owing to the organised system of enemy outrages.  While the Insurance Companies had guaranteed payment in the case of burnings, etc., two clauses had recently been inserted in the policies which rendered them null and void.  Those clauses meant that where insurers possessed Republican sympathies their policies were not worth the paper they were written on.  It was necessary that a scheme be compiled whereby such insurers could insure their property at ordinary rates.</P>
<P>On the suggestion of the SECRETARY FOR FINANCE the matter was referred to the Ministry, the Deputy for Tipperary to be present when it was discussed.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="NON-MINISTERIAL MOTIONS. - DEPUTIES'" RHead="EXPENSES' FUND: VOTE OF £1,000">
    <Title>NON-MINISTERIAL MOTIONS. - DEPUTIES' EXPENSES' FUND: VOTE OF £1,000.</Title>
<P>On the motion of the SECRETARY FOR FINANCE, seconded by the ACTING PRESIDENT, a sum of £1,000 was voted to the Deputies' Expenses' Fund.</P><P>This concluded the business of the Session, and the House adjourned at 6.45 p.m.</P>
  </MainHeading>
</Debate>
