<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE Debate SYSTEM "../Debate.dtd"[]>
<Debate DocTitle="Seanad Debate" Day="Thu" Date="15" Month="Nov" Year="1990" Vol="126" No="11" DateIrish="Déardaoin, 15 Samhain 1990" DateEnglish="Thursday, 15 November 1990" House="S" CommitteeEng="" CommitteeIr="" SubNameEng="" cnum="0">
  <MainHeading Type="Prelude" LHead="" RHead="">
    <Title>
    </Title>
    <P>
      <Col N="1461" /> Chuaigh an Cathaoirleach i gceannas ar 10.30 a.m.</P>
    <P Just="Center">
      <i>Paidir.</i>
    </P>
    <P Just="Center">
      <i>Prayer.</i>
    </P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Business" RHead="of Seanad">
    <Title>Business of Seanad.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="SeanDoherty" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I have notice from Seanator Éamon Ó Cuív that, on the motion for the Adjournment of the House today, he proposes to raise the following matter:</P>
      <P>To ask the Minister for Industry and Commerce to ask the Fair Trade Commission to examine the charges for telecommunications charged by Telecom Éireann particularly as they relate to rural areas.</P>
      <P>I regard the matter raised by Senator Ó Cuív as suitable for discussion on the Adjournment and it will be taken at the conclusion of business.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Order of" RHead="Business">
    <Title>Order of Business.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFallon" hpid="Mr. Fallon Mr. Fallon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Fallon</NameTxt>
      <P>It is proposed to take items Nos. 2, 3 &mdash; Committee and Final Stages &mdash; and No. 4.  There will be a sos between 1 p.m. and 2 p.m.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MauriceManning" hpid="Mr. Manning Mr. Manning">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Manning</NameTxt>
      <P>Were we to resume item No. 5 today?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFallon" hpid="Mr. Fallon Mr. Fallon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Fallon</NameTxt>
      <P>No.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MauriceManning" hpid="Mr. Manning Mr. Manning">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Manning</NameTxt>
      <P>When is it proposed to take item No. 1?  On a general point I am <Col N="1462" /> a little bit concerned about the absence of substantial business coming to the House. Perhaps the Leader could let us know if there is some substantial business coming over the forthcoming weeks.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeOToole" hpid="Mr. O'Toole Mr. O'Toole">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Toole</NameTxt>
      <P>On the European debate which was being discussed last night, I understood we were to conclude that debate yesterday afternoon or else continue it today.  I would prefer to continue today and conclude it today on the basis that I believe that next week there will be other subjects for discussion.  There did not seem to be a great queue of speakers last night on the issue.  I felt that it would be possible to conclude it easily enough.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TrasHonan" hpid="Mrs. Honan Mrs. Honan">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Honan</NameTxt>
      <P>The Senator is wrong there.  There were plenty of speakers.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatUpton" hpid="Dr. Upton Dr. Upton">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Upton</NameTxt>
      <P>Is there any question of the Environmental Protection Agency Bill being introduced in this House?  Can the Senator give us any indication of when we can expect it to be debated here?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PaschalMooney" hpid="Mr. Mooney Mr. Mooney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Mooney</NameTxt>
      <P>Would the Leader of the House convey to the Government the overwhelming desire of the majority of Irish people that the Birmingham Six be immediately released in the light of the reports that the DPP in Britain is not going to proceed with the appeal hearing?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PolOFoighil" hpid="Pól Ó Foighil Pól Ó Foighil">
      <NameTxt>Pól Ó Foighil</NameTxt>
      <P>Ba mhaith liom a fhiafraí den Cheannaire, tríd an Chathaoirleach, an mbeadh an Coiste um Nós Imeachta agus Pribhléidí sásta castáil liom inniu le ceist phráinneach an chóras aistriúcháin a phlé, mar ceapaim go bhfuil mo chearta bunreachtúla sáraithe sa Teach seo, mar a dúirt mé anseo cheana.  Tá faitíos mór orm nach mbeidh an córas ná an fhoireann le fáil tar éis na Nollag.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidNorris" hpid="Mr. Norris Mr. Norris">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norris</NameTxt>
      <P>I also had understood that we were continuing with statements regarding European Economic Monetary Union and European Political Union today.  Even if that is not the case I am hopeful you will be able to give us an assurance that there will be a satisfactory <Col N="1463" /> amount of time allowed next week.  I also indicated that I would be moving an amendment to the Order of Business, which I will be pressing.  That is, that we take item No. 80 first: &ldquo;That Seanad Éireann expresses concern at the Government's total lack of action in meeting the requirements of last October's judgment in the European Court of Human Rights concerning discrimination against homosexual citizens of Ireland&rdquo;.  I formally propose that amendment to the Order of Business and I will continue doing so until there is some sign of action from the Government.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanDoherty" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator Seán Fallon to reply.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFallon" hpid="Mr. Fallon Mr. Fallon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Fallon</NameTxt>
      <P>The various items&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BrendanRyan" hpid="Mr. B. Ryan Mr. B. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. B. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>May I second Senator Norris's amendment to the Order of Business?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanDoherty" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I am sorry I have made a ruling on this before.  I have called on the Leader of the House to reply.  The discussion must include the seconding. Otherwise, it cannot be accepted at this point.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFallon" hpid="Mr. Fallon Mr. Fallon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Fallon</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator Manning and other Senators asked about item No. 5 on the Order Paper, which deals with the European Economic and Monetary Union.  I think the record will clearly show that yesterday I said we would have a continuation next week.  That is the position and the Whips will be meeting regarding that.  Senator Norris asked could we have additional time for that discussion.  As far as I am concerned we, certainly, on this side of the House want extra time.  Yesterday, I have to say, despite what Senator O'Toole said, we had seven speakers waiting to speak on that matter yesterday.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeOToole" hpid="Mr. O'Toole Mr. O'Toole">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Toole</NameTxt>
      <P>My apologies.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFallon" hpid="Mr. Fallon Mr. Fallon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Fallon</NameTxt>
      <P>Accepted.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1464" />
    <Speaker pid="TrasHonan" hpid="Mrs. Honan Mrs. Honan">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Honan</NameTxt>
      <P>No, never.  We may be down, but we are not out.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFallon" hpid="Mr. Fallon Mr. Fallon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Fallon</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator Manning also referred to item No. 1 which, as I indicated to Senator Myles Staunton yesterday, is a private business.  We can take Second Stage next Wednesday, if that is what Senators want.  I understand it is in order to take it and the Whips will meet to talk about that Bill.  As regards the Environmental Agency Bill to which Senator Upton referred, I understand it is still not ready.  He also asked whether it will be introduced here or not.  My understanding again is that there are seven new Bills ready for initiation, and I am hopeful that we will get something. I cannot say specifically if we will get that Bill or not.  I would like to think we would, but we must wait and see.  Senator Mooney raised something which was not appropriate to the Order of Business and the point raised by Senator Ó Foighil was raised yesterday also on the Order of Business.  The Committee on Procedure and Privileges met last evening and hopefully cleared the situation for movement in that direction.  Senator Norris asked for extra time on the EC motion.  He also asked a question about Item No. 80 on the clár.  It is not proposed to take that today.</P>
      <P>Order of Business agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Indemnity of Cathaoirleach:" RHead="Motion">
    <Title>Indemnity of Cathaoirleach: Motion.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFallon" hpid="Mr. Fallon Mr. Fallon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Fallon</NameTxt>
      <P>I move:</P>
      <P>That Seanad Éireann requests the Minister for Finance to grant an indemnity to the Cathaoirleach and his successors in Office against any claims for personal liability that may be made against him on foot of the contract for televising of Seanad proceedings.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>In accordance with a resolution of Seanad Éireann, dated 10 July 1990, Windmill Lane Pictures Ltd. have been engaged to supply the system for televising Seanad proceedings.  It is hoped to sign the formal contract very soon.  The contracting party <Col N="1465" /> on behalf of the Seanad will be the Cathaoirleach.  The copyright of recorded material will rest in him also.</P>
    <P>It is essential that the Cathaoirleach be indemnified against any personal liability arising out of the contract and the vesting of copyright as aforesaid.  However, there are doubts as to whether Seanad Éireann is in a position to offer such an indemnity because it appears that it is not a legal entity capable of being sued.  It is proposed, therefore, that the Minister for Finance be requested to grant the indemnity. Legal advice has indicated that if the Minister for Finance wishes to grant an indemnity to the Cathaoirleach against personal liability with claims made against him on foot of the contract there appears nothing in the Constitution to prohibit him from doing so.  It suggests, however, that in order to make clear the Constitutional distinction between the Government and the Oireachtas he should do so only on a request from Seanad Éireann.  Accordingly, this motion is before the House for agreement.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MauriceManning" hpid="Mr. Manning Mr. Manning">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Manning</NameTxt>
      <P>This was discussed in some detail on the committee dealing with the televising of this House.  The matter has been examined in some fair detail, so I would have no difficulty in supporting what has been proposed today.  I would also like to say how pleased I am at the progress that has been made towards the televising of this House.  We were somewhat late into this in spite of the best efforts of the previous Cathaoirleach who certainly gave it her full support from the first moment, but we did tend to get somehow left behind. I am glad now that plans are very well advanced.  I would hope that we will be on screen almost as soon as the other House.  However, this particular motion today has my support.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeOToole" hpid="Mr. J. O'Toole Mr. J. O'Toole">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J. O'Toole</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not have any difficulty in supporting the thrust and the aims of this particular legislation.  I have also made that clear at the Committee on Procedure and Privileges; but I do have a problem with two aspects of it.  First, there is confusion despite the best legal <Col N="1466" /> advice available to us, as to who represents the Seanad for legal purposes in situations like this.  That should be cleared up.  I am more concerned about the confusion that exists between the role of Government and the role of the House.  It is my view that for the purposes of arrangements like this the Seanad itself should be in the position to indemnify the Cathaoirleach or, indeed, any other officer as the case would arise, in similar situations.  It seems to me that what we are trying to do here this morning is ask the Minister for Finance to bankroll the House.  That is a bit unusual.  It is somewhat unacceptable.  I have not come across a model to compare with this one before.  I do not know whether there has been any parallel situation.  I want to stress that I totally support the proposal, but it has raised two very serious questions which to me are merging together. There are not clear differentials between them.</P>
      <P>We have taken the decision as a House of the Oireachtas.  On the basis of that we should have clearly nominated an identifiable officer or representative to sign or take responsibility on our behalf. Having done that, we, as a House of the Oireachtas, should indemnify and guarantee that person against any liabilities that might arise when he or she acts on our behalf.  That seems to be a very clear arrangement.  It would be the arrangement that I would prefer to see introduced.  I am not clear as to why that cannot be done.  At the end of the day the Department of Finance have to pick up the cheque, as they do for all the decisions of this House.  I am not quite clear as to why we need to go on this roundabout way to do it.  It seems to me that the Government are in some way interfering with the autonomous role the House should have in ordering its own business, in taking responsibility for its own affairs and in making its own decisions.  Were the Minister for Finance to say tomorrow morning &ldquo;I am not going to accept this responsibility&rdquo; where then would we be?  I know there is not the slightest possibility of that happening, but you must see the point I am making.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="1467" /> We are now doing this at the will of Government, not at our own decision. The Minister for Finance could decide &ldquo;it is not within my brief to cover this indemnity, to underwrite the risk of the Seanad&rdquo;.  That leaves us somewhat exposed.  We should have been in a stronger position to take these kinds of decisions ourselves and to cover for whichever officers or individuals we put forward to sign on our behalf.</P>
    <Speaker pid="DavidNorris" hpid="Mr. Norris Mr. Norris">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norris</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not intend to delay the House very long on this matter.  This is another occasion on which quite complicated, technical material relating to the broadcasting of proceedings from this House has been laid before us without much preparation or discussion.  I do not really feel that, as ordinary Members of the House, we have been kept as fully informed of the developments as, perhaps, we ought to have been.  I am concerned at that.  Repeatedly, as I may make this point to the Leader of the House, this has happened.  I know that everybody is anxious that we should go on air as early as possible, but I am concerned because of the technical matters involved.  For example, is it for some particular technical reason that the copyright of every speech made by individual persons here is vested in the Cathaoirleach? Presumably it is vested in the Office of Cathaoirleach, not in the specific person who holds that position at the time of the recording.  What happens if, in 20 or 30 years' time, a controversial item from the past is broadcast and somebody then takes action?  This is not a laughable or hypothetical situation.  I can illustrate it from my own knowledge of Joycean studies.  A story appears in the Hades' episode of Ulysses about Ruben J. Dodd who commits suicide for love or attempts to and is rescued and is fished out.  His father gives the man who rescues him half a crown.  Simon Dedalus in this episode remarks wryly: &ldquo;one and six pence too much&rdquo;.  It was heard by Ruben Dodd in 1950 and he took a successful action for libel so there can be delayed impact in these things.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1468" />
    <Speaker pid="SeanDoherty" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Was it against the Cathaoirleach of the Seanad?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidNorris" hpid="Mr. Norris Mr. Norris">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norris</NameTxt>
      <P>Not against the Cathaoirleach of the Seanad.  I am afraid, Sir, your courage and daring did not extend on that occasion in 1904 to rescuing Ruben J. Dodd, junior, but I am sure if you had been there at the time you would have gallantly jumped into the water.  I want to know why the Cathaoirleach, rather than Seanad Éireann itself, is named here and, secondly, is it the person of the Cathaoirleach as an officer or as an individual who is involved?  I am sure there is, perhaps, a legal reason for it but because the speeches of all of us will be perhaps broadcast, we are entitled to be more fully consulted.  I do not know where the responsibility for that lies, but I really think it is an important matter. We should not just rush into it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MauriceManning" hpid="Mr. Manning Mr. Manning">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Manning</NameTxt>
      <P>There is a full legal briefing document on all of these questions which was available to the committee. It would be sensible if this could be made available to all Members, and if the senior counsel could speak to all Members on these matters.  It is technical. We are covering a great deal of ground here that has been covered already.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFallon" hpid="Mr. Fallon Mr. Fallon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Fallon</NameTxt>
      <P>I was about to say that this matter has been discussed.  We were informed at the time.  Obviously, the decisions we have made were made in the light of that legal opinion.  I presume that while Senator Norris talks about the Cathaoirleach we mean the Office holder of Cathaoirleach for the time being.  All I can say to further add to the correctness of this matter is that the other House has introduced a similar motion and it has been passed.  A lot of thought was given to it.  I understand very positively Senator Norris' worry about future events but my understanding is that what we are doing is correct and proper.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Statute of Limitations (Amendment)" RHead="Bill, 1990: Committee and Final Stages">
    <Title>Statute of Limitations (Amendment) Bill, 1990: Committee and Final Stages.</Title>
    <Col N="1469" />
    <Speaker pid="SeanDoherty" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Before Committee Stage commences I must inform the House that amendment No. 1 is out of order.</P>
      <P>Section 1 agreed to.</P>
      <P Just="Center">SECTION 2.</P>
      <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That section 2 stand part of the Bill.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BrianMullooly" hpid="Mr. Mullooly Mr. Mullooly">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Mullooly</NameTxt>
      <P>Subsection (1) states that references to &ldquo;that person's date of knowledge are references to the date on which he first had knowledge of the following facts...&rdquo;  Five facts are outlined in the subsection.  Will a person be required to have knowledge of all the facts or will knowledge of four of the five facts be sufficient?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DenisLyons" hpid="Minister of State at the Department of Tourism and Transport (Mr. Lyons) Minister of State at the Department of Tourism and Transport (Mr. Lyons)">
      <NameTxt>Minister of State at the Department of Tourism and Transport (Mr. Lyons)</NameTxt>
      <P>This section lists the items, knowledge of which a person must have in order for time to start to run against him.  Time will not begin to run against a person until he or she has obtained, or is fixed with, knowledge of all the relevant facts listed at subsection (1).  The person whose knowledge is relevant may be, depending on the circumstances of the case, either the injured person, taking the personal injuries action himself; the personal representative of a deceased injured person, taking the personal injuries action for the benefit of the estate of the deceased; a dependent relative of a deceased person who has died by the wrongful act of another, taking an action under section 48 of the Civil Liability Act, 1961, or having such an action taken on his behalf by another dependent relative.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The Senator asked what the items of knowledge may be.  The first item of which knowledge must be had is that the person alleged to have been injured has been injured.  Awareness of the injury <Col N="1470" /> does not always coincide with the act or omission which causes it.  For instance, exposure to asbestos dust or radiation may cause injury which does not manifest itself for many years.  The second is that the injury in question was significant. This is another aspect that might be relevant. This is a question of fact to be determined by the court in each case.  An injury of the same objective slightness may differ greatly in significance depending on the circumstances of different cases.  For instance, a light, glancing blow which would result in no more than minor temporary bruising in most people might have very serious consequences for other people, say, for instance, a haemophiliac. I hope that answers the queries raised by Senator Mullooly.</P>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFallon" hpid="Mr. Fallon Mr. Fallon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Fallon</NameTxt>
      <P>I should like to query the Minister on the point about the injury in question being significant.  As I understand it, the 1988 Private Members' Bill gave a definition of &ldquo;significant&rdquo;.  I would be of the opinion that, in the absence of a definition of &ldquo;significant&rdquo;, problems might arise.  There is a need for a clear and unambiguous definition of the word. We need to set out objective standards for assessing whether the injury is significant having regard to the various diagnoses and medical evidence available.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DanNeville" hpid="Mr. Neville Mr. Neville">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Neville</NameTxt>
      <P>I concur with Senator Fallon.  That was the point I was going to raise.  Concern has been expressed by the insurance organisations regarding the open definition that can be put on &ldquo;significant&rdquo;. I would also agree with his view that a concise definition should be included.  It would improve the Bill.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DenisLyons" hpid="Mr. Lyons Mr. Lyons">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lyons</NameTxt>
      <P>I am conscious of the &ldquo;significant&rdquo; being raised by the Leader of the House, Senator Fallon and by Senator Neville.  Perhaps I might give a background to this definition of &ldquo;significant injury&rdquo;.  I recall that Deputy George Birmingham's Private Members' Bill followed the English limitations legislation by reproducing the provision which defined &ldquo;significant injury&rdquo; as one which <Col N="1471" /> the plaintiff would reasonably have considered sufficiently serious to justify his instituting legal proceedings for damages against a defendant who did not dispute liability and was able to satisfy a judgment.</P>
      <P>The publication entitled <i>The Supreme Court Practice</i>, which is the authoritative guide to practice and procedure in English law, comments at paragraph 6152 of the 1988 edition that &ldquo;significant injury&rdquo; is defined in a somewhat curious way and it asks:</P>
      <P>On this basis, that liability is not in dispute and the money is there for the asking, what injury would not be sufficiently serious to make a claim for compensation worth while?</P>
      <P>To give further amplification of &ldquo;significant injury&rdquo; the Law Reform Commission, at page 17 of their report, noted this criticism and pointed out that the likely effect of such a provision would be that time would start to run against a person who because of an injury however trivial: thus, a person who received an apparently minor injury and let matters drift because of the minor nature could, if the injury turned out to have serious consequences after a period of years, find himself held to a date of knowledge considerably earlier than that on which he realised that the injury was significant in the normal sense of the word.</P>
      <P>The best way to illustrate this is to give an example.  A person slips on a wet restaurant floor and as a result gets a minor cut from broken glass.  Since that is his only injury and it heals rapidly without complications, the injured person decides not to sue: the injury is simply too trivial.  Some time after the expiry of the normal three year limitation period running from the date of accrual of the cause of the action, the injured person is debilitated by internal injuries from a shard of glass which, unknown to him, had lodged in the cut and had over time travelled within his body.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>If the law contained a definition of &ldquo;significant injury&rdquo; on lines of the English provision I have outlined, then <Col N="1472" /> the injury in this example would be &ldquo;significant&rdquo; and the injured person would be fixed with a date of knowledge contemporaneous with the accrual of the cause of action.  This would seriously diminish the effectiveness of the Bill.</P>
    <P>On the other hand, the approach taken by the Law Reform Commission and followed in this Bill means that a person injured in an apparently trivial way will only have time to start a case against him from the point at which he realises that the injury was significant.  I hope that clarifies the point raised on the significant injury aspect of the Bill.</P>
    <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
    <P Just="Center">SECTION 3.</P>
    <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That section 3 stand part of the Bill.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="DanNeville" hpid="Mr. Neville Mr. Neville">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Neville</NameTxt>
      <P>While this section compares closely with the Bill introduced by former Deputy George Birmingham and is quite acceptable to this side, I was disappointed that my amendment was ruled out of order.  The effect of this section will increase the cost of insurance to industry, motorists and employers resulting in increased costs all round.  I urge the Government to consider the situation.  Our motor insurance is four times higher than that of our nearest neighbour, employers' liability insurance is three times higher than that of our nearest neighbour and public liability is three times higher than that of our neighbour. This section will exacerbate the situation our insurers find themselves in <i>vis-a-vis</i> insurers anywhere else, apart from the US.  While we accept the contents of section 3 we would see it being introduced in the context of an overall review of insurance, bearing in mind that this will have an adverse effect on the insurance industry.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFallon" hpid="Mr. Fallon Mr. Fallon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Fallon</NameTxt>
      <P>Wearing my insurance hat, I would refer to the concerns expressed by Senator Neville.  There is scope for <Col N="1473" /> increased additional claims and, therefore, extra payments from insurance companies by way of claims and hence increased premiums for consumers. There are two aspects to this.  Estimating claims will become more difficult as a result of this Bill.  The problems of the old PMPA insurance company were caused because they regularly estimated claims on the very low side and found that they were paying much more than the estimate provided for.  In this case because we are not notifying claims in time there will be a big problem for insurers.  We have become litigious minded in recent years. There will be scope for many frivilous and vexatious actions in the area of latent personal injuries and this Bill might exacerbate this.  We thought the Courts Bill would reduce premiums or at least level them off but, unfortunately, that has not happened.  We find that awards are as high as ever hence insurance companies are losing greatly in the areas of liability insurance, motor insurance, and so on.  There is no point thinking one thing and saying another.  This Bill will add to the number of claims.  Obviously, if there are more claims there are more awards so the cost of insurance could possibly increase as a result of this Bill.</P>
      <P>The whole area of professional negligence and medical insurance may be affected by this Bill.  Doctors and other professional people say that the cost of professional negligence insurance is rising rapidly.  Having some knowledge of the insurance industry it is no harm to issue the warning that this could lead to increased premiums.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DenisLyons" hpid="Mr. Lyons Mr. Lyons">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lyons</NameTxt>
      <P>We are all concerned with the current level of premiums.  As I indicated in my Second Stage reply at columns 1224-25, Volume 126, of the Official Report on 31 October:</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Of course, we all acknowledge that the high cost of insurance is very serious for everybody but, while a passing reference is accepted, this is primarily a matter for the Minister for Industry and Commerce.  However, I can assure Senators that he and his <Col N="1474" /> Department are actively engaged in monitoring insurance costs and in examining ways of reducing those costs.  The Bill, lest we take it out of context, seeks to remedy an injustice and a possible unconstitutional provision in our law.  If that results in an increase in the cost of insurance, that is the price society must pay for a fairer system.  I should point out, however, that when changes similar to those in the Bill were brought about in another country's law, there was no significant leap in insurance costs and I do not see why there should be any major increase in insurance costs here either.</P>
    <P>I assure the House that there is ongoing concern at the high cost of insurance. That is why the Minister for Industry and Commerce and his Department continue to actively monitor the unacceptable level of premiums.  I want to state that even though it is outside the scope of this Bill, I understand the Members' concern about it.</P>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFallon" hpid="Mr. Fallon Mr. Fallon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Fallon</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister is correct when he says that it is a matter for the Minister for Industry and Commerce to deal with the cost of the insurance but this does not hide the fact that there could well be an increase in premiums.  At the June meeting this year of the Irish Public Bodies who are insurers who transact business for local authorities, health boards and vocational education bodies and who are wide open to the public and therefore more prone to being damaged as a result of this Bill than perhaps the normal or ordinary insurance company that would not be engaged in that type of activity, I asked the manager of the company had he read the Bill.  He had read it and was of the opinion that as far as his company was concerned, the Statute of Limitations (Amendment) Bill would bring in more claims.  If there are more claims, more money is paid out and if more money is paid out it has to be recouped.  The traditional way of recouping it is from the consumer.  The manager felt that there would be more claims and therefore his company would have to pay <Col N="1475" /> out more money which would result in increased premiums.  I stress that this type of business is prone to vexatious and fictitious claims.  I am aware that on my own council, you would get a solicitor's letter on the last day of the three years inviting a claim about which no-one knew anything.</P>
      <P>I agree with what the Minister says that, of course, the Minister for Industry and Commerce has responsibility for premia and for insurance generally but I still have to make the point that this could have an impact on premia.  I am not saying that it would be a major or dramatic increase but it would have some impact on them.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DanNeville" hpid="Mr. Neville Mr. Neville">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Neville</NameTxt>
      <P>The Irish Insurance Federation are in no doubt as to the effects of the Bill.  Obviously the Bill will admit more claims.  That is the purpose of the Bill and, as the Minister rightly says, in doing so it will correct an injustice, and we go along with that.  I quote the views of the Irish Insurance Federation:</P>
      <P>The cost to insurers of settling the increased claims will be directly reflected in increased motor and liability insurance premiums.  The increased cost of premiums will be borne by consumers as policyholders in some cases and will, in any event, ultimately be passed on to the consumer as price increases on goods and services provided by the policyholders.</P>
      <P>There is at present an attempt by the industry and the Government to reduce insurance costs which are already high in comparison with other countries and represents a threat to the competitiveness of Irish firms.  Any measure which tends to increase the cost as this does will increase the cost to industry and will reduce its competitiveness.  I ask the Minister to bring this matter to the attention of his colleague, the Minister for Industry and Commerce, and to express the view of both sides of the House that the difficulty with insurance settlements and the difficulty with the cost of insurance in Ireland must be tackled immediately.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1476" />
    <Speaker pid="DavidNorris" hpid="Mr. Norris Mr. Norris">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norris</NameTxt>
      <P>I support the Minister in his introduction of this measure.  I do so for the reason that I heard him on the monitor a few minutes ago outlining the simple case of natural and constitutional justice.  That is the important thing and I note that everybody around the House has said that.  There may come into play a balance between justice on the one hand and the cost on the other.  If that does come into operation there is no doubt in my mind and the Minister should be assured of this, that we must come down on the side of justice.</P>
      <P>With regard to the cost of insurance premiums and so on, we are always hearing this wailing from the insurance industry. I am not at all convinced that they are the best people to tell us what is going to reduce the cost of premiums.  We heard a little while ago that abolishing juries was going to reduce the cost of premiums because the cost of settlements would go down.  I have to tell the insurance industry this morning that it has not.  They know it has not.  They are not perhaps in quite so qualified a position as one might assume to advise this House with regard to fluctuations in terms of cost.  So I would say, first, in a situation where it comes to a conflict between justice and expense, we would need to be very seriously persuaded that the expense was inordinate before we limited our concern for justice and certainly before we took advice from a professional group who have proved themselves so clearly wrong in the so recent past.  I think we would be well advised to follow the clear speech of the Minister and give full support to the Bill.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFallon" hpid="Mr. Fallon Mr. Fallon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Fallon</NameTxt>
      <P>I have been saying what Senator Norris has said.  The Bill is one we all welcome.  It is clearly designed to remedy an injustice in the law which can, in some cases, result in a person losing his right of action for personal injuries before he is in a position to know that he has a cause for action.  There is no question but that is something we welcome but the down-side of it is that there could well be &mdash; I am not saying there will for certain &mdash; an increase in premiums. Senator Norris made the point as did I <Col N="1477" /> that we were told by the insurance industry that the Courts Bill was very nearly the answer to all their problems, that it would reduce awards and by so doing reduce premiums.  That has not happened. I accept that fully.  My own view at the time was that it might not increase premiums but would certainly level them off.  That has not happened.  At the moment, the cost of insurance, particularly for young drivers, is astronomical. You cannot get it.  That is the situation that prevailed 10 years ago and we are back to that again.  I have contacts with the insurance industry but I would have to agree that they wanted the Courts Bill. They thought it was the answer to all their problems, that awards would be reduced and so premiums would be reduced as a result.  It can be said loud and clear that that has not happened. From that point of view, the Minister is correct.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BrianMullooly" hpid="Mr. Mullooly Mr. Mullooly">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Mullooly</NameTxt>
      <P>We should ask the Minister to request the Minister for Industry and Commerce to ensure that the insurance companies will not use this legislation as a justification for increasing premiums.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DenisLyons" hpid="Mr. Lyons Mr. Lyons">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lyons</NameTxt>
      <P>As regards the point raised by Senator Neville, the views raised by the Insurance Federation in their submission was examined by my colleague in Industry and Commerce and brought to Government.  It was taken into account when this Bill was being debated at Government level.  It was their submission that we took account of when this Bill was being prepared.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DanNeville" hpid="Mr. Neville Mr. Neville">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Neville</NameTxt>
      <P>I accept that.  There are two separate issues.  I accept that my amendment was ruled out of order on that and just in case there was any doubt about our position, the Fine Gael Party have for a long time had as their policy the introduction of such a Bill.  I made this quite clear on Second Stage when it was discussed on 31 October but a lot of things were on people's minds&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1478" />
    <Speaker pid="SeanFallon" hpid="Mr. Fallon Mr. Fallon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Fallon</NameTxt>
      <P>It was an unreal world we lived in that day.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DanNeville" hpid="Mr. Neville Mr. Neville">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Neville</NameTxt>
      <P>Some of us decided that the Bill should go ahead that day.  The position of Fine Gael is quite clear.  In fact we introduced, through former Deputy George Birmingham, a Private Members' Bill which is almost exactly the same as the Bill before us.  Some drafting changes were the only appreciable differences I could detect when comparing both Bills.  While we are fully supportive of the Bill on the basis of natural justice, we must accept that there is a down side to the Bill which goes into the much broader area of insurance costs.  What we are saying is while the increase in insurance might be small enough as a result of the Bill, insurance costs and settlements and the insurance industry generally should be looked into by the Government.  I accept what Senator Norris said &mdash; that the insurance industry should not decide what is right and what is wrong.</P>
      <P>The Government should carry out a full investigation into costs, settlements, procedures, legal costs of settlements and the whole area of litigation.  A notable churchman recently pointed out the immorality of submitting some claims and the tendancy by insurance companies to settle such claims out of court because they know that to go to court would result in higher expenses for the insurance companies which would be passed on to policyholders anyway.  What we are saying is that the whole insurance area requires urgent investigation by the Minister for Industry and Commerce.  I urge the Minister present to bring the views of the Seanad on this to that Minister.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DenisFoley" hpid="Mr. Foley Mr. Foley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Foley</NameTxt>
      <P>The Bill is designed to alter the present position whereby a personal injuries claim will be statute barred if not taken within three years of the date when the injury occurred.  It is only natural to anticipate that costs will rise.  What concerns me, and previous speakers have referred to, is control over insurance companies and their charges.  Have they formed a cartel where they agree on <Col N="1479" /> rates?  The Minister for Industry and Commerce should look into the matter. It has now reached the stage where many people are no longer in a position to carry insurance.  That is a major problem.  As a result of this section costs could again increase substantially.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasHussey" hpid="Acting Chairman (Mr. Hussey) Acting Chairman (Mr. Hussey)">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman (Mr. Hussey)</NameTxt>
      <P>The Senator's contribution does not come within the section being discussed.  I would ask Members to keep to the section we are dealing with, section 3.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DenisFoley" hpid="Mr. Foley Mr. Foley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Foley</NameTxt>
      <P>I accept that but the Bill is designed to alter the present position where a personal injuries claim will be statute barred if not taken within the three year period.  As a result of this costs will increase.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DenisLyons" hpid="Mr. Lyons Mr. Lyons">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lyons</NameTxt>
      <P>I and other Members acknowledge the extensive passing reference allowed by the Cathaoirleach and now yourself to this item.  By passing reference, I mean the insurance element and the premia.  As I said earlier, that has been allowed because of the widespread concern with regard to insurance. However, that discussion is really for another day and I am not suggesting for a moment that we should not have such a discussion.  I am pleased the Cathaoirleach and the Leas-Chathaoirleach have allowed us the freedom to extend the passing reference.  I want to assure Senators Mullooly and Foley that this debate will not be the end of it.  I will bring it to the attention of my colleague and convey to him another chapter on this whole question.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P Just="Center">SECTION 4.</P>
      <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That section 4 stand part of the Bill.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFallon" hpid="Mr. Fallon Mr. Fallon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Fallon</NameTxt>
      <P>I presume there is no problem with this.  Obviously it applied in the past where an action was brought before the expiration of three years from the <Col N="1480" /> date of death, or the date of the personal representative's knowledge, whichever is the later.  Obviously who should be the personal representative is clearly defined in the Bill.  From that point of view it should not present any problems.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>Sections 5 and 6 inclusive agreed to.</P>
      <P Just="Center">SECTION 7.</P>
      <P>Amendment No. 1 not moved.</P>
      <P>Section 7 agreed to.</P>
      <P>Section 8 agreed to.</P>
      <P>Title agreed to.</P>
      <P>Bill reported without amendment and received for final consideration.</P>
      <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That the Bill do now pass.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFallon" hpid="Mr. Fallon Mr. Fallon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Fallon</NameTxt>
      <P>The Bill is necessary and is designed to remedy injustices in the present law.  It is no harm to say, and the Minister has acknowledged this, that our concern is that insurance costs might rise. It is no harm that the debate centred on this.  It shows the concern Senators have about the cost of insurance.  This is a very pressing matter however, the Minister handled the situation well.  He has made the point that insurance costs are not his responsibility.  We have put down a marker on what could happen, and we have been proper and correct in doing so.  Senator Mullooly suggested that we endeavour to ensure that the passing of the Statute of Limitations (Amendment) Bill, 1990, will not lead to increased premiums.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Contractual Obligations (Applicable" RHead="Law) Bill, 1990: Second Stage">
    <Title>Contractual Obligations (Applicable Law) Bill, 1990: Second Stage.</Title>
    <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That the Bill be now read a Second Time.&rdquo;</P>
    <Col N="1481" />
    <Speaker pid="DenisLyons" hpid="Minister of State at the Department of Transport and Tourism (Mr. Lyons) Minister of State at the Department of Transport and Tourism (Mr. Lyons)">
      <NameTxt>Minister of State at the Department of Transport and Tourism (Mr. Lyons)</NameTxt>
      <P>The purpose of the Contractual Obligations (Applicable Law) Bill, 1990, is to give the force of law to two EC Conventions. The first is the 1980 Rome Convention on the law applicable to contractual obligations, and the second &mdash; the 1984 Accession Convention &mdash; provides for the accession of Greece to the 1980 Convention.</P>
      <P>Before going into any detail on the Bill or the conventions I think it would be useful if I put this measure in context and explained its importance.  This Bill deals with a specific area of our private international law; that is, which country's law should be applicable in deciding a dispute involving a contract with an international element.  In the case of litigation concerning an international contract three key issues arise.  They are which country's courts will have jurisdiction to try the dispute; what law will those courts apply where there is a choice between the laws of the different countries involved; and will the the resulting judgment be enforceable in other states?</P>
      <P>Two of these issues, that is, jurisdiction and enforcement, are already dealt with in the 1968 EC Judgments Convention which was brought into force in Ireland by the Jurisdiction of Courts and Enforcement of Judgments (European Communities) Act, 1988.  It is the remaining issue, that of the applicable law, which this Bill, and the conventions it will bring into force, addresses.  I must emphasise that although an international contractual dispute might fall to be tried in Ireland by virtue of the provisions of the EC Judgments Convention, that does not necessarily mean that Irish law would be applied.  Another law connected with the dispute might be the appropriate law to determine the dispute.  This distinction between jurisdiction and applicable law can be overlooked thus giving rise to misunderstandings.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>As will be evident to those who have studied the Bill and the conventions, this area of the law is complex and technical. Nevertheless it is an area of considerable importance.  We are all aware of how vital <Col N="1482" /> international trade is to our economy.  A high proportion of economic activity in this country relates to the import and export of goods or services.  Behind these transactions lie some form of contract. As the trade is international there is an inevitable interaction between the legal system in Ireland and in the countries with which we do business.  In addition, if international trade is to flourish it needs a suitable legal framework to underpin it.  That is what the 1980 convention and this Bill is about.  The 1980 convention provides a modern and clear code of rules in an area where our existing law is currently unclear and uncertain.  The Bill by giving effect to the 1980 convention will facilitate the growth of our international trade.  It is a practical measure which will be of real benifit to Irish business people entering into contracts with an international element.</P>
    <P>The implementation of the 1980 convention is also of importance in the context of our membership of the European Communities.  The Commission of the European Communities, and in particular the directorate dealing with the Internal Market have taken the view that the lack of uniform rules in this area was impeding the free movement of persons, goods and capital among the member states.  They favour its early implementation in all member states.  I might make the point at this juncture that, while the 1980 convention is a Community convention, the rules laid down in the convention will be applicable even if the law to be applied is not that of a member state of the European Communities.</P>
    <P>The convention has not yet entered into force for any of the member states of the Community.  It requires ratification by seven member states to bring it into force in those states which have ratified it.  To date, six states have ratified and I understand that the United Kingdom will do so shortly with the result that the convention will enter into force in those states in early 1991.  I would hope that this Bill will get a speedy passage through both Houses of the Oireachtas so that we will keep in step with our EC partners.</P>
    <P>The Bill has four sections and four <Col N="1483" /> Schedules.  Section 1 and section 4 are straightforward procedural provisions. Section 2 gives both conventions the force of the law in the State.  The 1980 convention contains the rules to determine which country's law will be applicable in a choice of law situation.  The 1984 convention provides for the accession of Greece and makes the Greek text of the 1980 convention equally authentic with the other seven language texts.</P>
    <P>Members of the House will note that subsection (2) of section 2 provides that Article 7 (1) of the 1980 convention will not have the force of law in the State. The convention itself allows states not to apply Article 7 (1) and we propose to avail ourselves of this option for reasons which I shall make clear when I turn to the main provisions of the convention.</P>
    <P>Section 3 of the Bill relates to the interpretation of the conventions.  There are two matters involved here.  The first relates to the interpretation of the conventions by the Court of Justice of the European Communities.  In December 1988 the twelve member states agreed that powers should be conferred on the Court of Justice to interpret the 1980 convention as an aid to the uniform interpretation of the convention throughout the Community.  This was done by means of a protocol to the 1980 convention. Since the protocol would empower the Court of Justice to give rulings which would be binding on the courts of the contracting states, it is not possible under the Constitution for Ireland to ratify this Protocol.  Accession to the 1980 convention or the protocol is not necessitated by the obligations of our membership of the European Communities and, therefore, is not covered by the terms of the constitutional amendment &mdash; now Article 29.4.3 of the Constitution &mdash; which <i>inter alia</i> enabled our courts to be bound by interpretative decisions of the Court of Justice on the EC Treaty and the 1968 Judgments Convention.  Therefore, while decisions given by the Court of Justice on the interpretation of the 1980 convention will not be binding on the Irish courts, they are decisions which the Irish courts <Col N="1484" /> may consider in interpreting the convention. Section 3 (1) (a) provides accordingly that judicial notice shall be taken of such interpretative decisions.</P>
    <P>The second matter covered by section 3 is the official report on the 1980 convention by Professors Giuliano and Lagarde.  It is standard practice when an international convention is being drawn up for a report to be prepared by persons involved in the drafting explaining the intentions of the drafters.  Section 3 provides that judicial notice shall be taken of the report and that the courts shall have discretion to decide what weight they shall give to the report when interpreting the convention.  There is a similar provision in section 4 of the Jurisdiction of Courts and Enforcement of Judgments (European Communities) Act, 1988, in relation to the reports on the 1968 Brussels Convention.</P>
    <P>I turn now to the 1980 convention.  I will not go through the convention in detail now.  What I propose to do is to deal with the main features of the convention.</P>
    <P>At one stage it was intended that the convention would govern choice of law in the area of torts as well as contracts. However, it became apparent that it would be difficult to reach agreement on rules in the torts area and so it was decided to concentrate, initially in any event, on contract law.  Even then certain types of contracts are excluded from the convention by Article 1 for a variety of reasons.  Rights in property arising from a matrimonial relationship are excluded because it is a family law matter and not appropriate for inclusion in a convention dealing primarily with commercial law principles.  Another example of an exclusion is in the area of insurance contracts. Insurance contracts where the risk is situated in the Community are excluded because special choice of law rules appropriate to them were being drawn up to form the basis of a separate EC instrument.  Overall, however, this convention will apply to the generality of commercial contracts.</P>
    <P>The two basic rules of the convention are set out in Articles 3 and 4.  The first, <Col N="1485" /> contained in Article 3, is that parties to a contract are free to choose whichever law they wish to govern their contract. The law chosen does not have to be related to the contract.  For example, two Irish people entering into a contract to be performed here could conceivably decide to choose a law other than Irish law to govern their contract.  This reflects the existing law in Ireland.  The Supreme Court in 1988 accepted that parties are free to choose the law they wish to govern their contract even to the extent of choosing a law wholly unconnected with the contract.</P>
    <P>If the law governing the contract has not been chosen by the parties the second basic rule, contained in Article 4, applies. The purpose of this rule is to determine the applicable law in the absence of choice.  It provides that where no choice has been made the contract will be governed by the law of the country with which it is most closely connected.  This reflects existing Irish law which is to the effect that in the absence of choice a contract is to be governed by the system of law which has the closest and most real connection with the contract and transaction.</P>
    <P>How does one decide which country has the closest connection with a contract? The convention provides in Article 4 for a series of presumptions to be used to determine the country with the closest connection.  Under existing law the court has to look at all the factors involved to determine which system of law has the closest connection with a contract.  The convention rules should provide greater certainty, although in most cases they will produce the same result as would be achieved under the present law.</P>
    <P>These two basic rules are supplemented by other rules dealing with specific issues.  Like the EC Judgments Convention, this convention contains special provisions, which have no equivalent in present Irish law, to protect the weaker parties to certain consumer and employment contracts.  These provisions are contained in Articles 5 and 6 respectively.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="1486" /> The consumer contracts in question relate generally to the situation where the supplier of the goods or services or the supplier of credit for the purchase of such goods or services has sought out the consumer across national frontiers &mdash; for example, by advertising or direct mailing. The convention in keeping with the general principle of freedom of choice enables the supplier and the consumer to agree a choice of law but any such choice cannot deprive the consumer of the protection of the mandatory rules &mdash; which are defined in the convention as rules that cannot be departed from by contract &mdash; of his own country.  Such mandatory rules will be found in the consumer legislation of each member state of the Community, including Ireland.</P>
    <P>If there is no choice of law in a consumer transaction of the type in question then, provided the supplier has taken the initiative, the contract as a whole will be governed by the law of the habitual residence of the consumer and the mandatory rules of that jurisdiction will apply automatically.</P>
    <P>Similar rules apply in the case of a choice of law by the parties to an individual contract of employment. Where there is no choice then the law that will normally apply will be the law of the country where the employee habitually carries out his work or, if he does not habitually carry out his work in any one country, the law of the place of business through which he was recruited.</P>
    <P>I have already mentioned mandatory rules in the case of certain consumer and employment contracts.  There are a number of other provisions in the convention concerning mandatory rules.  As I have explained, a mandatory rule is a rule of law which cannot be derogated from by contract.  In giving parties to a contract wide freedom to choose which law should govern their contract there is a danger that this freedom could be abused to avoid the application of a mandatory rule of a country which has a legitimate interest in the matter.  The approach taken in the convention to resolve this problem is to allow freedom <Col N="1487" /> of choice but to make that freedom subject to the application of relevant mandatory rules.  In addition to the specific instances of consumer and employment contracts, the mandatory rules of a country are applicable where all the elements relevant to the contract are connected with that country but the law of another country has been chosen to govern the contract.  This is provided for in Article 3 (3) of the convention.  Under Article 7 (2) the mandatory rules of the country where the case is being tried are always applicable irrespective of the law otherwise applicable to the contract.</P>
    <P>Controversy surrounds the remaining provision in the convention &mdash; Article 7 (1) &mdash; which deals with mandatory rules. Article 7 (1) provides that courts shall have discretion to apply the mandatory rules of another country with which the contract has a close connection.  Objections were made to the inclusion of this provision in the convention on the basis that it would place a too onerous task on national courts and would create uncertainty. For that reason, although the provision was maintained in the convention, member states may, under Article 22, enter a reservation against its application. It is proposed that Ireland should avail itself of the reservation as have Germany, Luxembourg and the United Kingdom and the Bill proposes accordingly.</P>
    <P>The difficulty with Article 7 (1) is its vagueness and the uncertainty that would result from its application.  In a contract involving a number of countries it may be impossible to predict in advance which countries might be considered to have a close connection with the transaction &mdash; close connection not being defined in the convention.  It might also be impossible to predict whether a court would apply the mandatory rules, if any, of that country.  This would make it extremely difficult for Irish companies entering into international contracts to be advised fully in advance on the implications of a contract or the likely outcome in the case of a dispute.</P>
    <P>I might mention that the views of the Law Society and certain academics <Col N="1488" /> expert in this field were sought on this issue and they were strongly in favour of entering a reservation regarding Article 7 (1).</P>
    <P>This Bill is of crucial importance to the business community and will have implications for all those involved in the drawing up of international contracts.  It will clarify many of the areas of our law which are presently unclear as well as providing a modern up-to-date code of law which will be in full harmony with the laws of our Community partners in this area.</P>
    <P>I am conscious that this is a very technical Bill.  It is also a Bill which I think should not and hopefully will not be noncontroversial. I look forward to hearing the contributions of Senators.</P>
    <P>I commend the Bill to the House.</P>
    <Speaker pid="TomRaftery" hpid="Professor Raftery Professor Raftery">
      <NameTxt>Professor Raftery</NameTxt>
      <P>I welcome this Bill. I do not intend to talk very long about it. I will leave the technical matters of the Bill &mdash; as the Minister rightly said, it is a very technical Bill &mdash; to my legal colleagues, Senator Cosgrave and Senator Kennedy.</P>
      <P>I cannot over-emphasise the importance of this Bill.  For a community, for a country to survive in a harmonious fashion, it is necessary that we have laws that we respect and uphold.  It is clear, as the Minister said, that we are going to have more disputes between companies and individuals internationally as a result of the growth in business which will arise and is arising from our increased participation in the economic life of the Community and in the freedom of movement of goods, services, people and capital. It is quite clear, therefore, that in order to have some kind of order in our business and in our relationships we must have harmonisation of our laws.  This is what the principle point in this Bill is all about.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I am very pleased to note that in December 1988 the Twelve member states agreed that the powers should be conferred on the Court of Justice to interpret the 1980 convention as an aid to the uniform interpretation of the convention <Col N="1489" /> throughout the Community.  I am disappointed, however, that we still do not have the seven member countries ratifying this convention.  The Minister is confident that we will have the seventh shortly, in the United Kingdom.  I hope he is right.  Certainly, present indications from that country about falling into line with anything in the Community are not very good.  Let us hope that he is right.</P>
    <P>As I have said, it is essential for a community, for a country, to have laws that are harmonious, harmonised and, about all, respected.  In that regard I would say it is essential that the legislators in the first instance respect the laws.  It is very difficult to expect the private citizen of the country to uphold and respect the laws if the legislators who draw up the law themselves are not good respectors of the law.  Indeed, I regret to say that too often we, the legislators, do not set a good example in this regard.  I regret also to say that the Government of our country have given a very bad example by in the first instance in 1987 introducing a law which they knew was against Community law imposing the 48 hour restriction on travellers going outside of the State.  At that time I took grave exception to the change.  I made that known in the European Parliament and as a result the Government were taken to the Court of Justice in Luxembourg.  They were, as many of us anticipated, found to be in breach of the law.  That is fair enough, but what is not right is that after they had been found to be guilty of breaking international law they still continue to ignore the findings of the court.</P>
    <P>I understand the reason the Government did it in the first instance.  If they knew, and I believe they knew they were breaking the law, they felt it would take a long time for the court to deal with it and they felt they would get a bit of a rest by it in terms of the amount of goods crossing the Border.  Of course, that was a nonsense.  As it is patently clear now. At the time I pointed out that we were selling twice as much in Northern Ireland as they were buying here.  If they retaliated we would be the main losers.  I pointed out that it was ironical that the <Col N="1490" /> Government or the party that always boasted about getting rid of the Border were now reinforcing it.  Furthermore, I pointed out that if items as large and as loud and smelly as pigs and cattle were being smuggled across the Border, how in Heaven's name could we stop the smuggling of items as small, as valuable and as silent as whiskey, tobacco, electronic goods and so on?  Of course, we could not and we did not.</P>
    <P>The ESRI report showed nearly 12 or 15 months after the introduction of the restriction that there was no significant decrease in the flow of goods from the North to the South.  There are very easy ways of establishing certain items of how much went one way or the other.  Because there are only two bonded warehouses in this country, for instance, for whiskey &mdash; one in Northern Ireland and one in Southern Ireland, we know from the records how much is released from these two bonded warehouses.  We know from these records that probably two out of three bottles of whiskey sold in the South are smuggled from the North having been made in the South in the first instance.</P>
    <P>The point is that the real beneficiaries of that kind of smart-alec legislation to get over a problem of where our VAT rates were too high were the smugglers who, by and large, were terrorists.  The real losers were the citizens.  The point is that if we do not as legislators and if we do not as a Government respect the law that we introduce, how can we expect the ordinary citizen to respect the law?  We introduce the law; we must set an example by respecting it.</P>
    <P>I welcome this Bill.  I leave the technical aspects to my legal colleagues, but I would urge this House to give it a quick passage, because, in order for us to benefit from the economic gains we can have and will have from increased trade with the Community, we must have harmonious and harmonised laws governing this trade, governing the movement of people, goods, capital and services.</P>
    <Speaker pid="BrianMullooly" hpid="Mr. Mullooly Mr. Mullooly">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Mullooly</NameTxt>
      <P>I welcome the opportunity to make a short contribution to Second Stage debate on this Bill.  The <Col N="1491" /> explanatory memorandum circulated with the Bill informs us that the purpose of the Contractual Obligations (Applicable Law) Bill, 1990 is to give legal effect to two European Community conventions namely the 1980 Convention on the Law Applicable to Contractual Obligations and the 1984 Accession Convention which provides for the accession of Greece to the 1980 convention.  The Bill provides that both conventions will have the force of law in this State.</P>
      <P>This is a significant Bill because the area of law with which it deals is of considerable importance to all Irish business interests who are involved in international trade and commerce.  It is an area of private international law which is not well defined in Ireland and which was, heretofore, surrounded by a considerable degree of uncertainty.  The main benefit of this Bill will be the replacement of the existing uncertainty with a coherent and comprehensive set of rules.</P>
      <P>Since Ireland joined the European Community there has been a substantial growth in our international trade.  This development has increased and underlined the need for major changes in our existing private international law in the civil and commercial sphere.  The 1980 convention, therefore, has a particular benefit for Ireland.  The Bill before the House, taken together with the 1988 Jurisdiction of Courts and Enforcement of Judgements, European Communities Act, in so far as that Act deals with contractual relationships, will provide us with a modern code of private international law in the area of contract law will facilitate our international trade.</P>
      <P>The 1980 convention resulted from a recognition that the harmonisation of national rules of conflict would facilitate the workings of the Common Market.  It had become increasingly evident that the escalating development of economic links within the Community would considerably increase the number of cases in which questions of applicable law would arise.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="1492" /> There would be a growing number of cases in which the courts would have to decide which country's laws would be applicable.  If this situation were allowed to continue it is obvious that there would be a great degree of uncertainty in the whole area of legal relationships between contracting parties in the different member states.  The 1980 convention addressed this problem by harmonising the rules of conflict in the various member states.</P>
    <P>The central notion of a contract as a legally binding promise is easy to understand. However, the range of conduct covered by the notion of a contract can be extremely wide.  There may, for example, be a contract for the sale of land or of a television set.  There may also be a contract of employment or a contract for the carriage of goods or persons.  Some contracts may be between large corporations and others may be between the members of the same family.</P>
    <P>The average domestic contract between persons within the same jurisdiction in general presents little difficulty. In an action, on the foot of such a contract, the Irish court will deal with the matter by applying Irish law.  For example, if the action concerns whether a valid contract exists the Irish court will examine such concepts as offer and acceptance, consideration moving between the parties and the intention to create legal relations.</P>
    <P>Much more difficult, however, are contracts with a foreign element.  For example there could be a contract between an Irish businessman and a German businessman negotiated and made in Italy to be performed in France.  In the case of such a contract the question of what law should govern the contract would arise in the case of a dispute.  Should it be Irish law or German law or should it be Italian law because the contract was negotiated and completed in Italy?  Perhaps it should be French law because performance was to take place in France.  Each of these systems of law would look at contractual matters differently.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="1493" /> It is important, therefore, to be able to say with some degree of certainty what system of law will govern a contract.  This is of considerable importance to all sections of the Irish business community involved in international trade and commerce. The importance of certainty in the choice of law is not, however, confined to the business community, it is important to the consumer who purchases imported goods and to the employee who signs a contract to work abroad or to work here for a foreign company.</P>
    <P>The present law in this area as far as Ireland is concerned is, as I stated, very unclear.  Because of the fact that the question of applicable law has seldom been raised in Irish courts in disputes involving Irish parties and parties of other nationalities. There is a great deal of uncertainty in relation to what position the Irish courts would take on such issues.</P>
    <P>It was considered at one time that the law which should apply was the law of the place of contracting.  However, the difficulties in this choice of law quickly became apparent.  The place of contracting could be fradulently selected to suit one of the parties involved.  Alternatively, the place of contracting might be fortuitous and have no real connection with the contract.  The courts have also considered that the applicable law should be the law of the place of performance, that is, the place where the contract is to be carried out but, of course, the place of performance offered no solution whereas in the case of a bilateral contract each party was to perform in a different country.</P>
    <P>In more recent times the courts have held that the applicable law is the proper law of the contract, that is, the law which had the closest and most real connection with the contract.  This law gradually evolved to include two central features. The first of these gave priority to the parties own choice of what law should govern the contract.  Alternatively, where such a choice did not exist the law which should govern the contract was identified by having regard to all the circumstances of the case.</P>
    <P>The question of whether the party <Col N="1494" /> should have complete freedom to choose any law they wish has always been a matter of considerable controversy. Again, this question is addressed in the 1980 convention.  The freedom to specify the law applicable to a contract is enshrined in the convention.  However, this freedom of choice may be affected by the application in certain circumstances of the mandatory laws of a system other than that chosen.  This provision will ensure protection for individuals in the case of certain consumer and employment contracts.</P>
    <P>This Bill, in giving effect to the 1980 convention, reaffirms our Government's commitment to a more unified Europe. Unifying the law facilitates the replacement of the existing rules of private international law by a more coherent and comphrehensive set of rules.  By harmonising the rules of conflict the Bill, in giving effect to the convention, will reduce forum shopping and will give greater legal certainty to all parties in legal relationships.  Parties to international contracts will be allowed the maximum freedom of choice in relation to whichever countries' laws they consider to be appropriate.  This freedom of choice is qualified only to the extent that certain mandatory rules will remain operable.</P>
    <P>The scope of the convention is wide. Under Article 2 it is to have world wide effect.  It will apply to all contract cases having a foreign element irrespective of whether they have any connection with the European Community.  However, as the Minister stated, certain matters are excluded from the scope of the convention. These are listed in Article 1, and include contractual matters relating to wills and succession and questions involving the status or legal capacity of natural persons.</P>
    <P>Article 3 provides that the parties are free to choose the governing law.  This choice need not be expressed, but it must be determined with reasonable certainty. Article 4 provides that in the absence of choice of contract is governed by the law of the country with which it is most <Col N="1495" /> closely connected.  This is rebuttably presumed to be the country where performance is supposed to take place.  This doctrine of characteristic performance is derived from Swiss law.  This is, in some respects, similar to existing Irish law. Many of the articles of the convention are similar to Irish law.  Like the Brussels Convention on Jurisdiction and the Enforcement of Judgments this convention contains special provisions which have no equivalent in Irish law.  These will protect the weaker parties and consumer in employment contracts.  The convention, in keeping with the general principle of freedom of choice, enables supplier and consumer to agree a choice of law but this agreement will not deprive the consumer of the protection of the mandatory rules of his or her own jurisdiction. For instance, in the case of an Irish consumer the protection of the Sale of Goods and Supply of Services Act, 1980, will obtain.</P>
    <P>In the Bill the Minister has very wisely entered a reservation under Article 22 of the convention in respect of Article 7 (1). Article 7 (1) permits the court to give effect to the mandatory rules of some other third country with which the contract has a close connection.  While this provision would no doubt reduce forum shopping, its practical implementation would be difficult.  It would also introduce an element of uncertainty in cases of dispute which would make it extremely difficult for any Irish company entering into an international contract to be fully advised on the implications of such a contract. This provision was the most controversial provision of the convention. As the Minister stated, reservations have also been entered by some of the other parties to the convention, namely, Germany, Luxembourg and the United Kingdom.</P>
    <P>The enactment of this legislation will ensure that Ireland will have a modern code of private international law in the area of contract law, which will facilitate our international trade.  Accordingly, I welcome the Bill and thank the Minister for introducing it in Seanad Eireann.</P>
    <Col N="1496" />
    <Speaker pid="PatUpton" hpid="Dr. Upton Dr. Upton">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Upton</NameTxt>
      <P>At the outset I welcome the introduction of this Bill.  As the Minister said in his opening remarks, the purpose of the Bill is to approve the Rome Convention of 1980.  That convention regulates conflicts between Irish law and foreign law in relation to a contract.  It provides rules for determining which country's law is applicable to an international contract.  In as far as it does this, it is welcome enough.</P>
      <P>In discussing the Bill it is appropriate at the outset to pay tribute to the role of Mr. Justice Brian Walsh who was a member of the international committee which drew up the convention which we are approving today.  It is a shame the Government have taken so long to bring to fruition the walk which Mr. Justice Walsh began so many years ago.  Indeed, perhaps the Government might wish to explain the rather extraordinarily long delay in bringing this legislation before the House.</P>
      <P>Ireland signed the Rome Convention in 1980 and it has taken ten years for this legislation to arrive.  The delay is difficult to understand because the drafting of this Bill was not a complex task.  The Bill has only four sections with the convention text contained in a Schedule.  As the explanatory memorandum to the Bill openly admits, there are six to seven other European countries whose Legislatures have beaten us in introducing similar legislation.  Once again it seems that we are falling behind Europe in updating our legislation to fulfil our obligations as part of the European Community.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>It is interesting to ask if the Government would have bothered to reform the legislation at all if it were not for the pressures which are being exerted on us from Europe.  My suspicion is that they would not.  This legislation is fairly typical of a series of differing types of legislation which have come before the House this year, all ultimately at the instigation of the European Community.  The similar type Bills which have come arising from our obligations in Europe include the Carriage of Goods Bill, the Radiological Protection Bill, the Sea Pollution Bill, the <Col N="1497" /> International Development Association Bill and the new Bill on child abduction.</P>
    <P>The bankruptcy of the Government's legislation programme in relation to contract law is illustrated in this Bill.  This Bill deals with a very small area of contract law.  Other aspects of contract law for the most part have been left to the courts to interpret.  Do the Government propose to introduce comprehensive legislation relating to contract law in the near future?</P>
    <P>There is another aspect of the Bill which is referred to in the Schedule, and that is its constitutional implications.  If I remember correctly, there is in paragraph 26 of the explanatory memorandum, a reference to constitutional issues.  There we are told that, for constitutional reasons, the Bill leaves the interpretation of the international convention to the Irish courts and does not allow the European Court to make rulings which will be binding on Irish courts. I suppose you could argue that this may or may not be desirable, but usually one would expect that legislation which has international implications arising from Europe might be interpreted by an international court.  Maybe the Minister would fill us in on the constitutional factors and issues which give rise to this provision in the Bill.  It would be very interesting to hear his views on that and it would also be very interesting if he could make available the advice of the Attorney General on this very important matter.</P>
    <P>There are one or two minor points in the Bill to which I want to refer.  The first is the length of the Title &mdash; the Contractual Obligations (Appicable Law) Bill.  Why could it not be called simply, Contracts (Applicable Law) Bill?  Maybe the Minister would give us an explanation why it is necessary to use those extra words.  With Senator Fallon, I think I am one of a very small minority here who believe in vigorous editing: I suspect I may be in a minority of one in this belief. As I said, I would welcome the Minister explaining the basis for the Long Title.</P>
    <P>Why did the Minister not include the list of signatories to the convention?  This <Col N="1498" /> might be interesting from historical point of view.  Maybe on Committee Stage the Minister might be prepared to include the list of signatories to the convention.  I understand that the Minister for Foreign Affairs, Deputy Collins, was a signatory and for simple historical reasons it might be desirable if that could be included in the Schedule.</P>
    <P>Overall, the Labour Party welcome the Bill.  We are disappointed it has taken so long for it to arrive in the House.  It is a minor measure but nonetheless a welcome one.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PaschalMooney" hpid="Mr. Mooney Mr. Mooney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Mooney</NameTxt>
      <P>In welcoming the Bill, it is important to put on record that this is yet another piece of legislation reflecting the Government's commitment to closer harmony in a variety of areas within the European Community.  While I suppose my friend and colleague, Senator Upton, has to justify his position on the Opposition benches, it is somewhat churlish of him to suggest that the Government are being dragged, kicking and screaming, into the legislative areas.  After all, in 1987 we debated in this House the Single European Act and the obligations deriving from that Act that directives from Europe would be an ongoing process in the legislative framework leading up to the eventual cohesion of the market.  The House is discussing the possibility of full economic and monetary union.  In the context of the Government's wish to play their full role in European affairs this legislation fits in with that objective.</P>
      <P>I might also draw attention to the remarks by my distinguished colleague Professor Raftery who objected strenuously to the introduction of the 24 hour law in the context of the freedom of goods and services.  I do not think any of us, consumers or legislators, would have welcomed with open arms that legislation.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I must confess, I was surprised to learn Professor Raftery had raised the matter in the European Parliament and had, by implication, criticised the Government for their decision.  Perhaps Senator Raftery, who was spending most of his time in Europe at that time and also &mdash; here I chose my words extremely carefully &mdash;<Col N="1499" /> because of his geographical location, coming from County Cork, was not aware that in the period leading up to the initiation of the 48 hour rule large sections of this country, even from as far south as Cork city, were hiring buses, coaches and trains to cross the Border. The haemorrhage in financial terms to the economy of this part of Ireland was so severe that action had to be taken.  It was not action taken in isolation by an Irish Government.  Indeed, one of our fellow European members, Denmark, who have similar difficulties with their citizens flying over the border into Germany to buy cheaper consumer goods took action.</P>
    <P>Media hype, and a psychological impact, created a myth about a wide variety of goods available across the Border, suggesting that they were cheaper than the South, led to this exodus.  It is interesting that, since the introduction of the 48 hour rule, this type of consumer smuggling has all but been eliminated.  I do, of course, take Professor Raftery's point in relation to smuggling in the agriculture sector.</P>
    <P>It is important to put on record that we should not be criticised for this particular law in a European context.  Surveys have proven that this country, and its citizens, are in the forefront of encouraging closer cohesion between the European partners. We welcome, enthusiastically, the development of consumer laws and of life in general moving towards a Europe speaking with one voice with member states retaining their independence of thought.</P>
    <P>This legislation is an indication yet again of a general coming together.  I am pleased that it clarifies the legal situation for Ireland and Irish business.  Ireland has an export driven economy.  We would not survive without oversees markets.  Since our accession to the European Community in 1972 the country's exports to our European partners, excluding the UK, have risen considerably.  In 1972, and leading up to accession, more than two-thirds of our exports were with our nearest neighbour, Great Britain.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="1500" /> However, the situation has altered considerably in the intervening period in that there has been a general reduction in dependence on the UK market with a resultant increase in exports to our other European partners.</P>
    <P>As an export driven economy, an increasing number of industries and business people are spending more time within the European Community, excluding Great Britain, on business dealings.  It is, therefore, essential that laws governing contracts as they apply in the business sector primarily and secondly, in the consumer area, are clarified to the point that there should be no doubt whenever any Irish business enters into contracts with our European neighbours, that in the event of default or legal difficulties arising over contracts that they will have a legal redress which will not be complicated by adherence to national laws.  In that context this legislation is, as the Minister and other speakers have pointed out, essential to the continuing well-oiled export machine that this country has built up in recent years.</P>
    <P>I am interested to know &mdash; perhaps the Minister will dwell on this to some small extent &mdash; whether he sees any difficulties arising where Irish businesses attempt to initiate contracts with the emerging democracies of Eastern Europe.  I had the privilege to be a member of a parliamentary delegation to Poland last month where Ireland has established its first Embassy and where our first Irish Ambassador, Mr. Richard O'Brien, is in residence.  I was pleased to learn that Córas Tráchtála are moving to open up the Polish and Eastern European markets.</P>
    <P>It is important that the House should realise that those emerging democracies in the main are economically devastated relative to the prosperity of Western Europe.  While they have substantial populations &mdash; for example, in Poland it is in the order of 40 million to 50 million people &mdash; the consumer purchasing power is very limited.  However, this is but temporary.  The European Community, including Ireland, are taking steps to move towards economic parity <Col N="1501" /> which, obviously, will be a long haul but, eventually, will be achieved.</P>
    <P>I welcome the initiative of the Government in opening up lines of communication both at diplomatic level and, through Córas Tráchtála, at a business level.  Obviously, these initiatives will encourage an increasing number of Irish business people to seek out these markets. I am interested to know if the Minister has any thoughts on that.</P>
    <P>I presume, from my reading of the Bill, that the choice of law where a dispute may arise will protect any business enterprise here who fail to get compensation for goods that may have gone astray or who fail to receive a payment which seems to be the biggest difficulty as hard currency is a scarce commodity in these East European countries.</P>
    <P>Eastern Europe, obviously will grow in importance over the next couple of decades.  From my interpretation of the Bill, and the Minister's Second Stage speech, it seems that this general tightening up of the law on business contracts will have a beneficial effect and will be a further protection for business people working and dealing in Eastern Europe.</P>
    <P>The legislation gives further protection to the consumer.  Specifically, I am glad the Government have addressed the difficulty that has arisen with Article 7 (1). The Minister said reservations will be entered in relation to this.  That is again an indication of the importance of maintaining a watch on legislation from Europe in order to protect the consumer at every level.  As we become more and more open with the opening up of the market, the free movement of goods, services and people it is essential that legislation is enacted that protects all European citizens at consumer level in their cross-border dealings.  Because of the travel and the geography involved, it is not always possible for a consumer to claim compensation.  This country sadly has witnessed a people haemorrhage in the last decade.  The area covered by this new legislation on employers' contracts is also to be welcomed.  An increasing number of our citizens choose to work and live abroad and are turning their <Col N="1502" /> faces towards Europe rather than the traditional environments of America and the United Kingdom.</P>
    <P>I was surprised to learn recently that in Munich there are several thousand Irish people domiciled in that southern German city quite a long distance away from Ireland, yet obviously doing well. This seems to be an increasing trend with the free movement of goods, people and services.  Our well-trained and well-educated Irish population may choose to go to Europe, particularly the younger members of our population.  They will choose to go to continental Europe, hopefully in the short term, to acquire expertise and then return home bringing that experise here for the benefit of this country.  Indeed, quite a number of them are doing that.  Therefore, where the legislation addresses itself to the tightening up and clarification of the law in relation to employer contracts it is to be welcomed.</P>
    <P>Overall, like my colleagues, I welcome this piece of legislation as yet again an important milestone in the evolvement of the communities of Europe into a cohesive factor where laws governing the activities of individuals in businesses and large corporations will be closely monitored and the protection will ultimately be for the betterment of all the citizens of the community.  Like the Minister, I commend the Bill to the House.</P>
    <Speaker pid="LiamTCosgrave" hpid="Mr. Cosgrave Mr. Cosgrave">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cosgrave</NameTxt>
      <P>I too, welcome the opportunity to contribute briefly in relation to the Bill before the House. In the light of an evolving Europe and coming to 1992, Ireland is going to have quite a significant contribution to make. I am not saying it is the present Minister who is to blame for the long delay in bringing the legislation forward.  I hope this is not going to be indicative of the attitude which may prevail in relation to how we approach 1992.  My worry is that we are within a year of 1992 and we do not appear to be fully ready.  I am afraid that Ireland will get left behind.  We will only react when it is upon us.  We will be asking why we were not better prepared. Other countries may be better prepared <Col N="1503" /> than we are though I hope that that will not be the case.  There is some anxiety as to whether we are making adequate preparations for 1992.  I would like to ask the Minister when it is proposed that we sign the convention?  Will it be when this legislation is passed?  I would be interested to know how long it has been since other countries have signed the convention and why we are so late in doing so.  I see that six have signed so far &mdash; Belgium, Denmark, France, Germany, Italy and Luxembourg.  It is understood that the United Kingdom are expected to ratify it shortly.  There may be good reasons for the delay on our part. If we are talking in terms of getting ready for 1992, in order to gain the benefit of one market and the benefit of the opportunities which that will present we should be better prepared than we have been in the past.</P>
      <P>I listened with interest to what Senator Mooney said in relation to the whole question of cross-Border shopping.  I would accept and support him in the opinion that while there has been difficulty with the 48 hour rule, it certainly solved some problems.  We all hope that people would be patriotic and buy goods down here but that would be easier if the goods here were a bit cheaper.  The reality is that for certain goods, particularly petrol, liquor and electrical goods, people go over the Border to buy.  The gap in price is far too large between North and South for the same article.  Most of the Members here would agree with that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>There are taxation and excise duty reasons, but the reality is that some goods are dearer down here.  We should try to improve the tax system.  I would ask the Minister here to implore his colleagues to make every effort to do that as quickly as possible.  He certainly would have the support of us all.  I know it is not a simple solution.  If it was that easy, Fine Gael would have done it when we were in Government or the Fianna Fáil side would already have done it.  We are all aware that total reform of taxation is necessary.  People want to make their wages go further, particularly at <Col N="1504" /> Christmas.  The 48 hour rule may have worked but the point remains that the gap in prices of certain goods as between here and Northern Ireland is too great. One can only hope that with the reform and harmonisation of our tax laws, improvements will be brought about after 1992.</P>
    <P>This Bill deals mainly with technical aspects particularly in relation to commercial contracts.  With, we would hope, expanded business contracts and links, and the import and export levels we can expect in the years ahead, it is important that rights, responsibilities and obligations are enforceable and can be effected under contracts.  In the light of our expanding business markets, it is important that Irish people have their rights with regard to contracts in other countries.  If Irish contractors are defaulting or making difficulties in relation to contracts or agreements abroad it will be up to members of other States to enforce their rights against Irish people.  If it is sauce for the goose, it will be sauce for the gander.  If commercial life is to be expanded with a greater flow of goods it is important that there is the mechanism to ensure that people will be able to insist on their rights.  Does the Minister envisage many difficulties in relation to the question of where cases will be heard? Will there be difficulties with language barriers and foreign documents in deciding where a case will be heard?  In certain cases, the law may decide that cases may be tried under Irish law or French law or some other country's law.</P>
    <P>Can the Minister give an assurance that there will not be undue difficulties for people in bringing these actions? Obviously, this could happen with laws changing and a European dimension to it.  Speaking, if you like, against the legal profession, it should be made easy and reasonable for ordinary individuals to bring actions under this Bill.  There are difficulties with certain people trying to take actions.  There are difficulties of service of documents.  All these matters should be looked at so that these difficulties can be easily resolved.  At times there are difficulties between company <Col N="1505" /> law and contract law as to whom to sue and where to sue.  I would ask the Minister, when replying to give an indication of how he sees the difficulties being overcome.</P>
    <P>I support, in principle, the measures contained in this Bill.  It is to be hoped that full discussion will take place in relation to various matters under the various articles.  I note the Minister has said that Ireland is going to exercise its reservation under article 7.  This is something the Law Society have suggested.  It is to be hoped that under this Bill people's rights under commercial contracts will now be given greater safeguards and greater security than before.</P>
    <Speaker pid="DenisFoley" hpid="Mr. Foley Mr. Foley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Foley</NameTxt>
      <P>I welcome the opportunity to make a few brief comments on this important Bill.  The purpose of the Bill is to enable Ireland to ratify the EC Convention on the Law applicable to Contractual Obligations opened for signature in Rome on 19 June 1980 and the Convention on the Accession of the Hellenic Republic to the 1980 convention signed in Luxembourg on 10 April 1984.</P>
      <P>Since our entry to the EC we have seen tremendous growth in international trade in regard to Ireland.  This has brought about the need for changes in our existing national and international laws in the civil and commercial context.  The Minister referred to the fact that when we have studied the Bill and the conventions we can see that this area of the law is complex and technical.  Be that as it may, it is an area of considerable importance.  We are aware of how important international trade is to our economy.  A major proportion of economic activity in this country relates to the import and export of goods and services.  In these transactions we have a contract.  As the trade is international there is an inevitable interaction between the legal system in Ireland and the country with which we do business.  In addition, if internationl trade is to flourish it needs a simple legal framework to underpin it.  That is what this Bill is all about.  That is what the 1980 convention also indicates.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The Bill, as already stated by other <Col N="1506" /> speakers, is most important for business people and major companies involved in international contracts.  We have seen over the past number of years where many companies sought clarification on points of law with regard to such international contracts.  This Bill sets out the position very clearly, especially where points of our law were not clear and were in conflict with some of our Community partners.  We will now have a most up to date code of law which will benefit all concerned.  This is of tremendous importance to the Irish business sector involved in international trade and commerce. The principle of it is that parties involved in international contracts will be allowed to choose whichever country's laws they think will be most appropriate.</P>
    <P>I welcome that where parties to a contract omit to specify which country will govern these contracts the courts will apply a series of presumptions to decide the issue.  Special protection is provided in the case of certain consumer and individual employment contracts.</P>
    <P>The convention has not yet entered into force for any of the member states of the Community.  I understand it requires ratification by seven member states to bring it into force in those states which have ratified it.  To date, six states have ratified it and I believe the United Kingdom will do so shortly with the result that the convention will enter into force in these states in early 1991.</P>
    <P>I would hope that we can accede to the Minister's request that this Bill will get a speedy passage through this House.  I welcome the Bill and I commend it to the House.</P>
    <Speaker pid="RichardConroy" hpid="Professor Conroy Professor Conroy">
      <NameTxt>Professor Conroy</NameTxt>
      <P>I would like to make a few comments on this Bill.  First, it is an important Bill with considerable obligations and implications for law in this country.  There are implications of various sorts, but they certainly will be of great importance for business and for the financial implications of international trading.  In relation to its size, Ireland is probably involved in international trade to a greater extent than any other member of the Common Market.  This is <Col N="1507" /> an important Bill but at present, we are discussing it effectively in the absence of the media.  I have no doubt that, from time to time, there will be cases arising from this that will be on the front pages in all our newspapers in the coming years.</P>
      <P>To take some simple examples: we have an Irish company exporting goods to Italy.  The goods are being exported by truck travelling through the United Kingdom, perhaps, through France and possibly Switzerland on the way to Italy, and something happens that consignment. This may or may not be covered by a specific contract between the parties as to where any dispute is going to be discussed in law.  That may simplify the matter although, as this Bill suggests and reminds us, there are mandatory matters which a contract between the two different parties cannot exclude.  The mandatory matters might apply in either country or in the countries through which those particular goods are traversing.  If, as frequently happens in business, there is not a specific written contract between the two parties, then it may, indeed, be extraordinarily difficult to decide under whose law the matter will be judged.  This Bill helps considerably to clarify that situation.  I have given the simple example of exporting goods in a lorry but it could equally apply to far bigger transactions.  This will have great relevance to an individual carrier working his own lorry and carrying goods or to some multinational corporation.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>It is interesting also that non-member states will be affected too.  This is not just purely a European convention law, <i>per se.</i> It goes widely outside that.  Yesterday we were discussing the economic and social business implications of political union, as well as the monetary situation. Over the next two or three years in financial and monetary terms the Twelve will come much closer together.  Yet the laws of these states are extraordinarily diverse.  In some of our discussions and, indeed, in the very excellent speech by the Minister, we are naturally looking at it from the point of view of law as it is <Col N="1508" /> evolved here.  Even that can be complicated enough.  There is mention that matrimonial property will be excluded.</P>
    <P>When we were discussing the question of land property laws here we very quickly discovered that we were discussing the laws as expressed in this State since we attained independence.  We were discussing the laws which applied to the United Kingdom between 1800 and 1922, the laws of the then Kingdom of Ireland prior to 1800, case law within this State and case law since 1922 in the United Kingdom.  Of course, the courts here take into account the decisions of judges in the United Kingdom if those decisions relate to law which evolved or came into being before 1922 or which evolved from pre-1922 laws.  It very rapidly became extraordinarily complicated. Yet, we were only dealing with the very simple situation of us and Britain.</P>
    <P>We are going on to a very important, but very technical, aspect of law in contract obligations.  We are now moving outside the relatively simple situation that exists between Britain and ourselves and going to the mainland of Europe where, of course, the basic law is totally different from Irish or British law.  It is Napoleonic law.  Their attitude towards contracts, the legal framework on which they are working and the interpretation of those laws is very different from the laws as we understand them here.</P>
    <P>It is going to be a very important development.  If we are truly merging in monetary terms, our currency, and our monetary policies with those of the other 11 member states, must relate to the underlying contractual and business law. I am delighted to see this Bill before us. I would not altogether agree that we are the last to introduce such a measure. We are, in fact, the sixth or seventh.  A number of other countries still have to ratify it apart from ourselves.  A great deal of law like this will need to come into effect if we are going to proceed towards EMU as we were discussing yesterday. I do not think we have fully taken on board that laws emanating from the <Col N="1509" /> Community are going to have an enormous impact not only on major international businesses but, in fact, on the ordinary citizen.</P>
    <P>There are many other matters that I would like to go into.  I hope to bring up some of them during Committee Stage.  I am referring to such things as subrogation and Articles 15 and 16 which got little notice in the explanatory memorandum.</P>
    <Speaker pid="DenisLyons" hpid="Minister of State at the Department of Tourism and Transport (Mr. Lyons) Minister of State at the Department of Tourism and Transport (Mr. Lyons)">
      <NameTxt>Minister of State at the Department of Tourism and Transport (Mr. Lyons)</NameTxt>
      <P>First, I want to acknowledge the contributions by Senators.  It is only right that I place on record my appreciation of the contributions of Senators Mullooly, Raftery, Upton, Mooney, Cosgrave, Foley and Conroy.  I should acknowledge the interest shown in the legislation by other Senators who attended here and did not contribute.  I should like to acknowledge the interest of Senators Ó Foighil, Farrell and Haughey.  In the time available to me I will do my best to reply to the questions raised.  Some of them will have to be referred to at a later stage.</P>
      <P>Senator Raftery cast some doubt on the possibility of the 1980 convention coming into force shortly.  The position is that only one further notification is required, as I indicated in my opening address.  My understanding is that the United Kingdom, despite the doubts expressed by Senator Raftery, having passed the necessary legislation will deposit their instrument of ratification this month.  My hope is that we will not be too long after that.</P>
      <P>Senator Upton raised the question of the Title of the Bill and asked that the list of signatories be included in it.  Very briefly, I would say that it is not the practice to include the list of signatories in a Bill.  I suggest for the benefit of the Seanad that we should have the list of signatories of the convention.  They are available, it the Senators are interested, in the versions published in the Official Journal 266, Volume 23 of 9 October 1980.  It is not the usual practice to include lists of signatories in a Bill.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Senator Upton, of course, was correct <Col N="1510" /> in saying that the Minister, Deputy Gerard Collins, signed the convention on behalf of Ireland in 1980.  The Senator went on then to complain about the ten year lapse.  I do not wish to introduce a note of politics into this but Senator Upton should consider for a moment when he is making statements like that that we were not in power all the time between 1980 and 1990.  I am very tempted to say that people in glasshouses should not throw stones.  What were his party doing when they were in Government? I will leave it at that; I am sure he knows what I am talking about.</P>
    <P>Senator Mooney asked about contracts with East European countries.  The rules contained in the 1980 Convention will apply here in the case of disputes arising out of contracts with those countries.  I cannot say, of course, what rules those countries might apply, but it is open to an Irish business person to choose the jurisdiction where any dispute will be litigated and also what law will apply.  This is provided for in the Bill.  The jurisdiction of courts, and employment of judgments, as I mentioned earlier, is covered in the European Communities Act, 1988.</P>
    <P>Senator Cosgrave asked when would we be signing the convention.  The position is that Ireland was one of the countries which signed the convention when it was opened for signature in 1980. The other nine member states signed at the same time or shortly afterwards.  We will ratify the convention once this legislation has been passed by the Oireachtas. I would like to mention in passing the need for speed and urgency as expressed by Senators.  We should not delay this legislation.  That is a welcome view by the Senators.</P>
    <P>Senator Cosgrave also asked where cases will be heard.  That matter is covered by rules contained in the 1968 EC Judgments Convention which was given effect in Ireland by the 1988 Jurisdiction of Courts and Enforcement of Judgments Act.  The matter is already covered comprehensively in our law.  In regard to the service of documents, we <Col N="1511" /> signed the Hague Convention on the service abroad of documents in April.  On commercial matters arrangements are now being made to enable Ireland to ratify that convention by means of a rule of court.</P>
    <P>I again want to thank the Senators for their speedy treatment of this Stage of the Bill and for their contributions.</P>
    <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Acting Chairman Acting Chairman">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman</NameTxt>
      <P>When is it proposed to take the next Stage?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DenisLyons" hpid="Mr. Lyons Mr. Lyons">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lyons</NameTxt>
      <P>On 28 November 1990, subject to agreement between the Whips.</P>
      <P>Committee Stage ordered for Wednesday, 28 November 1990.</P>
      <P>
        <i>Sitting suspended at 1 p.m. and resumed at 2 p.m.</i>
      </P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Adjournment Matter. - Bord" RHead="Telecom Charging System">
    <Title>Adjournment Matter. - Bord Telecom Charging System.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="EamonOCuiv" hpid="Éamon Ó Cuív Éamon Ó Cuív">
      <NameTxt>Éamon Ó Cuív</NameTxt>
      <P>Ba mhaith liom i dtosach buíochas a glacadh leis an Aire as ucht teacht isteach inniu agus éisteacht leis na pointí a bheidh á dhéanamh agam i dtaobh na ceiste seo.</P>
      <P>The question is to ask the Minister for Industry and Commerce to get the Fair Trade Commission to institute an inquiry into the charging system operated by Bord Telecom.  I compliment Bord Telecom on the improved system that has been instituted in recent years.  It is hard for us now to visualise the situation we had in my part of the country and many other rural areas where, as late as 1986, to make a telephone call one had to go through a series of operators.  I would be the first to give due credit to the board for totally automating the system and for bringing us from 19th century technology to the very latest in digital technology in one leap.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>It is time that we looked at the whole question of how Telecom Éireann charge <Col N="1512" /> for their calls.  I have often argued that telephone charges, energy costs and insurance costs are the biggest burdens any industry face.  Steps taken to equalise and reduce them would be much more important to both the ordinary consumer and industry than all the grants in the world.</P>
    <P>Basically, the telephone service was developed from the original telegraph service which, as we know, ran along the railway lines during the last century.  It is amazing to think that this history is still apparent when one examines the telecommunications charge structure for telephone calls.  We have a late 20th century system being charged on a 19th century system.  Despite developments in the technology of transmission, telephone charges are based on areas which are still based on the railway lines.  A typical example of this occurs in my own part of the country with which I am obviously very familiar and this is replicated throughout the country.  For example, in Cornamona where I live the telephone line and the postal service comes to us via Claremoris and Ballinrobe.  As a consequence, living in Cornamona it is possible to make a local call to Claremorris or to Tuam but it is impossible to make a local call to, for example, Galway or Castlebar.</P>
    <P>As you know until the phasing out of the manual service the transmission system was along telephone lines.  This has largely been replaced by a modern system.  We now use microwave lengths as a very important intrinsic part of the telephone service.  Where each telephone in the old days had to have a single line, we also now use multi-line cables and we are even developing into fibre optics.  This has meant that the cost of the infrastructure per call made has reduced dramatically in recent years.  At the same time, there has been a very rapid increase in the number of telephones throughout the country, but particularly in rural Ireland.  For example, there are many areas, including my own area, and throughout Connemara, where the numbers of telephones have increased ten fold since the mid-seventies.  When one <Col N="1513" /> looks at the appropriate charging system that Bord Telecom should have, it must be first recognised that even for the urban subscriber the more complete the system, the more people on the system, the more options in the long term that subscriber has.  Therefore, it is very important for the completeness of the system that it is attractive to have a telephone.</P>
    <P>It is often argued that the extra cost of providing telphones in rural areas justifies the particular layout of the telephone charge areas.  The reality is that it is only the exceptional long lying cases, as Telecom Éireann refer to them, that is where you have a phone maybe three miles from the local exchange, where there is any real extra cost in providing rural telephones.  For example, as long as one person in Cornamona needs a telephone the line would have to come as far as Cornamona and the extra charge of putting 50 or 100 lines into a little village like that is not significantly greater than it is for putting in one.</P>
    <P>At present, as we know, telephone charges are at four rates within the Republic.  You have a local call rate which is 11.17 pence and has no duration limit on it.  You have an A, B and C trunk rate with different charges for peak and offpeak hours.  People living in STD areas can in certain circumstances ring people in adjacent STD areas direct and in other circumstances they cannot.  The information regarding this is available to anybody. It is in the front of the telephone directory.  However, there are a few areas in the country particularly on the west coast, for example, Caherciveen, Belmullet and Clifden, where one cannot ring in any circumstances in any direction outside the STD area without making a trunk call.  It also must be stressed that the areas where you can ring outside your own STD area are not necessarily the areas of most usage or the ones that would be most convenient to a subscriber but are based, as I said before, on the layout of the postal service and the railway line.  A good example of this arises in the Tuam-Headford area in Galway which is an 093 area and the code there means that people can ring Claremorris <Col N="1514" /> or Ballindine but they cannot ring areas from Claregalway into Galway city as a local call.  For example, in Connemara, you cannot ring Kilkerrin to Rosmuc, neighbouring villages, as a local call.  It is a trunk call.  Within a local call charge area two computers could be connected and left running.  Leaving aside rental, if they were left running continuously year after year the total charge would be 11.17 pence.  We have to look at the logic of this.  It is true that there would be an extra cost initially in providing the service but it would seem logical since this is a once off cost that the way to recoup it would be to charge more for installation in rural areas.  There might be a fractionally more expensive cost but with modern telephones breakdowns are rare particularly with the digital system.  The logical thing to do if you wanted to charge for that on a commercial basis would be to increase slightly the rental for the phone.  However, Telecom Éireann policy is in direct contradiction of this. They have a uniform connection fee and a uniform rental, and they charge extra by the minute.  What does this mean?  As well as the rural subsidising the urban which is happening, we also have the situation where the rural person who makes many telephone calls is basically subsidising the subscriber who very rarely uses his system.  This defies all commercial logic.</P>
    <P>I do not dispute the necessity for Bord Telecom to make the telephone service economic.  They must make a profit. However, within those parameters there has to be an element of public service in the provision of a public utility.  One of the common elements of this type of economic public service is that the overall cost of providing the service is spread evenly among the various subscribers to such a service.  The ESB charge extra for the initial installation of electricity but ESB unit charges for electricity are uniform throughout the country.  Similarly, An Post charge the same for a letter whether you are getting a letter delivered from one place in Dublin to another or from Dublin to Galway, Cornamona or Clifden.  Similarly, county councils make <Col N="1515" /> uniform charges, for water and spread the cost evenly among the subscribers. The reasoning and logic behind this is that if you continually weight all your services in favour of the centre you quickly arrive at a situation where you have totally denuded the countryside because people would leave the areas where there was a high cost for services. Bord Telecom recognise this.  I accept that with modern services, for example, telex, although that is now becoming defunct, Eirpac services and so on they do not charge on the old system but have uniform charges throughout the country. In my business I can get in through my Eirpac system to Dublin at the charge of a local call.</P>
    <P>We must have a positive policy to create active decentralisation.  Anything that causes cost differences between urban, provincial and rural areas must be a hindrance to that aim.  Further, as a country on the periphery of Europe our only chance of survival post-1992 will be to have a competitive cost structure.  As a result of our location and the increasing part that telecommunications will play in business, it will be of paramount importance that we have an efficient and cheap telephone service.  It is important that this does not put customers outside urban centres at a serious cost disadvantage.  I recognise that Bord Telecom have taken steps to reduce the cost of international telephone calls but I would argue that was solely because it was cheaper to ring from, for example, America to Ireland than to ring from Ireland to America and Telecom Éireann were losing business.  It is a terrible travesty of justice that people in business or private citizens phoning in their county towns have to pay at the rate of a trunk call.  We all know what happens when you ring up the county council, or the Department of Agriculture livestock office or the local solicitor or hospital. You get through to the switch and they say: &ldquo;I wonder if you would mind hanging on a few minutes?&rdquo; If you are in Dublin or in a local call area it is no problem. But all the time the rural subscriber is left hanging on he is being charged.  You <Col N="1516" /> get through eventually and begin to talk and then you are asked if you would mind holding on for a minute until the person gets out the file.  You wait another three or four minutes while they get the file and look at it.  You could tell them to ring you back but I think we all know that the bird in the hand is worth two in the bush and it is very important to hold on to somebody when you have them, otherwise you go through the whole rigmarole again.</P>
    <P>The Fair Trade Commission should look at this.  It would do more for rural Ireland than many other proposed developments.  It is something that would be simple and cheap.  My proposal is &mdash; I would like to see this looked at &mdash; to have a step by step approach.  In the long term all calls made in this island should be charged at the same rate as is the case with the postal service and the ESB.  I accept that it is not likely to happen overnight and that we do not know what cost adjustments would have to be made to pursue such a policy.  I suggest that a first step might be taken by making what is now an A rate call a local call; a B rate trunk call an A rate, and a C rate a B rate.</P>
    <P>The effect of this on revenue could be monitored and a second step could be subsequently taken.  This would also help An Bord Telecom to sell their Eircell system which is growing rapidly, more so here than in most other countries. I understand that international reports back up what I am saying.  It has been proven quite conclusively that when such rational steps were taken with air transport, when it was opened up and the State monopoly was forced to compete to be customer led as the jargon is, it resulted in an increase in revenue.  I want Telecom Éireann to be profitable, to be out in the market looking for extra business and for more subscribers.  I remember, much to their surprise, one time canvassing a valley for telephones and out of 42 houses in one of the most remote rural areas I got 41 houses to sign up to take a telephone and they have never regretted the day.</P>
    <P>I am absolutely convinced that if the <Col N="1517" /> Minister instituted an investigation by the Fair Trade Commission, everything I have said here would be borne out and that if An Bord Telecom changed their system they would be better off.  A huge cost anomaly for rural Ireland would be eliminated and we would all be better off.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelSmith" hpid="Minister of State at the Department of Industry and Commerce (Mr. Smith) Minister of State at the Department of Industry and Commerce (Mr. Smith)">
      <NameTxt>Minister of State at the Department of Industry and Commerce (Mr. Smith)</NameTxt>
      <P>Is mian liom, ar an gcéad dul síos, a chur in iúl don Seanad an t-áthas atá orm a theacht isteach anseo inniu, mar chaith mé cuid mhór aimsire anseo i rith na n-ochtóidí.  Is mian liom freisin moladh a thabhairt don Seanadóir Ó Cuív as ucht an tsuim atá léirithe aige i gcúrsaí eacnamaíochta na tíre go háirithe chomh fada agus a bhaineann sé le muintir na Gaeltachta agus muintir na tuaithe; agus go speisialta an tsuim a thaispeáin sé i gcásanna faoi leith i chuile cheantar ar a bhfuil athrú tagaithe, go mór mhór laghdú ar an daonra agus na deacrachtaí speisialta atá sna háiteanna sin.</P>
      <P>It is always a pleasure to come into the Seanad and join some of my colleagues where I have had the pleasure to serve for quite a considerable time in the eighties. It is also a pleasure to hear Senator Ó Cuív who clearly has a very great interest in and insight into the problems of outlying areas throughout the country particularly in Galway and in west Galway where demographic changes have led to rural depopulation and where there is a need to update and provide services which will ultimately help the rehabilitation of these areas as far as that is humanly possible.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The question is to ask the Minister for Industry and Commerce if the Fair Trade Commission would examine the charges for telecommunications charged by Telecom Éireann particularly as they relate to rural areas.  There are one or two disappointing aspects about that, in that the Postal and Telecommunications Act, 1983, governs the functions of Telecom Éireann.  It sets out the financial objectives of the company which are basically that it should generate sufficient revenue to cover all its costs.  Section 90 obliges <Col N="1518" /> the company to publish their charges and these can be increased only with the agreement of the Minister for Communications. It is clear, therefore, that it is the Minister for Communications who has the responsibility in this matter.</P>
    <P>The Restrictive Practices Acts set out the functions of the Fair Trade Commission. The commission is not a prices advisory body and is not a substitute for the long-abolished National Prices Commission. The Fair Trade Commission can prepare and publish fair practice rules in relation to the provision of services.  It can carry out inquiries into the conditions which obtain in regard to the provision of any service.  It can do the same with respect to the supply and distribution of goods.  Such inquiries may deal with prices or charges but these are not the focus of inquiries.  The inquiries are designed to establish whether there are restrictive practices or interferences with competition that are unfair or operate against the common good.</P>
    <P>The procedure for inquiries is formal. It is usually lengthy and action on foot of reports is not easily taken.  Even where an inquiry results in a decision to make a restrictive practice order, the order does not become effective until confirmed by an Act of the Oireachtas.  The cumbersome nature of these procedures is one of the reasons why new legislation or competition is favoured.</P>
    <P>As I said at the outset, legislation gives a role to the Minister for Communications in relation to charges by Telecom Éireann.  Earlier this year, however, the Senator made representations to the Minister for Industry and Commerce on this subject where he outlined the special difficulties of outlying rural areas and the need for change.  On foot of these representations we have been in correspondence with the Minister for Communications.  I consulted him on the matter before coming here.  His Department has had discussions with An Bord Telecom on this matter with a view to the construction of a more equitable, balanced charging system.  Bord Telecom Éireann hope to be able to make an announcement about this matter in the <Col N="1519" /> very near future.  In these circumstances, I do not consider it appropriate to refer the matter to the Fair Trade Commission, and I think the Senator will understand that if the developments which we cannot anticipate fully at this stage are on the lines that he anticipates, perhaps the queries and problem that he refers to will be addressed in a satisfactory way.  I am not in a position, however, to outline how these matters will be dealt with ultimately by An Bord Telecom.</P>
    <Speaker pid="EamonOCuiv" hpid="Éamon Ó Cuív Éamon Ó Cuív">
      <NameTxt>Éamon Ó Cuív</NameTxt>
      <P>I thank the Minister of State for his reply.  I am very encouraged that investigations are taking place and that my various representations in this matter are being attended to.  I just ask him once again to bring this matter to the attention of both the Minister for <Col N="1520" /> Communications and the Minister for Industry and Commerce.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelSmith" hpid="Mr. Smith Mr. Smith">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Smith</NameTxt>
      <P>As I indicated in my reply, while the Minister for Industry and Commerce has no direct responsibility here, we have, on foot of the Senator's representations, commenced discussions with An Bord Telecom and the indications to us at this stage are that An Bord Telecom will be in a position to make an announcement fairly soon.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DanNeville" hpid="Acting Chairman (Mr. Neville) Acting Chairman (Mr. Neville)">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman (Mr. Neville)</NameTxt>
      <P>When is it proposed that the Seanad sit again?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TrasHonan" hpid="Mrs. Honan Mrs. Honan">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Honan</NameTxt>
      <P>It is proposed to meet again next Wednesday at 2.30 p.m.</P>
      <P>The Seanad adjourned at 2.30 p.m. until 2.30 p.m. on Wednesday, 21 November 1990.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
</Debate>