<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE Debate SYSTEM "../Debate.dtd"[]>
<Debate DocTitle="Seanad Debate" Day="Wed" Date="9" Month="May" Year="1990" Vol="124" No="16" DateIrish="Dé Céadaoin, 9 Bealtaine 1990" DateEnglish="Wednesday, 9 May 1990" House="S" CommitteeEng="" CommitteeIr="" SubNameEng="" cnum="0">
  <MainHeading Type="Prelude" LHead="" RHead="">
    <Title>
    </Title>
    <P>
      <Col N="1569" /> Chuaigh an Cathaoirleach i gceannas ar 2.30 p.m.</P>
    <P Just="Center">
      <i>Paidir.</i>
    </P>
    <P Just="Center">
      <i>Prayer.</i>
    </P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Death of Cardinal Ó Fiaich:" RHead="Expression of Sympathy">
    <Title>Death of Cardinal Ó Fiaich: Expression of Sympathy.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="SeanDoherty" hpid="An Cathoirleach An Cathoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I propose to call on the Leader of the House, Senator Lanigan, to make a statement in connection with the expression of sympathy to the family and relatives of the late Cardinal Tomás Ó Fiaich.  It is the usual practice that the leaders of the individual groups follow.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MickLanigan" hpid="Mr. Lanigan Mr. Lanigan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lanigan</NameTxt>
      <P>In line with the tradition of the House I would like to ask the permission of the House to raise the matter of the passing of a vote of sympathy to the people of Ireland on the death of Cardinal Tomás Ó Fiaich.  It is necessary from a procedural point of view that the permission of the House be obtained to raise this matter.  I agree with the Cathaoirleach, if the House agrees, that statements should be made by the leaders of the groups in the House.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Senators Senators">
      <NameTxt>Senators</NameTxt>
      <P>Agreed.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MickLanigan" hpid="Mr. Lanigan Mr. Lanigan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lanigan</NameTxt>
      <P>It is with deep regret that I rise here today to propose a vote of sympathy first to the family of Cardinal Tomás Ó Fiaich who died very suddenly on a pilgrimage to Lourdes last evening. When I say to the family of Cardinal <Col N="1570" /> Tomás Ó Fiaich, I think we would include in that everybody who lives on this island and not just his own immediate family, because his influence has extended into every family in Ireland, not alone since he became Cardinal but since he became a public figure.</P>
      <P>His death at the early age of 66 years is a tremendous blow to those of us in Ireland who have criticised the spiral of violence that has invaded this island over the past years.  He will be deeply missed by the people who espoused the cause of peace and reconciliation in this island. He will be tremendously missed by the Church he loved so well and for which he worked so unstintingly over the past number of years.  It is ironic &mdash; but perhaps not so ironic &mdash; that he died in the middle of his duties as pastor in accompanying the diocesan pilgrimage to Lourdes.  He was a supporter of that pilgrimage and he accompanied it as a matter of love over many, many years.</P>
      <P>As a person who was born in Cullyhanna, near Crossmaglen, 66 years ago, he was very well aware of the difficulties anybody in his position would have if selected within the politics of Ireland or the politics of the Church.  I know some of his colleagues who went to school with him in Maynooth.  They are some friends of mine who studied with him and they spoke throughout the years with nothing but the greatest of friendship towards him.  Indeed, they also suggested he was a man of extremely high intellect which at times seemed to be hidden because he seemed to be a man who was bluff and who spoke in a very forthright way.  However, he got his message across.</P>
      <P>He had a deep love of the Irish language and indeed of Irish history.  He served as chairman of the Government commission on the restoration of the Irish language, on Comhairle na Ghaeilge, he was a member of the Senate of the National University of Ireland, was President of Cumann na Sagart and was a member of the Higher Education Authority.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>He was ordained Cardinal in St. Patrick's Cathedral in 1977 and since then <Col N="1571" /> he has not neglected at any stage to come out in public against the spiral of violence. He believed in a peaceful withdrawal by Britain from Ireland.  He stated in an interview, &ldquo;I believe there should be a declaration of intent.  I know it is a coloured phrase but it is the only thing that will get things moving.&rdquo;  However, it is in his pastoral role that he will be missed by the bishops and priests of Ireland and, indeed, by the Church which is made up of bishops, priests and the people.</P>
    <P>We cannot but reiterate the sentiments he always expressed that it did not matter from which side violence came within these islands it should be condemned out of hand.  Ar dheis Dé go raibh a anam dílis.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MauriceManning" hpid="Mr. Manning Mr. Manning">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Manning</NameTxt>
      <P>The sudden death of the Cardinal has come as a great and genuine shock to all of us.  He was a man of enormous vitality and zest, a man who loved life.  He was human, approachable, compassionate and unpretentious.  He had very strong views, which he vigorously expressed.  There was no doubt about his enthusiasm whether it was for the Irish language, football or his love of the traditional values of his own native Armagh.  His ideal Ireland was one which, again, is fairly easy to piece together from his writings and his talking. It was an Ireland which was Gaelic, Catholic and Republican.  In recent years, especially since becoming Cardinal, he was increasingly a great conciliator, a man who saw the complexity of things. He had, in recent times especially, an awareness of and respect for the other traditions in this island.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>For me, the most striking aspect of the tributes that have been pouring in over the last hours have been those from the other Churches, from Church leaders and from ordinary churchmen, praising his ecumenism, his hatred of injustice and his genuine wish for reconciliation.  Also, what comes across in the tributes &mdash; and I was especially struck by the tribute on the BBC early this morning from the Minister of the First Presbyterian Church in Lisburn &mdash; was the sense of the personal impact the Cardinal made through <Col N="1572" /> sheer force of personality on members of other Churches.  His generosity, his courtesy, his friendship and his openness were the characteristics which most impressed themselves on the leaders of other Churches, who saw in him somebody with whom they could disagree, but somebody whose good faith they could not, in any circumstances, doubt.</P>
    <P>He was an honest, open and a good man and on behalf of the Fine Gael Party, I would like to convey our sympathy to his family, to the priests an the people of the Archdiocese of Armagh.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatUpton" hpid="Dr. Upton Dr. Upton">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Upton</NameTxt>
      <P>On behalf of the Labour Party, I would like to extend our sincere sympathy to the family of Cardinal Ó Fiaich, to his fellow bishops and priests and to the laity of the Archdiocese of Armagh and, indeed, the whole country.</P>
      <P>Cardinal ÓFiaich will be missed, in particular, because of his anxiety and efforts to bring peace ad reconciliation to this country.  We will be missed because of his great concern about the problems and difficulties that afflict Northern Ireland.  He will be missed particularly because of his concern for those who suffered or were compromised as a result of those difficulties.  He will also be missed by those who have knowledge and understanding of Irish history and culture. In the torrent of tributes perhaps this aspect of his work has not been given as much attention as it may deserve.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>He was, of course, unmistakably Irish. He embodied many of the finest characteristics which make Irish people interesting and different.  The respect and affection in which he was held by the ordinary people of the Archdiocese of Armagh and in particular, by people in the Crossmaglen area in Armagh are a great tribute to him.  To the extent that one could judge, he seemed to be happiest and most relaxed when he was among those people, talking to them and, in the fullest sense, being part of their whole existence, sharing in it and indeed contributing to it.  He was a man of his own people.  He will be missed by the people in the Archdiocese of Armagh. He will be missed by the Irish Catholic Church and by Catholics worldwide.  He will be missed by all people who have a <Col N="1573" /> respect and appreciation for and who are at peace with their Irishness.  He was an Irishman who, as far as I could judge, seemed to be happy and relaxed.  He was a very worthy figure who represented in the finest ways the very best aspects of what it is to be Irish.  Ar dheis Dé go raibh a anam dílis.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JohnMurphy2" hpid="Professor Murphy Professor Murphy">
      <NameTxt>Professor Murphy</NameTxt>
      <P>Thar ceann na Seanadóirí Ollscoile, is mian liomsa mo chomhbhrón a chur in iúl chomh maith. Ó mo thaobh féin de, cuimhneoidh mé ar Tomás Ó Fiaich mar scoláire agus mar staraí.  Is báúil iad lucht aon cheirde, mar a deirtear, agus bhí aithne agam ar an staraí le fada an lá agus meas agam air dá réir.  Bhí cáilíocht aige mar staraí nach raibh ag mórán, is é sin bhí tíriúlacht a phearsantachta le tabhairt faoi ndeara ina chuid saothair.  Bhí féith na samhlaíochta stairiúla go láidir ann, agus, mar scoláire, bhí sé préamhaithe go daingean ina dhúiche féin agus go forleathan san Eoraip chomh maith.</P>
      <P>I am speaking on behalf of the group of University Senators.  We associate ourselves very sincerely with the vote of sympathy. I would just like to say I have known the late Cardinal perhaps longer than most people in this House because our common interests as scholars and historians go back quite a distance.  He brought to his scholarship qualities which every historian is not fortunate enough to possess in that in addition to his professionalism and his precision, he brought imagination and a passion for the past &mdash; and for his own Gaelic past &mdash; which illumined the material he worked upon. That sympathetic imagination extended from his own locality and from his own Ulster, so rich in history, to Europe as a whole where he pursued, indeed, casán na naomh, the pathway of the saints.  As a Gaeilgeoir, a lover of the games, of the language, and the culture, he was generous in that while he cherished these things dearly he did not attempt to impose them as a criterion of Irishness.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>As a nationalist and as a south Armagh man, it was natural he should have had strong feelings about a united Ireland. Predictably, he was maligned for this in predictable quarters and, predictably, it did not bother him.  It was also unfair in <Col N="1574" /> my view and inaccurate to have depicted him, as some people did, as a kind of an Irish Makarios, a kind of politicoreligious ethnarch.</P>
    <P>One has to say nonetheless, that his interests as a Catholic prelate did not always sit easily with his interests as an Irishman.  As an historian, he understood and admired the ideals of the United Irishman, but he did not find it possible to promote them in his own contemporary Ireland.  Regrettably, he supported, albeit with moderate enthusiasm, the Catholic ethos in education and sexual morality.  He apparently failed to see the incompatibility of that with the ideals of a united Ireland and a Protestant-Catholic reconciliation which he so warmly cherished, ideals which will be achieved, if at all, only through our acceptance of a secular, political framework in the whole of this island.</P>
    <Speaker pid="HelenKeogh" hpid="Miss Keogh Miss Keogh">
      <NameTxt>Miss Keogh</NameTxt>
      <P>I would like to join in the expressions of regret at the unexpected and untimely death of Cardinal Ó Fiaich. The many tributes we have heard here today and heard through the media have attested to the admiration and affection in which the Cardinal was held by the people of Ireland and people from across the divide in Northern Ireland.  He is a great loss to the Catholic Church, of course, but he is a great loss to all the people of Ireland.</P>
      <P>He was his own man.  He was a noted scholar and historian.  He was a man of great humanity.  We must remember that although he looked forward to the day of a united Ireland he totally rejected the use of violence as a means to that end.  I can think of his great humour and humanity that attested to the fact he was a man of his people and that is the way we should remember him.  We express our sympathy particularly to his family, to his many friends and the priests and bishops of the diocese.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanDoherty" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I would like to be associated with Members of the House in conveying sympathy to the family and relatives of the late Cardinal.  The House will stand in silence for one minute.</P>
      <P>
        <i>Members rose in their places.</i>
      </P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Business" RHead="of Seanad">
    <Title>Business of Seanad.</Title>
    <Col N="1575" />
    <Speaker pid="SeanDoherty" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I have notice from Senator Avril Doyle that, on the motion for the Adjournment of the House today, she proposes to raise the following matter:</P>
      <P>The need for the Minister for Health to ensure that the South Eastern Health Board appoints immediately a full-time consultant paediatrician to Wexford General Hospital as recommended by Comhairle na nOspidéal.</P>
      <P>Tá fógra agam ón Seanadóir Pól Ó Foighil:</P>
      <P>Go gcuirfear Teilifís na Gaeltachta ar bun láithreach agus go niarrtar ar Aire na Gaeltachta gníomhú láithreach i mbunú na seirbhíse seo.</P>
      <P>I also received notice from Senator Joe Costello of the following matter:</P>
      <P>The need for the Minister for Education to urgently provide permanent accommodation and proper facilities for the pupils of St. Aidan's Christian Brothers Secondary School, Whitehall, Dublin 9 to replace the present totally inadequate prefabricated structure which has been in existence for over 20 years.</P>
      <P>I also received notice from Senator David Norris of the following matter:</P>
      <P>The need for the Minister for Education to intervene personally to prevent a List 1 building, No. 20 North Great George's Street, from further deterioration and from being vandalised at the hands of the City of Dublin Vocational Educational Committee.</P>
      <P>I regard the matters raised by Senators Doyle, Ó Foighil, Norris and Costello as suitable for discussion on the Adjournment. I have selected the matter raised by Senator Doyle and it will be taken at the conclusion of business.  Senators Ó Foighil and Costello may give notice on another day of the matters they wish to raise.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I must point out that in the script I have here it refers to Senator Norris' matter as being suitable for discussion on the Adjournment.  That is not correct.  I <Col N="1576" /> regret I have to rule the matter raised by Senator Norris as not suitable for discussion on the Adjournment on the grounds of lack of ministerial responsibility.  It was a typographical error that resulted in it being included.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Order of" RHead="Business">
    <Title>Order of Business.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="MickLanigan" hpid="Mr. Lanigan Mr. Lanigan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lanigan</NameTxt>
      <P>It is intended to take Items Nos. 1, 2, 3 and to resume the Fianna Fáil motion.  There are two hours left for that motion this evening.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MauriceManning" hpid="Mr. Manning Mr. Manning">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Manning</NameTxt>
      <P>I would like to make a few comments.  It is some time since we met.  We meet after probably the most damaging and disruptive session in the history of the Seanad.  We are all aware that the standing and perception of the House has been damaged.  Serious questions have been raised about our existence. In those circumstances I, and I think everybody else on this side of the House, would have expected today that the Government side would come in with a clear, defined programme of work for the coming weeks with proposals for change and with clear ideas as to the way in which the Seanad can begin to restore confidence in itself.  To expect that would be the minimum we could ask.</P>
      <P>Unfortunately, the minimum has been too much to expect.  There is no programme of work.  We do not know what is coming up over the coming weeks.  We do not know what legislation we are going to get, when we will get it or whether we will get any legislation at all.  I have to say, in fairness, that this is not the fault of the Government Leader in the House or the Whip.  It is the fault of the Government. Clearly there is no legislation coming up over the coming weeks.  That is what I believe to be the case.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Certainly, there has been a very retrograde step in that this House now is not getting Bills in the way it did in the past or in the way in which the Government initiated various Bills here.  I really want to know whether the Government are serious about the situation in this House, and about giving us a defined programme of work.  Are they serious about using this House in the way in which it was used in the past to start discussion on Bills <Col N="1577" /> here?  I want to know if the Leader of the House is making a serious case to the Government Whip and to the Government about the great disquiet which all of us on this side of the House feel about the current situation.</P>
    <P>I want to raise a number of other matters. First, on the Order Paper at present there are 94 different motions.  Some of these are out of date.  Others have lost their importance.  I believe we have the time &mdash; and there would be the will in this House &mdash; to group some of these motions together for a debate.  Some come under the heading of law and institutional reform.  Others have an agricultural theme.  Very few of these motions were put down lightly.  I would like to see a determined effort to take a number of these in a composite fashion over the coming weeks so that we can at least get through these motions.  There are also a number of private Bills.  Items Nos. 4 and 6 were originally Fine Gael Bills.  I am very keen to see those taken, if possible during the current session, especially when there is such a scarcity of Government work around.  I want clarification on Item No. 9 on the Order Paper &mdash; the order for local elections.  Since the local elections are to be held in June &mdash; which is next month &mdash; must this order be taken before the date for the local elections?  If so, when can we expect it? We will be opposing it strongly and we would like a full debate on the matter.</P>
    <P>There is one other matter and that is the question of the proposed visit to this country of Nelson Mandela.  It was stated by the Taoiseach in the other House that it is his intention that if Mr. Mandella speaks in the Oireachtas he will speak in the other House only.  Why is this House being excluded, as indicated by the Taoiseach? Have any discussions taken place with the Taoiseach and the Leader of the House?  Has the case for a joint sitting been made to the Taoiseach?  Will it be made and will he report to us on this on an ongoing basis?</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatUpton" hpid="Dr. Upton Dr. Upton">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Upton</NameTxt>
      <P>At the outset, may I ask your indulgence to extend my congratulations to my colleague, Senator Costello, on his election to the position <Col N="1578" /> of President of the Association of Secondary Teachers in Ireland.</P>
      <P>If I can take up from where Senator Manning left off I, too, wish to express my alarm at the apparent attitude that we are going to go on the way we were even though the situation seems to have deteriorated quite significantly during the last session.  I, too, regret there is no programme of work laid out or that there is no statement to the effect that we are going to set about doing our business in a more ordered and effective way during this coming session.  May I ask the Leader of the House if he will use his influence to set about initiating the introduction of more Bills in the Seanad so that they can be debated in a more extensive and comprehensive manner than is sometimes possible in the other House?</P>
      <P>May I ask the Leader of the House if he has plans to utilise the undoubted expertise of the membership of the House?  There is a great level of expertise there as evidenced in the case of education where we have as Members of the House two leading figures in education, Senator Costello and Senator O'Toole. Are there any plans to utilise the expertise of Members of this House in relation to culture?  Some of the foremost figures in the area of culture are sitting on seats behind me and, indeed, beside me.  There are others on the other side of the House. There is a very difficult Industrial Relations Bill going through the House. I have beside me an outstanding expert in industrial relations, Senator Harte, not to mention many others.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Will the Leader of the House be prepared to review Standing Orders so that they can be modified and made more appropriate to the needs of a modern Parliament?  For example, will a facility be made available so that topical items can be raised in an immediate and prompt manner, rather than have us here in the House debating things when they have long since gone out of date while we are unable to deal with what is topical?  May I ask the Leader of the House if it would be feasible to allow for more Adjournment debates?  I would have no objection at all to the time which is allowed for Adjournment debates being restricted, nor would I have any objection, broadly <Col N="1579" /> speaking, to the time which is being made available to speakers to contribute being limited.  I am of the school of thought that if you cannot say something in ten or 15 minutes, then perhaps it is not worth saying at all.</P>
    <P>By way of conclusion, may I ask the Leader of the House if it would be possible to reach some sort of agreement or consensus on the introduction and passage of Bills which are effectively non-contentious? There is a series of Bills on the Order Paper.  I can see no reason for this.  I can see no reason why they would not be let progress rapidly through the House.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JoeOToole" hpid="Mr. O'Toole Mr. O'Toole">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Toole</NameTxt>
      <P>On a point of order, there is a process in this House by which the second speaker is traditionally from the largest group.  The third largest group is the Independent group.  In calling on people to pay tribute to Cardinal Ó Fiaich, I notice the Cathaoirleach went to the Labour Party first and I notice he has done so now again.  If that just happened through the course of events, I can live with it, but if it is an indication of the way we mean to continue I intend to object to it.  I would like to be clear on it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanDoherty" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>It is not an indication, Senator.  I looked directly at the Senator a few moments ago in the hope that he would indicate if he wished to speak&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeOToole" hpid="Mr. O'Toole Mr. O'Toole">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Toole</NameTxt>
      <P>I had indicated.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardHourigan" hpid="Mr. Hourigan Mr. Hourigan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hourigan</NameTxt>
      <P>I would like to ask the Leader of the House the position with regard to motions Nos. 72 and 73 on the list of motions.  These items have been on the Order Paper for quite some time and they have now been relegated to being listed with motions.  Motion No. 73 is much more important than anything in Private Members' time.  People concerned with the entire agricultural business will agree with the sentiments expressed in that motion which calls on the Government and the EC to adopt, immediately, appropriate measures to counteract the serious decline in the <Col N="1580" /> income of Irish farmers, particularly those farmers not producing milk for sale.</P>
      <P>Apart from the serious position of farmers up to this year, the experts are now projecting a further decline of 5 to 6 per cent in the income of farmers for the current year.</P>
      <P>In conjunction with that motion I wish to draw attention to motion No. 72 which calls for massive investment on the part of farmers in the whole area of effluent disposal.  I urge the Leader of the House to make arrangements at the earliest possible moment to have these matters debated meaningfully in this House.  If time is allowed to slip by, the position of a very large and important segment of our community, namely, the farming community, will have become dire and disastrous.  It is already developing in that direction.  I am appalled that such little attention has been given to it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeOToole" hpid="Mr. O'Toole Mr. O'Toole">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Toole</NameTxt>
      <P>Just to reiterate the opening remarks of Senator Manning, it is crucial that the Leader of the House presents to the House as soon as possible a programme of legislation which will take us through this term.  In terms of planning, effectiveness and of the operation of the House, it is essential that we have that programme.  I differ from Senator Manning in that the only person I can blame in this matter is the person who presented us with the legislation and that has to be the Leader of the House. I understand there are other pressures on him.  Nevertheless, his duty is to the House and the House needs to know the legislation that will come before it.  The disgracefully small amount of legislation which has been available to the House makes one wonder what we are at.</P>
      <P>In reference to the number of motions at the moment on the Order Paper, we raised the matter early in the last term about extending Private Members' time so that motions on the Order Paper could be cleared.  I would again put it to the Leader of the House that Private Members' time might now be increased to three hours a week rather than three hours a fortnight.  That would allow for the clearing of many of the motions.  I would like a response on that point.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="1581" /> On our last sitting day I raised with the Cathaoirleach the item which is now No. 5 on the Order Paper, that is, an Act to remove the statutory obstacle to free access to secondary education for girls and deleting a discriminatory subsection regarding the education of girls.  I asked the Leader about it and he gave me a commitment he would check it out.  I intend raising this point on every sitting day.  It is disgraceful in these days of equality and progress that such an obscene item should remain in our legislation.</P>
    <P>Finally, I would also like to extend my congratulations to my teacher colleague, Senator Joe Costello, on being elected President of the ASTI.  I wish him well and I look forward to working with him in that capacity.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JoeOReilly" hpid="Mr. O'Reilly Mr. O'Reilly">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Reilly</NameTxt>
      <P>I want to begin by joining in the congratulations to Senator Costello, to wish him well in his new post.  I have no doubt, given his level of competence in so many areas and his commitment to principled politics, that he will be a great addition to the educational debate over the next number of years.</P>
      <P>I share Senator Manning's concern about the lack of coherence in the Government programme for the House. Many people are waiting anxiously for the Seanad to take an initiative in this area but it is not forthcoming.  In that regard there must be a coherent programme of work, an in-depth reform of the Seanad and an immediate signal to the people of Ireland that we are serious about our business; otherwise the people will let us know they no longer want us. I am serious about that.</P>
      <P>In that regard, the question of farm income would provide an immediate start for us to address an important issue of social and economic concern.  As a new Senator, I am disgusted that we do not properly address the socio-economic concerns of our people at a time when milk prices have fallen by 20 per cent.&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TrasHonan" hpid="Mrs. Honan Mrs. Honan">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Honan</NameTxt>
      <P>Speech.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeOReilly" hpid="Mr. O'Reilly Mr. O'Reilly">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Reilly</NameTxt>
      <P>No, it is a reference to the Order of Business.  At a time when <Col N="1582" /> sheep and mutton prices have fallen by 30 per cent. and milk and beef prices have fallen, it is a disgrace that we attempt to conduct the business of the House without addressing this question.  We must develop a coherent programme of legislation, of discussion of socio-economic issues.  We should as a priority have a serious, long debate on the grievous situation of the farming community.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidNorris" hpid="Mr. Norris Mr. Norris">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norris</NameTxt>
      <P>First, I would like to assist the Cathaoirleach in a little bit of clarification about the question of the matter on the Adjournment.  Our relations appear unusually accident prone but I would like to support what the Cathaoirleach said.  This morning I received a courteous letter from the Cathaoirleach indicating precisely what you said, that the matter I had attempted to raise on the Adjournment was ruled out on the grounds of no ministerial responsibility. I was, therefore, rather surprised to hear you including it but not surprised to hear you correct the statement.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanDoherty" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Thank you.  We are in perfect agreement.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidNorris" hpid="Mr. Norris Mr. Norris">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norris</NameTxt>
      <P>Absolutely.  I would like to raise a number of matters.  The first is item No. 4, the Interpretation Bill.  I would like to ask the Leader of the House what is the position at the moment.  I got an undertaking that this would be advanced.  It would increase the prestige of this House if the Government ceased being niggardly and allowed one Bill after 30 years to proceed to fruition and completion from the University benches.</P>
      <P>I would like to ask about item No. 7, the Irish Nationality and Citizenship (Amendment) Bill which, again, is a technical Bill, which has been urged upon me during the recess by the constituent who is directly involved.  It is now for other reasons also a matter of some urgency that this Bill should be looked at.</P>
      <P>I would like to turn to four matters on the Supplement to the Order Paper.  First item No. 7 which states:</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>That Seanad Éireann welcomes the conferring of University status on the University of Limerick and Dublin, <Col N="1583" /> City University and calls on the Government to extend Seanad voting rights to the graduates of the new Universities.</P>
    <P>In the last session I appended my name to motion and I recall protests from Senator Manning at my impertinence in so doing. I wonder why my name is not on it because it was referred to in the House.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MauriceManning" hpid="Mr. Manning Mr. Manning">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Manning</NameTxt>
      <P>On a point of order the Senator's name is on the motion to which he appended it which is item No. 77.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidNorris" hpid="Mr. Norris Mr. Norris">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norris</NameTxt>
      <P>That is splendid.  That is, indeed, good news because I was surprised at the lack of courtesy involved. Most of the university members, if not all, would be glad to join with this and were somewhat surprised that when the question of the constituency which elects us is involved we are not consulted.  I understand a great noise is being bruited about a petition organised by a Member of this House who assured me that she had voted for me in this constituency when she is not even on the electoral register.  I sincerely hope her information will be better the next time.  Perhaps if she consults with me she will have better information for her petition and another name for it.</P>
      <P>In regard to item No. 30, I said I would be raising this.  I do not wish to be bothersome but the question of the Government's response to the European Court ruling is a continuing matter of scandal. I will be addressing a meeting in Copenhagen of international lawyers on this subject and I have every intention of remarking on this in that forum.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Motion No. 32 deals with the IRA and the rail link between Dublin and Belfast. The reason I raise this matter is because the Leader of the House in the last session gave an undertaking that that motion would be taken and a day was actually mentioned in the House for it.  This motion has passed through the Dáil and through a number of councils North and South and is presented at the European Parliament.  I would like the Leader of the House to give us a firm date.  It is important.  That resolution was drafted on the peace train by Members of this <Col N="1584" /> House, including myself, and this is an appropriate place for it.</P>
    <P>Finally, with regard to the question of Nelson Mandela, I would like heartily to concur with what the leader of Fine Gael, Senator Maurice Manning, said.  If the Senator looks at item No. 87, he will find that at the end of the last session I had already put down a motion which I presume should have alerted the Government to the fact that there was concern in the House about this, which says:</P>
    <P>That Seanad Éireann calls upon the Government to arrange a joint session of both Houses of the Oireachtas to be addressed by Mr. Nelson Mandela on the occasion of the conferring upon him of the Freedom of the City of Dublin.</P>
    <P>As a generous person, I invite Senator Manning and the rest of Fine Gael to put their names to that motion and get a discussion on it.  I agree heartily with him that I was concerned at the remarks of Deputy Haughey which appeared to exclude a joint session.  I hope this may be agreed.</P>
    <Speaker pid="RichardConroy" hpid="Professor Conroy Professor Conroy">
      <NameTxt>Professor Conroy</NameTxt>
      <P>On the Order of Business, I would like very much, if I may, as a former secretary of one of the University teaching federations to join in congratulations and good wishes to Senator Costello on his elevation to the very important, crucial, post of President of the ASTI and I take the opportunity of also congratulating and sending best wishes to Senator O'Toole on his election to the secretaryship.  It is a great tribute to the individuals concerned and I think they will carry out the duties very well. Their many contributions to the debates here have always been interesting and effective.  We on this side of the House might not necessarily always agree with them entirely but we would all agree that they have been very impressive and major Members of this House.  We are very proud of their further progress.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DanNeville" hpid="Mr. Neville Mr. Neville">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Neville</NameTxt>
      <P>I would like to join in the congratulations to Senator Joe Costello and to wish him well for the future.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I understand that the First Stage of the Limerick Market Trustees Bill was taken <Col N="1585" /> in this House some time ago and has been introduced in Dáil Éireann.  I understand the Bill it must be taken between seven and 14 days.  I ask the Leader of the House if he intends placing the Bill on the Order Paper for next week and if he would confirm that my information is correct, that it must be taken between seven and 14 days.</P>
    <P>I also ask the Leader of the House if, as a matter of urgency, he would allow a two hour debate within the next two weeks on the serious situation that has developed in our custodial service.</P>
    <P>I accept and fully support that the law of the land must be upheld in our prisons and that no unjust treatment must take place but I believe at present there is a movement to discredit our prison service.</P>
    <P>It is time we asked why people are in prison.  I accept that many people are in prison who should not be there.  There should be alternatives to prisons and we have motion 79, on the Order Paper to deal with this.  I will say that many people are in prison because they have committed murder, because they are rapists or are child molesters or have robbed with violence.  There is a movement now to romanticise the situation.  We must not allow this.  Many of the persons in prison have created a lot of suffering for many people.  The whole situation should be put in proper context.  Therefore, I ask the Leader of the House to allow a two hour debate on the serious situation that has developed over the past several months, highlighted by the crisis in the past few days.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JohnMurphy2" hpid="Professor Murphy Professor Murphy">
      <NameTxt>Professor Murphy</NameTxt>
      <P>I want to associate myself with the criticisms that have been made as to the continued unsatisfactory nature of the ordering of business.  I support Senator Manning in expressing concern, which indeed is the responsibility of all of us, about the padded-out nature of the Supplement to the Order Paper and the need to streamline that.  I support Senator Upton in arguing that there should be some way of bringing before us matters of topicality and urgency other than under the emergency Standing Orders.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Ba mhaith liomsa chomh maith a <Col N="1586" /> ghradam nua a threaslú leis an Seanadóir Joe Costello.</P>
    <P>Among the items that we could be usefully debating under the heading of urgent topical interest is the question of extradition, on which considerable public and political interest has been focused since we last met and which seems to be the subject of a civilised difference of opinion between the partners in Government, which makes it a very appropriate topic for us to debate here.  I might put that to the Leader of the House, that time should be made available to discuss our existing extradition arrangements, whether they are satisfactory or otherwise. After all, there is very little we can do about the unification of Germany. Whether Seanad Éireann agrees or disagrees, Germany is going to be unified but there is a great deal we can do about curing the malaise of extradition.  The cure lies in our own hands.</P>
    <Speaker pid="TrasHonan" hpid="Mrs. Honan Mrs. Honan">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Honan</NameTxt>
      <P>Just for the record of the House because Senator Upton made reference in his address about matters on the Adjournment, on the last day this House sat, Senator Costello was given time by the Cathaoirleach, for a matter on the Adjournment to the Minister for Education on St. Aidan's Christian Brothers' School at Whitehall.  When the House adjourned to take the motion on the Adjournment, Senator Costello was missing and we had a Minister here present.  Senator Costello, by being missing and the Cathaoirleach or Leas-Chathaoirleach not being in the Seanad, I had the great honour again of taking the Chair for two minutes and it was I who adjourned the House.  At least Senator Costello in not turning up gave me the chance of adjourning the House.</P>
      <P>Having put on the record the fact that he was missing for his Adjournment motion, I would like to congratulate Senator Costello and Senator O'Toole on their positions in such extraordinarily important bodies.</P>
      <P>A Chathaoirligh, during Senator Norris's contribution you said your relations with him were perfect.  If your relationship is perfect at the moment or in past weeks, a Chathaoirligh, I would hate to be around when you become enemies.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1587" />
    <Speaker pid="SeanDoherty" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator Honan, you misunderstood the definition I put on &ldquo;relationship&rdquo;.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryJackman" hpid="Mrs. Jackman Mrs. Jackman">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Jackman</NameTxt>
      <P>While we are on educational matters, I would like to extend to Senator Costello, as a fellow ASTI member, my congratulations on his new position as president of the ASTI.  I hope educational matters will come to the fore in the Seanad, which have not been discussed very much since August.</P>
      <P>I want to talk about Item No. 77.  I am surprised at the little bout of temper displayed here today by Senator David Norris about this petition.  The petition from the 50 people who are here behind me with 1,000 signatures shows that the young people of Ireland certainly look towards the Seanad as a House of the Oireachtas in which there can be an input.  I see nothing wrong with them bringing 1,000 signatures to Dublin to put pressure on the Government to ensure that the committee I asked for and which has been agreed to would be set up immediately to ensure that the franchise would be extended, not just to the University of Limerick.  May I say the initiative came from the University of Limerick who formed an action committee called LUSAG &mdash; Limerick University Seanad Action Group.  Surely we should be applauding those young people for taking that initiative, for travelling to Dublin, for taking the interest in coming to see the working of the Seanad, to see obviously that there are over 90 motions on the Order Paper that we have not addressed.  I do not know what we have been doing here.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I hope that today the Leader of the House will agree to the meeting of the five group leaders to select that committee in order to speed up the process of extending that franchise, not just to Dublin and Limerick but also to other third level appropriate institutions.  It should be done in a spirit of support, not of acrimony.  I am putting a question mark on whether Senator David Norris is stepping in or stepping out of the motion because his name is in but I had thought <Col N="1588" /> I had full all-party support for this and I am hopeful that I have.</P>
    <Speaker pid="DavidNorris" hpid="Mr. Norris Mr. Norris">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norris</NameTxt>
      <P>You did not ask for it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryJackman" hpid="Mrs. Jackman Mrs. Jackman">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Jackman</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not think it is a question of asking.  It is a question of seeing that representation is totally out of balance when you think in terms of a small Trinity electorate with three representatives&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanDoherty" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>We cannot debate that now.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryJackman" hpid="Mrs. Jackman Mrs. Jackman">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Jackman</NameTxt>
      <P>And the huge NUI electorate with just three.  I hope the Dublin City University and the University of Limerick plus the other third level institutions will be represented&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanDoherty" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>We are entering into a debate on that now.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryJackman" hpid="Mrs. Jackman Mrs. Jackman">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Jackman</NameTxt>
      <P>&mdash;&mdash;to ensure that we debate issues of education and youth and various other issues in which they would be interested.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TomFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Fitzgerald Mr. Fitzgerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Fitzgerald</NameTxt>
      <P>Ba mhaith liom a fháil amach an bhfuil aon scéala agat mar gheall ar an gcóras aistríucháin don Seanad.  Cheapas féin go riabh geallúint faighte againn go mbeadh sé againn anseo sa Seanad tar éis na Cásca.</P>
      <P>I want to ask the Cathaoirleach about the instantaneous translation of the Irish language.  I thought it was promised it would be installed after Easter.  I am slightly hard of hearing and I did not realise until the other day that we do not have an amplification system here for Senators.  I must say on a personal basis I find it very difficult from time to time to hear other Senators.  Perhaps that matter could be looked into as well.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ShaneRoss" hpid="Mr. Ross Mr. Ross">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Ross</NameTxt>
      <P>I would like, first of all, to support fully what Senator Manning said but perhaps not in quite such a reasonable and moderate fashion.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>First, it should be acknowledged by everybody in this House that we stand at a very low point in public esteem due to the catastrophic events towards the end of last term.  It would have been helpful <Col N="1589" /> if the Leader of the House had come back to us at the beginning of this term and made some effort to present a constructive programme and give a new meaning to the Seanad.  I do not think the Leader of the House or whoever he takes his instructions from when he introduces business has put any effort into that so far.</P>
    <P>This Order Paper is a collection of the fag end of the business of the last session. There is nothing new on it except Item No. 1 which will take about one minute to go through.  There is nothing new on it and there is nothing constructive on it. I made this plea before: if he is serious and if the other side of the House is serious about the Seanad, which I doubt, the first thing I would ask the Leader of the House to do is to accept discussion of Private Members' Bills, from this side of the House.  The Government have nothing to fear from discussion of such Bills but apparently they have had to be refused and have been refused up to now. Certainly Senator Murphy and others on the Independent benches would like to introduce amendments to the Extradition Act of 1965 and of 1987.</P>
    <P>Because the issue of extradition was first raised in this House in 1982 and continued in this House up until recently when it was introduced in the other House in 1987, it is appropriate that it should be debated, discussed and thrashed out here in the form of a relevant Bill.  The truth of the matter is that although the Opposition and the Independents have the time to introduce motions, their effect is meaningless. What we would like to have is the time to introduce Bills which could be discussed and which, if enacted, would come into law and if not enacted would be voted down by the Government for good reasons.  If the Leader of the House is serious about this House &mdash; and I doubt if anybody on that side of the House is serious about this House any longer &mdash; he might give us that particular privilege and we might be able to produce some constructive things.</P>
    <Speaker pid="TrasHonan" hpid="Mrs. Honan Mrs. Honan">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Honan</NameTxt>
      <P>Withdraw that remark.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1590" />
    <Speaker pid="ShaneRoss" hpid="Mr. Ross Mr. Ross">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Ross</NameTxt>
      <P>I will not withdraw that remark.  Certainly not.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TrasHonan" hpid="Mrs. Honan Mrs. Honan">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Honan</NameTxt>
      <P>On a point of order.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanDoherty" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>There is no such thing in the circumstances.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TrasHonan" hpid="Mrs. Honan Mrs. Honan">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Honan</NameTxt>
      <P>I am a former Cathaoirleach. Sorry a Chathaoirligh, there is such a thing.  He has made a statement that he is now convinced that nobody in this House, nobody a Chathaoirligh, is serious about Seanad Éireann.  That is a very serious statement to make.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanDoherty" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>It is a political comment and he may believe it to be true.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ShaneRoss" hpid="Mr. Ross Mr. Ross">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Ross</NameTxt>
      <P>I should correct Senator Honan and say that I thought nobody on that side of the House was serious about this.  I did not apply it to this side of the House.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TrasHonan" hpid="Mrs. Honan Mrs. Honan">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Honan</NameTxt>
      <P>His comment&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanDoherty" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator Ross, without interruption.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ShaneRoss" hpid="Mr. Ross Mr. Ross">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Ross</NameTxt>
      <P>Finally, I would like to ask the Leader of the House if he could tell us when we are going to get the Companies Bill back which started in this House.  Perhaps he could monitor it and tell us at what stage it is in the Dáil?  It started in this House in 1987; it is now 1990 and obviously it will come back here.  He might use his influence to see that it comes back here quickly, goes through and becomes law as soon as possible.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BattOKeeffe" hpid="Mr. O'Keeffe Mr. O'Keeffe">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Keeffe</NameTxt>
      <P>I want just to make an observation on the Order of Business.  I want, in particular, to take up one point made by Senator Murphy, who has now left the Chamber, that was the unsatisfactory nature of the Order of Business. Today we have had something like 13 to 15 speakers on the Order of Business.  I recall that on the first day Seanad Éireann sat, there was a desire on all sides of the House that we would steamline the Order of Business and get down to the proper business of this House.  I would make <Col N="1591" /> the point that in order to improve the situation <i>vis-à-vis</i> the Order of Business the Whips arranged to meet once a week so that business could be ordered.  I would suggest to you, a Chathaoirligh, and, indeed, to the Whips on all sides that we have now spoken for an hour on the Order of Business thereby wasting valuable time for discussing a very important Bill.  Could I suggest to the Whips that in future when they sit down to order the business members of their respective parties or alliances could convey to them the problems they see forthcoming so that we could cut down the delaying tactics and the utter nonsense that goes on here from time to time in relation to the Order of Business so that individual speakers may get publicity for themselves.  If all Senators on both sides of the House are serious they will take up this suggestion. It is not appropriate that people who have Whips operating for them can come in here and act independently even after agreement has been reached on the Order of Business.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MylesStaunton" hpid="Mr. Staunton Mr. Staunton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Staunton</NameTxt>
      <P>First, I would like to congratulate my colleague, Senator Joe Costello, on his appointment as Secretary of ASTI.  I wish him well in that post.  I have no doubt he will do a very good job.</P>
      <P>I find myself in considerable sympathy with the sentiments expressed by Senator O'Keeffe.  I had not intended speaking on that specific issue but now that he has spoken I can support him fully.  There should be closer liaison between the Whips of the various groups in this House.  It is now 3.30 p.m.; business started at 2.30 p.m. and this is one of the Houses of Parliament.  It is understandable that for the first few minutes tributes were paid to the memory of the late Cardinal Ó Fiaich.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>It is also a fact that if we go back to when this House was elected last year and the days on which it sat an entirely inordinate amount of time has been spent on what is termed the Order of Business. It is a vehicle for speeches and for points of views to be expressed, of antagonism to issues and all kinds of things but it is carried to an unreasonable extent.  There is enormous scope for a tightening up of <Col N="1592" /> the procedure but that depends on the goodwill of all the Members of this House to recognise that if we are to function coherently and effectively we need less semantics and more business and more getting down to things at an earlier time then we have been doing.  I support the Senator's views fully in that regard.</P>
    <P>What I had got up to say was something different.  I think, a Chathaoirligh, you have got to get to grips with these motions.  If you take this Order Paper that is put in front of us, this House is under all kinds of threats at present for all kinds of reasons.  If you look at this Order Paper at the present time there are 94 non-Governmental motions and, of these 52 were put down in the year 1989. We are now out in May 1990 and I think, if the House is to have any relevance, you have got to get to grips with these issues, a Chathaoirligh, expedite them, knock heads together if necessary and get a composite motion that could embrace five or six of each of these things and bring that issue up to date.  I think there is a credibility problem if we do not as a House do so.  It is ludicrous.  If you look, for example, at motion No. 45, which refers to the establishment&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    <Speaker pid="DavidNorris" hpid="Mr. Norris Mr. Norris">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norris</NameTxt>
      <P>Could I ask if the Senator is expediting or delaying the business?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanDoherty" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator Staunton without interruption.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MylesStaunton" hpid="Mr. Staunton Mr. Staunton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Staunton</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not abuse my function in this House and I wish Seantor Norris would allow me to speak.  I speak perhaps 5 per cent as much time as he does in this House during the Order of Business.</P>
      <P>In relation to motion No. 45, as an example, a Chathaoirligh, there is a desire to establish a committee of foreign affairs and in that motion it gives notice of a briefing to take place in the Philippines by somebody called de la Toma which was to take place on Tuesday, 28 November 1989.  We are now in May 1990 and it is quite irrelevant.  I do not think any commercial organisation could function as we are purporting to function in this issue.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>May I say, as an aside, the fact that on <Col N="1593" /> all of these motions there is such a huge concern about foreign policy issues, relating both to European Community and other issues, again begs the question on this issue of a foreign affairs committee, which, if established, would mean that there would not be a fraction of the necessity for the numbers of motions that are being put down in this specific area.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JoeCostelloLAB" hpid="Mr. Costello Mr. Costello">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Costello</NameTxt>
      <P>I would like to thank all the Senators from both sides of the House who offered their congratulations and made complimentary remarks in relation to my appointment as President of the ASTI.  I hope during my term of office that I will be able to make some contribution to education and particularly here in the House.  I would also like to thank Senator Tras Honan for her congratulations, even though she did condemn me with a certain degree of faint praise by then raising the question of my absence&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TrasHonan" hpid="Mrs. Honan Mrs. Honan">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Honan</NameTxt>
      <P>I meant the congratulations.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeCostelloLAB" hpid="Mr. Costello Mr. Costello">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Costello</NameTxt>
      <P>I note the congratulations and I am very thankful for them, Senator Honan.  I would like to explain my absence and I apologise for it.  I am very sorry I was not here but the reason was that the debate in the House collapsed about four hours in advance of the time appointed.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TrasHonan" hpid="Mrs. Honan Mrs. Honan">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Honan</NameTxt>
      <P>That is not right.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeCostelloLAB" hpid="Mr. Costello Mr. Costello">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Costello</NameTxt>
      <P>It continued to 4 p.m. or 4.30 p.m.  I was in the House at 1 o'clock. I think it says something about the ordering of business here: if it cannot be seen that a matter is going to take up the full length of time, perhaps we are not organising the business properly.  I must say I am very sorry I was not here and I apologise.  However, I did think I had a number of hours' space at the time.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>On the Order of Business, I want to refer to Items Nos. 41, 48 and 50 the Labour Party have on the Order Paper in relation to prisons, deaths in prisons, prison conditions and so on.  I raised this issue on a number of occasions.  We have, as I have pointed out, traversed Europe, <Col N="1594" /> we have gone from Central Europe to Hong Kong and from the Middle East to South Africa on issues we have debated, but we have not yet debated an issue of local, indeed national importance, and that is our prison system.</P>
    <P>We have a tremendous amount of trouble there.  It comes up on a regular basis.  We move from crisis to crisis.  What I would like to do is to request the Leader of the House that either at this time because of the most recent developments which were of an extremely serious nature and because of the possibility of similar developments, certainly the potentiality for similar developments occurring in the prisons, he would allow statements to be made by each of the groups represented in the House; or, alternatively, that he would set a time aside next week for a debate on the issue.</P>
    <P>I note the Minister for Justice has stated that both the visiting committee reports and the annual prison report for 1988 is going to be published on Friday, so perhaps it would be a suitable time then for the Leader of the House to make some time available at our sitting next week for a debate on this matter, which is of considerable national importance.  I would certainly welcome a statement by Senator Lanigan on that matter.</P>
    <P>May I lend my support to items Nos. 7 and 77, which have been raised, particularly by Senators Jackman and Neville, in relation to the extension of the franchise, again in the context of the Seanad elections in regard to the universities and the other third level institutions. I think it is extremely important that we should have as wide a base and as wide a franchise as possible in that area of election.  I would welcome an opportunity for that matter to be debated also.</P>
    <P>Finally, I would like to mention the question of the ordering of business in the House.  I think greater recognition could be given by the Leader of the House to the motions being put down.  I stopped putting motions on the Order of Business because the Leader of the House indicated they are not going to be debated.  I am at present preparing a Bill on the prisons, which I think is long overdue. If I am going to be told there is no <Col N="1595" /> possibility of that Bill being allowed to be debated, again I am wasting my time. I think it is important for the status and the authority of the House that legislation is allowed to be initiated in this House. We have had one Bill in the House in the last term that was initiated through the House but we have not had any Private Members' Bill.  I would ask the Leader of the House to consider seriously looking again at the ordering of business in terms of the motions and particularly the legislation that could be introduced here by Private Members because there is a very considerable degree of expertise in the House and it should not be wasted.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PaddyMcGowan" hpid="Mr. McGowan Mr. McGowan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGowan</NameTxt>
      <P>For the record, on the last sitting day Senator Costello had a motion on the Adjournment of the House and the House waited for more than 20 minutes for the Senator to turn up.  I would have expected the Senator to apologise to the House without any comment because the House waited.  It was discourteous of the Senator to keep the House sitting and now he comes in and complains about the procedure in the House.  I would have felt that the Senator owed more to the House than to be critical at this point.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeCostelloLAB" hpid="Mr. Costello Mr. Costello">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Costello</NameTxt>
      <P>May I clarify that?  The Order of Business stated that the last item prior to the Adjournment would cease either at 4 o'clock or at 4.30 p.m. That was the Order of Business that was written down and presented to me.  What was I to expect except that the Adjournment would take place then?  I arrived a 1 o'clock.  I was there a good three hours prior to the Adjournment.  Therefore, while I apologise for not being there.  I think I have a very good reason as well to explain myself.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MickLanigan" hpid="Mr. Lanigan Mr. Lanigan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lanigan</NameTxt>
      <P>On the last point, I do not think it is enough just to say that because something is written in the Order of Business and because discussions on a Bill breaks down in the House that that is an excuse for a Senator who has asked to address the House not being present. All Senators are supposed to be in the <Col N="1596" /> House at all times or in the vicinity of the House to take any debate.</P>
      <P>However, I would like before I get into the specifics of the questions on the Order of Business to deal with a few general points because I think it is necessary that they be dealt with.  The opinion seems to be going out from here that there is no business being done in this House and that this House is not being operated in a business-like manner.</P>
      <P>Just to put the record straight, I would like to remind the House of the Dáil Bills that have been passed by Seanad Éireann and I will go no further back than November 1989: The Children Bill, 1989; Prohibition of Incitement to Hatred Bill, 1988; The Údarás na Gaeltachta (Amendment) Bill, 1989; Trustees Savings Bank Bill, 1989; Video Recordings Bill, 1987; Appropriation Bill, 1989; Bord Glas Bill, 1989; Decimal Currency Bill, 1990; Building Control Bill, 1984, B &amp; I Line Bill, 1990; Derelict Sites Bill, 1989; Social Welfare Bill, 1990, Defence (Amendment) Bill, 1990 and the Dún Laoghaire Harbour Bill, 1989. Seanad Bills passed by Seanad Éireann since November, 1989 were: Criminal Justice (Forensic Evidence) Bill, 1989, Local Government (Provisional Order (Confirmation) Bill, 1989, International Carriage of Goods by Road Bill, 1990, Marine Institute Bill, 1989.  Seanad Bills passed by Seanad Éireann in the House: International Carriage of Goods Bill and the Marine Institute Bill.</P>
      <P>We have gone through a series of Private Members' motions.  It was stated by one of the speakers that we did not deal with anything topical or anything of an Irish nature, that we seem to deal with foreign matters a lot.  That is quite true, but we did have debates on Private Members non-party motions on Cambodia, on democracy in Eastern Europe, the Middle East, Oireachtas reform, overseas aid, Arigna, tourism, South Africa, overseas development aid, storm and flood damage, amendment of the Constitution and the homeless.  There were Government motions passed on bovine diseases levies, the NESC report, Ireland and the European Community, health contribution regulations and the wintertime order.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="1597" /> That would indicate that there has been a lot of work done in this House over the past number of months.  Indeed, I would suggest that more Bills have been put through this House, even though we do seem to be in a certain amount of disorder at times.  I do not want it to go out from this House day after day that there is no work being done here.  It seems to me the media are being manipulated on the Order of Business day after day to ensure that the word gets out that this House is not doing its work.  The work is being done in this House on a regular basis.</P>
    <P>There have been criticisms of the ordering of business.  The ordering of business is the ordering of business for the day in question; it is not a general ordering of business for months in advance.  Having said that, the Whips for the first time, on my initiative and with the help of the other leaders, have set up a formal Whips meeting on every Thursday morning.  Unfortunately, this meeting has not been attended by one of the groups in the House who have been most vociferous in coming in here and complaining about the Order of Business for the day.  The University or Independents group &mdash; I am not too sure which they are or whom they represent as a group &mdash; do not attend the Whips meetings, so, therefore, it is very difficult for us&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    <Speaker pid="DavidNorris" hpid="Mr. Norris Mr. Norris">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norris</NameTxt>
      <P>I think it is&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanDoherty" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>The Leader of the House, without interruption.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MickLanigan" hpid="Mr. Lanigan Mr. Lanigan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lanigan</NameTxt>
      <P>I want to put on the record of the House certain things that have never been put on the record before and it is time they were put on the record because&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidNorris" hpid="Mr. Norris Mr. Norris">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norris</NameTxt>
      <P>It is you&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MickLanigan" hpid="Mr. Lanigan Mr. Lanigan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lanigan</NameTxt>
      <P>Otherwise, this question will come up day after day and we will have this type of disruption.  There is no problem for me in answering questions which are of a specific nature and I will attempt at all times to give as accurate a description of the facts as is possible on the day but when people jump up here on the Order of Business and ask me a <Col N="1598" /> question I cannot immediately answer it. I have to get the information and I come back as soon as I can with the information when it is available.  Senator Manning started off today on a very positive note when he suggested that the 94 motions on the Supplementary Order Paper are, infact, a nonsense.  There should be an amalgamation of a lot of these.  If the leaders get together we could do a chopping job on that.  The unfortunate part about it is that we could do the chopping job on it and the next week the person who has the motion on the Order Paper could come back and ask that it be replaced on the Order Paper, because it is up to each individual Senator to ask to have a motion on the Order Paper.  I do not think we can take these off, but if there was agreement in the House it would address many of the problems. Questions were asked &mdash; motion 72 and 73 &mdash; by Senator Hourigan on farm incomes and disease eradication &mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardHourigan" hpid="Mr. Hourigan Mr. Hourigan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hourigan</NameTxt>
      <P>Sorry, correction.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MickLanigan" hpid="Mr. Lanigan Mr. Lanigan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lanigan</NameTxt>
      <P>Effluent, sorry.  There was an amalgam of questions &mdash; motions 41, 48 and 50 &mdash; on prison reform raised by Senator Costello.  If these were all put together it would make more sense. Instead of putting down, day after day, individual motions it would be easier for us to deal with these motions more urgently than they have been dealt with up to the present.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>On the question of business, we will have business and tomorrow morning the Whip will be able to tell you that among the Bills coming up in the very near future &mdash; and when I say &ldquo;in the very near future&rdquo; I have no doubt that it will be next week, although we will not be able to take the whole lot of them next week &mdash; are the Planning and Development (No. 2) Bill and the Firearms and Offensive Weapons Bill.  There is a Turf Development Bill and there are a number of other Bills that are in the pipeline that will be coming up within the next few weeks.  However, I am not going to get up here on a daily basis on the Order of Business and give a programme of legislation that I do not know anything about on the day.  I can give a general <Col N="1599" /> hint as to what is coming up but it is up to the Whips after that to say what the Order of Business will be for the next week.</P>
    <P>The question of Private Bills has been raised again and again.  I am waiting for confirmation as to the status of these Bills.  In one case it is a matter of the Government waiting for the Bills Office to get the actual wording of Senator Norris on the Interpretation Bill.  The Criminal Justice (Abolition of Death Penalty) Bill, as everybody knows, will be before both Houses of the Oireachtas very shortly.  There is no question or doubt about that.</P>
    <P>On the question of a joint sitting, I have no doubt that it is intended that a joint sitting of both Houses will be held but that it will be held in the other House. When I say that I have not read the Taoiseach's statement yet on that matter and I will confirm that for the House tomorrow morning, but I have no doubt that is what is intended.</P>
    <P>On topical items to be raised &mdash; again that is not a matter for me; it is a matter for another group.  We extended the Private Members' time for the Labour group so that they would be able to address themselves on a reasonable basis to matters they wanted to raise.  At any stage when there was a request made to me to extend Private Members' time or to have a debate on motions I have always agreed if it were at all possible.  We have extended the time beyond the three hour limit in the House in this session.  Agreement or consensus on why non-contentious Bills should be debated &mdash; I would go along with that but I will talk with the leaders of the groups on that matter.  We are talking about a committee system really such as they have in the other House; that a select committee would sit and go through Committee and Report Stages on these Bills.  I am not too sure exactly what is intended, but it would seems as if Committee and Report Stages would be taken from the House to a select committee of the House but not in the House.</P>
    <P>I am not taking these matters in order; I am taking them in the order in which the papers are coming before me. <Col N="1600" /> Senator Ross mentioned his doubts about the commitment of Members of this side of the House to the House.  I can guarantee that the vast majority of people in this House as a whole are committed to this House.  It was an unfortunate statement by Senator Ross, no doubt looking for a certain amount of publicity which he may indubitably get.  I am not too sure whether he will or not.  I do not think he was being serious in his comments but it sounded like a good thing to say on the day.  That is about as much as I could say about it.</P>
    <P>As regards the Companies Act, we have had that Bill for a long long time. It is now in the other House and until it comes out of the other House there is nothing we can do about it.</P>
    <P>Senator O'Reilly mentioned farm incomes, lack of support and so forth. That comes into the same area as Senator Hourigan's item.  If Senator Hourigan and Senator O'Reilly feel these are the matters of prime urgency for their side they can bring it in as their motion.  I think they are the next group to have a Private Members' motion, so if that is the order of priority they want it is in their ball court to take it in that manner.</P>
    <P>On the question raised by a number of speakers &mdash; Senator Jackman, Senator Manning, Senator Norris, Senator Costello, Senator O'Toole &mdash; of the extension of the franchise to Limerick and the University of Dublin, I see no problem in the University&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    <Speaker pid="DavidNorris" hpid="Mr. Norris Mr. Norris">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norris</NameTxt>
      <P>The City of Dublin University.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MickLanigan" hpid="Mr. Lanigan Mr. Lanigan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lanigan</NameTxt>
      <P>The City of Dublin University &mdash; I am dyslexic as well as everything else &mdash; it was agreed that the leaders would meet and set up a sub-committee to deal with this matter.  I think that can be done immediately.  However, I would say that cannot do anything but make a recommendation which will be given to the Government because this House cannot legislate for the extension of the franchise.  It has to be a matter for both Houses of the Oireachtas but the idea of a committee sitting to look into the implications and the application of the <Col N="1601" /> extension of the franchise can be done immediately.</P>
      <P>Bhí cheist ag an Seanadóir Fitzgerald mar gheall ar an chóras aistriúcháin.  Ní fheadar an bhfuil aon freagra agat, a Chathaoirligh, mar níl aon freagra agam ag an bpointe seo.</P>
      <P>Item No. 5 on the Order Paper was raised by Senator O'Toole, the question of discrimination against girls.  I will raise that matter with the Minister concerned and report back to him.</P>
      <P>On the question asked about the Limerick Markets Bill, that matter has to come before the House within the next 14 days &mdash; well, 14 days from the time it went through the Dáil, so it will have to come back in here next week.  I think those were the main points.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MauriceManning" hpid="Mr. Manning Mr. Manning">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Manning</NameTxt>
      <P>Item No. 9?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MickLanigan" hpid="Mr. Lanigan Mr. Lanigan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lanigan</NameTxt>
      <P>I will report back to the House tomorrow morning on that matter.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidNorris" hpid="Mr. Norris Mr. Norris">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norris</NameTxt>
      <P>Item No. 7?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MickLanigan" hpid="Mr. Lanigan Mr. Lanigan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lanigan</NameTxt>
      <P>I mentioned the fact that there were certain Private Members' Bills and that there were difficulties with one, the Interpretation Bill.  I will check and see what is the status of the Irish Nationality and Citizenship (Amendment) Bill with the Minister.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidNorris" hpid="Mr. Norris Mr. Norris">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norris</NameTxt>
      <P>In regard to the motion on the supplementary Order Paper concerning the Belfast-Dublin rail link, a date was set and then interrupted by certain events.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MickLanigan" hpid="Mr. Lanigan Mr. Lanigan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lanigan</NameTxt>
      <P>We can discuss that again with the Whips tomorrow morning and see when it can get back on the Order Paper.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatUpton" hpid="Dr. Upton Dr. Upton">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Upton</NameTxt>
      <P>In regard to having two or three Adjournment matters instead of one as at present, is that agreed?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanDoherty" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>That is a matter for the Committee on Procedure and Privileges. Is the Order of Business agreed?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MickLanigan" hpid="Mr. Lanigan Mr. Lanigan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lanigan</NameTxt>
      <P>Since people have been <Col N="1602" /> expressing concern about timing and about times, it is intended that the Horse Breeding Bill, 1985, would proceed no longer than 5.30 p.m. and that item No. 3, the Larceny Bill, would be taken at 5.30 p.m. to conclude at 6.30 p.m.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeCostelloLAB" hpid="Mr. Costello Mr. Costello">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Costello</NameTxt>
      <P>I would like to ask if a statement would be allowed or whether there would be a debate on the prisons, which was a matter I raised on Item 44.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MickLanigan" hpid="Mr. Lanigan Mr. Lanigan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lanigan</NameTxt>
      <P>I will talk to the Senator later about that.</P>
      <P>Order of Business agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Statute of Limitations (Amendment)" RHead="Bill, 1990: Order for Second Stage">
    <Title>Statute of Limitations (Amendment) Bill, 1990: Order for Second Stage.</Title>
    <P>Bill entitled an Act to amend and extend the Statute of Limitations, 1957, by making new provision as regards the date from which the period of limitation is to run in respect of actions for certain personal injuries, and to amend related provisions in other statutes, and to provide for other matters connected therewith.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MickLanigan" hpid="Mr. Lanigan Mr. Lanigan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lanigan</NameTxt>
      <P>I move: &ldquo;That the Second Stage be taken on Wednesday, 16 May 1990.&rdquo;</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Horse Breeding Bill, 1985: Second" RHead="Stage (Resumed) and Subsequent Stages">
    <Title>Horse Breeding Bill, 1985: Second Stage (Resumed) and Subsequent Stages.</Title>
    <P>Question again proposed: &ldquo;That the Bill be now read a Second Time.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="TomRaftery" hpid="Professor Raftery Professor Raftery">
      <NameTxt>Professor Raftery</NameTxt>
      <P>The purpose of this Bill, as was pointed out by the Minister when we last discussed it, was to repeal the Horse Breeding Act of 1934.  That is an Act which required all non-thoroughbred stallions to be licensed and the Minister felt there was no need for this any longer.  In fact, he pointed out that Bord na gCapall had recommended that we get rid of licensing of stallions.  I would point out, however, that Bord na gCapall is now gone out of existence and there is coming into being, if not already in being, a Horse Advisory Committee.  I think <Col N="1603" /> it would have been appropriate had the Minister delayed the repeal of this licensing of stallions until we get the opinion of the Horse Advisory Committee.</P>
      <P>The situation, of course, with regard to horses has changed radically since stallion licensing was introduced back in 1934. The total number of horses has dropped from about half a million down to relatively low levels in this country today. In fact, although we have a very great reputation overseas for horses, particularly for sport horses, we do not in terms of numbers match up with many of our continental counterparts.  The reputation of our horses, of course, is based primarily upon the Irish draught horse, and the Irish draught mare crossed with thoroughbred stallions gives probably the foremost sport horse in the world today.</P>
      <P>Ireland produces at present time about 3,500 foals per annum.  That used to be about 10,000 or more not so very long ago.  By contrast, the Germans produce 35,000 foals of this category; Holland about 10,500; France about 8,500; Belgium about 4,500; Denmark about 4,000 and we &mdash; the ones who have supplied most of the stock for this breeding &mdash; are back, as I say to about 3,500 foals per annum.  The time has come to have a new look at the horse breeding sector particularly in the light of the fact that it could play, and I am confident will play, an important part in an alternative enterprise on farms when farmers are having such difficulties with traditional enterprises due to surpluses.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I note a number of points in the national programme for the development and servicing of the non-thoroughbred horse industry.  In this it said that the basic objective is to increase the output and improve the quality of horses for use in the many types of equine sports and activities but particularly showjumping. I think everybody would have to agree with that objective.  It goes on to say that the production of Irish sport horses has been traditional rather than based on strictly commercial criteria.  That is quite true indeed.  It goes on further to point out how it might be a very useful alternative farm enterprise.  It makes the point, and rightly so, that we have a <Col N="1604" /> dwindling number of horses, and particularly Irish draught mares, and something has got to be done because this cross between the Irish draught mare and the thoroughbred stallion is giving, as I said probably the best sport horse in the world today.</P>
    <P>As an attempt to encourage the breeding of pure bred Irish draughts I am glad to note that the Government introduced a £400 grant to be paid on each pure bred Irish draught foal.  The purpose of this was to try to bridge the income gap.  In other words, the value of the Irish draught foal was about £400 less than the value of the Irish draught thoroughbred cross.  I am delighted that this new grant is coming in in 1990 and hopefully it will do much to encourage the breeding of Irish draught mares to Irish draught stallions with the view to building up the stock of Irish draught mares in the country.</P>
    <P>I am pleased, too, to note that 1989 saw the introduction of the headage payments for horses, or that horses became eligible for headage payments &mdash; I am referring, of course, to the non-thoroughbred sector here again &mdash; and the grants are available for housing, the storage of feed, the storage of manure and so on for all horses in the disadvantaged areas other than the thoroughbred horses.</P>
    <P>With regard to the Irish horse register, the report says that accurate identification of individual animals and complete and accurate recording and registration of pedigree and performance data are fundamental to successful breed improvement, marketing and trade.  That is absolutely true.  The only way we can make any real progress in probing the genetic merit of these sport horses is to have accurate data and performance testing of the animals.  That is the way we must proceed.  The Minister has, therefore, decided that the register will be maintained by the Department of Agriculture and Food.  The authenticity of the register will be maintained it says, and the standards and procedures will be followed for the registration and documentation of horses which will allow the register to be approved under proposed <Col N="1605" /> European community zootechnical legislation. I can only agree that this is a move in the right direction.</P>
    <P>It goes further on and says that the requirement that these grants that were referred to already, will be paid only on registered animals and this will have the beneficial effect of encouraging people to have the horses on the register.  In that way we will get a reliable data base, which can be used as the source of information for improving our breeding stock.  Of course it will cover not only Irish draught horses but also Connemara ponies etc. All of these are important in the sport horse breeding industry.  There are very many other things that I would like to see in relation to this important industry, which must be promoted.  A lot has to be done in relation to the preparation of selling, marketing our horses properly and so on.</P>
    <P>I must refer to the proposed EC legislation to enable intra-Community trade in horses, which is being drafted.  The object of it is to liberalise trade in horses between Community countries and not only horses but horse semen, horse embryos and so on.  We must take a great interest in this since we are very large exporters of horses.</P>
    <P>In relation to these proposals I want to make a few points.  The first proposal provides for the approximation of the animal health protection rules to be applied in the member states.  The removal of the existing disparaties will help to foster intra-Community trade in horses.  That is important for us because we are interested in exporting horses.  It will help to foster intra-Community trade in horses while keeping certain animal health requirements designed to avoid the spread of disease.  It will also provide for Community arrangements in respect of imports of horses from third countries. That is a rather important one which I will come back to later.</P>
    <P>The second proposal lays down basic rules intended to remove disparaties in member states due to differences in policy as regards breeding and rearing. That has some significance to, but is probably not as important as the first proposal. This proposal covers horses, their embryos, semen, ova, etc. in a single <Col N="1606" /> market.  It aims to prevent unfair practices and to liberalise the trade in horses, in semen, ova and embryos.</P>
    <P>The third proposal in the directive aims to remove disparaties in equestrian competition rules which may constitute a barrier to intra-Community trade in horses. Equestrian competitions include horses, horse racing, show jumping, eventing, dressage and events for horse drawn vehicles.  This is a step in the right direction, too, that any disparaties which would cause any difficulties in intra-Communtiy trade should be removed.</P>
    <P>One final point has to do with at lest one disease that is found in two Community countries but which is, fortunately, not found in Britain and Ireland.  I refer to African horse sickness. This is an infectious disease of equines transmitted by biting midges and flies and very often has a high fatality rate.  As things stand, we know this has occurred in Spain and Portugal.  We have to ensure, whatever about intra-Community trade, that we try to avoid getting that kind of disease into our country when it has such a high fatality rate and indeed would damage the good reputation of the health of our horses.</P>
    <P>I am also glad to note that the Minister intends that Teagasc would take initiatives to develop the advisory, educational and training programmes to improve the fertility breeding merit, feeding and husbandry of Irish sport horses.  This is a very important aspect of the business if it is to become a successful alternative farm enterprise.  He also has ambitions to improve the breaking, training and marketing of horses.  This is equally important because there is no point in having a good product if you do not market it properly and present it to the best of your ability to prospective buyers. He goes on to refer to the needs for farriery.  Of course we all know that the village blacksmith is largely extinct today and, therefore, there is need to have a supply of people who are capable of looking after horses in that respect.</P>
    <P>In general I support the aims of the Minister in trying to build up the sport horse industry in the non-thoroughbred sector.  The aims are most laudable.  With regard to getting rid of the necessity for <Col N="1607" /> licensing horses, I do not shed any tears about that I can assure the Minister but I would have thought it would be appropriate if the Minister had withheld making that decision until the new Horse Advisory Committee had a chance to give their view on the matter.</P>
    <Speaker pid="RichardHourigan" hpid="Mr. Hourigan Mr. Hourigan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hourigan</NameTxt>
      <P>I, too, support the measures which this Bill suggests should be introduced.  On the point that Senator Raftery raised perhaps it might have been more appropriate if the final recommendations from the horse committee, which I understand are working in conjunction with the Minister's office, had made their report.  It would have been more appropriate to have that final recommendation available before introducing a Bill.  The Bill basically suggests the abolition of the licensing of the non-thoroughbred horse, the sport horse.  I believe, provided matters relating to confirmation etc. are fully taken into account that this is a better approach than just licensing.</P>
      <P>When we talk about the half bred or sport horse very often it is not quite clear what we are talking about.  The half bred horse, ideally, is a cross between the Irish draught and the thoroughbred.  Some experts will, in fact, suggest that it is desirable that the dam be the Irish draught and that the sire be the thoroughbred. That is a matter of opinion but we are basically talking about that cross.  I particularly mention this factor because Irish draught mares are becoming a scarce commodity.  I believe there should be more concentration in this whole area to ensure that we do not run out of the reservoir of Irish draught basic breeding stock.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>As a country we have earned for ourselves an excellent reputation in the whole area of sport horses.  I believe that we can develop that reputation even further and gain handsomely from it in the context of the export of horses at very competitive prices.  There is no doubt that we need to have performance testing introduced.  Conformation is very important but we must find out what the progeny of any sire are capable of doing if we are to continue the usage of that sire <Col N="1608" />&mdash; indeed the same applies to the dam &mdash; which would be responsible for the production of a lot more horses per annum or on a per time basis.  We have established a position here in Ireland as a producer of very high class horses for use in various sports and leisure activities throughout the world.</P>
    <P>Senator Raftery referred to the slot that the half bred horse could fill in the context of farming.  This is a very important matter because with the need for diversification in farming and with the worsening position of many areas of farming activities and the restrictions on the production of milk, cereals and lesser return from beef, the Irish half bred can fill a very important need for our country and for many individual farmers.  In former times most farmers kept horses and these horses performed the dual activity of doing farm work and producing some top class hunting-type animals when they were crossed with the thoroughbred.  At present, with the introduction of mechanisation of various sorts horses are no longer used for farm work. Therefore, the person keeping horses does so entirely from the point of view of gaining a return from the production of a good sport horse which he hopes to sell either on the home market or abroad after a few years, either trained or untrained.</P>
    <P>In the past 20 years or so the main outlet for our horses has been show jumping, eventing, dressage, showing at various shows and hunting.  We must remember while we have produced a lot of excellent horses that are top of any league, we have also produced, and continue to do so, very second and third rate animals.  We must be mindful of that and must, so far as we can, reduce the balance of the very good horse in terms of quality and performance or increase the number of horses that are good and performing well and reduce the number that do not. We have produced many horses which have no value apart from their slaughter value and this is a very limited value.  I suggest we need much in-depth screening in our whole breeding process and we must do whatever is required to achieve effective selection and correct breeding.</P>
    <P>The Irish draught mare is the basis <Col N="1609" /> on which we can build an efficient sport industry.  The animal today is a lighter boned animal but not that much lighter boned than the mares of 20 or 30 years ago when the pulling of machines and so on was such a vital factor.  In the past there was a lot of haphazard breeding. The farmer just brought his mare to the nearest stallion for convenience purposes and it did not really matter what the progeny was.  There was no real planning put into the exercise.  In the years gone by the overall horse population was such that sufficient numbers resulted from the total breeding programme to encourage foreign buyers to visit and purchase young stock from farmers directly here in Ireland in most cases or through a third party.  There were many more horses so by the law of averages the likelihood was that the buyer, who was very precise about what he or she wanted, would find the animal he wanted to buy.  Now, with fewer horses we have to be more vigilant in ensuring that we produce the right type of animal.  We must, as a general criterion, ensure that we produce the sort of horses that will sell on the foreign market in particular.  We must be mindful of the fact that many mistakes have been made in the past and we must learn by those mistakes.  We have produced some outstanding animals and we must emulate the pattern that led to that situation.</P>
    <P>I believe a central agency is a very appropriate body where we can have the maximum professional approach available to all breeders.  That kind of objective would require a high degree of professional approach by all breeders. It must be spearheaded by a dynamic, central authority which would include the whole area of registration, dissemination of information, organising good marketing in a professional and sophisticated manner and generally acting as a meaningful organising and co-ordinating body. Teagasc has become a good deal more interested in recent years in the horse industry than it had been previously.  This is a good thing.  In the past there was no formalised programme to deal with horse breeding, particularly the area of the sport horse.  Consideration should be given to group activities in the context of producing the best type of basic stock <Col N="1610" /> where a number of farmers are selected very carefully and are given attractive incentives to engage in a breeding programme under the aegis of some type of a central authority.  This group should be a pilot group to set the headlines and let all concerned be aware of what can be done by careful and proper breeding.</P>
    <P>In the past sales centres have not been up to the required standard for people with top class horses.  Some improvements have been made and we have some recognised sales centres.  Further improvements need to be made.  We must remember that we are talking in the context of a three or four year old half bred horse that may or may not have been broken or trained.  The cost of producing that animal and keeping it to that age is quite considerable.  For that reason, bearing in mind that it is just as cheap to keep a very good horse as one that is not so good, no stone should be left unturned by all agencies concerned to assist and to guide the farmer, producer or breeder in producing the best horse possible.  In very highly organised sales centres in Germany in recent years $10,000 approximately was the average price while here in Ireland at national sales centres the average price would be approximately $2,000.  That is for three year old geldings while the average price for fillies of the same age would be in the region of $1,500.  Regrettably at more rural and less well known centres prices would even be lower than that.</P>
    <P>It is absolutely essential that we have good sales centres so that breeders will know that good horses are available.  If they know that they will come and pay good prices.  Very often a highly priced horse in Germany may be no better than the horse worth one-fifth the price in Ireland.  The reason for the low prices in Ireland is the lack of competition.  We must develop a greater and a more sophisticated mentality in the Irish mind towards the whole area of selling and the methods to be adopted.  To illustrate the poor marketing structure, many of the very best horses are sold privately here for between $5,000 and $10,000 at the three year old stage.  These are top figures: we are not talking about average prices.  This kind of horse would make <Col N="1611" /> much more if presented better and sold at a centre where there was the appropriate level of demand.</P>
    <P>The prospects for the production and sale of the Irish sport horse are good.  We have earned a very high reputation.  In the last Olympic Games, for example, a high percentage of the horses that won were Irish bred.  In a lot of very prestigious events throughout the world such as showjumping the horses were of Irish origin.  A good reputation in this field of horse breeding is very important.  We have a need for a greater promotions effort at this time.  I am quite satisfied that the Irish draught society and all the various breeding agencies in conjunction with the Minister and his Department, can do a marvellous job provided the entire effort is co-ordinated and that it is not left in the hands of a few people who, by trial and error, will tackle the job.</P>
    <P>The breeding of ponies is very important. We have a great demand on the home market for ponies and, quite frankly, there are not enough to meet the demand at present.  High-class ponies are scarce.</P>
    <P>One thing that is often forgotten is the genetic factor in the production of any sport horse.  We talk about an Irish draught mare but unless there is that spirited dimension in that animal we will never produce a top level showjumper or top level horse in any other category. I go back again to performance testing which is very very important.  Many of our heavily boned half bred mares that are not registered would provide an excellent basic stock.  They are being used as appendage mares and are not registered as draught mares and indeed are producing very good horses.  This should be borne in mind because we do not have the pure bred draught mare in sufficient numbers to produce horses at the moment to meet the demand that could be there.</P>
    <P>One of the factors I would like to emphasise is height.  We must endeavour to produce a substantially sized animal. The height of a stallion is something like 15 and three-quarter hands and up to 16 and three-quarters.  The mares are 15 and a quarter hands, a hand being four inches. <Col N="1612" /> If one were to go into all the finer points and the aspects to look for in a horse such as the head, shoulders, neck and front, the hindquarters, legs, action and so on one could talk a long time about it and I have no intention of doing that.</P>
    <P>The Irish half-bred horse, or more correctly speaking, the non-thoroughbred has enjoyed the reputation throughout the world of being the best, excelling in all areas of work and sport.  The Irish half-bred is well renowned for its stamina, temperament, ability and agility.  These very outstanding qualities and others stem largely and almost exclusively, from the Irish draught.  Jumping ability is a very important basic quality.  The potential is there, provided proper care is taken to ensure that there is good selection in the breeding programme and that we do not start breeding from second-rate animals.  I am also of the view that abolition of the licensing of half-bred stallions will not in any way lower our level of horse quality but, in fact, is something that should be replaced very positively by a very thorough and strict form of selection.</P>
    <P>In conclusion, I support the measures proposed in the Bill and express the view that it would have been better had the final recommendations of this advisory committee been available to the Minister before the Bill was introduced.</P>
    <Speaker pid="RichardConroy" hpid="Professor Conroy Professor Conroy">
      <NameTxt>Professor Conroy</NameTxt>
      <P>I am very pleased, as Government spokesman in the Upper House on Industry and Commerce, to make a very brief contribution.  In many ways we have given a lot of lip service to the horse industry but we have not really regarded it as an industry.  We are doing so now.  It is all to the credit of the Minister and his colleagues for giving agriculture its proper status as an agribusiness. In business one has to compete. If there is one area in the agricultural business in which we can and should compete it is in the horse industry.  We have an established reputation there.  Many other countries would be very pleased indeed to have the reputation we have for our horses.  We have the natural advantage of a climate, probably among the best in the world, for the breeding and development of really good horses. <Col N="1613" /> We are in a competitive position also in that with modern air freight and various other methods of transport, we are able to compete in an international market. Our otherwise peripheral position is not the handicap it would be in certain other industries or aspects.  We have not taken that on board fully on a commercial basis. It tends to get mixed up and there are accusations of elitism.</P>
      <P>In the rest of our industries in agriculture, and right through industry and commerce, what has been said of us was that we were right up at the top of the market.  If we are to succeed we must be up at the top of the market in all aspects of our industries.</P>
      <P>I make no apology for coming in very briefly on this industry, although I bow to the vast knowledge of Senator Hourigan and his colleagues on both sides of the House in their individual knowledge of and participation in the horse industry and in its many different aspects.  I think a general change in perception is very badly needed and that is one of the reasons why I welcome this Bill.  It should have been given priority by the Minister and brought before the House.  It is 60 years since the previous Bill was introduced. A lot has happened in that time.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Mention has been made of the changes in scientific knowledge, genetics and blood testing and of the changes in the actual use of the horse.  The position has now changed to a situation which suits us very well indeed.  The market we are competing in now is that of the quality horse and not of the draught horse, which many other countries could probably compete in as well as or far better than us.  It is an international market.  One of our problems is that so many of our better quality horses are being exported at an inappropriate time.  We see this in show jumping where we have the best record in the world in relation to the actual number of horses and mares in the country.  The number of showjumping champions in every country in the world who have Irish blood or breeding is of an astonishingly high percentage.  We talk glibly of how we appreciate the horse industry.  It is really only when we go to Germany, the United States, Canada or France that we find a true appreciation <Col N="1614" /> of the quality and contribution of the Irish horse industry and of the quality of Irish horses.</P>
    <P>In relation to showjumping, we have had this enormous change associated with television, whereby showjumping has become a mass television spectacular watched by tens of millions throughout the world.  I do not think we fully appreciate the contribution to this country generally, and specifically to the Irish horse industry, of having it constantly mentioned that such-and-such a horse, or such-and-such a champion jumper was Irish bred, or the mother of an Irish mare, or an Irish stallion, and so on.  If we were trying it in some other industry we would probably willingly spend millions on promotion to get the sort of thing that we take for granted and pay very little attention to.  In this connection it is a pity that our demonstration team, our Army group of the Blue Huzzars, was abolished. The Government should think very seriously about bringing back some sort of unit, not for any sort of elitism, but because of the tremendous tourist boost it would give in reference to the standing of the Irish horse.  It could have enormous advantages which would far outweigh the expenses involved.</P>
    <P>I am very pleased that this country has so much limestone.  One of the advantages of the limestone which we have in this great central plain of ours is the enormous contribution it makes to the good bone structure of horses.  Again, this is something we take for granted.  We think of milk quotas, the sheep breeding industry, and so on.  We are not all that competitive in those industries.  We do very well.  One area in which, without any doubt, we could do extraordinarily well &mdash; far better than we are doing at present &mdash; is in the horse industry.</P>
    <P>Another advantage of the horse industry is that it is labour intensive.  We are looking for jobs.  In this industry there is tremendous direct employment and a tremendous spin-off and the value-added is enormous compared with any other aspect of agriculture in which we are involved.  There is an open market niche for us.  In other areas we are struggling desperately to find some niche in which this country could compete.  In some ways <Col N="1615" /> we consider the horse industry &mdash; apart from the betting angle, which is great fun &mdash; to be a joke.  We do not realise that the joke is on us rather than the other way round.  It could be very profitable and very effective.  I would like to take the opportunity of paying tribute to the people in the industry at all levels who have often, without a tremendous amount of support or encouragement, made such a success of it.</P>
    <P>I welcome the Bill.  It is a very welcome intervention in the horse industry.  I would like to support it.  I also hope that it is an indication of new thinking within the Department of Agriculture whereby this industry &mdash; our prestige flagship industry &mdash; which can be so competitive and so successful, is given the status it so rightly deserves.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JoeWalsh" hpid="Minister of State at the Department of Agriculture and Food (Mr. Walsh) Minister of State at the Department of Agriculture and Food (Mr. Walsh)">
      <NameTxt>Minister of State at the Department of Agriculture and Food (Mr. Walsh)</NameTxt>
      <P>First, I would like to express my appreciation to the Senators who contributed to the debate on this Bill, Senator Avril Doyle, Senator Raftery, Senator Hourigan and Senator Richard Conroy.  The contributions were unanimous in their positive attitude to this tremendously valuable resource which we have in Ireland and which, regrettably, we tended to neglect over the past few decades.  I take on board totally the points made by Senator Conroy in his most recent contribution that not alone the horse industry itself but the entire image of Ireland was enhanced by the performance of the Irish horse, not only on the Irish team but on international teams.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Only last week I was in Italy promoting the Irish food industry.  One of the people who has become involved in a joint venture with an Irish food company put me to the pin of my collar to talk to him in detail about the Irish horse and, particularly, the pedigrees and the breed, and the cross arrangement and the bone structure of the Irish horse.  His first visit to Ireland was to the Irish Horse Show which is a premier international horse show and, resulting from that and his contacts with the horse industry, a very valuable joint venture was set up in a <Col N="1616" /> totally different and unrelated industry. It is a tremendously valuable asset.</P>
    <P>I want to pay tribute to the participants in the industry because there was not a great deal of money out of the non-thoroughbred horse industry.  Relative to other farm enterprises, for example, the dairy industry, the beef industry or the tillage industry, people stuck with the Irish horse through bad times for only one main reason and that was their love of horses.  There is this symbiotic relationship between Irish people and the Irish horse.  We know how to manage them well.  We know how to handle them.  It is something we are good at.  As an alternative farm enterprise, where we have large tracts of land without sufficient livestock of any kind on them, here is an opportunity which any other country they would grasp eagerly and regard as an obvious area for massive investment and development.</P>
    <P>I am absolutely delighted at this stage to be in a position to help with this development.  I am delighted with the general across the political board positive response to the development of the Irish horse industry and I hope there will be further development.  For example, under the Structural Funds scheme I hope the non-thoroughbred horse industry will be earmarked for further development as an alternative enterprise.  I am giving very considerable support to the improvement of the quality.  Senator Hourigan repeatedly emphasised the importance of quality. There is no use in increasing the actual number of horses.  The quality has to be taken care of and looked after.  We will insist on that.</P>
    <P>Marketing centres were referred to by a number of Senators.  We have a programme for the development of a number of strategically located marketing centres, where there would be proper sales and marketing and proper rewards for the people involved, not alone in the actual sales rings but also opportunities for lunging and for performance, so that people could actually see the movement of the horse and the attributes of the particular animals they are purchasing. That marketing centre development is a part of the whole programme.</P>
    <P>Teagasc is involved in the advice and <Col N="1617" /> the support for the development of the Irish horse industry.  We have at the Kildalton Centre particularly ongoing courses for young farmers and for people interested in a livelihood in the horse industry.  We have very important seminars and symposia.  The response there is absolutely outstanding.  There is an oversupply of people looking for participation in courses.  At the seminars there is always a full house.  The interest is there because this is a traditional industry. We have built up a tremendously important international reputation, but we now have internationally this growing development of outdoor sports.  There is no better outdoor sport nowadays than horse riding in the countryside.  We are in a position to make available the very best and most suited animal as a sport horse here in Ireland.</P>
    <P>The development of farriery was mentioned. We remember a couple of decades ago at almost every crossroads there was the blacksmith but it is not a feature of Irish life any more.  We had people in various towns and villages who were gainfully employed in making and repairing the tackle but that is gone as a feature of Irish life, as well.  We now have courses for all those activities coming onstream to be in tune and in line with the development of this industry.</P>
    <P>I certainly have tremendous hope for the Irish horse industry.  It will be one of our major successes over the next few years.  I expect when the figures become available for 1990, which is the first year of the development programme in which grant-aid is paid and the marketing centres are available, that we will see a dramatic improvement not alone in the numbers but in the quality as well.</P>
    <P>In response to a number of items raised by Senator Avril Doyle in her very interesting and very informative contribution on 15 February, the Senator particularly referred to EC legislation.  This was also referred to today by Senators.  In line with the general harmonisation of regulations and directives we will be debating and discussing, and eventually agreeing, directives affecting the horse industry.  I want to say that the EC proposals currently under discussion at official level are aimed at generally liberalising trade <Col N="1618" /> within the European Community.  I do not think that Senator Doyle or any of the other Members of this House need be alarmed at the proposals which, as presented by the Commission, are along the lines of previous ones in the livestock breeding and, indeed, other sectors.</P>
    <P>The proposals set out in broad terms the areas on which Community policy is to be agreed but leave the detailed decisions to be settled later under a standing committee procedure.  Issues like criteria for stud book entry will not fall to be decided by the Council of Ministers but will be subject to separate proposals from the Commission to be considered and voted on by member states at official level.  Again, in line with the whole development of the Irish horse industry by consensus, officials at the Department of Agriculture and Food are regularly meeting the practitioners on the ground in the horse industry interests to thrash out with them the best way for the industry to go.  We will continue to do that.  I am glad things are coming along in a very enlightened fashion in that particular area.  There is no question of interfering in the internal arrangements of the stud book organisations, never mind the Department taking them over.  The criteria for recognition will not be unduly onerous or unreasonable.</P>
    <P>I want to assure this House that the negotiations on the present proposals are proceeding favourably under our Presidency and from our Irish point of view I am confident our horse industry interests will be adequately safeguarded.  I think we owe it to the industry.  We owe it to the practitioners to ensure that not alone are the interests of the Irish horse industry safeguarded but that under the new directives and regulations they will be enhanced.  I am happy to put on record that the various interests are kept fully informed before each of the meetings and the working parties to make certain that the industry is in tune with the developments that are taking place and that they have an input to them.  As regards the thoroughbred and some other horse industries' ban on artificial breeding, the European Commission has now altered its proposals to recognise this fact, following strong pressure from Ireland and <Col N="1619" /> a number of other member states.  In other words, whatever a particular stud would require at present will be honoured under future European Community regulations.</P>
    <P>Since I last spoke on this Bill we received a formal request from the Oireachtas Joint Committee on Secondary Legislation for information on these proposals.  A detailed reply was sent to them very shortly after that, in fact about five or six weeks ago.  If anybody else is interested in that detailed reply on the draft proposal for Council directives on animal health conditions governing inter-community trade in and import from third countries of live equity it is available for them because that is in line with keeping all interests informed as to what is going on.</P>
    <P>Senator Doyle was quite critical of and had quite a lot to say about the stallion registration system.  She rested her case on examples of stallions which had not been accepted for registration but which are said to be producing good stock.  She referred to the dissatisfaction with inspectors' decisions and said that the Department of Agriculture and Food, and myself, stand indicted if the system continues any longer.  Yet Senator Doyle went on to tell me what is already well known &mdash; that if I canvass opinions from various interests I will get as many different views.  Everybody knows that there are various interests in the horse industry and they stick rigidly to their particular interest in some aspects of the industry. They are quite notorious in championing their own particular area of interest.  To get a consensus is quite difficult.  In fact Senator Doyle knows as well as I do that this divergence of opinion on most issues is a feature of the horse breeding industry. We are great individuals.  In fact, that is a very good trait in many respects. Senator Doyle concluded by saying that quite often the horse industry should be taken by the &ldquo;scruff of the neck&rdquo; and saved from itself.  I agree totally with her. The system we have has, by and large, stood the test of time and nobody has yet come up with a better system.  I want to record my appreciation of the sterling work of the inspectors who, year after <Col N="1620" /> year, perform a thankless task with courage and integrity.  It is not an easy job by any means to please everybody.</P>
    <P>Senator Doyle urged caution in relation to the use of continental warm bloods and the impact this could have on our horse industry.  I will be happy to be guided by the horse advisory committee on this and on the use of outside breeds and crosses generally.  We have to bear in mind, however, that we will be open to imports of all breeds and types of horses when the European Community legislation is enacted.  Ultimately breeders must decide for themselves.  The horse advisory committee is made up of nationally and internationally known individuals and practitioners in the horse industry.  Most of them were nominated by the various organisations.  They are meeting regularly under the chairmanship of a senior Department inspector and are doing a tremendous job in bringing the views of the industry to the attention of the Department and making sure that there is a streamlined, comprehensive development programme for the development of the non-thoroughbred horse industry.</P>
    <P>In relation to national hunt sires, the reason that the progeny of national hunt sires and Irish horse registered mares are not eligible for entry to the Irish horse register is simply because such sires are not being offered for registration at annual inspections.</P>
    <P>Senator Doyle made a plea for headage payments to be available all over the country.  I would like to point out that the purpose of headage payments is to provide an income supplement to maintain the population in disadvantaged rural areas.  They are not a breeding aid as such.  Personally, I believe they are a very important aid to the development of the horse industry.  Not alone is there £400 headage on each pure-bred registered Irish draught foal but there is a very substantial headage available to the non-thoroughbred horse industry in disadvantaged areas.  I am extremely hopeful that the area of the country which will be designated as disadvantaged will be substantially increased in the next few months.  I would expect that almost three-quarters of the country will be designated <Col N="1621" /> as disadvantaged and that that will be announced later on this summer, so that headage will apply to most of the country.</P>
    <P>With regard to the national programme for the non-thoroughbred horse industry, it should be remembered that responsibility for this sector reverted to the Department of Agriculture only recently.  That is why I suggested earlier that this year will show the first fruits of that programme.  We have indications already that there is a very positive response from the industry itself around the country.  Now that the advisory committee on the horse industry is up and running I expect to receive sound, constructive suggestions to build on what we already have.  I am prepared to consider its recommendations carefully and to act on them where appropriate.</P>
    <P>Senator Doyle made great play of the fact that the Equestrian Federation of Ireland will be making a proposal to the next meeting of the horse advisory committee for a return to stallion licensing.  I understand the EFI did indeed make a proposal for a system for registering all stallions and their progeny.  I await the committee's formal recommendations on this matter.  This is a far cry, however, from a return to statutory licensing.  The recommendations were for registration.</P>
    <P>In conclusion, I repeat that there has been no concerted pressure whatsoever from any sector of the industry for a return to the old stallion licensing system. We are now in a different era.  The demands of the industry are totally different from those which necessitated the provisions of the 1934 Act.  Senator Hourigan, Senator Conroy and Senator Raftery made those points, that the draught horse was at one time a draught horse for taking loads of beer and pulling ploughs and harrows.  That day is gone.  We now want a spirited animal to be of benefit for showjumping, for dressage, for three-day eventing and for general sport.  Riding schools are now a tremendous feature of rural Ireland.  Under the alternative enterprise programme and the agri-tourism programme they will be encouraged even more.  The point has been made that the market itself will quickly weed out what cannot be sold.  I agree with that <Col N="1622" /> wholeheartedly.  That is why encouragement rather than compulsion should be our guide.  Accordingly, I commend this Bill to abolish stallion licensing under the 1934 Act once more to this House.</P>
    <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
    <P>Agreed to take remaining Stages today.</P>
    <P>Bill put through Committee, reported without amendment, received for final consideration and passed.</P>
    <P>
      <i>Sitting suspended at 5 p.m. and resumed at 5.30 p.m.</i>
    </P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Larceny Bill, 1989:" RHead="Report Stage">
    <Title>Larceny Bill, 1989: Report Stage.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHoward" hpid="Acting Chairman (Mr. Howard) Acting Chairman (Mr. Howard)">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman (Mr. Howard)</NameTxt>
      <P>Before Report Stage commences, I would like to remind the House that Members may speak only once on Report Stage except for the proposer of an amendment who has the right of reply.  I call Senator Costello to move amendment No. 1.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeCostelloLAB" hpid="Mr. Costello Mr. Costello">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Costello</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 1:</P>
      <P>In page 3, between lines 24 and 25 to insert the following:</P>
      <P>.&mdash;Section 29 of the Principal Act is hereby amended by the deletion in subsection (3) of the words `or any solicitation, persuasion, promise or threat offered or made to any person whereby to move or induce such person to commit or permit the abominable crime of buggery, either with mankind or with any animal'.</P>
      <P>I welcome the Minister here today.  I am delighted that he, and not the junior Minister, is here in the Seanad.  Certainly, I am delighted the Minister has been here for the previous debates and is here again to finalise the debate here in the Seanad.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The reason for the amendment is that this legislation &mdash; the Larceny Bill &mdash; which I agree with in principle, has quite a number of shortcomings.  We have a golden opportunity here to amend the <Col N="1623" /> Principal Act, which is the 1916 Larceny Act.  That Act is very considerably outdated in many respects.  What I am identifying here is one area where the Act is inadequate and that is in relation to the crime, as it is called there, &ldquo;committing or permitting the abominable crime of buggery&rdquo; and so on.  That is outdated, I state, because we have decisions in the European Court of Human Rights taken as a result of the Dudgeon case and the Norris case &mdash; one of our own Senators here &mdash; in relation to decriminalising homosexuality. In that respect we do not as yet have legislation enabling us to introduce a protection for people of homosexual orientation.</P>
    <P>This legislation contains a provision, as is outlined there, whereby such a person can be penalised and can be criminalised. We have an opportunity of eliminating that particular section from the legislation at this time.  I do not know if the Minister is going to introduce legislation in relation to both the Norris and Dudgeon cases but certainly it would be useful if we could eliminate the existing provision which criminalises homosexual acts.  We should, in fact, be thinking in terms of decriminalisation of homosexual acts.  My complaint about this Bill is that so much of it is merely tinkering with the 1916 Act when we have an opportunity to introduce some worthwhile amendments. This, I believe, is one.</P>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Acting Chairman Acting Chairman">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman</NameTxt>
      <P>Is the amendment seconded?  If the amendment is not seconded, it lapses.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DanNeville" hpid="Mr. Neville Mr. Neville">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Neville</NameTxt>
      <P>I second it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Acting Chairman Acting Chairman">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman</NameTxt>
      <P>The amendment is seconded.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RayBurke" hpid="Minister for Justice (Mr. Burke) Raphael P. Burke">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Justice (Mr. Burke)</NameTxt>
      <P>The amendment is opposed now for the same reason as it was on Committee Stage. The primary reason is that it falls outside the scope of the Government's aim in introducing the Bill.  That aim was clearly defined by me on Second Stage as being to update the law on receiving stolen property and in possession of burglarious <Col N="1624" /> implements and only the minimum consequential changes arising out of any of the proposals provided for in the Bill. Any other changes which may be required in the Larceny Act, 1916, have been deferred until the Law Reform Commission gives us its detailed report on how those changes should be made.  I would be the first to acknowledge that the Larceny Act needs a comprehensive overhaul.  However, I see no point in making a change now on the lines suggested by the Senator in the absence of an overall plan for such an overhaul such as can be expected when the commission makes its report.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeCostelloLAB" hpid="Mr. Costello Mr. Costello">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Costello</NameTxt>
      <P>I am pleased to hear the Minister say that he expects the matter to be dealt with by the Law Reform Commission. Of course, this Bill as it stands has scant regard for the recommendations of the Law Reform Commission in relation to the Larceny Act and how it should be revamped.  That is one of the major faults of the Bill, that it does not in any way comprehensively address the problems in the 1916 Act that need to be updated.  When the Minister says he is thinking of a major overhaul or a comprehensive overhaul, could he in winding up give us a clear indication of what he means by this?  Is the Minister talking about this particular area of legislation, namely, the finding of the European Court in relation to the criminalisation of homosexual acts, or is he talking about the 1916 Act?  Is the Minister talking about a major overhaul of the 1916 Act?  I think both are required, but what I am trying to seek here is a worthwhile amendment: that in the interim, before we get a comprehensive overhaul &mdash; and we do not know how long we will be waiting for that &mdash; at least we should seek to eliminate the problems and the offence which is enshrined in this Act against people of homosexual orientation.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The Minister can easily delete this section by accepting the amendment and that will not in any way interfere with the introduction of a comprehensive piece of legislation on the matter in question.  It would be a worthwhile change.  We may <Col N="1625" /> have to wait for years for a comprehensive overhaul of either the 1916 legislation or in relation to the European case, the Norris case.  Senator Norris is here himself.  The Minister could without in any sense interfering with any plans by the Law Reform Commission to update these matters, usefully accept this amendment.</P>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Acting Chairman Acting Chairman">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman</NameTxt>
      <P>Is the amendment withdrawn?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeCostelloLAB" hpid="Mr. Costello Mr. Costello">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Costello</NameTxt>
      <P>No.</P>
      <P>
        <i>Senator Norris rose.</i>
      </P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Acting Chairman Acting Chairman">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman</NameTxt>
      <P>I am afraid, Senator Norris, as I understand it, Senator Costello moved his amendment, the Minister responded and Senator Costello replied.  Since this is Report Stage that is all the discussion we can have on it.  Is the amendment withdrawn?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeCostelloLAB" hpid="Mr. Costello Mr. Costello">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Costello</NameTxt>
      <P>No, the amendment is not withdrawn.  It would be very appropriate, Sir, that Senator Norris would have a very short period to speak on this item.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Acting Chairman Acting Chairman">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman</NameTxt>
      <P>We are not on Committee Stage; we are on Report Stage.  I am advised that these are the rules of the House and I am afraid I have to apply them.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidNorris" hpid="Mr. Norris Mr. Norris">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norris</NameTxt>
      <P>I would have to accept you ruling, Sir, but may I just make one point?  It is that I was listening to this discussion on the monitor when this point emerged&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Acting Chairman Acting Chairman">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman</NameTxt>
      <P>No, I am afraid really.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidNorris" hpid="Mr. Norris Mr. Norris">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norris</NameTxt>
      <P>In that case I will of course, have to yield, drawing the Minister's attention to the point of misprision of felony which is advisable and I am requesting that he take it into consideration.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Acting Chairman Acting Chairman">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman</NameTxt>
      <P>Is the amendment withdrawn?  The question is &ldquo;That the <Col N="1626" /> amendment be made&rdquo;.  Those in favour say &ldquo;Tá,&rdquo; those against say &ldquo;Níl&rdquo;.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Senators Senators">
      <NameTxt>Senators</NameTxt>
      <P>Tá.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Acting Chairman Acting Chairman">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman</NameTxt>
      <P>I think the question is defeated.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidNorris" hpid="Mr. Norris Mr. Norris">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norris</NameTxt>
      <P>How can you think that since nobody said &ldquo;Níl?&rdquo; May I point out that there is absolutely nobody on the Government side and, therefore, the amendment has to be carried.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RayBurke" hpid="Mr. Burke Mr. Burke">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Burke</NameTxt>
      <P>Could I take the opportunity to answer the question I was asked by the Senator?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Acting Chairman Acting Chairman">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman</NameTxt>
      <P>I understand the Minister can answer the question.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeCostelloLAB" hpid="Mr. Costello Mr. Costello">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Costello</NameTxt>
      <P>Can we take it that the amendment has been put and that the &ldquo;Tás&rdquo; have won the day?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Acting Chairman Acting Chairman">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman</NameTxt>
      <P>My advice is that the Minister has a constitutional right to reply to a question.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeCostelloLAB" hpid="Mr. Costello Mr. Costello">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Costello</NameTxt>
      <P>But already the amendment has been put.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RayBurke" hpid="Mr. Burke Mr. Burke">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Burke</NameTxt>
      <P>The reason I am going to answer the question, and I did not include it in my initial response, is this, I make the point to help the Senators in the discussion of this and in the judgment as to whether they should put it to a vote.  I want to be helpful, and I am particularly trying to be helpful to the point that the Senators have made in view of what I know is their view on a particular issue. I just want to give it as a point of caution for them in their decision as to voting on it.  While their intention is to solve a particular problem as they perceive it, they may be creating a larger problem at that time.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Let me say that one of the reasons the amendment is being opposed is because it does not achieve the desired result that Senator Costello is trying to achieve.  The Senator's amendment would delete the reference to buggery related offences from section 29 (3) of the 1916 Act.  The net effect of that would be that while it <Col N="1627" /> would still be an offence under section 29 to blackmail somebody by threatening to accuse him of, say, rape, which is one of the offences listed at section 29 (3), it would no longer be an offence under that provision to blackmail him by threatening to accuse him of soliciting buggery and I do not think any of us would want to get into that type of situation.  It is my view that it is not a desirable change in the law and I do not really think it is what the Senators wish to achieve.</P>
    <P>It is up to the Senators, obviously, to indicate which way they want to go but I do not think really this is probably the way they want to go and I do not see it as being a desirable change in the law.  For that reason, as I said earlier, in relation to the amendments it was my intention to oppose them for the same reasons as I outlined on Committee Stage.  I am pleased to be able to answer the question that was asked by the Senator.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JoeCostelloLAB" hpid="Mr. Costello Mr. Costello">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Costello</NameTxt>
      <P>The other question I asked, seeing that we have gone past the vote, was in regard to the Law Reform Commission, whether or not the Minister has specific plans to update this law and could he give us a timescale on this? What exactly are we facing?  What are we looking forward to?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RayBurke" hpid="Mr. Burke Mr. Burke">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Burke</NameTxt>
      <P>I cannot give you a timescale on it just like this this afternoon.  I can give the Senator some information on it through the Leader of the House probably, which would be the most appropriate way.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Acting Chairman Acting Chairman">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman</NameTxt>
      <P>I put the question, &ldquo;That the amendment be made&rdquo;.  The only response I got was &ldquo;Tá.&rdquo;  Therefore, having considered the matter, I think the only option I have is to declare the amendment made.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidNorris" hpid="Mr. Norris Mr. Norris">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norris</NameTxt>
      <P>Hear, hear.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RayBurke" hpid="Mr. Burke Mr. Burke">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Burke</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not want to disagree with the Acting Chairman.  It would not be for me to do that.  I was in the position of answering some points being put forward by the Senator.  Could I suggest to the Acting Chairman that if this line is <Col N="1628" /> taken by the Seanad I am just going to have to go back to the Dáil and start all over again and then come back to you here.  Is it really in the interests of the general public that this Larceny Bill should be delayed by going right back through the whole procedure?  I was trying to be as helpful as I could on it to the Seanad.  I would ask that commonsense would prevail.  I appeal to Senators not to delay the passage of this Bill by what is a technicality, because I will have to go back to basics.  I am not going to accept this amendment for the reason I have given and I would ask for the cooperation of Senators on it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeCostelloLAB" hpid="Mr. Costello Mr. Costello">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Costello</NameTxt>
      <P>Certainly our co-operation has always been forthcoming on these matters.  This amendment was introduced not in any way to stymie or to cause trouble; it was introduced with the best will in the world to improve a piece of legislation that has got very considerable shortcomings and to update a situation that has changed dramatically since that legislation, the Larceny Act of 1960, was passed.  What we are seeking is a very reasonable amendment.</P>
      <P>I would be very agreeable if that amendment had been accepted in the principle that it was offered &mdash; we were not hung up on the precise wording of the amendment &mdash; but that the Minister would go back and address the issue behind it, which I have outlined, and that would have been the approach to it but, as I see it, we have now voted on the matter.  The Acting Chairman put the question, he put the amendment and there were three &ldquo;Tá's&rdquo; and there was no &ldquo;Níl&rdquo;; so, as I see it, our hands are tied on the matter.  That is where it stands.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RayBurke" hpid="Mr. Burke Mr. Burke">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Burke</NameTxt>
      <P>People may be open to blackmail&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeCostelloLAB" hpid="Mr. Costello Mr. Costello">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Costello</NameTxt>
      <P>I certainly&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Acting Chairman Acting Chairman">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not think we can have a discussion on the matter now. The question has been put, the response I got was &ldquo;Tá,&rdquo; there was no &ldquo;Níl&rdquo;, that I could hear at least, and therefore I have to declare the question carried.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="1629" /> Amendment declared carried.</P>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Acting Chairman Acting Chairman">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman</NameTxt>
      <P>We move now to amendments Nos. 2 and 3.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PaddyMcGowan" hpid="Mr. McGowan Mr. McGowan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGowan</NameTxt>
      <P>May I raise a question of procedure at this point?  I listened to the debate on the monitor here.  I listened to the Acting Chairman putting the question and I listened to the &ldquo;Tás&rdquo; and the Minister came in at that stage to question, so it was a question and answer situation. I do not think it is proper for the Acting Chairman to decide in the circumstances that the amendment is agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Acting Chairman Acting Chairman">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman</NameTxt>
      <P>I have been faced with the situation, I have been faced with this dilemma and I have ruled as I think correctly in the matter.  I have referred to Standing Orders.  I am now calling amendments Nos. 2 and 3.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TonyMcKenna" hpid="Mr. McKenna Mr. McKenna">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McKenna</NameTxt>
      <P>Before we move on&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Acting Chairman Acting Chairman">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman</NameTxt>
      <P>We have now disposed of that amendment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TonyMcKenna" hpid="Mr. McKenna Mr. McKenna">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McKenna</NameTxt>
      <P>On a point of order, I was listening on the monitor.  Your exact words were &ldquo;I think the amendment is defeated&rdquo;.  How could you decide that? There is a question of timing here &mdash; the whole issue &mdash; in relation to whether the Minister was answering the question that was being put or what exactly was the position.  Under the circumstances I think we are entitled to review that decision.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidNorris" hpid="Mr. Norris Mr. Norris">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norris</NameTxt>
      <P>I notice that people from the Government side stand up, too, to make a point in the debate.  If this is going to continue I will want to speak as well. You have made your ruling, Sir.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Acting Chairman Acting Chairman">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman</NameTxt>
      <P>To clarify the situation for Senator McKenna, Senator Costello moved his amendment, the Minister responded to the amendment, Senator Costello then replied to the amendment.  I put, as I am required by Standing Order, the amendment at that stage and the only response was &ldquo;Tá&rdquo;.  I now declare, as I have already declared, the amendment made and I am moving <Col N="1630" /> on to amendments Nos. 2 and 3.  I want to say they are related and that they be discussed together.  I now call on Senator Costello to move amendment No. 2.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeCostelloLAB" hpid="Mr. Costello Mr. Costello">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Costello</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 2:</P>
      <P>In page 3, line 31, to delete &ldquo;14 years or to a fine or both&rdquo; and to insert &ldquo;seven years or to a fine or to community service or to make compensation to any injured party or to any two of these penalties&rdquo;.</P>
      <P>I regard that as almost the most reasonable amendment that one could come up with and the most appropriate amendment in the circumstances we have seen over the past few days.  The reason I state is that if you look at any legislation it prescribes for the Judiciary two penalties &mdash; a term of imprisonment or a fine.  We have gone a long way down the road since those days and indeed in the present circumstances there are just two specified. In the 1916 Act there are a number of other types of penalties specified like the death penalty, like whipping.  We have got rid of some of the worst forms of sanctions.  What I want to do is to encourage the Judiciary to look into alternative sanctions.  Why should we have a piece of legislation, a criminal Bill simply limited to two sanctions?  Should we not focus the attention of the Judiciary on the range of sanctions that are available?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>This is an eminently reasonable amendment.  We have a situation where our prisons are grossly overcrowded as we saw over the weekend.  That has been admitted.  It has been detailed by the visiting committees in the report which we will see on Friday, I believe, but which has been leaked publicly.  But this has not just taken place this year; it has taken place over a period of time.  Why put people into an already overcrowded prison if we can explore various alternatives? The Whitaker committee of inquiry into the prisons in 1985 made one of its several recommendations that prison should be used as last resort.  Why then should it be one of the only two sanctions that are mentioned in this amending legislation, the Larceny Bill of <Col N="1631" /> 1989?  If we are thinking about appropriate developments and alternatives, if we are thinking about rehabilitation, we have an onus as legislators to draw the attention of the Judiciary to what has been developed, to areas like community service orders, which I mention here, to the question of compensation to an injured party, to provide the maximum of options.  I must say I cannot for the life of me see how the Minister could neglect or refuse to take on board this type of amendment which must improve the Bill and must improve the variety of sanctions that are available to a judge.</P>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Acting Chairman Acting Chairman">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman</NameTxt>
      <P>Is the amendment seconded?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidNorris" hpid="Mr. Norris Mr. Norris">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norris</NameTxt>
      <P>I would like to second it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Acting Chairman Acting Chairman">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman</NameTxt>
      <P>I wish to point out that amendments Nos. 2 and 3 are being taken together.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeCostelloLAB" hpid="Mr. Costello Mr. Costello">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Costello</NameTxt>
      <P>Could I object to that, please, on the grounds that amendment No. 3 is the opposite to amendment No. 2?  What amendment No. 3 is doing is worsening, if you like, penalties, whereas amendment No. 2 is giving a range of alternative sanctions.  Amendment No. 3 is in a sense worsening a particular sanction, if I may say so.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Acting Chairman Acting Chairman">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman</NameTxt>
      <P>I am advised that they both relate practically to the same subject matter.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeCostelloLAB" hpid="Mr. Costello Mr. Costello">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Costello</NameTxt>
      <P>If that is your ruling I will accept it, but I still would think that it is an unsatisfactory way of dealing with it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Acting Chairman Acting Chairman">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman</NameTxt>
      <P>We will take them together.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidNorris" hpid="Mr. Norris Mr. Norris">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norris</NameTxt>
      <P>In seconding this amendment I would like to say, first of all, that we are lucky to have a pragmatic Minister for Justice who has shown his capacity to respond to situations and to think imaginatively. I cannot entirely regret the fact that he will now have an opportunity to be pretty pragmatic because it seems that <Col N="1632" /> this Bill will have to go back to the Dáil, and the Minister has said that.  This provides him with the opportunity for further reflection on an amendment like this.  In a way, I am sure the Minister, because he is a very astute parliamentary tactician, will not hold it against me because I spotted the loophole that there were no responses from the Government side of the House, allowing the amendment technically to go through.  Will there be a possibility to comment on the general Bill when it is being put through, to make a comment on that amendment when the Bill is finally passing?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Acting Chairman Acting Chairman">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman</NameTxt>
      <P>On the next Stage.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidNorris" hpid="Mr. Norris Mr. Norris">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norris</NameTxt>
      <P>On the next Stage.  I will reserve any comment which I will have to make in a general sense for that Stage. However, the general point is that we have a pragmatic Minister.  He now has an opportunity, a window of opportunity, to use one of these celebrated cliches, where he can consider other amendments. This seems to me to be a very valuable one because the Minister, I am sure, knows much better than I do what the conditions are like in some of the prisons.  There has to be what amounts almost to an arbitrary system of release when prisoners are piled up at the prison gates and then people have to be dislodged from the system.  I am certainly not blaming this particular Minister for that.  The prison situation has continued for a very long time under various administrations but nobody can doubt whatever that the prison system is an absolute and continuing scandal and a scandal of dangerous proportions and not just with regard to overcrowding and to HIV infection and so on, and the Minister is as aware of those as I am.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>But this is a positive amendment.  It provides for a situation where the overcrowding may be lessened, and is not confined only to that.  I would remind the House, as the House is reminded very frequently &mdash; sometimes in tones of pious hypocrisy, I may say &mdash; that the Constitution of this State declares the Christian and democratic nature of the State. If anybody wants to consider the phrase &ldquo;the Christian and democratic nature of <Col N="1633" /> the State&rdquo; from a philosophers point of view, they will, I think, realise that this could not be more Christian.  It allows for the possibility of positive redemption.  It is not just the punitive attitude towards the penal system; that you punish people, you incarcerate them, that you damage them in revenge for some crime that they have committed, which is a fairly useless approach, in my opinion, but that they should have the opportunity of reparation by community service and perhaps community service in the interest of those whom they have damaged.</P>
    <P>It seems to me that lengthy prison sentences, which have no determinable effect except as a very considerable burden on the taxpayer, are not anything like as good an alternative as having the possibility, in certain circumstances, to impose a sentence of community service under which the person who committed the crime or the felony has the opportunity to learn from contact once again with the community, and perhaps that part of the community which he or she has damaged, to learn the consequences of their crime.  The Minister will be aware, of course, that in some of the Scandinavian countries, for example, people who have been convicted of dangerous crimes or of manslaughter or whatever, are sentenced to community service in hospitals where in casualty wards they are brought directly into confrontation with the results of their misdoings.</P>
    <P>It seems to me that this is a very worthy and proper amendment and, as I say, I am glad the Minister has the opportunity now to reflect, at some leisure perhaps, on this amendment since he has indicated that the Bill will be referred to the Dáil.</P>
    <Speaker pid="DanNeville" hpid="Mr. Neville Mr. Neville">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Neville</NameTxt>
      <P>I would like to comment, first of all, on amendment No. 2 and say that, while I fully agree with the second area of it, I do not accept that the sentence should be reduced from 14 to seven years.  I would like to add to the areas which Senator Costello has in his amendment and include the confiscation of assets, the forfeiture of bail, if further crimes are committed on bail, fines by instalment to allow people pay the fines <Col N="1634" /> rather than serve imprisonment, attachment of income for the same reason, participation in training courses and other areas, which I am sure the Minister can consider.  It is obvious that the present prison situation is in a state of chaos and I believe a dangerous situation has developed because of this.  It is due to overcrowding and a solution to this must be obtained.  The present situation whereby the prisons are overcrowded is creating the difficulties that have obtained over the past few months.</P>
      <P>There is almost a movement on now to discredit the prison service.  We must never forget why people are in prison. They are in prison because they have committed very serious crimes on many occasions.  These people should serve their full sentences, people who have committed murder, rapists, child molesters, people who have committed robbery with violence and so on.  We must not lose sight of the fact that these people are in jail for those offences and we must not forget the pain and suffering they have caused to the families of the victims and in some cases to the victims themselves. I feel that there is almost a tendency to romanticise the situation of the prisoners at the moment.  I think that is very dangerous and for this reason the Minister should look very seriously at the situation and include the suggestions of Senator Costello and myself in his approach to sentencing policy.  I presume both amendments can be put to the House separately.</P>
      <P>With regard to amendment No. 3 I believe the penalty for larceny should be the same as that for receiving stolen property.  Larceny with violence is very traumatic for the victims.  I know victims who have suffered from the effects of violence, of robbery with violence.  Many people in country areas live in fear of people calling during the night.  Those who have experienced it often do not fully recover from the psychological damage. This is especially true in the case of old people.  I believe that the penalty for larceny should equal the penalty for receiving.  In that context I would like to move amendment No. 3.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1635" />
    <Speaker pid="RayBurke" hpid="Mr. Burke Mr. Burke">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Burke</NameTxt>
      <P>These amendments are opposed.  The first amendment in the name of the Labour Party Senators seek to have the maximum sentence provided in the Bill for handling stolen property reduced from 14 years imprisonment to seven years.  This is totally unacceptable. The second amendment in the name of Senator Neville seeks to increase from ten years to 14 years the maximum sentence provided in the Bill for larceny and other related offences.  This is equally unacceptable.</P>
      <P>With regard to the question raised by Senator Costello, the point about the sanction of imprisonment, I want to reiterate what I said in the other House yesterday during the course of my reply to Private Notice Questions.  There is no point in hiding from reality by saying, for example, what we need are not more prisons but more alternatives to prison. There is no point in pretending that the prison population could be drastically and dramatically reduced by means of greater use of alternatives.  Alternatives are used quite extensively in this country. There are over 3,000 persons on alternatives of one kind or another as against 2,000 in custody.  I am specifically examining the scope for further expansion of alternatives at the present.  I have to say that looking at the present prison population, I would be misleading this House if I were to say that alternatives will provide a full answer.</P>
      <P>In relation to the incident that took place last weekend I want to correct a point made by Senator Norris.  It was not an overcrowding within the particular unit.  There was no overcrowding in that unit of the prison.  I am not saying there is not an overcrowded prison population there.  There is and we are trying to do something about it but in the particular section involved that was not overcrowded.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidNorris" hpid="Mr. Norris Mr. Norris">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norris</NameTxt>
      <P>I was speaking about overcrowding generally.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RayBurke" hpid="Mr. Burke Mr. Burke">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Burke</NameTxt>
      <P>I took it the Senator was speaking about the HIV section and the special section for prisoners who cannot be held securely in any other parts of the prison.  On the subject of community <Col N="1636" /> service orders, Senators will have received a copy of the report on the probation and welfare service with statistics for the year 1988 which was published recently.  The report showed that there were over 1,500 referrals for community service work by the courts in 1988 and over 1,200 such orders were made within a 12 month period for the first time.  This represents an increase of 55 per cent on the volume of orders made in 1985 which was the first year of the Act's operation. This bears out what I said during our debate on the Bill on Committee Stage on increasing use by the courts of this form of punishment as opposed to imprisonment for certain types of offences.</P>
      <P>The number of hours of community service work exceeded 130,000, which is equivalent to 70 persons working fulltime for a year.  This results not alone from a higher volume of orders made but also from a rise in the average number of hours specified per order, from just under 80 at the start of the scheme to 120 in 1988.  The maximum number of hours that can be ordered under the scheme is 240 and one in ten orders which were made specified over 200 hours work to be performed.</P>
      <P>In relation to the reference in amendment No. 2 to the payment of compensation, I have nothing to add to the undertaking I gave to the House on Committee Stage to have this whole question of compensation in the context of crime generally, and not just in the limited area of handling stolen property, examined in my Department as resources permit with a view to preparing comprehensive legislative proposals for consideration by the Government.  Senator Neville's amendment No. 3 would destroy the relationship set up by the Bill and indicated by the maximum sentences specified in it between the seriousness with which society views handling on the one hand and simple larceny on the other.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeCostelloLAB" hpid="Mr. Costello Mr. Costello">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Costello</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister in his reply has totally missed the point of the amendment. The function of the amendment is to put into the legislation some of the alternatives that are available at least, I would take on board what Senator Neville says about the scope for further <Col N="1637" /> alternatives.  My point is to ensure that the judge, when looking at an offence under the provisions of the Larceny Act, as it no doubt will be in 1990, will see before him the option of sanctions other than imprisonment or a fine.  In normal circumstances in relation to larceny a fine is not too relevant if the person is unable to pay the fine.  The most relevant sanction is community service.</P>
      <P>I am not trying to question in any sense the alternative or to say that alternatives are not in place.  The probation and welfare service refers to various community service sanctions that are imposed.  The entire function of this amendment is to draw the attention of the judge to the existence of a wider range of sanctions. That is not the point that the Minister addressed.  The Minister has not given me one good reason why there should not be a fuller range of sanctions put in the Bill.  If he can give me one good reason then I will certainly listen to it and, no doubt, withdraw the amendment, but until he does so I see no reason for considering withdrawing the amendment at all.</P>
      <P>With regard to the reduction from 14 years to seven years which he says is totally unacceptable, he has not stated why it is totally unacceptable.  He will be aware no doubt that Dr. Whitaker's commission in 1985 recommended that people should not be detained in prison for a period longer than seven years without their cases being reviewed because after that period of detention they stated that according to surveys that has been done institutionalisation set in, that people became damaged and that it was getting very difficult to have any possibility of reintegration into society.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="1638" /> I am proposing here what is in accordance with the recommendations of the Government commission that was set up to look into the prison system, the section where it recommends alternatives and the reasons for the alternatives.  One of the reasons is in relation to the length of time a person spends in prison, of the dangers of a prolonged period of time in prison in relation to their returning to society.  We must remember that all people in prison will return to society and the emphasis should be on ensuring that when they do come back that they are a better people and that they are better able to cope.</P>
    <P>I would not accept the suggestion by Senator Neville that there is any suggestion of trying to romanticise the prison system.  Certainly that is out of the question. I would have no wish ever to do that.  My function in proposing these amendments is to put order where there is a degree of disorder, to improve the system.  There is not much sense in talking in terms of the old traditional way of locking them up, throwing away the key, waiting for them to come out and expecting all to be well after that.  You must have a system that has a rationale, that has a developmental and a positive approach not a negative approach.  If we can introduce a positive element into our system of sanctions that would be desirable. I cannot for the life of me see why the Minister comes up with a response which misses the point.  I ask him to reconsider the matter and accept the amendment, or certainly to accept the principle of the amendment, if he does not agree with its entire substance, and perhaps take on board some of the extra alternatives that were suggested by Senator Neville.</P>
    <P>Question put: &ldquo;That the words proposed to be deleted stand.&rdquo;</P>
    <P Just="Center">The Seanad divided: Tá, 14; Níl, 15.</P>
    <P Just="Center">Tá</P>
    <table pgwide="1">
      <tgroup cols="2">
        <colspec colname="1" colnum="1" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <colspec colname="2" colnum="2" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry rowsep="1">Bohan, Eddie.<br />Cassidy, Donie.<br />Farrell, Willie.<br />Fitzgerald, Tom.<br />Honan, Tras.<br />Kiely, Rory.<br />Lanigan, Michael.</entry>
            <entry rowsep="1">McCarthy, Seán.<br />McGowan, Paddy.<br />McKenna, Tony.<br />Mullooly, Brian.<br />Ó Cuív, Éamon.<br />O'Keeffe, Batt.<br />Ryan, Eoin David.</entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
    <P Just="Center">
      <Col N="1639" />
      <Col N="1640" /> Níl</P>
    <table pgwide="1">
      <tgroup cols="2">
        <colspec colname="1" colnum="1" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <colspec colname="2" colnum="2" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry rowsep="1">Cosgrave, Liam.<br />Costello, Joe.<br />Harte, John.<br />Hourigan, Richard V.<br />Howard, Michael.<br />Manning, Maurice.<br />Murphy, John A.<br />Neville, Daniel.</entry>
            <entry rowsep="1">Norris, David.<br />Ó Foighil, Pól.<br />O'Toole, Joe.<br />Ross, Shane P.N.<br />Ryan, John.<br />Staunton, Myles.<br />Upton, Pat.<br /></entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
    <P Just="Center">Tellers: Tá Senators McGowan and Farrell; Níl, Senators Upton and Costello.</P>
    <P>Question declared lost.</P>
    <Speaker pid="SeanDoherty" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>This means that the words proposed to be deleted are deleted.  I must now put amendment No. 2 formally to the House.</P>
      <P>Amendment put.</P>
      <P Just="Center">The Seanad divided: Tá, 16; Níl, 16.</P>
      <P Just="Center">Tá</P>
    </Speaker>
    <table pgwide="1">
      <tgroup cols="2">
        <colspec colname="1" colnum="1" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <colspec colname="2" colnum="2" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry rowsep="1">Cosgrave, Liam.<br />Costello, Joe.<br />Harte, John.<br />Hourigan, Richard V.<br />Howard, Michael.<br />Jackman, Mary.<br />Manning, Maurice.<br />Murphy, John A.</entry>
            <entry rowsep="1">Neville, Daniel.<br />Norris, David.<br />Ó Foighil, Pól.<br />O'Toole, Joe.<br />Ross, Shane P.N.<br />Ryan, John.<br />Staunton, Myles.<br />Upton, Pat.</entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
    <P Just="Center">Níl</P>
    <table pgwide="1">
      <tgroup cols="2">
        <colspec colname="1" colnum="1" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <colspec colname="2" colnum="2" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry rowsep="1">Bennett, Olga.<br />Bohan, Eddie.<br />Cassidy, Donie.<br />Conroy, Richard.<br />Farrell, Willie.<br />Fitzgerald, Tom.<br />Honan, Tras.<br />Kiely, Rory.</entry>
            <entry rowsep="1">Lanigan, Michael.<br />McCarthy, Seán.<br />McGowan, Paddy.<br />McKenna, Tony.<br />Mullooly, Brian.<br />Ó Cuív, Éamon.<br />O'Keeffe, Batt.<br />Ryan, Eoin David.</entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
    <P Just="Center">Tellers: Tá, Senators Costello and Upton; Níl, Senators McGowan and Farrell.</P>
    <Speaker pid="SeanDoherty" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>There is an equality of votes and, therefore, pursuant to Article 15.11.2º of the Constitution, I have to exercise my casting vote.  I vote against the question in this case.  The numbers are now: Tá 16, Níl 17.</P>
      <P>Question declared lost.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeOToole" hpid="Mr. O'Toole Mr. O'Toole">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Toole</NameTxt>
      <P>On a point of order, the position now is that words have been deleted from the Bill.  New words have not been inserted.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanDoherty" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>That is right.  There is now an absence of words.</P>
      <P>Debate adjourned.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Unification of Germany:" RHead="Motion (Resumed)">
    <Title>Unification of Germany: Motion (Resumed).</Title>
    <P>Debate resumed on the following motion:</P>
    <P>That Seanad Éireann welcomes the unification of Germany.</P>
    <P Just="Right">&mdash;(Senator Lydon.)</P>
    <Speaker pid="ShaneRoss" hpid="Mr. Ross Mr. Ross">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Ross</NameTxt>
      <P>Are we waiting for the Minister?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MylesStaunton" hpid="Acting Chairman (Mr. Staunton) Acting Chairman (Mr. Staunton)">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman (Mr. Staunton)</NameTxt>
      <P>I am waiting for the Minister.  As soon as the Minister arrives I am proposing to call on you to speak.  Perhaps we could wait one <Col N="1641" /> minute.  If we do not have the Minister within a minute if you wish to speak without the Minister being present, feel free to do so.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RayBurke" hpid="Minister for Justice (Mr. Burke) Raphael P. Burke">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Justice (Mr. Burke)</NameTxt>
      <P>I will sit in.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Acting Chairman Acting Chairman">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman</NameTxt>
      <P>I call on Senator Ross.  The Senator has 15 minutes.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ShaneRoss" hpid="Mr. Ross Mr. Ross">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Ross</NameTxt>
      <P>I would like to thank the Minister for Justice for sitting in but I think he is obviously improvising.  I would prefer to make the point that the Seanad should not be treated in this cavalier fashion and that we should have the Minister for Foreign Affairs or his junior Minister present.  The sort of chaos that has reigned in this House this afternoon is simply being emphasised again by the presence &mdash; and he is very welcome &mdash; of the Minister for Justice.  I regret the fact that the Government has not for some reason, and without explanation, been able to provide the appropriate Minister for a motion of this sort.  Maybe we could have some explanation for that from a spokesman for the Government at some stage?  It is high time the Seanad was provided with the right Minister for the right motion at the right time, and that we did not have Ministers giving of their time, which is good of them, simply because the appropriate Minister has not turned up.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RayBurke" hpid="Mr. Burke Mr. Burke">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Burke</NameTxt>
      <P>The Senator can be assured that on a motion in relation to the unification of Germany, I would be more than competent and more than delighted to respond to the points the Senator would make.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ShaneRoss" hpid="Mr. Ross Mr. Ross">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Ross</NameTxt>
      <P>I take your point, Minister. The Minister has already spoken in this debate, so I do not think you would be entitled to speak.  I welcome the Minister for Justice.  I say that with all sincerity, but I think it might be better organised and that we might have the appropriate Minister for the appropriate motion.  This sort of thing has been happening continuously, and I regret it.  I have no doubt <Col N="1642" /> about the particular Minister's qualifications to speak on any topic, and particularly this one.</P>
      <P>Having said that I will get down to the substantial motion which is the welcome to the unification of Germany.  It is a Government motion.  The first thing that should be said about this, which was said by the Minister of State when he spoke here during the first half of this debate, is that there is no question that we or any other nation in Europe or around the world can stand in the way of a country like Germany which has so clearly expressed its will to self-determination in the popular vote and the popular expression of the people.  Whereas we may have reservations &mdash; indeed, I have reservations about the unification of Germany &mdash; there is such a clear will there from both parts of Germany and from both sides of Germany for this particular situation to come about that we cannot stand and should not stand in its way. We may urge notes of caution.  We may express reservations but the principle of German unification as expressed by the peoples of Germany cannot be obstructed by us or by anybody else.  Secondly, because Germany was such an obviously artificial divide it would be very wrong for us to say we wanted to perpetuate such an obviously artificial divide.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>We all remember very well the reasons for the division of Germany.  They should be remembered in this debate, and not just skimmed over.  They were really two fold.  One was a fear of Germany as a revived military power in 1945, where the great powers felt that Germany had proved over two world wars it was such a dangerous, belligerent nation and powerful nation that it could not be allowed to continue as one unit but that it had to be weakened and punished. That was the basis behind the division of Germany.  The other basis was the wish of the great powers, both the USSR, in particular, and America and France and Britain to a lesser extent for spheres of influence which included Germany and which divided Germany into East and West, one part into the eastern sphere of <Col N="1643" /> influence and the other into the US sphere of influence.</P>
    <P>We should not be afraid to ask ourselves when we are debating this particular issue whether those fears still hold. We should remind ourselves that Germany in the last century was a dangerous and militaristic nation and that it has been belligerent.  It has looked for conquest far beyond its borders.  We should not be frightened of asking whether there is something in the German nature and in the German people which is aggressive and which ought to be curbed and watched.</P>
    <P>In terms of modern warfare, modern military equipment and modern military methods those arguments probably no longer hold.  It would be unrealistic to say that Germany is going to conquer Europe or further afield by force of arms.  It would be unrealistic to say that Germany would have the power or would even necessarily have the will to be a military aggressor. What we have to look at is the possible economic consequences of Germany as it becomes a far greater unit.  While we welcome what is happening and the principle of what is happening, we should not be unaware of what is going to happen because a united Germany which is undoubtedly going to come about in the next year or so, is going to be by far the biggest country in Europe in terms of territory.  It is going to be by far the biggest in terms of population.  It is going to have a population of 80 million people, all with this very worthy and great characteristic for hard work and building up economic power which many of the nations of Europe do not share.  It is equalled only by Japan in the world today.</P>
    <P>What we have to ask ourselves is whether we will accept German unification, which we do.  Do we also accept that we are going to have Germany economically dominating Europe?  Do we want that particular dominance?  Should we take measures to check this economic dominance of Europe which seems to me at this stage to be the inevitable result of German unity?  What we are doing in <Col N="1644" /> our acceptance, and in some ways in our unquestioning acceptance, of German unity is accepting the transfer from Germany hegemony in Europe, which undoubtedly is there in economic terms, to possible German dominance in Europe in economic terms.  We should look at the possible consequence of that.  Already a divided Germany, West Germany, is by far the most powerful country in economic terms in Europe.  We should also look at the effects this will have on Ireland.  The principal effect it would have on Ireland would be on interest rates here.</P>
    <P>The Taoiseach has made a statement about this, but there are conflicting views about the consequences of taking East Germany on board into the European Community and taking it on board as part of West Germany and about whether it will have an effect on interest rates, the economy and inflation here.  What I suggest here is that inevitably the rush to German unity which is a political act in German terms as demonstrated by what they have done and which has made economics a subservient sphere will have economic effects on Ireland.  That is principally because, first of all, we are a member of the European monetary system which is a Deutsche Mark based currency zone in Europe.  We made a decision in 1979 to go into that.  It was the right decision but we have to accept the economic consequences, that we are tied to the Deutsche Mark and, therefore, we are tied to the German economy. Not only are we tied to the West German economy now, we would be even more tied to the economy of a united Germany that would, if it could dominate the European system even more.</P>
    <P>We have only to look at the promises which have been made by Chancellor Kohl in the past few weeks to the East Germans to realise the enormous cost which the West Germans are prepared to pay for this political and economic unity. The promise Chancellor Kohl made that the Deutsche Mark would be exchanged one for one against the Ostmark in terms of savings and, secondly, that after July wages and salaries in East Germany <Col N="1645" /> would be exchanged on the basis of one to one as between the Ostmark and the Deutsche Mark.  They are going to be extremely expensive promises for the West German Government to keep.  Herr Kohl refused assistance from the European Community on this as a matter of pride rather more than anything else, because he was telling us that this was an internal matter for Germany and that they could afford it.</P>
    <P>The significant matter for Ireland was that the promises which Herr Kohl made to East Germany, partly to persuade them towards unity and partly to hasten this great political desire which the Germans seem to have, were taken against the advice of the President of the Bundesbank who suggested this was going to be too expensive for the West German economy to take and that he should make a lesser offer.  The independence of the Bundesbank was on this occasion compromised by Herr Kohl because he had made a political decision.  It seems that he has the full support of the German people and that they are prepared to pay a heavy price for the unity of Germany. It seems also that he is prepared to make further concessions in order to achieve unity hastily.  It seems that the price that the Germans, who are a very money conscious people, are prepared to pay for it is a lot higher than has been revealed.</P>
    <P>The dangers to Ireland, I think, are basically economic ones.  The reason why I think interest rates here will rise and why the Taoiseach and others who say, more in hope than in reality, that they will not rise, is that in the German Democratic Republic, that was, there is a huge reserve of savings.  The people of the GDR, because they are not a consumerled society, have had nothing else to do with their money except to save it.  As a result of that, they have, I think 177 billion Ostmarks stored up in East German banks.  They could not spend the money because there were no consumer goods to spend it on.  As a result of this, they are going to spend that money at the exchange rate given in West Germany in the whole of Germany on consumer goods.  The result of this, and the price <Col N="1646" /> which the West Germans are prepared to pay, will be that West Germany will print an enormous number of new Deutsche Marks which with fuel inflation in that country.  That will, of course, have consequences not only for the Germans but for the whole of Europe.</P>
    <P>Germany is the leading country in Europe in economic and industrial terms. If inflation goes up there inflation will inevitably be imported into the other countries of Europe.  If that happens the interest rate will inevitably rise to protect the Deutsche Mark, which will be the answer from the Bundesbank to Herr Kohl. Being partly linked with the Deutsche Mark we will either have to devalue the £IR or we will have to raise our interest rates as well.  To say that German unity will not cost us anything is economically wrong.  We might be lucky.  Interest rates throughout the world may start to take a tumble.  It is unlikely, but they may, in which case in the natural course of events the interest rates in West Germany will fall and our rates will fall as well, but not as fast as they would normally.  Because we are linked, we will follow the Deutsche Mark and interest rates in Germany, up and down.  That is inevitable.  It is inevitable that it will cost West Germany a lot of money.  As a result, it is going to cost us some money &mdash; and possibly create inflation &mdash; but not so much in terms of inflation as in terms of interest rates.</P>
    <P>The other warning which I think I should issue &mdash; and I say this without pomposity because it is not an original idea &mdash; is that in the light of what was said on the other side of the House, which was uniformally favourable to German unification and no fault was found in it by Senator Lydon or by the Minister when he spoke with some caution but without any criticism, it seems that the expectations of the East German people are almost unlimited at this stage.  They have been exposed through television and by the media generally to the West German way of life.  Their dreams about the West German way of life are utopian.</P>
    <P>One of the reasons they wish to move towards unity is that they can see the consumer society as some sort of panacea <Col N="1647" /> for the ills and the lack of prosperity which they have suffered for so long. They think that unity will suddenly bring them this great wealth and prosperity which the West German people have enjoyed for so long.  They forget, I think, that the West German people have earned that prosperity very hard over a very long period of time.  They also, I think, are oblivious, and by choice oblivious, to the fact that they will also lose some rights and some privileges when they become part of a united Germany. Whereas the Eastern system had many faults, many drawbacks and was intolerable in our terms of freedoms, in terms of prosperity, in terms of consumer spending, in East Germany they had certain rights, like the right to a house, the right to homes, the automatic right to jobs, which they will not have when they become part of a united German state.</P>
    <P>Finally, I would like to say that in military terms a lot of controversy has surrounded the issue of whether a united Germany should be part of NATO.  I would have thought that the result of the unification of Germany should be that we look at NATO again.  We should say: &ldquo;No, this should be the start of a dismantling of NATO&rdquo; It is obvious to all of us that the Warsaw Pact is a dead duck and that as a military unity there is no such thing as the Warsaw Pact any longer. It is the ideal opportunity for the Western powers to get together and say: &ldquo;NATO is no longer relevant; it is no longer topical; it is redundant.  We do not need NATO&rdquo;.  I resent the sort of protective manner in which European countries and America are trying to put pressure on Germany for a united Germany to be part of the North Atlantic Treaty Organisation. The opportunity must be taken for the North Atlantic Treaty Organisation to be dismantled as the Warsaw Pact is being dismantled involuntarily.  I think as a military move and in military terms&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    <Speaker pid="SeanDoherty" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>You are running a minute over time.  There are other speakers who want to get in.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1648" />
    <Speaker pid="ShaneRoss" hpid="Mr. Ross Mr. Ross">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Ross</NameTxt>
      <P>I think the opportunity should be taken for NATO to be dismantled.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MickLanigan" hpid="Mr. Lanigan Mr. Lanigan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lanigan</NameTxt>
      <P>There is a vote in the other House.  The Minister is not formally paired.  Is it agreed that we adjourn for 15 minutes?  Agreed.</P>
      <P>
        <i>Sitting suspended at 7 p.m. and resumed at 7.15 p.m.</i>
      </P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelFinneranFF" hpid="Acting Chairman (Mr. Finneran) Acting Chairman (Mr. Finneran)">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman (Mr. Finneran)</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator Lanigan has 15 minutes.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MickLanigan" hpid="Mr. Lanigan Mr. Lanigan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lanigan</NameTxt>
      <P>In addressing ourselves to the motion, we have to be careful that we do not go overboard in suggesting that this remarriage between East and West Germany will create a Utopia either for the people of the East or the West.  Profound changes have been taking place in the political spectrum all over Europe over the past eight or nine months.  Not alone have we seen profound changes taking place on the European scene, but, equally, there is a willingness on the African continent by people who have been in conflict for many years to come together and address themselves to the problems which have kept them apart for so many years.</P>
      <P>We have seen changes take place on the South American continent.  Changes are taking place in Nicaragua and in the Central American states.  There are changes taking place all over the world at present and there is a genuine welcome for the re-emergence of political democracy as is seen in many of those countries where changes are taking place.  It should not be forgotten that in many countries which are now changing their political ways democracy was not the method by which they were ruled prior to the breakup in Europe in the thirties and forties. Many of those countries that are now changing into democracies were theocratic states or monarchies and were a long way away from democracy as we know it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>However, we must welcome the fact that profound changes have taken place in East Germany.  Fears have been <Col N="1649" /> expressed that we will see a monolithic Germany re-emerge which will change the balance of power throughout Europe and this at a time when it seems that the monolithic state of the USSR is breaking up into its former constituents, or if not former constituents back into ethnic and nationalistic areas which existed for a short time in the late 19th century and early 20th century.</P>
    <P>It has been said that the break-up of the USSR is of major importance and that it will weaken the status of Russia and its satellites and that this will bring the balance of power more towards the West than towards the East.  However, it should not be forgotten that irrespective of what is happening in the USSR at present that country still has the biggest army in the world and that if Mr. Gorbachev and the Supreme Soviet so decided they could by weight of arms take out many of the smaller states with whom they are now in political and economic conflict.  A member of the Supreme Soviet summed up the problems that exist in the Soviet Union at present when he said that <i>glasnost</i> had to be supported because there was no going back to the pre-<i>glasnost</i> era without going back the whole road to a Stalinist totalitarian society.  He also said that the USSR would still be a super power but a super power not of Bismarck but of Pushkin. In other words, they would be pushing to be a democratic and economic power rather than having the world's biggest army.  On the European scene we have seen changes taking place in all the states of Eastern Europe, changes which took place over a period of only three or four months.  One wonders if that was a genuine expression of need to change or a push from the existing systems of government in certain areas because there is no doubt but that many of the countries of Eastern Europe were economically on their knees.  There was a genuine fear among the Governments of those countries that the people were going to take over anyway.  There might have been a push in certain areas in those countries for changes, not from the need <Col N="1650" /> to democratise but for purely economic reasons and reasons of fear.</P>
    <P>People in Western Europe are fearful of the economic power that might be generated by the unification of Germany. I would not have great fears on that basis. There is no doubt that West Germany needs the workers from the East and the workers from the East need to increase their economic status.  The cost will not only be to Europe, it will be to Third World countries who have been supported by the European Community over a number of years.  There is a fear that because many resources will have to go towards rebuilding the economies of Eastern Europe and, from West Germany's point of view, to build up the economy of East Germany, we will see a reduction in the amount of aid and support that will be given to Third World countries, whether these Third World countries are in the Far East, Africa or the near East.  Many of the people in these countries are living in poverty at present and any reduction in aid from Europe would have drastic consequences.</P>
    <P>West Germany has been seen as the bastion of capitalism in the West and there is no doubt it was one of the major capitalist powers not alone in Western Europe but in the world.  There are fears in West Germany that because of the big influx of East German workers wage rates will go down in West Germany and, therefore, the standard of living will go down.  There are already hints of unrest among steel workers and mine workers because their compatriots from East Germany are willing to work for less than the going rate.  This could cause economic problems for the West Germans and for a united Germany.</P>
    <P>From Ireland's point of view we have to be a little fearful that interest rates might increase as a result of the coming together of these two huge countries. There are implications for us on political, economic and military levels.  The problems associated with NATO and the Eastern powers bloc have to be resolved. Nobody would like to see East and West Germany holding the balance of military <Col N="1651" /> power in the middle of Europe because there are still people who remember what happened when they had this power before.</P>
    <P>We wish the peoples of East and West Germany every success in their efforts to recreate one state.  Now that the East and West Germans have been able to sit down and iron out their problems there is a lesson to be learned here for those on this island and on the island of Britain who do not wish to see a reunification of this island.  When Mr. De Klerk and Mr. Mandela can sit down in conference to attempt to bring together two different peoples it should not be outside the bounds of political possibilities that the problems associated with the reunification of this country could not be addressed successfully.</P>
    <P>Like the other speakers in the House, I welcome the changes that are taking place in the two Germanys.  I look forward to the day when Germany will be a political entity playing a major part in supporting the economy of the EC with the other member states, including our own.  Even before 1992 the EC is the biggest economic bloc in the world, having taken over from Japan.  It is bigger than the USA at present.  Twenty five per cent of world trade now goes through the EC and that is a huge amount of trade by any standards.  With the coming of the integrated Community on 1 January 1993 I can see tht this economic power block will be much stronger and that the East and West Germans will play their part in that.  It is not being forgotten by trading partners, such as the United States, that this power bloc is emerging, because at present we see desperate efforts being made by the United States and Canada to form an economic power bloc.  They are coming together very rapidly.  I was just looking at an economic statement from the Canadians the other day that the State of Ontario does more trade with Japan than Japan does with the United States.  So one can see that Canada and the United States together will be a formidable economic power bloc as well. We congratulate the peoples of East and West Germany, the West Germans on <Col N="1652" /> their foresight and the East Germans on their ability to throw off the shackles that were holding them fast for the past 40 years.  We re-welcome them into the family of the West.  As I have said, I cannot but welcome this motion.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatUpton" hpid="Dr. Upton Dr. Upton">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Upton</NameTxt>
      <P>At the outset, may I welcome the fact that the Fianna Fáil Party, the Government Party, have seen fit to introduce this motion and put it before the House?  I think that it is very timely that they have done so.  I also welcome the developments in Germany and the moves towards the unification of Germany. I welcome them because in many ways it is inevitable but of course there are a series of other reasons also why it should be welcomed.  The unification of Germany involves enormous changes. You are talking in terms of creating a new Europe, and that has major implications for all of us.  In this country we must be very aware of what is happening. It is very important that we should play our part in determining what the ultimate shape of Europe will be.  There are approximately 18 million people in Eastern Germany on relatively lower standards of living, etc., and that, of course, has to have very profound implications when it works its way through the whole system.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>There are a number of practical aspects of the integration of Eastern Germany into Europe to which I feel, we have not given enough thought.  There will be very big questions in relation to the agricultural policy.  What adjustments will be made to the Common Agricultural Policy and how will those adjustments affect the Irish farming community and, indeed, the country in general?  I am not sure that we have fully thought through what the effects will be, although to be fair about it, I am not sure either that it is possible to say with clarity the manner in which those ramifications will work their way through the system.  Certainly, I feel confident that it is not easy to predict accurately what those effects will be on this country over, say, a ten year period and beyond that.  For example, what will be the effect of all this on milk quotas?  What <Col N="1653" /> will be the effect on the way Irish farming is organised?  What will be its effect on the food industry?  On the one hand, the expansion of Europe will create major extra opportunities in the market for Ireland; on the other hand, it may also create much greater pressure on our quotas which, at this stage, are pretty pressured anyway.  What will be the implication for the other aspects of farming, many of which are doing very badly at present?</P>
    <P>In addition to that, there is the question of the wider implications of the effect of German unity and the drift towards European unity which we are seeing at present.  This, of course, creates considerable economic opportunities for Ireland.  There must be great opportunities and scope for us to become involved in the development and in servicing the growth in the underdeveloped countries of Eastern Europe.  There will also, of course, be the question of aid. That has been discussed to a fair extent by a number of Senators already, but I think the implications there are very farreaching. There will be the impact of this development on inflation.  Certainly it seems as if the impact will be one of increasing inflation and that, in turn, even in the short term, has fairly profound implications for this country.  Whatever happens in Eastern Europe, and in Eastern Germany, or in the united Germany, it is very important that the European Community should in a very fundamental way shape the developments in Europe generally and should shape those developments as they affect Ireland.</P>
    <P>The history of central Europe has been one which has been littered with problems relating to ethnic minorities and feuding which has gone on for centuries. The potential for instability and confrontation in central and Eastern Europe is considerable.  The whole phenomena surrounding the unification of Germany and the wider questions of the unification of Europe create an atmosphere of uncertainty. It is very important that in that atmosphere of uncertainty effective processes and structures for co-operation and for the resolution of problems should <Col N="1654" /> be organised.  It is very important that these should be proper facilities and that every effort should be made to ensure that problems are resolved in a peaceful manner.  That certainly has not been the history of Europe in the past and one has to have a certain degree of concern about what way things may take shape in the future.</P>
    <P>The experience of the European Community is clearly very relevant to the developments in Eastern Europe and in Eastern Germany and it is very important that we learn from the developments which have taken place in the formulation and growth of the European Economic Community.</P>
    <P>In conclusion, again I welcome the fact that the Fianna Fáil Party have taken the initiative to introduce this debate in the Seanad.  We should approach the whole issue of German unity in a framework and in an attitude of optimism but we must also be very conscious of the fact that there are quite considerable risks involved if the problem is not handled properly.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MaryJackman" hpid="Mrs. Jackman Mrs. Jackman">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Jackman</NameTxt>
      <P>Like the other speakers I welcome the unification of Germany. Though politics have been described as the art of the possible, a recent quote by President Havel describes politics as the art of the impossible.  No one could believe that the Berlin Wall could come down so quickly with most of the European countries making brave attempts to achieve freedom, parliamentary democracy and a market economy.  We in Ireland have to respond quickly, openly and decisively to the thirst for freedom, personally and nationally, running right through Eastern Europe.  We have experienced that thirst and desire for freedom throughout the centuries and therefore, we welcome enthusiastically the prospect of German unification.  We cannot deny the people in these two countries the right to self-determination, which will be a reality in the near future.  Although German unity, a term more favoured by Willy Brandt, is principally a question for the Germans, it has, as other speakers <Col N="1655" /> have said, major repercussions for the Continent as a whole.</P>
      <P>We in Ireland are constantly concerned with our identity, our Irishness.  Germans now must address the intricacies of their identity.  West Germans had almost given up ever experiencing the re-integration of West and East Germany.  The idea of unity is embedded in the Federal Republic's basic law in the preamble that all future German Governments should work towards completing the unity of the nation; and, though it may have seemed a dream throughout the years, it is now a live option.  It is that dream really which sustained the East Germans during their darkest hours of serfdom.  What West Germans can offer now to their Eastern brethren comprises everything that they themselves have learnt since the inception of German democracy after World War II: democracy, the rule of law and the experience of setting up a successful economy.</P>
      <P>Of course, building a new Germany entails a new Europe.  The analogy of architecture has been used to describe this new Europe: democratic politics as the foundations, market economies on the ground floor and an over-arching security roof to keep out acids and nuclear rain.  The site has more than a few problems and, finally, not all of the inhabitants are house trained.  This is not my quotation; it is a quotation from Wittelsbrod, of Cabinet of Vice-President Andriessen of the European Commission in a paper he gave here to the Irish Council of the European Movement in March of this year.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>After designing the architecture, going back to the building analogy, the construction will start and, as in building ordinary houses, will take more time. Since the Federal Republic of Germany was founded it has been German policy to try to solve the German unity question at European level in co-operation with European neighbours and friends.  Any isolated or separate solution would contradict the logic of the process of unification embracing the whole of Europe. The dramatic and political changes have <Col N="1656" /> shown that the economic systems based on central planning and control have failed.  Over the years a massive prosperity gap formed between East and West.  Now that the borders are open these gaps will need to be bridged urgently.</P>
    <P>In the case of the two Germanys, where there are no legal, linguistic or cultural barriers to migration, the existing disadvantages in terms of income in a particular economic area, provide massive incentives for emigration, especially where in the German Democratic Republic the average income of gainfully employed persons is less than a third of that earned in the Federal Republic of Germany, No wonder 400,000 citizens of the German Democratic Republic have moved to the Federal Republic, many for economic reasons.  The danger here is that that number may increase dramatically if the people in the GDR do not get confirmation of an early improvement in their situation through fundamentally reforming their system of Government and their economy, and steps have been taken to ensure obviously at this stage that this is happening.</P>
    <P>It is urgent that development towards constitutionality, democracy and market economy is supported vigorously.  The required improvements in the economic field will only be achieved through a fundamental reform of the present economic system and a clear decision in favour of a system based on market economy and co-operation.  Competition has always been the hallmark of German competence. The reforms necessary for East Germany include (1) granting the freedom to choose one's trade, occupation or profession; (2) ensuring the freedom of contract; (3) enacting new constitutional provisions on property; (4) price reform; (5) reforms of regulations on the corporate legal structure, and (6), reform of the monetary and credit systems, the financial systems and taxation and the abolition of the Government's monopoly in foreign trade.  If that confidence can be created it will, on the one hand, reduce the pressure for emigration from the German Democratic Republic and, on <Col N="1657" /> the other hand, will permit that transfer of capital into the German Democratic Republic which is so necessary to level out the existing prosperity differential in what hopefully will be a foreseeable span of time.</P>
    <P>In the Federal Republic willingness to enter into commitments in the GDR is very strong.  Way back in 1953 Ludwig Erhardt predicted in the event of reunification &ldquo;That the entire economy of the Federal Republic will be ready to help the Eastern economy, both in word and in deed, to fulfil the task of bringing performance into line&rdquo;.  His words are prophetic. Yes, as many incentives as possible must be given to the people in East Germany to help them rebuild their country while allowing the full benefits of membership within a confederate Germany. That is the road they will take. The people of the Federal Republic must be educated about the price tag of reunification. We in Ireland must be educated about that price tag too.  Members have already referred to perhaps a possible reduction of EC aid to Third World countries, which would be very regrettable.</P>
    <P>The concept of financial responsibility, tax increases, etc., will be put before the people of West Germany and they have to face up to them.  Because, after the first euphoria, the realities of day-to-day demands in West Germany &mdash; where the housewife was crying that there were, for instance, no bananas on a specific day because of the influx of Eastern Europeans &mdash; will cause what I would consider day-to-day irritants and a certain amount of obvious disgruntlement.  So there will be growing pains, as it were, during the transition period and there must be patience and there must be tolerance.</P>
    <P>We, among Western democracies, have to anticipate great commitments to the previously socialist countries of Central and Eastern Europe; but, as other speakers have said, we must look positively at the exciting perspectives for Europe in the economic field.  Hopefully the nineties might develop into a decade of economic dynamism and prosperity for the whole of Europe.  Ireland will be <Col N="1658" /> faced with threats, will be faced with opportunities.  Our ability to exploit these opportunities will outweigh the threats if we use business and industry, State agencies, financial and educational institutions to forge links with our Eastern European neighbours; and these, hopefully, are already in progress within those agencies.  Many Senators and Deputies have visited Eastern Europe over the last few months and no doubt they are looking towards the forging of those links.</P>
    <P>Of course, the changes in Eastern Europe as a whole will have an impact on the European Community as it approaches 1992 and the goals of broader economic and monetary union, and the unification of Germany will have an impact on the speed with which European Community integration can be achieved. President Delors has given a figure of a price tag of IR£10 million for structural fund support for Eastern Europe on a level currently pertaining to the peripheral regions of the EC.  Of course, we must be vigiliant too in ensuring that our peripheral regions will receive what we need to build our economy.  But we must not be too selfish.  We must forget our own self-interest.  We must keep it in mind, but we must look towards whether we really want a unified Germany in action, not just in words or in a sort of acceptance, without realising that there is a price tag and that we will be affected. Mention was already made of perhaps rising interest rates as a result.  The debate at the moment is whether the funds will come from additional resources or whether existing budgetary flexibility will be used to channel funds to Eastern Europe.</P>
    <P>So, there are major implications, not just for ourselves but for the other peripheral regions of the Community.  As I said, we are living in an age of accelerated rates of exchange but at the same time we must respond decisively and positively in a spirit of co-operation and it is in that spirit that I welcome, with the other Senators in the House, the unification of Germany.</P>
    <Speaker pid="DavidNorris" hpid="Mr. Norris Mr. Norris">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norris</NameTxt>
      <P>I cannot really welcome <Col N="1659" /> this at all.  Actually I think this is just about the greatest load of tripe I have heard since I have come into this House and I will tell you precisely why.  Suppose for example, Seanad Éireann were to vote against the unification of Germany. What does this House imagine would be the effect?  Would Chancellor Kohl and his counterpart sit up in the Bundestag and say, &ldquo;Gosh, Seanad Éireann have voted against the unification of Germany. We must not go ahead with our plan&rdquo;?  I really think that the reason we are discussing this is that the Government have no serious business.  This has been evident during the day.  That is my candid opinion because the debate here can have very little effect.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="NoelTracey" hpid="Minister of State at the Department of Health (Mr. N. Treacy) Noel Treacy">
      <NameTxt>Minister of State at the Department of Health (Mr. N. Treacy)</NameTxt>
      <P>What about our fellow Europeans?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidNorris" hpid="Mr. Norris Mr. Norris">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norris</NameTxt>
      <P>I quite agree, Minister. That is a most effective and useful intervention. If we really cared about them I will tell you what we would do.  The Minister is a decent person and I am sure if he had the individual capacity &mdash; which I, as an Independent have &mdash; for stating a genuine opinion, he would agree that nothing highlights more than this debate the nonsensical and ludicrous situation that we are the only country in Europe that does not have a foreign affairs committee where this kind of matter could be properly discussed.  It is absolute nonsense to have an empty, rhetorical debate full of po-faced cermonising about what we have to do, what the Germans of various kinds have to do.  It is absolutely ludicrous.  However, that never prevented me from having my &ldquo;spake&rdquo;.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>We can learn even from the language employed not just in this debate but in the titles of the different countries.  The German Democratic Republic is what is at the moment being dismantled.  How did it become democratic?  It became democratic by being so named.  We are now in the process of examining minutely the crumbling of this species of &ldquo;democracy&rdquo; throughout Europe.  But before we <Col N="1660" /> bleat our way into self-congratulation we ought &mdash; since we are prepared to engage in strictures upon Eastern Europe &mdash; to engage in a critique of our own society and look at democracy in Ireland and look particularly at institutions like Seanad Éireann and Dáil Éireann and at the way in which they may be reformed. What we are looking at in Eastern Europe is people power, the invasion of the jealously guarded precincts of parliamentary power by a risen people.  I am not sure too many Members of either House here would be that enthusiastic for this to occur here and particularly the Government of the day.</P>
    <P>Consider the way in which legislation is so strictly controlled by the Government party, the way in which, for example, delegations to international parliamentary meetings are controlled and the small voices, the voices of individuals, of the minority groups or the weaker parties are ruthlessly squeezed out by both the main parties.  I can speak with some small experience of this as can the other Independent Members.  This has been done to me in the name of democracy at international meetings.  Let us be quite clear on our attitude.  Let us not be sanctimonious and hypocritical.</P>
    <P>May I ask how much time is remaining in the debate?</P>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Acting Chairman Acting Chairman">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman</NameTxt>
      <P>You have 15 minutes.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidNorris" hpid="Mr. Norris Mr. Norris">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norris</NameTxt>
      <P>My colleague, Senator Murphy, would like to come in and I am quite happy to give him a couple of minutes if it is necessary.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Acting Chairman Acting Chairman">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman</NameTxt>
      <P>There is no difficulty in allowing Senator Murphy in.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidNorris" hpid="Mr. Norris Mr. Norris">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norris</NameTxt>
      <P>Thank you.  If there was I would be more than happy to give him five or ten minutes or whatever is necessary.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>First, we have to look at our own attitudes, set our own house in order.  We have also got to look at the implications of a united Germany.  They are serious. There will be created an enormous, <Col N="1661" /> immensely powerful economic bloc right in the centre of Europe.  Make no mistake whatever about that.  My colleague on these benches, Senator Jackman, touched a memory chord of mine when she mentioned Ludwig Erhardt.  I remember Ludwig Erhardt very well &mdash; a most brilliant man, the designer of the <i>Wirt-schaftswunder</i> in the 1950s and 1960s, the economic miracle of German recovery. He was quite right, that this recovery was so strong it might in fact support reunification of Germany.  That will create so strong an economic bloc in the centre of the European Economic Community that it is going to distort the existing economic relationships.  Let there be no question of doubt about that.</P>
    <P>Let there be no question of doubt about another fact and that is the hypocrisy of people at the level of the European Economic Community.  Perhaps the Minister might address himself to this point. We are prepared to support Eastern Europe for political reasons; we are prepared to support the reunification of Germany; we are prepared to support East Germany, the former German Democratic Republic &mdash; how, very practically? We are prepared to engage through the European Community in the secondment of civil servants, of bureaucrats.  We are prepared to establish a banking support system.  Nothing wrong with that, you may say.  Is there not?  They have been asked for these services before.  They have been asked for these services to support what is sometimes called the Third World, the southern hemisphere countries, and they have refused.  They have refused, in other words, in the name of economic self-interest to support the most deprived, the most suffering, the most discriminated against peoples of this globe and they have refused to do precisely those things which they are doing in terms of political self-interest for Eastern Europe.</P>
    <P>I would like to ask why can they not use the economic muscle in a moral fashion to support people who are at least equally our brothers in the most deprived sections of the worlds.  If this country can add any little, small groat's worth of wit into <Col N="1662" /> this debate it should be from our experience of domination, of deprivation, of famine and of being marginalised at the extreme edge of a powerful colonial interest.  That is the kind of point I would make if there was a serious forum like a foreign affairs committee in which to make it.  Those are very important matters that need to be considered.</P>
    <P>Let us also consider the human angle in terms of the relationship between the two Germanys, because all is not sweetness and light there, and I am sure the Minister is well aware of this.  Look, for example, at the response of people in Berlin to the invasion into East Berlin of West Berliners in their fast cars with their fast bucks and their fast lane lifestyles and the way in which they have already succeeded in alienating considerable sections of that population by their vulgar display of wealth, their condescending attitudes and their view that they can buy anything or anybody and that the people who operate as waiters, attendants in shops and so on must jump to it because of the power of the almighty Mark.  There is strong resentment growing in East Berlin about this and the Minister, I am sure, knows this as well as I do.  It is going to be the same in East Germany when they wake up to the actual realities of economic life in the West.  I am not saying that everything was wonderful in East Germany.  Of course, it was not; it was deplorable, a lot of it but let us bear these things in mind when we are talking of East Germany and the reunification of Germany.</P>
    <P>Let us bear in mind a couple of other things.  I agree 100 per cent with Senator Shane Ross when he said that the Warsaw Pact is collapsing, disintegrating, and thank God for it.  We should assist in the ordered dismantling of NATO as well.  It is wasteful, immoral and against everything this country should stand for in terms of international diplomatic and political influence.  I hope we can get some degree of movement on this dismantling. Particularly since we are a neutral country, our position should be one of pushing people in the direction of the dismantling of NATO.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="1663" /> I have a final point to make about the record of Germany.  It is important and I made it in no racist sense.  I have just come back from Jerusalem.  While I was there I visited the Armenian museum where there was another attempted genocide &mdash; two million people killed in 1915 &mdash; an anniversary which we so conveniently forget.  I cannot forget that genocide.  I cannot forget the genocide committed against the Jews, nor can I forget that the trial run was made against the people with the pink triangle, the Gay community in Germany.  One question could be asked: I wonder if any Government politician from this country would have the guts to ask it of the German people, and it is about compensation.  I know that the East Germans are making available some comparatively small token sum of money as a gesture to compensate the Jewish people who were victims of the holocaust in Germany.</P>
    <P>I would like to remind the Minister that the first people incarcerated were the homosexual people of Germany.  They were the first people medically experimented upon and they were the first people exterminated.  They have never been compensated.  I attended a conference in Torino in Italy ten years ago and I asked the German delegation why none of the Gay prisoners had ever applied for compensation.  The answer was astonishing.  The answer was that they had applied and, having applied, they were returned by the Government of the Federal Republic of Germany, which we think is the really democratic one, to complete their sentences.  No question of compensation has ever arisen.</P>
    <P>This question came into my mind late in the day and I have had quite a lot to say about the international, economic and diplomatic status of the question of the reunification of Germany.  I think this is an important one.  Is there going to be in the reunited Germany any compensation? I would like to quote from the autobiography of the Commandant of Auschwitz, Rudolf Hoess, talking of the treatment of homosexual prisoners:</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="1664" /> Neither the hardest work nor the strictest supervision was of any help in these cases.  Whenever they found an opportunity they would fall into one another's arms.  Even when physically in a very bad way, they would continue to indulge in their vice, they were easy enough to pick out.  Their soft and girlish affectations and fastidiousness, their sickly-sweet manner of speech and their altogether too affectionate deportment towards their fellows distinguished them from those who had put their vice behind them and wished to be free of it, and whose steps on the road to recovery were visible to any acute observer.</P>
    <P>Could Jonathan Swift write more trenchantly &ldquo;their altogether too affectionate deportment towards each other&rdquo; by the Commandant of Auschwitz.  For this they were punished, for this they were tortured, for this they were medically experimented upon and they have never been compensated.  I would like some movement towards their compensation.</P>
    <P>I will close simply by reminding the Minister of how easily these people were put away into Dachau, Sachsenhausen and into Auschwitz.  Rudolf Hoess said this:</P>
    <P>During the Olympic Games the beggars and tramps were cleared off the streets and put in workhouses and concentration camps and, at the same time the many prostitutes and homosexuals were rounded up in the town and at the bathing places.  They were to be trained to do more useful work in the camps.</P>
    <P>This debate is a complete nonsense as I said at the beginning.  Were we in Seanad Éireann to vote against the unification of Germany it would have damn all effect so it is a nonsense in those terms.  We can do certain small things.  We can raise the economic discrimination practised as part of this package against the weakest sections of the globe and we can also raise the question of compensation for people. I admit there would be ironies, ironies that were revealed today here in the vote <Col N="1665" /> which the Government lost, in the fact that we still discriminate ourselves but I will leave it to the Minister.  If he wants to do anything at all practical &mdash; I do not believe he does &mdash; but if he does those are a few small suggestions.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JohnMurphy2" hpid="Professor Murphy Professor Murphy">
      <NameTxt>Professor Murphy</NameTxt>
      <P>I thank my colleagues. When I scribbled a note to Senator Norris asking for one minute I meant literally that because there has been so much said and so much written about this topic and, as Senator Norris says, it is rather <i>Skibbereen Eagle</i>-ish to think that this debate will make any difference. There are so many things in this country that we in these Houses can do to remedy that it seems a trifle academic to be talking about this matter.  Nevertheless, for any European not to make some comments on this momentous event would be very remiss and it is in that spirit that I mention a few points.</P>
      <P>When Germany becomes one Germany, becomes Berlin-centred rather than Bonn-centred, becomes a country which has rid itself of foreign occupation and, therefore, in a sense will be for the first time not only united but sovereign and enormously powerful, I hope it will not be a different Germany.  Senator Norris is right to raise the spectres of the past.  Any historian must raise a question mark about the reliability of the German people as good Europeans and as democrats. I hope the new Germany will be able to resist the blandishments of those Germans in the lost territories, as they see themselves, and who certainly will pursue trouble in their own interests.  I hope that will not happen.  I hope there will be no Fourth Reich or anything like it.  I also hope the East Germans insist on salvaging from the ruin of their own State the best values in that State, the concern for social values, the concern for human dignity, which frequently is absent from the rampant free market economy of the West.  I hope that will happen, too.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Senator Norris said we cannot do anything anyway about a united Germany but it is not altogether true.  As a member of the Community we can be more positive instead of tugging our forelocks to <Col N="1666" /> the paymaster and saying: &ldquo;Whatever you do yourself, Sir, is OK with us&rdquo;.  We can insist that this united Germany must not be part of a rearmed Europe, that the new Europe must be free of armed alliances apart from the minimum necessary to secure the security of its peoples from the Atlantic to the Urals.  These are things we must insist on and especially as a country which cherishes neutrality, we cannot complacently accept the idea of a united Germany in NATO.</P>
    <P>Finally, and most important for Irish people, let us not draw the wrong moral from German unification.  I am afraid this has already been done in a very simplistic and disingenuous way by certain politicians from the Taoiseach downwards, namely, the simplistic inference that because the Germans are fortunate to have ended the artificial division of their country that points up the so-called artificial division of our country.  The two cases could not be more different and we must realistically appreciate that.  The Germans are being reunited because they want to be reunited, because they are, indeed, one race, one culture and one language.  On this island we have the awkward and unpleasant fact that there are two nations on one island and that no matter how unjustly the Border was drawn it represents some kind of reality. To draw the German analogy and to apply that analogy is inaccurate, disingenuous and very dangerous.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JoeOToole" hpid="Mr. O'Toole Mr. O'Toole">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Toole</NameTxt>
      <P>Far be it for me to disagree with my learned colleague and historian Senator Murphy.  Whereas no two cases can ever be seen to be absolutely and completely similar, the fact that might be well considered from the history of Europe whether it be Cyprus, Germany, Ireland or indeed many other examples, Schleswig-Holstein or Alsace-Lorraine that partitionism does not work anyway.  That is in the sense of being somewhat of a facile comment in response to what Senator Murphy has said.  I do not think it is fair to draw the conclusion and I think he is quite right there.  Neither do I feel it proves the opposite.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="1667" /> We discussed in the House the changes in Eastern Europe last November and we listened to a lot of patronising comment about Eastern Europe.  I believe now there is a more realistic assessment of what is happening there and what is happening in Germany.  I want to talk about a number of aspects.  I want to talk in the first place about the whole question of NATO, which was touched on by my colleague Senator Murphy.  It seems to me that the most positive thing coming from the unification, or reunification depending on which point of view you take, of Germany would be the fact that we could look forward to seeing what is now West Germany retreating and leaving NATO.  Certainly that would be a matter of some importance.  I firmly support the idea of the non-aligned states.  I believe that the Warsaw Pact and NATO are neither progressive, positive nor helpful in the creation of a global understanding among peoples.  I hope that the reunfication of Germany will lead to a German involvement in the non-aligned countries of the world.</P>
    <P>I would like to put in a note of caution. It is fair to remind ourselves of the difficulties that have arisen in Germany, the difficulties that have arisen in the first 50 or so years of this century which really can be put down to the German policy of aggrandisement, of empire building and land grabbing or country grabbing.  It is fair to remind ourselves of that, it is fair to remind ourselves also, as Senator Norris has done, about the difficulties experienced by the Gay community, the Jewish community and by other minority groups.</P>
    <P>It is important that we take into consideration the loss of life to the German people.  The discussion we are having tonight could have taken place two years ago about Russia.  Two out of every three people who were killed in the Second World War were Russians.  The Russians have had enough of war.  They have lost generations.  The countries in Europe who had that experience have never been inclined to rush back into it.  I do not believe the German people want to be involved in that kind of situation ever <Col N="1668" /> again.  Maybe I was born a couple of years too late.  I do not remember the war.</P>
    <P>We have heard how the Germans created suffering for other races, groups and countries.  History proves that fact but they also suffered themselves in every way, physically and morally.  We must recognise that there is a sense of guilt in individual Germans about what happened earlier in the century.  I do not believe there is the slightest possibility of that ever happening again.  It is easy to go back through history.  It is a matter of whether one believes that history repeats itself or whether one believes that we learn from history.  If one believes that history repeats itself in this inevitable way then there is some substance to that.</P>
    <P>In 1988 I spent time studying the developments in Estonia, Lativa and Lithuania and the past between Stalin and Hitler which destroyed those two countries.  I do not know if the Members have had the opportunity to read a most poignant interview in <i>The Irish Times</i> this week with the last Foreign Minister of Lithuania.  This interview outlined the way that people suffered, a suffering created by a pact between Hitler and Stalin. We can criticise all that has happened in history.  We could look back over our own history during that period and find plenty that we would be critical of and think that we would not trust the descendants of the people who took part in certain events.</P>
    <P>This development is a positive one. Moves towards unity are, in the main, positive moves.  It is a creation of compatability amongst races and groups.  I worry somewhat that many of the negative statements that have been made about German unification have smacked of racism.  I do not think it is correct to assign views, attitudes and so on to people because they are part of a particular race.</P>
    <P>I would like to continue on the point that was raised by Senator Norris, the question of the values of the free market. The people of Eastern Europe who, in the main, have come from regressive centralised governments, totalitarian States running command economies, might now <Col N="1669" /> feel that there is some enlightened future in the selfishness of the free market.  The free market means that operations, factories and industries are established in order to create a profit.  The citizens of what is now East Germany will have to come to terms with unemployment, poverty, poor housing and the other difficulties that are experienced by citizens of Europe.</P>
    <P>There is very little remaining to add to the debate.  Most issues have been covered but there is one issue I would like to deal with quite firmly.  The citizens of this country have been misled and fed misinformation for the last two months about the economic impact of German unification.  The largest selling daily newspaper has had three banner conflicting headlines over the last month. One headline stated: &ldquo;German unification is going to create a hike in interest rates, mortgages etc.&rdquo;.  A week later &ldquo;This is not going to happen&rdquo;.  A week later a leaked document from the Department of Finance indicated that that is going to happen.  That is an issue that should be addressed by Government. The facts, as they are available to Government, should be made available to the people.</P>
    <P>I no longer trust economists.  I trust and believe economists when they are assessing, analysing and explaining past events.  They have never yet been correct in forecasting the future.  I listened to many of them spouting on radio and on television, and read their comments in the newspapers about the impact that German unification will have on increasing interest rates.  I also listened to our own Minister for Finance and the Taoiseach denying this.</P>
    <P>None of the economists I listened to gave me a logical reason why the unification of Germany will lead to a rise in interest rates.  On the other hand, the Minister for Finance and the Taoiseach, who did not accept this, did not give an explanation as to why they did not agree with them, either.  Unfortunately, we have a very poor history in this country in regard to making economic facts available to the people.  We have come <Col N="1670" /> through the last decade where at one stage we alternated Taoiseach &mdash; between an accountant who acted like an economist, and an economist who thought he was an accountant.  We never really got anywhere in terms of knowing where we were with economics.</P>
    <P>I have taken the time to study and look at the impact of German re-unification on the interest rates.  The West German economy is the healthiest economy in Western Europe, and if it is not the healthiest and wealthiest in the world it is very close to being so.  The proposal, in terms of exchange rates between the East German Ostmark and the Deutsche Mark and the various exchange rates that have been offered &mdash; one for one, two for one or three for one &mdash; is in black and white.  The population of East German is 16 million.  Each one of those 16 million will be able to convert approximately 4,000 East German Ostmarks for Deutsche Marks on a one to one basis.  It is easy enough to work out the cost of that.  It works out at something like 120 billion Deutsche Marks.</P>
    <P>We are really talking about printing money, printing West German Marks to the extent of 120 billion.  This is a huge amount of money in Irish terms.  It is the total amount of the budget for the Department of Education for one year. In terms of the gross national product of West Germany it works out at less than 5 per cent.  It is important for the Minister for Finance to put that on the record because there is a hype on this issue which is worrying people and is being abused by people in many ways.  The effect of the East German Mark being assimilated into the West German economy will create an inflation of 5 per cent.  This means printing money to the extent of 5 per cent of what is the present GNP of West Germany.  I believe West Germany can handle that very simply.  It can deal with it without any huge increase in interest rates.</P>
    <P>This depends on two things.  It depends on what the people do with the money. We now have the East German who has got 4,000 Deutsche Mark for the first time in his or her life.  Where did they get <Col N="1671" /> the money?  They got the money because in the old regime they saved.  Why did they save?  They had to save because they had nothing to spend the money on in the old regime so they had to put it in the banks.  They are now changing it into real money, they can buy real goods, consumerism will run rampant.  If they spend that money on West German goods, that will heap up the West German economy and will certainly create a certain level of inflation because there will be internal demand paid for by money they have just printed.</P>
    <P>On the other hand, if they spend it on Irish, Italian or Russian products, then it will have an effect on the German balance of trade, the trade surplus, which is extraordinarily healthy at the moment and will certainly absorb some level of that 5 per cent.  That must be thrown into the ball game.  The productivity of East Germany is not being thrown into the mixer at all.  They will not just be coming in sitting around and taking for the rest of their lives.  They will also be working, they will be producing, they will be adding to the economic growth of what will be a united Germany and will create a healthy economy there.  It certainly could lead to interest rates being raised in the rest of Europe but it is not inevitable. The more I look at it, the more I examine it, the less likely I feel it is.  The people who are worrying unnecessarily on this issue should be called to account and asked to prove it.  People are afraid of economists, they are afraid to ask a simple question.  Economists should always be approached in this manner saying, &ldquo;I do not understand the language you are using.  Would you please explain to me how the reunification of Germany will create an increase in my mortgage payments, take me step by step through it.&rdquo;  It is an issue that is there to be discussed.</P>
    <P>I personally welcome the developments towards a reunited Europe.  It is healthy.  Of course, it needs to be monitored. The Community should take every possible step to insist that the assimilation of Eastern Europe into the <Col N="1672" /> community will require the same stringent examination, the same fulfilment of conditions as we required of Portugal, Spain, Greece and we are now requiring of Turkey.  There should be no short cuts taken but at the end of the day we welcome the creation of a new Europe.  I would certainly look forward not just to a united Germany but a single Europe from the Urals to the Atlantic, that we would have a community understanding each others differences, accepting each others differences, a pluralist, multiracial community working for each other, where the question of being aligned on one side of Europe or another would not arise, and where being a European meant something that did not take from one's nationality, whether it be Irish, German, Russian or whatever it is.  I welcome the debate and I look forward to the Minister's reply.</P>
    <Speaker pid="DonLydon" hpid="Mr. Lydon Mr. Lydon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lydon</NameTxt>
      <P>I would like to thank those Senators who contributed to this debate. The contributions have been in a positive vein.  Some have expressed certain reservations and I want to deal with one or two of those.  For example, there is some reservation regarding expansionist policies that might sometimes arise in the future.  I wish to refer to a recent speech made by the President of the Federal Republic of Germany Richard Von Weizsächer at the dinner given in his honour by the President of the Republic of Poland, Mr. Wojciech in Warsaw on 2 May 1990.  He said:</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The central element of a European peace is the obligation of all nations never again to take up the accursed battle for borders and territories.  We Germans are aware of what this means for us with regard to the Poles.  Poland can be fully confident that the border issues between us are irrevocably resolved in substance and that they will be given the necessary contractual form, binding under international law, in the course of the Germany unification process.  Polands' current western border will remain unaffected.  We respect it and have no territorial claims <Col N="1673" /> against Poland or any of our other neighbours now nor will we have any such claims at any time in the future.</P>
    <P>He went on to say:</P>
    <P>The process of German unity is in keeping with a completely normal and human need for a nation that belongs together.  Statesmanship from whatever side can only consist in guiding a natural process of this kind and making use of it for further objectives and cannot consider in hindering it.  The European Community, which we are a member of, will develop more rapidly towards a political union than would have been the case without the German unification process.</P>
    <P>There have been reservations expressed about the whole economic issues.  I would like to remind the Senators that the Germans are not doing this on their own without being carefully monitored by nations outside the Community but, in particular, by the members of the European Community.  The Foreign Ministers of the Twelve meet monthly and they are briefed by the Foreign Minister of the Republic of Germany.  As the Minister for Foreign Affairs, Deputy Collins, said in reply to a question in the Dáil this morning:</P>
    <P>Similar briefings are provided by German Ministers to their colleagues in other Councils, including in particular ECO/FIN and Agriculture.  The special European Council held on 28 April considered the question of German unification and the informal General Affairs Council held in Dublin on 21 April 1990 to prepare for the special European Council considered <i>inter alia</i> a report drawn up by the Commission on the implications for the Community of German unification.</P>
    <P>The whole emphasis from the Commission is that the integration will proceed by stages and it will require transitional measures to facilitate the gradual application of existing Community legislation.</P>
    <P>Some Senators expressed concern <Col N="1674" /> regarding the impact of unification on the budget of the EC.  Figures, even those given by Mr. Delors, must at this stage by guestimates rather than estimates.  The situation will be clarified when the arrangement for the Inter-governmental inter-German Monetary Union are finalised. I will again quote from what the Minister said this morning:</P>
    <P>On the revenue side of the Community budget much will depend on the Commission's view, on the transitional arrangements and the macroeconomic impact of German unification.  In general terms, the Commission expects to see vigorous economic growth in the GDR, generating higher demand throughout the Community and an increase in imports from other member states.  This additional growth, which could add up to one half of 1 per cent of the Community GNP, will be reflected in additional revenue to the EC budget.  On the expenditure side, the cost will largely be determined by the impact of integration on a Common Agricultural Policy and the scale of intervention under the Structural Funds.</P>
    <P>On the question of Structural Funds, in reply to another question, the Minister referred to a statement made by Chancellor Kohl which says:</P>
    <P>German unification will not affect commitments already made to a member state regarding Structural Funds and these will be fully met.</P>
    <P>He also said:</P>
    <P>The European Council said that the Community will ensure that the integration of the territory of the GDR is accomplished in a smooth and harmonious way.  The heads of State and Government were satisfied that this integration would contribute to faster economic growth in the Community.</P>
    <P>Some Senators expressed concern also that some of the events that occurred many years ago during the Second World War would reccur.  Nobody can say that <Col N="1675" /> they will or they will not, but the statements from every person in Germany at the present time, and for many years since the war, have said the opposite. In my opening speech on this motion, I referred to a statement made by Chancellor Kohl of the Federal Republic of Germany on 1 September 1989 on the occasion of the 50th anniversary of the beginning of World War II when he said:</P>
    <P>We can take pride in our liberal constitution, in which we acknowledge the absolute precedence of human dignity in all areas of life, we reject war and force as a political tool.... and we are committed to the goal of a free and united Germany in a free and united Europe.</P>
    <P>These are hardly the words of warmongers. As Senator O'Toole said, the Germans themselves suffered as much as anybody else and I do not think they ever want to go through this suffering again.</P>
    <P>One of the Senators said it does not make a difference whether this motion is passed or not.  We cannot stop the process even if we wanted to, which I presume we do not.  It does make a difference.  If I were a German, no matter how rich and powerful I was, I think I would be happy <Col N="1676" /> to know that I had a small friend somewhere who agreed with me.  I will finish by referring again to that speech by Chancellor Kohl which he made in September 1989 when he said:</P>
    <P>We envisage a future in which the nations of the world are peacefully united in common freedom and we shall not relax our efforts to make that vision come true.  Remembering 1 September 1939 we know that this is the most valuable legacy we can bequeath on coming generations.</P>
    <P>If German unification can contribute in any way to peace, then I think we should support this.  I believe that it will.  I believe that it will draw together a nation of people who were separated unnecessarily and who, in future, will be a powerhouse of energy in the centre of Europe taking their place rightfully in the European community.  I commend this motion to the House.  I hope that it has the unanimous support of all the Members present.</P>
    <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
    <P>The Seanad adjourned at 8.35 p.m. until 10.30 a.m. on Thursday, 10 May 1990.</P>
  </MainHeading>
</Debate>