<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE Debate SYSTEM "../Debate.dtd"[]>
<Debate DocTitle="Seanad Debate" Day="Wed" Date="22" Month="Jan" Year="1992" Vol="131" No="1" DateIrish="Dé Céadaoin, 22 Eanáir 1992" DateEnglish="Wednesday, 22 January 1992" House="S" CommitteeEng="" CommitteeIr="" SubNameEng="" cnum="0">
  <MainHeading Type="Prelude" LHead="" RHead="">
    <Title>
    </Title>
    <P Just="Center">
      <Col N="1" />
      <Col N="2" /> Chuaigh an Leas-Chathaoirleach i gceannas ar 2.30 p.m.</P>
    <P Just="Center">
      <i>Paidir.</i>
    </P>
    <P Just="Center">
      <i>Prayer.</i>
    </P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Resignation of" RHead="Cathaoirleach">
    <Title>Resignation of Cathaoirleach.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>In accordance with Standing Order 10 I now call on the Clerk of the Seanad.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Clerk of Seanad Clerk of Seanad">
      <NameTxt>Clerk of Seanad</NameTxt>
      <P>Faoi Bhuan-Ordú 10 de na Buan-Orduithe i dtaobh Gnó Phoiblí, tá orm a chur in iúl don Seanad go bhfuair mé an litir seo a leanas:</P>
      <P>Pursuant to Standing Order 10 of the Standing Orders relative to Public Business I have to report to the Seanad that I have received the following letter:</P>
      <P>22 January 1992.</P>
      <P>Dear Ms. Lane,</P>
      <P>It is with profound regret that I find it necessary to ask you to notify Seanad Éireann of my resignation from the Office of Cathaoirleach.  I find it necessary to do this to preserve the Office of the Cathaoirleach and to preserve the integrity of the House from any impact resulting from last night's disclosures.</P>
      <P>It remains my duty to say a special thanks to all Members of the House for their courtesy, co-operation and understanding during the period I held the Office of Cathaoirleach.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I wish to express my sincere appreciation to my county colleague and Leas-Chathaoirleach, Senator Liam Naughten, likewise, the Leader of the House, Senator Seán Fallon, and the group leaders &mdash; Senator Maurice Manning, Senator Joe O'Toole, Senator Pat Upton and Senator John Dardis, together with the Party Whips.  To the panel of temporary Chairmen I also <Col N="3" /> express my gratitude.</P>
    <P>To the Political Correspondents in the Seanad I wish to convey a sincere thank you.</P>
    <P>I would like to put a special tribute on the record to yourself, as Clerk of the Seanad, for your invaluable advice and guidance on so many matters, and through you to the Clerk Assistant who on so many occasions gave similar assistance.  Equally, to the other members of the office staff my sincere gratitude and appreciation.</P>
    <P>To my colleagues on the Committee of Procedure and Privileges, please continue with the Reform Programme Recommendations as it can only contribute to the enhancement and public awareness of this House that all of us respect.</P>
    <P>I truly enjoyed the experience, honour and distinction of being the Cathaoirleach of this most prestigious House.</P>
    <P>Yours sincerely,</P>
    <P>(Signed) Seán Doherty.</P>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>In accordance with Standing Order 10 it is now necessary that an Order be made fixing a date for the election of Cathaoirleach.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Fixing of Date for the Election" RHead="of Cathaoirleach: Motion">
    <Title>Fixing of Date for the Election of Cathaoirleach: Motion.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFallon" hpid="Mr. Fallon Mr. Fallon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Fallon</NameTxt>
      <P>I move:</P>
      <P>That the date for the election of Cathaoirleach be tomorrow at 2.30 p.m.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>It is desirable that the Seanad now proceed to the election of a Cathaoirleach as soon as possible.  I propose that a meeting be fixed for tomorrow at 2.30 p.m. for that specific purpose.  This motion should not lend itself to a wide-ranging debate but, because of the interest in the matter, I am prepared to allow a debate to conclude not later than 5.30 p.m.  If the House feels that the debate should be extended by half an hour that may be <Col N="4" /> done at 5.30 p.m. and I would have no objection to it.  In making this suggestion I am not attempting to indicate in any way that the debate be stifled; I do so in the full knowledge that a full ranging debate should take place.  In regard to today's debate it is proposed that all speeches shall not exceed ten minutes.</P>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Is the allocation of time proposal agreed?  Agreed.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnMurphy2" hpid="Professor Murphy Professor Murphy">
      <NameTxt>Professor Murphy</NameTxt>
      <P>On a point of information, what has happened to the Order of Business on foot of which we were summoned here today?  We were brought here today to discuss Seanad business and now we are being diverted by a further instalment of this soap opera.  We should not be distracted from our business and we should proceed to a proper Order of Business.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>The resignation of the Cathaoirleach must be dealt with first.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnMurphy2" hpid="Professor Murphy Professor Murphy">
      <NameTxt>Professor Murphy</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes, but I do not see why we should have to talk about that for the next three and a half hours.  The man has resigned and that is the end of it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I asked if the proposal was agreed.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnMurphy2" hpid="Professor Murphy Professor Murphy">
      <NameTxt>Professor Murphy</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not agree to it. I would like to be recorded as not agreeing to this distraction.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>The Senator's discussion will be recorded.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFallon" hpid="Mr. Fallon Mr. Fallon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Fallon</NameTxt>
      <P>All the Whips agreed to this procedure.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MauriceManning" hpid="Mr. Manning Mr. Manning">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Manning</NameTxt>
      <P>I would like to say to the outgoing Cathaoirleach a word of thanks for the way in which he conducted himself in the Chair.  I found him courteous and helpful at all times and I know he genuinely wanted to pursue the programme of reform which had begun of late and which, I hope, will be continued.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="5" /> We have before us today two verions of the same event, the version of the outgoing Cathaoirleach, Senator Séan Doherty, and the more recent version of the Taoiseach which we heard over the last few hours.  Before deciding which version we believe, it is important to recall that what we are talking about is one of the most sordid episodes in recent history.  What we are talking about is a flagrant violation and invasion of human rights.  That was done not in the interests of the State or of the higher national interest but as a means whereby certain Ministers were spied upon.  That was the purpose of the episode we are discussing today.  The people who were spied upon were not criminals, potential criminals or subversives.  They were Cabinet Ministers and working journalists of the highest repute.  The Ministers had taken an oath under the Constitution to uphold that Constitution.  That is the central episode we are discussing today.  It was shameful ten years ago and it has continued to cast a shadow of shame over our public life since then.  It is something for which the Taoiseach never apologised or acknowledged responsibility.</P>
    <P>Nine years have passed and Senator Doherty has now made available his revised version of those events.  We have to decide today who we believe.</P>
    <P>Not only have we in this House to make that decision but the people of Ireland have to decide, and are making their minds up as to whose version of these events they believe.  I believe Senator Doherty's version.  I believe he was truthful when he said the Taoiseach knew what was happening and was truthful when he said that by implication the Taoiseach condoned what was being done.  I believe the Taoiseach, in the short term, benefited from the information which was made available to him. What is very clear is that the Taoiseach, knowing what was happening, made no attempt to stop it or to censure the person who was carrying it out.</P>
    <P>Over the past few hours there was a chance to listen to the defence put forward by the Taoiseach on the radio.  It was not a convincing defence.  We were <Col N="6" /> told that this is another instalment in the ongoing move against him by groups within his own party.  Deputies Albert Reynolds and Pádraig Flynn were singled out on this occasion as the main co-conspirators. All I can say is that it makes a difference from British spies, the normal people who are rolled out on occasions like this.  What we got from the Taoiseach was the same old conspiracy theory, blanket denials and, quite honestly, it simply will not wash any longer with the people of this country.  We got a character assassination of Senator Doherty from the Taoiseach today, all of that from a man who had been a colleague and a friend a few very short years ago.  It was not a pretty sight and one which very few people found convincing.</P>
    <P>I do not know why Senator Doherty chose this particular moment to do what he did, but I think I understand some of the reasons he did at last go public on his full version of the events.  I find his reasons credible.  What Senator Doherty has done is to sacrifice the highest office this House can bestow, he has sacrificed membership of the Council of State, he has invited scorn, ridicule and hatred upon himself and the almost certain expulsion from his own political party, and he may well have irretrievably damaged his political career.  He has done all that and has allowed this character assassination in because, I believe, he wanted at last to tell what he believed to be the true version of events.  I believe the truth of this matter has been welling up inside him for a very long time and at last he has put that truth on the record. In doing that, he had very little to gain. I believe what he said is true, in spite of a decade of cover up and lies and, indeed, many episodes which did him very little credit.  I believe his version; the Taoiseach stands indicted before Irish society today.  I believe he is unfit to stay on as Taoiseach, and that he should resign now.  As long as this Taoiseach stays, the contagious disease in public life will spread its web of cronyism, strokes, deals and low standards in high places.  It is time this Taoiseach went.  The vast majority of people in this House and <Col N="7" /> outside agree with me in their hearts when I say it is time this Taoiseach resigned.</P>
    <P>He is not the only one who should go.  Last week Senator Doherty let it be known that at least one other member of Cabinet, a Minister of the present Cabinet who was in Cabinet then, was also complicit in the telephone tapping affair. I call on Senator Doherty today to name that Minister and to let us have an end, once and for all, to the innuendo, the winks and the nods and the entire coverup. There are others who today are putting great distance between themselves and the Taoiseach, Deputy Haughey.  At that time they were among his most intimate and triumphalist supporters, people who fed his paranoia and power obsessions, people who saw enemies all round, people who created the environment in which the tapping took place and was condoned and became an acceptable way of doing political business.  These people too should be named and they should be asked to pay the same political price the Cathaoirleach is today paying.</P>
    <P>I believe that Senator Doherty did the State a service by coming clean.  He has ensured at least that we can now get to the bottom of this whole sordid episode. The Taoiseach has only one final service he can do this State, that is, to resign and preferably call a general election.  He must either resign or go to the country but he cannot continue to hang on.  I know, and everybody else here knows from experience, what exactly he will do. He will clutch at every straw, use every device and stratagem to maintain his hold on power, irrespective of the damage to the public, to the public perception of politics, to truth, to human rights, irrespective of the damage he is doing to his own party and to the supporters of his own party who in their souls know what he should do.</P>
    <P>On this strange day in the Seanad, I call upon the Taoiseach to set in train moves to set up the inquiry into the events of those years.  That can be done, but even if it is done it is not enough. The Taoiseach must resign or go to the <Col N="8" /> country.  Those are the only options which the people will accept.</P>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFallon" hpid="Mr. Fallon Mr. Fallon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Fallon</NameTxt>
      <P>I am saddened this occasion has arisen and that today we are debating a letter of resignation from the Cathaoirleach of the Seanad, Senator Doherty.  I prefer to address my sentiments to that letter and to Senator Doherty whom we know as Cathaoirleach of the Seanad.</P>
      <P>He has been a controversial political figure practically all his life but while in the Chair I found him to be a competent Cathaoirleach.  He was witty and quick. He had a flair for the job.  I regret he is not here with us as Cathaoirleach of the Seanad when we should be doing our normal Seanad business, the Patents Bill and the other legislation.  He is controversial &mdash; that has been his middle name for a long time.  From time to time, people found it difficult to understand the man.  He is a person of great charm, he is a good listener, a good debater and a good talker.  He was very innovative on the Committee on Procedure and Privileges and many of the proposals put forward at the Committee on Procedure and Privileges for the enhancement of the role of the Seanad were his ideas.  More than anyone, he was responsible for the progress made to ensure we will have a better Seanad in the future.  May I repeat that I regret he is not with us.  He has made the supreme sacrifice.  Whatever role he may play in the future, whether in the political or private sphere, to wish him every success in that role.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="CarmencitaHederman" hpid="Mrs. Hederman Mrs. Hederman">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Hederman</NameTxt>
      <P>In some ways this is a sad occasion.  Certainly it is a sad occasion for the former Cathaoirleach.  I respect Senator Doherty's decision to resign as Cathaoirleach of this Chamber for whatever reason.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I do not agree with Senator Manning that we or the people of Ireland have to decide which version of this story to believe.  I am convinced the people have far more pressing problems on their mind at this time than to waste too much time debating, discussing and worrying about this issue nine years later.  It seems to me <Col N="9" /> to lack importance today.  I do not know who is lying.  I do not know whether Deputy Haughey or Senator Doherty is lying but I am not going to waste too much time making up my mind.  Clearly one of them is lying and I believe we will never know the truth.  I believe it will never be resolved nine years after these episodes.  I think it is all totally irrelevant today and we should stop wasting the time of this Chamber this afternoon.</P>
    <P>We should spend the time considering the massive problems we face.  For the past six months we have had the &ldquo;knock Charlie brigade&rdquo;, the &ldquo;knock Charlie&rdquo; campaign and while that has been going on from all sides this country has lacked leadership and matters of major importance have been neglected.  The position is similar to that of a company that has no board of directors and no executive directors working effectively to run the company.  Sadly, that is the situation we have in this country; we have in-fighting in the boardroom while the country goes down the tubes.</P>
    <P>This House should address itself to the political malaise which permeates this country.  This morning I heard Deputy Tunney in a radio interview say the politicians were not behaving in the way that the people of this country had a right to expect them to behave.  I fully endorse that statement.  The reality is that this country has lost confidence in politicians in all of the political parties.  I do not think that it would make a very great difference to have Deputy O'Rourke or any other Deputy take over from Mr. Haughey as Taoiseach.  I will go further and say that if we had an election and if we had Deputy Bruton or Deputy Spring as Taoiseach I do not think that things would turn out very differently.</P>
    <P>What the people are concerned about now is not the events of nine years ago but about having a Government that will run this country effectively and will examine the massive problems we have. We have a national debt of about £25 billion, and that, with the other problems we have, leading to unemployment and to many social problems, is what should be addressed.  Instead, what have we got?</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="10" /> We are in a hole and we are digging ourselves deeper and deeper into it.  We are digging a bigger hole by increasing our borrowing for day-to-day items.  We must declare war on the national debt. We must declare war on unemployment. We must put this country on a war footing. What sort of policies and attitudes are needed at a time of national crisis such as this?</P>
    <Speaker pid="JohnHarte" hpid="Mr. Harte Mr. Harte">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Harte</NameTxt>
      <P>On a point of order, a proposition has been put to us by the Leader of the House and it has not been agreed yet but it appears we are slipping into the debate.  There are people with other points of view who might want to put down an amendment to the proposal made by the Leader of the House but we have now slipped into this debate without actually having agreed to take it.  Could the Leas-Chathaoirleach advise me in relation to procedure?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>We are discussing the proposal to fix the date and time for the election of the Cathaoirleach. I put the allocation of time proposal to the House and asked if it was agreed and it was agreed.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnHarte" hpid="Mr. Harte Mr. Harte">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Harte</NameTxt>
      <P>It was agreed.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Senators Senators">
      <NameTxt>Senators</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnMurphy2" hpid="Professor Murphy Professor Murphy">
      <NameTxt>Professor Murphy</NameTxt>
      <P>What are we discussing now?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>We are now discussing the fixing of the date for the election of the Cathaoirleach.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnMurphy2" hpid="Professor Murphy Professor Murphy">
      <NameTxt>Professor Murphy</NameTxt>
      <P>That is not the trend of the debate, I must say.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeCostelloLAB" hpid="Mr. Costello Mr. Costello">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Costello</NameTxt>
      <P>On a point of order, the rest of the agenda has not been considered so far.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MauriceManning" hpid="Mr. Manning Mr. Manning">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Manning</NameTxt>
      <P>What was done today was agreed by the Whips beforehand and it was agreed there now.  It is somewhat out of order by people to come in and try to question that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="11" />
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I am calling Senator Hederman.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeCostelloLAB" hpid="Mr. Costello Mr. Costello">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Costello</NameTxt>
      <P>What we want is some clarification because there are motions of no confidence in the Taoiseach and in the Government.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>The motions of no confidence have been circulated in the normal way and will be printed.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeCostelloLAB" hpid="Mr. Costello Mr. Costello">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Costello</NameTxt>
      <P>And they will be dealt with separately?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="CarmencitaHederman" hpid="Mrs. Hederman Mrs. Hederman">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Hederman</NameTxt>
      <P>A Leas-Chathaoirligh, could you please tell me how much time I have left?  I ask for clarification in view of the interruptions.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>The Senator has three minutes remaining.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="CarmencitaHederman" hpid="Mrs. Hederman Mrs. Hederman">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Hederman</NameTxt>
      <P>Thank you, I shall not need longer than that to finish what I have to say.</P>
      <P>I believe we need to put aside the kind of confrontational politics we have in this country, both in this Chamber and in the Dáil.  I believe that if we were to ask the people what they want now they would not say they want an election because they do not believe an election will solve anything.  We will have more of the same, we will have more of the political party bickering and in-fighting that has gone on both within parties and between parties.  I think that what the people of Ireland want now is for their politicians, the people whom they selected to rule this country, to do precisely that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>While the political parties sort out the mess they are in, I ask myself whether it is not time for us to address ourselves to the question of a national Government for a couple of years at least, so that we can get this country back on to a stable footing, so that we can provide a future in ths country for our young people and give the unemployed hope that some day they will find a job here.  If we look at those issues I believe that we would stop the practice that has evolved in the Dáil <Col N="12" /> over the past six months when the country had no leadership and no proper Government.  I ask the members of every political party to consider whether it is worth while going down the road we are taking and spending the time here this afternoon in an exercise which I consider to be useless and futile.  We should now be seriously addressing the problems of the country.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MartinCullen" hpid="Mr. Cullen Mr. Cullen">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cullen</NameTxt>
      <P>It is sad that this debate should have to take place because a Cathaoirleach had to resign office.</P>
      <P>At the outset I should like to say that I found Senator Doherty most helpful and courteous when he held the Chair of this House.  Nevertheless, the issue that led to his resignation was precipitated over the past number of days by Senator Doherty himself when he lit the fuse on a television programme, &ldquo;Nighthawks&rdquo;. His comments on the television programme left unanswered many serious questions.  Since that date, Senator Doherty chose to hold a press conference last evening and he went further on the record by describing events in which he was directly involved as Minister for Justice some ten years ago.  That, he feels, impugns him in his ability to carry out the role of Cathaoirleach in this House.</P>
      <P>After Senator Doherty had appeared on the &ldquo;Nighthawks&rdquo; programme Senator Dardis and I said we were deeply concerned about what he had said and seriously questioned whether he was fit to continue in office as Cathaoirleach, even at that point, given the political input of what he had said on that programme. I am and have been convinced and have been proved correct, as have my Progressive Democrat colleagues, that that was an impossible task.</P>
      <P>The reasons given by Senator Doherty for his resignation as Cathaoirleach led to a response from the Taoiseach at lunchtime today. The Taoiseach's response completely contradicts what Senator Doherty claimed occurred during what is euphemistically called the &ldquo;phone tapping affair&rdquo; of several years ago.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="13" /> Obviously, that presents a serious problem to all of us in the House and, indeed, to the public at large.</P>
    <P>It is fair to say at the outset that it is, first and foremost, a problem for the Fianna Fáil Party.  Once again they have an internal problem with two completely differing opinions as to what occurred in the past.  It is a matter on which I would expect the Fianna Fáil Parliamentary Party to meet if not now, certainly this afternoon, to have a full discussion and decide for themselves who to believe in this matter.  If they do not meet today or this evening it will be a great surprise to me, to my colleagues and to my party.  It is a most grave matter particularly for Fianna Fáil.  First and foremost they must decide who is telling the truth.  I will not make any pronouncements at present either on my own behalf or that of my party.  I would rather leave our colleagues in Government the time to have their own parliamentary meeting and make a decision without putting them in a particular corner.</P>
    <P>The telephone tapping Bill, referred to by Senator Doherty, has been on public record as Progressive Democrats policy since the foundation of the party.  It was not pursued by the Progressive Democrats, either in or out of Government, to pillory Senator Doherty or any other individual.  That suggestion is incorrect and does not do justice to the worth of the proposed telephone tapping Bill. Unlike the previous Coalition Government, who had the same matter in hand but did not bring it to a legislative conclusion, this Government are determined to do so.  I am proud that that has been my party's public position both in Opposition and in Government.</P>
    <P>The contents of that Bill are recognised not alone by all Members of this House but by all Members of the Dáil as being beneficial in setting out more stringent and specific guidelines on how those procedures could be carried out legally so that justice will be seen to be done.  It was wrong of Senator Doherty to suggest that it was to pursue him personally that the Progressive Democrats wanted to see this Bill enacted.  I do not believe for one <Col N="14" /> minute that anybody inside or outside this House believes that.  It is in the national interest that that Bill be enacted.</P>
    <P>This is regrettable when we are approaching budget day and have reached agreement on the <i>Programme for Economic and Social Progress</i> with the social partners.  It was because of the goodwill generated by workers not pursuing strikes that agreement has been reached between the Government and the social partners, setting a solid foundation for necessary job creation.  This Government and the Progressive Democrats' participation in it have clearly always been policy driven.  That is our aim.  We want to see a reduction in the serious levels of unemployment.  Unfortunately these matters divert our attention from the urgent and pressing matters that concern the majority of the people. Nevertheless, they have to be faced up to.  It is up to our partners in Government to face this matter this afternoon and choose for themselves who in their own party to believe.</P>
    <P>For the record, the Progressive Democrats did not support the nomination of Senator Doherty as Cathaoirleach in this House.  We had grave reservations at the time and those reservations have now been borne out.  We also opposed and voted against Senator Doherty on a motion of no confidence.  The Progressive Democrats' track record in this House is clear and unequivocal and we have been proved to be correct.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JohnMurphy2" hpid="Professor Murphy Professor Murphy">
      <NameTxt>Professor Murphy</NameTxt>
      <P>Seeing you did not want to be here in the first place.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MartinCullen" hpid="Mr. Cullen Mr. Cullen">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cullen</NameTxt>
      <P>Since the Senator is unclear as to what we are debating&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidNorris" hpid="Mr. Norris Mr. Norris">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norris</NameTxt>
      <P>You voted for him.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MartinCullen" hpid="Mr. Cullen Mr. Cullen">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cullen</NameTxt>
      <P>I will speak for myself, Senator Norris, at any time.</P>
      <P>
        <i>(Interruptions.)</i>
      </P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MartinCullen" hpid="Mr. Cullen Mr. Cullen">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cullen</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not need you or any of your colleagues to put the record straight on my behalf or on behalf of any <Col N="15" /> of my colleagues.  The record speaks for itself and it is accurate.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I ask Senator Cullen to address the Chair.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MartinCullen" hpid="Mr. Cullen Mr. Cullen">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cullen</NameTxt>
      <P>The Progressive Democrats are anxious to see this matter resolved.  We are anxious that our partners in Government should look at it themselves, that they should come to a conclusion and make that conclusion public, and hopefully that will allow for continued excellence in Government in the national interest.  That is what is required and what we hope to see happening.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Before I call the next speaker, I am sure Members will join with me in extending a very warm welcome to a former Leas-Chathaoirleach, Mr. Pat Lindsay.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatUpton" hpid="Dr. Upton Dr. Upton">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Upton</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator Doherty has done the proper thing in resigning.  It is essential that the office of Cathaoirleach should not be damaged or compromised. The developments of last evening and today would certainly have damaged the House and the office of Cathaoirleach if Senator Doherty had remained on in that position.</P>
      <P>He has acted properly in resigning even if the manner of his going has plunged this Government and Fianna Fáil into disarray.  The protection of this House and the protection of the office of Cathaoirleach, one of the great institutions of the State, is more important than any turbulence Fianna Fáil or the Government will have to endure as a result of what happened.  If the resolution of that turbulence, of the problems we are now experiencing, demands that a general election be held, so be it.  I would welcome such a development.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>In relation to Senator Doherty personally and the manner in which he conducted his business as Cathaoirleach, my experience has been that he was fair and courteous to me and my party, the Labour Party.  The telephone tapping <Col N="16" /> incidents of the early eighties which have caused this problem were appalling by any standards.  They were an invasion of privacy; they were an invasion of the human rights of two journalists who were doing their jobs.  It was worthy that those journalists had the opportunity to vindicate their names in the courts but it was dreadful that they were forced to take this action to clear their names.</P>
    <P>The question now is, who is to be believed?  There is a direct conflict between the statement of Senator Doherty last night and the statements made by the Taoiseach this afternoon at his press conference.  Clearly one or both of these people is telling lies.  This is the second occasion where the Taoiseach has been involved in a situation like this.  Mr. Justice Henchy claimed that the Taoiseach or another former Minister perjured themselves during a court case.  I repeat, this is the second occasion Deputy Haughey has found himself in this position in relation to whether he is telling the truth.</P>
    <P>There is one point in particular to which I want to draw the attention of the House in relation to the statement issued by Senator Doherty last night.  It relates to the last paragraph which is as follows:</P>
    <P>Each and every one of these relevant transcripts were transported by me to Mr. Haughey's office and handed to him directly.  He retained all but one of them making no comment on their content.</P>
    <P>I would like to know what has become of the transcript which the Taoiseach did not retain.  I ask Senator Doherty to clarify this matter, to tell us what became of it.  I cannot help wondering if the contents of that transcript are not another powder keg which we will find exploding on our television screens on the news at 9 p.m. in the months ahead.  I would welcome if Senator Doherty let us know what has become of the transcript he says the Taoiseach did not retain.  The Taoiseach seems to have inferred that the tapes were given to him by Senator Doherty over a period of time.  A careful reading <Col N="17" /> of Senator Doherty's statement would indicate that that was not in it.</P>
    <P>I come now to the position of the Progressive Democrats.  Following the statement by Senator Cullen I should like to ask what is the position of the Progressive Democrats now?  Senator Cullen was correct in stating that his party did not vote for Senator Doherty when the election of Cathaoirleach took place and did not vote confidence in Senator Doherty when the motion of no confidence in him as Cathaoirleach of this House was taken. However, they voted confidence in the Taoiseach and they voted to put him into office.  I repeat the Taoiseach is now in that 50:50 situation with Senator Doherty in relation to who should be believed.</P>
    <P>I am somewhat puzzled in relation to the conducting of the business this afternoon. It certainly is a change and, to some extent, that is understandable.  I propose that the Labour Party motion of no confidence in the Taoiseach which has been tabled be taken at the end of this debate.  If that is not possible, and if it is not in accord with Standing Orders, I will move that the motion be taken at the earliest opportunity.  I will be proposing that the motion be taken if we have what could be called an old fashioned Order of Business later this evening when this debate concludes.</P>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I clarified that when I said that the motion was circulated but not printed.  It will be printed on the Order Paper tonight.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatUpton" hpid="Dr. Upton Dr. Upton">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Upton</NameTxt>
      <P>The business we are discussing has been dragging on and on.  In some ways it has been going on since Deputy Haughey entered Irish politics but certainly it has been at an acute phase for the past ten years or so.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>In the national interest the matter should be resolved now.  A recurring stench of corruption and a recurring smell of sharp practice has emerged which is just as horrible and repulsive as it was when it first appeared nine or ten years ago.  The Irish people demand that the ghosts of GUBU be exorcised once and for all.  The only way that can be done is by <Col N="18" /> the resignation of the Taoiseach, Deputy Haughey.  In many ways what we have seen in the past 24 hours is a pathetic farce which is turning this country with all its problems into a laughing stock.  In any other country the politicians would be facing up to the real issues and would not be involved in this type of turmoil. The Taoiseach has been rendered incredible by the statements made last night. He is mortally wounded politically and I cannot see him recovering.  It is in all our interests, and in the national interest, that he should go immediately.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PaddyMcGowan" hpid="Mr. McGowan Mr. McGowan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGowan</NameTxt>
      <P>I join with other Members in expressing my regret that the Cathaoirleach has had to resign.  Senator Doherty was an excellent Cathaoirleach. I admired the calm way in which he handled the business of this House.  Many pious platitudes have been expressed today.  I feel sorry for Senator Doherty if he is depending on the sympathy, understanding, co-operation and help of those who have consistently tried to make it difficult for him to chair the proceedings in this House.  While he was Cathaoirleach his rulings were challenged, were the subject of a High Court case&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidNorris" hpid="Mr. Norris Mr. Norris">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norris</NameTxt>
      <P>Hear, hear.  That was a very good thing too.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PaddyMcGowan" hpid="Mr. McGowan Mr. McGowan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGowan</NameTxt>
      <P>I have never interrupted Senator Norris.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator McGowan to continue without interruption.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidNorris" hpid="Mr. Norris Mr. Norris">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norris</NameTxt>
      <P>The Senator is always interrupting.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PaddyMcGowan" hpid="Mr. McGowan Mr. McGowan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGowan</NameTxt>
      <P>Some Members keep themselves in the public eye by interrupting on the Order of Business and by raising current topics whether they are in order or not.  I will not name them in the hope that we will have harmony.  I try to practice what I preach in the House.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BrendanRyan" hpid="Mr. B. Ryan Mr. B. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. B. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>Will the Senator tell us about who he is talking?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="19" />
    <Speaker pid="PaddyMcGowan" hpid="Mr. McGowan Mr. McGowan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGowan</NameTxt>
      <P>I will not respond to that.  I hope Senator Doherty has a future that does not depend on the crocodile tears coming from the Opposition side. His future will not be great if he is depending on those who are now expressing sympathy for him and saying how great he was.  If he is it would be better for him to bow out.  I take with a pinch of salt all the groans, moans, regrets and the expressions of sorrow which came from the Opposition side of the House. All they are doing is using Senator Doherty and the Seanad to knife the leader of our party.  Senator Upton was honest when he said they had only one goal.  Fianna Fáil have been in the enviable position of being able to elect a Taoiseach, even with the help of the Progressive Democrats.  It is not surprising people are envious when one is a fragment of a party that will never be part of anything other than an arrogant group of right wingers.  That is what they are.  They are going nowhere and they have nothing to contribute.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BrendanRyan" hpid="Mr. B. Ryan Mr. B. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. B. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>Will Senator McGowan tell us about whom he is talking?  He is looking over my shoulder.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator McGowan to continue without interruption.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PaddyMcGowan" hpid="Mr. McGowan Mr. McGowan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGowan</NameTxt>
      <P>I am not looking in Senator Ryan's direction because he told this House he came from good Fianna Fáil stock.  I am not looking in his direction.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I ask Senator McGowan to address the motion before the House.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BrendanRyan" hpid="Mr. B. Ryan Mr. B. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. B. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>This is the first time I have ever been called a right winger.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PaddyMcGowan" hpid="Mr. McGowan Mr. McGowan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGowan</NameTxt>
      <P>I sincerely hope that when a Cathaoirleach resigns we will fill the vacancy in an orderly manner.  We should get on with the election of a <Col N="20" /> Cathaoirleach.  I agree with Senator Hederman that we spend much time complaining that we are not efficient.  We should elect a Cathaoirleach and get on with our business.  I came in here today intending to raise the slaughter of workmen in the North of Ireland.  Due to the change in the Order of Business to permit the election of a Cathaoirleach, I am deprived from raising a fundamental matter.  I am an Ulsterman who is concerned about workmen who were slaughtered in the North of Ireland.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>That is not relevant to this debate.  The Order of Business will be dealt at the end of this debate.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PaddyMcGowan" hpid="Mr. McGowan Mr. McGowan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGowan</NameTxt>
      <P>I agree there is urgent business to be dealt with.  Before the House adjourns tomorrow I expect I will have an opportunity to raise matters of fundamental importance in the part of the country I represent.  I would like to see this debate continue in a harmonious manner.  It is my wish that we will have no difficulty in electing a Cathaoirleach tomorrow and that we will proceed to run an orderly Seanad.  I regret Senator Doherty is no longer Cathaoirleach but his decision was taken voluntarily.  We should get on with our business and practice what we preach.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="AvrilDoyle" hpid="Mrs. Doyle Mrs. Doyle">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Doyle</NameTxt>
      <P>At the outset of this discussion on the motion concerning the election of a new Cathaoirleach of the Seanad tomorrow, I would like to offer my thanks to the outgoing Cathaoirleach, Seanator Seán Doherty, for the way he handled matters in this House and for his efforts to be impartial at all times.  There is no doubt that he has been the author of his own misfortune.  I have a particular difficulty addressing the topic before us because I do not believe either the outgoing Cathaoirleach or the Taoiseach even though there are elements of truth in that both of them have said.  There is a great deal of creative accounting in the way they have put forward their own views and the truth lies somewhere between both versions.  I agree with those <Col N="21" /> who say that we will probably never get to the bottom of it.</P>
      <P>Last night Senator Doherty outlined the case as he saw it, of the phone tapping of nine years ago.  He said &ldquo;firstly, the Government was concerned about leaks of confidential material from the Cabinet&rdquo;. It has been said, and I agree, that every Government are concerned about leaks; &ldquo;secondly, it was my job to have these leaks investigated&rdquo;; that is a statement of fact; it was his job to investigate them; and &ldquo;thirdly I did not come up with the idea.  I took the best advice available to me, tapping was the recommended action&rdquo;.  He stated specifically that he had sought the advice of the Deputy Garda Commissioner, Mr. Joe Ainsworth, who was then head of security and &ldquo;communicated to him the concern of members of the Government and my own concern.  Mr. Ainsworth agreed that the leaks were posing a national problem ...and recommended the option of tapping the phone of journalist Bruce Arnold.&rdquo;  Therefore, when Senator Doherty referred last night to the best advice available, he was referring to the advice of Mr. Ainsworth.  He stated that specifically.</P>
      <P>He went on to say &ldquo;fourthly, I signed an official Garda warrant to authorise such activity and finally, I showed the head of Government the results of the tapping&rdquo;.  In everything Senator Doherty said last night there is no indication that the matter was brought to Cabinet for the stamp of approval before phone tapping was initiated or put in place.  If one reads very carefully what Senator Doherty actually said last night, one will see there is no contradiction because all he said was that the Cabinet were originally concerned about leaks and that he came back to Cabinet some time later with the results of the phone tapping.  There is no indication that the Cabinet discussed it in the interim or if either they or the Taoiseach officially knew what was going on.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Let us now look at what the Taoiseach said today.  He stated, and I quote from the transcript of his lunch time press interview, &ldquo;I want to make it crystal clear <Col N="22" /> that the Government as such and I, as Taoiseach, knew absolutely nothing about any activities of this sort and would not countenance any such abuse&rdquo;.  We will leave the last reference to one side for a moment.  He went on to say &ldquo;the Government minutes and records of discussions at Cabinet contain no reference whatsoever to any phone-tapping: and persons who were members of the Government at the time have confirmed that they have no recollection of any reference to the subject&rdquo;.</P>
    <P>One can reconcile much of the Taoiseach's statement today and that of Senator Doherty yesterday.  The real difficulty is that I do not believe C.J. Haughey did not know what was going on.  The Taoiseach officially was not told, the Cabinet officially were not told, but I for one would take a heavy bet that C.J. Haughey knew what was going on There are no records officially anywhere to show that he knew, of course there is not; it would be the nod and the wink and the fixer syndrome at work again.</P>
    <P>Could anyone tell me, given our parliamentary system, that the permanent Government would not have dropped it to the Taoiseach's private secretary or his main advisers if the advisers or the civil servants in the Department of Justice, thought for one moment that Senator Seán Doherty was not going to tell the Taoiseach?  Those of us who have some little experience of Government even at junior ministerial level, know they know what we have for our breakfast, and rightly so, because they are there to do a job for the country.  Everyone right through the system knows exactly what is happening.  The message was definitely passed at permanent Government level. I accept that officially it may not have been given to C J as Taoiseach, but he knew it as C.J. Haughey and I will stand over that any day.</P>
    <P>Why did Senator Seán Doherty rake over the old coals now?  It is obviously a three item agenda.  There is obviously much to be gained from going back to Roscommon as a martyr, as I am sure the Acting Chairman is only too well aware. He is already a type of folk hero there.  I <Col N="23" /> hope, however, the people will open their eyes and see this for what it is.  We have known for many months now of the tragic scandals which have portrayed our country as a corrupt democracy.  We are the laughing stock of the international community, financial and otherwise, and they are looking for the next instalment of the national Irish pantomime at this stage.</P>
    <P>Through all this we have known of the ongoing push and shove in terms of the leadership within Fianna Fáil.  Obviously, Roscommon is number one on the hidden agenda of Senator Seán Doherty; second is the leadership of Fianna Fáil &mdash; I will not try to analyse it myself as I will probably get it wrong.</P>
    <P>The third point &mdash; and perhaps the one which prompted this disclosure at this stage &mdash; is the forthcoming phone tapping Bill to be initiated in the Seanad in a couple of weeks time.  It has been reported that the present Minister for Justice, Deputy Burke, and Senator Seán Doherty had strong words in recent times about the initiation of this legislation and that Senator Doherty felt he had been let down having, in his own words, carried the can for them on this issue for so long.</P>
    <P>If Senator Doherty is telling the truth now he must have perjured himself during the Supreme Court inquiry.  If that is so it must be investigated.  If Senator Doherty is lying now and the Taoiseach is telling the truth, I expect the Taoiseach to take an action for defamation of character against Senator Doherty.  Anything less would not be strong enough evidence that the Taoiseach's version is true.  We await the next move.</P>
    <P>The Taoiseach was acting Minister for Justice for three weeks during Senator Seán Doherty's reign as Minister for Justice. Anyone who knows how the Department of Justice work knows that the Minister for Justice or the acting Minister for Justice gets a daily and weekly intelligence report from his or her officials. As acting Minister for Justice, the Taoiseach, C J Haughey, would have received daily and weekly intelligence reports. Therefore, I do not accept that he would not have heard quite clearly from the <Col N="24" /> Civil Service and public service what was going on.</P>
    <P>Let us not forget that during this time the then Minister Ray MacSharry was bugging or, to put it more correctly, tape recording a fellow Cabinet colleague's phone calls, those of Mr. O'Donoghue. This type of syndrome was pervasive in the Cabinet at the time.  I suppose nobody knew that was going on.  However Ray MacSharry taped a colleague's phone calls; I expect that will be the next story.</P>
    <P>My colleague, Senator Manning, has very succinctly put the case for Fine Gael. He pointed out the violation of human rights which took place during that time. It is a tragedy in this day and age when we are full and equal members of the European Community and the OECD a developed western democracy, that we, in the Upper Chamber of Parliament, rightly accuse a Government of a few short years ago of violating human rights in operating the democratic system.  I thought we had abandoned the banana republic syndrome long ago.  This is a tragedy for all of us because all of us, as public representatives, will find ourselves tarred to some extent and trying to defend democracy, particularly to the young who have become so cynical about the comings and goings in these Houses, and particularly in the Lower House, over the past few months.</P>
    <P>My colleague, Senator Manning, has put the only two options: either the Taoiseach must go or we need a general election. Frankly, we need the cleansing.  I know we will be told the public have no appetite for a general election, but sometimes we have to take medicine when we do not like it; sometimes even the public good can be served by something they do not like.  We have to be very cool and calm in deciding what the next step should be.  I await with interest the response of the Progressive Democrats particularly in relation to what has happened.</P>
    <P>On a personal note, I would again like to thank Senator Seán Doherty and to wish him and his wife, Maura, and family all the best during the next few days and <Col N="25" /> weeks through what must be for him a personal agony.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JohnDardis" hpid="Mr. Dardis Mr. Dardis">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dardis</NameTxt>
      <P>It is my view and that of my party that the Cathaoirleach, Senator Doherty, has done the right thing by resigning his office.  It is our view that it would have become impossible, under Senator Doherty's continuing chairmanship, to conduct the business of this House with any degree of impartiality and authority.  That authority was damaged even before last night.  As has been explained by my colleague, Senator Cullen, the Progressive Democrats abstained in the original vote to elect Senator Doherty as Cathaoirleach on the basis that we had serious reservations as to his capacity to be fair and even-handed in chairing the House.  At the time, we were aware of our responsibilities to our Coalition partners and that is why we abstained rather than voting against.</P>
      <P>We subsequently, as the House is aware, supported a motion to remove the Cathaoirleach from office.  We did so because information had been withheld by him from the Committee on Procedure and Privileges of which I am a member.  That information had been withheld when the committee considered an alleged breach of privilege by Senator Norris.  During the course of that no confidence debate I said that I failed to see how we could continue in this House to operate without what I termed to be a whiff of sulphur.  I appealed directly to the Cathaoirleach to consider his position.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>In that debate, almost two years ago, on 28 March, I said there was a wider interest than our own interest in this House; the interest was that of the country and of the Oireachtas.  In the interest of the credibility of the political process and of the credibility of politicians I appealed directly to the Cathaoirleach at that late stage to reconsider his position. I said I was at a loss to know how we could continue to conduct the affairs of the House without continuing acrimony and without this continuing whiff of sulphur and that in the absence of such a gesture from the Cathaoirleach my party <Col N="26" /> would be supporting the motion of no confidence, which is what we did.</P>
    <P>It is getting to the point that not only do the public not know who to believe but Members of the Oireachtas do not know who to believe.  There are two opposing and contradictory versions of events and, indeed, it is also worth recording that there is a third version of events which differs from the other two, the version contained in Deputy FitzGerald's autobiography which I went through in some detail last night.  Perhaps that would bear some examination.  All we can say with absolute certainty is that somebody is lying, perhaps more than one person is lying.  As to where the truth lies, it is my fervent hope that over the next few days we will establish with some degree of certainty where the truth lies.  I take the view that the truth is indivisible. There is no such thing as a half truth or half a lie.</P>
    <P>None of us can claim that during our lifetime we have not told an untruth but that is not the issue.  There is a solemn responsibility of us as politicians to be even more aware of the necessity to tell the truth than there might be in private life.  There is an overriding responsibility on Members of all parliaments, wherever they are, to tell the truth before the parliament of which they are a Member.  It is worth making those points.  A political lie is no less a lie than any other lie; the public have a right to demand the very highest standards of their public representatives and their very low opinion of politicians, as revealed in recent opinion polls, confirms the onus which I am confident the vast majority of Members of both Houses accept to uphold such standards. It is not a required qualification of politicians to tell lies.</P>
    <P>In that respect I will go back once again to the debate of 28 March 1990 when the House voted confidence in the Cathaoirleach &mdash; and in which my party opposed that vote of confidence &mdash; when I stated that the need for high standards applies to every Member of both Houses of the Oireachtas.  How very much more must it apply to the most important offices of State of which the Cathaoirleach is one.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="27" /> I would add to that another important office of State, that of Taoiseach.  Not only must the standards be upheld, they must be seen to be upheld.  It is precisely because the Progressive Democrats recognise the constitutional importance of the office of Cathaoirleach that they believe the integrity of that office must be upheld, even at the expense of the person holding the office.  I do not think that anything said then or subsequently either on the floor of this House or within the Committee on Procedure and Privileges is different from the original position.</P>
    <P>I should say, lest there is any misunderstanding, that in my experience the Cathaoirleach, both as Cathaoirleach of the Seanad and as Chairman of the Committee on Procedures and Privileges, has at all times treated me with absolute courtesy.  He has been even-handed in all his dealings, nor indeed has he ever allowed any antipathy he might have had &mdash; it would be understandable for him to have such antipathy &mdash; to surface in any of his dealings with me.  For that he has my thanks.  However critical I may have been of the Cathaoirleach within this Chamber and and outside the House he, I must say, ran the business of the House particularly in the last session, calmly and smoothly.  It is my fervent hope that when the present turbulence settles his successor will bring us back on course to implement the reforms now before the Committee on Procedures and Privileges and that we will get on with our legislative programme.  I note in the Cathaoirleach's letter of resignation that he appeals to us to proceed with the reforms which are being discussed at present.  I share the general distaste, which I am sure there is throughout the country, about this matter, this sad and sorry situation.</P>
    <P>This morning Deputy Bruton gave the Progressive Democrats a lecture on their responsibilities to the country.  Deputy Bruton, and his colleagues in this House, may rest assured that my party will &mdash; I am sure this applies to all parties &mdash; fulfil their responsibilities to the country.  It is my wish that we will be able to proceed to <Col N="28" /> address and deal with the very important issues which confront us in relation to our economy, unemployment and the other pressing matters that need our attention. Senator Upton said &mdash; I am not sure what he said&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatUpton" hpid="Dr. Upton Dr. Upton">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Upton</NameTxt>
      <P>The Senator should know, I always say the same thing.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnDardis" hpid="Mr. Dardis Mr. Dardis">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dardis</NameTxt>
      <P>I am quite certain that there is no need to defend our credentials.  Our views on the existence of this House are well known but, as I have stated many times, as long as we are here and as long as this House remains a political institution of the State we will participate to the fullest as democrats in all its processes.  Our record stands up to examination in that respect in the way we have contributed to this House and we will continue to do so.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnMurphy2" hpid="Professor Murphy Professor Murphy">
      <NameTxt>Professor Murphy</NameTxt>
      <P>The Senator will be here as long as he can.  Thanks be to God that in all crises &mdash; if this can be called a crisis &mdash; there are moments of light relief. For me the undisputed moment of light relief was when Deputy Tunney said that the whole crisis left him at a loss for words.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MauriceManning" hpid="Mr. Manning Mr. Manning">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Manning</NameTxt>
      <P>Would that that were so.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnMurphy2" hpid="Professor Murphy Professor Murphy">
      <NameTxt>Professor Murphy</NameTxt>
      <P>He went on, of course, to immediately contradict this at great length.</P>
      <P>More seriously, it is a great pity &mdash; and it is not the first time I have said this &mdash; that Seanad Éireann gets into the limelight only on very notorious occasions. When I come to think of it, most of those notorious occasions have been linked with the outgoing Cathaoirleach.  In fact, the other widely publicised occasion was the Minister for the Gaeltacht's sole visit to his House when he took the Blasket Islands Bill and perhaps there is a link there as well.  I have to say we can do without that kind of notoriety.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>As I said on what I took to be the Order of Business but which was some <Col N="29" /> strange introduction to these proceedings, all this is a scandalous distraction from what we should be about, what we were called here to do today on a clearly indicated Order of Business and from vital matters of national concern which have been alluded to.  We were called here today to adopt the improbable role of referees in a lovers' quarrel, the estrangement of two cronies.  In effect, this is what it is, and the picture the Cathaoirleach drew last night of placing the transcripts on the desk of the Taoiseach fits very well with that picture of cronyism.  To me it is perfectly credible that nobody else saw those transcripts &mdash; he went to the boss, as in a Chicago gangster grade B movie, with his transcripts. This is what we are talking about &mdash; estranged cronies, mutual skulduggery. What business have we discussing that?</P>
    <P>I was much taken by Senator Doyle's incisive contribution and the way in which she said, for example, that Senator Doherty may be off to mobilise the provincial legions.  Let us hope that he does not march them back across the Shannon, burn his boats and cross the Rubicon.  It is true that Senator Doherty is a kind of a Greek tragic figure, in a very minor key let me add.  I do not want to do a particular injustice to Sophocles and others but he is like a figure out of a Greek tragedy because he is the author of his own misfortunes.  Senator Doyle was perfectly right in that respect.</P>
    <P>I must say I was aware of his faults as well as everybody else.  Indeed, I was the victim of some of his indiscretions.  I understand I would have gone to Nicaragua only for his machinations, whether that is true or false, and he evicted me from the House on at least one occasion.  However, I must confess that in a sense I am sorry he is gone.  Whatever his faults, whatever his roguery, he was extremely likeable.  It is one of the extraordinary facts of life, that you like people, that you are seduced by their charm even though on strict moral grounds you should not be.  I like Senator Seán Doherty.  When he had an unfortunate car accident some time ago I wrote <Col N="30" /> to him.  I was very sorry he was involved in the accident.  On a personal level I am sorry he is gone, at least for the moment anyway.</P>
    <P>To return to my point, the resignation of the Cathaoirleach is fundamentally no business of ours; he is gone and that is it. He did not do this House any further discredit than he had already done it.  We had no further quarrel with him than the last occasion on which we discussed a vote of no confidence.  It is Fianna Fáil who have the quarrel with him and it is their business to contemplate the consequences of his resignation.  That is why I believe this business in a sense should not detain us.</P>
    <P>Several quotations spring to mind: for example, &ldquo;It is a far, far better thing that I do, than I have ever done&rdquo;, and putting it more positively, &ldquo;Nothing in his life became him like the leaving it&rdquo;, &ldquo;They will not have Seán Doherty to kick around any more&rdquo;&mdash; of course, that was the prelude to a notorious comeback as well &mdash; and finally, and this is the last point of levity I will make, &ldquo;We have lost him surely, we have the lost the only playboy of the western world&rdquo;.</P>
    <P>Who are we to believe?  We were asked today by the Taoiseach to believe that Senator Doherty is telling further lies.  I have difficulty in accepting that because of the case he made last night as to why he had nothing to gain from this and why he was doing it now.  That squares with what we all know: the Cathaoirleach has said privately to more than one of us that he was hard done by, that he was the victim of a particular wrongdoing and so on and to that extent his announcement was not unexpected.  If he was not telling the truth last night, then he is an absolutely incredibly unprincipled rogue. Either that, or the Taoiseach is an unprincipled rogue.  It is possible, of course, that both of them are unprincipled rogues.</P>
    <Speaker pid="AvrilDoyle" hpid="Mrs. Doyle Mrs. Doyle">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Doyle</NameTxt>
      <P>That is the point.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnMurphy2" hpid="Professor Murphy Professor Murphy">
      <NameTxt>Professor Murphy</NameTxt>
      <P>Unless some official, some secretary or somebody who was in the Taoiseach's office in 1982 <Col N="31" /> comes forward and testifies to the presence of these transcripts or not, we are going to be a long time guessing.  In any case, I agree with those who said it is high time for the Taoiseach to go.  Whatever his contribution to this country and whatever his talents, I have always believed he spent so much time trying to get back to power and influence all through the seventies that when he finally made it to the top he really had no more to contribute. He has contributed very little to this country since 1979, except the exploitation of various crises in the most cynical way to opportunistically promote his own career.</P>
      <P>Dr. Conor Cruise O'Brien has often said that the Taoiseach would stop at nothing to retain power.  All of us would regard that as part of his neurotic obsession about him, but it is a good job the Progressive Democrats, with all their balancing trick of being at once in Government and in highfalutin' moral opposition, are there and I hope they will do their final service to the country in this instance.  It is a good job as well that democracy is there because the Taoiseach, Mr. Charles J. Haughey, has Bonapartist tendencies at the very least. Therefore, it is time he went.  Again, one cannot avoid quoting Shakespeare who seems to have words for all occasions.  At present the Taoiseach is like Macbeth at bay, &ldquo;those he commands move only in command, nothing in love.  Now does he feel his title hang loose about him like a giant robe upon a dwarfish thief&rdquo;.</P>
      <P>I agree with Senator McGowan and Senator Hederman who made the point that there are many vital issues we want to discuss here: the implications of the obscene atrocity last Friday in County Tyrone as well as the more chronic, social and economic problems facing us.  I hope we elect our new Cathaoirleach as quickly as possible and that we get on with our proper business.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TomFitzgerald" hpid="Acting Chairman (Mr. Fitzgerald) Acting Chairman (Mr. Fitzgerald)">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman (Mr. Fitzgerald)</NameTxt>
      <P>Before calling Senator Mooney, in view of what Senator Murphy said at the start of his contribution, I should like to clarify <Col N="32" /> that the Order of Business will be taken after this matter, the fixing of the date for the election of Cathaoirleach, has been concluded.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PaschalMooney" hpid="Mr. Mooney Mr. Mooney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Mooney</NameTxt>
      <P>While I do not always agree with him, I find the contributions of my colleague, Senator Murphy, enlightening, witty and original.  There has been a great deal of talk about assaults on democracy.  As I listened to my colleagues on the other side of the House I could not help but wonder if they are doing any great favour to demoncracy. They somehow seem to think they are outside the democratic process, that any faults, whether real or imagined, are on one side and that they can somehow escape from the shadow which has been cast over political life in several cases in recent months that I believe is unwarranted.</P>
      <P>Like Senator Fallon I will confine my contribution primarily to the role of the former Cathoirleach and his contribution to this House.  I am in a unique position in one respect in that I have known Seán Doherty all my life.  His family come from my home town of Drumshanbo.  His father, a member of a family of four brothers and a sister, was the only one to move across the Shannon to Cootehall. Members of the family live in the Drumshanbo area and I know them all.  Seán Doherty and I have the same <i>alma mater.</i> Although we were not in the same year we were there during the same period.  To use the words of Senator Fallon, Senator Doherty has always been a controversial figure.  Perhaps those of us who know him would say that a certain tradition of controversy surround him.  However, acted honourably, efficiently and courteously and at all times as Cathaoirleach he was conscious of the high honour that had been placed on him and attempted, successfully, to carry out the duties of Cathaoirleach.  This House is the worst for his passing as Cathaoirleach.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="AvrilDoyle" hpid="Mrs. Doyle Mrs. Doyle">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Doyle</NameTxt>
      <P>He is not dead.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PaschalMooney" hpid="Mr. Mooney Mr. Mooney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Mooney</NameTxt>
      <P>I am delighted Senator Doyle has made that comment because <Col N="33" /> one would get the impression listening to many of the comments today that he had passed away rather than resigned from the position of Cathaoirleach.  Those who know Seán Doherty do not believe they are dancing on his political grave today because, knowing the resilience of the former Cathaoirleach and his standing in his native County Roscommon, it is highly unlikely that this temporary passing will have any long term adverse effects on his political career which is far from over.  I hope his family, particularly his daughters will read the transcript of today's contributions because, irrespective of the political barbs that have been shot across the House and the analysis of many of my colleagues on the other side about the travails, real and otherwise, of Fianna Fáil and past Fianna Fáil administrations, what has come through in all contributions is the innate decency of the man in his role as Cathaoirleach.</P>
      <P>In the arena of political debate we sometimes forget the families of the protagonists. I do not think any of us enjoyed the spectacle of the last 24 hours, of listening to the langugage of confrontation first from Senator Doherty last night and today from the Taoiseach.  It has not been a pleasant experience.  It does not reflect well on politics or on the political life of this country that we should be subjected to this type of rhetoric.  I hope the matter has ended, that the issue has been put to bed and, as has been said on all sides of the House, that we can get on with the real business or organising and running this country.  I would say to those people listening to this debate who support Fianna Fáil and who up to now have been hearing about the alleged sins of the party to which they have adhered &mdash; taking the cue from Senator Upton &mdash; I do not believe there is any whiff of corruption about the supporters of Fianna Fáil or about my colleagues on this side of the House.  There is no smell of scandal from this side of the House. Fianna Fáil people are decent people.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="AvrilDoyle" hpid="Mrs. Doyle Mrs. Doyle">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Doyle</NameTxt>
      <P>Does the Senator mean they do not even recognise it when they are confronted with it?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="34" />
    <Speaker pid="PaschalMooney" hpid="Mr. Mooney Mr. Mooney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Mooney</NameTxt>
      <P>Fianna Fáil supporters are decent people who are proud of their tradition, proud of the record of service which is without parallel here.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="AvrilDoyle" hpid="Mrs. Doyle Mrs. Doyle">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Doyle</NameTxt>
      <P>There are decent people in Fianna Fáil who are not proud of this spectacle and the Senator is doing them no service.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Acting Chairman Acting Chairman">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator Mooney should be allowed to continue without interruption.  All Members will have their say.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PaschalMooney" hpid="Mr. Mooney Mr. Mooney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Mooney</NameTxt>
      <P>I am pleased the Chair pointed that out to my colleagues because I listened with mounting anger and great disappointment to the contributions of the other side of the House. I held my tongue and I would expect my colleagues to do the same now that I am on my feet.  They may not agree with what I have to say but I have a right to say it to almost 50 per cent of the people of this country who have consistently supported Fianna Fáil.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnMurphy2" hpid="Professor Murphy Professor Murphy">
      <NameTxt>Professor Murphy</NameTxt>
      <P>The figure is 42 or is it 39 per cent?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PaschalMooney" hpid="Mr. Mooney Mr. Mooney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Mooney</NameTxt>
      <P>The Senator can argue about semantics if he wishes but the essence of my point is that the majority of people have supported Fianna Fáil and would do so again tomorrow.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="AvrilDoyle" hpid="Mrs. Doyle Mrs. Doyle">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Doyle</NameTxt>
      <P>There are decent people in Fianna Fáil who do not like the scandals.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Acting Chairman Acting Chairman">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman</NameTxt>
      <P>The Senator must be allowed continue without further interruption.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PaschalMooney" hpid="Mr. Mooney Mr. Mooney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Mooney</NameTxt>
      <P>I am sick and tired of people branding me, my colleagues on this side of the House and the party we represent as a political pariah.  I accept that in the cut and thrust of debate allegations are made but I am not going to joust with Senator Doyle or the representatives of the Fine Gael Party about what Fianna Fáil have been accused of by <Col N="35" /> retorting with accusations at Fine Gael. That would not in any way, further this debate.  I am not attempting to dance on the grave of an innately decent man who has an innately decent family or of a Taoiseach who has an innately decent wife and family who must be also going through their own anguish at this time. Politics is about much more than this cut and thrust we have been listening to today, and I am only putting on the record that I see that as a greater priority.</P>
      <P>I issue a word of warning to those who have been dancing on the perceived grave of Fianna Fáil today, that in a general election all political parties and all politicians will face the cynical indifference of the general public towards politicians and towards politics as it is practised in this House.  That is a fair assessment.  I should like to say, in response to the calls for a general election, that it would not resolve anything.  It would probably turn this country into the type of banana republic to which Senator Doyle referred.  It is acknowledged on all sides that under the present constituency arrangements it is unlikely any one party would receive an overall majority.  Those of us who contested the local elections in the last six months will testify that there are single issue candidates who are waiting at the gate for the off.  In many cases they would get a response from a weary, indifferent and cynical electorate.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="AvrilDoyle" hpid="Mrs. Doyle Mrs. Doyle">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Doyle</NameTxt>
      <P>Is the Senator afraid of the polls?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PaschalMooney" hpid="Mr. Mooney Mr. Mooney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Mooney</NameTxt>
      <P>As a result of a general election we could be faced with a group of disparate independents who are interested in single issues and with little concern for national interests.  That would not serve any purpose and would certainly not serve the purpose of the governing of this country.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>On a personal level &mdash; I am sorry Senator Doherty has chosen the path he has taken.  His political motives are a matter for him, but I wish him well.  I hope he will resume his contribution to this House as a member of the Fianna <Col N="36" /> Fáil Party and that we can get back, to the issues that matter most here.</P>
    <Speaker pid="LiamTCosgrave" hpid="Mr. Cosgrave Mr. Cosgrave">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cosgrave</NameTxt>
      <P>I regret we are debating such an issue today, particularly in the light of the many real problems affecting the country.  The last speaker referred to the debacle of the past 24 hours.  I agree with his description but he should have gone further.  The debacle over the past four to five months has paralysed our political system and the operation of Government.  The real issues affecting men and women are bringing up families, trying to make ends meet, trying to get jobs, being able to live peacefully and safely in one's house, and in peace on this island.  The dark atrocity in part of this country a few days ago is being overlooked.</P>
      <P>I am sorry Senator Doherty has resigned as Cathaoirleach.  He is a most personable character.  He tried to help Senators in dealing with the business of the House.  It is fair to say he was the author of his own misfortune.  Whatever else this debate does, I hope it will unravel the issues of the past ten years.  I was asked earlier today: which lie do you believe?  Unfortunately, that is what is being asked.  I do not know who to believe; I do not know who is telling more of the truth.  Did we hear the truth today, yesterday, in 1982 or 1983?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>As Senator Doherty has left centre stage, the Taoiseach should follow suit in the national interest.  The two parties in Government will face difficulties.  Let me say to the Taoiseach, and to the other party in Government, that it is time for a change.  The past few months have highlighted the need for this.  Whether the Taoiseach goes today, next week or next month, we will have this internal wrangling in Fianna Fáil.  I do not care who becomes their next leader, but I care about who is running the country and dealing with the many problems bedeviling us.  The internal wrangling in Fianna Fáil has meant that the real issues are not getting the attention they deserve.  Are the Cabinet discussing today how best to frame the budget and the difficulties in <Col N="37" /> Northern Ireland?  Will they be able to discuss the worsening of serious crime here, particularly in urban areas?  Of course not.  They must deal with issues that took place over the past ten years. The public are cynical about the political process; we are all being dragged into this quagmire.  The public are looking for leadership.  Late in the day, as it is, it is important that politicians give that leadership in the coming weeks.</P>
    <P>Let me address the Members on the Government side.  The person they pick to succeed Senator Doherty is their choice.  No doubt well qualified candidates will come forward and I wish the person chosen every good wish in this high office.  The office of Cathaoirleach should not be dragged through every political mudbath and it is important to restore political credibility.  The public are sick to death of the wrangling over the leadership of Fianna Fáil and seeing headlines about who is going to challenge the Taoiseach.  At this difficult time our problems are not being tackled.  The most important thing that may come out of this debate is that Senators will resolve to put events behind them and deal with the real issues.</P>
    <P>Our concern is not who will lead Fianna Fáil in the future but it is high time they elected a new leader.  It is high time the public were given a chance to adjudicate on the Government.  The people are fed up with the mismanagement of the economy.  The real issues are ignored while we sensationalise other matters.  This is damaging further our country's image abroad.  It is time the Taoiseach resigned in the national interest.  We do not know who is telling the truth, or more of the truth, or whether these matters can be verified independently.  What is more serious is that there are major question marks over individuals in high office.  The Taoiseach should follow the action taken by the Cathaoirleach.</P>
    <P>I hope we will proceed to debate the real issues facing the country and will put another sorry mess behind us.  It is up to us to do so.  We were elected to legislate. We are at a crossroads and it is important <Col N="38" /> that Members recognise that.  I ask Members opposite to make the decisions they should have made recently.</P>
    <Speaker pid="AvrilDoyle" hpid="Mrs. Doyle Mrs. Doyle">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Doyle</NameTxt>
      <P>On a point of order, could we have some members of the Fianna Fáil Party in the House to listen to this debate or are they too embarrassed given the topic under discussion?  They should be present to listen to their colleagues address a most important topic.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Acting Chairman Acting Chairman">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman</NameTxt>
      <P>That is not a point of order.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="AvrilDoyle" hpid="Mrs. Doyle Mrs. Doyle">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Doyle</NameTxt>
      <P>We should have a quorum, because democracy demands that the Fianna Fáil Party listen to this most important debate which concerns their Taoiseach, their party and a former Cathaoirleach who is a member of their party.</P>
      <P>
        <i>Notice taken that 12 Members were not present; House counted and 12 Members being present,</i>
      </P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelFinneranFF" hpid="Mr. Finneran Mr. Finneran">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Finneran</NameTxt>
      <P>I am sorry Senator Doyle is upset that there were not a quorum to listen to what she had to say. I was the next speaker and I was not complaining about whether there were sufficient numbers here to listen to me. However, it obviously struck a cord with Senator Doyle, and she has made her point for publicity purposes.  This is not the first occasion she has done that; she is pretty adept at that procedure.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Acting Chairman Acting Chairman">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman</NameTxt>
      <P>I remind the Senator to keep to the business before the House, please.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelFinneranFF" hpid="Mr. Finneran Mr. Finneran">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Finneran</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes, indeed.  Senator Doyle prevented me from starting a minute ago.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="AvrilDoyle" hpid="Mrs. Doyle Mrs. Doyle">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Doyle</NameTxt>
      <P>There was no one to listen to the Senator.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelFinneranFF" hpid="Mr. Finneran Mr. Finneran">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Finneran</NameTxt>
      <P>It is with regret that I listened to Senator Seán Doherty's statement of resignation.  I know Seán Doherty as well, or possibly, better, than <Col N="39" /> most Members of this House.  I remember his first opportunity to enter political life.  I remember when he joined Roscommon County Council; for 12 years I was a member of Roscommon County Council with Seán Doherty.  I remember his first leap into national politics, his first leap to Minister of State and his leap into Cabinet.  I saw the glory days and I saw the sad days, and, to some extent, today is a sad day.  It is a sad day for Senator Doherty and his family.  Seán Doherty is to some people a folk hero; to others he would not have the same appeal, but one thing he does have is an extraordinary personality.  He is a man of great charm and ability.  Seán Doherty has left a mark on Irish politics; some would say it is not a good mark and others might not altogether agree.  As a person, you could not find finer than Seán Doherty.  He is very good company.  On a political level, he is sharp, intellectual, he has a great turn of phrase and he is a good man to throw the shot across the political bow. No Member of this House here today should attempt to dance on his political grave.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="AvrilDoyle" hpid="Mrs. Doyle Mrs. Doyle">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Doyle</NameTxt>
      <P>The Senator's colleagues said that&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Acting Chairman Acting Chairman">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman</NameTxt>
      <P>Please allow the speaker to speak without interruption.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelFinneranFF" hpid="Mr. Finneran Mr. Finneran">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Finneran</NameTxt>
      <P>That, I believe, would be a very foolish thing to do.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="AvrilDoyle" hpid="Mrs. Doyle Mrs. Doyle">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Doyle</NameTxt>
      <P>It was a Fianna Fáil man who suggested that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Acting Chairman Acting Chairman">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator Doyle, please stop interrupting the other speakers. I am sorry to have to caution you regularly.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="AvrilDoyle" hpid="Mrs. Doyle Mrs. Doyle">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Doyle</NameTxt>
      <P>It is very hard to have patience.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Acting Chairman Acting Chairman">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman</NameTxt>
      <P>I ask Senator Doyle to refrain from interrupting.  I call on <Col N="40" /> Senator Finneran to continue, without interruption please.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelFinneranFF" hpid="Mr. Finneran Mr. Finneran">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Finneran</NameTxt>
      <P>Thank you, Sir.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="AvrilDoyle" hpid="Mrs. Doyle Mrs. Doyle">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Doyle</NameTxt>
      <P>Sugary waffle.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Acting Chairman Acting Chairman">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator Doyle, please.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelFinneranFF" hpid="Mr. Finneran Mr. Finneran">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Finneran</NameTxt>
      <P>I did not interrupt the Senator today.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="AvrilDoyle" hpid="Mrs. Doyle Mrs. Doyle">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Doyle</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not think the Senator was here in fact, no one from the other side was in the Chamber.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Acting Chairman Acting Chairman">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator Doyle, please.  Every speaker&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelFinneranFF" hpid="Mr. Finneran Mr. Finneran">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Finneran</NameTxt>
      <P>We did not interrupt the Senator.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="AvrilDoyle" hpid="Mrs. Doyle Mrs. Doyle">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Doyle</NameTxt>
      <P>They could not interrupt me because there was no Fianna Fáil Senator present.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelFinneranFF" hpid="Mr. Finneran Mr. Finneran">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Finneran</NameTxt>
      <P>That is incorrect, Senator.  We were all here.  I was here for&mdash;&mdash;</P>
      <P>
        <i>(Interruptions.)</i>
      </P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Acting Chairman Acting Chairman">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator Doyle&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="AvrilDoyle" hpid="Mrs. Doyle Mrs. Doyle">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Doyle</NameTxt>
      <P>There was no fear of my being interrupted.  They were all downstairs.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardConroy" hpid="Professor Conroy Professor Conroy">
      <NameTxt>Professor Conroy</NameTxt>
      <P>We are used to the Senator waffling on for hours.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="AvrilDoyle" hpid="Mrs. Doyle Mrs. Doyle">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Doyle</NameTxt>
      <P>Is that right?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Acting Chairman Acting Chairman">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman</NameTxt>
      <P>Please.  Senator Finneran, please continue without interruption. If there is any more interruptions I will take a different line.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelFinneranFF" hpid="Mr. Finneran Mr. Finneran">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Finneran</NameTxt>
      <P>As I have said, today is a sad day for me as a Roscommon man and as a colleague of Seán Doherty's. Seán Doherty took his own decision for his own reasons; he set his own agenda, <Col N="41" /> possibly yesterday evening.  I did not have any prior knowledge of his statement or of the press conference yesterday evening.  I remember vividly Seán Doherty in late 1982 and 1983.  I was not privileged to the information he has given, nor was I at any time since informed of what took place then.  I have always taken what was made public.  I shall not go into that issue now.  That is a matter for our own party to discuss and debate.  However, I have no doubt that Seán Doherty will survive.  I also have no doubt that Seán Doherty has a part to play in political life.  As a colleague of his in Roscommon, I want to wish him and his wife, Maura, and his family the very best for the future.  I know this is trying time and a lonely time for them.  I appreciate that because I saw him in a similar situation some years ago.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeCostelloLAB" hpid="Mr. Costello Mr. Costello">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Costello</NameTxt>
      <P>I believe that Seán Doherty did the proper thing by tendering his resignation to the Seanad today.  Like Senators Finneran and Mooney, I have known Seán Doherty very well over the years.  I particularly know his wife's family.  In fact, I was in the same class in primary school as Maura, his wife, and want to express my sympathy to her and with their family.</P>
      <P>Seán Doherty has always been a controversial figure and I have no doubt that under that veneer of brashness there is a reckless but naive and gullible man.  That might not appear too obvious.  He was a fair man in the Chair; he was even handed, generous and humorous.  I have no complaints to make about the way he handled business and the way in which he treated me and the Labour Party in this House.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Some might say that in the wider political arena he was a man as much sinned against as sinning, but he did sin and he admitted it.  Ironically, he was, to a considerable degree, responsible for Charles J. Haughey coming to power in Fianna Fáil.  He was one of the organisers of the coup against the previous Taoiseach, Jack Lynch; indeed, it was Ray MacSharry who proposed Charles Haughey at the parliamentary party <Col N="42" /> meeting.  Both men were elevated and both publicly admitted that they were guilty of phone-tapping.  Seán Doherty, as Minister for Justice, phone-tapped two journalists and Ray MacSharry tapped the phone of a colleague in Government, Martin O'Donoghue.  I believe that that action by a person in a position of authority was an abuse of authority.</P>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Acting Chairman Acting Chairman">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman</NameTxt>
      <P>It is usual that speakers in this House do not refer to people in the other House.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeCostelloLAB" hpid="Mr. Costello Mr. Costello">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Costello</NameTxt>
      <P>I will remember that.  I will give them their official titles.  I referred to the then Minister, Ray MacSharry, and to the abuse of power by phone tapping.  I want to refer to the transcripts of the tapes that were taken by the Minister of the day &mdash; not Seán Doherty, the Minister for Justice, but by a previous Minister for Agriculture and Finance, who is now a Commissioner in Europe &mdash; who admitted that he was involved illegally and improperly in tapping the telephone of a colleague in Government.  Such an abuse of a ministerial power renders a person unfit to hold high office.  I voted against Senator Doherty becoming Cathaoirleach of the Seanad as did all the people on this side of the House.</P>
      <P>Senator Doherty admitted at the time that he had been involved in this abuse and what we are now getting is the rest of the story.  At that time he did not implicate the Taoiseach.  What he is doing now is spreading the net wider and implicating those who were involved at the time but for whom he was the scapegoat. The statement is categorical.  Last night Senator Doherty said:</P>
      <P>I am confirming tonight that the Taoiseach, Mr. Haughey, was fully aware in 1982 that two journalists' phones were being tapped and that he at no stage expressed a reservation about this action.</P>
      <P>There is the detail.  He continued:</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I wish to reiterate in specific terms Mr. Ainsworth forwarded to me the transcripts relevant to the Cabinet leak <Col N="43" /> problem, numbering some four or five out of the roughly 12 or 13 total.  Each and every one of these relevant transcipts was transported by me to Mr. Haughey's office and handed to him directly.  He retained all but one of them making no comment on their content. At no stage did he indicate disapproval of the action which had been taken.</P>
    <P>He went on to say, categorically:</P>
    <P>I did not seek nor did I get any instruction from any member of the Cabinet in this regard nor did I tell the Cabinet that this action had been taken.  Telephone tapping was never discussed in Cabinet.</P>
    <P>In other words, what the Taoiseach has done is to construct allegations that have not been made and demolish them.</P>
    <P>Let us look at the Taoiseach's record. There was the arms trial in 1971, and a question mark still remains there.  Judge Henchy categorically stated that either the then Minister for Agriculture or Deputy Haughey was telling lies.  There was the GUBU affair in the early eighties and the controversy surrounding that. The Taoiseach is a man of controversy. There are the present business scandals, Greencore, Carysfort, the Goodman and Desmond affairs.  When it was categorically stated by the Leader of the Labour Party that a meeting had taken place between the managing director of Greencore and the Taoiseach it was denied.  The Taoiseach's answers to the House was that no &ldquo;such&rdquo; meeting occurred.  According to the transcripts from the Taoiseach he said: &ldquo;The Government had no such meeting&rdquo;.</P>
    <P>If we look at all the elements here, we find that what appears to be a contradiction is not necessarily so.  It is avoiding the truth, bending it, making a suggestion, an innuendo, but nothing straightforward.  For example, the ex-Cathaoirleach, Senator Seán Doherty, said he had given the transcripts directly to the Taoiseach over a period of time, but the Taoiseach denied that.  Yet the <Col N="44" /> record clearly states that they were given directly to the Taoiseach over a period of time.  The Taoiseach quotes Mr. Ainsworth but Senator Doherty has clearly implicated Mr. Ainsworth.  Then the Taoiseach makes his own allegations. He refers to Senator Doherty's &ldquo;transparent and personal motives&rdquo;.  He says there is a &ldquo;flagrant inconsistency&rdquo;, that he is &ldquo;the author of his own downfall&rdquo;, that he is &ldquo;seeking to bring down the Taoiseach and the Government&rdquo; and that he has made &ldquo;monstrous and unfounded allegations&rdquo;, all without an iota of evidence.</P>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Acting Chairman Acting Chairman">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman</NameTxt>
      <P>The Senator has one minute to conclude.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeCostelloLAB" hpid="Mr. Costello Mr. Costello">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Costello</NameTxt>
      <P>This is a vital issue because over the past six months it has diverted our attention from the real issues of the day.  Unemployment is at a scandalous level, the reneging on the Programme&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Acting Chairman Acting Chairman">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman</NameTxt>
      <P>I would remind the Senator to conclude.  His time is up.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeCostelloLAB" hpid="Mr. Costello Mr. Costello">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Costello</NameTxt>
      <P>About ten seconds ago you said I had about a minute to conclude. I am concluding.  There is the housing problem, the fact that we have neglected to properly prepare for Maasstricht and the tragedy of Northern Ireland.  There are two groups who can resolve this problem.  The first is the Progressive Democrats.  They cannot wash their hands of this and leave it to Fianna Fáil because they were responsible for Deputy Brian Lenihan, the then Tánaiste, being forced to step aside and for Deputy James McDaid being forced to step aside.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Acting Chairman Acting Chairman">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman</NameTxt>
      <P>I must ask the Senator to resume his seat.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeCostelloLAB" hpid="Mr. Costello Mr. Costello">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Costello</NameTxt>
      <P>It is time to ask the Taoiseach to step aside.  The Fianna Fáil Parliamentary Party must do the honourable thing and decide that the Taoiseach must go.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="45" />
    <Speaker pid="ThomasHussey" hpid="Mr. Hussey Mr. Hussey">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hussey</NameTxt>
      <P>I will be very brief.  I did not intend to speak on this matter.  I regret to see so much time wasted discussing matters that are irrelevant when there are so many other problems facing the country.</P>
      <P>I am very sorry to see Senator Seán Doherty resign from the Chair because he has been a very successful Cathaoirleach and has done a very good job.  He has been very fair in running the business of this House.  As a constituency colleague, he has been an excellent worker in his own constituency of Roscommon which adjoins my constituency of East Galway.  He has done a tremendous amount of work for the people of Roscommon and he has very strong support there.  It is regrettable that he has had to make this decision.</P>
      <P>I do not know why we should be reverting back to things that happened nine or ten years ago.  The telephone tapping episode was dealt with in the courts and judgment was given.  I cannot see the logic of wasting time discussing events that took place nine or ten years ago when there are many other far more important problems that we could be discussing.</P>
      <P>We will elect a Cathaoirleach and it is important that that be done right away. I am happy the Leader of the House has indicated that that election will take place tomorrow.  I hope that once that is done we can put this whole unhappy episode behind us and get on with the business of the House.</P>
      <P>I am not going to go into the rights and wrongs of what has been said by the parties involved in this episode.  That will be for others to decide and others to judge.  I am sorry to see Senator Doherty depart as Cathaoirleach of the Seanad.  I wish him every success in whatever line of activity he decides to pursue.  I hope the new Cathaoirleach will be elected tomorrow and that we can proceed with our business from there.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidNorris" hpid="Mr. Norris Mr. Norris">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norris</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not join in the general sorrow that Senator Doherty has resigned as Cathaoirleach.  I am extremely glad.  I think it is about time.  I <Col N="46" /> would have preferred if he had done it a long time ago.  I do not intend this to be a bitter personal attack on the former Cathaoirleach.  As has been said, he is a highly intelligent, charming, engaging, witty person but one totally unsuited for the role of Cathaoirleach of this distinguished House, which he brought into discredit and which he continued to bring into discredit by his appearance on &ldquo;Nighthawks&rdquo; where he collaborated in the description of his colleagues in the Seanad as &ldquo;eunuchs&rdquo;, which I do not think was a particularly dignified term to apply to Senators of the Irish Republic.</P>
      <P>I have sympathy for his family.  It is extremely difficult.  One could not but be moved by the face of his wife at the press conference and of course I extend my sympathy to his family.  When people go into political life the cliché is that if you are in the kitchen you must be able to stand the heat.  Senator Doherty obviously felt he could not stand the heat but he lit the fire and I do not see why I should have great sympathy for him.  May I say I have sympathy for many people in this country.  I have sympathy for the 41 per cent or so of the electorate who vote for Fianna Fáil, most of whom are thoroughly decent people.  I am quite certain they must be confused and bewildered by what is going on here today.</P>
      <P>I would like to say with regard to the honesty of Senator Doherty that after sitting on top of a festering pile of lies for nine years he has suddenly discovered truth.  I am delighted and I hope it extends to a lot of other things that may be uncomfortable like the Dowra affair, the Sergeant Tully affair, etc; I am not going to list them but many people know them.  Perhaps if this honesty is such a continuing contagion we may be treated to more honesty from Senator Doherty.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I would like to say with regard to the general situation that there are people here throughout political life &mdash; not too many of them, I am glad to say &mdash; who have a curious view of truth and I am inclined to include both Senator Doherty and the Taoiseach in it, namely, that the truth can be manufactured and you can manufacture whatever you like as long as <Col N="47" /> it convinces a significant proportion of the electorate or confuses them to such an extent that they may be persuaded to believe it.  I am not in a position to say the Taoiseach is lying but I will say this: he is most extraordinarily accident prone. He seems to be some kind of lightning conductor.  In another part of this House, about ten minutes ago, a member of Fianna Fáil said to me that they felt he was being pilloried, that he was like a man in medieval stocks that people were throwing rubbish at him.  Maybe that is the case but it is a very uncomfortable and awkward position from which to attempt to rule the country.  I think it is one from which the Taoiseach should certainly resign.</P>
    <P>We have just heard that the question of telephone tapping is not important, that we do not have to rake it over. It was important to Senator Doherty.  I would like to say also that there is a question here of monumental egos. Senator Doherty said he had to come out with the truth now because his position was being made embarrassing.  That is a very interesting statement and I think it extends to other people in Irish political life.  They put themselves before their party, they put the party before the country; in other words, the country comes a very poor third.</P>
    <P>I have some feelings about telephone tapping.  I am very glad that a Bill is being introduced and I will tell you why.  Eight years ago or so when I was in the middle of a complicated legal case against the Government I was given substantial circumstantial evidence that my own telephone was being tapped.  I contacted my barrister, Mrs. Mary Robinson, and I asked what could be done about it.  I was actually told very little could be done about it.  A question could be asked in the House but it would be covered by national security so we did not enter it in the case that I used.  We did, however, put evidence on the record of the High Court that my mail was routinely separated in Sheriff Street sorting office and opened and they even abstracted items from it and referred a novel which was <Col N="48" /> sent to me by a former female student to the censorship of publications board, so I think there is a level of hypocrisy.</P>
    <P>I would like to address the level of hypocrisy that I have heard here this afternoon as well.  Everybody it seems is whiter than white with regard to the Doherty business.  I want to put on the record of this House that when I challenged Senator Doherty on a matter over which I still stand and on which I have produced a detailed documented case, laying aside the merits of what I alleged I was brought before a Star Chamber.  I attacked it on certain specific grounds, that Senator Doherty should not be judge and jury in his own case, that I should be entitled to cross examine witnesses, I should have access to evidence, I should be allowed to call witnesses, to have legal representation and to introduce evidence myself and may I say the representatives of every single party in this House on the Committee on Procedure and Privileges voted to violate my constitutional democratic and human rights.  Now we have the Progressive Democrats&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    <Speaker pid="JohnHarte" hpid="Acting Chairman (Mr. Harte) Acting Chairman (Mr. Harte)">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman (Mr. Harte)</NameTxt>
      <P>May I interrupt the Senator for a moment, please?  It is not a question of being out of order on all of what you are saying because most people who spoke today went a little overboard.  What I would like to suggest is that you cannot call the Committee on Procedure and Privileges a Star Chamber.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidNorris" hpid="Mr. Norris Mr. Norris">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norris</NameTxt>
      <P>The High Court decided that it violated my constitutional and human rights.  I am not worried.  Let us not delay over it because I have other things to say about it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="AvrilDoyle" hpid="Mrs. Doyle Mrs. Doyle">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Doyle</NameTxt>
      <P>That is incorrect.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidNorris" hpid="Mr. Norris Mr. Norris">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norris</NameTxt>
      <P>I will make the point that Members voted to violate those rights and they now whitewash themselves.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="AvrilDoyle" hpid="Mrs. Doyle Mrs. Doyle">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Doyle</NameTxt>
      <P>On the basis of advice we had from the Cathaoirleach at the time.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidNorris" hpid="Mr. Norris Mr. Norris">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norris</NameTxt>
      <P>With regard to the election <Col N="49" /> of officers, I thought Senator Doherty was inappropriate and I said it at the time.  He was not the only one.  Let us look at the way the Seanad was treated. Deputy Doherty had been rejected by the electorate in the general election for Dáil Éireann, in the European election and he then mysteriously turned up here as Cathaoirleach.  The Leader of the House, Senator Lanigan, was actually defeated at the general election for the Seanad and had to be parachuted in and the Leas-Chathaoirleach was defeated for the Dáil, so that shows the elevated regard in which the Seanad is held by the principal political parties.  I think that is quite an extraordinary damaging thing to happen.</P>
      <P>With regard to the image of this country we have had a succession of scandals one after another.  Because, unfortunately, RTE were off the air &mdash; and I have to say it also showed up the lack of news content in the other stations that broadcast regularly in this country &mdash; I had to watch Sky television to see what was happening and it was item No. 1 in their news programme.  It was made perfectly clear that here was a former Cabinet Minister saying quite specifically and categorically that there was no question that the Taoiseach, Deputy Haughey, was lying.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>That is an extremely serious charge to make.  I wonder what motivated it?  We are entitled to speculate about the motivation of Senator Doherty.  If it is the truth then I am very glad for that but it seems to be part of continuing internal problems inside the Fianna Fáil Party and I wish they would get this cleared up once and for all because we are here again wasting time this afternoon.  A number of us wanted, for example, to make proposals, to attempt to address the question of Norther Ireland, the economy, unemployment &mdash; and principally, the North &mdash; but each week during the past eight months I have been told, for example, that we cannot speak, about the North of Ireland because it would exacerbate the problem.  How can you exacerbate a situation where seven men travelling home <Col N="50" /> on a Friday afternoon are blown to smithereens? How much worse does it have to get before the democratically elected Parliament of this country can actually discuss such an issue?</P>
    <P>Why are we wasting another day?  Why can we not elect a Cathaoirleach this evening?  Why not get to it immediately? We are, after all, the elected representatives. There is no technical reason we cannot do that.  The real reason of course is that it gives the political parties time to manoeuvre and select their candidates. They can put the machinery into play and come up with a candidate who will be in their particular sectional political interests.  I call on the Seanad to elect a Cathaoirleach tonight.  I do not see why it should not do so.  It would be absolutely proper for it to do so and it would help to restore the image of this House.  I do not have to remind the House that in a recent opinion poll politicians in this country were held in extraordinarily low esteem by the general public.  When I see the behaviour of both Houses on certain occasions I am not entirely surprised.</P>
    <P>I usually get on extremely well with journalists but I am astonished by the comments that I read sometimes in <i>The Irish Times</i> by Mr. Waters, who has written the book <i>Jiving at the Crossroads</i>, and by his pontifications of two days ago. I will look with interest to see what he is now writing, but in <i>The Irish Times</i> today there is a revised version of the Water's line on the Doherty business and he has one extraordinary phrase on it.  He has decided to canonise the martyr Doherty now, because he says &mdash; I cannot remember the exact phrase &mdash; Senator Doherty has done something almost unique among politicians: he has told the truth.</P>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Acting Chairman Acting Chairman">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman</NameTxt>
      <P>The Senator has exceeded his time.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidNorris" hpid="Mr. Norris Mr. Norris">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norris</NameTxt>
      <P>I thank you for allowing me to exceed my time.  I would like to conclude on the point that I believe that is a libel on politicians.  It is grossly irresponsible for somebody to say that Senator Doherty &mdash; it is a laughable concept &mdash; having belatedly discovered the <Col N="51" /> truth is now to be canonised for Irish people for telling the truth on one occasion and the truth told was, &ldquo;I lied&rdquo;. It is a wonderful standard of truth the Irish people must be proud of &mdash; Mother Ireland you are rearing them yet.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardConroy" hpid="Professor Conroy Professor Conroy">
      <NameTxt>Professor Conroy</NameTxt>
      <P>It has sometimes been said that most political careers end in tears.  Certainly in politics we have to take the knocks as well the success.  In at least one respect Senator Doherty has set us all an example which perhaps at times we should be prepared, however difficult it may be, to follow, that is, first of all to admit to a mistake.  That is always a difficult thing to do.  It must be particularly difficult when one is admitting that what one said previously is not in fact correct.  I think also that all of us should think about whether we would be prepared to resign under certain circumstances. Perhaps some of the criticisms which the previous speaker has made and which are generally made about politicians would be less deep and have less substance if people were willing in certain circumstances to make what in political terms is the supreme sacrifice of resigning.</P>
      <P>On a personal basis, I have known Senator Doherty for many years; he was always extremely courteous and thoughtful both in and out of the Chair.  He has been very anxious to be helpful to Members on either side of the House. What has happened is a personal tragedy and I very much regret it.  As Senator Hederman has said, there are other matters of grave importance that we should be looking at.  Perhaps this is much more exciting television and so on but there are indeed much graver problems.  I believe we have an excellent Government who are tackling the problems which I think all sides of the House would agree need to be tackled.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PolOFoighil" hpid="Pól Ó Foighil Pól Ó Foighil">
      <NameTxt>Pól Ó Foighil</NameTxt>
      <P>Ba mhaith liom ar dtús comhbhrón a dhéanamh leis an Seanadóir Doherty, agus lena bhean agus a chlann, faoi céard atá tarlaithe dó.  Creidimise go ndearna an Seanadóir a chuid <Col N="52" /> oibre go díograiseach, go macánta agus go féaráilte.  Ach tá rud tarlaithe anois a thugann le tuiscint nach raibh sé feiliúnach don obair a bhí ar bun aige.  Tá sé éasca fear a chur síos nuair atá gach éinne anuas air agus a rá gur theip air.  Is minic a déantar dearmad ar na buntáistí a bhí ag an bhfear céanna agus ar na rudaí maithe a rinne sé i gcaitheamh a réimis, agus níl mise ag caint ach faoi a réimeas mar Chathaoirleach ar an Seanad.</P>
      <P>Tá cainteoirí ag dul siar ar cad a tharla deich mbliana ó shin, faoi chogadh inmheánach a bhí ar siúl i bhFianna Fáil. Tá an-deifir ar an bhFreasúra agus ar an Rialtas fáil réidh leis seo.  Tá siad ag déanamh iontais de nach bhfuilimid gabhtha thairis agus imithe ar aghaidh le obair an tSeanaid mar a tugadh anseo muid inniu le déanamh.  Caithfidh Fianna Fáil a thuiscint gurb iad féin faoi ndear na trioblóidí atá faoi chaibidil anseo.  Níl aon bhaint ag na páirtithe polaitíochta eile leis na himeachtaí seo.  Tá an milleán ar fad orthu féin.</P>
      <P>Mar a dúirt Seanadóirí eile, tá dhá scéal againn: tá an scéal atá fírinneach agus an sceál atá bréagach, nó finscéal. Ceapaim féin, ag scrúdú an dá scéal, go raibh an t-iar-Chathaoirleach ag insint na fírinne nuair a labhair sé aréir.  Mar a d'fhiafraigh go leor daoine eile, cén fáth nár dhúirt sé é seo blianta ó shin?  Bhí brúnna áirithe aisteacha air ó thaobh na polaitíochta de agus níl sé éasca teacht as deacracht den cineál sin.  Ach bhí sé soiléir domsa ó thús ama go raibh baint bunúsach ag an Taoiseach, Cathal Ó hEochaidh, leis an obair seo.  Ní féidir liomsa a shamhailt nach mbeadh a fhios aige céard a bhí ar bun i 1982 nuair a déanadh na fóin a thapáil.  Ní féidir liom glacadh leis ar bhealach ar bith nach raibh an t-eolas sin aige &mdash; Cathal Ó hEochaidh mar dhuine, mar Aire nó mar Thaoiseach &mdash; is cuma cén lipéad a chuirtear air &mdash; bhí a fhios aige céard a bhí ar bun agus go raibh sé tarlaithe.  Bhí ar Sheán Doherty ó thaobh na polaitíochta inmheánach de i bhFianna Fáil, é sin a iompar é féin ar feadh na mblianta.  Tá sé sásta teacht amach anois agus tá mé cinnte go bhfuil an fhírinne inste aige.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Tá na fadhbanna atá á gcruthú ag <Col N="53" /> Fianna Fáil ag déanamh an-dochair do mhuintir na tíre agus go háirithe do shuim an aosa óig i bpolaitíocht.  Níl iontas ar bith orm nach bhfuil aon mheas ag daoine óga ar an gcóras ná ar na páirtithe éagsúla. Is cuma cén taobh ar a bhfuilimid, de bharr na scannal seo táimid go léir tarraingthe isteach i rudaí nach raibh aon bhaint againn leo.</P>
    <P>Cé tá ag fulaingt as seo?  Iarthar na hÉireann, mar shampla, atá thíos leis, agus is as an iarthar an Seanadóir Doherty.  Tuigeann sé chomh maith le duine ar bith an dochar uafásach atá á dhéanamh ansin faoi láthair mar gheall ar an imirce, easpa fostaíochta agus go leor easpaí infrastruchtúir atá ag cur as dúinn.  Cuirfidh an scannal deireannach seo atá deich mbliana d'aois agus atá ag brúchtadh amach ó íochtar an phota i bhFianna Fáil bac eile orainn dul chun cinn sasúil a dhéanamh ó thaobh na polaitíochta de.</P>
    <P>Bhí press conference ag an Taoiseach inniu agus deireann sé a mhalairt go hiomlán is atá ráite ag an Seanadóir Doherty.  Tá ceannaire an Rialtais agus an Cathaoirleach ar Sheanad Éireann ag tabhairt bréagadóir ar a chéile.  Cén meas a d'fhéadfadh éinne a bheith orainn mar náisiún de bharr a bhfuil ag tarlú anseo seachtain i ndiaidh seachtaine agus, sa chás seo, a tharla deich mbliana ó shin.</P>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Acting Chairman Acting Chairman">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman</NameTxt>
      <P>Your time is up.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PolOFoighil" hpid="Pól Ó Foighil Pól Ó Foighil">
      <NameTxt>Pól Ó Foighil</NameTxt>
      <P>Mar fhocal scoir, ba mhaith liom mo bhrón a chur i iúl do mhuintir Uí Dhochartaigh, dá bhean agus dá chlann, de bharr a bhfuil tarlaithe dó.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DennisODonovan" hpid="Mr. O'Donovan Mr. O'Donovan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Donovan</NameTxt>
      <P>I intend to be very brief.  I would like to place on record my sincere regret at what has happened in relation to the Cathaoirleach's resignation. It is unique because, as far as I am aware, it is the first time in the history of the Seanad a Cathaoirleach has resigned.  I am told from the benches opposite it is not but certainly it has not happened in recent times.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I met Senator Doherty, the ex-Cathaoirleach, about two weeks before <Col N="54" /> he was elected to the position of Cathaoirleach of the Seanad.  Since then he has been subjected in this House from time to time to vilification by the Opposition and some of the Independents. Through all this he acquited himself with honour and distinction in the position of Cathaoirleach.</P>
    <P>I recall being spokesman for Justice during the famous Norris affair, when I came to his defence and as a result of all these matters I became close to the Cathaoirleach.  It was with great regret &mdash; and complete surprise &mdash; that I heard the announcement of his resignation.  I wish him every success in whatever role he intends to take up.  He must have felt very strongly about the matter to resign from the position of Cathaoirleach.  If he feels that his actions are right, proper and justifiable then he has done a noble and honourable thing.  Regardless of the veracity of what has happened and the comments from all sides of the House &mdash; some in support of what he has done and more condemning him &mdash; it is with some regret that I listened to Senator David Norris's comment that he was glad to be rid of him.  At this stage that is not helpful because Senator Doherty has behaved in a dignified fashion in an effort to clear his name and those of his wife and family, which should be respected.</P>
    <P>There is a lot of talk about the telephone tapping affair, but I was in England when it started.  I came back to Ireland in the early eighties and set up business.  Never having known the man personally, apart from what I read, it is with some personal regret that I am speaking here today.  I do not want to be long winded.  Many Senators from his own area in the west have contributed, they know his family background and they have had personal contacts with him in his constituency.  I have none of that to offer but I regret that he has taken this decision.</P>
    <P>I hope by this time tomorrow we will have a new Cathaoirleach and that the House can get back to its business.  There are many important issues to be dealt with and I have no doubt that in the past 18 months to two years good work was <Col N="55" /> done by this House.  The Seanad, as part of the Houses of the Oireachtas, has been under criticism from time to time but in my brief period here &mdash; over two years &mdash; excellent work has been done in this House.  There have been many excellent contributions and Senator Doherty in his time in the Chair carried out his role with honour and distinction.  I wish him well in his new role.</P>
    <Speaker pid="BrendanRyan" hpid="Mr. B. Ryan Mr. B. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. B. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not know about other Members of the House but this sort of issue, which involves something painful and unpleasant happening to another human being, is a very difficult one.  There is undoubtedly a very appealing human element to this.  It involves a man and his family and I would not like to give the impression that I am not aware of that.  However, we have to address the reality, not Senator Doherty's family and the personal pain a series of circumstances has brought him but the reality of what Senator Doherty has done to this House.</P>
      <P>I do not think he was a good Cathaoirleach. He was very good at chairing meetings of this House, but I expect more from a Cathaoirleach, which I got from a variety of Cathaoirligh from different political parties.  I first expect the Cathaoirleach to be a person whose history and record both add to and sustain the dignity of this House.  Senator Doherty came into the position of Cathaoirleach with a record which did nothing to add to the dignity of this House.  He did nothing in terms of his activities as Cathaoirleach which added to the dignity of this House; rather he politicised it to a degree that had not happened previously during my period in this House.  Apparently he could not resist involvement in party political controversies.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>It became increasingly obvious that Senator Doherty had only a passing interest in this House and that he regarded it as a place in which he had to reside until he could get back to where he really wanted to be.  I have no great <Col N="56" /> objection to my colleagues in this House who operate in that fashion but I strongly object when my colleagues in Fianna Fál pick from their ranks to be Cathaoirleach a person who is dominated by that ambition.  I blame Fianna Fáil for making that choice and I blame Senator Doherty for seeking the position in the first place. It has done us no good and has, in fact, considerably damaged this House.  That decision did not uphold the dignity of this House and it did not serve any purpose.</P>
    <P>No decision I have been involved in in this House brought me more negative reaction from acquaintances, constituents and people I met than to select Senator Seán Doherty as Cathaoirleach. I found enormous public resentment of the fact that an already less than important institution of the Oireachtas had made itself look even more ridiculous by the appointment as Cathaoirleach of a figure of such public odium as Senator Doherty.</P>
    <P>I restrained myself at the time because I did not want to get involved, but Senator Doherty's handling of the Norris case was consistent with his record.  It was a matter of considerable regret that the basic decencies of natural justice were lost not only on him but apparently on most if not all the members of the Committee on Procedure and Privileges until they were brought to their senses by the courts.  It was not, let it be said, my colleague Senator Norris who brought this House to the High Court.  Because of the committee's decision and because Senator Doherty withheld important legal advice, Senator Norris had to defend himself in High Court, a place where, preferably, the business of this House and the other House should not be carried out.  Senator Norris was forced to bring this matter to the High Court because there was a flagrant breach of the rules of this House.  This was obvious even to a lay person.  Anyone who has been involved in a large organisation such as the GAA, even as a minor functionary, appreciates that there is due process for dealing with any breach of the regulations that nobody can ignore.  Senator Doherty contributed to the demeaning of this <Col N="57" /> House by doing that.  I do not believe somebody who behaved like that could be described in anybody's book as a good Cathaoirleach.  I am not going to deny what I said about Senator Doherty almost two years ago and say I regret his departure. I regret the personal pain but this House is the better for his going, and there should be no denying that.</P>
    <P>We should move from personalities and look at the problems facing this country. One of these problems is the abuse of power.  The abuse of power is not something that applies only to Senator Doherty or Fianna Fáil.  The December 1982 Fine Gael-Labour programme for Government contained the following specific commitment: &ldquo;A judicial inquiry will be established into allegations of political interference with gardaí with terms of reference covering the previous three years&rdquo;.  That judicial inquiry was never established.  It would be nice to hear from some member of that Government why that judicial inquiry never happened. It could have unravelled many abuses of power.  Since it would have been convenient to tarnish Fianna Fáil, who had been in Government for a considerable period during the previous three years, one can only suspect that something which happened during the period Fine Gael and Labour were in Government and which they wanted to hide, prevented that judicial inquiry being held.</P>
    <P>In 1974 or 1975 I had the dubious privilege of being followed home by a Special Branch man who sat outside my flat until 3 a.m. simply because I happened to come out of a public house they did not approve of.  At that time also, a friend of mine was stopped at 1 a.m. and questioned as if he were in eastern Europe and asked where he was going by people who did not identify themselves as members of the Garda until they had completed their interrogation.  I want to say to this House that abuses of power do not necessarily reside exclusively in the lap of Fianna Fáil.  This country has a problem about not making institutions accountable. There is also a problem with all the political processes because it is believed <Col N="58" /> that the only kind of power is power that does not have accountability.  In fact, the only kind of acceptable power is accountable power.</P>
    <P>I have watched the spectacle of some of my colleagues in Fianna Fáil pretending this is not a very serious issue, that they do not have a serious problem and that somehow the likes of me made life difficult for Senator Seán Doherty who is a decent man.  I want to say to them that there used be be a decent organisation called Fianna Fáil, that I grew up in that decent organisation and that the values I stand for here are the values I learned when Fianna Fáil stood for something, when they stood for ordinary people.  As I said here when the former Senator Willie Ryan was retiring, Fianna Fáil once stood for the values and interests of small people who had small problems, small families and small concerns, not big business, big money and magic circles.  That is now the problem. Today that problem has been crystalised around the personalities of two men, one of whom is the ex-Cathaoirleach and the other the present Taoiseach.  Between them they epitomise what has happened to Fianna Fáil.  The ex-Cathaoirleach and the Prime Minister are involved in a public slanging match in which one called the other a liar.  I do not really care at this stage who is telling the truth because as somebody said we will never know unless some mysterious witness comes out of the woodwork.  The suggestion that that is somehow good for the country, that this is not an important issue or that it does not make a difference to the country, is among the most spurious distortions that could have ever been put before&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    <Speaker pid="MauriceManning" hpid="Mr. Manning Mr. Manning">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Manning</NameTxt>
      <P>It was one of the Senator's colleagues who said that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BrendanRyan" hpid="Mr. B. Ryan Mr. B. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. B. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>I am not particularly concerned who said it.  I have no brief; Independent Senators are allowed to think and speak for themselves.  If members of other parties were allowed to do the same we might have better politics in this country.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="59" /> Much as I regret saying it, I cannot lament the departure of Senator Doherty from the position of Cathaoirleach.  I look forward to a future when this House is noticed by the media not for its notoriety but for the hard work that is done when we change legislation to improve accountability, look after homeless children, declare the public interests of the director general of the Environmental Protection Agency and do the things legislators are supposed to do, but when one talks about these issues to journalists, their eyes glaze over and they lose interest.  Politics should be about issues, policy and changing this country for the better.  We could make a start by electing a good Cathaoirleach, and I hope we will do so tomorrow.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MaryJackman" hpid="Mrs. Jackman Mrs. Jackman">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Jackman</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not agree with Senator Ryan when he said he did not lament the departure of Senator Doherty as Cathaoirleach.  There is a human dimension to politics which must be stressed, and it has been stressed today by all Senators.  From a human viewpoint I consider this is a sad day for Senator Doherty and his family.  During my two and a half years here he extended courtesy to me.  I did not know him very well, but from a personal viewpoint it is sad.  I would like to thank him for the courtesy he extended to me.</P>
      <P>I cannot say that the two-and-a-half years were notable for their constructiveness. Pehaps &ldquo;disruptive&rdquo; would be a more suitable word to apply to that time.  It is significant that we returned from each session with the uneasy feeling that there might be another trauma, and we were never disappointed.  Whether it was post-summer or post-Christmas, we entered again controversial periods which, obviously, were not good for politics in Ireland.  Two-and-a-half years of such ups and downs cannot be good.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Having heard both statements I have to say, like many speakers today, that I do not know who to believe.  First, there is an obvious conflict of evidence.  The general public will believe neither statement, and possibly that is the consensus <Col N="60" /> today.  The public feel there is a specific code of conduct in politics which allows for stretching, twisting and bending the truth, and that is not a very good example for our young people who are so cynical now.  Whether in local politics or national politics, it will be a long time before the people of Ireland have confidence again in public representatives, and we are all tarred with the same brush regardless of political parties.</P>
    <P>Neither Senator Doherty or the Taoiseach should hold office as a result of the disclosures and the conflicts that have resulted from the two statements over the last few days.  It is reasonable to say that Senator Doherty has done the honourable thing in resigning.  The holder of the highest office in the land after the President, the Taoiseach, Deputy Charles Haughey, should follow suit.  He should not decide to stay for some weeks, months or years but should follow the example of Senator Doherty and resign immediately.  If he did that there would be quite a number of relieved Senators who today in their responses said what we would expect them to say about their colleague, but they very definitely have felt embarrassed, disappointed and a sense of shame at what has happened in the last few days.</P>
    <P>The reputation of the leadership of the Government has been brought into question and that has a negative effect on the country.  The Taoiseach made great play of the fact that he was going to resign, possibly after the Masstricht Summit, but that did not happen.  If one went through international newspapers, for example, <i>The Sunday Times</i> and others further afield, during the last six months one would see that the two major stories carried on Ireland were of public scandals and inquiries and IRA atrocities. Obviously, that is an international image we could well do without.  The business community here have lost confidence in the Government and young and old have a very cynical view of politics and all politicians.  That is very sad.</P>
    <P>A question has to be asked as to the ability or the determination of the Government to tackle major problems. <Col N="61" /> This is not a debate on unemployment, but in the media the scandals of recent times have been given prominence over the plight of the 300,000 people unemployed. When I mention scandals obviously leadership pushes and heaves are an integral part of them.</P>
    <P>When we talk of leadership the question of who should lead Fianna Fáil is largely irrelevant; what is more important is who should lead the country.  At present there are many questions relating to the leadership.  A leader must have cohesive support but this is not evident at present.  One of the hallmarks of leadership is credibility.  There must be full confidence in the leader.  Now that we have had the honourable example of Senator Doherty resigning, Fianna Fail Senators feel embarrassed, any sense of shame or embarrassment can be erased by demanding a vote for a new leader. Then Seanad Éireann could at least get on with the business we were elected to do.</P>
    <Speaker pid="ShaneRoss" hpid="Mr. Ross Mr. Ross">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Ross</NameTxt>
      <P>With the permission of the House I should like to share my time with Senator O'Reilly.  I am staggered by the tone of this debate in some quarters.  I welcome without equivocation the resignation of Senator Doherty.  I find it rather disingenuous to listen to the tributes being paid to him by members of Fianna Fáil.  Senator Doherty's resignation has relieved them of an enormous embarrassment, an albatross which has been hanging around their necks for many years, ever since he was elected Cathaoirleach.  For members of the Government party to say they regret his departure and to pay tribute to him when everybody knows the Cathaoirleach was a great embarrassment is something I find very difficult to understand.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasHussey" hpid="Mr. Hussey Mr. Hussey">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hussey</NameTxt>
      <P>That is not true.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ShaneRoss" hpid="Mr. Ross Mr. Ross">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Ross</NameTxt>
      <P>I accuse the Fianna Fáil Party of weeping crocodile tears for Senator Doherty today.  They are relieved he has gone and that they will possibly have less of an embarrassment in the Chair from now on.  I do not accept <Col N="62" /> the almost funeral attitude of the Fianna Fáil Senators to this matter, the inevitability of paying tribute to someone when they resign.  Senator Doherty was, to my mind, patently unfit for the post of Cathaoirleach from start to finish.  It is certainly history that he was involved in the telephone tapping &mdash; that is on his own word and that is accepted.  He had questions to answer also about his role in other areas in Justice such as the Dowra affair.  I do not believe we can, with any honesty, pay tribute to him and say he was a good Cathaoirleach.  He was not a good Cathaoirleach.  I do not believe, in terms of the country, that it matters two hoots whether he was telling the truth or whether the Taoiseach was telling the truth.  What happened is that two men who had gone so far up the ladder together and assisted each other's career have fallen out.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I agree with what my Leader, Senator Manning, said so rightly earlier, that it is now the time to look at the position of the Taoiseach, not just because of the scandals we have endured, the finger that is being pointed and the questions he had to answer but because of his direct involvement in Senator Doherty's career. It was the Taoiseach who allowed or promoted Senator Doherty to Cathaoirleach of the Seanad when he could have stopped Senator Doherty's appointment. Traditionally the Taoiseach has had a major influence, if not a deciding influence on who becomes Cathaoirleach of the Seanad.  The Taoiseach allowed Senator Doherty to take that extraordinarily sensitive post in this House.  It was the Taoiseach who, when a motion of confidence was debated in this House less than two years ago, failed to give any signal to the Fianna Fáil.  Members of this House that Senator Doherty was unsuited for office at that time.  The House needs very little reminding that at that time Senator Doherty had concealed vital evidence from the Members of this House.  It is well known that many members of the Fianna Fáil Party wanted to dump him on that occasion.  Many of them looked to the Taoiseach for a lead on that occasion.  They looked to him to <Col N="63" /> get instructions to dump Senator Doherty and no such signal was forthcoming. Senator Doherty survived when the Taoiseach obviously knew that he was unfit for office.  What is happening today and what has been happening in recent months is that we are seeing the final kick of politicians who are basically yesterday's men with yesterday's standards. It is not just the series of extraordinary revelations, it is the complete public dissatisfaction with activities like those of Senator Doherty and of the Taoiseach which make it essential that the Taoiseach should resign in the wake of the appalling incident which has happened.</P>
    <P>I would like to ask a serious political question.  What are the Progressive Democrats about to do on this occasion?</P>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Acting Chairman Acting Chairman">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman</NameTxt>
      <P>The Senator agreed to share his time with Senator O'Reilly which would give each speaker seven minutes.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ShaneRoss" hpid="Mr. Ross Mr. Ross">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Ross</NameTxt>
      <P>I will give him a minute or two less.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Acting Chairman Acting Chairman">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman</NameTxt>
      <P>May I explain that I will have to call a speaker from the other side of the House for a couple of minutes and I will then return to Senator O'Reilly.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ShaneRoss" hpid="Mr. Ross Mr. Ross">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Ross</NameTxt>
      <P>I will be very brief.  It is absolutely imperative that we do not allow the Progressive Democrats off the hook on this issue even if, at this stage, they put the gun to the Government's head.  The Progressive Democrats have shored up the Government for the past two years when it was known that the integrity of the Government was in question. It is not good enough for them when they are confronted with the facts as put before us, to withdraw from Government when for at least six months public unease about the integrity of the Taoiseach and the Government has been rife.  On each occasion they found an excuse to stay in Government.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="64" />
    <Speaker pid="BrianMullooly" hpid="Mr. Mullooly Mr. Mullooly">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Mullooly</NameTxt>
      <P>I will be brief.  I have known Senator Doherty as a political and party colleague for almost 20 years.  I served with him as a member of Roscommon County Council for 17 years.  I know his wife, his children, his brothers and sisters; I knew his late father and I know his mother.  I regret that this further trauma has arisen for all of them.  Senator Doherty is no stranger to controversy but I was dumbfounded when I heard the content of Senator Doherty's statement last night.  On a personal basis, I was saddened by his announcement that he had decided to submit his resignation as Cathaoirleach.  He was an efficient, courteous and helpful Cathaoirleach and I wish him well for the future.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeOReilly" hpid="Mr. O'Reilly Mr. O'Reilly">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Reilly</NameTxt>
      <P>I have always found Senator Doherty to be courteous in the Chair and I wish him well on a personal level in his future career, wherever it may be.  I wish to progress from that to a fundamental point.  When one looks at the statement of Senator Doherty after the chain of events in recent weeks and, indeed, at the Taoiseach's statement today, all one can reasonably conclude is that the Government can no longer stay in office.  There is too much of a stain on the Government's performance.  Outside of Leinster House, the ordinary people have become cynical and alienated from politics.  People no longer believe in the political process, or that we are serious about delivering on jobs, on the economy or on social issues.</P>
      <P>It is time for a general election.  We urgently need a general election to clear the air.  It should result in the election of a Government who will have the respect and confidence of the people.  As a result of the recent chain of events not only has our and the Government's reputations been damaged here but our reputation has been damaged internationally.  I was shocked and embarrassed to hear the BBC World Service and BBC 4 treatment of the Irish political scandals.  It is clear we are going to be either the object of a lack of respect or the object of scorn internationally.  That is a very sad for the country.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="65" /> What should be done &mdash; and I direct this specifically at the Progressive Democrats' Leader, Deputy O'Malley, at the people concerned in the Government parties and at the Members across the floor of the House &mdash; is that this matter be brought to a head.  I know the public are not fond of elections and would want us to do our business, but in present circumstances we have no option but to call a general election to steady the ship of State and get back to the real agenda which must be the creation of jobs.  It is wrong not to look at the matter in this way.  Otherwise the level of cynicism rampant in this country will put the whole democratic process in danger.</P>
    <Speaker pid="DonLydon" hpid="Mr. Lydon Mr. Lydon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lydon</NameTxt>
      <P>While Senator Doherty was Cathaoirleach I always found him to be a humorous, generous, kind and courteous person.  I concur with some of the statements made earlier that most of today's discussion was a complete and utter waste of time and that we should have been dealing with other business.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Acting Chairman Acting Chairman">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman</NameTxt>
      <P>We agreed to conclude this business at 5.30 p.m.  I must put the question.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnMurphy2" hpid="Professor Murphy Professor Murphy">
      <NameTxt>Professor Murphy</NameTxt>
      <P>Is there no chance that Senator Doherty could be asked to reconsider his resignation in view of the high expression of esteem from the Fianna Fáil benches?</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Business" RHead="of Seanad">
    <Title>Business of Seanad.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I have notice from Senator Costello that, on the motion for the Adjournment of the House today, he proposes to raise the following matter:</P>
      <P>The need for the Minister for Health to make provision for the disposal of clinical waste from hospitals which will not involve on-site incineration.</P>
      <P>I also received notice from Senator Cosgrave of the following matter:</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="66" /> The need for the Minister for the Marine to outline his plans for the future of shipping services at Dún Laoghaire, in view of the ports importance to the Dún Laoghaire area.</P>
    <P>I also received notice from Senator Norris of the following matter:</P>
    <P>The need for the Minister for the Environment to accede to the expressed wishes of Seanad Éireann and Dublin Corporation by making a substantial cash grant from lottery funding for the rebuilding of the Hirschfeld Centre in Dublin.</P>
    <P>I regard the matters raised by Senators Costello, Cosgrave and Norris as suitable for discussion on the Adjournment.  I have selected Senator Costello's matter and it will be taken at the conclusion of business.  Senators Cosgrave and Norris may give notice on another day of the matters they wish to raise.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Order of" RHead="Business">
    <Title>Order of Business.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFallon" hpid="Mr. Fallon Mr. Fallon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Fallon</NameTxt>
      <P>It is proposed to take the Labour Party Private Members' motion dealing with the <i>Programme for Economic and Social Progress</i> from 6.30 p.m. to 8 p.m.  I am proposing a sos from now until 6.30 p.m.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Is that agreed?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatUpton" hpid="Dr. Upton Dr. Upton">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Upton</NameTxt>
      <P>No, it is not.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MauriceManning" hpid="Mr. Manning Mr. Manning">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Manning</NameTxt>
      <P>On the Order of Business, I want to raise a number of issues. First, I want to put on the record the total abhorrence of my group, and I am sure the entire House, at the massacre last week in Northern Ireland and the appalling pass things have come to, the political vacuum, the failure to get talks going and the sheer hypocrisy of Sinn Féin and the IRA.  It is almost impossible to describe the depth of the revulsion and the sense of hopelessness we feel in face of what is happening.  I want to express, once again, a hope that political dialogue can commence in Northern Ireland and <Col N="67" /> that all those who can will shun Sinn Féin, make them an unwanted organisation and expose the hypocrisy behind which they masquerade.  I had intended asking the Leader of the House to have an immediate debate on Northern Ireland but because of other events it did not prove possible.  There are no talks that can be stopped and it is past time when Members of this House should be granted and opportunity to have their say about what is happening in Northern Ireland.</P>
      <P>Secondly, I should like to move an amendment to the Order of Business to include the motion in my name and that of other Fine Gael Members which was criculated at the beginning of today's business; it is not on the Order Paper but it has been circulated.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>On a point of order, I cannot take that amendment as it is not on today's Order Paper or on the Supplementary Order Paper.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnMurphy2" hpid="Professor Murphy Professor Murphy">
      <NameTxt>Professor Murphy</NameTxt>
      <P>I should like to reiterate my disapointment that, having been summoned to meet in Seanad Éieann to discuss a firm agenda, we were distracted into discussing events which had nothing to do with this House, except to note the resignation of the Cathaoirleach. There are many other items that claim our immediate attention, as has already been indicated by Senators McGowan, Hederman and others.</P>
      <P>I hope we will get an opportunity soon to discuss item No. 22 on the Supplementary Order Paper, which draws attention to a scandal which may well rank as the greatest of all scandals &mdash; and I know that the field is a severely competitive one.  I am talking about the injustice which has been suffered by Nicky Kelly and which is admitted now on virtually all sides except where it really matters, and redress for which may be coming from outside bodies which may shame us into addressing this injustice.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I support Senator Manning's request for an urgent debate on Northern Ireland.  On the appalling atrocity he said that words fail us, and so they do, but in <Col N="68" /> respect of shunning Sinn Féin I do not really agree with that because I believe that one should not adopt such a cosy attitude in matters of public debate. Rather we should examine to what extent our own attitudes to Northern Ireland, unification and so on, lend them aid and counsel.  In either case, we need an urgent debate on Northern Ireland, which would be one of the most practical ways to express our sympathy.</P>
    <Speaker pid="HelenKeogh" hpid="Miss Keogh Miss Keogh">
      <NameTxt>Miss Keogh</NameTxt>
      <P>I was very pleased to hear Senator Manning raise the subject of the appalling atrocity that occurred last Friday.  With all that has been happening politically down here, it is important that we do not lose sight of the need to begin talks on the appalling situation in Northern Ireland and to find a political solution.  It is essential to put on the record the abhorrence of Senators from all sides of last weeks atrocity.  I was pleased to hear Senator Manning and Senator Murphy say that.  It keeps things in context when one realises that nearly every day people in Northern Ireland are being butchered.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatUpton" hpid="Dr. Upton Dr. Upton">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Upton</NameTxt>
      <P>I join other speakers in expressing my abhorrence and disgust at the appalling events which took place in Northern Ireland in the past few days.  I also join other speakers who requested the Leader of the House to reconsider his attitude to have a debate on Northern Ireland.  In view of the present circumstances, I believe that it is well worth trying.</P>
      <P>I have noted the Chair's ruling on Senator Manning's motion.  For that reason, I am not going to make a similar proposal in relation to an almost identical motion in the names of my Labour Party colleagues and myself.  However, under Standing Order 123, I propose that the motion in the name of the four Labour Party Senartors &ldquo;That this House has no confidence in the Taoiseach&rdquo;, be taken this evening.  In other words, Standing Orders should be suspended.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>From reading Standing Order 123 (2) I understand this is a matter on which you <Col N="69" /> have the discretion to use your judgment, and I sincerely hope you allow this vital matter to be debated this evening.  The country is talking about this central issue. Despite the fact that we have important items on the agenda I hope you will use your discretion and allow the House to just consider the question at this stage the question of whether the item should be debated.  I hope you will be able to accede to that request.  For my part, I hope the House will go along with this urgent item and allow the debate to take place.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PaddyMcGowan" hpid="Mr. McGowan Mr. McGowan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGowan</NameTxt>
      <P>I join other speakers in asking the Leader of the House to give time for an urgent debate on Northern Ireland.  On at least five previous occasions I and other Members have requested such a debate.  If the Leader of the House were to continue to ignore requests from all sides of the House for a debate on Northern Ireland he could be misunderstood.  Regardless of what forums we have for debating the problems in the North, it is only proper that the Leader of this House respect the wishes of Members which have been expressed very clearly and that we have an opportunity to express our strong views.  If workers were being slaughtered nearer Dublin I am sure the matter would be dealt with with greater urgency.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>It is time reasonable honest thinking people stood up and clearly stated at every opportunity that we abhor and oppose anybody who murders innocent workers in the name of Irish people.  This House must be given an opportunity to <Col N="70" /> discuss the issue and to give its verdict on those who continue to slaughter innocent people in the name of the Irish.</P>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>In relation to the point raised by Senator Upton under Standing Order 123, in my opinion this matter satisfies Standing Order 123 (2). Is the motion proposed by Senator Upton opposed?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFallon" hpid="Mr. Fallon Mr. Fallon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Fallon</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Under the procedure, the proposer and the opposer may make a statement on the matter.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatUpton" hpid="Dr. Upton Dr. Upton">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Upton</NameTxt>
      <P>The subject of the resolution now to be considered by the House is being spoken about by practically everybody in this country today.  It has occupied the House all afternoon. It is a key question, namely, whether this House has confidence in the Taoiseach.  The various conflicts have been well illustrated.  The whole matter has been very well teased out and I thank you, a Leas-Chathaoirligh, for giving the House the opportunity to decide whether this motion will be taken this evening.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFallon" hpid="Mr. Fallon Mr. Fallon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Fallon</NameTxt>
      <P>I am opposing the motion. The matter has been dealt with.  I indicated quite clearly that there would be a great deal of latitude on that debate, and I do not propose to add further to what I have already said.</P>
      <P>Question put: &ldquo;That Standing Orders be suspended for today's sitting.&rdquo;</P>
      <P Just="Center">The Seanad divided: Tá, 23; Níl, 30.</P>
      <P Just="Center">Tá</P>
    </Speaker>
    <table pgwide="1">
      <tgroup cols="2">
        <colspec colname="1" colnum="1" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <colspec colname="2" colnum="2" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry rowsep="1">Cosgrave, Liam.<br />Costello, Joe.<br />Cullen, Martin.<br />Dardis, John.<br />Doyle, Avril.<br />Harte, John.<br />Hourigan, Richard V.<br />Howard, Michael.<br />Jackman, Mary.<br />Kennedy, Patrick.
<Col N="71" />Ryan, John.<br />Staunton, Myles.</entry>
            <entry rowsep="1">Keogh, Helen.<br />Manning, Maurice.<br />Murphy, John A.<br />Neville, Daniel.<br />Norris, David.<br />Ó Foighil, Pól.<br />O'Reilly, Joe.<br />Raftery, Tom.<br />Ross, Shane P.N.<br />Ryan, Brendan.
<Col N="72" />Upton, Pat.</entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
    <P Just="Center">Níl</P>
    <table pgwide="1">
      <tgroup cols="2">
        <colspec colname="1" colnum="1" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <colspec colname="2" colnum="2" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry rowsep="1">Bennett, Olga.<br />Bohan, Eddie.<br />Byrne, Hugh.<br />Byrne, Sean.<br />Conroy, Richard.<br />Fallon, Sean.<br />Farrell, Willie.<br />Finneran, Michael.<br />Fitzgerald, Tom.<br />Foley, Denis.<br />Hanafin, Des.<br />Haughey, Seán F.<br />Honan, Tras.<br />Hussey, Thomas.<br />Kiely, Dan.</entry>
            <entry rowsep="1">Kiely, Rory.<br />Lanigan, Michael.<br />Lydon, Don.<br />McCarthy, Seán.<br />McGowan, Paddy.<br />McKenna, Tony.<br />Mooney, Paschal.<br />Mullooly, Brian.<br />O'Brien, Francis.<br />Ó Cuív, Éamon.<br />O'Donovan, Denis A.<br />O'Keeffe, Batt.<br />Ormonde, Donal.<br />Ryan, Eoin David.<br />Wright, G.V.</entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
    <P Just="Center">Tellers: Tá, Senators Upton and Costello; Níl, Senators Wright and Fitzgerald.</P>
    <P>Question declared lost.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Order of Business" RHead="(Resumed)">
    <Title>Order of Business (Resumed).</Title>
    <Speaker pid="JoeOReilly" hpid="Mr. O'Reilly Mr. O'Reilly">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Reilly</NameTxt>
      <P>At the outset I join with our party leader in the Seanad, Senator Manning, in unequivocally condemning the outrage in Tyrone last week.  As a person from a Border area I think it is appropriate that I do that, and I do not&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PaschalMooney" hpid="Mr. Mooney Mr. Mooney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Mooney</NameTxt>
      <P>I am very sorry to interrupt my colleague but it is purely on a matter of clarification.  What exactly is happening?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>We are on the Order of Business (Resumed), I stated that earlier.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PaschalMooney" hpid="Mr. Mooney Mr. Mooney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Mooney</NameTxt>
      <P>I thought the Senator was making a speech.  I am sorry.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeOReilly" hpid="Mr. O'Reilly Mr. O'Reilly">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Reilly</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not propose to develop the point except to say it should be condemned absolutely as an attack on working people and as something horrendous. I ask the Leader of the House if he would consider a proposal that would give much credibility to this House in the eyes of the general public, that is, devoting at least one day to a complete debate on unemployment and on strategies to create employment.  I appeal to the Leader to make that time available shortly.  It would do much to enhance the image of this House throughout the country.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MartinCullen" hpid="Mr. Cullen Mr. Cullen">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cullen</NameTxt>
      <P>Can the Leader of the House convey to the Minister for Finance my encouragement for what he has achieved in the recent discussions with the unions on the <i>Programme for Economic and Social Progress</i> programme? We all hope that that will be brought to a satisfactory conclusion and that the Programme for Government and the <i>Programme for Economic and Social Progress</i> will be a reality.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="AvrilDoyle" hpid="Mrs. Doyle Mrs. Doyle">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Doyle</NameTxt>
      <P>The Senator will have to get back into the fold after voting against them a minute ago.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator Cullen to continue without interruption.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MartinCullen" hpid="Mr. Cullen Mr. Cullen">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cullen</NameTxt>
      <P>We all obvously hope that the very valuable work done on that programme will be brought to fruition in the years ahead.  Secondly, I wish to join with my colleagues, and in particular Senator Keogh, in condemning the outrageous bombing in Northern Ireland last week. <Col N="73" /> I want to put on the record of this House my view that if the political process in Northern Ireland is not seen to be credible, then the vacuum will be filled and continue to be enhanced by terrorism, and it is up to the constitutional parties in Northern Ireland on all sides to get around the table and start talking.  The longer they prevaricate, the stronger will the terrorists grow in that part of our island.  That message must go home loud and clear.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>A question to the Leader of the House.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MartinCullen" hpid="Mr. Cullen Mr. Cullen">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cullen</NameTxt>
      <P>I would ask the Leader of the House, a Leas-Chathaoirlaigh, if we could have a debate on Northern Ireland as soon as possible?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidNorris" hpid="Mr. Norris Mr. Norris">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norris</NameTxt>
      <P>I second Senator Cullen's request for a debate on Northern Ireland. I think all sections of the House have requested this debate for the last six to eight months and we have been told from time to time that we could exacerbate the situation.</P>
      <P>It is difficult to comprehend how the situation could be exacerbated by a debate in the Oireachtas, and in pursuance of this, I would like formally to propose an alteration to the Supplementary Order Paper, that we take Item No. 43, as the first item, which reads:</P>
      <P>That Seanad Éireann strongly supports the Government in taking all necessary measures to defeat the clear intention of the so called Provisional IRA to provoke sectarian civil war in the North of Ireland.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I am not going to expand on it because I know I would not be allowed to make a speech but I strongly feel it is important that we have the opportunity to have a debate on this important matter.  I say this with particular strength because I am one of two members of the Church of Ireland who are elected to this House. I do not say it in any sectarian fashion but it is notable that the seven victims were of the same persuasion.  It is an <Col N="74" /> attempt to provoke sectarian civil war. This House must debate it and debate it as quickly as possible.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JohnMurphy2" hpid="Professor Murphy Professor Murphy">
      <NameTxt>Professor Murphy</NameTxt>
      <P>I wish to second that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MickLanigan" hpid="Mr. Lanigan Mr. Lanigan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lanigan</NameTxt>
      <P>I join with other Members of the House in condemning absolutely the murder campaign of the IRA and other paramilitary bodies in the North.  Eight people were killed in the last paramilitary bombing but it should be said, be it one or 1,000 victims we must condemn each and every one of these atrocities.</P>
      <P>There is a degree of prevarication about a certain incident which took place in the south-east in the recent past.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>A question please to the Leader of the House.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MickLanigan" hpid="Mr. Lanigan Mr. Lanigan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lanigan</NameTxt>
      <P>I put it to the Leader of the House, if we are to discuss the bombings in the North of Ireland, that we should equally condemn the robbery which took place in Waterford.  People, including members of the staff of the AIB, have said &ldquo;it was only money&rdquo;.  I put it to the Leader of the House that we should have a debate on where the money the paramilitary bodies take in raids in the South goes to; it is used to kill people in the South and in Northern Ireland.  The two must be taken together, otherwise we will be wasting our time.  A debate should take place to discuss the totality of the atrocities.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>The Senator has made his point.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MickLanigan" hpid="Mr. Lanigan Mr. Lanigan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lanigan</NameTxt>
      <P>On that issue we should not attribute blame but rather ask ourselves each time we hear somebody praising people who had &ldquo;a good robbery&rdquo;&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>The Senator cannot make a speech on this matter.  He has asked the Leader of the House a question and I am sure the Leader has taken it on board.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="75" />
    <Speaker pid="MaryJackman" hpid="Mrs. Jackman Mrs. Jackman">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Jackman</NameTxt>
      <P>I, too, join with other Senators in condemning the atrocities and ask the Leader of the House now that we have returned to normality if we can have an early debate.  I also ask him to request the Minister for Education, Deputy Davern, to reconsider his decision to means test maintenance grants for students of regional technical colleges.  We have not begun to discuss the colleges Bills but I would have to say that the students who will be most affected by that decision will not be the students who are well off but rather those who are disadvantaged.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>A question please to the Leader of the House.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryJackman" hpid="Mrs. Jackman Mrs. Jackman">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Jackman</NameTxt>
      <P>I would go further and suggest rather than reconsidering his decision the Minister should drop the idea of means testing grants for third level students.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnDardis" hpid="Mr. Dardis Mr. Dardis">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dardis</NameTxt>
      <P>We have heard many calls in this House both today and during the last session for a debate on unemployment. In supporting those calls I suggest to the Leader of the House that the most appropriate way of covering that and many other aspects would be to have a full debate on the report of the Review Group on Industrial Policy, the so-called Culliton report.  I ask the Leader of the House to make time available to allow the House to consider that report and to say when that debate might take place.</P>
      <P>I should also advise the House that the reason we supported the motion to suspend Standing Orders was that we believed there was really no point in deferring the matter.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>That is not a matter for the Order of Business.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BrendanRyan" hpid="Mr. B. Ryan Mr. B. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. B. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>I want to support a number of my colleagues.  Lest there be any dispute I will formally second Senator's Norris's amendment to the Order of Business.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="76" />
    <Speaker pid="JohnMurphy2" hpid="Professor Murphy Professor Murphy">
      <NameTxt>Professor Murphy</NameTxt>
      <P>I have done so already.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MauriceManning" hpid="Mr. Manning Mr. Manning">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Manning</NameTxt>
      <P>Do not fall out about it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BrendanRyan" hpid="Mr. B. Ryan Mr. B. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. B. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>We are in a permanent state of falling out.  What I have to say is much more serious.  I do not want to make a statement about the atrocities because there are no words left that could express one's view on them.  What is clear is that we have reached a strange position in Irish politics where our colleagues north of the Border cannot, apparently, get themselves to talk about their problems while it would appear south of the Border we will not be allowed to talk about their problems.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>A question please to the Leader of the House.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BrendanRyan" hpid="Mr. B. Ryan Mr. B. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. B. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>My question is not whether we can have one debate on Northern Ireland but rather whether we can have regular debates about the single most insidious, destructive and cancerous issue afflicting this island.  We should not have to ask for a debate.  All responsible politicians in this country who claim they are committed to democracy should talk about that issue, from our various perspectives within the democratic framework, on a regular basis.  The idea that anything is served by&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I have to ask the Senator to refrain from making a speech.  He has asked the Leader of the House a question.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BrendanRyan" hpid="Mr. B. Ryan Mr. B. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. B. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>I am trying to explain to the Leader of the House the reason it is important we should have a debate.  I am not talking about Northern Ireland, rather I am talking about the business of this House.  Perhaps the Leader of the House can explain to me, privately, what is wrong with the idea of democratic politicians discussing a problem.  The only people who speak publicly and consistently about these problems&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I think the <Col N="77" /> Leader of the House understands the Senator's intention.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BrendanRyan" hpid="Mr. B. Ryan Mr. B. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. B. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>He might understand it better when I finish.  All I can say is that if we do not speak regularly others outside Parliament, in particular the Provisional IRA, will express only their view of the problem through their methods. We should be as vocal as they are and should be allowed to be as outspoken as they are within the democratic structures. That is the reason we need to discuss that issue, not just once but on a regular ongoing basis.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeCostelloLAB" hpid="Mr. Costello Mr. Costello">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Costello</NameTxt>
      <P>I wish to support Senator Dardis who stated that he would like to see the Report of the Review Group on Industrial Policy, under the chairmanship of Jim Culliton, form the basis for a debate on unemployment.  It would be an ideal vehicle for us to have a wide-ranging debate and I ask the Leader of the House to consider that request as a matter of urgency.</P>
      <P>Secondly, in relation to ESF funding, the Leader of the House should make the views of the Members of the Seanad known to the Minister for Education whose unilateral decision will effect those who are already in receipt of funding from Europe on the pretence that equity is being introduced into the system as regards higher education grants.  That decision should be opposed as strongly as possible.</P>
      <P>In relation to Northern Ireland, may I ask the Leader of the House if he would change his opinion, which he has expressed in this House so often, that we would only exacerbate the situation if we were to have an ongoing debate on Northern Ireland?  He has indicated that he will allow a debate but he has expressed the view that it would aggravate the situation.  May I give an example to highlight the problem we face?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>No, we cannot have a debate now.  The Senator has put a question to the Leader of the House and I ask him to co-operate.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="78" />
    <Speaker pid="JoeCostelloLAB" hpid="Mr. Costello Mr. Costello">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Costello</NameTxt>
      <P>We should not be unable to discuss current affairs.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="AvrilDoyle" hpid="Mrs. Doyle Mrs. Doyle">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Doyle</NameTxt>
      <P>While I support the sentiments expressed by Senator Lanigan in relation to the bank robbery which took place in the south-east, I do not think, in the interests of accuracy, that it has actually been established whether paramilitaries or a criminal gang were involved.  I hope the matter will be resolved and that those responsible will be brought to justice as soon as possible. The biggest problem we face, both in this House and outside, is that there are still far too many sneaking regarders when it comes to the type of atrocity we have witnessed.  It behoves all of us in every party to root them out as well as the criminals and those who perpetrate appalling acts such as the one which occurred last Friday.</P>
      <P>May I ask the Leader of the House when we will see the Electoral (No. 2) Bill, 1991, in the Seanad, whether it will be initiated in the Seanad and whether we will have time to debate it thoroughly before the next general election?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFallon" hpid="Mr. Fallon Mr. Fallon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Fallon</NameTxt>
      <P>A number of Senators asked for a debate on Northern Ireland. The events of last Friday, the callous murder of those seven building workers, strongly indicates to me the depths to which the IRA will go to fuel sectarian hatred in the North.  To suggest that because people were working for a building firm they were legitimate targets is ludicrous.  They were ordinary working people doing their job, earning a living and providing food and clothing for their families.  I support the view that we extend sympathy to the families.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>In so far as a debate on Northern Ireland is concerned, I will consider seriously again &mdash; and pursue as actively as I can &mdash; a debate on Northern Ireland. I know the concern of the Senators and I promise to do so.  I was of the view that Senators would want a debate on he events of last Friday and I had planned a debate on that for an hour sometime today.  Unfortunately, events have changed so we will not be able to have <Col N="79" /> that now, but perhaps we will sometime in the future.</P>
    <P>Senator O'Reilly, Senator Dardis and others asked about a debate on unemployment and the way forward is as I have indicated &mdash; Item No. 9 on the Order Paper.  On receipt of the Culliton report I placed it on the Order Paper and I would like to think that we will get a chance of debating the matter as soon as possible.</P>
    <P>Senator Cullen referred to the <i>Programme for Economic and Social Progress.</i> As he knows, there is a debate tonight on that matter.  Senator Norris asked about Item 43.  I have no plans to take that as a specific item but it would be ideal for a Private Member's motion and he might pursue that area.</P>
    <P>Senator Jackman and others referred to means testing ESF grants.  I will certainly bring the concern of Senators to the attention of the Minister for Education. Senator Costello also mentioned that matter.  Senator Doyle referred to the Electoral (No. 2) Bill, 1991, and I am confident that will be taken in this House as quickly as possible.</P>
    <Speaker pid="AvrilDoyle" hpid="Mrs. Doyle Mrs. Doyle">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Doyle</NameTxt>
      <P>Before the general election?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFallon" hpid="Mr. Fallon Mr. Fallon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Fallon</NameTxt>
      <P>Before the general election.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator Norris has moved an amendment to the Order of Business,.  &ldquo;That Item No. 77, motion 43, be inserted after Item No. 17, motion 41&rdquo;.  Is the amendment being pressed?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidNorris" hpid="Mr. Norris Mr. Norris">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norris</NameTxt>
      <P>In the light of the Leader stating that he will be considering a debate on Northern Ireland, it would be obstructive to push it to a vote so I do not propose to do so.  I withdraw my amendment to the Order of Business.</P>
      <P>Order of Business agreed to.</P>
      <P>
        <i>Sitting suspended at 6.15 p.m. and resumed at 6.30 p.m.</i>
      </P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Programme for Economic and" RHead="Social Progress: Motion">
    <Title>Programme for Economic and Social Progress:  Motion.</Title>
    <Col N="80" />
    <Speaker pid="JoeCostelloLAB" hpid="Mr. Costello Mr. Costello">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Costello</NameTxt>
      <P>I move:</P>
      <P>That Seanad Éireann agrees that the <i>Programme for Economic and Social Progress (PESP)</i> which was a solemn agreement entered into freely by the social partners, namely the Government, the trade unions, the farmers and the employers, for the welfare of the people of Ireland and for the benefit of the national economy, be fully honoured by the Government; and further that Seanad Éireann fully supports and congratulates the trade union movement in its industrial action to ensure that the Government honour their commitments under the programme.</P>
      <P>The House is quiet after the storm we had earlier.  I wish to welcome the Minister for Labour to the House.  I hope he has a happy period &mdash; I am not sure if I should say a long period &mdash; in office.  I trust it will be both useful and beneficial.</P>
      <P>This motion, which was tabled prior to the recent decision of the Government, which has been presented to the public service trade unions, relates to the changes announced on 13 December and the unilateral decision by the Minister for Finance.  The Minister for Finance simply stated the Government's position and that the trade union movement could not negotiate on the matter.  The new proposals relate to pay and not to the nonpay elements of the <i>Programme for Economic and Social Progress.</i>  The Labour Party Senators consider the motion to be valid and have decided to proceed with it.  We want a number of issues clarified and I hope the Minister will be able to throw light on some of them.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Social partnerships are a very beneficial development in that they enable the major groupings &mdash; the trade union movement, farmers, employers and the Government &mdash; to decide on a programme which will be in the interests of the economy and the country.  I wholeheartedly support that development.  I <Col N="81" /> would, of course, like to see greater consultation with the Dáil Opposition parties and the Seanad in this process because an agreement can be presented as a <i>fait accompli</i> and apart from discussing it we have no input.</P>
    <P>The <i>Programme for Economic and Social Progress</i> is a solemn and important agreement.  We know what happened in 1987 in relation to the <i>Programme for National Recovery.</i>  The trade union movement entered into that agreement willingly and accepted a 2.5 per cent pay increase over a three year period knowning that the rate of inflation would be in excess of that.  They were willing to make sacrifices in order to bring about an upturn in the economy, considerably reduce the national debt, and give the new Government an opportunity of getting the show on the road.  That agreement was enormously successful and it gave a tremendous boost to the economy by increasing our level of exports over imports.  There was a surplus of approximately £2 billion in exports during that period.  Obviously, many companies made great profits.</P>
    <P>Workers in the public service remained on the same level of pay and special pay claims were deferred until the programme was completed.  Therefore, the special awards we talk about in the context of the <i>Programme for Economic and Social Progress</i> are special pay awards which were deferred under the <i>Proramme for National Recovery.</i>  The Minister is proposing further deferral.  It is a serious matter if a relativity agreement is deferred further by the Government when we had sacrificed so much all along in the line.  The agreement has been deferred until 1993 but the question must arise whether the Government will be in power at that time and indeed if they are in power, whether we can believe that they will honour the agreement?  Those are two major considerations regarding the special pay that should have been paid by September of this year.</P>
    <P>As regards the general pay levels there is no retrospection in relation to the £5 maximum in 1992 and the £6.50 in 1993 <Col N="82" /> even though the Government have promised that the full payments will be made by December 1992 in the first instance and December 1993 in the second instance.  I acknowledge that what is proposed in relation to people on retiring is welcome.  Any money lost as a result of the ceiling that has been opposed is subject to negotiations with Congress in 1993, with possible payment in 1994.  It is not acceptable for a Government who are pretty much on their last legs at present to transfer payments to December 1992, 1993 and 1994.  My summing up of the decisions announced by the Minister on 17 January is that they are a rescheduling of promises.  They have already broken promises which should have been honoured.  These payments are being rescheduled again for a period of time but the Government have no authority to make promises in regard to payments simply will not be around to honour them and if that is the case a new Government can state that they did not make such promises.  This is a very serious matter and I would like the Minister to respond to it and I would also like him to clarify a matter that has been of concern to me in relation to a statement he made in his speech.</P>
    <P>It seems as though all of the deferments are subject to the new time schedule and also to another constraint under the four-year programme to which the Government have committed themselves, and which involves a budgetary discipline for 1992 and 1993 from which there can be no deviation and which provides that the Exchequer borrowing requirement does not exceed 1.5 per cent of gross national product in 1993.  I would like clarification, in the context of these key objectives, of the Government's commitment to honour in full the payment provisions in the <i>Programme for Economic and Social Progress.</i>  The Minister has given one set of proposals with a time schedule for December 1992, January 1993 and 1994 &mdash; that is in the context of the three-year <i>Programme for Economic and Social Progress</i>&mdash; and on top of that is a new programme which was never entered into or known about when the <Col N="83" /><i>Programme for Economic and Social Progress</i> was being negotiated &mdash; the Joint Progress for Government agreed by the Progressive Democrats and Fianna Fáil.  What are we to read into that?  Are all of the promises about deferment to be totally subject to the Government's objectives as stated in the second agreed programme?</P>
    <P>It was foolhardy of the Government to breach their trust.  They should honour their commitments.  Appendix A, article 7 of the programme states:</P>
    <P>This agreement precludes strikes or any other form of industrial action by trade unions, employees or employers [everybody except the Government] in respect of any matter covered by this agreement where the employer or trade union is acting in accordance with the provisions of the agreement.</P>
    <P>In other words nobody on the trade union side, the farmers' side, the employers' side or the employees' side can breach that agreement.  It precludes strikes or any other action.  However the Government unilaterally decided they were going to breach it.  Article 8 states:</P>
    <P>The parties to this agreement shall meet not earlier than October 1992 to review the operation of this agreement in the light of economic and fiscal developments over the period of the agreement.</P>
    <P>There is a blatant breach of the agreement. The budgetary reasons the Minister brought forward, for example, the fact that the economy had not worked as successfully this year as it had in 1990, are not included in this programme.  That is not a valid reason, even though the Minister has put it forward as such.  This is a blatant breach of the agreement that was entered into.  Deputy Albert Reynolds, as Minister for Finance, last year envisaged a borrowing requirement of £460 million but at the end of the year it was £501 million.  The budgetary estimate was out of line by a mere £41 million, considering that the entire revenue is £8.77 billion.  It is really scandalous that for such a relatively small sum <Col N="84" /> the Government see fit to breach the agreement as set down in the programme. It would be absolutely foolhardy of the Government to continue with the existing pay deferral unless their commitments are very solid.  They should not defer all the payments to 1993-1994, with the big question mark that they are subject to the Government's budgetary disciplinary policy.  That is leaving the matter totally up in the air and is the wrong way to do business.  They should be more sure of their figures and their sums.</P>
    <P>The Minister has not referred in his contribution to the non-pay element.  He referred to it on 13 December when he said that the Minister for Finance would consider the deferral in a budgetary context. Reading the Estimates I cannot see that provision has been made to honour the non-pay elements of the <i>Programme for Economic and Social Progress.</i>  If anybody thinks that I as a teacher, that a health worker or a nurse entered an agreement purely on pay elements they are totally wrong.  I consider the non-pay elements to be more important than the pay elements.  They are crucial.  The quality of life for teachers in the educational system and for the nursing community depends on the non-pay elements and we have got no commitment as of yet to honour those elements.  If they are not honoured the industrial dispute that is referred to in this motion will be embarked upon, certainly by the three teacher unions.  The three teacher unions have simply deferred their decision until there is a clear-cut statement on the non-pay elements from the Department of Finance, the Department of Labour or from the Minister who is here, and I would be delighted to hear it tonight.  The quality of Irish education deteriorated in the eighties.  Class sizes are the highest in Europe.  We have the lowest spending <i>per capita</i> of any EC country.  The OECD report strongly criticised the Government because there was no professional development for the education profession. A teacher may spend more than 40 years in the classroom without a break. <Col N="85" /> That is scandalous.  Are the developments built into the <i>Programme for Economic and Social Progress</i> to go down the drain?</P>
    <P>It is incredible in this day and age that provision is not made in the primary and secondary education systems for the employment of secretaries and caretakers. A school of 600 to 1,000 pupils has to function without this basic infrastructure being provided by the Department of Education, in spite of the constitutional entitlement.  These are just some elements and I could go on about the range of health services provided. Where people have embarked already on a vocational training scheme can they be cut off just like that?  I hope the Minister is in a position to state the Government's position on the non-pay elements of the <i>Programme for Economic and Social Progress.</i></P>
    <P>My understanding of the conciliation and the arbitration scheme is that when a special pay claim is granted the Government have two months in which to alter it, and then they have to bring a motion before the House to do so.  They are technically wrong to alter it after that time.  Since the pay deal was made in December 1990, more than a year has expired.  I am not sure of the legal basis for the Minister's action on those terms because no motion was brought before the House to vary what was agreed in arbitration.  No attempt was made in the Oireachtas to vary the arbitration award which I understand is necessary.  That procedure was adopted when the teachers award was varied in 1985. Would the Minister respond to that as well?</P>
    <P>What we are saying is that we are far from a satisfactory resolution of this matter.  If the budgetary commitments to the non-pay elements of the <i>Programme for Economic and Social Progress</i>, which are essential to the social, developmental, educational, health and social welfare aspects as well as the commitments to job creation are not incorporated in what the Minister for Finance has to say later, then I have no doubt that what people think is the end of the <Col N="86" /> proposed industrial action will, only be the beginning of a long period of industrial strife.</P>
    <P>It would be a shame if the successful social partnership developed over the past number of years were to be jettisoned because of a very small miscalculation in budgetary terms.  In the interest of the country, in the interest of the Minister's own party and in the interest of avoiding industrial strife in the future, the Government would do well to ensure commitments are honoured in full.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JohnHarte" hpid="Mr. Harte Mr. Harte">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Harte</NameTxt>
      <P>This is the Minister's first time in the House in his new portfolio. May I welcome him and wish him the best of luck in the forthcoming discussions and negotiations and all the difficulties he will have to deal with.  I welcome the agreement on the pay aspects of the <i>Programme for Economic and Social Progress.</i> Having regard to the fact that the agreement covers a very wide range of interests for the betterment of society it was imperative that everyone would try to get some sort of agreement on pay.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RoryKiely" hpid="Acting Chairman (Mr. R. Kiely) Acting Chairman (Mr. R. Kiely)">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman (Mr. R. Kiely)</NameTxt>
      <P>Did the Senator second the motion?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnHarte" hpid="Mr. Harte Mr. Harte">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Harte</NameTxt>
      <P>I second the motion.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="AvrilDoyle" hpid="Mrs. Doyle Mrs. Doyle">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Doyle</NameTxt>
      <P>Is the Acting Chairman in the running tomorrow?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Acting Chairman Acting Chairman">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator Harte without interruption.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnHarte" hpid="Mr. Harte Mr. Harte">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Harte</NameTxt>
      <P>I hope the non-pay elements will be dealt with satisfactorily. Since I am no longer on the inside track of the trade union movement, I am not in a position to say exactly what the general attitude is to pay, but I take Senator Costello's word that the unions are determined to see that they will be brought to a very successful conclusion.  The concept of the social partners coming together is very good for the country as a whole. Naturally one wants to see the agreement succeeding, not only for the trade union movement but for the country as a whole. <Col N="87" /> We will be particularly interested in seeing it succeed for the farmers who have been going through a difficult period over the past couple of years.  It may seem strange that as a trade unionist I am backing the farmers and am worried about their income but I would not be a good trade unionist if I was not concerned about the incomes of all people.  While I do not have the complete picture I know farmers have been having a bad time and from that point of view I hope negotiations succeed.</P>
      <P>The real problem I see with the <i>Programme for Economic and Social Progress</i> is that the Government had to give guarantees to the trade unions and to other bodies and yet there is an absence of detail.  For example under the <i>Programme for Economic and Social Progress</i>, our debt which stands at 100 per cent now, must be reduced to 60 per cent by 1996.  I do not know how the Government propose to achieve that.  I do not know what was said in the course of negotiations, but development of these points in the Seanad might assist the social partners.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I do not expect the Minister to tell us what he is going to agree to, but he can outline some of the ways the Government propose to tackle certain difficulties that will affect the agreement.  For example, I do not know whether the Government would admit to errors in forecasting or if they did not take advice when determining the pay agreements.  What are the forecasts?  Do the Government think they can live up to the agreements they are about to make?  Were our economic disasters of our own making or can we blame the Gulf War or other factors?  They are important and are of great concern to me and other representatives.  When growth is low unemployment is high and, naturally, we are concerned that growth be considered also.  We have insufficient detail to enable us decide if the Single European Market will affect growth. What is the outlook?  The outlook, according to the relevant Minister speaking in the Seanad, is optimistic, but is it <Col N="88" /> as optimistic as it was when the negotiations at Maastricht took place?</P>
    <P>When we look back on 1991, a year of unfulfilled promises, we must ask questions about forecasting.  Are we using the correct system of forecasting?  Are we taking the right advice?  What is the position?</P>
    <P>For 70 years we have enjoyed independence yet we have 20 per cent of our labour force unemployed, compared with 4 per cent in Holland, 6 per cent in Germany, 7 per cent in the USA, 9 per cent in Britain, 10 per cent in Italy and 15 per cent in Spain.  In essence, we have the highest rate of unemployment in the European Community.</P>
    <P>The borrowing rate of 13 per cent of gross national product equates to one-eight of our national production.  Will we be able to do anything about the borrowing so that any agreement made will last?  I accept that progress here has not been uniform but have we any fall-back position in progress is not uniform?  How can we make the worry or concern of those who have to negotiate agreements less acute?  What information is available to help in negotiating agreements?</P>
    <P>We have been criticised about our marketing. We do not know whether that is relevant to economic recovery but it is relevant to the agreement and to people negotiating the agreement.  They must know where we can sell abroad, what we are selling abroad and whether we can do better.  For example, the UK is still one of our main export markets.  What is the strength of our market in the UK? If that market will be negligible, which appears to be the case, what is the view of the Government?  Are there other markets we can fall back on?  Can we make up for our loss in that market? Those matters are important when negotiating an agreement.  We must get the sums right.  We are anxious about market policy.  I am concerned that the agreement be a success.  I was one of the first advocates of national agreements, long before the social partner idea, because I saw the number of people in the trade union movement who became the victims <Col N="89" /> of free-for-alls.  The dog-eat-dog mentality relegated people to very poor positions and, ultimately, kept down negotiations.  I recognise results come from national efforts.</P>
    <P>I am anxious that the agreement succeeds. I am concerned that perhaps we are not looking far enough ahead and have not taken cognisance of the errors we made in the past or the forecasters made.  Will the Minister express his opinions based on his long experience in political life and reduce the worry of people who are going into negotiation.</P>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Acting Chairman Acting Chairman">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman</NameTxt>
      <P>I am calling Senator McKenna to move the amendment.  I understand the Senator wishes to share his time with Senator McGowan.  Is that agreed?  Agreed.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TonyMcKenna" hpid="Mr. McKenna Mr. McKenna">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McKenna</NameTxt>
      <P>First, I join Senator Harte in welcoming the Minister, Deputy O'Kennedy, to the House as the Minister for Labour.  I congratulate him on his appointment and wish him well in that portfolio.</P>
      <P>As spokesperson for Fianna Fáil on Labour, I look forward to working closely with him.</P>
      <P>I move amendment No. 1:</P>
      <P>To delete all words after &ldquo;Seanad Éireann&rdquo; and substitute the following:</P>
      <P>&ldquo;fully supports and congratulates the Government on the sensitive and balanced package of measures which the Minister for Finance presented to the Irish Congress of Trade Unions and the public service unions on 17 January 1992; endorses the reaction of the latter to the package and welcomes the deferment of the day of action which was scheduled for 28 January 1992 and the basis which now exists for a return to the consensus between Government and ICTU which underpins the <i>Programme for Economic and Social Progress.</i>&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>In moving the amendment, I wish to point out that the Labour Party motion <Col N="90" /> is to a large extent irrelevant.  It refers to the day of industrial action, which will not now take place.</P>
    <P>Senator Costello described the review as a breach of the agreement.  That is not so.  It would be wrong if any programme for economic and social progress or plan was so rigid that changes could not be made.  There has to be room for manoeuvre.</P>
    <P>The preamble to the <i>Programme for Economic and Social Progress</i> states clearly that the programme depends on budgetary constraints at the time.  There is a mechanism in the programme for any of the parties at any time to ask for a review of it.  Effectively, that is what the Government were doing and they did so for very good reasons.  When the programme was agreed no one could have foreseen the difficulties in the world economy in the early part of last year or that the subsequent fall out would be as severe as they were.</P>
    <P>All the problems arose as a result of those difficulties.  For example, the Gulf War had huge repercussions throughout the world, particularly in small countries like Ireland.</P>
    <P>We have a very small, open economy and we depend to a large extent on international trade.  What happens in other countries, and the performance of other economies affects us greatly.  If we put a rigid programme in place and said there was to be no deviation, good, bad or indifferent from that programme it would be a bad programme.  We must realise that when we prepare a programme it is based on certain assumptions.</P>
    <P>Any person with a bit of understanding and common sense will recognise that we do not have a crystal ball, that we cannot see into the future.  We could not foresee the tragic events that occurred in the world at large and particularly in the Middle East with all their repercussions in the early part of that year which had such devastating effects right around the world.  Experts predicted that the recession in Great Britain would peter out but statistics show that that is not happening.  The reverse is the case and the recession is lasting much longer than <Col N="91" /> expected.  That has huge repercussions for us on this side of the Irish Sea, particularly in relation to unemployment which is our single major difficulty here.  That has been exacerbated by the recession in America and in the United Kingdom which has resulted in the return of many young people who see they are better off at home and looking for jobs.  That adds extra strain.  People will say we should be able to provide job opportunities for all our young people, but we have never been able to do that.</P>
    <P>There are no soft options.  There are no short term solutions to the problems we have today.  Unemployment must be of major concern to every politician.  We must create a climate of real strength and growth which will give jobs and support all our needs.</P>
    <P>At the same time, let me reiterate that our economic performance in recent years has matched and, in many respects, exceeded the performance of our EC partners.  The great improvement in our public finances and improved price and wage competitiveness resulted in the economy performing extremely well in the last four years, and the potential for growth remains extremely good.  We cannot throw all that aside for the sake of short term expediency.  The Government must recognise that.  I want to congratulate the trade union movement on appreciating the difficulties facing the Government and for accepting the revised proposals.  I want to share my time with Senator McGowan.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PaddyMcGowan" hpid="Mr. McGowan Mr. McGowan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGowan</NameTxt>
      <P>I too welcome the Minister, Deputy O'Kennedy, to the Seanad.  We are lucky to have a Minister who has a reasonable approach to most matters.  The <i>Programme for Economic and Social Progress</i> is fundamental.  I am surprised at Senator Costello threatening that, if the Minister does not make certain statements before he leaves the House, we will be facing a serious situation. I believe Senator Harte has a more reasonable approach.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeCostelloLAB" hpid="Mr. Costello Mr. Costello">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Costello</NameTxt>
      <P>Could I correct that?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="92" />
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Acting Chairman Acting Chairman">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator McGowan, without interruption.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeCostelloLAB" hpid="Mr. Costello Mr. Costello">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Costello</NameTxt>
      <P>I have not threatened the Minister.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Acting Chairman Acting Chairman">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman</NameTxt>
      <P>You will have an opportunity to reply.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeCostelloLAB" hpid="Mr. Costello Mr. Costello">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Costello</NameTxt>
      <P>I want to clear my good name.  I did not threaten the Minister.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PaddyMcGowan" hpid="Mr. McGowan Mr. McGowan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGowan</NameTxt>
      <P>I must claim extra time because I am being interrupted.  Senator Harte's approach is better because he recognises that progress has been made. I, too, recognise that tremendous progress has been made by people like the Minister for Labour who is reasonable, and by people like the Minister for Finance who fully understands.</P>
      <P>This country has come through difficult financial constraints very well compared to a big and wealthy country like America where the President may not be re-elected because it is alleged he neglected the economy of his country, and instead was flying to Japan and other places trying to recover lost ground.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="AvrilDoyle" hpid="Mrs. Doyle Mrs. Doyle">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Doyle</NameTxt>
      <P>Does the Senator think Deputy Haughey will be re-elected?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PaddyMcGowan" hpid="Mr. McGowan Mr. McGowan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGowan</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes, if he goes before the people.  Desperate calls from the other side of the House&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Acting Chairman Acting Chairman">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman</NameTxt>
      <P>We are dealing with the <i>Programme for Economic and Social Progress</i> in Ireland, not America.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PaddyMcGowan" hpid="Mr. McGowan Mr. McGowan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGowan</NameTxt>
      <P>I will try to stay at home.  I hope Senator Costello is listening when I say that a progressive and successful trade union official in Donegal told me he had survived for 30 years as a trade union official and that he never brought workers out on the street but had always been able to negotiate and get a satisfactory deal for them.  However, he also said a trade union official who is also a politician is a dangerous mix.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="93" />
    <Speaker pid="JoeCostelloLAB" hpid="Mr. Costello Mr. Costello">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Costello</NameTxt>
      <P>Is the Senator threatening me?  It is a veiled threat.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PaddyMcGowan" hpid="Mr. McGowan Mr. McGowan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGowan</NameTxt>
      <P>Today, we have an educated people who make their own assessments and know that at the end of the day it is not the State purse but the people lucky enough to have jobs who are paying.  The negotiations were well supported throughout the country.  I encourage the Minister, and those good reasonable people who have taken part in the negotiations to stay on course. There are signs that the outcome expected by the majority will be achieved, and I compliment those involved in the negotiations.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelOKennedy" hpid="Minister for Labour (Mr. O'Kennedy) Michael O'Kennedy">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Labour (Mr. O'Kennedy)</NameTxt>
      <P>First, I welcome the opportunity to address this motion.  I should like to reassure the House that the <i>Programme for Economic and Social Progress</i>, which the Government negotiated when it was badly needed, is an essential core element of our approach to the economy and to the partnership which was a feature of the last few years and I hope it will be a feature of negotiations over the next few years.  It is a pity Senator Costello did not adopt the same approach as his colleague, Senator Harte, who has been a Member of this House for many years &mdash; I think he was a Member when I was a Senator.  The Senator's party, who had an opportunity from time to time in Government, did not advance the cause of the programme and partnership that we introduced.  I would like to have heard the Senator endorse a concept which is recognised here and throughout the world as being a very important instrument of coherence and common purpose.  I have returned this week from a meeting of the OECD Council of Labour Ministers from the 24 most prosperous nations in the world.  All of them pointed out that the programme we put in place here was the kind of instrument that should be in place in every members state of the OECD.  I would like to have that acknowledged by Senator Costello.  I would like to have someone from this <Col N="94" /> House recognise the reality that is recognised abroad rather than concentrating on the negative.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeCostelloLAB" hpid="Mr. Costello Mr. Costello">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Costello</NameTxt>
      <P>I acknowledged that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelOKennedy" hpid="Mr. O'Kennedy Mr. O'Kennedy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Kennedy</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator Harte showed a more balanced approach to it, the type of approach that I would expect from a trade union representative that I have known for some time and for whom, I am glad to say, I cast a vote on occasions when we were finished with our own votes in the Fianna Fáil Parliamentary Party.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="AvrilDoyle" hpid="Mrs. Doyle Mrs. Doyle">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Doyle</NameTxt>
      <P>No. 17.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PaddyMcGowan" hpid="Mr. McGowan Mr. McGowan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGowan</NameTxt>
      <P>We will forgive you.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelOKennedy" hpid="Mr. O'Kennedy Mr. O'Kennedy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Kennedy</NameTxt>
      <P>I recognise a gutsy man.  We should recognise how important this programme has been to economic progress since 1987.  I want to assure the House that this Government will not risk this programme being undermined.  I am glad to make specific commitments to it. I had better give some examples of what has been achieved.  The economy grew under this programme while our inflation rate was the lowest in the European Community, in sharp contrast to the condition we inherited in 1987.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="AvrilDoyle" hpid="Mrs. Doyle Mrs. Doyle">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Doyle</NameTxt>
      <P>What about the unemployment figures?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelOKennedy" hpid="Mr. O'Kennedy Mr. O'Kennedy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Kennedy</NameTxt>
      <P>I will come to that. The exchange rate was stable in the EMS, the balanced of payments was healthy.  All the factors which led to strong growth over the period of the <i>Programme for National Recovery</i> between 1987 and 1990 were and could be seen as a consequence of a discipline not just imposed by Government but a discipline and direction which was part of this programme. We increased our competitiveness vis-á-vis our trading competitors and there was a degree of moderation on the pay element.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I want to pay a particular tribute to the trade union movement.  Someone put it <Col N="95" /> very well when he said that this has taken the unacceptable risk &mdash; hyper inflation and hyper interest rates &mdash; out of the equation.  For that reason there has been a buoyancy in the enterprise sector, and they owe it to the trade union movement and the other quarters, including Government, to demonstrate their response by generating the maximum economic activity.  Workers take home pay has increased but moderate pay agreements contributed greatly to the progress we made on the export front also.  Exchequer borrowing was mentioned. Obviously the key contribution has been the reduction in Exchequer borrowing. Good governments do not throw things out or take the easy option and to hell with Exchequer borrowing. Good governments take difficult decisions despite opposition and criticism. We took control of the budget and that was the key to developing and strengthening the economy.</P>
    <P>This House needs to be reminded of the facts.  Facts are stubborn things, they will not run away.  Senators asked what we were about to do about the scale of improvement in Exchequer borrowing already achieved.  In 1986, the year before we came into Government, the Exchequer borrowing requirement amounted to almost 13 per cent of our total gross national product.  We were borrowing at the rate of one eighth of our total national production, piling up commitments, storing up trouble.  Firm and disciplined action was taken which reduced spending and improved tax collection and by the end of 1991 the Exchequer borrowing requirement &mdash; excluding the proceeds of the Irish Life flotation &mdash; was 2.1 per cent of GNP. That is some achievement.  It was not a popular or easy decision but we appreciate the co-operation of the unions and the social partners in bringing that about because we needed to rescue the country from the bankruptcy which obtained in 1986.</P>
    <P>As a small open economy Ireland cannot insulate itself from developments <Col N="96" /> in the international economy.  Some commentators and political critics wanted us to make judgments on Ireland as if the rest of the world did not exist.  They will not be allowed to get away with that delusion.  Any slowdown in economic activity abroad has an impact on the domestic economy.  I will give some examples of the better performances here compared to elsewhere and any objective analysis will illustrate this.</P>
    <P>World trade decelerated to slightly over 3 per cent in 1990 compared with over 5 per cent growth here; Ireland's export markets continue to expand but at a more modest rate than in recent years primarily because of the weaker import demands in the United Kingdom.</P>
    <P>Senators have asked about unemployment. The OECD surveys for instance, show that unemployment growth was higher in prosperous countries like Finland, Australia, New Zealand, the United Kingdom and Canada, than in Ireland.  Our economic growth by comparison with any of those countries was also much higher.  The forecast suggests that we will have a higher rate of growth than Japan, the United States, the United Kingdom, Switzerland and Germany.  These are not Irish figures; they are OECD figures.  It is right that the Irish people be made aware of the facts despite suggestions that we are always struggling against the odds&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    <Speaker pid="AvrilDoyle" hpid="Mrs. Doyle Mrs. Doyle">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Doyle</NameTxt>
      <P>How many of the countries have 20 per cent unemployment?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelOKennedy" hpid="Mr. O'Kennedy Mr. O'Kennedy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Kennedy</NameTxt>
      <P>I will come to unemployment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="AvrilDoyle" hpid="Mrs. Doyle Mrs. Doyle">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Doyle</NameTxt>
      <P>They started at a lower figure.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelOKennedy" hpid="Mr. O'Kennedy Mr. O'Kennedy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Kennedy</NameTxt>
      <P>The Senator is a lady and I have to treat her as such, through she has a habit of interrupting.  That has been a feature of her contributions in this House.  Between April 1989 and April 1991 Ireland recorded a 2.8 per cent growth in employment.  Over the same period, a number of economics did not achieve anything to compare with that, <Col N="97" /> the United States achieved 1.7 per cent, the UK -0.7 per cent, Denmark -1.9 per cent and Switzerland 2.1 per cent.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="AvrilDoyle" hpid="Mrs. Doyle Mrs. Doyle">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Doyle</NameTxt>
      <P>What is the unemployment rate in Switzerland?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelOKennedy" hpid="Mr. O'Kennedy Mr. O'Kennedy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Kennedy</NameTxt>
      <P>I am talking about gross employment.  This has been a successful programme and we will not allow it to be undermined by anybody for their own reasons.  At the recent OECD conference they specifically pointed out the success and key elements of this programme.</P>
      <P>We performed well in 1991 despite difficulties and I will not go into all the details now.  For instance, the provisional labour force survey results indicates a rise of 7,000 in non-agricultural employment in the year to mid-April last but let me turn to unemployment &mdash; Senator Doyle knows this and I do not suppose she would want to conceal it.  Unemployment rose in 1991.  Why?  In the year to mid-April net emigration fell as employment in the United States and the United Kingdom declined; On average, the number of those on the live register rose by over 29,000, which is less than the actual reduction in emigration.  There was a reduction in the underlying rate of increase in unemployment in recent times.  That is not to give the impression that everything is cosy and comfortable, but to give some of the facts.  I hope that politicians on all sides would record those facts and not try to distort them.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>This programme is important because it is designed to promote economic and social development and to prepare us for the 21st century, particularly in the union of Europe and because it is based on co-operation we are determined to maintain it.  It has been fully accepted by the parties to the <i>Programme for Economic and Social Progress</i>&mdash; and this is a wonderful breakthrough &mdash; that macro-economic stability is vital to economic progress in a small open economy.  Unless the growth potential of the economy is secured and strengthened by pursuing the sound macro-economic policies to which I have <Col N="98" /> referred, our capacity to meet the objectives of the <i>Programme for Economic and Social Progress</i> will be seriously diminished. The fact that the trade unions accept the macro-economic targets, realities and disciplines has been a great development.  The improvements achieved are attributable in no small way to their response to Government leadership.</P>
    <P>Under the <i>Programme for Economic and Social Progress</i>, the national debt-GNP ratio is to be reduced towards 100 per cent by 1993.  We are on target.  I think it was Senator Costello who raised the question of the 60 per cent discipline under the EMS.  Given that we are moving consistently towards that figure. I have no doubt that our partners in the European Community will endorse our qualification for full membership of the EMS under European union.  We do not anticipate any difficulty in that direction.</P>
    <P>When the Taoiseach and I and other members of Government, the Minister for Finance, the Minister for Industry and Commerce and the Minister for Social Welfare, met the social partners we explained to them the difficulties arising from the economic downturn; the difficulties which impacted on our economy despite the fact that we had put effective programmes in place.  We delivered a strong message and I have never suggested otherwise but we followed with a series of bilateral contacts, which have been a feature of the relationship between this Government and the trade union movement.  We did not stand off. I said &mdash; my colleague, the Minister for Finance, is active on this matter &mdash; we were not interested in confrontation; only in conciliation.  I said specifically, because I respect and admire the trade union movement, that we wanted to confront the outrageous abuses that have been evident in some aspects of Irish business life over the past year or so.  Tax evasion must have tested the patience of the PAYE sector to the very limit.</P>
    <P>Following those discussions we met the employer organisations.  We introduced, and got agreement, for special training and employment schemes to take 25,000 <Col N="99" /> people off the register at no cost to the taxpayer.  As we do not believe in sitting back and reacting to others we announced an initiative which was agreed with the commercial banks &mdash; the first of its kind &mdash; under which the banks will provide £15 million in loans on favourable terms for the creation or development of small and medium business with employment potential.  We explained this to the ICTU when we met them.</P>
    <P>We also explained the position on public service pay when we indicated that if all the liabilities on public service pay were to be met in 1992, the public service pay bill would increase by over 10 per cent.  Obviously, that was not sustainable and, accordingly, we announced that the Government had decided to adjust the package and amend the pay terms.  That is now a matter of history and record.  The Irish Congress of Trade Unions indicated that the package was unacceptable to them, although it is fair to say that one member, during the course of the meeting, said that perhaps there was a possibility of what he called &ldquo;sullen acceptance&rdquo; which we would have understood. Both sides were very anxious to maintain this programme.  We are very happy that their determination to do so is evident in their response to the readjusted package which can be accommodated within the projections of the Government's macro-economic policy.</P>
    <P>When the whole issue was reviewed at Government the Minister for Finance got the full and vigorous endorsement of the Government to consult again with the social partners.  As I am sure by now Members are familiar with the details of the package I do not intend to repeat them although I am tempted to do so because it seems an attempt has been made to distort them.  If anyone wants me to repeat all the elements of the package at this hour of the evening I can do so but one thing is quite clear &mdash; this has to be put on record &mdash; that there will be &mdash; if the House will bear with me for one minute&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    <Speaker pid="JoeCostelloLAB" hpid="Mr. Costello Mr. Costello">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Costello</NameTxt>
      <P>It is a distortion of the <Col N="100" /><i>Programme for Economic and Social Progress.</i></P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelOKennedy" hpid="Mr. O'Kennedy Mr. O'Kennedy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Kennedy</NameTxt>
      <P>I will come back to it in a moment because I want to give a specific assurance in relation to its impact on the overall economy and on those directly concerned.</P>
      <P>An attempt was made to convey the impression that we were prepared to reverse, reject and repudiate our obligation to the people who were entitled to special increases.  There was never any such intention.  The fact of the matter is that the Minister for Finance confirmed to Congress and the public service unions the irrevocable commitment given by the Taoiseach last December to pay the balances of special pay increases due with full retrospection to the dates on which the outstanding phases were due to be paid.  He also announced that with effect from 1 December the pay rates of those entitled to special increases would be increased to the levels which would have been payable under the previously agreed phasing arrangements.  In respect of all the elements, what is significant is that there will be no income losses.</P>
      <P>In the context of the constraints which I have mentioned, which were real the Government are prepared to have further discussions &mdash; I want to stress this point in particular, apart from the elements announced in the package which I am glad to say they have now recommended to their constituent members &mdash; with Congress in 1993 and before the <i>Programme for Economic and Social Progress</i> expires so that we can agree on a specific timetable for recoupment of the losses arising from the application of the ceilings of £5 and £6.50 per week at the earliest possible dates; in any event not later than 1994.  That, too, is entirely consistent with the position we have taken.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>As was the original intention and commitment, we want this programme to remain in place with all its vigour until the end of this decade.  The review of the position due to take place at the end of 1993, for 1994, will enable us to do just that, particularly in the context of the <Col N="101" /> projected economic growth internationally in 1993-94.  It is projected there will be economic growth, although of course no one can ever work on the basis that what is projected will be realised.  I think we are in the position&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    <Speaker pid="JoeCostelloLAB" hpid="Mr. Costello Mr. Costello">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Costello</NameTxt>
      <P>How can the Government give a promise and commitment for 1994?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Acting Chairman Acting Chairman">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman</NameTxt>
      <P>The Senator will be given an opportunity to reply.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelOKennedy" hpid="Mr. O'Kennedy Mr. O'Kennedy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Kennedy</NameTxt>
      <P>We are talking about our capacity, as a Government, to work within the disciplines we have set ourselves &mdash; no one has imposed them on us &mdash; to work within the GNP ratio.</P>
      <P>Senator Costello said an attempt has been made to vary the terms of the teachers' arbitration award but no such attempt has been made.  The first phase of the award has already been paid, with effect from 1 May 1991, and the remaining phases will be paid under the Government package with effect from 1 December 1992.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeCostelloLAB" hpid="Mr. Costello Mr. Costello">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Costello</NameTxt>
      <P>They are to be paid in March and September, not the following year.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelOKennedy" hpid="Mr. O'Kennedy Mr. O'Kennedy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Kennedy</NameTxt>
      <P>&mdash;&mdash;with full retrospection to the due dates payable on 1 January 1993.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeCostelloLAB" hpid="Mr. Costello Mr. Costello">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Costello</NameTxt>
      <P>Another promise from a Government that&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PaddyMcGowan" hpid="Mr. McGowan Mr. McGowan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGowan</NameTxt>
      <P>He does not like to hear the facts.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelOKennedy" hpid="Mr. O'Kennedy Mr. O'Kennedy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Kennedy</NameTxt>
      <P>It is not a promise, it is a fact.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeCostelloLAB" hpid="Mr. Costello Mr. Costello">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Costello</NameTxt>
      <P>I said that I pointed out that it amounted to a rescheduling of promises.</P>
      <P>
        <i>(Interruptions.)</i>
      </P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Acting Chairman Acting Chairman">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman</NameTxt>
      <P>Let us hear the Minister without interruption.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="102" />
    <Speaker pid="JoeCostelloLAB" hpid="Mr. Costello Mr. Costello">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Costello</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister has just repeated what I said.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelOKennedy" hpid="Mr. O'Kennedy Mr. O'Kennedy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Kennedy</NameTxt>
      <P>It is a rescheduling of payment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeCostelloLAB" hpid="Mr. Costello Mr. Costello">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Costello</NameTxt>
      <P>It is a rescheduling of promises.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelOKennedy" hpid="Mr. O'Kennedy Mr. O'Kennedy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Kennedy</NameTxt>
      <P>I am stating a fact.  It is not a variation of the amounts payable which is the point the Senator tried to put across in this House.  We should concentrate on the facts and not distort them to suit our own purposes.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PaddyMcGowan" hpid="Mr. McGowan Mr. McGowan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGowan</NameTxt>
      <P>He is not interested in the facts.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeCostelloLAB" hpid="Mr. Costello Mr. Costello">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Costello</NameTxt>
      <P>Stick to the <i>Programme for Economic and Social Progress</i> and do not distort it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Acting Chairman Acting Chairman">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman</NameTxt>
      <P>I would appreciate if Senators allowed the Minister to proceed, please.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelOKennedy" hpid="Mr. O'Kennedy Mr. O'Kennedy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Kennedy</NameTxt>
      <P>We should acknowledge that the stark alternative to the rescheduling of the pay increases due in 1992 would have been further cutbacks in public services, in areas such as health, education and social welfare.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="AvrilDoyle" hpid="Mrs. Doyle Mrs. Doyle">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Doyle</NameTxt>
      <P>We pointed that out.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelOKennedy" hpid="Mr. O'Kennedy Mr. O'Kennedy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Kennedy</NameTxt>
      <P>If we had listened to Members on that side of the House we would have driven the country even further into bankruptcy.  If we had listened to their recipes we would now have reached 20 per cent of GNP in our borrowing requirements.</P>
      <P>
        <i>(Interruptions.)</i>
      </P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="AvrilDoyle" hpid="Mrs. Doyle Mrs. Doyle">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Doyle</NameTxt>
      <P>Have the grace to say we were right.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TonyMcKenna" hpid="Mr. McKenna Mr. McKenna">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McKenna</NameTxt>
      <P>Is the <i>Programme for Economic and Social Progress</i> not a good arrangement?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Acting Chairman Acting Chairman">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman</NameTxt>
      <P>The House should <Col N="103" /> be treated with the dignity it deserves; let the Minister proceed.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelOKennedy" hpid="Mr. O'Kennedy Mr. O'Kennedy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Kennedy</NameTxt>
      <P>The Senator will recognise that there were good, cogent reasons for not taking advice from Senator Doyle's party, who, literally reduced us to bankruptcy.  We reduced the figure of 13 per cent of GNP to 2 per cent.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="AvrilDoyle" hpid="Mrs. Doyle Mrs. Doyle">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Doyle</NameTxt>
      <P>We were proved right on this issue, have the grace to admit it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelOKennedy" hpid="Mr. O'Kennedy Mr. O'Kennedy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Kennedy</NameTxt>
      <P>Obviously the <i>Programme for Economic and Social Progress</i> envisaged certain developments involving additional Exchequer costs, notably in the health and education areas, and funding was announced in the 1991 budget for such improvements.  The full year costs for these improvements &mdash; £23 million has been provided for in the abridged Estimates volume for 1992 which was published last month &mdash; and the extent to which it will be possible to make further progress in such initiatives in 1992 is being considered by the Government in the context of the budget. I will not deprive my colleague, the Minister for Finance, with whom I am working very closely on this, and my colleague, the Minister for Education of the opportunity to indicate the Government's position on this.  Suffice it to say that I underlined in a radio programme last Sunday that education has always been top priority for our party.  We demonstrated that over the years.  I was Parliamentary Secretary in the Department of Education in 1970, although I do not claim credit for the drive behind the education policy.  We have shown our commitment to education and I have no doubt we will show sensitivity in this matter also.  However, it is not appropriate for me to say any more at this stage.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Equity in taxation is an essential feature of this programme.  The Revenue Commissioners are putting together a new initiative for 1992 which will be designed to release experienced staff for <Col N="104" /> an increase in audits and at the same time to increase staff numbers engaged in the collection of arrears.  We will not stand back and watch the PAYE sector paying as they earn, while others for one reason or another, as I said earlier, avoid or evade their responsibilities in an outrageously unacceptable way.  Our performance here to date and our commitment to the future will leave no doubt about the Government's seriousness of purpose in this area.  We are committed to reducing income tax rates and to ensuring that all sections of the community pay a fair share of taxes.  We are also committed in the <i>Programme for Economic and Social Progress</i> and under the review of the programme to further radical reform of the income tax system in the next two years.  We are committed to trying to achieve the objective of a further significant reduction in rates and will work towards the objectives of a considerable widening of the standard base while increasing the personal allowance. My colleague, the Minister for Finance, my predecessor in this job, will obviously address the taxation issues along those lines in his budget next week. This Government &mdash; and their predecessor &mdash; have achieved a great deal with their partners under the <i>Programme for National Recovery</i> and the <i>Programme for Economic and Social Progress.</i></P>
    <P>Although I was reassured by Senator Harte's recognition of the importance of the motion, it is clear that those who put it forward at this point in the light of recent developments are demonstrating their disregard for the welfare of the public by calling on the House to condone the taking of industrial action, which, happily, did not happen, by public service employees.  Thankfully, the union leaders, with whom we have a partnership, were as determined as we were&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    <Speaker pid="JoeCostelloLAB" hpid="Mr. Costello Mr. Costello">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Costello</NameTxt>
      <P>The Government suddenly found the money when industrial action was threatened.  Only for the trade union movement the Minister would have welched on the deal.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="105" />
    <Speaker pid="MichaelOKennedy" hpid="Mr. O'Kennedy Mr. O'Kennedy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Kennedy</NameTxt>
      <P>There would have been widescale disruption and I am not sorry that we deprived the Senator of that pleasure.  I reject the motives behind the motion and we should all be grateful that wiser counsel prevailed.  When historians in future look back on 1992 and the <i>Programme for Economic and Social Progress</i>, they will acknowledge that 1992 was a year when industrial relations reached a new plateau despite the difficulties. It will be remembered as a year in which we came of age in the conduct of industrial relations, a year in which it was acknowledged that co-operation is always preferable to conflict, which serves nobody's interests.  This represents the culmination of the process of co-operation which was begun in 1987 by the previous Government and continued by the present Government.  The Opposition would get some credit if they acknowledged and gave a little credit to the Government's that succeeded the Fine Gael-Labour Coalition, who did nothing about this.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The amendment to this motion quite rightly asked the House to congratulate the Government on their package of measures presented to the trade unions. I do not take the credit because it was a team effort and a major achievement in averting the threatened industrial action by an imaginative packet of measures which meets the concern of public service employees, while at the same time remaining true to the economic imperatives of the <i>Programme for Economic and Social Progress.</i>  The amendment also acknowledges the valuable contribution of the Irish Congress of Trade Unions and the public service unions in their response to the package and calling off their threatened day of action.  I reiterate the respect the Government have for the trade union movement, for their discipline and co-operation since this programme was launched by the Taoiseach in 1987.  We are totally committed, despite the best efforts of some Members of the Opposition, to keep that programme in place.  It will remain in place because it will be the key to further <Col N="106" /> economic development through the next decade and beyond.</P>
    <Speaker pid="AvrilDoyle" hpid="Mrs. Doyle Mrs. Doyle">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Doyle</NameTxt>
      <P>It was interesting to listen to the Minister pleading and begging for some credit from the Opposition for the achievements of the last few years in Government.  He might have had the grace then&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TonyMcKenna" hpid="Mr. McKenna Mr. McKenna">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McKenna</NameTxt>
      <P>The Senator is distorting the facts.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Acting Chairman Acting Chairman">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator Doyle, without interruption.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="AvrilDoyle" hpid="Mrs. Doyle Mrs. Doyle">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Doyle</NameTxt>
      <P>If the Minister was looking for grace and acknowledgement the very least that he should have done at the outset of his remarks was to recognise that the warnings in relation to the ability of this nation to pay, under the agreement that was signed last spring in the <i>Programme for Economic and Social Progress</i>&mdash; by Fine Gael, regrettably, turned out to be justified.  We would love to have been in a position to say that we fully endorsed <i>Programme for Economic and Social Progress</i> last spring.  In fact we were the only party who recognised economic reality and the fairytale basis of the figures being offered.  Indeed it was quite unfair to the social partners who were sitting round the table to lead them down the road and to give them the impression that the Government would be capable of honouring the pay element of <i>Programme for Economic and Social Progress</i> when, as we said quite clearly, it would not be possible.  Would that it could have been but it was not possible at the time.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TonyMcKenna" hpid="Mr. McKenna Mr. McKenna">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McKenna</NameTxt>
      <P>Did the Senator's party have a crystal ball?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="AvrilDoyle" hpid="Mrs. Doyle Mrs. Doyle">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Doyle</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister should have started his contribution here this evening by giving credit to the only party to recognise the reality last spring.  I take the point he makes.  He might also have given credit to the Tallaght strategy, which in 1987 when Fianna Fáil came in, made life much easier and&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="107" />
    <Speaker pid="TonyMcKenna" hpid="Mr. McKenna Mr. McKenna">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McKenna</NameTxt>
      <P>That is the very reason the Senator's party dumped him.</P>
      <P>
        <i>(Interruptions.)</i>
      </P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Acting Chairman Acting Chairman">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator Doyle, without interruption.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TonyMcKenna" hpid="Mr. McKenna Mr. McKenna">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McKenna</NameTxt>
      <P>Is that not the very reason&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="AvrilDoyle" hpid="Mrs. Doyle Mrs. Doyle">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Doyle</NameTxt>
      <P>If the Minister wants&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Acting Chairman Acting Chairman">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman</NameTxt>
      <P>Please, Senator McKenna.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TonyMcKenna" hpid="Mr. McKenna Mr. McKenna">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McKenna</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator Doyle expects us to give credit to the Tallaght strategy&mdash;&mdash;</P>
      <P>
        <i>(Interruptions.)</i>
      </P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TonyMcKenna" hpid="Mr. McKenna Mr. McKenna">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McKenna</NameTxt>
      <P>They got credit for the Tallaght strategy.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeCostelloLAB" hpid="Mr. Costello Mr. Costello">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Costello</NameTxt>
      <P>That side of the House is very unruly.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Acting Chairman Acting Chairman">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman</NameTxt>
      <P>Please desist from interrupting.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="AvrilDoyle" hpid="Mrs. Doyle Mrs. Doyle">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Doyle</NameTxt>
      <P>The vultures on the other side of the House are giving the Chairman great practice and I hope he will be rewarded tomorrow when the vote is taken.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Acting Chairman Acting Chairman">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman</NameTxt>
      <P>Will the Senator speak to the motion, please?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="AvrilDoyle" hpid="Mrs. Doyle Mrs. Doyle">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Doyle</NameTxt>
      <P>Certainly.  I will be supporting the motion but not the amendment. Apart from the political tit-for-tat which has taken place in the House, there are some very serious issues to be addressed.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The insensitive way in which the Government made unilateral moves to dishonour the commitments in the <i>Programme for Economic and Social Progress</i> before Christmas must be recognised for what it was.  The Minister referred to the importance of the collective bargaining system, of honouring <Col N="108" /> it, of sitting down around the table and hammering out various decisions and agreements.  Yet, he did not refer to the insensitive way both he and his colleagues made the statement before Christmas that they could not pay.  The agreement reached last week by the Minister for Finance would not have been hammered out&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelOKennedy" hpid="Mr. O'Kennedy Mr. O'Kennedy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Kennedy</NameTxt>
      <P>As a matter of record and fact&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="AvrilDoyle" hpid="Mrs. Doyle Mrs. Doyle">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Doyle</NameTxt>
      <P>As the Minister knows, there is no such thing as a matter of record and fact, only a point of order.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelOKennedy" hpid="Mr. O'Kennedy Mr. O'Kennedy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Kennedy</NameTxt>
      <P>I specifically referred to the meeting the Taoiseach and other Ministers had with the trade union movement to explain what we did and why we were doing it.  I referred to it specifically&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="AvrilDoyle" hpid="Mrs. Doyle Mrs. Doyle">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Doyle</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister did not refer to the insensitivity shown by the Government in unilaterally deciding that the commitments in <i>Programme for Economic and Social Progress</i> would not be honoured.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelOKennedy" hpid="Mr. O'Kennedy Mr. O'Kennedy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Kennedy</NameTxt>
      <P>The Senator said I did not refer to the Government's position.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="AvrilDoyle" hpid="Mrs. Doyle Mrs. Doyle">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Doyle</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister should look at the review clause on page 92 of <i>Programme for Economic and Social Progress</i> which states that &ldquo;The parties to this Agreement shall meet not earlier than October 1992...&rdquo;  What revisionist view can the Minister now offer for changing his mind unilaterally on that?  The Minister should thank the unions for accepting the package put to them by the Minister for Finance.  The Minister for Finance only put forward that package which, to be honest, really only postponed the inevitable on the pay end, when faced with a one-day strike by the public sector.  This is why the Minister for Finance gave a little along those lines. Without the threat of a one-day strike by the public sector this would not have happened.  Would that we did not have <Col N="109" /> to face these threats and the unions did not have to face up to the Minister. However, the Minister threatened to unilaterally dishonour an agreement which is an essential part of the collective bargaining process.</P>
      <P>Last spring Fine Gael pointed out the difficulties facing the Government.  When you enter an agreement, as an honourable partner you cannot dishonour it unilaterally. This point must be clearly made.  Fine Gael believe that once an agreement has been entered into it must be honoured in full.  Far greater risk is posed to our economy, production, which, as the Minister pointed out, is so important, and employment if collective bargaining agreements such as this one are not honoured.  If we break the collective bargaining system and return to where we were a few years ago when we faced industrial chaos, the costs will be immeasurable and will be far greater than the costs of honouring the agreements which were entered into.</P>
      <P>The pay element of the agreement has been salvaged by postponing the inevitable for future budgets.  The Government have given a commitment to increase public sector pay by 9.25 per cent in the 1993 budget and by 10 per cent in the 1994 budget.  I hope the Government, who seem to have the neck to give a vote of confidence to themselves by assuming they will be around to deliver on this commitment&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TonyMcKenna" hpid="Mr. McKenna Mr. McKenna">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McKenna</NameTxt>
      <P>Fine Gael have some neck if they think they will be in Government&mdash;&mdash;</P>
      <P>
        <i>(Interruptions.)</i>
      </P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator Doyle without interruption.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="AvrilDoyle" hpid="Mrs. Doyle Mrs. Doyle">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Doyle</NameTxt>
      <P>Thank you, a Leas-Chathaoirligh, for your protection.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelOKennedy" hpid="Mr. O'Kennedy Mr. O'Kennedy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Kennedy</NameTxt>
      <P>Fine Gael's warm relationship with the trade union movement is coming through here.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="AvrilDoyle" hpid="Mrs. Doyle Mrs. Doyle">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Doyle</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister had half an <Col N="110" /> hour and he should let me have my share of the time.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelOKennedy" hpid="Mr. O'Kennedy Mr. O'Kennedy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Kennedy</NameTxt>
      <P>I have no doubt that Congress are waiting for the Senator and her party to develop a new warm relationship.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Please, Minister.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="AvrilDoyle" hpid="Mrs. Doyle Mrs. Doyle">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Doyle</NameTxt>
      <P>Changes need to be introduced to the public sector arbitrator's terms of reference to include an ability to pay clause.  This omission has caused some of the problems in relation to the pay elements of the <i>Programme for Economic and Social Progress</i> in recent times.  I ask the Minister to address this issue.  There is an ability to pay clause in the private sector which can be called on by industry if they genuinely cannot pay. Such a clause should be included in the public sector arbitrator's terms of reference.</P>
      <P>I ask the Minister to immediately ensure that several of the non-pay elements of the <i>Programme for Economic and Social Progress</i> are honoured. I am thinking in particular of the agreements entered into with the three teacher unions and the pupil-teacher ratio issue. I want to specifically ask him how many of the promised 250 new posts at primary level were created last September or whether that commitment was dishonoured also.  I should also like to know the pupil-teacher ratio at second level, whether half of the additional 500 posts were provided in 1991 and if the balance will be provided in 1992.  We need specifics and less waffle&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TonyMcKenna" hpid="Mr. McKenna Mr. McKenna">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McKenna</NameTxt>
      <P>Figures are statistics.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="AvrilDoyle" hpid="Mrs. Doyle Mrs. Doyle">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Doyle</NameTxt>
      <P>I should like the Minister for Labour to come to Wexford and tell the 24 per cent of people in my county who are unemployed just how marvellous are the macro-economic indicators.  As long as the unemployment figure is 20 per cent nationally and 24 per cent in County Wexford and other counties, the Minister will have to give a better line <Col N="111" /> than the one he gave us here tonight.  It was a good try&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I must ask the Senator to conclude.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="AvrilDoyle" hpid="Mrs. Doyle Mrs. Doyle">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Doyle</NameTxt>
      <P>&mdash;&mdash;but many of us did not buy it.  The Minister's revisionist views will not be accepted because the dole queue is the bottom line.  The Minister cannot blame returning emigrants for the increase in unemployment.  That is not an acceptable reason.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I call on Senator Costello to conclude.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelOKennedy" hpid="Mr. O'Kennedy Mr. O'Kennedy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Kennedy</NameTxt>
      <P>May I ask Senator Doyle to clarify a point?  I want to be clear on what she requires of me as Minister. She said that she wants specifics and less statistics.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="AvrilDoyle" hpid="Mrs. Doyle Mrs. Doyle">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Doyle</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelOKennedy" hpid="Mr. O'Kennedy Mr. O'Kennedy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Kennedy</NameTxt>
      <P>How does the Senator expect me to achieve that?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="AvrilDoyle" hpid="Mrs. Doyle Mrs. Doyle">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Doyle</NameTxt>
      <P>How many of the 250 new posts at primary level which were due last September were created?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I call Senator Costello to conclude.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="AvrilDoyle" hpid="Mrs. Doyle Mrs. Doyle">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Doyle</NameTxt>
      <P>How many of those posts were created?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TonyMcKenna" hpid="Mr. McKenna Mr. McKenna">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McKenna</NameTxt>
      <P>The Senator does not want statistics.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="AvrilDoyle" hpid="Mrs. Doyle Mrs. Doyle">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Doyle</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister cannot give the specifics.  The pay element is only a portion of the dishonourable&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I ask the Senator to refrain from interrupting Senator Costello.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="AvrilDoyle" hpid="Mrs. Doyle Mrs. Doyle">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Doyle</NameTxt>
      <P>I want the Minister to give me the specifics and not waffle&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PaddyMcGowan" hpid="Mr. McGowan Mr. McGowan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGowan</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator Doyle is not&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="112" />
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I would ask Senator Doyle and Senator McGowan not to interrupt Senator Costello.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PaddyMcGowan" hpid="Mr. McGowan Mr. McGowan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGowan</NameTxt>
      <P>May I&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I have called Senator Costello.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeCostelloLAB" hpid="Mr. Costello Mr. Costello">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Costello</NameTxt>
      <P>Thank you, a Leas-Chathaoirleach. I need your protection here tonight.  Unquestionably, the <i>Programme for Economic and Social Progress</i> was unilaterally broken by the Government.  There can be no denial of that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="AvrilDoyle" hpid="Mrs. Doyle Mrs. Doyle">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Doyle</NameTxt>
      <P>Dishonourably.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TonyMcKenna" hpid="Mr. McKenna Mr. McKenna">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McKenna</NameTxt>
      <P>It was not.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeCostelloLAB" hpid="Mr. Costello Mr. Costello">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Costello</NameTxt>
      <P>This decision was taken by the Government unilaterally, with no negotiation or consultation.  There is no point in Senator McKenna saying&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelOKennedy" hpid="Mr. O'Kennedy Mr. O'Kennedy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Kennedy</NameTxt>
      <P>The <i>Programme for Economic and Social Progress</i> is alive and well, and the Senator knows it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeCostelloLAB" hpid="Mr. Costello Mr. Costello">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Costello</NameTxt>
      <P>&mdash;&mdash;that it would be a very bad programme which did not have provision for renegotiation.  This programme has provision for a review only after October 1992.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TonyMcKenna" hpid="Mr. McKenna Mr. McKenna">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McKenna</NameTxt>
      <P>Read the preamble.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeCostelloLAB" hpid="Mr. Costello Mr. Costello">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Costello</NameTxt>
      <P>It is specifically stated&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TonyMcKenna" hpid="Mr. McKenna Mr. McKenna">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McKenna</NameTxt>
      <P>Read the preamble.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator Costello without interruption.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="AvrilDoyle" hpid="Mrs. Doyle Mrs. Doyle">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Doyle</NameTxt>
      <P>I hope that crowd will not write our history books.  If they do, God knows what version we will get.</P>
      <P>
        <i>(Interruptions.)</i>
      </P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator Costello has only a few minutes in which to <Col N="113" /> reply and I ask Senators to show him the courtesy of allowing him to reply.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeCostelloLAB" hpid="Mr. Costello Mr. Costello">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Costello</NameTxt>
      <P>It was said that for short term expediency it would be wrong for industrial action to be taken.  The issue of short term expediency is in the Government's court.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TonyMcKenna" hpid="Mr. McKenna Mr. McKenna">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McKenna</NameTxt>
      <P>I did not say that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeCostelloLAB" hpid="Mr. Costello Mr. Costello">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Costello</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister for Finance had an estimate of £40 million when he knew what the terms of the <i>Programme for Economic and Social Progress</i> were last year.  He was only £41 million out.  If this is so, it shows short term expediency on the Government's part to be breaching the terms of the <i>Programme for Economic and Social Progress</i> on that small amount of money.</P>
      <P>Senator McGowan stated that he knew a trade unionist in County Donegal who was proud that he had never brought members out on the street.  I want to categorically state that it was not the trade union movement who wanted to bring their members out on the street in the proposed industrial action; it was the Government who were doing this by their unilateral decision which forced the trade union movement to compel the Government&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelOKennedy" hpid="Mr. O'Kennedy Mr. O'Kennedy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Kennedy</NameTxt>
      <P>The Fine Gael-Labour Coalition Government&mdash;&mdash;</P>
      <P>
        <i>(Interruptions.)</i>
      </P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Order. Senator Costello without interruption.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PaddyMcGowan" hpid="Mr. McGowan Mr. McGowan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGowan</NameTxt>
      <P>For Senator Costello's information, that&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator McGowan, please allow Senator Costello to speak.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PaddyMcGowan" hpid="Mr. McGowan Mr. McGowan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGowan</NameTxt>
      <P>&mdash;&mdash;trade union official in County Donegal said that every union has to have a hatchet man.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I have to ask <Col N="114" /> Senator McGowan to please desist from interrupting Senator Costello.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="AvrilDoyle" hpid="Mrs. Doyle Mrs. Doyle">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Doyle</NameTxt>
      <P>It looks as if every side of the Seanad has a hatchet man as well. Are you also going for the position of Cathaoirleach, Paddy?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator Costello without interruption, please.  I am absolutely stunned at the way Senators are behaving and I will suspend the House if this continues.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeCostelloLAB" hpid="Mr. Costello Mr. Costello">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Costello</NameTxt>
      <P>I hope I will get back the time I have lost because of these unwarranted interruptions from the other side of the House.</P>
      <P>I say to the Minister that I support the <i>Programme for Economic and Social Progress.</i>  I am a supporter and a promoter of a social partnership.  I do not knock it.  It is because I support it wholeheartedly that I want to ensure that the agreement is honoured.  We cannot go forward to another programme if the Government decide that all the other partners must fulfil their part of the bargain but because the budgetary calculations are £40 million out, the Government can breach the agreement. That is why the trade union movement had to take such resolute action.  That is the only reason the Minister and the Government climbed down.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I acknowledge the good work that has been done over the years reducing Exchequer borrowing and I applaud the Government but it was only done with the co-operation of the trade union movement.  That is why it is so important to retain their co-operation.  Once it is breached it is breached forever and there will be no trust.  Why are the public sector workers always the first to feel the economic squeeze?  I am sure everybody has seen the posters &mdash; why squeeze the public servants all the time?  In the Comptroller and Auditor General's report for this year he identified quite clearly £426 million that is collectable at present.  Why is that money not brought in?  If that were brought in this year it <Col N="115" /> would meet all these demands.  The Minister has said there is a commitment to tax equity and tax collection, but that £426 million is money we can get our hands on immediately.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelOKennedy" hpid="Mr. O'Kennedy Mr. O'Kennedy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Kennedy</NameTxt>
      <P>We will hear from the Minister for Finance next week.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeCostelloLAB" hpid="Mr. Costello Mr. Costello">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Costello</NameTxt>
      <P>I have very specifically asked for a commitment or for some information from the Minister about the non-pay elements which are critical for certain sectors of the public service, and I have clearly identified the health and education areas.  I have seen nothing either in the Estimates or in the Minister's speech &mdash; he has kicked it for touch to the Minister for Finance &mdash; to convince me that there is anything substantial being delivered in this area.  What are the specifics on the pupil-teacher ratio?  The commitment in that regard was delivered in 1991, but will it be delivered in 1992? Where is the money to bring the vice principals outside the quota, for the career guidance teachers, to meet the commitments to the disadvantaged or for in-service training?  We have the worst record in Europe for professional training for our teachers.  Where are the commitments to that?  Where are the commitments to the £17,500 required to ensure that there is a secretary and a caretaker in each school?  Until and unless those commitments are met, industrial action is only deferred.  I do not want to see a situation after 29 January where the three teacher unions and the health unions get together and say they are sorry but they simply cannot accept this proposal because it is a substantial breach of the agreement they entered into and affects substantially the quality of the education and health systems. These are critical areas because they include a social aspect.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Sacrifices were made by the public service in the <i>Programme for National Recovery</i> over the three previous years. They were bumper years in terms of gross national product, exports, profits and the repatriation of a great deal of money.  We <Col N="116" /> cannot be expected to suffer indefinitely and if there is a problem the people in the public service should not be expected to further tighten the belt.</P>
    <P>There will be a budgetary bottleneck in 1993 and 1994.  Many non-pay elements were transferred from 1991 to 1992 specifically to avoid a budgetary bottleneck in 1991.  Now they are being transferred from 1992 to 1993 and 1994 to avoid a budgetary bottleneck in 1992.  We have to deal with this at some stage and this is the time to do it.  I exhort the Government and the Minister to realise that they do not have a major budgetary problem in financial terms because they can fulfil the commitments in the <i>Programme for Economic and Social Progress.</i> It may involve a slight variation of the Exchequer borrowing requirement and the expected income in tax revenue in the coming year, but I think that can be borne.</P>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I must ask the Senator to conclude.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeCostelloLAB" hpid="Mr. Costello Mr. Costello">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Costello</NameTxt>
      <P>If that is not done industrial relations and the social partnership will go down the drain.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Is the amendment agreed?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeCostelloLAB" hpid="Mr. Costello Mr. Costello">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Costello</NameTxt>
      <P>No.</P>
      <P>Amendment put and declared carried.</P>
      <P>Motion, as amended, agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>When is it proposed to sit again?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFallon" hpid="Mr. Fallon Mr. Fallon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Fallon</NameTxt>
      <P>It is proposed to sit tomorrow at 2.30 p.m.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Adjournment Matter. -" RHead="Disposal of Clinical Waste">
    <Title>Adjournment Matter. - Disposal of Clinical Waste.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="JoeCostelloLAB" hpid="Mr. Costello Mr. Costello">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Costello</NameTxt>
      <P>I welcome the Minister to the House.  I did not expect to meet him again so soon.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The disposal of clinical waste is a very <Col N="117" /> serious matter.  This waste emanates from hospitals &mdash; I refer particularly to Dublin &mdash; and has to be disposed of in residential and densely populated areas.  There are two ways of disposing of it, one by landfill disposal and the other by incineration. Landfill disposal is a very dangerous and limited method because segregation of the material is required and that means no infectious material can be put into a landfill site.  Obviously this requries a high level of segregation and segregation facilities are not in place in the hospitals. Consequently the normal method of disposal of clinical waste is through incineration. If you go to any hospital in Dublin you will see a tall chimney puffing black sooty smoke into surrounding residential areas a number of times a day.</P>
    <P>It is ironic that a hospital which is a place for healing pollutes and causes illnesses. This soot falls on clothes lines and an enormous amount of pollution is caused.  Residents complain about this pollution all the time.  It is ironic that while we have disposed of the problem of smog from burning bituminous fuel in the city of Dublin we still have pollution from clinical waste, particularly from hospitals.  It is a contradictory situation and cannot be tolerated.  The situation is worse in that while we have an air pollution Act we do not have any specific Irish standards for the incineration of and disposal of hospital waste.  We cannot adhere to the British or the German standards because of the antiquated incinerators operating in our hospitals.  That is very serious.</P>
    <P>The Department of the Environment recommend adhering to British standards but we do not have the facilities to do so.  The level of heat requried under the British and German standards cannot be matched by our antiquated incinerators. It appears there are no guidelines covering private incinerator operations and when inspection of them was carried out, some were found to be in breach of the recommended standards of the Department of the Environment.  That is very serious.  The incinerators were not designed for the temperatures now required.  The equipment is not adequate <Col N="118" /> for the volume of waste.  Maintenance either does not take place or is neglected. The personnel manning the incinerators have little or no training for the job and, consequently, their efficiency of the incinerators is extremely poor.  The monitoring of the incineration of clinical waste is virtually nil.</P>
    <P>We operate almost in a vacuum.  We do not know how the radioactive waste emanating from our hospitals is being treated or disposed of.  There seems to be no firm evidence about it.  That is extremely serious.  Is radioactive waste being dumped in landfill sites?  How does one incinerate and dispose of radioactive waste properly?  Are infectious materials being dumped in landfill sites?  Nobody seems to know.</P>
    <P>We have reached the stage where we have an optimum of two years or thereabouts remaining in the existing corporation sites in Dublin.  We will be faced with a bigger problem in disposing of waste whether of a general or a clinical nature later.  We do not have systems for separating waste, whether radioactive material, infectious material or other waste that may not be dangerous.  That is why I am asking the Minister for Health if some better procedure can be put in place.  A better procedure should be developed.  We need to look at the question of waste in the national as distinct from the Dublin context.  We must look at the question of the management of hospital waste and develop a coherent approach so that we are simply not relying on the hospital authorities to make a decision on incineration, the use of private operators or landfill sites for waste disposal.</P>
    <P>There are no regulations, no standards and no procedures for disposing of waste. It is incredible in this day and age that we are operating a system that has not been updated since Victorian times. Waste disposal is not subject to surveillance or to any Irish standards and regulations.  We do not know the dangers of the material that may be emanating from hospitals.  We express concern about the nuclear threat from across the water yet we have not taken precautions <Col N="119" /> to ensure that our hospitals do not dispose of radioactive material.</P>
    <P>How can we deal with this?  We must get an alternative to on-site incineration. Hospitals by their nature deal with large numbers of people, and are, therefore, located in urban areas.  Generally hospitals are surrounded by large residential areas.  Dublin has 37 hospitals, and many people live adjacent to these hospitals.  If we are to protect the health of the people who reside in those areas we must have an alternative system to on-site incineration.  We must choose another location and another method of waste disposal.  I am not sure incineration is the solution.  It may well be but the incinerator should not be sited near a hospital.</P>
    <P>I wish to bring to the attention of the Minister the serious nature of the matter, the volume of complaints on a daily basis from people who expect hospitals to deal with and protect their health.  The Minister, and the Department of Health, should have a policy on this and develop a plan that will ensure the present unsatisfactory situation is discontinued.  We should have emission control levels, and methods of dealing with clinical waste. Above all, we must ensure that there is no detrimental effect on the population in the vicinity of a hospital from which clinical waste material emanates.</P>
    <Speaker pid="ChrisFlood" hpid="Minister of State at the Department of Health (Mr. Flood) Chris Flood">
      <NameTxt>Minister of State at the Department of Health (Mr. Flood)</NameTxt>
      <P>I am pleased to have an opportunity to respond to this important issue and I thank Senator Costello for raising it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>First, I should explain that my Department's technical officers have been examining for some time a number of options for the disposal of hospital waste, including clinical waste, with a view to arriving at the most economic and environmentally acceptable solution.  The policy of the hospital authorities is that hospital waste should be segregated into infected and non-infected categories, the infected waste being incinerated and the non-infected waste being sent for disposal by deep burial at tipheads.  The two main <Col N="120" /> current methods of disposal are, therefore, incineration and burying at tipheads.  Other technologies which are under investigation include steam sterilisation and a grinding and chemical sterilisation process.</P>
    <P>It must be recognised that hospitals, by the nature of the medical treatments which are performed in them, will produce waste which is bacteriologically dangerous and must be made safe.</P>
    <P>Infectious waste contains pathogens in sufficient concentration or quantity that exposure to it could result in disease.  This category includes cultures and stocks of infectious agents from laboratory work, waste from surgery and autopsies on patients with infectious diseases, waste from infected patients in isolation wards, waste that has been in contact with infected patients undergoing haemodialysis, for example dialysis equipment such as tubing and filters, disposable towels, gowns, aprons, gloves and laboratory coats and waste that has been in contact with animals inoculated with an infectious agent or suffering from an infectious disease.</P>
    <P>The best method of rendering such infectious waste harmless is to raise it to a temperature which will destroy all living organisms.  This has traditinally been done in the hospital incinerator.  Unfortunately, the incineration of hospital waste gives rise to the production of products of combustion which must be discharged into the atmosphere.  With the present generation of incinerators, these products will frequently include visible smoke and can cause atmospheric pollution. There is no way of avoiding the production of infectious waste from hospitals and so the challenge is to render it safe while not causing pollution.  This can be done but it cannot be done cheaply and it cannot be done overnight.</P>
    <P>This whole area involves complex economic and technical considerations and one conclusion which has emerged is that incineration is the preferred method of disposal.  However, hospital waste is difficult to incinerate in a smokeless fashion and the equipment required to meet the current stringent environmental <Col N="121" /> standards is tending to become more and more expensive and sophisticated. Within the incineration option there are a number of alternatives including incineration on each hospital site using incinerators manufactured to an acceptable standard; on-site incineration of biologically hazadous material with off-site disposal of other waste; central or group incineration on selected hospital sites serving a number of hospitals; and contract incineration off site.  The high cost of the chemical scrubbing and filtration equipment required to meet environmental standards rules out incineration on each hospital site.</P>
    <P>I am aware that criticisms have been made from time to time in relation to the arrangements currently in force for the disposal of hospital waste.  Some of these criticisms relate to the use of incinerators that are alleged to be defective or, indeed, inadequate.  Many of the hospital incinerators currently in use have been stated to be incapable of reaching the required temperatures for efficient operation.</P>
    <P>While the implementation of waste disposal procedures is a matter for the health agencies concerned in the first instance, I do accept that many of these criticisms are justified.  The fact is that many of our hospital incinerators are not geared to the level of performance required to meet today's rigorous standards on a continuous basis.  These standards are becoming more demanding year by year in response to society's increasing concern for the environment.</P>
    <P>Because of the inability of many of our individual hospital incinerators to meet the required standard, my Department consider that the most cost-effective and environmentally acceptable solution to the problem appears to be the provision of large centralised incinerators to cater for more than one hospital.  A proposal to establish a central incinerator to cater for the clinical waste from all Dublin hospitals is well advanced.  I am determined that this proposal, and any other proposal for the disposal of clinical waste, will be subject to the fullest scrutiny to <Col N="122" /> ensure compliance with today's environmental standards.  That scrutiny will involve the completion of an environmental impact study by EOLAS, and the seeking of planning permission and a licence under the Air Pollution Act.</P>
    <P>The question arises whether it is better to locate a central incinerator on a hospital site or in a separate location. One advantage of locating a central incinerator on a hospital site is that the heat produced by incineration can be recovered and used to heat the hospital. The recommended temperature for incineration of hospital waste varies from one country to another.  A survey of emission rules in seven countries, published some time ago in the Journal of the Institute of Hospital Engineering, shows recommended temperatures of 800ºC to 1,000ºC and I am taking the steps necessary to ensure that all waste will be incinerated in conditions which comply with these requirements.</P>
    <P>As I have already mentioned, this whole question is extremely complicated and my Department are in constant touch with the Department of the Environment in relation to the central incineration arrangements envisaged and in relation to an EC proposal to include hospital and other clinical wastes in a new and extended definition of hazardous waste.</P>
    <P>In relation to the disposal of hospital waste by incineration, the Air Pollution Act, 1987, obliges the occupiers of non-domestic premises, including premises belonging to the State, to use the best practicable means to prevent or limit air pollution.  Hospital incinerators are within the scope of this Act and are subject therefore to its general provisions. The Minister for the Environment has made regulations establishing a licensing system for new plant to which the Act applies and it is the intention that, in due course, all existing plant, including existing hospital incinerators, will be brought within the scope of the licensing system.</P>
    <P>I should like to thank the Senator again for raising this important question and I assure the House that every effort is being made by my Department to <Col N="123" /> implement a hospital waste disposal policy that will overcome the difficulties associated with current practices and comply fully with the demanding requirements <Col N="124" /> of modern environmental and other standards.</P>
    <P>The Seanad adjourned at 8.30 p.m. until 2.30 p.m. on Thursday, 23 January 1992.</P>
  </MainHeading>
</Debate>