<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE Debate SYSTEM "../Debate.dtd"[]>
<Debate DocTitle="Seanad Debate" Day="Wed" Date="26" Month="Feb" Year="1992" Vol="131" No="10" DateIrish="Dé Céadaoin, 26 Feabhra 1992" DateEnglish="Wednesday, 26 February 1992" House="S" CommitteeEng="" CommitteeIr="" SubNameEng="" cnum="0">
  <MainHeading Type="Prelude" LHead="" RHead="">
    <Title>
    </Title>
    <P>
      <Col N="821" /> Chuaigh an Cathaoirleach i gceannas ar 2.30 p.m.</P>
    <P Just="Center">
      <i>Paidir.</i>
    </P>
    <P Just="Center">
      <i>Prayer.</i>
    </P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Business" RHead="of Seanad">
    <Title>Business of Seanad.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="SeanDoherty" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I have notice from Senator Haughey that, on the motion for the Adjournment of the House today, he proposes to raise the following matter:</P>
      <P>The need for the Minister for the Marine to outline the current situation regarding the report by his Department's inspectors and other reports into the collision between two ships near the entrance to Dublin Port on 21 November.</P>
      <P>I also received notice from Senator Costello of the following matter:</P>
      <P>The need for the Minister for Education to rescind the decision to means test ESF grants for students enrolling in the regional technical colleges and Dublin Institute of Technology colleges.</P>
      <P>I also received notice from Senator Neville of the following matter:</P>
      <P>The need for the Minister for Justice to recognise and deal with the urban deprivation and absence of opportunity in life which is contributing to the high levels of urban crime in sections of our cities and towns.</P>
      <P>I also received notice from Senator Brendan Ryan of the following matter:</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="822" /> The need for the Minister for Social Welfare to clarify, in the light of recent reports, the interpretation by his Department of the requirement that recipients of unemployment assistance and unemployment benefit be genuinely seeking work.</P>
    <P>I also received notice from Senator Doyle of the following matter:</P>
    <P>The need for the Minister for Health to provide funds for the provision of permanent residential accommodation for the old and infirm of Wexford town and surrounding area.</P>
    <P>I also received notice from Senator Fitzgerald of the following matter:</P>
    <P>To ask the Minister for Health to provide extra funding to the Southern Health Board for the staffing of a dialysis unit in Tralee General Hospital.</P>
    <P>I also received notice from Senator McKenna of the following matter.</P>
    <P>The need for the Minister for the Environment to derate Gurteen Agricultural College, Ballingarry, Roscrea, County Tipperary.</P>
    <P>I regard the matters raised by Senators Haughey, Costello, Neville, Ryan, Doyle and Fitzgerald as suitable for discussion on the Adjournment.  I have selected Senator Haughey's matter and it will be taken at the conclusion of business. Senators Costello, Neville, Ryan, Doyle and Fitzgerald may give notice on another day of the matters they wish to raise.</P>
    <P>I regret I have to rule the matter raised by Senator McKenna as not suitable for discussion on the Adjournment on the grounds of lack of ministerial responsibility.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Seanad" RHead="Appointments">
    <Title>Seanad Appointments.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="SeanDoherty" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Before I call Senator Wright, I would like to announce, for the information of the House, that the appointments of Senator G.V. Wright as Leader of the House, of <Col N="823" /> Senator Eoin Ryan as Government Chief Whip and of Senator Tom Fitzgerald as Assistant Government Chief Whip have been confirmed.  I warmly congratulate them on their appointments and wish them well in their new roles.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Order of" RHead="Business">
    <Title>Order of Business.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="GVWright" hpid="Mr. Wright Mr. Wright">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Wright</NameTxt>
      <P>Thank you, a Chathaoirligh. The Order of Business for today is as follows: Item No. 1 until 6 p.m.; there will be a sos from 6 p.m. to 6.30 p.m., and we will take Motion 44 from 6.30 p.m. to 8 p.m.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MauriceManning" hpid="Mr. Manning Mr. Manning">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Manning</NameTxt>
      <P>On the Order of Business, I would like first to congratulate Senator Wright on his appointment as Leader of the House.  In the short spell he has been Acting Leader he has shown qualities of great courtesy, innovation and a willingness to look at new ways of doing our business.  I know he will continue in that way and I wish him every success as Leader of the House.  I would like to ask him, as Leader of the House, to confirm as quickly as possible the changes which have been agreed by all groups and parties: the first phase of Seanad reform could be put into effect virtually immediately.</P>
      <P>A number of items have been raised over the past number of weeks on which Senators would like to have a debate, namely, the future of broadcasting, the banking system and some other issues. Perhaps the Leader of the House might put in place some structure whereby these matters can be taken in a fairly orderly way.  May I also congratulate Senator Eoin Ryan on his appointment as Government Chief Whip and assure him of our full co-operation.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanDoherty" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator Upton.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeOToole" hpid="Mr. O'Toole Mr. O'Toole">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Toole</NameTxt>
      <P>I would like to point out that the Independent group is the second largest group on this side of the House.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanDoherty" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>My apologies.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="824" />
    <Speaker pid="JoeOToole" hpid="Mr. O'Toole Mr. O'Toole">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Toole</NameTxt>
      <P>I welcome the appointment of Senator Wright as Leader of the House and I wish him well.  It is a job he will discharge effectively and efficiently, as he has always done in his previous role and in his role as Acting Leader of the House.  I am glad to go on the record on that point.  I have no doubt that there will be many differences of opinion during his period in office.  Nevertheless, it is important that he should begin with our best wishes and with a guarantee of support and co-operation as far as that can be offered at any given time.  Similarly, I congratulate Senator Eoin Ryan on his promotion and wish him well in the hazards of being Whip &mdash; not to let them off to funerals and weddings and to make sure he has them all in the House in time. Finally, may I also extend congratulations to my fellow townsman, Senator Fitzgerald, for holding his position despite all the changes around him.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TrasHonan" hpid="Mrs. Honan Mrs. Honan">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Honan</NameTxt>
      <P>One of the few who did.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeOToole" hpid="Mr. O'Toole Mr. O'Toole">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Toole</NameTxt>
      <P>As well as supporting Senator Manning's proposal, may I ask the Leader to slot in a period of time each week for the next number of weeks in order to deal with a number of outstanding issues on which there is general agreement that they should be dealt with?  This has been discussed on the Order of Business time and time again. It should be done, and done efficiently. We should slot in some period of time on Thursday morning or Thursday afternoon or late on Wednesday night or whatever in order to deal with those matters and just get them off the Order Paper.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I would ask the Leader to put on the Order of Business for early discussion the Government's proposed Green Paper on Education.  I think it is irresponsible, incompetent, no way to do business, and mismanagement on the past of the Government that we hear of their policies on education through leaks to the media. It is just not good enough.  This is far too important an issue to have people going off at half cock, responding to stories and half stories.  The Government now have <Col N="825" /> a responsibility to clear the air on this matter and insist that the Green Paper be published and circulated to the people who will be taking decisions at the end of the day.  They are the people in this House, in the other House and in the Department of Education.  As far as I am concerned, this is not the way to do business.  It reflects on Government and I ask that the matter be put on the agenda as early as possible.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatUpton" hpid="Dr. Upton Dr. Upton">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Upton</NameTxt>
      <P>I congratulate Senator Wright on his appointment and also congratulate Senators Ryan and Fitzgerald. While Senator Wright has been Acting Leader he has been very easy to deal with, he has been courteous and pleasant and I am especially pleased to see him getting the job on a permanent basis.  I wish Senator Ryan well on his promotion and I am pleased to see that Senator Fitzgerald goes on and on and on as many other things seem to change.</P>
      <P>It is about six months now since we had the O'Keeffe initiative on banking and I would like to ask the Leader of the House if we are any nearer to the debate on banking.  I would also like to ask him when we are likely to have a debate on Item No.3 &mdash; Oireachtas (Allowances to Members) and Ministerial and Parliamentary Offices (Amendment) Bill, 1991.  Certainly, there seems to be quite a number of our colleagues in the other House who are very anxious that that Bill would be taken in the near future.  I would also like to ask the Leader what is the present position in relation to the proposed reform of the Seanad?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MartinCullen" hpid="Mr. Cullen Mr. Cullen">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cullen</NameTxt>
      <P>On behalf of the Progressive Democrats, I join with the other Members and wish Senator Wright every success and congratulate him on his appointment as Leader of the House.  I also congratulate Senator Ryan and Senator Fitzgerald.  The Leader has a clear opportunity now to bring in the reforms that are necessary and recognised as such in the House.  He does not come with any baggage of institutionisation and he can bring a fresh approach to business.  I ask him to pursue <Col N="826" /> matters such as the introduction of legislation in this House.  There is an opportunity for him to exercise his authority and leadership abilities for the benefit of the Seanad and I hope he will do that.  I ask him to move as quickly as possible on the issue of the foreign affairs committee which we have been asking for the past two years.  If he could be seen to deliver on that committee it would be a good start for him in his new position.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeOReilly" hpid="Mr. O'Reilly Mr. O'Reilly">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Reilly</NameTxt>
      <P>I join with other speakers in their good wishes to the three Senators.  Laat year I had the privilege of spending time working on the Child Care Bill and proposing amendments, one of which was accepted.  I now ask the Leader of the House to convey to the Minister for Health my concern and the concern of this side of the House about the alarming report today from the ISPCC in relation to child sexual abuse and, indeed, to general physical abuse.  I am concerned that the Minister should back up what I believe to be an excellent Child Care Bill with the necessary finance to make it effective in dealing with child care abuse. I urge the Leader to convey that to the Minister.  Indeed, if he feels it necessary, he should take the issue to the House again for further discussion so that we can give effect to the very fine principles in the Bill.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PaddyMcGowan" hpid="Mr. McGowan Mr. McGowan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGowan</NameTxt>
      <P>I join with the other speakers in extending congratulations to Senators Wright, Ryan and Fitzgerald.  I would also ask the House to send their support and good wishes to the Taoiseach for his meeting this afternoon with the British Premier.  I am delighted the Taoiseach has decided to put the North of Ireland and the relationship between Britain and Ireland at the top of the agenda.  All of us would like to see a very successful meeting and it would be appropriate if we sent our support and good wishes to the Taoiseach.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanHaughey" hpid="Mr. Haughey Mr. Haughey">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Haughey</NameTxt>
      <P>I would like to join with other Senators in congratulating Senators Wright, Ryan and Fitzgerald on appointment to their new positions.  It is good to <Col N="827" /> see three young men appointed to these positions of authority.  The fact that Senator Fitzgerald has survived in his position demonstrated that he is, indeed, universally popular around this House and the Oireachtas in general.</P>
      <P>There are reports that the chairman of the Irish Wheel chair Association could not gain admittance yesterday to an Oireachtas Joint Committee.  He is reported as saying he had to suffer the indignity of being lifted up several stairs to gain admittance to a meeting of the Oireachtas.  The meeting took place in Kildare House.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanDoherty" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>It is not appropriate, Senator Haughey, but I am giving you a little leeway.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanHaughey" hpid="Mr. Haughey Mr. Haughey">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Haughey</NameTxt>
      <P>I appreciate that probably it is not appropriate, but it is very serious.  I think all buildings associated with the work of Parliament should be fully accessable to disabled people and perhaps you might use your good offices to investigate that report.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanDoherty" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Certainly.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryJackman" hpid="Mrs. Jackman Mrs. Jackman">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Jackman</NameTxt>
      <P>I would like to extend my congratulations and good wishes to the three Senators &mdash; Senator Wright, Senator Ryan and to Senator Fitzgerald for retaining his position.</P>
      <P>I would like to support what Senator O'Toole said in regard to the issue of the Green Paper and to ask that it be published and circulated for discussion in this House first.  It has been promised to us for well over a year.  It is sad we have to read about leaks, to hear all sorts of rumours of what is in the Green Paper, with lobbying going on already, when we are not even aware of what is in it.</P>
      <P>Secondly, what has happened to the promise made by the Minister for Justice that he would have legislation before us in relation to matrimonial property and joint ownership of the family home?  That is something that should be addressed immediately.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="828" />
    <Speaker pid="BattOKeeffe" hpid="Mr. O'Keeffe Mr. O'Keeffe">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Keeffe</NameTxt>
      <P>I would like to be associated with the congratulations to the Leader of the House.  His promotion to that position today proves that a person can have genuine aspirations to Dáil Éireann and have a full and total commitment to the effective operation of the Upper House.  Senator Wright manifests the efficiency and effectiveness with which this House can operate.  I also extend my congratulations to Senator Ryan and Senator Fitzgerald.  Speaking abut Senator Fitzgerald, may I say he reminds me a bit of Fungi, forever playful but always loyal.</P>
      <P>I raise also the issue of the role of the Seanad.  We have spent a number of days speaking on the role of the Seanad and the reform of the Seanad.  We have been talking about a debate on the banks for well over 12 months.  I did not realise it was being called the O'Keeffe initiative, but the banks are a major issue.  If the reforms that are proposed for the Seanad were brought into effect it would get over a number of problems we are experiencing and would make it far easier for us to debate issues of common concern. I ask the Leader of the House to ensure that these reforms are brought to fruition at the earliest date possible.</P>
      <P>May I also ask the Leader of the House if, in view of the Culliton report, the Seanad will be given an opportunity to have our say on the creation of employment. It is a matter of concern to everybody and the Seanad should be afforded an early oportunity to discuss it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeCostelloLAB" hpid="Mr. Costello Mr. Costello">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Costello</NameTxt>
      <P>I, too, would like to congratulate Senators Wright, Ryan and Fitzgerald on their appointments.  I am sure on his first day as Leader of the House.  Senator Wright will have good news for me about a matter I raised here previously in relation to Nicky Kelly.  He promised he would have a word with the Minister for Justice to see whether the Attorney General had come forward with recommendations.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I would like to support Senator O'Toole and Senator Jackman in relation to the request for a debate on the Green Paper on Education.  We have had more <Col N="829" /> leaks on this matter than virtually on any other issue in the past 12 months.  Indeed, this Green Paper was supposed to have been published 12 months ago, the White Paper in the autumn and the legislation was intended to be enacted under the <i>Programme for Economic and Social Progress</i> by last Christmas.  It would be valuable if we could have the Green Paper debated here in the House at an early date.  I understand it is now intended to have it published next week.</P>
    <P>Finally, in relation to the debate we have had on the role of the Seanad, could we get agreement urgently on the matters that were agreed by all speakers with a view to expediting business and arranging debates on a greater number of topical matters that are coming up on the Order of Business again and again?  Matters of concern have been raised in the past couple of weeks in the context of unemployment, Northern Ireland, broadcasting and so on, we urgently need to debate them.</P>
    <Speaker pid="DavidNorris" hpid="Mr. Norris Mr. Norris">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norris</NameTxt>
      <P>I would like to join in congratulation to Senator Wright, Senator Ryan and Senator Fitzgerald. They are all decent, honourable men, who are very courteous and efficient in dealing with the business of the House.  I am sure that their appointment in two cases, and continuance in office in the third case, will enhance the operations of the House.  I think these appointments are welcomed on all sides of the House.</P>
      <P>I add my voice to that of Senator McGowan in sending best wishes to the Taoiseach on his meeting in London with the British Prime Minister.  I welcome the fact that he had established such a good working relationship with John Major, when Mr. Major was Chancellor of the Exchequer and the present Taoiseach was Minister for Finance.  It is a positive basis on which to begin.  I ask the Leader of the House to fix an early date for a major debate on the North of Ireland. There have been a number of requests for such a debate.  It is something that would be welcomed throughout the House.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I want to ask the Leader of the House <Col N="830" /> if I can have some clear, specific information about the Government's plans for reform of the laws on homosexuality.  He indicated there was a White Paper in the pipeline.  I take it that means the Government's plans are shaping up.  I would very much welcome a specific date. I do not intend to be obstructive, but it is three and a half years since the judgment of the European Court and I may have to move towards opposing the Order of Business if I do not rapidly get some specific and clear information with regard to a date.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHoward" hpid="Mr. Howard Mr. Howard">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Howard</NameTxt>
      <P>I wish to extend my good wishes to Senator Wright on confirmation of his appointment as Leader of the House and I congratulate Senator Ryan on his appointment as Chief Whip.  I am sure he will have all the enjoyment and satisfaction that office offers.  Senator Fitzgerald is an experienced man in his job and I wish him success also.</P>
      <P>I want to raise the following points with the Leader of the House.  In relation to the Culliton report, I understood the Leader to indicate that time would be provided for a debate on the report.  An indication was given some weeks ago, as far as I understand it.  It is necessary to have such a debate particularly in view of the emphasis that is, rightly, being put on unemployment.  It is important that this House would have an early opportunity to debate the report.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I had intended raising the matter of a discussion on the role of the banks and financial institutions.  I am glad to say Senator O'Keeffe has come back on this subject.  I had a feeling he had gone silent on the issue and I welcome his return to the matter.  I support his call, because I think it is of very limited value to deal with the Culliton report, jobs or whatever, unless there is a critical examination of the role of the financial institutions and the banks.  It is important that a debate on the banks is not subsumed in a discussion on the Culliton report.  The performance of the financial institutions and what we require from them at this stage deserves to be examined on its own. Therefore, I request the Leader of the <Col N="831" /> House to provide as soon as possible time for a debate on the role of financial institutions and a separate time for the Culliton report.</P>
    <Speaker pid="TomRaftery" hpid="Professor Raftery Professor Raftery">
      <NameTxt>Professor Raftery</NameTxt>
      <P>Some time before Christmas I asked for a debate on unemployment. The Leader kindly agreed and the House agreed to have a debate on it. Much time has passed since then.  Unemployment has got worse.  I ask the new Leader of the House for such a debate.  I think we could couple that with the debate on the Culliton report on industrial policy and I ask the Leader to consider giving time at an early date for a discussion on these two very important topics.</P>
      <P>The second point I want to make is the one that has been so eloquently made by Senator Howard already.  We need an early debate on the banking system.  We need a debate on the provision of credit, on money for start-up industry, which seems to be very slow in coming from banks.  They are like a person who would give you an umbrella on a fine day but they want it back on a wet day.  We have a chance of discussing it now that Senator O'Keeffe has reintroduced the subject and I urge the Leader to arrange for this debate as early as possible.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LiamTCosgrave" hpid="Mr. Cosgrave Mr. Cosgrave">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cosgrave</NameTxt>
      <P>I wish my former opposite number every success in his new post.  I thank him for the co-operation he gave me and Members on this side.  I also wish Senators Ryan and Fitzgerald every good fortune and success in their posts. I would say to the Members opposite: respect your Whips and they will treat you fairly.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PolOFoighil" hpid="Pól Ó Foighil Pól Ó Foighil">
      <NameTxt>Pól Ó Foighil</NameTxt>
      <P>Ba mhaith liom comhghairdeas a déanamh leis an dtriúr sna poist nua atá acu.  Ba mhaith liom a fhiafraí den Cheannaire cé comh luath is a bheidh díospóireacht againn ar an Culliton report mar tá sé fíor-thábhachtach do iarthar na hÉireann go speisialta, marmá chuirtear cuid de na moltaí atá sa Culliton report i ngníomh beidh an t-iarthar bánaithe. Tá sé sách bánaithe mar atá sé ach <Col N="832" /> beidh sé imithe go hiomlán má chuirtear an tuarascáil sin i gcrích.</P>
      <P>Arís fiafraím den Cheannaire cén t-am a chuirfear na Billí éagsúla a thagann os comhair an Tí seo ar fáil i nGaeilge agus i mBéarla de réir mar atá riachtanach faoin mBunreacht.  Tuigim gur socraíodh anseo cúpla bliain ó shin go gcuirfí gluais ag deireadh na mBillí, is é sin go mbeadh cuid den fhoclaíocht le fáil i nGaeilge, ach níl an méid sin déanta tar éis dhá bhliain.  Ní féidir liom leanúint ag plé le Billí nach dtuigim go hiomlán ó thaobh tearmaíochta de. Tá mé ag iarraidh, dá bhrí sin, go ndéanfar é nó, mar dúirt mé cheana, caithfidh mé rud éigin a dhéanamh faoi taobh amuigh den Teach seo.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BrendanRyan" hpid="Mr. B. Ryan Mr. B. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. B. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>Maraon le gach éinne eile, déanaim comhghairdeas leis an triúr faoi na jobanna nua atá acu.  Tá súil agam nach gcuirfimid ar an taobh seo go romhór isteach orthu san obair a bheidh ar siúl acu.</P>
      <P>I want a debate on what we do to 300,000 unemployed people.  Every day I, and I suspect everybody else meet cases of blatant persecution of the unemployed by the Department of Social Welfare. Women of 30 years of age are being asked in Dublin why they are not living with their parents down the country and their right to the dole is questioned.  There are people having their means test based on their parents' income when the parents live 60 miles away.  The list is endless. I know what you are going to say, a Chathaoirligh, that I may not make a speech but, since my please fall on deaf ears I simply want to illustrate what is involved.  I propose to speak on it on the Appropriation motion as will be appropriate, but I would like the rest of this House to have an opportunity to speak also.  We talked about the unemployed about a year and a half ago.  Members of this House spoke eloquently in the debate but it was ignored outside this House because apparently the unemployed are not news.  I would like us to try yet again to make the unemployed newsworthy.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Like all of my colleagues, I think it is <Col N="833" /> high time we debated the banking institutions in this House.  It is a singular lack in the Culliton report that the banks or their role is barely mentioned.  I am beginning to worry that, as we demolish sacred cows, we are liable to recycle them in new forms.  I have a funny feeling that the Culliton report is becoming a substitute gospel of all that is right.  It deserves the same critical scrutiny as all other sources.  My own view is that it is severely defective in many areas and is ideologically loaded.  I would like a chance to discuss the banks, their ineptitude, inefficiency and their persecution of small businesses in particular.  I hope we have that debate soon.</P>
    <Speaker pid="RichardHourigan" hpid="Mr. Hourigan Mr. Hourigan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hourigan</NameTxt>
      <P>I, too, would like to congratulate Senator Wright on his promotion as Leader of the House.  I wish him well and assure him of our co-operation. I would also like to congratulate Senator Ryan on his promotion as Chief Whip and Senator Fitzgerald on his continued role as Assistant Whip.</P>
      <P>I would like to ask the Leader when we can expect a meaningful debate on Northern Ireland.  Unemployment has been discussed here previously.  It is a matter of urgency and I would like to have an early debate on the topic.</P>
      <P>The entire situation relative to the banks needs to be examined urgently and thoroughly.  Apart from money availability and interest rates there are new dimensions in banks and lending institutions today.  People may not be aware of handing charges of one sort or another. Many charges have been neatly and discreetly introduced by banks, for which they stand condemned.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanDoherty" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator, you are making a speech.  I would prefer if you would ask a question.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardHourigan" hpid="Mr. Hourigan Mr. Hourigan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hourigan</NameTxt>
      <P>Finally, I would like to ask the Leader if the very important visit of the Taoiseach to the House may be expected soon.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="834" />
    <Speaker pid="DanielKiely" hpid="Mr. D. Kiely Mr. D. Kiely">
      <NameTxt>Mr. D. Kiely</NameTxt>
      <P>I would like to congratulate Senator Wright on his promotion to the role of Leader of the House.  He has impressed all sides of the House in his capacity as Acting Leader. I also wish good luck to Senators Ryan and Fitzgerald in their posts.</P>
      <P>I agree with many of the speakers here today about the Culliton report.  It should not be taken as the gospel of this country for the future.  There is real need for an open debate on the report, particularly on the proposal to introduce regional councils and on their formation.</P>
      <P>I would also like to ask the Leader of the House about the formation of a foreign affairs committee.  This has been mentioned frequently.  I ask him now to use his good offices and to call on the Taoiseach to ensure that Members of the Seanad will be involved in that committee if it is to be set up.  It is all the more necessary now, as there are large numbers of homeless Irish people in England. The committee should be set up forthwith.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GVWright" hpid="Mr. Wright Mr. Wright">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Wright</NameTxt>
      <P>I would like to thank all those on the Opposition side of the House&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeOToole" hpid="Mr. O'Toole Mr. O'Toole">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Toole</NameTxt>
      <P>&mdash;&mdash;and the Independents who are not necessarily the Opposition.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GVWright" hpid="Mr. Wright Mr. Wright">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Wright</NameTxt>
      <P>&mdash; those the far side of the House and my own colleagues on my own behalf and on behalf of Senator Ryan and Senator Fitzgerald.  It is indeed an honour and privilege to have been appointed Leader of this House and I would like to thank the Taoiseach and my colleagues for their support.  As Whip and Chief Whip I was committed to the efficient running of the House and I hope that will continue while I am Leader.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>That brings us to the matter of reforms, to which I am committed.  I hope some of the reforms we have mentioned at the Committee on Procedure and Privileges will be part and parcel of the Seanad operations before the end of March.  That would be in the interests of the House. On a personal note, to coin a phrase of <Col N="835" /> the new Taoiseach, I would like to assure everyone that I will give it my best shot.</P>
    <P>Senator Manning mentioned reform.  I have already stated that we hope to see that take place shortly.  We hope to have an opportunity in March to debate the issue of broadcasting.  I am committed to a debate on the banks also.  The type of issue raised on the far side of the floor and by my colleague, Senator O'Keeffe, and others, needs to be debated here.</P>
    <P>With regard to the Green Paper on Education, I will certainly pass the Senators' comments to the relevant sources.  Item 3 will be taken next week subject to the Whips.  On the matter of child care, I would like to assure Senator O'Reilly that I will convey his comments to the Minister in question.</P>
    <P>Several Senators today expressed good wishes to the Taoiseach and the Ministers for Foreign Affairs and Justice in their meeting today with Prime Minister Major.  I am sure everyone in the country hopes that out of this meeting a start will be made to arrive at some solution that would alleviate the tragic circumstances people have to live with in the North of Ireland.</P>
    <P>On the White Paper, I assure Senators that, in most speeches made by the Taoiseach and the Minister for Justice, there is an absolute commitment to an early discussion of the White Paper.  I cannot be more specific but I hope in time I will be able to come back on that.  Senator Ó Foighil, mentioned a matter more appropriate to the Committee on Procedure and Privileges.  I will have a chat about that.</P>
    <P>Jobs, unemployment and the Culliton report were mentioned.  In view of the debate initiated by Fine Gael and the Minister last night, it may well be that we should discuss job creation.  If the Government are coming forward with the concept of a job forum and so on, it may well be that this House should contribute to the debate.  I would like to see it as a positive debate, perhaps with Members giving their ideas as to how we would create jobs, not just looking back on where the problems may have originated. <Col N="836" /> It may well be, subject to the Whips, that we would agree in the next few weeks to have such a debate, in which the ideas and wisdom of this House would be available to the Government.</P>
    <Speaker pid="SeanDoherty" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Is the Order of Business agreed?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeCostelloLAB" hpid="Mr. Costello Mr. Costello">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Costello</NameTxt>
      <P>The Leader of the House has not replied&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanDoherty" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I am sorry, Senator Costello, the Leader has replied.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeCostelloLAB" hpid="Mr. Costello Mr. Costello">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Costello</NameTxt>
      <P>Not to all the items.</P>
      <P>Order of Business agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Appropriation Act, 1991:" RHead="Motion (Resumed)">
    <Title>Appropriation Act, 1991: Motion (Resumed).</Title>
    <P>Debate resumed on the following motion:</P>
    <P>That Seanad Éireann notes the supply services and purposes to which sums have been appropriated in the Appropriation Act, 1991.</P>
    <P Just="Right">&mdash;(Senator Hussey.)</P>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. Farrell Mr. Farrell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Farrell</NameTxt>
      <P>I was speaking on the last occasion on tourism.  We do not give sufficient credit to Bord Fáilte and to the Minister for Tourism for the work they have been doing in that regard.  We seem always to be critical of our situation. Early last year we had nothing but complaints that there would be no tourists, that nobody was doing any business. Nevertheless, it was quite a good tourist season.  Bord Fáilte are doing a good job. We should remember the saying, &ldquo;Let each man learn to know himself, to do that he must labour; and prove those failings in himself which he condemns so in his neighbour&rdquo;.  We are to willing to condemn people.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I am delighted that Sligo, my own area, is part of the Cavan-Monaghan region and I would like to pay tribute to our Regional Officer, Dan O'Neill, and the staff who do a good job for us in the <Col N="837" /> north-west.  I have no doubt we will get good results in that region.  I have often thought, however, that there should be more liaison between the county councils in those regions.  The county council has a major role to play in promoting tourism. Our council has done a great job sign-posting scenic routes and points of interest, but there is not enough liaison between the county councils at official or elected representative level.  It would be a good exercise for the county councils to meet with the regional tourism office and the regional manager once a year to discuss how they could work together to make better use of all the available facilities.</P>
    <P>When we go abroad on holiday, we should try to sell and promote our area. Last year there were not many Americans in Ireland.  I had the honour of representing my county on St. Patrick's Day in New York in 1990, and 1991 was the centenary of the formation of the Sligomen's Association in New York.  I was delighted to be able to invite many people back here to include Sligo in their celebrations.  Last year more than 100 Americans came to Sligo for a week as part of the centenary celebrations.  Many more would have come but for the Gulf crisis, but those who came were very high in their praise of Sligo.  I was in Long Island last July for the final part of the celebrations.  I have no doubt from talking to more than 1,500 people who were there that night that this year a large number of people will be coming to Sligo because those who came last year were so well received.  Some of them had not been back to Sligo since they left 40 years ago.  Such promotion can do a great deal to help tourism.  We should all work in co-operation with Bord Fáilte and our regional tourism office.  Instead of complaining, we should be constructive and get work done.</P>
    <P>I would like to see a change in the agri-tourism grants.  At the moment grants are available for developments other than accommodation.  That is very good.  I am delighted to see that golf is becoming one of our tourist attractions.  As an enthusiastic one-armed golfer and a member of <Col N="838" /> the international one-armed golfer assocation, for many years I have travelled abroad for one meeting a year and I have seen how golf as a tourist attraction is sold in other countries.  I have raised that point at my own council meetings and in many other places.  I am glad that today we are selling golf as a tourist attraction. In Japan there is a driving range three storeys high with 115 bays, and people queue up from early morning to late at night just to beat a bucket of balls into space.  They will never see a golf course but they buy clubs, change clubs, and wash, shower, as if they had just played 18 holes of golf.  Yet, they will never get on a golf course.  That market is there. We are now providing facilities and it is about time.</P>
    <P>We cannot guarantee a sunshine holiday but we have what other countries do not have.  I once said we would have a great country if we had more sun, but someone replied that if we had more sun we would not have that green mountain of Benbulben.  We have beautiful green mountains, but if we had sunshine the green fresh grass would be burned up. We have a great deal to offer &mdash; orienteering, scenic walks, pony trekking etc.  Such activities do not need sunshine but our mild weather is ideal.  That is where we must concentrate our tourism efforts.</P>
    <P>Agri-tourism was designed to help farmers diversify.  A farmer has everything necessary for a farm holiday-maker. He has land where the tourist can wander, he has cattle, sheep, ponies and donkeys, but the accommodation in his house may not be up to standard.  The tourist today wants grade A hotel accommodation at boarding house prices.  If farmers are to do well in tourism they must bring their houses up to a certain standard and have hot and cold water, and even <i>en suite</i> bathrooms.  The farmer who wants to diversify will not get a grant to upgrade his house, unless he spends 60 per cent on other activities, such as a pitch and putt.  That is wrong, because he has the essentials &mdash; his home and family. That is what tourists want to see.  They do not want to go to a cold hotel.  They <Col N="839" /> like to meet people, talk to them and see how farming is carried out in this country. I would like to see money made available under the agri-tourism grant to allow a farmer who decides to go into agri-tourism to improve his house, to add on rooms and to make his farmyard suitable for bringing people in.</P>
    <P>The Hotel Federation spoke yesterday about a problem we have experienced in my area.  There is a new EC directive which will militate against temporary workers.  Many small operators in seaside towns do not think they will open their restaurants this year because they are now required to have a special register. All staff have to be registered and the hours they work, what they are paid, etc. entered.  That is extra bookkeeping.  We have gone mad book-keeping.  We have VAT, PAYE, tax returns, rates, bank, PRSI and so on.  Now there is another register for an official from the Department of Labour who will call three or four times a year.  This inspector can interview staff asking what they are paid, ensuring that they know all their rights and are getting full wages etc.</P>
    <P>In our part of the country, in the seaside towns, the restaurants open around 12 noon and close at 12 midnight.  They have two six-hour shifts and they pay £10 a day &mdash; that was last year's rate, £60 a week &mdash; for school-leavers.  Some of the proprietors got a rude awakening.  They had to pay back money at the end of the year because the minimum wage last year was £90.  If those same employees went to FÁS or AnCO would only get £60 per week while training; they are still only trainees.  For them, it was just a summer, temporary job.  The restaurant owners could not pay these wages together with all the other overheads and still be competitive. Everyone says prices are too high and must be kept down, but employers cannot do the impossible, and this last EC Directive will increase unemployment this year.  I appeal to he Minister to look at this, because there is no way anyone can give more than £10 per hour to temporary employees of 15 <Col N="840" /> or 16 years of age, who have just left school.</P>
    <Speaker pid="BrendanRyan" hpid="Mr. B. Ryan Mr. B. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. B. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>£10 an hour?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. Farrell Mr. Farrell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Farrell</NameTxt>
      <P>Sorry, £10 a day.  I should have said £60 a week.  They are also given their food.  They could of course give them £200 a week, if you had a system whereby it could be added on to the bill and if nobody objected to paying, but in reality the end product would become too expensive.  In Germany they work a 35 hour week but now they are starting to have unemployment.  They cannot sell their products because they are not competitive with the Japanese who work a 45 hour week.  We are competing in an open market where you must give value for money.  It is getting very difficult to do that.  There is no incentive to the employer.  All the laws are on the employee's side.  When I worked with firms there were no unions.  They were badly needed, but it is the other way around now.  In my own town a firm was looking for six people and they had difficulty getting them despite the fact that unemployment is so high.  Last year one person came home from England on a Wednesday and they were working by Thursday.  That person could not believe they could get a job so quickly.</P>
      <P>I spoke about patriotism and love of country last week, and I will finish on the same note.  It was John Fitzgerald Kennedy who said, &ldquo;Ask not what your country can do for you; ask what you can do for your country&rdquo;.  In this country we have paraphrased that and we say: &ldquo;Do not ask what your country can do for you but what can you do your country for.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BrendanRyan" hpid="Mr. B. Ryan Mr. B. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. B. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>First, I wish to record my astonishment that a Member of either House of the Oireachtas would suggest paying somebody £10 a day for any full-time job in 1992.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. Farrell Mr. Farrell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Farrell</NameTxt>
      <P>It is not a full-time job.  If the Senator, who has two secure jobs, was trying to give employment he would speak differently.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="841" />
    <Speaker pid="SeanDoherty" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator Ryan, please, without interruption.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BrendanRyan" hpid="Mr. B. Ryan Mr. B. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. B. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator Ryan stands over his assertion.  I apologise to Senator Farrell, which is more than he ever does when he makes utterly irrelevant remarks about my personal circumstances, if he did not mean full-time.  £10 per day is a peculiar figure.  Perhaps the Senator would tell me if that is for two, four, six or eight hours.  I would be interested in the clarification.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. Farrell Mr. Farrell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Farrell</NameTxt>
      <P>A six hour day.  I did not make it clear.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanDoherty" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator Ryan, without interruption.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BrendanRyan" hpid="Mr. B. Ryan Mr. B. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. B. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>For a six hour day that is £1.66 per hour.  On a quick calculation, if you are talking about a restaurant, wages of £10 a day distributed over 50 or 100 meals works out at around 20 pence per meal.  Even if that was doubled it would not account for the cost of meals. The truth is that the general provision of services in this country is appallingly inefficient, badly thought out, unimaginative, and depending on high prices for small volume rather than reasonable prices for high volume.</P>
      <P>I know, without a shadow of a doubt, that the price of labour, food and property is considerably greater in Germany, for instance, than it is here.  Yet, one can pass through a dozen restaurants on a street in Frankfurt and get food of a quality that would only be available in cordon bleu restaurants here.  It is a fraction of the price you would pay for a crude meal of chicken and chips in many restaurants in Irish holiday resorts.  It is not the price of labour that is the cause of their meals being cheaper than ours. It is well-run services, well-run premises, run by people who are able to meet both their commercial targets and their social obligations.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I am astonished at the suggestion of £10 a day as a wage rate, particularly when one realises that the chances are that the majority of these people would <Col N="842" /> be women.  We are simply further consigning women to a role of something close to servitude in what is supposed to be a working environment.</P>
    <P>The Appropriation Bill is essentially about public expenditure and public expenditure is now a bad thing.  Every single international organisation, in particular the OECD, but also the International Monetary Fund, has its ideologically beady eye on public expenditure. The first thing they tell any country with a problem is that they must reduce public expenditure and, if they are pushed, they will say they must reduce expenditure on health, education, welfare, housing and food subsidies.  They have this extraordinary selectivity so that they target those areas.  They never tell people they must reduce expenditure on armaments or State security but that is an issue for another day.</P>
    <P>I would like to insist that quite the opposite is the truth.  Public expenditure is a good thing.  It has been a major contributor to the quality of life in western Europe.  The quality of housing, education, infrastructure, health care, and low infant mortality all over western Europe, have been possible because of public expenditure.  The United States have failed miserably to provide anything like the same success, having taken the preferred route of most of our ideological advisers about public expenditure.</P>
    <P>Public expenditure is a good thing. Public expenditure via moderately high taxes is a good thing, it works well and does not stifle enterprise.  There is no empirical evidence to suggest that relatively high levels of taxation stifle enterprise. There is a sense of grievance among some people who are relatively successful who believe they are paying too much tax.  They express this as a detached objective feeling that it is deterring other people from enterprise, but I do not believe, and I know that there is no empirical evidence to suggest, that high levels of public expenditure deter enterprise.  If high levels of public expenditure deterred enterprise, then the Swedish, Danish and Norwegian economies would have been going down the <Col N="843" /> tubes for the past 20 years, because it is about 20 years since public expenditure, as a proportion of GNP, in Sweden and Denmark passed out the level we are at today.  If the ideological insistence on reducing public expenditure was based on any empirical evidence, those two countries would have been in terminal decline for the past 20 years.  They manifestly are not, they are successful thriving economies working extremely well.</P>
    <P>The idea that public expenditure is a bad thing is one of those things that is now almost accepted almost without question. The usual line in any newspaper editorial, in any passing commentary, even by people in RTE who are not supposed to editorialise, is that Governments must reduce public expenditure, in order to reduce taxes, in order to encourage job creation.  No evidence has been provided by anybody to suggest that those three connections operate.  The famous &mdash; I would suggest, notorious &mdash; Culliton report in its introduction makes that equation without a scrap of empirical evidence to sustain it.  I believe the proper way to develop an economy, to develop a country, is to have efficient levels of public services of a quality that makes a decent contribution to people's lives. There is no point in putting together public services that are so bad that people do not want to use them and we are liable to do that if we allow ourselves to be bounced into this daft notion that public expenditure is anything other than a good thing.</P>
    <P>I believe in public expenditure and the other Members of both Houses of the Oireachtas when they bother to think about it also believe in it because they want good health care, good housing and good education and they know the only way to achieve these is by collective State provision.  Nobody has found another effective way of doing it.</P>
    <P>This Appropriation Act contains a considerable number of items that merit discussion. I did a quick sum and discovered that the total provision for State security is 28 times higher than the provision for Overseas Development Aid.  Last year <Col N="844" /> we spent £316 million on the Garda; £317 million on the Armed Forces and £82 million on the Prison Service, a total of £715 million.  In the same period we spent £25 million on Overseas Development Aid and that figure was boosted by a politically tainted contribution to what were described as the victims of the Gulf War, which did not include the innocent citizens of Iraq.  The contribution was made to external countries who as good boys took the western line and were compensated ultimately by a fund.  That obscene contribution was inserted in the figure for overall contribution to Overseas Development Aid and used to prove how well we contributed last year.</P>
    <P>This year that sum has been taken out; the claim is that it does not represent a reduction because it was a once off provision.  What is particularly shameful about the level of State expenditure on ODA is that while the Government is the stingiest perhaps of OECD Governments in terms of percentage of GNP contributed to people who are poor in a way we cannot imagine, voluntary donations from Irish people are the most generous in the OECD as a percentage of GNP. That trend has persisted through the eighties in spite of recessions, unemployment, hardship and what some people describe as high tax.  Irish people are generous and are betrayed by a Government using a soft target and an easy option to reduce public expenditure.</P>
    <P>The phrase &ldquo;bankrupt country cannot afford to give aid to anybody&rdquo; which surfaced during the famous star chamber investigations of the late eighties into public expenditure was made by an eminent economist who presided over an analysis of all Departments' expenditure. It is a shameful record and a betrayal of the Irish people's own spontaneous generosity.  It ought to be remedied and if the Government want a suggestion I suggest that we cross off £50 million of our defence expenditure.  Much of the defence budget is spent on items like the FCA which serves no other purpose than to give people the opportunity to spend a few weeks playing at being toy soldiers. We could do without this and could spend <Col N="845" /> the money saved on Overseas Development Aid and to encourage increasing numbers of our under-utilised workforce to spend a period working in development aid.  This will not happen because the idealogues who run both our thought processes and our governments do not approve of public expenditure and want to reduce it everywhere except in the areas of defence where they always blink and pretend not to notice.  This has happened in most major European countries. Those who thought that public expenditure should be reduced in Britain blinked as their defence budget remained as it had been when Britain had a colonial empire, spending four times proportionately as much as France on so called defence.  We are doing that here now.</P>
    <P>Public expenditure can be made more efficient by openness, by accountability and the office that can do that most efficiently is the Ombudsman.  It is a scandalous under-funding to leave only a fraction of a million pounds to the Office of Ombudsman.  I know this amount is bigger than it use to be, but it leaves the Ombudsman based largely in Dublin with two-thirds of the country at a remove and therefore at a disadvantage.  It could be different; the lack of will to change it deserves further comment.</P>
    <P>I do not want to go through a catalogue of areas of expenditure but to dwell on one area, expenditure on social welfare. For reasons beyond my comprehension what the Department of Social Welfare do to unemployed people is a matter of absolute indifference to the liberal establishment in this country.  It gives travellers the Star of David treatment every Thursday morning at a fixed time in every labour exchange.  One can count the travellers in a town by going to the labour exchange at 11.30 on a Thursday morning because that is when they have to be there.  If we did this to any other group there would be outrage but the liberal establishment apparently blinks at this because these people are travellers and unemployed.  That is not the end of what the Department of Social Welfare do to unemployed people.  They give them an <Col N="846" /> income which is barely adequate; they then attach conditions to that income that would do justice to the most bizarre and Byzantine complications of Franz Kafka's <i>The Trial</i>, they tell people that in order to be eligible for money they must be available for work and actively seeking employment.</P>
    <P>This is the interesting testimony of people in various parts of the country. One signs on at the labour exchange and if one is single the first question asked is why one is not living at home.  I know of a 30 year old single woman who worked for years in England.  She came back to Dublin, her family lived down the country and the first question she was asked in the labour exchange was why she was not living with her parents.  Her parents lived 60 miles away.  It was grossly humilitating to suggest to an adult woman that she make herself a dependant again.</P>
    <P>The next trick is to check one's address.  If the person is not there when they arrive they regret that they have to postpone payment for another week because they could not confirm the address.  If the person is there they will imply that she/he is not looking for work. &ldquo;If you were looking for work you would be out looking for it; what are you doing hanging around at home all day?&rdquo; If one is not available regularly when they come they will suggest that you are not available for work but are doing something else and, therefore, are &ldquo;fiddling&rdquo;.  This practice does not take place on an occasional basis; it happens on a cyclical basis to people who have been unemployed in some cases for one, two or three years.  I have a letter in my files from a 52 year old man who worked for 37 years continuously through recessions and good periods; He was made redundant at 52 which most would acknowledge as a difficult age at which to find new employment.  Within three months of signing on at the labour exchange he was told he was being cut off because he had not made sufficient efforts to look for work.</P>
    <P>That pattern repeats itself in every Irish labour exchange and nobody gives a tuppenny damn.  It is never written <Col N="847" /> about or commented upon; there are no eloquent features about it.  We get the occasional series of articles, usually during the &ldquo;silly season&rdquo; in August about what it is like to be unemployed.  For most of the people most of the time this persecution is invisible; it demands that people be actively seeking employment, genuinely looking for work.  I can genuinely look for anything that exists but I cannot look for something that does not exist.  I do not know where to look for it, where to find it and I do not know how I am supposed to prove that I am looking for it if I do not know where it is.  Work in this country does not exist except as Senator Farrell said at £50 a week slave labour in a restaurant.  I do not think any other Member of this House believes in that sort of thing.  For the rest work is unavailable, work does not exist; yet, the Department of Social Welfare insist that every person on the dole should look for work.</P>
    <P>Let me tell you about that Department's tricks.  It will not allow a person produce letters to box numbers in the paper as evidence of work sought.  If one producers a copy of the <i>Evening Press</i> and proves one sent letters to box numbers given in job advertisements, the Department of Social Welfare would say that was not good enough, one was not really looking for work.  Box numbers do not suffice.  One is expected to plead on bended knee with employers to obtain a letter confirming that one applied to the employer for work and that work was not available.</P>
    <P>The Department of Social Welfare had no right to humiliate people.  Conditions laid down to regulate eligibility for social welfare when work was available are now being used to effect perhaps the most rigid social control that exists outside what used to be eastern Europe.  Some 250,000 people who are perceived to be a possible threat to the State are treated to what on the surface is meant to be a system of benevolent care but which demands personal humiliation and subjugation in exchange for the State pittance. Labour exchanges around the <Col N="848" /> country do not do this all the time but a cyclical pattern has been created.  People working with the unemployed allude to this maltreatment regularly.</P>
    <P>When one raises this matter with a Government Minister one is told the staff have clear guidelines on it which sounds very good.  Yet, when one asks if unemployed people may have a copy of the guidelines to know what conditions they have to meet, one is told the guidelines are confidential.  We have a situation where 250,000 people are told they must satisfy the Department of Social Welfare that they are looking for work.  How do they do that?  The Department cannot tell them it is up to them to find out.  How do they prove they are seeking work? The Department will say; it is up to them to prove it.  What is proof?  The Department will not say.  What is a lack of effort? Again, the Department will not say. Every so often when pushed the Department suggest that people try the next town, or the next parish.  Half the time they say one should have more letters from more employers.</P>
    <P>Social welfare recipients in West Cork live in such a remote area that there would not be any reasonable expectation of finding work there and the Department of Social Welfare disqualify people on the grounds that work is unavailable in this area.  I interpret that as a directive to leave the area and move to the cities where one can go through the pretence of work being available.</P>
    <P>Such treatment of the unemployed is the most systematised, cruel and most invisible persecution of a minority in any civilised western European country today.  Nobody gives two pence about it, in politics, media or anywhere else, with the glorious exception of some of the Churches and their agencies who have seen what is being done to unemployed people.  The abuse experienced by unemployed people does not impinge on and is not part of the experience of any of us in jobs, we do not have to go through this process, therefore, it is not on our list of social concerns.</P>
    <P>This condition of one's availability for work is used to discriminate particularly <Col N="849" /> against women.  The number of women I have met who have been asked who will mind the children if they go to work, is endless.  The number of men I know who have been asked a similar question, unless they are a single parent, is zero. This condition is used consistently all around the country to persecute women.</P>
    <P>The Department of Social Welfare play glorious tricks on women.  They tell them to do a FÁS scheme where they will be paid £40 or £50 a week, about the same as the dole.  When a woman says she will have to pay somebody to mind her children and, therefore, cannot do it for that money they decide she is not available for work.  Of course she would be available for work if the work paid a decent wage which would enable her to pay somebody to mind the children.  She is then cut off the dole, one more victory, one numberless, another attempt to keep the unemployment figures from being seen as the obscene spectacle they are.</P>
    <P>Again, the Minister will say clear directions are given to officials not to discriminate against women but those directions or guidelines remain confidential, a matter for internal report. Women are left with an assurance from a male Minister that the officials of his Department who, at senior levels given the structure of the Civil Service are predominantly male, are not prejudiced against them in principle even though they know the question of who will mind the children will be pursued vigorously. If they attempt to suggest that a sister, who is perhaps a single mother or is unemployed herself or on deserted wife's allowance might mind the children then the Department of Social Welfare will descend on the sister and say, &ldquo;We understand you will be paid by your sister.  Are you really available for work yourself?&rdquo; The sister will get the treatment.  In the west of Ireland this issue was second only to the rod licence controversy during the last general election.</P>
    <P>Bhí eolas agam ar cheist na &ldquo;gaugers&rdquo; i gConamara le linn an toghcháin deiridh agus ba mhór an cheist í in iarthar na tíre.</P>
    <P>Stories abound about the famous Department of Social Welfare outdoor <Col N="850" /> investigation branch, as my colleague Deputy Stagg outlined in the Dáil before Christmas.  Officials inspected people's fingernails for dirt to ascertain if they had been working that day.  They inspected the soles of their shoes for mud.  They actually rubbed their hands to see if they were horny from work.  A woman in the midlands was asked by an official where she got a fur coat.  If she was genuinely unemployed the implication was that she should not be able to afford a fur coat. Others were asked how they could arrive in a car if they were unemployed?  I have documented hundreds of these cases which occur all over the country.  It is time this abuse ended.  If this country cannot supply work for people, could it not at least leave them their dignity?  That matter should be addressed by anybody who cares about minority rights.</P>
    <P>These measures affect 270,000 people directly and their spouses and children indirectly.  It is as good a way of breaking people's spirits as any I could imagine; it is systematic, widespread, consistent and cruel.  The situation is not alleviated by smart ass comentators writing trivia in the media about welfare abuse.  A major international consultancy firm, Craig Gardner conducted a study and found that not more than 1.5 per cent of welfare expenditure in Dublin city could be suspected of being misappropriated.  The corollary to this finding is that 98.5 per cent of welfare expenditure is deemed appropriate.  It is manifestly wrong to persecute 98.5 per cent of welfare recipients in order, allegedly, to catch the 1.5 per cent guilty of abuse.</P>
    <P>On the same issue, I denounce the scam underlying the alleged generous expenditure on social welfare in Ireland. The taxpayers' element of social welfare expenditure has barely increased in real terms since 1987 and dropped in absolute terms for a couple of years.  The social welfare budget has been augmented; payments have been extended to the self-employed while at the same time, eligibility for pay-related benefits has been reduced by increasing the number of contributions necessary before payment begins.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="851" /> Pay-related benefit has been reduced in value.  The social insurance fund has gone from deficit to surplus.  The State contribution needed to top up the social insurance fund has been dramatically reduced so that the actual net contribution of taxpayers to the alleviation of poverty has gone down in real terms in spite of the upsurge in unemployment, and despite the small but welcome increase in payment rates.  What the State has done is to make self-employed people, many of them poor themselves, carry the can for the general taxpayer, many of whom are quite well off.</P>
    <P>The central issue is something like this. Without addressing each item in turn I assert that public expenditure is a good thing.  If we did not have the ingrained hostility to public expenditure that now dominates most economic and political thinking we would not need to witness the persecution of 250,000 unemployed people nor the hostility shown by many commentators to the public sector <i>per se</i> in outrageous remarks about public sector pay.  Opposition to public spending means that inefficiencies are highlighted while good quality service is not commented on.  We would not suffer any of these consequences if we had the sort of perspective on public expenditure that an intelligent rational forward-looking western European democracy ought to have. Our problem is that we are dominated by people who, for biased and ideologically based motives, pretend to us that public expenditure is inherently inefficient, that it inhibits enterprise and somehow puts pressure on ordinary people.</P>
    <P>Public expenditure is our security; it protects us all.  It provides education for our children and national health care because VHI costs for those of us privileged to be in it, would be more expensive were it not subsidised by public expenditure. Public expenditure is the bedrock of a civilised society.  Those societies that do not have a decent level of public expenditure, i.e. in the region of 40 per cent of gross national product, are not only short-sighted but fundamentally uncivilised.</P>
    <Col N="852" />
    <Speaker pid="EamonOCuiv" hpid="Éamon Ó Cuív Éamon Ó Cuív">
      <NameTxt>Éamon Ó Cuív</NameTxt>
      <P>Ba mháith liom fáilte a chur roimh an Aire Stáit go dtí an Teach agus ceapaim gurb í seo an chéad uair dó ann ó athtoghadh mar Aire é.  Fáiltím roimhe chuig an díospóireacht seo ar na cuntais, an bundíospóireacht is tábhachtaí gach bliain.  Is ann a phléitear caiteachas uilig an Stáit.  I mbliana tá £7,000 milliún i gceist, suim mhór airgid.  Caithfimid ceisteanna a chur ar an chaoi a bhfuil an t-airgead seo á chaitheamh.</P>
      <P>The Appropriation debate is one of the most fundamental debates held in this house every year; in it we discuss the overall financing of the State.  I do not intend getting into a detailed debate on tax or social welfare policy because they are more appropriate to the Finance Bill and to the Social Welfare Bill.  Since the previous speaker referred in some detail to the question of social welfare, any of us with a Christian conscience has to acknowledge the importance of expenditure on social welfare.  The improvement in the delivery of services to social welfare recipients since 1987 has been fantastic and recipients recognise that the system treats them much more favourably now than it did and that their right to information, access to payment and the quality of the service regarding offices, etc., has been radically improved.</P>
      <P>As somebody who lives and works much of my time with people in receipt of various forms of social welfare, I know that progress has been substantial although there is a lot yet to be done in that particular sphere to improve the delivery of services, particularly to those in receipt of social welfare payments.  I hope we will address that matter in more detail on the social welfare debate.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>When I talk about expenditure and its effects on the community at large, I will refer to the interaction between social welfare and employment/unemployment and our fundamental policies thereon. Before that I would like to comment on the general level of expenditure.  I did a very short exercise &mdash; unfortunately we do not have the resources to do the kind of research I would like &mdash; on the level of expenditure and tried to sort out for myself, the myths from the reality, the <Col N="853" /> myths of the perennial cutback from the reality of the figures allowing for inflation forever going up.  The figures are interesting.  I took the Estimate of expenditure for 1985 and the Estimate of expenditure for 1992 and compared them with the consumer price index.  What I found was startling to say the least.  In that period, according to my figures, inflation was at 22.3 per cent and Government expenditure overall went up by 22.6 per cent.  Current expenditure went up by the rate of inflation, 22.3 per cent, and capital expenditure rose by slightly in excess of inflation, by 24.4 per cent.  In other words, in real terms we are going to spend as much in 1992 as we did in 1985.  When you add on to that &mdash; since net appropriations-in-aid from Europe are not included &mdash; the extra money we are told is coming from Europe, we have to start moving from the simplistic to a more detailed analysis of why we are not able to provide better services for our people and where the real problems are.</P>
    <P>I did one further exercise.  I compared health expenditure in 1985 to the Health Estimate for 1992; we are again talking about a period when inflation stood at 22.3 per cent.  I found out, if my figures are correct &mdash; and I am so startled that I am subject to correction here and stress that I do not have the resources of time to do all the research I would like to &mdash; that there was something like a 50 per cent increase in health expenditure in that period.  Without getting hung up on small figures, the increase in health expenditure in cash terms has far exceeded the rate of inflation.  That is not true when we come to expenditure on the environment.  There have been real cutbacks in environment spending and the people of Connemara can testify to that given the condition of their roads. There has only been a 6.72 per cent increase in environment expenditure since 1985 while the inflation rate has been 22 per cent.</P>
    <P>It is easy for people to talk about more cash without grasping the awkward nettle that we have to look sooner or later at how money is spent.  This is not a time to write volume after volume but to conduct <Col N="854" /> simple comparative studies to find out why in certain cases our services have not improved and in other cases have regressed when the total amount of expenditure in real terms is at least staying stable.</P>
    <P>I address myself to the question of health care because it would seem that there are very fundamental questions now to be answered if our health expenditure continues to rise as it is at present and if, at the same time, old people cannot get geriatric beds, except 60 and 80 miles from their place of residence. This causes grave hardship for relations and families visiting them and also takes the elderly out of their own environment and communities.  The agencies are playing a game of I blame you and you blame me.  This has been going on for a long time.  We must have the will to tackle waste and ensure that all our efforts are directed towards providing the most efficient service on the ground.</P>
    <P>Those who have experience of headage grant payments to farmers know what I am talking about.  The lack of investment in computerisation and in the provision of an efficient service is not only causing farmers great frustration but is adding significantly to administrative costs. Carrying out large volumes of administrative work manually is totally unsatisfactory because it neither provides the service nor is efficient or cost effective.</P>
    <P>I often look at the services we provide and try to analyse why we do not get a better service at times.  I often feel we are reluctant to admit that there are problems in the way a service is provided.  We are reluctant to accept change and, in particular, new technological ways of providing better services.  I have maintained that far from doing away with employment, technology properly applied makes for a better service with a wider scope for the same cost.</P>
    <P>We must look at how State expenditure has been increased by the increasing number of regulations coming not only from this Parliament but from Europe. Every time a proposal is put before us to set up a new agency I ask myself how much will this cost.  Are we talking about <Col N="855" /> £50 million?  What will it cost to provide a headquarters, and all the paraphernalia involved in establishing an agency?  How much do we add to the cost of running this State, each year?</P>
    <P>One thing I have found out about agencies is that though they might suffer a metamorphosis at times they are very rarely done away with.  They seem to take on a life of their own and have an ability to increase their role and size, duplicating and overlapping services that already exist.  This is a sensitive subject because obviously the people who work in these agencies feel &mdash; and they are probably right &mdash; they work very hard.  I do not dispute that.  However, as Members of the Oireachtas, we must take the overall view and see to it that we provide an efficient and cost effective service for our people.</P>
    <P>I know there is demand on the ground for basic services, such as, the provision of hospital beds, basic education, houses, roads, jobs and social welfare but at the end of the day, we run the country for the people and we must take cognisance of their priorities.  We must ensure that with whatever resources we have &mdash; we will never have enough to do all we want &mdash; priority is given to the basics.  At present, that cannot be said to be true.</P>
    <P>We must review and evaluate all our services, agencies and regulations.  We must put a stop to duplication and to the process where decisions that could be taken at regional level must even in small matters, be referred to Dublin or the central Government Department, wherever they might be located.  We have a perfect example of this in the operation of the new house grant.  This could and should be handled by the local authority. Instead, people who apply to the county council for housing loans must go through the same rigmarole with the Department of the Environment in order to receive a grant of £2,000.  We are saying we cannot trust county councils to pay out a grant of £2,000, whereas we allow them, quite rightly, to be involved in much greater expenditure.  Health boards are also involved in housing; they were part of a <Col N="856" /> task force operation but have become another agency involved in housing.  In Gaeltacht areas somebody who wanted to carry out minor house improvements could end up applying under four schemes to three agencies.  That should be examined to see where major savings could be made and, at the same time, provide more efficient, streamlined service to the public at large.</P>
    <P>Thagair an cainteoir romham do cheist na dífhostaíochta agus leasa shóisialaigh agus, mar a dúirt mé, níl sé beartaithe agam dul isteach go míon sa scéal.  Ach ba mhaith liom an t-ábhar sin go ginearálta a cheangal le ceist traenála, ceist dhearceadh ar airgead agus ceist na fostaíochta.</P>
    <P>The biggest problem facing us at the moment is unemployment and presumably in the next few weeks, there will be a major debate on the matter.  I hope this will be a broad debate because down the years there has been a certain amount of blinkered thinking regarding employment that has annoyed me.  There is a concept that either a job is viable or it is done away with.  Let us look at this from the State's point of view.  Somebody with a salary of £10,000 or £12,000 a year will contribute £3,000 a year to the State, through PAYE and PRSI.</P>
    <P>If that person were put on the dole, the net cost to the State between the payment of social welfare and all the benefits that go with it would be at least £6,000 a year and if we take into account the fact that they probably will be forced to seek help from the local authority for house repairs, etc., the cost could be much higher.  The cost to the State of this person being unemployed could be £9,000 per annum or more, and that is for a relatively low paid worker.  I do not understand why this has not been examined before now.  If we could cut the cost to the State to £4,500 by maintaining the job, not only would we save a lot of money but all the personal, community and national consequences that arise from unemployment would be avoided. How such a mechanism would work is not for this forum today, but we must open our minds and not accept as dogma things that were laid down for us years <Col N="857" /> ago.  If we do not, we will never begin to solve the problems that face us at the moment.</P>
    <P>I know from experience as a development worker that ideas were put to me which I resisted because of their radical nature.  When I freed my mind of my prejudices and preconceived notions and looked at them on merit, often I could see a lot of good in them.  There is no reason that, with an open mind, we cannot create employment for most of the people who are looking for it.  I do not accept that it is impossible to create employment but tinkering with the system as we are at present, providing more training, etc, will not resolve the problem.  It is not enough to see what is happening abroad because many similar economies are beginning to face the problem of increasing unemployment.</P>
    <P>We should play a leading role, stand back from preconceived notions and ways we have of doing things, and look at everything in a global fashion.  We should assess every possibility and come up with innovative ways of looking at the whole concept of employment.</P>
    <P>There are many services that could be done usefully and profitably which will not be totally self-sustaining but which would provide a service on one hand and, on the other, would be cheaper than having people drawing social welfare.  I would call these jobs semi-viable because we tend to say a thing is black or white but most things fall into a grey area. Of course my suggestion would involve checks and controls to make sure the system was not abused, but I have no doubt that could be done.</P>
    <P>One of the concepts I am very interested in is the community or private sector matching a contribution from the State to provide services or manufacturing industry &mdash; fishing, farming or whatever.  In that regard it is particularly appropriate to look at the small farmer because here is somebody who has work to do but whose income is not sufficient to enable him to provide for his family. We have tackled that problem in latter years by working out what he would have if he had no farm, subtracting the farm <Col N="858" /> income and giving him the difference. The effect was to put the person in a poverty trap out of which he could not escape.  It would have been much better to say that person has employment but he does not have a viable income.  The challenge is to devise a system which will allow him the right to develop and subsidise him to ensure that he has a proper income.  Rather than penalising him for going ahead, we should encourage him and be glad when he makes a success of his enterprise.</P>
    <P>Tá áthas orm go bhfuil éirithe leis an Rialtas trí chéile breis airgid a chur ar fáil do 1992 thar an bhliain seo caite.  Tá ardú suntasach sna Meastacháin do 1992.  Tá faitíos orm, áfach, i ngeall ar na harduithe pá atá i gceist ann agus, chomh maith leis sin, de bharr nach bhfuil, dar liomsa, dóthain athruithe agus breis éifeachta curtha leis na seírbhísí, nach bhfeicfidh an pobal a bhfuilimid ag freastal orthu mórán feabhais ar na seirbhísí atá á soláthar ag an Stát i mbliana.  Bheadh súil agam anois go mbreathnóidh an Rialtas nua ar an bhfadhb seo as an nua agus go ndéanfaidh siad gach iarracht féachaint chuige go gcuirfear, mar is féidir a chur, leis na seirbhísí atá á gcur ar fáil don phobal, go ndéanfar cinnte de go bhfuil an tseirbhís sin curtha ar fáil go héifeachtach agus go ndíreoimid ár n-intinn i gcónaí ar chearta na ndaoine go bhfuil na seirbhísí á gcur ar fáil ar a son lena chinntiú gurb iad siúd, is é sin gnáthphobal na hÉireann, a bhainfidh tairbhe as an £7,000 milliún atá á chaitheamh ag an Stát seo chuile bhliain.</P>
    <Speaker pid="RichardHourigan" hpid="Mr. Hourigan Mr. Hourigan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hourigan</NameTxt>
      <P>I welcome the Minister of State at the Department of Finance, Deputy Treacy, to the House and congratulate him on his recent appointment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I would like to review what has happened in the past 12 months which is the normal way to examine the Appropriation Act.  One very striking, and regrettable point is that we had many scandals towards the end of 1991 which impinged on Government activity.  I do not suggest that any Government members were involved but the scandals affected adversely the Government of <Col N="859" /> this country.  That is regrettable but I hope we have seen the end of that era and are now in a position to move forward and tackle the many problems which have been referred to.</P>
    <P>One lesson we can learn from the events to which I have referred is that there are a limited number of people who have access to a large section of the wealth of the country.  It is highly undesirable where the wealth of what one could consider to be a poor nation, greatly under-developed is held in the hands and in the control of so few people. We must do something about it.  I am not anti-capitalist.  I believe the capitalist system has served some of the economies in the world best but, at the same time, there is a limit beyond which one does not go.  In recent months in this Chamber and in the Dáil, we have spoken about social welfare, how inadequate it is and the serious situation regarding unemployment. Yet, we see from the various developments to which I have referred, millions upon millions of pounds being tossed around here and there.  This created a very bad impression on the public.  However, having said that, we must be positive.  We must recognise that among those to whom I have referred there are excellent people who have done well for this country and the economy but the system must be ordered in a way that will not allow some people to become billionaires and others to be virtually on the breadline on an ongoing basis.</P>
    <P>When we talk about future prospects for the country, unfortunately the situation does not look too bright.  One would like to say there are bright years ahead in the nineties but as of now it does not look that way.  I do not lay the blame for this at the Government's table.  There are international events over which we have absolutely no control and until these improve we cannot hope for significant improvements.  However, we must play our part the best way we can.  For that reason, I wish the Taoiseach and his Government well in the time ahead and <Col N="860" /> hope they will be successful in improving our economy.</P>
    <P>I am a realist.  I do not think the Government will be in a position to reduce unemployment from its present enormous level of 269,000 &mdash; some would say 300,000 taking emigration into the equation.  It is unacceptable and I am sure a Government, working diligently, will make an impact on it.  However, I am certain that no Government in a short period of time would be in a position to totally alleviate that problem.</P>
    <P>There are a number of areas which should be addressed far more vehemently and with greater determination than has been the case up to now.  One of these is tourism.  It was stated in this House that the potential for the development of tourism has not been exploited to the full. We have approximately a £1.5 billion return from tourism to the Exchequer each year.  This is a fairly substantial sum of money and is very welcome but the potential to increase that figure dramatically is enormous.  I do not believe the recent injection of £1 million by the Government in the tourist business is sufficient when we are talking about that volume of business and the value to the economy.  I urge the Government, therefore, to address tourism in a more positive and realistic way to ensure that the potential is fully exploited.</P>
    <P>We must ensure that tourism is an all-year round operation.  We must get away from the seasonal aspect and attract people here throughout the year.  This, of course, entails the development of certain leisure pursuits and activities which are currently not available here.  It would pay dividends if we promoted Ireland as an all-year round tourist area and not just in the summer months.  Golf, indoor sport, and other activities could be developed to attract repeat tourists.  Our climate is very mild; we never have extremes of cold or heat.  We have a very balanced climate.  Those who travel from very hot or very cold countries describe it as a nice temperate climate.  We should develop and expand this asset to a far greater degree than we have been doing.</P>
    <P>One could talk about tourism <i>ad</i><Col N="861" /><i>nauseam</i> but I have no intention of doing that.  I urge the Minister to ensure that every effort is made to exploit all avenues so that we get the returns that are available. We must get these returns from tourism because, regrettably, agriculture is very restricted.  Already milk production is restricted and restrictions on beef and sheep production are inevitable. Even if there were no restrictions we do not have many outlets.  The returns from agricultural activities which were quite lucrative until recently have now ceased. Agriculture has always been our top industry but regrettably, it is slipping, not because of internal factors but because of external decisions such as the Common Agricultural Policy and the GATT negotiations. Neither the Common Agricultural Policy nor the GATT can be discussed in isolation; they are synonymous.</P>
    <P>America was the big influence in the GATT.  There are 105 countries involved in the GATT &mdash; America, the Cairns Group, South America, Canada and so on.  The Americans, supported by many of their strong allies, are aiming for a free trading arrangement.  That would be disastrous from our point of view because we are a very disadvantaged nation, a small island, distant from the mainland of Europe and from the marketplace. In reforming the Common Agricultural Policy and renegotiating GATT, we must demand special concessions, and we must not apologise for doing so.  We are an important location from a military point of view and that is worth a great deal to the nations with whom we will be talking. We must hold out for special and positive concessions otherwise, we will not reap the maximum benefit.</P>
    <P>As I said, agriculture is very restricted and we can no longer look to it for solutions. Therefore, tourism is our main plank which we should develop in order to alleviate our problems.</P>
    <P>We also have a lot of light industry and that can do well here.  We must, of course, provide the economic atmosphere for industrial development by having our interest and inflation rates at the right levels.  Industrial development, <Col N="862" /> as anybody knows depends almost totally on inflation and interest rates.  Mention has been made in this House of banks and lending institutions.  There is a need for positive scrutiny of the lending institutions and how they operate.  They are imposing new charges, which are having an adverse effect on the development of small businesses.  They also have a major and severe effect on the lives of many people.  I look forward in the near future to a debate on the banking system.  Suffice to say that, at present, the lending institutions are exploiting the system and are not serving the people as they should.</P>
    <P>Most of the decisions that affect this country are not taken by the Government, but in Brussels or wherever the European Community makes its decisions for the Twelve.  Many of these decisions are influenced, governed and tied very closely to the decisions of other trading nations, like the GATT countries. For that reason our decisions are affected by the world scene.  We are now playing much more on the world stage. When we consider that 17 per cent of our population are primarily involved in farming and that only 3 per cent of the population of the GATT countries are involved in farming, it does not augur well for the attitude, thinking and outlook of these countries towards the development of our primary industry, agriculture.  However, and I will say it again at the risk of being repetitive, we must make a strong case for special conditions because of our location, our under-developed state, our small population and various other reasons.  Our Government can capably and ably put forward the proper arguments to ensure we are treated fairly.</P>
    <P>Our country, which we all love so dearly, is facing a serious challenge from the point of view of population location in the years ahead.  At the moment one third of our population live in Dublin and this trend is definitely ongoing.  People are leaving rural areas in counties Galway, Mayo, Leitrim, Sligo, Westmeath, Limerick, Roscommon and elsewhere and moving to the city and towns, perhaps even going abroad to London, <Col N="863" /> New York or other places.  There has been a massive population drift from rural areas and I am not talking exclusively about farming.  This is changing the whole social fabric of society.  Over a period of years many millions of people will have drifted away from rural areas and it is a great tragedy.  We cannot counteract this trend completely but we certainly can take some measures to control it.</P>
    <P>The State should finance our political parties but there should be strict and clear accountability as to how the money is spent.  I am not advocating that blank cheques should be given to political parties but it is not good for political parties whether in Government or not to have to rely heavily on large contributions from big commerical operations, which has been the practice up to now.  This practice is not politically or economically healthy and can lead to undesirable events such as those I referred to earlier which took place in the latter part of 1991.  I ask the Government to consider financing our political parties.  It is no secret that at present the main political parties, in particular, have major financial difficulties.  A major political party, whether in Government or in Opposition, should not have to face those difficulties when other matters in the economy should be attended to.  The Government should finance these parties and there should be a strict code of accountability to ensure there is no misappropriation of funds.</P>
    <P>Taxation levels are far too high. However, I welcome the downward adjustment in the recent budget.</P>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I should remind the Senator that taxation is more appropriate to the Finance Bill than to this debate.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardHourigan" hpid="Mr. Hourigan Mr. Hourigan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hourigan</NameTxt>
      <P>Taxation is important in the sense that many taxes remain uncollected and our financial affairs would be significantly improved if those moneys were collected.  Will the Minister say what amount of money is outstanding <Col N="864" /> in unpaid taxes?  Those taxes are from the corporate and various business sectors and are very relevant to what we are talking about.</P>
      <P>It is important that we do not lose out on any money that is available from Europe because we are not in a position to match it pound for pound.  We must ensure that we maximise grants, headage payments or anything else that is available from Europe.</P>
      <P>I have talked about tourism, agriculture and industry but there are other areas of our economy which are not income earners but which, nevertheless, are no less important.  Health, education, social welfare and the maintaining of law and order are all areas that do not earn money but are, nevertheless, in dire need of finance.  If one were to pick a needy area, it would have to be health and nobody could argue with that.  There is a great need for a better health care service here.  There is also a need for a better education service, a better system of law and order and social welfare payements should be greater but I emphasise the area of health.  It affects the most vulnerable sections of our society, the sick, who are often young and, indeed, not so young, but who are at a disadvantage.</P>
      <P>Reference has already been made to the various services which are set up from time to time and their costs.  There should be a more thorough investigation into the matter before final decisions are taken in this regard.</P>
      <P>Words could never explain the seriousness of unemployment.  Unemployment is like a cancer causing terrible problems on an ongoing basis.  It is the cause of our increasing crime rate and various other undesirable problems which could be avoided.  Those who are unemployed lose all sense of dignity and the people of this country, like any country, are entitled to the opportunity of having a job.  Some perhaps are not too eager to work but they represent a small percentage.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Another important matter is the Maastricht Treaty on which a referendum will be held later this year.  Various important changes have been built into the recent Maastricht agreement which will have <Col N="865" /> long term, and indeed short term, implications for our economy.  It is important that we pass the referendum, putting the stamp of approval on the Maastricht Treaty.  If we do not there will be serious consequences for us.  While we may not have got all we would have liked from the Maastricht Summit, if we are to be responsible citizens we must ensure its principles are approved by the people.  I hope this referendum is successful.  I am confident that with the co-operation of those who understand the situation and who realise the serious economic consequences for us the treaty will be approved.  However, we must not take anything for granted and, therefore, we must do everything possible to ensure this referendum is passed.</P>
    <P>I wish the Government every success in their new approach to domestic and international problems.  It is incumbent on all political parties in this House to ensure that they make a constructive contribution to enable the Government to do a good job in the years ahead.  I acknowledged already that all these problems are not necessarily of the Government's making but they do exist and, therefore, I urge the Government through the Minister to ensure that we do whatever we can to alleviate at least some of our serious financial and other problems.</P>
    <Speaker pid="DonnieCassidyFF" hpid="Mr. Cassidy Mr. Cassidy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cassidy</NameTxt>
      <P>I concur with many of the sentiments expressed by the last speakers. This is a very appropriate motion on which Members of the Oireachtas can express their views, can look back over the previous year, assess value for money in relation to all Departments and, in general, have a look at how the Government have performed over that time.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>As a Member of the Oireachtas from County Westmeath I am pleased with the Government's performance over the past 12 months and I look forward to the performance of this new Government under their new leader who comes from the midlands.  We are delighted with his appointment as Taoiseach and, knowing his track record in the business community over the years, he will make <Col N="866" /> decisions without delay.  Those of us who have known him in the various Departments in which he excelled over the past 14 years will expect the same efficiency and effectiveness from him as Taoiseach. He has a great track record, he has got off to a good start and I wish him and his new Ministers every success in the years ahead.  Indeed, the Minister of State who is with us today, Deputy Noel Treacy, is one of the most efficient and dedicated Ministers of State we have had for some time.  We have all been impressed by him and I congratulate him on his reappointment to a portfolio in which he excelled in the past.</P>
    <P>In relation to the motion before us, you, a Leas-Chathaoirligh, will know that in the past 12 months the biggest project ever undertaken in Westmeath was the bridge across the Shannon which cost £35 million.  This was done in co-operation with Longford County Council and it was a milestone for us all to see the opening of that bridge.  In the past few days work has also started on the Mullingar bypass, at a cost of £17 million.</P>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>With Roscommon County Council, not Longford.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DonnieCassidyFF" hpid="Mr. Cassidy Mr. Cassidy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cassidy</NameTxt>
      <P>I beg your pardon, I meant to say Roscommon County Council. This was a great archaeological as well as a great engineering achievement.</P>
      <P>As I said, work has started on the Mullingar bypass which will cost £17 million. This will shorten my journey to this House by about 20 minutes.  Also in the past 12 months a new wing has been opened to the Mullingar Hospital at a cost of £11.5 million.  This is now one of the finest hospitals in this island.  I am glad the former Minister for Health sanctioned the tender documents for a new X-ray department and admissions unit for that hospital at a cost of £4.5 million.  As a member of the Midland Health Board I know that is very welcome. It is great to be able to relate these great tidings.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Last year the Minister for the Environment sanctioned the spending of £2.3 million on a new sewerage scheme for my <Col N="867" /> own town of Castlepollard.  We are also getting a new fire station there at a cost of almost £500,000 and work commenced on the building of six old persons dwellings two weeks ago.  This is all great progress. Whether one is a county councillor, a town commissioner or a Member of the Dáil or Seanad, it is great to be able to look back over the past 12 months and see the investment the Government have made in the areas we represent.  I look forward with confidence to more progress in the future.</P>
    <P>I am delighted to note the extent to which the urban renewal reliefs have helped to bring about development to run down areas of our cities and towns.  I am particularly pleased with the extent of private investment and the knock-on benefit provided for the construction industry.  We have only to look at what has happened on the Dublin quays.  Up to four or five years ago the quays of Dublin, from the Aisling Hotel to O'Connell Street, were the prime location for making films about the 1939-45 war.  That is no longer the case.  The quays were popular because nothing happened to them for 40 years or more, but now we see all the modern developments there.  The urban renewal incentives have brought this about.</P>
    <P>To ensure that the benefits of the reliefs are properly controlled, I urge that no further designated areas be approved &mdash; and I am speaking now about Dublin in particular &mdash; until the existing designated areas have been satisfactorily redeveloped.</P>
    <P>In this regard I would draw attention to the special development requirements, commercial, rental and residential, of the north inner city.  In my view the reliefs have been slower to take off in that area. I would suggest that a special effort be made by the planning authorities to assist development there to ensure that this part of our city is not left behind in securing a fair share of the available scarce investment resources.  I do not have to spell out here what that really means.  We are all aware of the cliché about north of <Col N="868" /> the Liffey and south of the Liffey.  It appears that most of the investment by private enterprise and State and SemiState organisations is being made south of the Liffey.  Indeed, I am delighted to welcome the Temple Bar project, which came on stream with such speed over the last 12 months.  At least the investment in and development of our capital city is moving in the right direction.  But when we come to Parnell Square and Mountjoy Square, with its beautiful Georgian buildings, we find absolutely no development in that area.</P>
    <P>When people visit our capital city they drive from the airport along the motorway through Whitehall &mdash; and then they hit Dorset Street.  There is no development there whatsoever.  I know it is part of the Minister for Finance's constituency and I will be looking forward in the future to his investing in this area.  I understand from former parliamentarians that flats were built here as a short term measure in the late fifties and early sixties to deal with the horrific housing problem at that time.  I do not think the flats were intended to be a long term solution.  Up to 38 per cent of the people in the Dorset Street area are unemployed.  There are people there with nothing to do all day and no incentive whatsoever.  You know the old saying about idle hands.  I am calling on the Government to make it a priority to properly house those people north of the Liffey, in particular those who are living in flatland.  We have before us the good example of the beautiful new houses that were built in the inner city in 1981, 1982 and 1983.  We see the pride those tenants have in their houses and how beautifully they have kept them.</P>
    <P>Investment should start north of the Liffey because, for various reasons which I will not go into here, it is difficult to entice investment into an area where the environment might not be as friendly as it should be.  But, having said that, we find only 500 yards from O'Connell Street so many derelict buildings and so much inactivity that it is hard to believe you are in the same city.  Some long term plan will have to be put together as a matter <Col N="869" /> of urgency to develop Dublin north of the Liffey.</P>
    <P>I must pay a tribute to Deputy Haughey, our former Taoiseach, for the dedication and the commitment he showed in giving a lift to our cities and capital towns through this urban renewal legislation.  As a north Westmeath man, I am disappointed that Mullingar has not been included in the urban renewal scheme.  All our neighbours are in it, including our other capital town, Athlone, but for various reasons Mullingar has not been included.  I would love to see Mullingar included because not alone is it the capital town of Westmeath but it is also the capital town of the midlands.</P>
    <P>I would like also to mention an industry of great inportance in the development of tourism, that is, a branch of the entertainment and leisure industry, that I think deserves special encouragement.  I refer to the travelling shows, circuses, live entertainments, museums and folklore centres.  These activities enhance the quality of life, bring pleasure to families and visitors, keep us in touch with our history and help us relate as a nation to our foreign guests.</P>
    <P>The employment potential is particularly significant.  Sadly, most operations in the area are under capitalised and unable to realise their full economic potential.  To assist in the development and expansion of this branch of the entertainment and leisure industry I propose that a zero rate of value-added tax should apply for a period of ten years, provided certain conditions are met by each applicant, that they have a proven track record for three to five years and a business plan to be presented to Bord Fáilte, the IDA and the Revenue Commissioners.</P>
    <P>I refer in particular to once-off attractions, which bring people here for family holidays and attract repeat business.  Any hotelier will tell you that word of mouth is of the greatest importance in the hotel and catering business.  The same applies to the restaurant business, cinemas, museums or places of folklore.  These places find it very hard to make a profit; in fact, most of them do not make a profit. <Col N="870" /> The Revenue Commissioners know that none of the museums run by the State or local authorities ever make a profit.  In fact, most of them provide free admission because they are of educational, historical or culture importance.  Because of the enormous investment made by the State in the past, finance for these projects is becoming scarcer; yet, tourism is one of the main areas we look to here to generate income over the next 25 years.</P>
    <P>I am not asking the Government to consider giving grant aid to any of these projects; but there should be a plan acceptable to Bord Fáilte, the IDA and the Revenue Commissioners, under which, for three to five years, there would be financial encouragement to private enterprise.  Multinational companies and others would be encouraged to invest in these projects and be enabled to market and promote them properly.  I understand that if the Exchequer should forego VAT on these enterprises the loss to the Exchequer would be less than £1 million. That would not mean very much to the Exchequer but it would mean that an enormous amount of money would be available for marketing and the further expansion of these businesses.  I would ask that that proposal be considered.</P>
    <P>I mentioned on the Appropriation Act a few years ago the basic essentials needed in the hotel industry.  I must say that the enormous progress over the last four or five years in providing modern facilities in relation to accommodation and restaurant facilities is credit to everyone invovled in the tourism industry.  I congratulate Bord Fáilte, Dublin tourism and the various regional tourist boards for the great work they are doing, but I would make a special case for family run hotels and family run guesthouses because the season is so short.  The Minister present would know of this at first hand in his beautiful county of Galway. You are lucky now if you have a four month season; and last year many of them had no more than a two month season.</P>
    <P>The basic essential nowadays is a bathroom <i>en suite.</i>  Some sort of financial <Col N="871" /> incentive should be given by the Government, either through grant aiding or a tax credit, for improvements of that nature. However, it should only be given to family run accommodation.  I am not talking about big companies who build hotels and put in various facilities.  I am talking in particular about rural Ireland, which has to be allowed to develop as well as the cities and the towns.  Rural Ireland does not have conferences, soccer internationals, big GAA games or anything like that.  All they have is the tourist season.  They have to cater for the fishermen on the bridge of Finea, they have to provide the little golf course in Oughterard etc.  They have to be able to compete. They have to be able to provide at the weekends the same facilities the business executives and others avail of during these golfing or fishing holidays are accustomed to.  This is a very basic requirement.  It would create jobs in the building industry.</P>
    <P>Like the last Senator, I also look forward to all-weather tourist facilities being available in Ireland in the future.  We have a great climate for golfing and fishing. We are well positioned geographically to attract Europeans, and they are coming in here in vast numbers. All that is lacking to attract Europeans, Americans, Canadians or Australians to Ireland for their holidays is marketing.</P>
    <P>We have some of the best golfing facilities in the world; they are incredible. There are 68 new golf courses being constructed here &mdash; two per county.  It is a massive growth sport.  It is a sport you can take up when you are ten years of age and continue until you are unable to walk.  We have an enormous amount to offer here.  The success of our young players abroad, in the Dunhill Cup and so on, speaks well for us.  In my area there is a new course being constructed in Delvin, a town where there is only one Bord Fáilte registered house.  There is an opportunity now in Delvin to have 50 registered Bord Fáilte houses.  They all must have bathrooms <i>en suite.</i>  We have young married couples there with fabulous new modern bungalows.  The whole <Col N="872" /> area is going to develop because one family decided to get out of farming and turn their farm into a beautiful golf course.</P>
    <P>There are enormous opportunities, but I think a few million pounds will have to be spent to target these areas.  Some 40 per cent of the population of County Westmeath live in the towns of Mullingar and Athlone.  I am speaking for the majority of the people of Westmeath, those living in the rural areas, where we have 60 per cent of the population, and very little is happening there.  In the far end of my parish, 22 per cent of the population emigrated in the past seven years; and the houses of the last four people who died in my parish have been closed up.  That shows the gravity of the situation in rural Ireland.  A Leas-Chathaoirligh, you are from the west of Ireland and our Minister of State is from the west of Ireland.  I know it is the same in your area as it is in mine, but I am talking about an area only 50 miles from Dublin.  In the parish of Coole, where Bord na Móna closed down one of their plants, there has been a 14 per cent decrease in the population of 430 in four and a half or five years.  These are serious problems the Government have to face up to and all of us collectively as Oireachtas Members, have to pool our ideas and come up with constructive proposals.</P>
    <P>The proposals I am making here relate to tourism.  In Westmeath there is a lake for every day of the year; we have 364 lakes &mdash; you can have one day off, Christmas Day.  Yet, as I have said, we have only one Bord Fáilte registered guesthouse in the parish where this new golf course is being created.  There will have to be an incentive for rural development. I am delighted the Government have appointed a Minister in charge of rural development and I look forward to taking him to that area.  There should be new schemes for job creation and there is no better place to create jobs than in the services sector.  That is where there will be a need for jobs.  You will find very often that the people living in rural Ireland do not need as much money to <Col N="873" /> live as those who live in the capital towns or in the capital city.  It is not unusual for an employee or an employer in the leisure or tourism business to work 60 hours plus per week; you are lucky to have one day off when you are in that business.  From that point of view there is an enormous amount that can be achieved.</P>
    <P>The biggest challenge facing the Government and our country at the present time is job creation.  We have a population of 3 million; we have a million students and one million working.  We have a third of a million unemployed and two-thirds of a million on pension or retired.  That is a large proportion of the population not working.  We all have to take a share of the blame.</P>
    <P>At present there is a recession in Australia, America, Canada and the UK.  I belive we are doing better than most of them.  I do not have to tell you what happened last Christmas when so many of our boys and girls came home from England and did not go back.  I cite an example of my own little town from which 11 young people four years ago emigrated to a place called Bell Street in Melbourne and ten of these young people have returned home.  This is happening in every town and village in the country. They are not going back because there is nothing for them there.</P>
    <P>Anyone in Australia at present who has an overdraft for in excess of one year with the main banks, whether it is for $1 or $10 is paying 20.5 per cent interest.  I think we are doing very well compared to what is happening outside, but we can do better, because we are a great race when our backs are to the wall.  It is then that we get up and do something. Everything we discuss for the next couple of months must be focused on job creation.  I would love to be involved in an Oireachtas Committee set up to further job creation in the tourism industry.</P>
    <P>The other most important thing in our area, as the Leas-Chathaoirleach will know, is the Mullingar-Sligo railway line and I hope that in the coming year we will see great progress in that regard.  The industrial development of the midlands <Col N="874" /> of Sligo and of Donegal depends on this line.  The Minister of State is from this area.  I want him to bring word back to the Minister for Finance and to our Taoiseach, who also comes from this area, that this line is the life of every town and village from Dublin to Sligo and into Donegal, because it is the only link Donegal has with the rail system.  We had a long discussion on the adjournment here on this matter.  We had Deputy Lyons, then Minister of State, give us a very detailed reply.  One could imagine little factories closing down in every village and town along this line if anything were to happen to it.</P>
    <P>I am hopeful that the Taoiseach, the Minister, the EC Commissioner, who was born in and represented part of this constituency, the Ministers of State, Deputy O'Rourke and Deputy Dempsey, will take a personal interest in this line.  They all know its importance. As I said, we have had no urban renewal in Mullingar.  What greater way could we have development of our town than by having some of our workforce commuting each day to and from Dublin. We had no decentralisation to Mullingar either, but what greater decentralisation could we have in northwest Meath, and Mullingar than a decent rail system?</P>
    <P>The Leas-Chathaoirleach knows the state of that line.  Some of the signals have been there for a hundred years.  The track has been there for 50 years, and the locomotives on the line for the last 30 years.  Major investment is needed, and it will give some employment.  The Mullingar line will be my priority in this House for the next 12 months.</P>
    <Speaker pid="TomRaftery" hpid="Professor Raftery Professor Raftery">
      <NameTxt>Professor Raftery</NameTxt>
      <P>First, I welcome the Minister to the House and thank him for coming.  As another Galway man I would like to congratulate him on his promotion and wish him well.  Indeed, I would like also to extend good wishes to the Government because it is in all our interests that they do a good job and that the economy is improved somewhat.  I find it difficult to agree with Senator Cassidy when he seems to feel that we are doing better than most in this particular recession.  In <Col N="875" /> the area of unemployment, which is the real criteria by which you can judge the failure or success of a nation, we do not rank too well.  The US has its problems, but it has got only 6 per cent unemployment. Likewise, the other countries the Senator mentioned are in that bracket of 6 to 8 per cent unemployment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DonnieCassidyFF" hpid="Mr. Cassidy Mr. Cassidy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cassidy</NameTxt>
      <P>I was talking about inflation and bank interest rates.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TomRaftery" hpid="Professor Raftery Professor Raftery">
      <NameTxt>Professor Raftery</NameTxt>
      <P>I am talking about what really matters at the end of the day, and that is unemployment.  We have at least 20 per cent unemployment and, if you take into consideration all those who have emigrated in the last five years, you are probably getting another 2 or 3 per cent unemployment.  This is serious and you have to add that our national debt, which has grown by £4 billion in the last four years.  There seems to be an idea in the media that we are reducing our national debt.  It has grown by £4 billion in the last four years and servicing the debt is now costing us £2.4 billion per year, or roughly 10 per cent of GDP.  In effect, that is equivalent to the contribution made by agriculture; so you might say that it takes the whole performance of our main industry, agriculture, to service the national debt. Therefore we have a very serious problem and I wish the Government well.  As far as this side of the House can help, you can be assured of it.</P>
      <P>However, that is not the only problem facing us.  Our main industry, agriculture, is under threat from the reform of the Common Agricultural Policy and the negotiations in the GATT.  We know, on the basis of the reform proposed, that agricultural output will drop by about £500 million, that employment in the agri sector will drop by about 12,000 to 14,000 or 15,000 and that the number of farmers leaving agriculture will probably increase to about 20,000 in total.  These are fairly serious matters.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I know the Commissioner has talked about compensatory payments to our farmers, but we are not sure whether they <Col N="876" /> will ever materialise.  I also know that, if they ever materialise, they will not last, for the following reason.  Other industries in the Community, principally steel, shipbuilding, car manufacture and so on, have lost probably a million jobs.  They got their redundancy and a good bye. They are going to be asking why should farmers alone continue to get compensatory payments.  They are going to point out that they lost their jobs for the very same reason that farmers are losing their jobs &mdash; surplus production capacity, new technology and increased imports. The unemployed are going to ask why that money is not being used to generate new jobs and the taxpayers are going to ask why should they be supporting this sector.  Why not use the money to improve the roads, education, health, housing and transport?  The compensatory payments, I think, are illusory; they are a mirage.  If they ever appear, which is doubtful, they will not last.</P>
    <P>In the midst of all that, I regret to say that our Government saw fit to cut back on support for agriculture.  When the going gets tough, they say, the tough should get going, but when the going gets tough that is when farmers need more support, not less.  According to Commission figures, during the period 1987 to 1989 Ireland cut support for agriculture more than any other county in the Community. At one end of the scale Ireland cut support to agriculture by 46 per cent; at the other end of the scale the Germans increased support for their agriculture by 55 per cent, or a total of £2 billion &mdash; and we are talking about a level playing pitch.</P>
    <P>If there was any equity in the Community, if we had any sense, we would be asking the Commissioner responsible for competition to examine the situation in relation to agriculture and Government supports, because if it were happening in any other industry complaints would be made to the Commissioner responsible for competition and the matter would be rectified.  We find our farmers trying to compete, for instance, with the German farmers who have massive Government support in research, education, VAT, etc. adding up to a total <Col N="877" /> increase of £2 billion.  Our poor farmers meantime have the little support they are getting, which was very low by European standards, cut by 46 per cent.</P>
    <P>Let me take a simple example.  When ACOT and the AFT were amalgamated the combined budget was cut, in the first year, by 46 per cent and it has been cut every year since.  We are eroding the technological base of our main industry. If we continue to do that we will be unable to compete.  We are eroding a base that was already only one-third the European Community average, and one-sixth of what the British spend as a percentage of total agricultural output &mdash; and we have decided to halve it.  That does not make sense.</P>
    <P>We are facing the kind of competition that you find, for instance, in the Netherlands where their very high levels of research and technology have brought them to the fore in areas in which we should be involved.  For instance the Dutch recently transplanted a human gene into a cow to produce milk containing the human immune globulin.  If that succeeds &mdash; and it looks very like succeeding &mdash; the Dutch will have captured the world babyfood market overnight.</P>
    <P>A British company has transplanted another human gene into a sheep.  The patent has been bought by a German firm to produce milk with a particular type of human protein that is lacking in a certain percentage of people.  The German company obviously thought it worthwhile to pay a very high price for it.</P>
    <P>We are neglecting that area.  We tend to talk in generalities.  We are advising our farmers to diversify, to go into frog farming, fish farming, rabbit farming, donkey farming, pony farming, farmhouse holidays and so on.  Worthy though these alternative farm enterprises may be, they will not provide an alternative farm income or even a supplementary income for more than a very small number of our farmers.  With farming in decline, rural towns and villages will decline and the services thereto like the post offices, transport, communications and so on will die.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="878" /> Senator Cassidy has already mentioned the railway line to the west and he is right in emphasising it.  If the railway line dies the economy of certain towns and villages will die.  This line is in a bad state.  I know that.  I have not travelled on it recently but when I did so four years ago I was surprised at the quality of the wagons.  The journey was slow by comparison with the service to Cork.  We must face up to all these problems.</P>
    <P>I agree that there is potential in farmhouse holidays.  However, if you look at the grants available from Brussels at the moment, to encourage farmhouse holidays, you will see it is virtually impossible for a farmer to avail of them.  Many farmers in seaside, lakeside and riverside areas would be very happy to improve their houses and extend their accommodation. A grant is available but there is a catch.  The farmer must provide some form of entertainment as well as the extra accommodation, which makes the grant a nonsense for 99.9 per cent of the applicants. They simply cannot avail of it. There is great potential in that area. Modern society, in urban centres, and even in the countryside, means that we have a situation now that the vast majority of young people have never had the pleasure of touching a calf or a lamb, have never seen chickens under a hen, piglets suckling or animals born.  They miss having pets.  As a youngster I had a pet.  Children miss this joy and being exposed to it is a wonderland for them.</P>
    <P>I had an experience recently in Fota wildlife park.  A farmer's wife from west Cork looked very distraught, she was with a child of nine or ten years of age who was leading her back to the pets corner to see the pigs.  Imagine, a child from west Cork &mdash; the home of the pig industry for so many years &mdash; had never seen a pig and he was nine or ten years of age.  That kind of development has been taking place before our eyes, and we hardly noticed it.  There is a demand and a market, but it requires organisation, investment, marketing and, above all, a commitment to consumer satisfaction.  There are other prospects but I cannot see them replacing the two <Col N="879" /> main enterprises we have in rural Ireland &mdash; beef production and milk production. Nevertheless we must pursue them and ensure that they are developed to their full potential.</P>
    <P>Tourism in general is a growth area.  I was disappointed to see no reference to it in the Culliton report.  Tourism is a labour intensive industry but, unfortunately, it is also capital intensive.  For that reason people must get into all-year-round accommodation.  I am involved in a small scheme of houses in Baltimore, County Cork.  They opened last year late in the season.  With good marketing they are completely sold out for Easter and for May, June, July, August and September. It is a question of good marketing. Money spent on marketing overseas is paying off.  It is not enough to market, however, you must have a satisfactory product when the people arrive.  You must generate the kind of satisfaction that will encourage them to return.  As Senator Cassidy said, word of mouth is the best kind of marketing. When the visitors get here you must have something to keep them satisfied and their children happy.  I have in mind activities like fishing, pony treking, golf, walking and riding.  Our climate is suitable for many activities but not for what we were selling for so long; sea, sun and sand holidays.  We should not look for that market, which is beginning to decline.  People are getting more concerned about being exposed to the sunshine, with ozone depletion, the risks of cancer and, of course, the cost of going to seaside resorts abroad.  We could encourage many more Irish people to holiday at home if we provided the necessary facilities, they would return again and again.</P>
    <P>Job creation must be our number one priority and the money spent on it must be examined very carefully.  What results are we getting?  I am greatly concerned that the investment through the IDA over many years has given less than satisfactory results in terms of permanent, viable jobs.  I do not blame the IDA as an organisation.  It got its remit and <Col N="880" /> followed it as best it could.  It attracted overseas industries which gave good employment, but the net cost per job is excessively high.  In the meantime, we have neglected our indigenous small and medium sized enterprises and failed to encourage native industry.  We have been over-influenced by the high-tech, high profile glamorous industries.</P>
    <P>Another area which is totally neglected is the promotion of the arts.  I was astonished a couple of years ago, reading a report in the <i>Financial Times</i>, to find that the net foreign earnings from the arts in Great Britain exceeded the net foreign earnings from their car manufacturing industry.  That is an astonishing figure, but a better example can be given.  The Australians, who had no tradition in the arts and no great culture that one could admire, have had phenomenal success selling their soap operas and some very good films overseas.  In recent times, I am glad to say, some great films have been made here.  I saw &ldquo;The Field&rdquo; recently, a very impressive film.  I have not seen &ldquo;The Commitments&rdquo; but I have seen &ldquo;My Left Foot&rdquo;.  These films stand comparison with films made anywhere in the world.  There is a market for this type of film.  We have also made our mark in the music area with bands like U2. Business like this is growing, creating wealth and jobs, but I do not think, in all fairness, it got enough Government support.  Some taxpayers' money might be very usefully spent helping to increase growth in this area, particularly in the film industry.</P>
    <P>Smaller and medium sized industries are the best hope for a small economy like ours; we can never hope to attract car manufacturers or other big industries. Generally speaking, people who want to start an industry are probably skilled with their hands while their administrative skills are scarce.  People who are good at building, block laying, plumbing, carpentry and so, on usually lack administrative skills and they need help in that area.  One way around this would be to encourage batteries of small industries with a common office and administrative <Col N="881" /> centre which would deal with their taxation and administrative problems rather than expecting a person with three or four workers to do that kind of work for himself or herself.  As one unit, a person like that could not afford to employ a full-time secretary.</P>
    <P>The other area in which our small and medium sized industries suffer is venture capital.  Our banks are great at pushing money where it is not really needed, but where it is really needed, to start up a business, as venture capital, they are very slow to accommodate people.  If we do not have venture capital, we will not have new industry.  We also need to change our culture in relation to failure in industry. Other countries accept failure; they regard a 50 per cent success rate as quite good &mdash; I am referring to countries like Germany and the US.  If a person fails at an industry here, they feel a sense of shame.  In America a person who fails again and again and tries again and again is admired.  We do not have that ethos. The sooner we recognise that not everything we start can be a success the better. The sooner we compliment a person who gets up and starts again, rather than saying he did not deserve to succeed, the better.</P>
    <P>We are spending a lot of money on education because a very high percentage of our young people are at school and at university, which is a good and essential thing, but it costs the nation roughly £100 million for third level education for those who leave the moment they are qualified. That is an enormous burden on the taxpayer with no obvious return.  That person is going overseas to make money, to settle and perhaps set up an industry elsewhere.  We must look at the cost of third level education and see what can be done to get these people to contribute something in return for what the taxpayer has given them.  The quality of our education is good, although I am concerned about the pressure we are putting on young people.  It now starts at primary level; it is getting horrific at secondary level, particularly at leaving certificate level, all with a view to getting into university. Students at second level should <Col N="882" /> be reminded that there are other avenues open to them besides university.  People can make a very good contribution to an economy without university qualifications. I know youngsters, and particularly their parents, like them to get a university qualification, but it is not the only thing in the world.  However, if a person is not inclined towards a university education, they would probably be much happier and more fulfilled and would make a better contribution in some other area.</P>
    <P>I wish to make a few brief comments on the Maastricht Summit.  We will be discussing the summit and having a referendum on it later in the year.  I am sorry our nearest neighbour and largest trading partner could not see fit to join the monetary union or the Social Charter.  As a result we, as a nation, will be unable to gain as much from the Maastricht Treaty as we would otherwise have got.  We will lose much of the benefit of a single currency because our biggest single trading partner is Britain.  We will become less competitive relating to the UK in terms of attracting overseas investment.  It is regrettable, but, at the end of the day we will have no option but to encourage our electorate to approve this Treaty.  I sincerely hope it is not endangered by the events of recent weeks.</P>
    <Speaker pid="DanielKiely" hpid="Mr. D. Kiely Mr. D. Kiely">
      <NameTxt>Mr. D. Kiely</NameTxt>
      <P>I welcome this debate.  I am impressed by some of the remarks made by previous speakers.  I agree with much that was said here this evening.  A great deal of the money spent in this country, particularly by the IDA, over the years was badly invested.  In the earlier years, it was well invested but we now have vacant factories all over the country. The prospect of getting any foreign industry into those vacant factories is quite slim.  We must move our sights and resources to our own people and, in particular, we must gear them towards tourism in a big way.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Coming from a tourist county &mdash; even though my own area is more industrial &mdash; I feel there is a real urge for growth in the tourist business and the day of the sand bucket is over.  I would like to see <Col N="883" /> the Government looking at the seaside resorts, once the backbone of the industry, and offering a life line to the people there.  I was involved in business in a seaside resort for some years and I remember when you could predict a season of perhaps four or five months. Regardless of the weather, people started coming on holidays in May and continued until September.  However, when foreign holidays became popular many of our people started to holiday abroad.  They went for the sun, and who can blame them.  Now, many people may want to get away from the sun and have a different type of holiday.</P>
    <P>In Germany or Spain a trip to an historical site can consist of a three hour bus journey, followed by an hour walking around the monument or site and another two or three hours travelling back again by bus.  Here in Ireland we have such a wealth of monuments, archaeological sites and tourist attractions that one can see six, seven, eight or nine all in one day, and have a fantastic day.  We should gear ourselves to our own market.  We need to increase the number of bed nights people spend here and we should market our museums, heritage centres and places of culture.  We can also develop our sea sports, walks, golfing and other attractions in order to extend our season.</P>
    <P>A recent survey in the Kerry region showed that the longest time we can keep the tourist in Kerry is a day and a half. That is a staggering statistic.  After only a day and a half they move on.  There are enough areas of interest in County Kerry, as in other countries, to keep people for four, five or six days.  This is an area with enormous potential.</P>
    <P>Irish people like meeting others and attending to them.  That is why we have such a reputation for friendliness and hospitality.  Abroad, particularly in Italy, if you asked the time of day they would nearly shout at you.  If you asked an Irish person the same question and if they did not have a watch on them they would nearly go to a neighbour's house to find out the time.  That is the difference.</P>
    <P>Banks were mentioned in this debate <Col N="884" /> and many Senators were very critical of the financial institutions.  When you do not want money they are inclined to throw it at you, but when you really need it they do not want to give it to you. When your business is in financial difficulties they do nothing to help.  They should be more compassionate towards people who are trying to create business and improve the overall economy of an area.  The banks will have to be taken to task eventually.</P>
    <P>The FÁS system needs to be looked at also.  The system whereby 100 young people are put into a training programme for carpenters, for example, only to find when they are trained that there are about five jobs available, is unsatisfactory. We must change that.  We must look for a new type of training to deal with the open market.  We should consider areas for which we have never trained people, like perhaps bird watching on the sloblands.  That would enable people to gain qualifications in areas of interest that would be new and would benefit the country.  There are many avenues open to us.</P>
    <P>I am grateful to have had the opportunity to make my contribution and I would like to welcome the Minister to the House.</P>
    <Speaker pid="LawrenceMcMahon" hpid="Mr. McMahon Mr. McMahon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McMahon</NameTxt>
      <P>This has been a wide-ranging debate and all the contributions have been extremely valuable.  I sincerely hope that what has been said in the debate will be listened to by the Government.</P>
      <P>It surprised me to hear the previous speaker say that the average length of time they can hold a tourist in his very famous county is just one and a half days. Any time I visited Kerry I found it very difficult to leave.  I have no doubt the Senator has checked it out and has the figures to support his statement but it surprises me that anybody visiting County Kerry would leave it within a day and a half.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>There is tremendous potential in tourism. We tend to think of tourism simply as advertising abroad and hoping the tourists will come here but not enough <Col N="885" /> thought is given to providing for them when they come.  We think of tourists visiting our land and accepting the hospitality of our people, but there are many areas where we have failed to expand our services.  The EC offered grants in recent years to assist tourism and a recent motion in the House congratulated them for the attention they give to the tourist industry.  However, more could be done to make the EC grants more readily available because many of them are tied up in red tape.  For instance, if a small farmer in County Kerry wishes to go into the tourist industry he has to look at what is available or unavailable in his area, and then see what he can provide.  Some farmers can provide accommodationn some can provide ponies for trekking, or boats for sailing on the many lakes in the countryside, or fishing facilities. However, the EC grants, I understand, are given on the basis that a person provides both accommodation and leisure activities.  I would like the Minister to look into this matter.  Perhaps EC grants to all countries have the same provision, but not every person who is geared to providing accommodation for the tourists, be they foreign or national, can provide recreational facilities.  Similarly, the person who can provide recreational facilities may be quite unable to provide accommodation.</P>
    <P>Debate adjourned.</P>
    <P>
      <i>Sitting suspended at 6 p.m. and resumed at 6.30 p.m.</i>
    </P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Food Prices:" RHead="Motion (Resumed)">
    <Title>Food Prices: Motion (Resumed).</Title>
    <P>The following motion was moved by Senator Raftery on Wednesday, 19 February 1992.</P>
    <P>That Seanad Éireann condemns the failure of the Government and, in particular, the Minister for Industry and Commerce to ensure that savings made from the drop in prices paid to farmers for basic food products have been passed on to the consumers.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="886" /> Debate resumed on amendment No. 1:</P>
    <P>To delete all words after &ldquo;Seanad Éireann&rdquo; and substitute the following:</P>
    <P>&ldquo;notes the enactment by the Oireachtas of the Competition Act, 1991, commends the Minister for Industry and Commerce on the speedy commencement of the Act in October, 1991, and further notes the important proposals in the Culliton report on the development of food industry.&rdquo;.</P>
    <P Just="Right">&mdash;(Senator McGowan.)</P>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHoward" hpid="Mr. Howard Mr. Howard">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Howard</NameTxt>
      <P>I did not hear the debate last week but have read all the contributions and welcome the opportunity of coming in this evening on it.  I support the motion.  What is sought here is that the benefit of reduced prices for farm produce be passed on to the consumers. There is no doubt that that is not happening and that the difference in margins between the farm gate and the consumers' table is growing.</P>
      <P>Irish farmers receive the lowest prices in Europe for their produce which is not reflected in consumer prices.  Prices for agricultural products are depressed now in Ireland and farm incomes have been reduced.  It is not too much to expect that when that happens, its benefit to the consumer should be insured through whatever steps are necessary.  That benefit is not currently reaching the consumer.</P>
      <P>An unjustifiable rake off is taking place in distribution and supply of food margins between producers and consumers and should be investigated.  Later in my contribution I will produce figures to support my argument.  First, I want to comment on the Government amendment to this motion.  The wording does not attempt to address the central issue put forward in the motion.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I am reminded of remarks made by the Taoiseach recently on his election when he spoke about frank and open Government. That promise finds no expression in the amendment before the House.  It <Col N="887" /> would be better for all concerned, and certainly for Irish consumers, had the Government parties approached our motion with an honest admission of its validity and proposals.  Instead we get a waffling amendment, referring to two planks of this amendment &mdash; the Competition Act, 1991, and the Culliton report on the development of the food industry.  The Competition Act has been in force for some time and the position of consumers has not improved since the enactment of that legislation.</P>
    <P>The proposals in the Culliton report are a long way from implementation; if Irish consumers are waiting on the implementation of those proposals to benefit from the reduced prices farmers are obtaining for their produce they will be waiting a long time.  For the Government to seek refuge as it were from this motion on two such flimsy arguments is to opt out of their responsibility and to neglect the interests of the consumer. The amendment avoids the clear and implicit purpose in the motion before us.</P>
    <P>By asking the Seanad to reject the motion the Government are ignoring their duty to ensure that the benefits of lower farm gate prices are passed on to consumers.  The figures I intend to use to support my case are provided by the Central Statistics Office.  In the five years 1985-90 cattle prices dropped by 10 per cent yet the price of beef to consumers was 18 per cent higher in 1990 than it was in 1985; milk prices increased to the producer by 7 per cent in 1985-90, yet the cost of butter and cheese to the consumer increased by almost 40 per cent; cereal prices remained roughly the same in 1985-90, yet the price of bread to the consumer increased by 25 per cent. During the 15 years period between 1975-89 comparing the ratio prices between what farmers received and what consumers paid over a range of products, marketing margins increased by almost 30 per cent.</P>
    <P>I will highlight some of these instances. Pigmeat price margins went up by 56 per cent.  The margins on lamb increased by 46 per cent, on steak by 32 per cent, on <Col N="888" /> eggs by 33 per cent and on liquid milk by 38 per cent.  If the Minister and the Government parties want to refute the motion, let them refute these figures first; the argument stands or falls on their accuracy and validity.  A week ago contributions were made by Members representing the Government side of the House from counties as far apart as Donegal and Kerry, who spoke of local situations which do not give the national picture and do no refute the figures I have quoted here.</P>
    <P>In Britain liquid milk sold in supermarkets is 11p sterling per litre cheaper than the doorstep delivery price.  If that price differnce were applied here it would save the consumer £20 million per annum.  Therefore, given clear evidence of producers receiving reduced prices from which the consumer has not benefited, I find that the Government decision as implied in their amendment, is a refusal to face up to a situation that needs to be rectified or else a pretence that the position I have outlined is not correct.  Even if they admit that it is correct, it appears that they are not prepared to take action to resolve it.</P>
    <P>The Competition Act, 1991, has been in operation for some months; no attempt was made by speakers on the Government side to indicate if it had in any way improved the lot of consumers.  It has not.  In relation to the development of the food industry as outlined in the Culliton report, I submit, that it has nothing to do with ensuring that the consumer receives the benefit of lower farm gate prices.</P>
    <P>I refer the House to the fact that we are faced with the reform of the Common Agricultural Policy.  That will result in significant cuts in farm prices and on the performance to date we cannot with any confidence say that the benefit of these reduced prices, no more than the reduced prices we have had over the last few years, will be transferred to the consumer. This motion which my party put down in good faith deserved to be accepted on its merits and if there was an argument to be made against it, it should have been a factual one.  The content of the motion cannot be rejected without <Col N="889" /> rejecting the figures I have quoted here which is impossible for the Government since the figures were obtained from the Central Statistics Office.  I strongly recommend our motion to the Seanad.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JohnDardis" hpid="Mr. Dardis Mr. Dardis">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dardis</NameTxt>
      <P>May I join with other Members who have welcomed the Minister and wish her well in her portfolio, which I am sure she will execute with the expertise and efficiency she has brought to all the offices she has held.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryORourke" hpid="Mrs. O'Rourke Mrs. O'Rourke">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. O'Rourke</NameTxt>
      <P>I have some learning to do but I am willing to try.  Thank you for your good wishes.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnDardis" hpid="Mr. Dardis Mr. Dardis">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dardis</NameTxt>
      <P>The Progressive Democrats oppose this motion and we are in favour of the amendment.  I accept the premise that farmers's incomes have fallen over the past two years together with prices received by farmers at the farm gate.  I know most Members of this House are aware of the depth of the problem in rural Ireland caused by those factors and that many people are living in silent desperate poverty as a result, a poverty as debilitating as any other in society.</P>
      <P>I do not dispute those facts but I dispute the suggested close connections between that situation and the price of food on supermarket shelves, and there are grounds for argument there.  Senator Raftery, when he opened this debate, presented a range of statistics which have since been repeated, most recently by Senator Howard.  We all know about statistics. I would never accuse Senator Raftery or any Senator of telling lies but certain effects can be achieved with statistics which might not always be a correct representation of the truth.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHoward" hpid="Mr. Howard Mr. Howard">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Howard</NameTxt>
      <P>Was I wrong?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnDardis" hpid="Mr. Dardis Mr. Dardis">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dardis</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not accuse the Senator of telling lies.  We will come to the question of whether the statistics are right or wrong.  If they are true and if the farmers, share of the market price is falling, which is arguable, the reason is simple.  The Irish consumer or the Irish marketplace <Col N="890" /> does not determine farmer prices; intervention determines them.  The Irish marketplace has a minor impact on what Irish farmers receive given our dependence on intervention and the high proportion of Irish produced food exported.  Factors other than the Irish marketplace need to be examined when we look at farmer incomes.</P>
      <P>The dependency of the farming economy and farm prices on intervention has been unhealthy; but it is also certain that intervention payments are a diminishing part of farmers incomes.  Senator Raftery and his colleagues, when we debated matters such as GATT and Common Agricultural Policy, made similar statements.</P>
      <P>Intervention is increasingly becoming less rewarding and under Common Agricultural Policy and GATT we will move further away from intervention and allow the marketplace to determine farmers' incomes.  In those circumstances, I am confident that measures such as the Competition Bill, to which the Minister referred in her address to the House, will have precisely the effect Senator Raftery and his colleagues wish for.</P>
      <P>A great deal of reference has been made to the Culliton report, and I agree with many others that it is an excellent document and that it charts the way forward in industrial policy for the food industry.  However, there is a significant table in the appendix to the Culliton report which shows the Irish share of EC beef production versus the Irish share of EC subsidies for beef.  In the years 1988, 1989 and 1990 the beef production share was 5 to 7 per cent, whereas in 1988 our share of the subsidies was about 33 per cent.  This share went down to about 20 per cent in 1989 and it rose to somewhere around 25 per cent by 1990.  That bears out my argument that it is the intervention system, the support system of the European Communities, not the Irish marketplace, which is determining largely, the prices received by Irish farmers.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Apart from the intervention argument, there are other reasons the proportion of the market price received by the farmer may not reflect market movements in <Col N="891" /> Ireland.  One reason is the high proportion of Irish food exported.  The Minister underlined the importance of the food industry to the Irish economy when she said that it accounted for 10.5 per cent of gross domestic product, 14.5 per cent of employment and 25 per cent of all exports.  Our reward to farmers is eroded by the quantity of our exports.  I think the benefits to Irish consumers from the reform of the Common Agricultural Policy and changes as a result of the GATT are questionable.  I think it is correct to say that Senator Raftery in the debates on the Common Agricultural Policy and the GATT made this point also, that Irish consumers consume such a small proportion of all Irish farm produce that consumer benefits will be exported to consumers abroad and will not significantly affect Irish consumers.</P>
    <P>I come now to figures for the period 1975 to 1989 for the ratio between farmer prices received and consumer prices paid over a range of products.  I do not find these figures surprising.  During the term of the Fine Gael-Labour Coalition Government, levels of inflation rose along with costs, interest rates and so on and we look back at them now in horror. Is it surprising that the people handling these products when faced with increasing labour charges, increasing fuel bills, increasing wage rates, increasing everything, had to recover their costs from the marketplace?  Is it then any wonder that the proportion which the farmer was receiving from those markets fell?  Farmers too, had to endure these price rises and I know from personal experience what it was like to farm through that period.</P>
    <P>In a previous incarnation I once had to trace chrysanthemums from Rush to Dawson Street during the Christmas period.  We took a typical box of chrysanthemums and began in Rush where they were produced.  We went to the producer and found out what he was paid. We went through the stages of the Dublin wholesale market, to the van man and finally to one of the premier flower shops in Dawson Street where we found that <Col N="892" /> the markup on a box of chrysanthemums was 330 per cent from the farmer to the consumer in Dawson Street.  I am confident that every person involved in that chain could argue a valid case as to why their particular cut out of that 330 per cent is not excessive.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MaryORourke" hpid="Mrs. O'Rourke Mrs. O'Rourke">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. O'Rourke</NameTxt>
      <P>The former Taoiseach says he is going to grow chrysanthemums.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnDardis" hpid="Mr. Dardis Mr. Dardis">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dardis</NameTxt>
      <P>If the former Taoiseach decides that he is going to grow chrysanthemums I would recommend that he acquire a flower shop in Dawson Street.</P>
      <P>Under the Competition Bill producers have recourse to court if they feel that competitive practices are not being operated fully and it is also significant that the Restrictive Practices Grocery Order, 1987 was retained when that Bill was introduced.  I was in favour of retaining that order because of the effect its removal would have on small country grocers who fulfil a valuable social function and cannot operate on the same terms as large supermarkets.</P>
      <P>There is a ban on below cost selling as a result of the retention of the grocery order which has been a serious problem for producers.  &ldquo;Hello&rdquo; money remains a problem and the State must intervene to some extent to modify the consequences of a totally free market, particularly when the market is dominated by large supermarket chains.  The Minister is aware of those things and his record shows that he is prepared to take on these strong vested interests.  He has addressed the dangers of concentrating the food processing industry in individual hands, and I applaud him for that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The solution to these difficulties is in the hands of producers and farmers. Good guidelines for the food industry are included in the Culliton report.  I have said many times on the Order of Business that we must debate this blueprint report in full in this House, and I hope that will happen before long.  If it is a priority of the food industry, as I am confident it is, to add value and to improve the price received for the food exported, then we must maintain the proportion which the <Col N="893" /> farmer receives out of that and increase it if possible.  Means to this end are available and should be used more widely, such as the producer group idea which has not been exploited fully and could bring benefits through joint venture and unified activity.</P>
    <P>The more people who can make a living out of our food industry which is going to become increasingly important as intervention payments recede the better for our society; and I include farmers, processing industry workers, co-op workers and the shop-keepers.  If we can go on from there to exploit our undoubted capacity for a green image and for high quality food, then we will have done a good day's work.  Irish food was never better value or of better quality; excellent products are available on supermarket shelves and that is the way forward.  The consumer will benefit if we attend to the items included in this report, and for that reason I and my party support the amendment.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MaryJackman" hpid="Mrs. Jackman Mrs. Jackman">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Jackman</NameTxt>
      <P>I welcome the Minister of State, Deputy O'Rourke to the House. I was disappointed she did not retain a full Cabinet portfolio having seen her perform exceptionally well in Education, and we saw signs of her input in the budget as Minister for Health.  I know she will make a marvellous job of the new portfolio for which she is eminently suited.  The concept of front of house image and marketing is a challenge which will be enormously satisfying for the Minister and I wish her every success.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryORourke" hpid="Mrs. O'Rourke Mrs. O'Rourke">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. O'Rourke</NameTxt>
      <P>I thank Senator Jackman and appreciate her remarks.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryJackman" hpid="Mrs. Jackman Mrs. Jackman">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Jackman</NameTxt>
      <P>I am glad to support the Fine Gael Private Members' motion and the input of Senator Raftery.  I too am concerned about the ever increasing gap between prices paid to the farmers and consumer prices.  Women, particularly, who are the principal shoppers are aware of the high prices consumers pay for Irish produce.  I refer not to luxury items but to basic dietary products, such as liquid milk, eggs, bread, potatoes and <Col N="894" /> meat, all essential products for good health.</P>
      <P>During the debate on the Common Agricultural Policy and the GATT in this House it was revealed that Irish farmers get the lowest prices in Europe for their products; this is not parallelled by proportionately lower prices, for the consumer. As motorists, we know when oil prices increase we pay more for our litre of petrol and when it drops, we pay lower prices for our petrol.  We know there is a tax element taken by the Government, but outside of that we are very much aware of what it costs to fill the car tank</P>
      <P>We are not conscious of the same drop in price when it comes to food products. What prompted this motion, which was initiated by Senator Raftery, was the realisation by consumers that the price paid to the farmer is continually declining and that the distribution and retail sectors have increased their margins.  These facts have been stated by various Senators. The products we are talking about are consumed on the domestic market, particularly milk, pork, bacon and wheat products.  Perhaps there is a higher export value in beef and lamb but we still eat beef and lamb here.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Farming organisations believe that consumption levels in the domestic market will increase considerably if consumers are given a fair deal.  I suppose one area we are very conscious of is the drop in the consumption of butter.  When spreads appeared on the market, straightaway people went for the very clever marketing of spreads.  This led to a reduction in the consumption of butter. Other EC countries did not follow suit.  I read in a newspaper the other day that the Germans consume an inordinately high percentage of Irish butter, much greater than we do at home.  We, the consumers, must see what is best for us and should not be taken in by glossy brochures and extremely sophisticated advertisements that say we will look better and be slimmer if we keep spreads and forget about butter.  There were slim people when they ate nothing but butter. <Col N="895" /> It is a question of moderation.  As consumers we must be very vigilant.</P>
    <P>I do not propose to repeat statistics already mentioned, but farming organisations spend a lot of time compiling statistics.  I will refer to the method of analysis in relation to the whole cycle, where the farmer sells milk and the consumer buys it in its processed form as butter or cheese and where the farmer sells cattle and the consumer buys steak. The approach adopted by one farming organisation was to look at the price ratios between the primary products sold by the farmer and the food products purchased by the consumer.  They stated that they used the Central Statistics Office national average retail prices published quarterly, so those statistics are up front. They also used the CSO's agricultural prices providing monthly data and their agricultural output tables giving annual data.  People talk about statistics but regardless of what anybody says, prices to the consumer are increasing at a time when they are dropping to the producer. We must ask about the middleman.</P>
    <P>All we have to do is to look to Third World countries and we see in an exaggerated form what happens to their produce.  To an extent, I see the farmer in the same category as the Third World producer.  The consumer does not get value and we must ask why.</P>
    <P>The price of beef is prohibitive.  We hear farmers at marts agonising over the drop in beef prices and yet in supermarkets we are still paying high prices.  I believe consumers must be aware of this and must continue to be vigilant.</P>
    <P>Take the statistics in relation to beef. There are three representative cuts of beef &mdash; round steak, which is cheaper, sirloin and rib steak.  Taking round steak as an example, let us look at the 1975 figures because there is no point looking at recent figures only: the price of round steak was 1.45 times the price of heifers in carcase weight, in 1989, round steak prices had increased to 1.89 times the price of heifers and in the first half of 1990, round steak prices had increased to 2.06 times the price of heifers.  For the <Col N="896" /> three cuts of beef, the average increase in the markup between 1975 and 1989 was 32 per cent and between 1975 and 1990, 46 per cent.  These are reputable statistics.</P>
    <P>Looking at recent trends, that is, comparing the first half of 1989 and 1990, it is seen that the markup for round steak increased from £1.76 in February 1989 to £2.10 in February 1990, an increase of 19 per cent, while the markup in May 1989 to May 1990 increased from £1.67 to £2.01, an increase of 20 per cent.  This is explained by the fact that although heifer prices fell by 15 per cent in the 12 months to February 1990 and by 16 per cent in the 12 months to May 1990, beef prices to consumers actually increased.  These are the facts.</P>
    <P>In her presentation, the Minister stated that much has been done in the consumer affairs area, but are extra staff needed? The consumer can only check the prices and moan but at the end of the day unless the Office of Consumer Affairs has an effective monitoring system, all we can do is shrug, wave our hands in the air and continue to complain.  There must be strict monitoring to ensure that the price increases paid to the middleman are kept in line.  At the end of the day the consumer must be protected.  Something must be done to ensure that too much is not creamed off by the processing sector, as was stated by Senator Raftery, and in the marketing and retail areas.  I know the Minister is concerned that consumers be protected.  I hope we will see a drop in prices and I look forward when next I shop to a drop in milk prices.</P>
    <P>I was surprised when Senator Raftery told me that in Britain if one gets a door-to-door delivery of milk one pays more for it than if one gets it off the supermarket shelf.  In my area I have not seen door-to-door deliveries for the past ten years, so we are not even getting the service.  I look forward to a drop in the price of milk to the consumer and an increase in the price of milk to the farmer, likewise for beef, eggs, bread and so on. At the end of the day, the consumer must be looked after.</P>
    <Col N="897" />
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. Farrell Mr. Farrell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Farrell</NameTxt>
      <P>Fáilte mór roimh an tAire Stáit agus comhgháirdeas.  I am sure, as with the other portfolios she has held, she will handle this portfolio in an expert and excellent fashion.  The Minister comes from a good family who have wide experience in farming, business and teaching and I have no doubt that her background makes her such an excellent Minister.</P>
      <P>I support the amendment.  The motion is worth while.  Statistics show there is a need to tighten up on the share of profits to middlemen.  In reality, that is not always so.  I remember when the late, internationally known, Fr. McDyer of Glencolumbkille tried to bridge the gap between the producer and retailer.  He set up 22 co-operatives which were involved in activities ranging from growing rhubarb to producing pedigree cattle. One co-operative he set up was involved in vegetable production in Glen-columbcille. I was involved in the &ldquo;Save the West&rdquo; campaign in 1954 and saw all the work he did there.  That was what motivated me to work in my own area around Grange.  We set up a vegetable factory in north Sligo at that time also. Fr. McDyer sold carrots in the first enterprise at four pence a pound.  He did some market research and discovered they were selling at 20 pence a pound in the shops in Sligo.  He had samples of the vegetables in the boot of his car which he showed to the shopkeepers who said the quality was good but the vegetables would have to be washed, graded and packed.  Fr. McDyer bought new machinery and set up a grading and packaging plant.  However, when he had them delivered in Sligo and other areas, he discovered he was better off taking four pence a pound for them as they were growing in the field.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>One of my first jobs after my accident was delivering milk in Sligo town.  I was delivering grade A milk.  Milk at the time was a shilling a gallon in the creameries &mdash; in pre-decimal currency &mdash; and I was delivering milk at 7½d a pint or five shillings a gallon, a huge difference in price. The owner of Ardgarmond Dairy did not become a millionaire despite his best <Col N="898" /> endeavours because he had to produce milk all the year round, not just in the grass period.  The man who sent milk to the creamery produced it off grass without any overheads.  He did not have to buy expensive cows and keep up production. He did not have big meal bills. Many tests and regulations governed the production of grade A milk.  Elaborate milking equipment was necessary and the milk had to be cooled to a certain degree.</P>
    <P>I became an agent and was the first to bring pasteurised milk into Sligo.  If I left a bottle of pasteurised milk outside a door when I was short of grade A milk there would be a note on it the next morning saying the children would not drink it.  One could not give away pasteurised milk at that time.  Now one could not give away grade A milk.  Everyone wants pastuerised milk.  It shows how things have changed since the 1950s.</P>
    <P>The price of a product at the farm gate accounts for 20 per cent of the total cost. If a shopkeeper buys in a ton of potatoes he is lucky if he sells 18 cwt. of them. There is always wastage.  Everything is prepacked now but this costs a lot of money.  It is not as simple as it seems. There are many people involved between the time a product leaves the farm and reaches the housewife's table.  Fr. McDyer thought he cut out the middlemen but it did not work then and it will not work today.</P>
    <P>I am glad Senator Jackman mentioned butter.  I always thought it was wrong for creameries to import vegetable oils to produce spreads.  It was against agricultural production.  They should not have done it.  I am pleased that North Connaught in County Sligo is the first creamery to produce a spreadable 100 per cent low fat butter.  It is being marketed nationwide and I sincerely hope it gets a good response.  It had a huge response in the west.  There is no doubt that it is 100 per cent butter.</P>
    <P>We have the cleanest and greenest vegetable shops in the world but we are talking about a small market.  The biggest market is in beef, bacon, and milk products. A large amount of that goes into <Col N="899" /> intervention or is sold on the markets in the EC.</P>
    <P>I take this opportunity to say fáilte agus comhghairdeas to the Minister.  This is the first visit of the Minister of State, Deputy Ahern to this House and I am delighted to see him here.  It is good to see new blood coming through the system and I have no doubt he will be a very good Minister.</P>
    <P>The Competition Bill went through the House and it will take care of any irregularities that may arise with regard to overpricing. The worst thing that ever happened was the advent of supermarkets. People thought they would save money by buying in supermarkets but they buy items they do not need to avail of the &ldquo;three for the price of two&rdquo; bargains. They might only want one item, but buy three and two will probably go to waste.  Supermarkets have destroyed small shops in rural areas.  Good stores in rural Ireland provided a service down the years and created a market for home produced goods because they bought from the local farmers.  There was a trade in every village that the supermarkets destroyed.  People were put out of work and that is one of the reasons for the depopulation of rural areas.</P>
    <P>Supermarkets are supposed to give the housewife better value, according to their advertisements, but, unfortunately, they import many foodstuffs.  For example, one will see sweet cake from Denmark and other European countries, but our bread and cakes are as good as those produced in any country.  It is a pity supermarkets are not more patriotic and do not sell more Irish produce.  They say they will, but only if they meet their standards.  If a person wants to do something he can find six good reasons to do it; if he does not want to do something, he can find ten reasons not to do it.  I do not think supermarkets are the blessing we were led to believe.  Maybe I am biased but I believe they destroyed shop-keeping in rural areas.  People do not take into account what it costs to drive their car into say, Sligo.  Often times, they buy what is not really needed, whereas, in the <Col N="900" /> olden days, they went into a shop and bought what they wanted.</P>
    <P>There are many different cuts of bacon and meat but I do not see any butchers becoming millionaires.  As a matter of fact, many of them have gone out of business.  They cannot have their own abbatoir because it costs too much and they have to buy meat from a meat factory. Vacuum packed meat is all lean meat and a lot of meat which is being cut away was sold in years gone by.  There is no fat on the meat being sold now and there are no bones in meat sold to the customer.</P>
    <P>Years ago, people liked to get a bone and a bit of marrow.  They used to say it made better soup, but the day of making soup is gone.  Even in the hotels they use packet soups.  I do not know whether boiling beef is sold now.  As far as I can see, there is only stewing steak or roast. There is only so much top quality meat in an animal.  A great deal of what I said will apply to bacon.  Some rashers are from the belly of the pig and, naturally, are not as good as back rashers and although they are cheaper, people will not buy them.</P>
    <P>It is easy to talk about statistics but statistics can prove anything.  We must deal with hard facts.  Food is cheaper here now than in the North.  People come from Northern Ireland to Ballyshannon to buy food, clothes and shoes.  If commodities are cheaper here than in Northern Ireland, we must not be over-charging. Our prices must be reasonable.</P>
    <Speaker pid="CharlesBMcDonald" hpid="Mr. McDonald Mr. McDonald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McDonald</NameTxt>
      <P>I take this opportunity to offer my best wishes and congratulations to the new Minister of State for Science and Technology and wish him well.  I had the pleasure some years ago of serving in both Houses with his late father.  I wish the Minister every success in his career and in the important post with which he has been entrusted.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I support the motion.  Many salient points were made in this debate but to those of us who are close to the farming economy and the farming industry, it is evident that there are retracting profit <Col N="901" /> margins in agriculture, restrictions in production and ever-increasing price inputs for services.  More importantly, it is clear that farmers are producing top class produce, including a very high percentage of organic produce.  There has been a drop in the sales of artificial fertilizers. The quality of our produce in improving all the while.</P>
    <P>Unfortunately, as the price paid to the primary producer is decreasing, as has been very clearly pointed out, a corresponding reduction is not being passed on to the consumer.  I do not know what the Government or the Minister can do about that.  In a free society, it is not ideal to look for price control but there must be some way to control the larger supermarkets chains who seem to constantly strive for preferential price concessions in addition to fairly lengthy credit periods from the co-ops and plcs.  It is all right for the rich to get richer but it is evident that small farmers feel the pinch and the last year or so have been very difficult for them.  One has only to look at the queue of none too happy people waiting to approach their bank manager or being invited in for discussions.</P>
    <P>I note the Taoiseach has appointed a new Minister with responsibility for rural development.  Perhaps the Government might look at the possibility of reintroducing farmyard husbandry, something many of us were reared on before the battery hens and factory-type production units came into vogue.  Other ways of creating a family farm income must be reintroduced.  If organic products were brought in, for example, the production of eggs or chickens there would be a market for them.  I see no reason high quality produce should not be able to command a premium price.</P>
    <P>I know that for decades farmers have been in the habit of complaining that one year is worse than the other but nevertheless the facts speak for themselves. In opening this debate last week Senator Raftery very clearly demonstrated the huge discrepancies that exist, and showed that, as far as Irish agriculture is concerned, the graphs all point in the wrong direction.  I do not <Col N="902" /> know what the Minister for Industry and Commerce can do about this but it is time the problem was brought to the attention of Government.</P>
    <P>The fact that Irish farmers get the lowest prices in Europe is not reflected in the price of food to the Irish consumer. Comparisons of food prices across the Community are difficult but we can see that the consumer in Northern Ireland and England gets better value on most items.  At the same time, their farmers get better prices.  When prices to our farmers go up it is reflected immediately and totally in consumer prices, but when prices to the farmer drop there is a time lag in the fall in food prices and the drop is never fully reflected.  Amidst all the fluctuations in prices there is one disturbing underlying trend, namely, that the proportion of what the consumer pays that goes to the farmer, is in continual decline.  The margin to the distribution chains appears to be on the increase all the time.  The Minister, if he does not have power at present, should look very seriously to see how the balance can be maintained.</P>
    <P>Looking beyond next year, if we want to maintain the maximum population here in gainful employment we must look not just at the small farming industry and try to maintain the numbers on the land but also at the small family-type entrepreneur, to try to provide increased employment opportunities in small family run businesses.  That is the only way we can meet competition.  There is no point in producing anything unless it is of the highest quality, produced to the most exacting standards so that we can compete with the best anywhere in the world.</P>
    <P>The environment is extremely important. I agree with Senator Farrell who was decrying the fact that many of the large co-ops were importing vegetable oil to include in a butter mix.  I agree with him because vegetable oil should only be used for energy purposes.  It is time we started growing more of it here as a non-food crop because energy is perhaps the only area where the Community is not self-sufficient. I note that both the German <Col N="903" /> and French Governments have undertaken not to tax agricultural crops grown for energy purposes.  Perhaps the farming organisations and the Minister for Agriculture and Food might look at the possibilities in that area.  All it would take would be for the Government or the EC to allocate the set-aside subsidy for non-food crops over the next couple of years. It would introduce a new industry or revive an old industry in this country.</P>
    <P>To refer to the motion before the House, if we take a few examples over a five and a 15 year period, using CSO figures, it is easy to see that the consumer is getting less than value for money and that trade is taking an increase in their margins.  Comparing 1985 with 1990, we find cattle prices were 10 per cent lower in the autumn of 1990 than they were in 1985 but beef prices to the consumer were 18 per cent higher.  This bears no relation to the cost to the farmer for finishing cattle.  Milk prices in 1990 were 7 per cent above the 1985 level but butter and cheese prices were almost 40 per cent higher than in 1985.  Cereal prices were roughly the same in 1985 and 1990; yet, the price of bread was roughly 25 per cent higher in 1990.  It is not sufficient for the Minister for Industry and Commerce to say that there must be a free market or that he is not interested.  He owes it to the primary producers to ensure that the farming industry can continue and that people can go on producing top quality products in the knowledge that they will get a fair and economic price.</P>
    <P>If agricultural incomes fall and the industry is in difficulties the creditors or banks will press for their money.  Everybody feels entitled to be paid the last shilling except the person at the bottom of the ladder who is dong the work.  If there is a depression in the agricultural industry no one seems to feel they should share the burden.  There is a reluctance among young farmers to take on traditional farm holdings at present.  Many of them are emigrating.  You have only to drive through any part of the countryside to see the demographic trend going, unfortunately, in the wrong direction. <Col N="904" /> That is frightening.  At present the future prospects for young people taking on, working or inheriting a holding, are not bright.  They cannot see an income or a decent and acceptable standard of living emanating even from very hard an intensive work.  I do not know what the Minister can do but I hope he will at least give a guarantee to the House that the problem will be examined in depth, and that some proposals will come forward to help stabilise the situation and to return to enhanced profitability especially to the primary producers.</P>
    <P>I would like to put forward a few figures which more than adequately demonstrate the necessity for this House to pass this motion tonight.  Taking the 15 year timescale, 1975-89 and comparing the ratio of the prices the farmers received with what the consumer paid over a range of products, we find the marketing margin increased by over 30 per cent.  The meat marketing margins increased most, steak went up by 32 per cent, lamb by 46 per cent and bacon or pork by 56 per cent.  The marketing margin increases for other items were: liquid milk 28 per cent, cheddar cheese 26 per cent, butter 11 per cent, bread 18 per cent, and eggs 33 per cent.  We need to be more vigilant about prices.  Competition is not always a sufficient safeguard especially when the bulk of the grocery trade is controlled by a very small number of companies.  I hope the Minister will take an initiative to safeguard the future, not just for the primary producers, but to give the consumer the benefit of the changes and the cuts which will arise in the reform of the Common Agricultural Policy over the next two or three years.</P>
    <P>The quality of Irish farm produce is improving significantly.  More and more people are going into organic food production, which seems to be welcomed by many consumers.</P>
    <P>I support the motion.  I hope it will be possible for the House to support it and that the Minister will be able to introduce some measures to ensure that the consumers get a fair deal.</P>
    <Col N="905" />
    <Speaker pid="TomRaftery" hpid="Professor Raftery Professor Raftery">
      <NameTxt>Professor Raftery</NameTxt>
      <P>May I begin by welcoming the Minister to the House and congratulating him on his promotion.  I wish him well in office.  We are feeling rather elated in Cork as we now have a senior Minister and two new junior Ministers.  Before we get carried away, however, we should remind ourselves that there are more Government Ministers in Salthill than in the whole of Munster: two senior Ministers live there and one floats between Salthill and Dublin. However, having said that, I want to come back to the motion before the House.</P>
      <P>The time is opportune to consider this motion in the House.  We all know of the proposals for reform of the Common Agricultural Policy: We all know of the GATT negotiations and we all know that no matter what the outcome may be it is certain to result in very significant drops in prices for the farmers.  Regrettably &mdash; I regret this sincerely &mdash; these moves are initiated and fully supported by an Irish Commissioner.  Having said that, we must ensure that whatever drop occurs in prices to the farmers is fully passed on to the consumer.  If the consumers do not benefit, and the farmers lower prices, the country loses out in both directions.</P>
      <P>I have put my arguments here about the drop in prices to farmers and the lack of reflection of that to consumers over a five year period and over a 15 year period.  I heard the other side of the House address anything and everything in relation to the food industry except the actual motion, which essentially says that the consumers are not getting the benefit of the lowering of prices to the farmers.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>We had a lesson from the Minister about the importance of agriculture and the food industry in the economy, about the percentage of the workforce employed in agriculture and in the food processing sector, about the percentage of GNP which is contributed by agriculture and so on.  We had a lesson from Senator Dardis on the percentage of our products going into intervention and various other issues, but none of them addressed themselves to the issue.  The margin going to the trade is increasing, <Col N="906" /> the price to the farmer is falling but the price to the consumer is not falling to the same extent.  I agree with Senator Dardis that consumers today have a greater range, higher quality and lower cost food available to them now than at any time in history, but that is not the issue.  My point is that food should be even cheaper as a consequence of the very significant drop in prices to farmers.</P>
    <P>Senator Dardis went off on a tangent. I can forgive the man.  He is a successful farmer but he has to defend his leader, the Minister for Industry and Commerce. He must be doing it very reluctantly in this situation.  He talked about irrelevant issues such as inflation under the Fine Gael Government.  He seems to have missed the point.  When Fine Gael came into Government inflation was 22 per cent; when Fine Gael left Government, it was under 4 per cent.  He also missed the fact that from 1977 to 1982 some other rather peculiar things happened in the economy.  For instance, in 1977 we had the lowest energy, transport and communications costs in the Community. Five years later, as a consequence of certain policies which were supposed to give us full employment, we had the highest energy, transport and communications costs in the Community, significantly higher than in any other country.  That is what the Deputy Garret FitzGerald Government inherited in 1982 and Senator Dardis seems to think it was the Fine Gael-Labour Government of 1982-87 who caused these problems.</P>
    <P>Senator Dardis also talked about chrysanthemums and a mark-up of 300 per cent.  I think that is making my point, although chrysanthemums are not a food product.  Senator Farrell also reinforced my point when he talked of the farmers getting only 20 per cent of what the consumer is paying.</P>
    <P>I do not want to go back over more statistics, but my statistics have not been refuted.  The reality is that the farmer is getting a declining percentage of what the consumer pays while the trade is taking a growing percentage.  I do not think this is acceptable and in certain areas it is equivalent to a rip off, particularly in the <Col N="907" /> retail price of liquid milk in supermarkets. As I said, if we had the price difference between the supermarket and doorstep delivery they have in Britain, 11p sterling per litre, it would save the consumer roughly £20 million per annum.  That is not to be sneezed at. This figure has not been contradicted by anybody I know of, anywhere, nor have any of my other figures.  Instead, the Government side went off at a tangent talking about the Culliton report which has not yet been discussed or adopted in either House of the Oireachtas, and about the Competition Bill which was introduced in 1991.  I am, in fact, talking <Col N="908" /> about the periods 1975-90 and 1985-90. The lesson to be drawn from the experiences of that period is that unless we are more careful, the consumers will not get the full benefit of the reduced prices to farmers when the Common Agricultural Policy reforms come in and the GATT negotiations are completed.</P>
    <P>For these reasons, I urge the House to support the motion.  The amendment is irrelevant in this situation.  I hope that in the years ahead all Senators will support me in trying to ensure that consumers get all the benefit from the fall in farm gate prices.</P>
    <P>Amendment put.</P>
    <P Just="Center">The Seanad divided: Tá, 27; Níl, 14.</P>
    <P Just="Center">Tá</P>
    <table pgwide="1">
      <tgroup cols="2">
        <colspec colname="1" colnum="1" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <colspec colname="2" colnum="2" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry rowsep="1">Bennett, Olga.<br />Bohan, Eddie.<br />Byrne, Hugh.<br />Byrne, Seán.<br />Conroy, Richard.<br />Dardis, John.<br />Farrell, Willie.<br />Finneran, Michael.<br />Fitzgerald, Tom.<br />Foley, Denis.<br />Haughey, Seán F.<br />Honan, Tras.<br />Hussey, Thomas.<br /></entry>
            <entry rowsep="1">Keogh, Helen.<br />Kiely, Dan.<br />Kiely, Rory.<br />Lydon, Don.<br />McGowan, Paddy.<br />McKenna, Tony.<br />Mooney, Paschal.<br />Mullooly, Brian.<br />O'Brien, Francis.<br />ÓCuív, Éamon.<br />O'Keeffe, Batt.<br />Ormonde, Donal.<br />Ryan, Eoin David.<br />Wright, G.V.</entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
    <P Just="Center">Níl</P>
    <table pgwide="1">
      <tgroup cols="2">
        <colspec colname="1" colnum="1" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <colspec colname="2" colnum="2" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry rowsep="1">Cosgrave, Liam.<br />Doyle, Avril.<br />Hourigan, Richard V.<br />Howard, Michael.<br />Jackman, Mary.<br />Kennedy, Patrick.<br />McMahon, Larry.</entry>
            <entry rowsep="1">Manning, Maurice.<br />Naughten, Liam.<br />Neville, Daniel.<br />ÓFoighil, Pól.<br />O'Toole, Joe.<br />Raftery, Tom.<br />Ryan, Brendan.</entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
    <P Just="Center">Tellers: Tá, Senators E. Ryan and Fitzgerald; Níl, Senators Cosgrave and Neville.</P>
    <P>Amendment declared carried.</P>
    <P>Motion, as amended, put and agreed to.</P>
    <Speaker pid="SeanDoherty" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>When is it proposed to sit again?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GVWright" hpid="Mr. Wright Mr. Wright">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Wright</NameTxt>
      <P>It is proposed to sit at 10.30 a.m. on Thursday, 27 February 1992.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Adjournment Matter. -" RHead="Dublin Bay Collision">
    <Title>Adjournment Matter. - Dublin Bay Collision.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="SeanHaughey" hpid="Mr. Haughey Mr. Haughey">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Haughey</NameTxt>
      <P>I thank the Cathaoirleach for allowing me raise this matter on the Adjournment.  I congratulate Deputy <Col N="909" /> Woods, on his appointment as Minister for the Marine and wish him every success.  He will be aware that Dublin north-east is a marine constituency and his constituents, like his friends in Howth, will be delighted that he has been appointed Minister for the Marine.  I am sure fishermen in particular will be calling on him to make their views known.</P>
      <P>The matter I now raise relates to the collision on 21 November 1991 at about 9.25 p.m. between the <i>mv Kilkenny</i> owned by the B &amp; I which was approaching Dublin Port and the <i>mv Hasselswerder</i> on charter to the B &amp; I which was outward bound for Le Harve.  The <i>mv Kilkenny</i> sank quickly with the loss of three lives.  The rescue services are to be congratulated for the work they did that night.  When one considers that 11 of the <i>mv Kilkenny</i> crew were saved within 20 minutes, that is an impressive outcome.  Many organisations and institutions were involved in the rescue operation and all are to be congratulated.</P>
      <P>On the following day the then Minister for the Marine ordered an inquiry under section 465 of the Merchant Shipping Act, 1894, into the causes of the casualties and collision.  I call on the Minister for the Marine tonight to ensure in due course full disclosure of the details of this inquiry.  I appreciate that the Minister informed Dáil Éireann on 19 February 1992 that preliminary findings have already been submitted to the Garda Síochána and that the file may end up with the Director of Public Prosecutions. However, I stress that following the Garda investigation the families of the three crew members who died that night have a right to full disclosure of the facts. A similar marine tragedy took place in Ballycotton, albeit involving different circumstances.  The public on that occasion demanded an inquiry and subsequently demanded full publication of the facts of that tragedy, so the precedent is there.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>There are many unanswered qúestions in relation to the collision in November 1991 and the public has a right to answers in due course.  Everybody would like to <Col N="910" /> know who was to blame for the tragedy. It has been asked why two ultra-modern ships, with sophisticated equipment, on a calm night, in an almost traffic free port, were involved in such a collision.</P>
    <P>Another important question has arisen since that night, why no helicopter from the Air Corps in Baldonnel was requested.  One would have thought that Baldonnel was much nearer to the scene of the tragedy than other helicopter bases.  It has also been asked, why the lifeboats at Howth and Dún Laoghaire only put to sea one hour after the disaster. These questions come from the public and answers are being sought. Above everything else, we need to ensure that a similar tragedy never happens again.  We need to know what lessons we must learn and if new procedures should be designed to avoid other accidents.  In short, the public are entitled to know all the facts.</P>
    <P>It has also emerged that corrosive organic acid on board the <i>mv Kilkenny</i> was declared as furniture on the ship's manifest.  This is a serious situation with great consequences for public health and safety.  Bags containing chemicals were washed up on Dollymount Strand in Clontarf.  The health and safety of residents in Clontarf then and on following days was put at risk.  Such incidents should not be allowed to happen again.</P>
    <P>It has been pointed out that an antiquated cargo listing system is used by Irish shipping companies, a manual system that must surely be open to error. I have read reports about what happens in situations like this.  It has been suggested, for example, that when a ship is leaving port there could be a last minute loading of cargo onto the ship if it is realised there is spare capacity.  No paperwork may be done in these cases. We need to look at that practice.</P>
    <P>The ship's manifest must be accurate. I have seen reports suggesting that up to 40 per cent of a cargo could be mislisted in some way.  That is neither efficient nor satisfactory and it must be improved.  The listing system is antiquated and the answer maybe to introduce some form of computerisation.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="911" /> The EC Council of Transport Ministers discussed this matter in December 1991 and were briefed on the mislabelling incident. I would like to ask the Minister if there are any definite proposals from the EC Transport Commissioner on this issue.  I understand that proposals from the Commission are expected and that new directives are now being examined. We need to bring these matters to the attention of the Oireachtas to see how we can improve this situation.</P>
    <P>Mislabelling of cargo could present a problem for the Customs clearance services where personnel are entitled to know what they are examining.  There are questions there in relation to public health and safety and perhaps the body set up to deal with health and safety issues in the workplace could examine that issue also.</P>
    <P>Perhaps the Minister could update me on the progress of the salvage operation. Thankfully, we were spared a major oil or diesel spillage in Dublin Bay which would have had serious consequences for beaches and wildlife around the bay area. I imagine most of the oil has now been removed from the ship and perhaps the Minister could assure me that all the dangers have now passed.</P>
    <P>There was one other issue I wanted to raise in relation to shipping in the Dublin area which was the recent decision by Irish Continental Lines to aware a tender for the overhaul of the <i>mv Leinster</i> to an English company, Wright and Veyer.  It is serious that the ship did not go to an Irish company for service and overhaul and companies in Dublin and Cork and throughout the country could have undertaken this work at competitive prices and completed it to the highest standard.  Perhaps the Minister could use his offices to investigate this situation to ensure that Irish Continental Lines in future when examining their ships for service would consider Irish companies. There is no doubt that jobs in Dublin will be at stake if Irish Continental Lines decide to send further ships to England for service and overhaul.  I mention that in the context of the overall debate <Col N="912" /> because I know there is much concern about this issue.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelJWoods" hpid="Minister for the Marine (Dr. Woods) Michael J. Woods">
      <NameTxt>Minister for the Marine (Dr. Woods)</NameTxt>
      <P>The salvage operation has been progressing satisfactorily bearing in mind the fact that the weather has delayed the operation from time to time.  It is practically at the last stage and coming to a final and very sensitive part of the operation with regard to the missing seaman. The last part of the ship is due to be salvaged shortly, depending on the weather.  We have in the past two days reminded the B &amp; I and the salvors that this is a very sensitive stage and they are aware of that.</P>
      <P>All the details about the events of the collision will be covered in the report, together with details about the times at which various people were called out and the debris which got onto the beach, apart from the few dangerous items mentioned by the Senator.  Senator Haughey raised the question about the publication of a report at the appropriate time.  I agree with that.  Historically, in the Department of the Marine it has been policy for internal Departments of the Marine reports to remain confidential to the Minister for a number of reasons.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The Senator mentioned the Ballycotton inquiry which had a different standing and we are well aware of the tragic events there.  The reasons normally given for confidentiality are that if such findings were published witnesses might be less willing to be frank with the Department of the Marine surveyor especially where victims may have died due to carelessness or negligence.  Confidentiality is essential given that the Department's officer cannot offer the protection of a court of law.  There is no legal representation.  Consequently, people say they are not prepared to give information without the guarantee of confidentiality.  Bearing in mind that the principal objective of the surveyor is to establish the cause of the accident and to try to ensure that such accidents do not occur again, the surveyor would be anxious to get information even if on a <Col N="913" /> strictly confidential basis.  That was one of the reasons reports were not published.</P>
    <P>Another reason was that the purpose of a marine casualty report by the Department of the Marine is to review safety procedures and to establish quickly the cause of the accident.  It is not to allocate blame to anyone, but to establish the procedures which were in operation and the reason for the casualty.  Very often, however, disclosure of a report is sought as a basis for litigation or as a means of apportioning blame.  The reports were never intended for such use and more appropriate for a exist in which to pursue these issues.</P>
    <P>The third reason normally for not publishing reports was that as the casualty reports are compiled without legal representation of interested parties, by people without legal training, and since those held responsible in a report would have no right of reply, publication could lead to legal problems.  These are the kind of reasons cited for not publishing reports.</P>
    <P>On Committee Stage of the Merchant Shipping Bill, 1991, in the Dáil on Wednesday, 19 February, a number of Opposition spokespersons called on me to release the reports of marine accident investigations.  I indicated in my response on that occasion that I was sympathetic to the view that marine accident investigation reports should be made available to the Houses of the Oireachtas and to the general public.  While there are good policy reasons this has not been the practice, the time has come, I believe, to alter policy in this area.</P>
    <P>I would like to draw Senators' attention to my statement in Dáil Éireann earlier today when I announced that I have directed that my Department will &mdash; unless legally debarred from so doing &mdash; release a report of marine accident investigations undertaken by the Department of the Marine.  This is being done in the interests of maritime safety and to allay public concern about marine accidents. We intend to release as comprehensive a report as is feasible given the legal constraints and limitations.</P>
    <P>This new policy will have implications <Col N="914" /> for the conduct of inquiries by the marine surveyors of my Department and as such it will operate on an experimental basis. Following my decision work has already begun to devise a new <i>modus operandi</i> for future investigations.  This new policy will apply to the <i>Kilkenny-Hasselwerder</i> collision in November last and to all subsequent marine accident investigations conducted by my Department.  I have asked the chief surveyor of my Department to keep me advised if the objective of an investigation, which is to establish the cause of an accident and set about preventing its recurrence, is impeded in any way by this new open approach.</P>
    <P>Senators should be aware that there will often be a time lag between the date of an accident and the date of release of the related report.  Delays can occur in cases where the pursuit of civil or criminal proceedings arising from a casualty prevents release of a report by the Department until after the completion of the legal process.  I trust that this significant policy change will receive wide support and will be an indication of an effort on my part to move to a more open and frank style of administration in the maritime safety area.</P>
    <P>In relation to the <i>Kilkenny-Hasselwerder</i> collision on 22 November last, on the day following the collision, the Tánaiste and then Minister for the Marine, Deputy Wilson, ordered a preliminary inquiry under section 465 of the Merchant Shipping Act, 1894.  The collision between the two vessels resulted in the deaths of three crew members of the <i>mv Kilkenny.</i>  Preliminary findings indicated that the matter required investigation by the Garda Síochána and the papers were referred to the Garda Commissioner. A senior Garda officer has now been assigned to lead the investigation which is already under way. When their investigation is completed the Garda authorities will decide whether a file should be sent to the Office of the Director of Public Prosecutions.</P>
    <P>I am advised that it would be inappropriate for me to comment further at this stage.  I have also been legally advised that, in view of the Garda investigation, <Col N="915" /> it would be inappropriate at this stage to release a report based on the inquiry under the Merchant Shipping Act, 1894. I hope, subject to legal considerations, to be in a position to publish a report of the Department of the Marine inquiry when the legal processes have been completed.</P>
    <P>I know the Senator acknowledges that there might be such a requirement and that consequently it might not be possible to release a report at this time.  I have noted the points made in relation to the <Col N="916" /> new directive on labelling being considered at EC level and I want to inform the Senator that this case has already been brought to the attention of the committee involved.  It is a very important practical example of the dangers and difficulties that have been spelled out by the Senator here this evening.  That has already been brought to his attention and we will continue to pursue it.</P>
    <P>The Seanad adjourned at 8.25 p.m. until 10.30 a.m. on Thursday, 27 February 1992.</P>
  </MainHeading>
</Debate>