<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE Debate SYSTEM "../Debate.dtd"[]>
<Debate DocTitle="Seanad Debate" Day="Thu" Date="12" Month="Nov" Year="1987" Vol="117" No="13" DateIrish="Déardaoin, 12 Samhain 1987" DateEnglish="Thursday, 12 November 1987" House="S" CommitteeEng="" CommitteeIr="" SubNameEng="" cnum="1437">
  <MainHeading Type="Prelude" LHead="" RHead="">
    <Title>
    </Title>
    <P>
      <Col N="1437" /> Chuaigh an Leas-Chathaoirleach i gceannas ar 10.30 a. m.</P>
    <P Just="Center">
      <i>Paidir.</i>
    </P>
    <P Just="Center">
      <i>Prayer.</i>
    </P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Business of" RHead="the Seanad">
    <Title>Business of the Seanad.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I have notice from Senator Joe O'Toole that on the motion for the Adjournment of the House today he proposes to raise the following matter:</P>
      <P>The proposed closure of the National Social Service Board.</P>
      <P>I regard the matter raised by Senator O'Toole as suitable for discussion on the Adjournment and it will be taken at the conclusion of business.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Order of" RHead="Business">
    <Title>Order of Business.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="MickLanigan" hpid="Mr. Lanigan Mr. Lanigan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lanigan</NameTxt>
      <P>It is proposed to take Items Nos. 1, 2, 3 and 4.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MauriceManning" hpid="Mr. Manning Mr. Manning">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Manning</NameTxt>
      <P>The Order Paper mentions the Second Stage of Item No. 2 only.  Would all Stages of that Bill be taken today?  We certainly would be agreeable to that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MickLanigan" hpid="Mr. Lanigan Mr. Lanigan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lanigan</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MauriceManning" hpid="Mr. Manning Mr. Manning">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Manning</NameTxt>
      <P>When can we expect the next Committee Stage debate on the Video Recordings Bill and when will the remaining Stages of the Companies Bill be ready for the House?  May I also ask <Col N="1438" /> the Leader of the House if he has any idea at this stage of new legislation which may be introduced in the House in this current session?  Finally, on yesterday's Order of Business would he think again about the possibility of a debate on the security situation some time in the coming week?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelFerris" hpid="Mr. Ferris Mr. Ferris">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Ferris</NameTxt>
      <P>In connection with the Insurance Bill, when are we likely to get to the Committee Stage?  The Minister in his Second Stage speech intimated that he had amendments, which we hope he will not bring forward; but we are anxious to know what the format is and when we are likely to have the Minister on that particular legislation.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BrendanRyan" hpid="Mr. B. Ryan Mr. B. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. B. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>On yesterday's Order Paper there was an innocuous little reference under &ldquo;Páipéar a leagadh faoi bhráid an tSeanaid, Papers laid before the Seanad&rdquo; that I would like to ask the Leader of the House about.  It was a special report from the Ombudsman.  It is most unusual for the Ombudsman to have to do this.  It is one of his legal powers that where something serious happens he can supply a special report. It is an extremely important issue.  It behoves the Government if they take the Office of the Ombudsman seriously, which I doubt, but if they do&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>It is not allowed to expand on the argument.  The Senator certainly can raise a question.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BrendanRyan" hpid="Mr. B. Ryan Mr. B. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. B. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>I was not expanding, I was contracting, and I was about to conclude.  I think the Leader ought to allow a matter of such seriousness and such gravity, which has been seen by the Ombudsman to be so serious, to be debated in this House and to be debated in Government time.  A fundamental question of justice in our society&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>There are two motions on the Order Paper, No. 47 and No. 50, dealing with that subject.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MickLanigan" hpid="Mr. Lanigan Mr. Lanigan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lanigan</NameTxt>
      <P>On the question raised <Col N="1439" /> by Senator B. Ryan, the papers laid before the Seanad come before the Seanad.  If the Senator wants to raise this matter he can put in a notice of motion and then we can consider the matter. On item No. 6 &mdash; the Insurance Bill, Committee Stage &mdash; we will be taking that next week.  The Video Recordings Bill will also be taken next week.  So also will the Adoption Bill and the Nítrigin Éireann Teoranta Bill.  I am not too sure of the Companies Bill, but it will more than likely be the week after.  We will contact the Members in good time if the Companies Bill is coming on next week. On the question of a debate on security, I will reserve at this stage any comments on that.</P>
      <P>Order of Business agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Customs and Excise (Miscellaneous Provisions)" RHead="(No. 2) Bill, 1987: Report Stage">
    <Title>Customs and Excise (Miscellaneous Provisions) (No. 2) Bill, 1987: Report Stage.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Before we proceed with the Report Stage I would like to remind the House that the proposer of an amendment has the right to reply on that amendment but no other Senator may speak more than once on each amendment.  Where two or more amendments are being discussed together, the right of reply rests with the mover of the first amendment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelFerris" hpid="Mr. Ferris Mr. Ferris">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Ferris</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 1:</P>
      <P>In page 3, lines 30 and 31, to delete &ldquo;with reasonable cause suspects&rdquo; and substitute &ldquo;has reasonable grounds to suspect&rdquo;.</P>
      <P>That would mean that section 2 would read: &ldquo;An officer of the Customs and Excise who has reasonable grounds to suspect.&rdquo;  I think it is a reasonable amendment. It is wording that is used in similar legislation and has been used before.  I cannot understand why the Minister has used &ldquo;reasonable cause&rdquo; as opposed to &ldquo;reasonable grounds&rdquo;.  It is only a technicality but I want the legislation to be in line with previous legislation.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1440" />
    <Speaker pid="KatherineBulbulia" hpid="Mrs. Bulbulia Mrs. Bulbulia">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Bulbulia</NameTxt>
      <P>I ask the Minister to clarify why it was seen as appropriate to put in &ldquo;with reasonable cause&rdquo;, how he justifies the use of that phrase and how he feels it is the most effective in the circumstances.  I would be very interested in his reply.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFallon" hpid="Mr. Fallon Mr. Fallon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Fallon</NameTxt>
      <P>On a point of order, I would like to have clarification.  It seems to me that in some way what we are having today is a repeat of Committee Stage.  I was under the impression that what was passed on Committee Stage is gone by, that it is now part and parcel of the Bill and that Report Stage should be different and has been different over the years.  I ask clarification in regard to this matter.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I would just point out to the Senator that this is just a normal procedure on Report Stage. The fact that there are more amendments than usual indicates the vigilance and the hard work of our colleagues.  It is certainly within the rules of the House and there is nothing unusual about it as far as the Chair is concerned.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TonyMcKenna" hpid="Mr. McKenna Mr. McKenna">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McKenna</NameTxt>
      <P>What is the difference between Committee Stage and Report Stage.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not think it arises at this stage but the amendments on Report Stage may properly be tabled on questions that arise from the discussion on Committee Stage.  That is the normal procedure, the machinery there from the inception of the State.  The only difference is that the Members can make only one contribution on any one amendment.</P>
      <P>Debate adjourned.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Customs and Excise (Miscellaneous Provisions)" RHead="(No. 2) Bill, 1987: Motion to Recommit">
    <Title>Customs and Excise (Miscellaneous Provisions) (No. 2) Bill, 1987: Motion to Recommit.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="BrendanRyan" hpid="Mr. B. Ryan Mr. B. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. B. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>I move:</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>That the Customs and Excise (Miscellaneous Provisions) (No. 2) Bill, 1987, <Col N="1441" /> be recommitted in respect of amendments Nos. 1 to 13, inclusive.</P>
    <P>Precisely for the reasons outlined by you I would like to propose that amendments Nos. 1 to 13, inclusive be recommitted. This is a normal part of the procedures of the House and there are a variety of reasons for doing it, one being the disappointing failure of the Minister to produce any amendments in the light of the commitments that were both given and widely reported on Committee Stage.  Therefore, the depth and extent of debate that is required on these amendments goes well beyond the normal procedures of Report Stage and I propose that these amendments be recommitted so that we can take them in the more intensive form of consideration that is permitted on Committee Stage.</P>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>It is a little used procedure, Standing Order 91.  First, is the suggestion or proposal by Senator Ryan opposed?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFallon" hpid="Mr. Fallon Mr. Fallon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Fallon</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes, it is.  I formally oppose the proposal.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>The proposer may make an explanatory statement.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelFerris" hpid="Mr. Ferris Mr. Ferris">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Ferris</NameTxt>
      <P>May I speak on the proposal that is before us now about the recommittal or on the point of order raised by Senator Fallon?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I will allow Senator Ryan to speak on the reasons for the recommital.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BrendanRyan" hpid="Mr. B. Ryan Mr. B. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. B. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not want to go so far as to make accusations but it is quite clear to me and to other Members on this side of the House who participated in what we considered was an extremely constructive debate on Committee Stage on some of the issues that emerged on this Bill and in which we thought commitments were given.  I know the procedures of this House fairly well and I know the sort of language that is used. When a Minister undertakes to examine <Col N="1442" /> something again it is a reasonable expectation that he will come up with some proposals, not necessarily the proposals that we would want but some proposals. When you get to a stage where there are no proposals at all from the Minister on issues which the Members raised and on which the Minister made conciliatory noises under considerable pressure and then nothing happens, Members of this House are entitled to feel aggrieved. Since the issues which are raised in these amendments are issues that deserve far more detailed scrutiny than would be available under the limited procedures of Report Stage it is, therefore, urgently necessary that we have the freedom to go through these things since apparently the Minister is not prepared to facilitate us by introducing his own amendments.  The only procedure available to do that is to recommit these amendments so that we can debate them in the proper format amendments of this complexity deserve. Therefore, I move under Standing Order 91 that amendments Nos. 1 to 13, inclusive, be recommitted.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeOToole" hpid="Mr. J. O'Toole Mr. J. O'Toole">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J. O'Toole</NameTxt>
      <P>I would like to speak in support of the proposal by Senator Ryan.  I am not sure if the word &ldquo;misled&rdquo; is an appropriate one which should be used in parliamentary debate but, as reported in the Official Report of 22 October, the Minister gave an assurance that he would try to find the middle ground, that he would definitely reconsider the matter, seek the most expert advice available, talk to both the Minister for Health and the Minister for Justice and come back with an answer.  The Minister said he would not say whether this would necessitate an amendment but he was prepared to reconsider and do his utmost to find the balance in what the Senators believed was necessary to have the law fully implemented.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>A lot of work went into this Bill on all sides of the House.  There was no difference of opinion between Senators. I recognise that Members of Fianna Fáil feel a need to support the Minister's procedure but I want to put on record that I have also consulted with the interested <Col N="1443" /> parties, including those mentioned, and I am demanding an answer from the Minister as to why he has not come back with a response to the points which were legitimately raised.</P>
    <P>We are talking about more lives here per year than were lost in Enniskillen over the weekend.  I am not prepared as a legislator to walk away from responsibility and I will certainly point up and emphasise the irresponsibility of people who bring in legislation which allows criminals to walk free.  I appeal to my Fianna Fáil colleagues.  This is not point scoring, this is not making political capital of something.  This is a case where we are not being responsible to the people we are here to represent.  We must take on board the proposal made by Senator Ryan and I heartily support it.</P>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFallon" hpid="Mr. Fallon Mr. Fallon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Fallon</NameTxt>
      <P>I am sure the Minister will reply but Ministers generally when they come to this House, including the present Minister, make no firm commitment.  I am sure he examined, as he agreed to examine, all the points that were raised and I am sure he will reply suitably himself. Ministers tend to say they will examine matters which they do and, if it is found feasible, they will act; if it is not workable then they will not act.  Having gone through the various amendments that have been submitted, I feel that many of them are unnecessary, many of them are not workable and there is existing law to cover many of them.</P>
      <P>To come back to the point at issue the Minister never gave commitments.  He undertook to examine the points raised and obviously having made further investigations he found that he could not facilitate the House.  I am certain that if he replies that will be his explanation.</P>
      <P>
        <i>Mr. Ferris rose.</i>
      </P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Under Standing Orders the Chair is now required to put the question.  As a matter of fact the Chair has been a little liberal.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="1444" /> The Standing Order is quite clear so I want to put the question.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelFerris" hpid="Mr. Ferris Mr. Ferris">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Ferris</NameTxt>
      <P>I was not allowed to speak at all, Senator Fallon gave his opinion of the amendments.  It is a most unusual performance from anybody on any side of the House to question a Member's right to put amendments and then to give his opinion even before the Minister replies.  I hope Senator Fallon is not insinuating that we do not have rights on Report Stage to try to improve the Bill if we can.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>It is time to implement the Standing Orders of the House, no more and no less and I am obliged to put the question.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="KatherineBulbulia" hpid="Mrs. Bulbulia Mrs. Bulbulia">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Bulbulia</NameTxt>
      <P>On a point of order, since it is such an unusual procedure and one which I support in the context of&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Not unusual; little used.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="KatherineBulbulia" hpid="Mrs. Bulbulia Mrs. Bulbulia">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Bulbulia</NameTxt>
      <P>It is a little used procedure but it is available to Members when they feel they have a legitimate grievance.  In his response to the very finely and detailed arguments put up here the Minister certainly indicated to my mind, and I am not naive, that he would examine the points closely.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>That is not a point of order.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="KatherineBulbulia" hpid="Mrs. Bulbulia Mrs. Bulbulia">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Bulbulia</NameTxt>
      <P>My point is, would you be kind enough to read out this little used Standing Order before you put the motion?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Every Member has been supplied with a copy of Standing Orders.  I am now putting the question that the Bill be recommitted in respect of amendments Nos. 1 to 13, inclusive.</P>
      <P>Question put: &ldquo;That the Bill be recommitted in respect of amendments Nos. 1 to 13, inclusive.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P Just="Center">
      <Col N="1445" />
      <Col N="1446" /> The Seanad divided: Tá 12; Níl 19.</P>
    <P Just="Center">Tá</P>
    <table pgwide="1">
      <tgroup cols="2">
        <colspec colname="1" colnum="1" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <colspec colname="2" colnum="2" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry rowsep="1">Bulbulia, Katharine.<br />Daly, Jack.<br />Doyle, Joe.<br />Ferris, Michael.<br />Harte, John.<br />Hogan, Philip.</entry>
            <entry rowsep="1">Kelleher, Peter.<br />McCormack, Padraic.<br />Manning, Maurice.<br />O'Shea, Brian.<br />O'Toole, Joe.<br />Ryan, Brendan.</entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
    <P Just="Center">Níl</P>
    <table pgwide="1">
      <tgroup cols="2">
        <colspec colname="1" colnum="1" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <colspec colname="2" colnum="2" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry rowsep="1">Eogan, George.<br />Fallon, Sean.<br />Farrell, Willie.<br />Fitzgerald, Tom.<br />Fitzsimons, Jack.<br />Haughey, Seán F.<br />Kiely, Dan.<br />Lanigan, Mick.<br />McEllistrim, Tom.<br /></entry>
            <entry rowsep="1">McGowan, Patrick.<br />McKenna, Tony.<br />Mooney, Paschal.<br />Mullooly, Brian.<br />Mulroy, Jimmy.<br />O'Callaghan, Vivian.<br />O'Connor, Nicholas.<br />O'Toole, Martin J.<br />Ryan, William.<br />Wallace, Mary.</entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
    <P Just="Center">Tellers: Tá, Senators B. Ryan and O'Toole; Níl, Senators W. Ryan and S. Haughey.</P>
    <P>Question declared lost.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Customs and Excise (Miscellaneous Provisions)" RHead="(No. 2) Bill, 1987: Report Stage (Resumed)">
    <Title>Customs and Excise (Miscellaneous Provisions) (No. 2) Bill, 1987: Report Stage (Resumed).</Title>
    <P>Debate resumed on amendment No. 1:</P>
    <P>In page 3, lines 30 and 31, to delete &ldquo;with reasonable cause suspects&rdquo; and substitute &ldquo;has reasonable grounds to suspect&rdquo;.</P>
    <P Just="Right">&mdash;(Senator Ferris.)</P>
    <Speaker pid="KatherineBulbulia" hpid="Mrs. Bulbulia Mrs. Bulbulia">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Bulbulia</NameTxt>
      <P>I made a brief contribution on that amendment and I asked the Minister if he would care to explain and justify his use of the phrase &ldquo;with reasonable cause&rdquo;.  I asked for clarification on that.  Is it possible that you could invite the Minister to reply?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BrendanRyan" hpid="Mr. B. Ryan Mr. B. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. B. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>I want to join with Senator Bulbulia.  Is the Minister going to speak.  Sorry.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="NoelTracey" hpid="Minister of State at the Department of Finance (Mr. N. Treacy) Noel Treacy">
      <NameTxt>Minister of State at the Department of Finance (Mr. N. Treacy)</NameTxt>
      <P>I am delighted to be back in the Seanad.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BrendanRyan" hpid="Mr. B. Ryan Mr. B. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. B. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister will be here for a while.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="NoelTracey" hpid="Mr. N. Treacy Mr. N. Treacy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. N. Treacy</NameTxt>
      <P>I am prepared to stay as long as the Senator wishes and will cooperate to the maximum with the Seanad to bring about a conclusion to this very important Bill.</P>
      <P>At the outset I want to re-echo commitments I gave here on the last occasion I was in this House that I would consider every submission, every statement and every proposal put forward by all the good Members of this House, that I would consult with my colleagues and the various Departments and State agencies. I want to assure the House that I have done this.  The consensus we have arrived at is that we must ensure that the Bill before the House will not be in conflict with the powers already vested in the Garda Síochána or already vested in the Misuse of Drugs Act, 1977.  We have had detailed discussions on this, dialogue and negotiations, including communication with international customs agencies.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>On amendment No. 1, in relation to section 2 which merely extends the powers that customs officers already have in relation to search to cover meeters and greeters, these powers have been used in a responsible manner by customs officers to date and I am satisfied that sufficient <Col N="1447" /> safeguards exist to ensure that this continues to be the case.  I want to emphasise that the language of this section is taken from the Misuse of Drugs Acts, 1977 to 1984, and unless we stay in tandem with that Act and transfer the powers already vested in the Garda Síochána by the Customs and Excise Act we will find ourselves in difficulty and in conflict with the law.  We cannot allow that to happen in any facet of State activity or any work of any State agency.  I will have more to say on this on amendment No. 13 but I regret that I have to oppose the amendment.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelFerris" hpid="Mr. Ferris Mr. Ferris">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Ferris</NameTxt>
      <P>In replying to the amendment that I had put forward, I wanted to elicit from the Minister the reason he used the words he used and not the words as suggested in the amendment.  The Minister has given a valid reason in his response.  I said I wanted the legislation to be worded in the same way.  The Minister has given the reason.  The wording he has used has operated successfully in the two other Acts that the Minister mentioned. In my view the other wording is better but I am satisfied that the Minister's reason for leaving the words as they are is legitimate and for that reason I will not press the amendment.</P>
      <P>Amendment, by leave, withdrawn.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelFerris" hpid="Mr. Ferris Mr. Ferris">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Ferris</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 2:</P>
      <P>In page 3, line 31, to delete &ldquo;in the vicinity&rdquo; and substitute &ldquo;within three square miles&rdquo;.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>In line 3 the words &ldquo;in the vicinity&rdquo; are used.  In my speech on Second Stage I wondered what &ldquo;in the vicinity&rdquo; was because every part of Ireland is in the vicinity of some place &mdash; in the vicinity of an airport, a ferry, or port of entry.  I thought the words &ldquo;in the vicinity&rdquo; were rather loose.  I wanted to tie down what was in the Minister's mind, or in the mind of the Parliamentary draftsman and, for that reason, I put in what I considered a reasonable vicinity of any port of entry, that is, three square miles, not as an arbitrary figure but as a figure we could <Col N="1448" /> discuss and which would be considered to be reasonably &ldquo;in the vicinity&rdquo;.  One hundred miles is not in the vicinity of some place but it could be interpreted that way.</P>
    <P>I want to ensure that the legislation deals with the problem we are trying to come to grips with and we must be as specific as possible in what we do in this House before the Bill goes elsewhere. For that reason, I formally propose the improvement of the Bill by being specific about the words &ldquo;in the vicinity&rdquo;.  I consider three square miles would be reasonably in the vicinity of an airport, or a ferry port, or any other port of entry where drugs might be smuggled into this country.</P>
    <Speaker pid="BrianOShea" hpid="Mr. O'Shea Mr. O'Shea">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Shea</NameTxt>
      <P>I formally support the amendment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PaschalMooney" hpid="Mr. Mooney Mr. Mooney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Mooney</NameTxt>
      <P>Bearing in mind that the thrust of the Bill indicates that it is to strengthen the existing law in relation to illegal importation and considering the size of this country, I would have thought it would be better for the customs officers to be given full access to the entire territory of the State rather than as might be suggested, not just by the amendment but by the actual wording &ldquo;in the vicinity&rdquo;, operating with one hand tied behind their backs.  I, too, will be interested to hear the Minister's clarification.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="KatherineBulbulia" hpid="Mrs. Bulbulia Mrs. Bulbulia">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Bulbulia</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not think I can bring myself to support this amendment because it would circumscribe in a very definite way the limits and powers of the Customs and Excise people.  In reference to what Senator Mooney said, as reported at column 636 of the Official Report of the Committee Stage on Wednesday 21 October, the Minister spoke about the use of common sense in this provision and I support the Minister in that point of view.  He felt that &ldquo;in the vicinity&rdquo; was allowing a Customs and Excise officer a certain latitude in pursuit of somebody importing drugs and that it would extend to the airport carpark, somebody leaving the carpark and so on, and that the limits on this were common sense.  Therefore, <Col N="1449" /> I am happy about the phrase &ldquo;in the vicinity&rdquo; and I am convinced that the Minister's thinking on the matter is correct. I would be unhappy about any amendment which would seek to circumscribe to a limited area the powers of pursuit of the Customs and Excise people.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFallon" hpid="Mr. Fallon Mr. Fallon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Fallon</NameTxt>
      <P>Whilst I understand and appreciate the sentiments of Senator Ferris, in this case from a customs officer's point of view &ldquo;in the vicinity&rdquo; is preferable to nominating a particular area and I agree with the points made by Senator Bulbulia.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeOToole" hpid="Mr. J. O'Toole Mr. J. O'Toole">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J. O'Toole</NameTxt>
      <P>I certainly understand why the amendment was put down because, as I recall it, in the earlier debate the Minister stressed that he was talking about the carpark of an airport and places in very close proximity to the port or airport.  The idea here was not to restrict it, but to make it quite clear that it went beyond the immediate vicinity of the port or airport.</P>
      <P>It is my understanding, but I am not absolutely certain, that there is a statutory instrument or a ministerial order which covers the area of ports around the coast to such an extent that, even though there is not a port every couple of miles or every three miles around the Irish coastline, by virtue of a statutory instrument which extends the power of Customs and Excise around particular ports it covers every mile of coastline around the country and that the Customs and Excise have authority around the whole coastline.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Since we discussed this we have had a proposed change in the 12 mile limit.  I wonder would &ldquo;in the vicinity&rdquo; cover the new 12 mile limit.  I raise this for two reasons.  I believe that it does not at the moment.  I believe it needs a ministerial order or statutory instrument to make sure that Customs and Excise can work within the 12 mile limit area.  It should be pointed out to the House that it is all very well for us to say &ldquo;in the vicinity&rdquo; of ports but our customs officers, unlike any other customs officers in Western Europe who <Col N="1450" /> have a coastline to patrol, do not have any boats or any sea vessels and, therefore, there is a blank area there that we might need to look at.  It might be that the powers of Customs and Excise as we see them being extended under this Act, in order to cover the vicinity of three miles should be extended to people like the Navy, or the Garda, or whoever can cover that area.  It seems that this is another gap that will be left after this Act goes through, just one of many.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JohnHarte" hpid="Mr. Harte Mr. Harte">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Harte</NameTxt>
      <P>The draftsmen were probably employing the safety of generalities when they use the term &ldquo;vicinity&rdquo;.  In industry, for example, if a driver is unloading or delivering stuff, on his sheet will probably be &ldquo;Town and Vicinity&rdquo; which can take in the suburbs.  Perhaps in the case of Dublin, all of North County Dublin would be considered &ldquo;vicinity&rdquo;. This is the real problem &mdash; to get some definition of what is meant by the Minister when he talks about &ldquo;vicinity&rdquo;.  This is where the confusion may be.  As a person who grew up in industry, if I were being sent out to do a delivery I would consider &ldquo;vicinity&rdquo; to be out in the Naul or out in Balbriggan.  This is the type of confusion it creates.  If we could get a definition of what exactly is meant by &ldquo;vicinity&rdquo; it would be much easier to deal with it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BrendanRyan" hpid="Mr. B. Ryan Mr. B. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. B. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>This is something I have said frequently in the past: there seem to be extraordinary variations in standards in the quality of drafting of our legislation. Some words seem to be acceptable and other words seem to be unacceptable. I am quite certain that something as vague as the term &ldquo;in the vicinity&rdquo; would be entirely unacceptable in something like the Finance Bill and would keep half the lawyers and half the wealthiest in this country busy for years to come.  In an area where there is a possibility of extensive litigation and extensive analysis, such sloppy drafting is never acceptable.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>In an area like this people seem to feel that, because you leave it vague, it will never be defined.  Sooner or later, that <Col N="1451" /> term will be defined in a court of law.  It may not be defined in a way that suits the intent of this Bill.  You cannot get away forever with vague meanings.  Sooner or later a court of law will have to adjudicate on what &ldquo;in the vicinity&rdquo; means and a corpus of judgments will build up which will define the term anyway.  I do not understand why we have to wait until &mdash; probably in the process some drug smugglers will get away because some court will rule that they were not &ldquo;in the vicinity&rdquo; in terms of what the court regards as a reasonable interpretation.</P>
    <P>It would be far more sensible and it is far more sensible, both in terms of policy and in terms of drafting legislation, to say precisely what you mean when you write legislation.  I do not think I could support the Labour Party amendment but I share fully the objective they have which is to insist that in legislation words should have a precise meaning which is understandable to the person who reads the Bill.  We should not have to wait for a succession of judicial interpretations to get a precise meaning.</P>
    <Speaker pid="NoelTracey" hpid="Mr. N. Treacy Mr. N. Treacy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. N. Treacy</NameTxt>
      <P>I appreciate very much the sincere and vigilant manner in which Senators are taking the different sections. I also appreciate that people want to be specific on the type of law proposed to be put through the House.  Allowing powers of search, and I quote from the amendment &ldquo;within three square miles&rdquo; of any port, airport or the land frontier could not make geographical sense.</P>
      <P>To give an example, Dublin Airport property contains approximately six square miles.  If we are to talk about people coming into the actual airport terminal, they are three miles from the terminal and they are still three miles inside the frontier of the airport.  If we take the land frontier to the south of the Border, it stretches officially for 20 miles southwards. If you could take a port on either the western seaboard or the eastern seaboard and a point 20 miles south from the frontier and 20 miles inland from the port, a person is still &ldquo;in the vicinity&rdquo; of both the port and the land frontier.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="1452" /> If we take another connotation a person is seen or observed by either a customs officer or a garda at a particular time in a particular place close to, or within reasonable distance of, an airport, or a seaport, or the land frontier, or whatever and maybe is not searched on that occasion but due to information which comes forward later, it may be necessary for the Garda and the customs officers collectively, or otherwise, with warrants to search him then.  They must have the flexibility to be in a position to search those people irrespective of where they may be at that later date in view of the fact that those people were observed in a particular place &ldquo;in the vicinity&rdquo;, if you so wish, of the airport, or the seaport, or the land frontier.</P>
    <P>We must ensure that no constraints are placed on the officers in what they do. Powers going back to the 19th century already enable customs officers to carry out searches of travellers who have landed in the State and there is technically no geographical constraint on this power of search.  This consideration has not led to abuse of the powers of the Customs Service because the spirit as well as the letter of the law has been observed over the decades by the customs officers.</P>
    <P>Senator O'Toole raised a point regarding the territorial waters.  The 1881 Act gives powers of search on ship, boat, on hovercraft &mdash; I think as a result of an amendment we passed on the last occasion &mdash; to the customs officers and the Department of Defence if they wish to board or the Garda if they wish to board.  The Navy are under the control of the Department of Defence and they would be called upon to supply the necessary facilities to enable customs officers and gardaí to board any ship or boat, or whatever kind of vessel was within the territorial waters.  We can also search persons if they jump off those vessels or disembark.  They can also be searched. The 1881 Act gives that power.  There are sufficient powers of search within the territorial waters.  I regret that, in view of the points I have made, I must oppose the amendment on all these counts.</P>
    <Col N="1453" />
    <Speaker pid="MichaelFerris" hpid="Mr. Ferris Mr. Ferris">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Ferris</NameTxt>
      <P>We have now at least by way of this amendment elicited from the Minister exactly what he wants in this area.  It was because of the element of doubt in people's minds about what was required by the Minister that we wanted to give the fullest power within the whole jurisdiction.  I take up the point Senator Mooney made.  If the Bill had mentioned the words &ldquo;within the jurisdiction&rdquo; that would be another matter.  I do not know what &ldquo;the jurisdiction&rdquo; means on the Minister's side of the House.  Is it <i>de facto</i> jurisdiction or <i>de jure</i> jurisdiction?  If that is the case&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="NoelTracey" hpid="Mr. N. Treacy Mr. N. Treacy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. N. Treacy</NameTxt>
      <P>We are always concerned with the constitutional power&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelFerris" hpid="Mr. Ferris Mr. Ferris">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Ferris</NameTxt>
      <P>Right.  Why not be specific in this section?  We were talking about officers of the Customs and Excise.  The Minister mentioned in part of the section the word &ldquo;at,&rdquo; so we take it that at the point of entry officers of the Customs and Excise have powers.  I felt that &ldquo;in the vicinity&rdquo; which as he mentioned, might be a car park or otherwise, was not definite enough.  What you are actually saying is that if they are not caught at the point of entry, whichever way they enter, the Customs and Excise officer as in this section has the power to arrest or search them in any place at any time.  If that is what we want to do then let us say it, but do not give the impression that it was confined&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="NoelTracey" hpid="Mr. N. Treacy Mr. N. Treacy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. N. Treacy</NameTxt>
      <P>The police would be involved of course at a later date.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelFerris" hpid="Mr. Ferris Mr. Ferris">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Ferris</NameTxt>
      <P>Right.  In another section members of the Customs and Excise and the Garda are being treated similarily for the purpose of this Act.  This is fair enough, because you cannot have a Customs and Excise officer on duty in the central part of the country where there are no ports of entry; but under this definition that would still be &ldquo;in the vicinity&rdquo;.  This is fine as long as I know that you are talking about the jurisdiction.  I deliberately made it three square miles so as to <Col N="1454" /> exclude parts of Dublin from Dublin Airport. If it was six square miles the Minister would not have been able to make the counter arguments which I wanted him to make.  I welcome the fact that he has now clarified the position, that this section deals with the whole of Ireland. I am in no doubt about what I am talking about.  I am talking about the whole of Ireland in accordance with the constitution of the Labour Party &mdash; not sections 2 and 3 of our own Constitution, which I respect, but the constitution of the Labour Party, which says that Ireland is an island surrounded by water.  Any place we catch them now, under this section, we have the power to arrest and search them and so on, particularly in the control of drugs.  I welcome that and I welcome the amendment.</P>
      <P>Amendment, by leave, withdrawn.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeOToole" hpid="Mr. J. O'Toole Mr. J. O'Toole">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J. O'Toole</NameTxt>
      <P>May I ask&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>No, the amendment is withdrawn.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeOToole" hpid="Mr. J. O'Toole Mr. J. O'Toole">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J. O'Toole</NameTxt>
      <P>In that case, may I draw attention to the fact that we do not have a quorum in the House.</P>
      <P>
        <i>Notice taken that 12 Senators were not present; House counted and 12 Senators being present</i>,</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Amendment No. 3 is next.  Amendment No. 7 is consequential on amendment No. 3 and they may be discussed together.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelFerris" hpid="Mr. Ferris Mr. Ferris">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Ferris</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 3:</P>
      <P>In page 4, lines 2 and 3, to delete &ldquo;for such time as is reasonably necessary&rdquo; and substitute &ldquo;for such period as is authorised by this section&rdquo;.</P>
      <P>I think the Minister knows what I am talking about.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BrianOShea" hpid="Mr. O'Shea Mr. O'Shea">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Shea</NameTxt>
      <P>I support the amendment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BrendanRyan" hpid="Mr. B. Ryan Mr. B. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. B. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>I have always said that you cannot avoid precision in legislation. <Col N="1455" /> One may wish to avoid it and it might suit many people to have it.  There can be huge arguments about what people call &ldquo;mere technicalities&rdquo; on which people often escape in court cases.  &ldquo;Mere technicalities&rdquo; are what turn us into a society of laws &mdash; in other words, we regulate ourselves, with all the difficulties that implies, not by what we feel would be appropriate in a specific circumstance when it confronts us but by generally applicable legislation which is written down and which is understandable and which means precisely what we want it to mean.  That makes it very difficult for us. Like everything else that is imprecise in legislation, these sections will sooner or later have to be interpreted.  It would not necessarily be the fact that they will be interpreted in a way which suits the objectives in the legislation.  Thankfully the Judiciary is independent, at least in the legislative sense if not in a class identity. Therefore it will interpret this legislation not according to what is said in this House &mdash; they may have reference to it &mdash; but according to what they believe to be correct.  Therefore the more precise legislation is, the more we can be certain what we want is what will be achieved.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="NoelTracey" hpid="Mr. N. Treacy Mr. N. Treacy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. N. Treacy</NameTxt>
      <P>I presume we are taking both amendments together?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>We are discussing both together.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="NoelTracey" hpid="Mr. N. Treacy Mr. N. Treacy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. N. Treacy</NameTxt>
      <P>I will be replying to both together.  The purpose of the two amendments is to clearly define the period of time for which a person can be detained, which is placing a constraint on the Customs and Excise services and is not allowing the flexibility they would need.  I have listened with interest to what the Senators have had to say.  I have also noted the various difficulties which have been raised with the amendments and in regard to the drafting of these and other amendments.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The powers of search of travellers go back to 1876 and these powers have been exercised so as to detain the traveller only <Col N="1456" /> for so long as the search takes place.  The chief purpose of section 2 is to assign to customs officers the identical powers of personal search assigned to the Garda in respect of the Misuse of Drugs Acts, 1977 to 1984.  I am sure the Senators will have noticed that the language of section 2 mirrors the corresponding section of the Misuse of Drugs Act.  We must be legislatively and constitutionally certain that these two Acts, which purport to do the same thing and which have been brought forward to do the same thing, will not be in conflict with each other in their language, verbiage or words that are used.  The net effect of this section is not to alter the nature of the powers of search assigned customs officers since 1876 but rather to enable searches of meeters and greeters to be made.  As the law now stands, only travellers or persons suspected of an exportation offence may be searched by the customs officers.</P>
    <P>The question of the alteration of the nature of existing powers of search of travellers was considered in the course of the preparation of this Bill and has been further considered at my direct request by the Revenue Commissioners, the Departments of Health, Justice and Finance, with the advice of the Attorney General's office, and also in consultation with international customs services as a result of the thoughtful and concerned contributions of a large number of Senators during the Committee Stage.  I am advised that the Revenue Commissioners are satisfied with their present search procedures of travellers and that the Department of Health see no need to alter the nature of the powers of search provided under the Misuse of Drugs Acts, 1977 to 1984.</P>
    <P>I am not at all suggesting that Senators may be overstating the risk of stuffers and swallowers.  I would venture the opinion that stuffing and swallowing is inherently highly dangerous to the individual concerned, not to mention unpleasant, and a means which is naturally limited in terms of the volume of drugs which can be smuggled.  Hence, having regard to the location of the major drug producing regions &mdash; Colombia, Bolivia, the Golden <Col N="1457" /> Triangle and the Far East, for example &mdash; and the cost of travel, particularly air travel, the profitability of stuffing and swallowing is constrained in a way which more straightforward smuggling is not. Furthermore, random detention of travellers who may &mdash; and I want to emphasise the word &ldquo;may&rdquo;&mdash; be swallowers is hugely wasteful of customs resources, is unproductive and is greatly offensive to the travelling public.</P>
    <P>A crucial factor in successful drug detection is intelligence gathering, both domestically and internationally.  I am happy that where there are strong grounds to suspect smuggling by individual travellers the procedures at present operated by the customs service and the Garda are adequate and appropriate to the perceived scale of the problem. In all the circumstances, I would not at present wish to take the powers of detention set out in the amendment, which are incidentally not assigned to the Garda under the Misuse of Drugs Act, 1977 to 1984.  I want to assure the House that I do not underestimate the threat posed by the availability of drugs, particularly hard drugs, on our streets.  Let me further assure the House that, if extraordinary powers of detention are required to deal with the situation in the future, the Government will bring forward legislative proposals which will be adequate to the task.</P>
    <P>In the United Kingdom I understand that both the customs and the police can hold suspected stuffers and swallowers for 96 hours.  It is generally accepted that the minimum period of detention for a swallower is 48 hours.  In the present circumstances the Government do not wish to assign the powers of detention to customs officers until such time as the available evidence and professional advice considers such a draconian incursion into the rights of travellers is fully justified.</P>
    <P>I want to re-echo what I said: that we must allow flexibility to the customs officers to detain people for as long as is necessary.  We plead that we must give them the flexibility, that we should not be specific, that we understand the difficulties they encounter, that we must rely <Col N="1458" /> on their judgment to detain people, be they travellers or meeters and greeters, for as long as is necessary.  As far as we are concerned to be specific would be curtailing or constraining our officers in the execution of their duty.  We would say that in comparison to the British system, where people can be detained for up to 96 hours which is a huge period of time, it would be a terrible invasion of travellers' privacy and rights.  For these reasons I am confident that the laws we propose will be properly administered by the customs officers and that we should not constrain them.  We must allow them flexibility and I regret that I must oppose the amendment.</P>
    <Speaker pid="BrianMullooly" hpid="Acting Chairman (Mr. Mullooly) Acting Chairman (Mr. Mullooly)">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman (Mr. Mullooly)</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator Ferris has the right of reply.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelFerris" hpid="Mr. Ferris Mr. Ferris">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Ferris</NameTxt>
      <P>The source of these amendments, Nos. 3 and 7, would be the Criminal Justice Act, 1984.  We wanted to give the Minister the power that he is giving himself in the section.  He had left the wording in regard to time a little bit vague.  If he were designating specific times under the section, then the Bill should say so.  It is just a matter, as Senator Brendan Ryan said, of being as specific as possible, to make sure that the Act is not called into question at some future date by some smart Alec.  We want to ensure that the right powers are there. The source that I was using for that suggested power is in the Criminal Justice Act, 1984.  I accept that the Minister is satisfied on the advice available to him. The only way I can solicit that advice is by way of amendments because the advice is not available to me until I hear the Minister.  I take it that he has sought advice and got it.  I was using another piece of legislation, which was a strong piece of legislation, and I thought it was sufficient to justify the amendment.  I accept what the Minister says and I will have to wait and see and hope for the best.</P>
      <P>Amendment, by leave, withdrawn.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Acting Chairman Acting Chairman">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman</NameTxt>
      <P>Amendments Nos. <Col N="1459" /> 4 and 5 are alternatives.  Is there a proposer for amendment No. 4?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelFerris" hpid="Mr. Ferris Mr. Ferris">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Ferris</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 4:</P>
      <P>In page 4, line 3, after &ldquo;search&rdquo; to insert &ldquo;: provided that</P>
      <P>(A)  the officer conducting a search of a person being detained shall ensure, so far as practicable, that the person understands the reason for the search and that it is conducted with due respect for the person being searched;</P>
      <P>(B)  a person being detained shall not be searched by an officer or person (other than a designated medical practitioner) of the opposite sex;</P>
      <P>(C)  where a search of a person being detained involves removal of clothing, other than headgear or a coat, jacket, glove or similar article of clothing, no officer or person of the opposite sex shall be present unless either that person is a designated medical practitioner or the officer considers that the presence of that person is necessary by reason of the violent conduct of the person to be searched;</P>
      <P>(D)  a search of a person in custoday involving removal of underclothing shall be carried out by a designated medical practitioner.&rdquo;.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I think the amendment is not unreasonable and I sincerely hope that the Minister will respond accordingly.  I have been forthcoming on other amendments and the arguments the Minister made against them.  I accepted his opinion and advice, and I hope that he will accept these particular amendments, those in the names of the Labour Party Senators and Senator Bulbulia and Senator Manning providing that, in conducting a search of a person being detained, the officer shall ensure that as far as is practicable the person understands the reason for the search and that it is conducted with due respect for the person being searched.  At all times <Col N="1460" /> in legislation we must have regard for the rights of innocent people.  We take it that they are innocent until we prove that they are guilty.  In the area of searching people if the Customs and Excise officers are to be as diligent as this House wants them to be, we also want them to ensure that the vast majority of people coming in, apart from those that the officers have information on, are clean and innocent. If a Customs and Excise officer had any grounds to suspect otherwise, naturally we want to make sure that the person would be subjected to the proper search. I want the Minister by agreeing to this amendment to have regard to the fact that people have certain rights and rights of privacy as well as everything else.  Subparagraph (A) of the amendment suggests that in the searching there would be due respect for the person.  Subparagraph (B) provides that a person being detained shall not be searched by an officer or person, other than a designated medical practitioner, of the opposite sex.  We are now talking about bringing in drugs concealed in private parts of the body.  But people would be entitled to some common decency in the conduct of the search.  It is hoped that the search would be successful but I have to have regard to the fact that in the area of common decency at least they would be entitled to examination by somebody not of the opposite sex and certainly by a medical practitioner.</P>
    <P>Subparagraph (C) says:</P>
    <P>Where a search of a person being detained involves removal of clothing, other than headgear or a coat, jacket, gloves or similar article of clothing, no officer or person of the opposite sex shall be present unless either that person is a designated medical practitioner or the officer considers that the presence of that person is necessary by reason to the violent conduct of the person to be searched.</P>
    <P>I think that section speaks for itself.</P>
    <P>Subparagraph (D) also refers to clothing, particularly underclothing, and provides that removal of underclothing be <Col N="1461" /> carried out by a designated medical practitioner. All these subsections I am suggesting here after the word &ldquo;search&rdquo; are designed to have some regard for the individual.  I am particularly worried about innocent individuals who would be legitimately subjected to search in the course of the officer's duty but may not be guilty.  I hope that the Minister in his reply to this amendment would understand the reason I put it forward.  I would hope he would accept the reasonableness of the amendments and that it would be accepted that there would be common decency and courtesy shown by officers of the Customs and Excise at the points of entry whether port or airport.  I am just asking for special facilities and specially designated people.  I do not think that is unreasonable and I hope the House will agree.</P>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Acting Chairman Acting Chairman">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman</NameTxt>
      <P>Amendments Nos. 4 and 5 are being discussed together.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeOToole" hpid="Mr. J. O'Toole Mr. J. O'Toole">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J. O'Toole</NameTxt>
      <P>I was not aware that you were going to take amendments Nos. 4 and 5 together.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Acting Chairman Acting Chairman">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman</NameTxt>
      <P>I announced that amendments Nos. 4 and 5 are alternatives and amendment No. 5 can only be pressed if amendment No. 4 is withdrawn. They are being discussed together.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeOToole" hpid="Mr. J. O'Toole Mr. J. O'Toole">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J. O'Toole</NameTxt>
      <P>I am not objecting, Sir. The general thrust of both amendments is very vital to be included in the Bill for a number of reasons.  We have discussed this time and time again.  The objective of the Bill has been to put a stop to the importation of drugs, in particular, and how we go about this is important.  One thing that has been forgotten is the position of the actual customs officer on the ground.  The customs officer on the ground can only take a body search so far.  They do not have the expertise to search beyond a certain level.  It seems to me that one thing is absolutely certain: the question of somebody of the opposite <Col N="1462" /> sex not being present for close body searches is absolutely vital unless that person happens to be a medical practitioner.</P>
      <P>The customs officers say to me that they do not have the expertise for close body search, particularly in trying to identify people who have stuffed contraband into their bodies.  It seems to me that if that is the case, it is a job for a medical officer.  If it is a job for a medical officer the Bill must contain some reference as how a medical officer would be designated, how a medical officer would be reached and how, indeed, the person would be detained until such time as the medical officer arrived.</P>
      <P>From the point of view of the customs officers they would certainly prefer if this kind of search would be done and that it should not be done by themselves because they would not feel competent or ready to partake in such a form of search.  It is all very well to make the point that when somebody is fairly closely suspected, when there is hard information, that they may well have stuff in their body, that they can be held for a certain period.  But there is always the case where the customs officer might have a certain suspicion and would not feel that that suspicion would allow him to hold a person for a number of days but at the same time would feel that there was enough there to have the person searched.  That searching is the general area talked about here.  The search can only be conducted on certain very close conditions.</P>
      <P>The conditions we are talking about here are very reasonable: that there should be a medical officer and that where the removal of clothing is involved there should not be present a person of the opposite sex &mdash; in other words that there should be a back-up and support for the customs officer, that life should be made more difficult for the criminal and that persons' rights and dignity would be maintained and protected.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="KatherineBulbulia" hpid="Mrs. Bulbulia Mrs. Bulbulia">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Bulbulia</NameTxt>
      <P>In support of amendment No. 5, and indeed No. 4, I would like to say that for me this is a very contentious area and one that we spent a <Col N="1463" /> lot of time speaking about on Second Stage and, indeed, on Committee Stage we had an extended debate on it.</P>
      <P>The Minister, in justifying his use of the phrase &ldquo;with reasonable cause&rdquo; in the first amendment we considered today, cited that he felt that the words used in the legislation should be, and his phrase was &ldquo;in tandem with the language used in the Misuse of Drugs Act&rdquo; At a later point in our discussions this morning he talked about language mirroring the use of language in other legislation, in the Misuse of Drugs Act.  This insertion which is proposed in this amendment has as its source the regulations under the Criminal Justice Act, 1984 dealing with the treatment of persons in custody in Garda stations.  The logic of what I am saying in the light of what the Minister said about language mirroring the language in the Misuse of Drugs Act, is the same as that used by the Minister in that this insertion has as its source the regulations under the Criminal Justice Act. Therefore, it is a perfectly reasonable and logical wish to see this measure inserted into the legislation to give protection to anybody challenged by customs officers and, indeed, to afford a framework of protection for the Customs and Excise people who are put into this situation by virtue of the powers we are giving them in this legislation.</P>
      <P>Subparagraph (A) states:</P>
      <P>The officer conducting a search of a person being detained shall ensure, so far as practicable, that the person understands the reason for the search...</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>It is not inconceivable that the person being detained would be, in fact, a drug addict and might indeed be under the influence of a particular substance.  As such, his powers of understanding of what was happening to him would be limited. For that reason it is necessary to insert this provision to ensure that the person would understand, given the context of the legislation and the subject we are talking about and the difficulties which customs officers would have.  That is a <Col N="1464" /> very valid reason for ensuring that that type of insertion was made as a consequence of this amendment.  It also refers to the fact that the search should be conducted with due respect for the person being searched.  I have the height of praise for customs officers and I have made my views on that very clear in the course of the debate on Second Stage and Committee Stage.  Again, we are talking about human nature, we are talking about the weaknesses of human nature and we are talking about certain weaknesses which are worldwide and which crop up from time to time, particularly among uniformed people in authority.  I have no reason to feel that Irish Customs and Excise officers are totally immune from such human weaknesses.  Therefore, it is important to insert that the searches should be conducted with due respect for the person being searched.</P>
    <P>That is a decent, humane and civilised attitude to adopt in the course of the search.  Our legislation should reflect decent, humane and civilised attitudes of one human being to another in what is a very fraught, tense and difficult situation. We can only improve our legislation if we insert that type of provision.  Again, I would repeat that the source of this insertion is the regulations under the Criminal Justice Act, 1984.  As such, given the logic of that allied to what the Minister said in his justification for retaining his wording in the first amendment which we discussed on Report Stage, I am making a very strong argument in favour of the insertion of this particular provision.</P>
    <P>Subparagraph (B) states:</P>
    <P>A person being detained shall not be searched by an officer or person, other than a designated medical practitioner, of the opposite sex.</P>
    <P>Again, that to me is civilised, decent, correct and proper.  In an area of search it is appropriate that that type of provision should be in the legislation.  For that reason I am pressing this amendment.</P>
    <P>We talked very factually and openly about the way in which stuffers and swallowers bring in drugs.  We also talked <Col N="1465" /> about the necessity to examine body orifices and that cannot be done without the presence of a medical practitioner and, indeed, any search of the person should not have an officer or person of the opposite sex to the person being detained involved.  If this insertion is not accepted by the Minister, this legislation does not reflect the reality of the situation on the ground, as expanded on in the Committee on Crime, Lawlessness and Vandalism Report, and, indeed, by all search and observation which we brought to the Minister's attention which highlights this particular method of drug importation.</P>
    <P>The Minister in reply to another amendment talked about the limited amount of drugs being brought in by such stuffers and swallowers and the fact that it was hardly worth the candle in that it was unpleasant and distasteful and that the quantities involved would not be great.  Since I have not got the Minister's reply in front of me I am just going from memory.  He seemed to minimise that aspect of drug importation and seemed to say that the scarce resources of the Customs and Excise people could not be deployed in a lengthy follow-up of that particular form of importation.</P>
    <P>If the legislation is reflecting reality at all, it must take cognisance of that method of importation.  We have got to remember that we are dealing with people who are prepared to put up with the distasteful, unaesthetic and unpleasant methods involved in stuffing and swalling and who do not give a damn, in fact.  They must be gone after with the full rigours of the law within a framework such as is part of this subsection.  I am really pressing that the Minister should take on board this amendment.  I cannot understand how if he says, as he did state, that he had consultations with the Minister for Health, the Minister for Health did not see the absolute sanity and wholesomeness, decency and necessity of this amendment.  To me it is incontrovertible. I cannot understand why it is not being accepted.</P>
    <P>Subparagraph (C) talks about the search of the person being detained involving removal of clothing, other than <Col N="1466" /> headgear or a coat, jacket, glove or similar article of clothing, no officer or person of the opposite sex shall be present unless either that person is a doctor or the officer considers that the presence of that person is necessary by reason of the violent conduct of the person to be searched.  I do not think there is need for me to dwell on that as it is self-explanatory.</P>
    <P>Subparagraph (d) talks about the role of a designated medical practitioner.  To my way of thinking you cannot have the kind of body search that is necessary without having a panel of designated medical practitioners on stand-by in order to implement this legislation effectively and within an ethical framework.  Again, I cannot understand why the Minister, who seemed to take on board our arguments when we made them on Committee Stage and, indeed, on Second Stage, has not come forward himself with an amendment which reflects the legitimate concerns. He admits that they are legitimate and sincere and have been made in good faith by Senators.</P>
    <P>I waited every day coming up to this legislation to see the Minister's amendment. I was sure and confident &mdash; indeed, that is why I supported the recommittal motion &mdash; that the Minister would bring forward an amendment similar to this one which has been brought in by the Labour Party and Fine Gael.  I am quite honestly at a loss to understand why, if he has had the detailed consultations which he tells us he had, such an amendment was not brought in by the Minister.  It would give the Bill teeth.  It would reflect reality and it would deal with the very real practical arguments which Senators brought forward. Certainly on behalf of Fine Gael I will be pressing this amendment.</P>
    <Speaker pid="BrendanRyan" hpid="Mr. B. Ryan Mr. B. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. B. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>I think I heard the Minister say that one of the reasons he did not feel it necessary to introduce an amendment similar to this was that those who are described as the stuffers and swallowers would not be in a position to import large quantities of drugs.  He mentioned the cost of air fares and, therefore, implied that the risk involved relative to the expected gain would be so <Col N="1467" /> insignificant that it would not be worth people's while.  I think he said the Revenue Commissioners and various other agencies confirmed that to him.</P>
      <P>I left the House and checked from a source that for various reasons I shall not quote.  The Minister can argue with me and if he wishes I will pass him a note and tell him who to ask.  The officially accepted figure for the street sale of heroin is £300 per gramme.  That works out at about £30,000 for 100 grammes. One hundred grammes is approximately three ounces.  Is the Minister seriously suggesting that it is impossible to conceal three ounces of heroin in any of the orifices of the body?  Is he seriously suggesting that the possibility of £30,000 worth of sales of heroin will be deterred by the cost of an air fare from either South America or the Golden Triangle? I know the Minister said there would not be large quantities but the precise truth about drugs is that you do not need large quantities to make large amounts of money when you can sell three ounces for £30,000.  That is precisely why this most distasteful procedure, which flies in the face of all my own civil libertarian instincts and those of the Labour Party &mdash; I know Senator Bulbulia's record &mdash; must be confronted.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I find myself in an astonishing position that I have to ask again and again why a procedure cannot be accepted, which is quite clearly necessary, given as Senator O'Toole quite rightly said, that more people will die from the consequences of the inadequacies of legislation like this than died at Enniskillen on Sunday.  This is a threat to the lives of innocent people, the fact that people use these methods. We tolerate searches of this kind where there are likely to be breaches of security. I find it astonishing that we will not tolerate it in this case and I find it astonishing that a Government Minister would be so poorly advised by his advisers &mdash; the Minister bears no culpability in this; it is those who advised him &mdash; that that scale of profit from stuffing and swallowing was insufficient to promote it on a large scale. Those who gave him that advice, whether it be his ministerial colleagues or who <Col N="1468" /> else I do not know, but the realities are that three ounces of heroin will sell on the street for £30,000 and that is big bucks. Therefore, because the profits are so high and because the human consequences are so horrific, it is our duty to confront the problem and not walk away from it simply because it is distasteful or difficult.  That is why I support these amendments.</P>
    <Speaker pid="NoelTracey" hpid="Mr. N. Treacy Mr. N. Treacy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. N. Treacy</NameTxt>
      <P>I have listened with great interest to the sincere contributions of the four Senators, Ferris, O'Toole, Bulbulia and Ryan.  I recognise their very sincere passion to ensure that the maximum rigours of the law are applied and that the most effective wording possible is put into the Bill.  The Minister and his advisers seem to be castigated for not bringing forward amendments.  I personally feel, even though it is the prerogative of the Minister or the Government if they so wish to put forward amendments, it is the duty of the State or the duty of Government to bring forward a Bill and democracy should be allowed take over.  I acknowledge that in this House we have people who are very committed, dedicated and sincere and they have brought forward amendments. I am prepared to debate and discuss them and accept them if I can and reject others if I have to.  I think that is good, broad democracy, good, broad dialogue and debate in the interests of the people and I hope that in the end we can get the best consensus possible to deal with this terrible drug problem.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>First, subparagraphs (B) and (C) of amendment No. 4 &mdash; I am taking amendments Nos. 4 and 5 together &mdash; are incorporated in existing customs guidelines and I would be the first to propose such legislation if I thought it was necessary.  I have considered what Senators have said and I am giving it further thought as I speak to the House.  The stipulation in subparagraph (B) is already satisfactorily covered by section 185 of the Customs (Consolidation) Act, 1976, and section 2 of the Customs (Amendment) Act, 1942, which provide that a female may only be searched by an officer of the same sex. As regards subparagraph (D), it is not <Col N="1469" /> either Garda or customs service practice to carry out intrusive body searches, so the question of a medical practitioner being present does not arise.  We do not propose it at any time in this Bill and I will not be proposing it to the House. Searches involving the removal of underclothing already take place under the guidelines and legislation already referred to.  I might mention that there was an additional safeguard contained in the 1876 Act which provides in section 185 that, before any person is searched, he or she can ask to be taken before a justice, or before a senior official of customs who must determine whether reasonable cause for the search exists.  I want to emphasise again that we will not undertake intrusive body searches. Therefore, the necessity for a medical practitioner does not arise.</P>
    <P>Senator Bulbulia, Senator Ferris, Senator O'Toole and Senator Ryan made the point that a person must be told clearly why the search is taking place.  We respect that and we want to adhere to that.  It will be adhered to.  All people have to be told under law why they are being searched, arrested or whatever. That is always the case in all facets of law and in the implementation of law.</P>
    <P>Senator Bulbulia talked about a person understanding the reasons for the search. She talked about persons who may have taken drugs or may be carrying drugs on their person, particularly in their body, and the effect that they would have.  If Customs and Excise or the Garda found a person in any place, a port, inland, or whatever in that condition, medical treatment would be required preferably at a proper drug centre.  If these people were in that condition they would not understand the reasons for the search.</P>
    <P>I want to assure Senator Ryan that we are happy with the existing powers pertaining to detention.  I have given this matter the utmost consideration.  I compliment the people who put down these amendments.  I am happy to say to the House that I am prepared to accept subparagraph (A) of amendment No. 4, subparagraph (B) of amendment No. 4 to exclude the words inside the brackets <Col N="1470" />&ldquo;other than a designated medical practitioner&rdquo;, subparagraph (C) of amendment No. 4 in its entirety.  I cannot at all accept subparagraph (D).  I hope I have gone a long way to meeting the wishes and demands of Senators and to enshrining in the Bill the constrictions and constraints they want placed and the adherence requested.  I ask Senator Ferris to move that amendment again to exclude that subparagraph which I cannot accept.  I presume that acceptance of those parts of amendment No. 4 by me would be sufficient.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelFerris" hpid="Mr. Ferris Mr. Ferris">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Ferris</NameTxt>
      <P>I thank the Minister for his forthcoming response to what was a very considered amendment.  As Senator Bulbulia said, this amendment arises from existing regulations under the Criminal Justice Act, 1984, and they are precisely the words used in the regulations or guidelines which the Minister laid down. I welcome the fact that the Minister has conceded to the principle of this amendment in subparagraphs (A), (B) and (C). In amendment No. 4 (D) the Minister is saying that subparagraph (D) would not come into play at all because it is not the Minister's intention to carry out body searches by the removal of underclothing. That is exactly how it came across to me.  There would not be a need for a medical practitioner because the Minister did not intend to carry out this kind of searching.  That would concern us because we want that kind of searching to take place if necessary under the actual proper regulation.  If it happened, we would like it to come into play.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Because we are on Report Stage I want clarification on what the Minister said about subparagraph (D).  My interpretation was that he would not be proceeding with that type of searching based on his original comments that a lot of drugs are not brought in by stuffers and swallowers.  All the advice available to us is that it is believed by many people that a considerable amount of stuff can and could be brought in in that way.  Because of that factor we want to ensure that that source of illicit importation is not used. If a search is required under this Act we <Col N="1471" /> want to ensure that it is not brought in in this way; then, and only then, would subparagraph (D) come into play.  Please correct me if I am wrong &mdash; and I hope I am wrong in my interpretation of what the Minister said &mdash; because I want to ensure that every source of illicit importation will be tracked down by Customs and Excise, including this obnoxious way of doing it, which is used in a very widespread way by people in other countries and I am quite sure here as well.</P>
    <P>I know it is a risky way to do it and the people who are using this method are running the risk of losing their life.  The consequences for them, materially and financially, as outlined in graphic detail by Senator Ryan are an indication that we are worried that this method is used. We want to ensure that we can come to grips with it and do it properly.  Please forgive me if I misrepresented what the Minister said but I am worried that he now feels he will not be doing these things at an airport or on a ship.</P>
    <Speaker pid="NoelTracey" hpid="Mr. N. Treacy Mr. N. Treacy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. N. Treacy</NameTxt>
      <P>In response to Senator Ferris's request subparagraph (C) of amendment No. 4 covers the fact that only an officer or a person of the opposite sex can search another person.  We have taken everything into account.  We do not propose to have intrusive body searches, that is, searches of the orifices of the body.  At no stage in Irish legislation, at no stage in the implementation or the administration of law in this country by any arm of the State, the Garda, Army, customs officers or any other officers, has this type of search been carried out.</P>
      <P>Under the Constitution we recognise we must protect the rights of individuals and that they are entitled to their integrity, the integrity of the human person. We do not want to be in conflict with this. We also want to be consistent with the main thrust of Irish law as it stands today and the implementation of the laws of the land by various agencies of Government.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>We do not intend to have intrusive body searches.  Therefore there will be no necessity for a designated medical practitioner.  A simple example of an <Col N="1472" /> inspection and search by a female customs officer of a female person would be that the outer garments would be removed and, if necessary, all underclothing would be removed.  Only by visual inspection would detection be done.  There would be no more than that. That is the position as it pertains in Irish law today.  We want to be consistent in that, both in the thrust of the law and in the recognition of the constitutional rights of the individual.  Therefore I regret that I cannot accept subparagraph (D).  I have outlined as clearly as I can the exact position as it pertains at present in Irish law and as we envisage after the implementation and passage of this Bill.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JoeOToole" hpid="Mr. J. O'Toole Mr. J. O'Toole">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J. O'Toole</NameTxt>
      <P>Do I take it that subparagraphs (B) and (D) will be put separately to the House?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Acting Chairman Acting Chairman">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister has proposed an amendment to the amendment.</P>
      <P>Government Amendment to Amendment No. 4:</P>
      <P>In subparagraph B to delete &ldquo;(other than a designated medical practitioner)&rdquo;</P>
      <P>and to delete subparagraph D and substitute:</P>
      <P>(D) a search of a person may be carried out by a designated medical practitioner&rdquo;.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeOToole" hpid="Mr. J. O'Toole Mr. J. O'Toole">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J. O'Toole</NameTxt>
      <P>I understand what the Chair is saying.  We discussed amendments Nos. 4 and 5 together and one excludes the other as was rightly pointed out at the beginning.  May I take it that the Minister's amendment is now being put and that there are parts of amendment No. 5 which are not being put? Is amendment No. 5 still liable to be discussed further?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Acting Chairman Acting Chairman">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman</NameTxt>
      <P>The question is that the amendment to amendment No. 4 be made.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1473" />
    <Speaker pid="KatherineBulbulia" hpid="Mrs. Bulbulia Mrs. Bulbulia">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Bulbulia</NameTxt>
      <P>May I ask for a ruling please?  Since I am the proposer of amendment No. 5 I did not have an opportunity to reply.  I take it that although the two amendments were discussed together I still have an opportunity to reply.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Acting Chairman Acting Chairman">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman</NameTxt>
      <P>Sorry Senator, the position is that where two or more amendments are discussed together the right of reply rests with the mover of the first amendment.  Is the amendment to amendment No. 4 agreed?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelFerris" hpid="Mr. Ferris Mr. Ferris">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Ferris</NameTxt>
      <P>I want clarification that the Minister has now amended my amendment, if his amendment is carried.  I welcome the fact that the Minister has agreed to the majority of my amendments and I thank him.  Whichever way the vote goes, those amendments will be incorporated in the legislation because he is accepting them.  The only thing that worries me is that he is excluding body searches from the duties of Customs and Excise officers. We are of the opinion that drugs are getting in that way.  We welcome what the Minister is doing but he is not doing enough.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="NoelTracey" hpid="Mr. N. Treacy Mr. N. Treacy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. N. Treacy</NameTxt>
      <P>I want to re-emphasise and restate that intrusive body searches are not practised by any agency of the State.  It has never been done and we do not propose to do it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Acting Chairman Acting Chairman">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman</NameTxt>
      <P>The question is that the amendment&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeOToole" hpid="Mr. J. O'Toole Mr. J. O'Toole">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J. O'Toole</NameTxt>
      <P>I understood that such body searches took place in prisons.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Acting Chairman Acting Chairman">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman</NameTxt>
      <P>I must put the question&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeOToole" hpid="Mr. J. O'Toole Mr. J. O'Toole">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J. O'Toole</NameTxt>
      <P>We must base our decisions on the basis of fact and on the information that is available to us.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Acting Chairman Acting Chairman">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman</NameTxt>
      <P>I am going by Standing Orders.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1474" />
    <Speaker pid="NoelTracey" hpid="Mr. N. Treacy Mr. N. Treacy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. N. Treacy</NameTxt>
      <P>As far as I am concerned I am dealing with a customs and excise Bill.  I have the most up to date and expert advice available to me from all sections of the State and, indeed, outside the State.  We are not dealing with a Department of Justice Bill and if what Senator O'Toole alleges is not done I suggest that he should proceed to investigate it.  I know nothing of it and I have been absolutely assured that our system does not do this and does not allow this. I want to stick by that system.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Acting Chairman Acting Chairman">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman</NameTxt>
      <P>I must put the question.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="KatherineBulbulia" hpid="Mrs. Bulbulia Mrs. Bulbulia">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Bulbulia</NameTxt>
      <P>On a point of order, I would like an explanation.  I am happy that subparagraphs (A), (B) and (C) with minor modification have been accepted by the Minister but I oppose subparagraph (D).  As I see it this legislation, without the bodily search aspect, is making this country a haven for stuffers and swallowers.  How can I support subparagraphs (A), (B) and (C) and vote against subparagraph (D) if it is being taken as a whole?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelFerris" hpid="Mr. Ferris Mr. Ferris">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Ferris</NameTxt>
      <P>We want subparagraph (D) included.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="KatherineBulbulia" hpid="Mrs. Bulbulia Mrs. Bulbulia">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Bulbulia</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Acting Chairman Acting Chairman">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman</NameTxt>
      <P>The question is that the amendment to amendment No. 4 be made.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelFerris" hpid="Mr. Ferris Mr. Ferris">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Ferris</NameTxt>
      <P>I have to say níl because it excludes subparagraph (D) and I feel it should be included.  I accept the other amendments to my amendment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeOToole" hpid="Mr. J. O'Toole Mr. J. O'Toole">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J. O'Toole</NameTxt>
      <P>Will we be able to vote on amendment No. 5?  That is the point at issue.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Acting Chairman Acting Chairman">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman</NameTxt>
      <P>No.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeOToole" hpid="Mr. J. O'Toole Mr. J. O'Toole">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J. O'Toole</NameTxt>
      <P>You made it quite clear to us at the beginning that amendments Nos. 4 and 5 were being discussed together and that one excluded the other.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="1475" /> That made perfect sense at the time but when one is now amended we must also be able to look at amendment No. 5 and dispose of this business quickly.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelFerris" hpid="Mr. Ferris Mr. Ferris">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Ferris</NameTxt>
      <P>I understand that if the Minister's amendment to amendment No. 4 is carried, No. 5 will fall in total. For that reason subparagraph (D) would be excluded.  That is the only reason I am opposing the Minister's methods of accepting my amendment because he has not accepted it in total.  I want to thank the Minister for having come this far but I feel he should have gone the whole hog. Even if we do not use the system it would be a very important section to have.  In order to use that section in the future the Minister will need to bring another Bill before the House if we are to be effective.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Acting Chairman Acting Chairman">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman</NameTxt>
      <P>Just to clarify the position. If Amendment No. 4, as amended, is accepted amendment No. 5 cannot be moved.  My advice is that amendment No. 5 cannot be moved as it is an alternative. The question before the House is: is the amendment to amendment No. 4 agreed?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnHarte" hpid="Mr. Harte Mr. Harte">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Harte</NameTxt>
      <P>With your indulgence, Sir, it is important that we are clear on this. The fact is that if the Minister's amendment to the amendment is defeated then the full section stands the way it is at present, unamended.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Acting Chairman Acting Chairman">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman</NameTxt>
      <P>Amendment No. 4 as it is will then be put to the House.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="NoelTracey" hpid="Mr. N. Treacy Mr. N. Treacy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. N. Treacy</NameTxt>
      <P>I wish to reconsider what Senator Ferris said and I wish to respond if possible.  Senator O'Toole was out at the time.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeOToole" hpid="Mr. J. O'Toole Mr. J. O'Toole">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J. O'Toole</NameTxt>
      <P>I was listening.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1476" />
    <Speaker pid="NoelTracey" hpid="Mr. N. Treacy Mr. N. Treacy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. N. Treacy</NameTxt>
      <P>The Senator is very vigilant.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="A Senator A Senator">
      <NameTxt>A Senator</NameTxt>
      <P>That is our problem.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="NoelTracey" hpid="Mr. N. Treacy Mr. N. Treacy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. N. Treacy</NameTxt>
      <P>I enjoyed the contributions made.  It shows the interest there is in this legislation and indeed in all legislation.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelFerris" hpid="Mr. Ferris Mr. Ferris">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Ferris</NameTxt>
      <P>I thank the Minister.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="NoelTracey" hpid="Mr. N. Treacy Mr. N. Treacy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. N. Treacy</NameTxt>
      <P>As a result of what the Acting Chairman said and adhering to the rules of the House, the only offer I could make to amend any of the two amendments was on amendment No. 4 as that was the first amendment moved. I could not offer anything on amendment No. 5 until we disposed of amendment No. 4.  But in view of what Senator Ferris has said and in deference to the commitment and sincerity of requests which were made consistently on Committee Stage, and again today on Report Stage, I am prepared to further consider subparagraph (D) provided the Senators accept a clear amendment which would read as follows:</P>
      <P>A search of a person in custody may be carried out by a designated medical practitioner.</P>
      <P>I want to be clear on this.  The purpose of the amendment would be that if the customs officers feel it is necessary to have a search of the orifices of the body they have the flexibility to call a medical practitioner.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelFerris" hpid="Mr. Ferris Mr. Ferris">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Ferris</NameTxt>
      <P>Exactly, then and only then.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="NoelTracey" hpid="Mr. N. Treacy Mr. N. Treacy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. N. Treacy</NameTxt>
      <P>We do not want a situation again where people can say: &ldquo;My clothes were removed and there was no doctor present.&rdquo;  I want to be quite clear that the discretion of the custom officer, or officers, shall be such that if after the removal of all garments they feel it is necessary to have an inspection of the orifices of the body they may call a medical doctor to do so.  I am putting it to <Col N="1477" /> Senator Ferris to accept the amendment. I propose without voting if at all possible.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Acting Chairman Acting Chairman">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman</NameTxt>
      <P>Could I clarify the situation?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelFerris" hpid="Mr. Ferris Mr. Ferris">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Ferris</NameTxt>
      <P>There is a new amendment to the amendment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Acting Chairman Acting Chairman">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman</NameTxt>
      <P>There is a further amendment to amendment No. 4, sub-paragraph (D).  Subparagraph (D) will then read:</P>
      <P>A search of a person in custody may be carried out by a designated medical practitioner.</P>
      <P>I am putting the amendment&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnHarte" hpid="Mr. Harte Mr. Harte">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Harte</NameTxt>
      <P>The other amendment is made as well.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Acting Chairman Acting Chairman">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman</NameTxt>
      <P>The other amendment is made.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="NoelTracey" hpid="Mr. N. Treacy Mr. N. Treacy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. N. Treacy</NameTxt>
      <P>It is an amendment to the amendment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Acting Chairman Acting Chairman">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman</NameTxt>
      <P>I must&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelFerris" hpid="Mr. Ferris Mr. Ferris">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Ferris</NameTxt>
      <P>If it was possible to applaud in the Seanad for a confession by a Minister I would applaud.  I thank the Minister. He has met the wishes of this side of the House in total and in the way it should be done.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BrendanRyan" hpid="Mr. B. Ryan Mr. B. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. B. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>I want to be associated with that.  He has been more than reasonable. He deserves our congratulations and he is welcome to them.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="KatherineBulbulia" hpid="Mrs. Bulbulia Mrs. Bulbulia">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Bulbulia</NameTxt>
      <P>I would like to express my warm appreciation to the Minister for meeting us so fully on this measure and for taking on board so much of what was finally argued and presented to him.  We have seen at work here the process of legislation, a meeting of minds and a reasonable and conciliatory and intelligent response from the Minister.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFallon" hpid="Mr. Fallon Mr. Fallon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Fallon</NameTxt>
      <P>Very briefly, I would like to congratulate the Minister for meeting <Col N="1478" /> the wishes of this House.  There are very sincere people on the other side who went out of their way obviously to study this Bill in great depth.  I was impressed by the contributions by all Members but in particular by Senator Bulbulia who I felt was extremely sincere in expressing her case.  The Minister, I know, had problems too.  There were guidelines and other Acts which he felt were sufficient but he has now gone 99 per cent of the way to accommodate the wishes of all the Members of this House.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Acting Chairman Acting Chairman">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman</NameTxt>
      <P>I must conclude.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFallon" hpid="Mr. Fallon Mr. Fallon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Fallon</NameTxt>
      <P>It is now in the legislation and certainly I am glad of that.  I thank the Minister again.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="NoelTracey" hpid="Mr. N. Treacy Mr. N. Treacy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. N. Treacy</NameTxt>
      <P>Perhaps the Acting Chairman would re-read sub-paragraph (D) so that is will be quite clear.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Acting Chairman Acting Chairman">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman</NameTxt>
      <P>The full amendment to the amendment No. 4 is to delete &ldquo;(other than a designated medical practitioner)&rdquo; in subparagraph (B) and to amend subparagraph (D) to read: &ldquo;a search of a person in custody may be carried out by a designated medical practitioner.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="NoelTracey" hpid="Mr. N. Treacy Mr. N. Treacy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. N. Treacy</NameTxt>
      <P>There are two words I do not want inserted.  The words are &ldquo;in custody&rdquo;.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeOToole" hpid="Mr. J. O'Toole Mr. J. O'Toole">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J. O'Toole</NameTxt>
      <P>I welcome that amendment and congratulate the Minister on bringing it in.  It strengthens the Bill immeasurably; it makes a complete difference. In my discussions with the customs officers, they asked time and again to have included in the Bill that the person may be examined by a medical officer.  The words struck are exactly right because none of us wants it to be a requirement; none of us wants it to be a an inhibition.  I congratulate the Minister and I feel that this has been a good morning's work.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Acting Chairman Acting Chairman">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman</NameTxt>
      <P>I must now put the <Col N="1479" /> question.  Is the amendment to amendment No. 4 agreed?</P>
      <P>Amendment to amendment No. 4 agreed to.</P>
      <P>Amendment No. 4, as amended, agreed to.</P>
      <P>Amendment No. 5 not moved.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelFerris" hpid="Mr. Ferris Mr. Ferris">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Ferris</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 6:</P>
      <P>In page 4, between lines 19 and 20, to insert a new subsection as follows:</P>
      <P>&ldquo;(2) In the case of a complaint by any person arising from the operation of this section the Garda Síochána (Complaints) Act, 1986 shall apply to an officer of Customs and Excise as if he were a member of the Garda Síochána within the meaning of that Act and the provisions of that Act shall be construed accordingly&rdquo;.</P>
      <P>The Minister will remember that on Second Stage I wanted to ensure that the method of dealing with complaints against members of the security forces would be consistent.  I did not want Garda officers to be disadvantaged in that members of Customs and Excise would not be subjected to the same critical analysis for all their actions.  Recently, unfortunately, people have been quick to criticise members of the Garda Síochána and many of us have used every forum to defend them and compliment them on some of the acts they have been performing in very difficult circumstances. We must have regard to the fact that many members of the Garda Síochána feel constrained by the Garda Síochána (Complaints) Act.  They are extremely careful not to do anything which could lead to either a frivilous complaint or any other type of complaint against them.  In the performance of their duties they have this Act in the back of their minds.  Many of us were involved in enacting that Act and passed various comments on it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I want to make sure that the first line of defence at the port of entry is the <Col N="1480" /> Customs and Excise officer, they should also feel constrained by the complaints Act, not because I want a softly softly approach to anybody found guilty of the importation of drugs but because I do not want one section of our security forces at a disadvantage by being subject to different regulations.  I hope there is no reason why the Minister cannot accept this amendment to remove any ambiguity there might be in the minds of the members of the Garda Síochána.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JohnHarte" hpid="Mr. Harte Mr. Harte">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Harte</NameTxt>
      <P>I support that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeOToole" hpid="Mr. J. O'Toole Mr. J. O'Toole">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J. O'Toole</NameTxt>
      <P>I have a difficulty with this amendment.  I certainly believe in accountability and that people should be answerable and responsible for their actions.  I have not had time to study it but as far as I am aware gardaí had some input and were consulted about the setting up of the complaints board to investigate complaints against the Garda.  The customs officers had no such contact and I would be slow to set up a structure like this, to which a group would be answerable, if they had not consulted in the first place.</P>
      <P>State workers should be cleaner than clean and should be absolutely responsible and accountable for their actions. That is not my reason for objecting but in such circumstances there should be clear consultation with the group.  We cannot superimpose the problems or the accountability of one group on another body just because it happens to be there.  I do not feel I can support this amendment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFallon" hpid="Mr. Fallon Mr. Fallon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Fallon</NameTxt>
      <P>It seems to me that in many ways the Senator is equating customs officers with gardaí in some respects. That would obviously be incorrect.  Perhaps the Minister, when replying, will comment on that.  That would be my reading of the amendment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="KatherineBulbulia" hpid="Mrs. Bulbulia Mrs. Bulbulia">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Bulbulia</NameTxt>
      <P>I support this amendment and, indeed, my name is appended to it.  It is in line with my thinking of civil liberties and protection of the individual when faced with the institutions and powers of the State.  It is very important <Col N="1481" /> that a member of the public should have redress and should have a forum to direct his complaint or grievance to it he is apprehended under this legislation.  If we found it necessary in the context of the criminal justice Bill to establish a Garda Síochána Complaints Tribunal, when we are giving the extended powers to the Customs and Excise people, and indeed they have elaborate and extensive powers as matters stand, it is only reasonable to put in a concomitant safeguard for the members of the general public so that they can feel they have an area, if they require redress against an action of the Customs and Excise people.  I support this amendment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnHarte" hpid="Mr. Harte Mr. Harte">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Harte</NameTxt>
      <P>Having listened to Senator O'Toole, I am quite clear in my own mind with regard to the question of the principle of redress.  I also feel very strong about the idea of prior consultation and discussion, not necessarily agreement.  In that context if the Minister could find it possible to provide either by ministerial order, or something else, that something could be done in the matter of the right of redress for people who might be detained by customs officers at any particular time, or, if he could indicate to us any section of the Bill that takes care of that, that would solve the problem; but I do not think there is any such section in the Bill.  I have mixed feelings about it.  I believe there should be the right of redress and, as I said earlier, I feel very strongly that people should be consulted before anything is implemented that would have an adverse effect on them. Could the Minister give some indication that he would make some arrangement, either by ministerial order or some other way, so that people who may be detained could have the right of redress?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="NoelTracey" hpid="Mr. N. Treacy Mr. N. Treacy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. N. Treacy</NameTxt>
      <P>I appreciate the concern and sincerity of Senators that there should be adequate redress afforded to the aggrieved traveller as well as the meeter and the greeter.  The Garda have more extensive powers than customs officers.  They perform a different job, which is much more complex and much <Col N="1482" /> more wide ranging.  Customs officers have specific duties to perform in very specific areas of operation within our country.  Therefore, the operation of those powers by the Garda is naturally subject to more checks.  Customs officers have had powers of search and detention for over a century and they have used those powers responsibly.  The effect of this legislation is to extend these powers to cover meeters and greeters and, as such, is not a significant departure from the present position.</P>
      <P>People can make complaints to the Garda Complaints Board because the range of duties and powers vested in the Garda Síochána under several Acts is much more wide ranging and much broader than that envisaged or that given to the Customs and Excise section of the State over the years, or indeed than that we propose now.  However, any person who has a complaint against an officer of the Customs and Excise can complain, first, to a superior officer; secondly, to the Revenue Commissioners; thirdly, to the Ombudsman and, fourthly, to the courts.  I am satisfied that these safeguards are adequate and require no amendment at this stage.  I want to assure the House that if this situation should change the Government will move quickly to tighten up and extend the safeguards as necessary.</P>
      <P>The amendment as proposed is also technically deficient in that it would not be possible to simply treat a customs officer as a member of the Garda Síochána for the purposes of applying the Garda Síochána (Complaints) Act, 1986. It would require a much more complex and comprehensive amendment to the Garda Síochána (Complaints) Act, 1986, and possibly to other legislation if we were to extend the provisions of the 1986 Act to customs officers.  Therefore, I regret I have to oppose this amendment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelFerris" hpid="Mr. Ferris Mr. Ferris">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Ferris</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister has gone down some way of the road to met us.  I take the point made by Senator O'Toole that there was no way we wanted to impose this section without discussion with the Customs and Excise officers, <Col N="1483" /> because that is what we did with the Garda Síochána.  When we brought in the Bill we gave an assurancce that it would not come into operation until the Garda Complaints Board Act was also passed. Now that the Minister has defined the difference between the extended role of the Customs and Excise officer and the Garda Síochána, the Garda might be satisfied that there is a fundamental difference. They felt disadvantaged that in certain areas, there was a similarity about their role and their function, and while one area of the security forces was subjected to a critical analysis under the complaints legislation another area was not. The Minister might lay down a set of guidelines or regulations for officers in the Customs and Excise force under which they would act.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="NoelTracey" hpid="Mr. N. Treacy Mr. N. Treacy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. N. Treacy</NameTxt>
      <P>Guidelines already exist, but we could update them.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelFerris" hpid="Mr. Ferris Mr. Ferris">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Ferris</NameTxt>
      <P>If a code of conduct were laid down we would be satisfied.  If the Government feel at any time that the Minister should act quicker and more strongly than is suggested in my amendment, I would accept that, and that will be on the record of the House.  The Minister has said that regulations already exist, but if he could set out a code of conduct I would be satisfied and he would have met what I am trying to deal with in my amendment.  I will give the Minister's assurance to the members of the Garda Síochána with whom I have already had discussions that there is a distinct difference between their role and function and that of the Customs and Excise officers.</P>
      <P>Amendment, by leave, withdrawn.</P>
      <P>Amendment No. 7 not moved.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Amendments Nos. 8, 9 and 10 are related and may be discussed together.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelFerris" hpid="Mr. Ferris Mr. Ferris">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Ferris</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 8:</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="1484" /> In page 4, lines 22 and 23, to delete &ldquo;or to such other place as may be specified by the officer&rdquo;.</P>
    <P>This amendment was tabled for obvious reasons, which can be seen from reading the full section as amended.</P>
    <P>In amendment No. 9 we are trying to insert after the word &ldquo;Office&rdquo; the words &ldquo;provided that a person shall be detained only in an Office which has facilities to enable him to be treated in accordance with the provisions of this section and with due and proper respect for his person and right to privacy&rdquo;.  That would be consequential on our agreement to the Minister's amendment to our amendments. Now that the Minister has met us on the other amendments, it is not unreasonable to have a proper place set aside at the area of importation, or of the breaking of the law, where a proper examination in accordance with the Customs and Excise officer's opinion could be carried out.  That is the substance of what I am trying to do.  Now that the Minister has conceded the other amendments, he will have no problem conceding these.  It is probably the intention to have proper facilities available, or perhaps they already exist, but this examination should not be carried out at the passport counter or in the area where baggage is claimed.  I want that to be done properly I am sure the Customs and Excise officer will have a proper office in which to talk to people, to examine them and to carry out whatever he considers necessary in accordance with the Act.</P>
    <Speaker pid="KatherineBulbulia" hpid="Mrs. Bulbulia Mrs. Bulbulia">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Bulbulia</NameTxt>
      <P>I support this amendment. I am confident the Minister will yield on these amendments because they are about standards &mdash; standards of decency in a person to person situation. We know that at many of our ports and airports facilities are not necessarily all that we desire and there is a danger that in some very small out of the way areas where a person is apprehended, such a meeting between a customs officer and a suspect would take place in a sort of shack out the back which might be insanitary, <Col N="1485" /> draughty, miserable and totally inadequate. It is to bring about a proper standard that we propose amendment No. 9.</P>
      <P>In relation to the Minister's reference to language in this legislation mirroring language in other legislation, in amendment No. 9 the source of the insertion is similar to the regulations under the Criminal Justice Act, 1984, dealing with the treatment of persons in custody in a Garda station.  To my way of thinking, it is entirely logical that the treatment of persons by Customs and Excise officers should be identical to that meted out to people in custody in a Garda station. The standards and the facilities should be appropriate to the situation.  That is why I support amendment No. 8, but to my way of thinking, it is a bit too loosely worded.  The insertion in amendment No. 9 sets out the sort of standards and parameters within which such a meeting should take place.  Accordingly, I support these three amendments which have been discussed together.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeOToole" hpid="Mr. J. O'Toole Mr. J. O'Toole">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J. O'Toole</NameTxt>
      <P>I listened to the two Senators and I agree with everything they said but I am not convinced that any of the amendments meets the point they make.  The phrase &ldquo;to such other place&rdquo; is loose.  If a traveller is detained at an airport on suspicion of carrying drugs or whatever, it might be in his best interests not to be taken as far as the customs office.  I was looking very closely at this when I was researching the legislation.  I have before me the British Police and Criminal Evidence Act, 1984, and the codes of practice which have also been applied to the customs officers in Britain. I will read two short sections.  First, regarding the conduct of a search:</P>
      <P>Every reasonable effort must be made to reduce to the minimum the embarrassment the person being searched may experience.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>That is the first point being put by the proposer and seconder and I do not think the Minister or anybody else would disagree with that.  The British Act goes on to say that searches in public must be restricted to a superficial examination <Col N="1486" /> and that if there is anything more than the taking off of a coat or a jacket or gloves, even if it is simply taking off head gear, that must take place in private.  I would like that to be taken on board in the Bill.  I think this amendment intends that a person's privacy will be respected and that any traveller, or any meeter or greeter, need not be embarrassed more than is absolutely necessary &mdash; it should not be necessary to embarrass them at all in public.  I agree with that thinking. Could the Minister tell us what would happen in an airport, where the searches would take place &mdash; we are not talking about the full medical examination but a close body search &mdash; and how they would take place?  The idea of a search in a public place, even if the public place is empty, would be totally unacceptable to me.  I agree with the spirit of the amendment, but I do not think the amendment as phrased meets the point.</P>
    <Speaker pid="NoelTracey" hpid="Mr. N. Treacy Mr. N. Treacy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. N. Treacy</NameTxt>
      <P>I will respond to the three amendments together.  I appreciate the complex points which have been made by the various Senators.  In the majority of cases, a suspect would be brought to a customs office, but in certain circumstances it may be deemed desirable to bring such a person to a Garda station, or perhaps to a hospital, or to some other location.  In all cases, and at whatever location a person is being searched, he or she is treated with due care and with proper respect under strict guidelines laid down by the Revenue Commissioners for Customs and Excise officers.  I am satisfied that the present procedures in relation to searches are operated in a careful and sympathetic manner by Customs and Excise officers. I listened with great interest to the many points that have been made but I feel that, if we were to accept any of these amendments, we would be constraining the customs officers in the execution of their duties.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I will take a number of examples.  Let us consider a chartered plane coming into Dublin Airport.  The normal daily work and routine of the airport go on and customs officers are doing their normal <Col N="1487" /> work.  There could be five, ten, 15, 20 or 30 people on that plane carrying drugs, or maybe assisting with the carriage or distribution of drugs.  Flexibility must be left to the customs officers so that, if they wish at any time, they can take those people to an Aer Rianta office, or an Aer Lingus office, or bring in a mobile office and so on.  If a ship or boat is landing at a private location the customs officers must not be constrained from administrating the full rigours of the law.  They must have flexibility to take these people to a Garda station, a Government office, a State agency office, or a State agency department, whatever is near to them.  A yacht pulling into our shores would create an opportunity for people to get off quickly, take drugs on land, and drive off in a mechanically propelled vehicle &mdash; a bus, a motor car, a van, or whatever.  We cannot constrain customs officers as to where they should search those people. There must be flexibility.</P>
    <P>I want to assure the House, and reassure the House, that searches have always been carried out in strict privacy and always in the officially designated offices in the Customs and Excise premises at the various ports and airports.  I suggest that it is in the best interests of our people and in the proper detection of drug smuggling into our country, that we must give the Customs and Excise officers this flexibility.  Therefore, I sincerely regret that I have to oppose all these amendments.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelFerris" hpid="Mr. Ferris Mr. Ferris">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Ferris</NameTxt>
      <P>I accept the Minister's assurance that there will always be an element of privacy when people are searched or interrogated.  I was concerned that at least there would be an element of privacy if all the other sections came into play.  The Minister has assured me that that will take place.  Our amendment did not exclude the right to remove these people to a Garda station, where there would be an office with the proper facilities, or a hospital.  I would not rule out moving them anywhere that was necessary, provided the facilities are there, that the suspects' rights to privacy <Col N="1488" /> are protected and that the Customs and Excise officer is assisted in the proper performance of his duty, not using some corner where there might be a curtain pulled across and the person involved could be seen by other people because of this lack of privacy.  This procedure should apply to everyone who comes into this country whether they come by chartered plane or any other way.</P>
      <P>As Senator Bulbulia mentioned, we should try to apply a certain standard in this area.  If we have high standards we will have the full co-operation of the Customs and Excise officers but we also want to ensure that the rights and the privacy of individuals, who might eventually be found to be innocent, are protected.  That is the only reason I wanted to define that an office should be clean and capable of providing the facilities we address in other sections.  I do not want to constrain the Minister but I want his assurance that he will provide the facilities I am looking for.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="NoelTracey" hpid="Mr. N. Treacy Mr. N. Treacy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. N. Treacy</NameTxt>
      <P>They are already there.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelFerris" hpid="Mr. Ferris Mr. Ferris">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Ferris</NameTxt>
      <P>I accept that.</P>
      <P>Amendment, by leave, withdrawn.</P>
      <P>Amendments Nos. 9 and 10 not moved.</P>
      <P>Debate adjourned.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Business" RHead="of Seanad">
    <Title>Business of Seanad.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="MickLanigan" hpid="Mr. Lanigan Mr. Lanigan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lanigan</NameTxt>
      <P>I understand that the Leas-Chathaoirleach has to leave the House from 2.45 p.m. today.  I, accordingly, move that Senator Martin J. O'Toole be appointed as Cathaoirleach in the absence of the Leas-Chathaoirleach and the Cathaoirleach.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeOToole" hpid="Mr. J. O'Toole Mr. J. O'Toole">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J. O'Toole</NameTxt>
      <P>I formally second that with some regard that my blood relation should aspire to such high office.  It gives <Col N="1489" /> me great pleasure to be the one to second him to that position.</P>
      <P>Agreed.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Customs and Excise (Miscellaneous Provisions) (No. 2)" RHead="Bill, 1987: Report Stage (Resumed) and Final Stage">
    <Title>Customs and Excise (Miscellaneous Provisions) (No. 2) Bill, 1987: Report Stage (Resumed) and Final Stage.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Amendments Nos. 11 and 12 are alternatives and may be discussed together.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelFerris" hpid="Mr. Ferris Mr. Ferris">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Ferris</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 11:</P>
      <P>In page 4, between lines 24 and 25, to insert a new paragraph as follows:</P>
      <P>&ldquo;(b)  Where a person has been brought to a Customs Office an officer of Customs and Excise may at his discretion require the said person either to be subject to X-ray examination or to permit a designated medical practitioner to take from the person a specimen of his blood or, at the option of the person, to provide for the designated medical practitioner a specimen of the person's urine: provided that such person may opt for either of the said tests to be carried out at any time during his detention and the results of such test or tests, as the case may be, shall be taken as conclusive proof for the purposes of establishing that there are no longer reasonable grounds for detention under subsection (3).&rdquo;.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I am leaving it to the discretion of the Customs and Excise officer whether to use an X-ray in the performance of his duty.  This is not unreasonable in view of the fact that the Minister said that if all the other examinations take place, and if they do not produce the desired effect, particularly as it affects those who conceal drugs by swallowing, an X-ray might be desirable.  If there were grounds for suspicion and the Customs and Excise officer so desired it, it is appropriate that he would be able to subject a person to an X-ray.  I want to strengthen the power <Col N="1490" /> of the officers and make sure the facilities are written into the Bill</P>
    <Speaker pid="JohnHarte" hpid="Mr. Harte Mr. Harte">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Harte</NameTxt>
      <P>I support the amendment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="KatherineBulbulia" hpid="Mrs. Bulbulia Mrs. Bulbulia">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Bulbulia</NameTxt>
      <P>I wish to speak on amendment No. 12 which excludes the X-ray examination provision.  I would be happier if such a provision was not part of the tests which could be visited on a suspect by the Customs and Excise people as a consequence of their apprehension. There are cases where the use of an X-ray could be injurious and inadvisable, for example, a pregnant woman who was suspected of smuggling drugs by ingestion or insertion should not be subject to X-ray examination.  The whole matter of X-ray examination is fraught with possible difficulty and danger.  For that reason I would not support any inclusion of such a measure in the legislation. It is perfectly reasonable, however, to include all the other provisions. They would be helpful in the determination of guilt and, as such it is necessary to include them in the legislation. Advances have been made, and will continue to be made, in the area of ascertaining whether substances have been taken by people.  It is important that legislation should reflect the possibilities of such detection.  Apart from the X-ray examination facility in that amendment, I am proposing amendment No. 12 as being the more desirable of the two alternatives.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeOToole" hpid="Mr. J. O'Toole Mr. J. O'Toole">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J. O'Toole</NameTxt>
      <P>What I have to say will not surprise anybody because I have said it <i>ad nauseam.</i>  Since our last discussion, I had discussions with customs officers and with people from the investigation branch.  There is no doubt but that they need the extra powers.  We have done a good morning's work in covering one of those areas.  The Minister has to be congratulated on that.  It is something that will be well received in all places.  That covers people who stuff contraband into body orifices.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>We are now dealing with those people who smuggle drugs by swallowing into their bodies.  We carried out a check this <Col N="1491" /> morning on the actual cost of a pound of raw heroin.  It would be quite simple for somebody to take a half pound of heroin inside their body.  The amount of money involved is enormous and makes the risk very worth while.  There is a huge temptation for people to take heroin particularly into the country in this way.  I have spoken to people from the Drug Squad who are still of the view that most of the heroin which comes into Ireland comes in in this form.  When I spoke here last I think I gave the impression that most of the drugs brought into this country come in the body.  I said that at the end of the discussion and I did not get a chance to put the record right.  I was talking about the very hard drugs, and almost exclusively heroin.</P>
    <P>A person can easily take a half pound of heroin inside their body.  We are talking about £70,000 or £80,000 which is the street value of that amount of drug.  We are trying to close certain avenues.  We have covered the area of meeters and greeters.  The Minister has also given the customs officers the necessary powers and those people who smuggle drugs into this country by swallowing them are covered in this Bill.  There are three proposals put forward here &mdash; X-ray, blood test, the urine test as proposed by Senator Ferris, and the blood and urine test as proposed by Senator Bulbulia.  I do not know the value of a blood test.  I am not competent to speak on that and I am not sure that it can be helpful here but there could be developments which I am not aware of.  I seek the Minister's response to that.  I do know that X-ray is important and can show up any irregular substance carried in the body.  I also recognise that X-ray can be dangerous to some people. I have a slight problem with the idea of an X-ray, because it could actually lead to difficulties later if people claimed they did not have a choice.  I would go along with the idea that X-ray as an option might still be considered.</P>
    <P>I am speaking to amendment No. 12 when I say specifically that the urine test has been proven in many different countries as something that will show up and <Col N="1492" /> identify the smallest trace elements within the body.  It is the single most effective technological development in the area of detection.  Since our last discussion I have made inquiries as to what is happening in other countries.  I am aware that the majority of countries only have this as an option but I have also spoken to customs authorities in other countries and they said quite clearly that they would feel that, assuming there are reasonable grounds for suspicion &mdash; we are talking here about more lives per year than the number of people who died in Enniskillen last Sunday &mdash; it is a problem on an even bigger scale than this.</P>
    <P>To the Minister's credit, he has brought this Bill this far.  I would ask him to see what he can do with this section.  I would ask him particularly to address himself to the question of the urine test.  I know his Department have invested in the machines for urine testing even though they are not being used yet and I think everybody is in agreement about their value.  There is no doubt about that, so we are not arguing about it.  What we are saying is that rather than have somebody in detention for days or hours on end, this would be a way that would sort out the difficulties straight away.  Either we bring in legislation to make it compulsory for a person to give a urine sample or else have it written into legislation that the refusal to do so would be used as evidence or would be part of evidence and would be seen almost as an admission of guilt. I think the last one is too cumbersome.  I would certainly go for what is here, that they should be required to give a urine test.</P>
    <P>By taking this step here this morning we could literally closedown one of the bigger avenues of heroin importation to this city.  I am not saying it would stop it, nothing will ever stop it.  No customs legislation will ever stop the drugs problem but this is one area of it.  The area of supply has to be cut down and we are talking about the supply here.  I am certain from discussions with customs officers, with the investigations branch and also with the Drugs Squad of the <Col N="1493" /> Garda Síochána that it would be of great benefit and great use to them if the Minister could work his way towards taking these amendments on board.</P>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFallon" hpid="Mr. Fallon Mr. Fallon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Fallon</NameTxt>
      <P>I must confess I share the concern of Senator Bulbulia and other Senators on the question of X-rays because for obvious reasons it would be preferable if they were used in medical spheres rather than what is envisaged in this Bill.  Going back to the other aspects, I would pose a question to the Minister. I am of the opinion that if the customs officers felt that X-ray equipment was necessary whether for urine testing or blood samples or in any other area it would have been on board long before now.  The point I am making is that these areas can be problem areas for customs officers.  Having made that point, I would like to say that if they think it is necessary then they should have it if that is what they want.  I invite comments from the Minister in that area.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="NoelTracey" hpid="Minister of State at the Department of Finance (Mr. N. Treacy) Noel Treacy">
      <NameTxt>Minister of State at the Department of Finance (Mr. N. Treacy)</NameTxt>
      <P>Is soiléir go bhfuil an-spéis as gach éinne anseo san mBille seo agus go háirithe san leasú seo agus gach aon alt den Bhille freisin.</P>
      <P>I have considerable difficulty with amendment No. 11 which seeks to assign discretionary powers to customs officers to X-ray individuals.  I have to admit that and I want to try and balance all the viewpoints, pro X-ray and against X-ray. Those of us who are concerned about the dangers posed by Sellafield are aware that such radiation is potentially very injurious to health and ought not to be administered except for purposes of medical diagnosis.  As I indicated to the House on Committee Stage the customs service has equipment capable of detecting the presence of drugs in urine, that is the EMIT equipment.  We are awaiting its delivery and as soon as it comes we will be putting it into use.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I would not wish to introduce precipitative legislation hinging on the reliability of this equipment before it can be thoroughly evaluated.  It will be used on a voluntary basis and if it is used in the field, so to speak, and if evaluation <Col N="1494" /> tests warrant it, I will give consideration to a measure along the lines suggested by this amendment.  I must, however, say that blood and urine tests are problematical in that they can detect the present of morphine or cocaine-based medications legitimately present in a traveller's system.  Recent information from the United Kingdom indicates a degree of disappointment with the overall efficiency of the urine test.  Furthermore, such tests obviously cannot detect drugs concealed by a traveller in his clothing or luggage.  For this reason alone a negative test, as the amendment proposes, cannot be accepted as proof positive of innocence either.</P>
    <P>I hope I have covered all the points. We feel we have gone as far as we can go.  We are giving the voluntary opportunity for the EMIT test.  We are awaiting the delivery of the equipment and it will be used voluntarily on arrival.  We believe that at this stage we could not, in any circumstances, use X-ray equipment.  It would be too injurious to health and it would be too risky from every point of view.  Consequently, I sincerely regret I am unable to accept these amendments.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelFerris" hpid="Mr. Ferris Mr. Ferris">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Ferris</NameTxt>
      <P>I was not unmindful when I put down the wording in amendment No. 11 of the consequences of X-ray and some people's views on it.  I think the medical evidence would substantiate the view that has been expressed by Senator Bulbulia.  I put down in the amendment the word &ldquo;may&rdquo; and I was allowing it at the discretion of the customs officer. Naturally if a pregnant person who swallowed four of five ounces or half a pound of cocaine was worried about the pregnancy and she communicated this worry to the customs and excise officer, he could use his discretion as to whether an X-ray was the appropriate diagnostic instrument to use.  In other sections there are the rights of examination and internal body searches and so on but also under this amendment a person could opt for or against an X-ray, could opt for or against a blood test, because they might be haemophiliac, or they could opt for or against the urine test.  It left a certain <Col N="1495" /> amount of discretion to the person being examined or detained and to the customs and excise officer.  I accept that the Minister in some voluntary kind of way is going to bring in this.</P>
      <P>There is no doubt in any of our minds, and it has been confirmed by Senator O'Toole in discussions with Customs and Excise officers, that they need additional powers in this area of testing if their work is going to bear fruit.  This is what this legislation is about.  I was satisfied that we could legislate with a certain amount of discretion and giving options to the person in detention, having regard all the time to the fact that persons who were innocent would have no problem whatsoever in giving their consent to any of these tests.  An innocent person who was pregnant could, in fact, say to the customs officer: &ldquo;I am pregnant&rdquo;, and of course we have ultra sound now to diagnose pregnancy.  There is a widespread use of X-ray and other detection facilities at airports for luggage and for people walking through particular doorways. You have a whole lot of facilities in existence already.</P>
      <P>This was not making it obligatory on anybody but was allowing the Customs and Excise officer some discretion.  I do not think that was an unreasonable section to ask the Minister to put in, certainly in view of what Senator O'Toole has just said.  It is important that the officers to whom we are giving additional powers would feel that we were giving them powers that were necessary.  I hope the Minister will look at what we are trying to do here.  At any time that he feels additional powers are required by way of regulation or otherwise, he will have the fullest support of the Members of this House from all sides in bringing it in.  If his power of regulation does not confer these rights on him, then I think it should confer them on him.  That is what I wanted to do and I wanted to have regard for the reservations people have about X-rays and so on.  I felt I had covered that particular point.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeOToole" hpid="Mr. J. O'Toole Mr. J. O'Toole">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J. O'Toole</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister referred <Col N="1496" /> to one point of which I was not aware, and I freely admit it, and that was that there seems to be evidence coming from the British side that it is not as effective as we were led to believe it to be in the beginning.  If that is the case and obviously I take the Minister's word for it if he has this evidence, it would be unwise to make it a compulsory requirement. That would be bad law.  Perhaps the way to do it is to introduce it, to continue with it and to assess it after a while.  The National Drugs Abuse Coordinating Committee would take an interest in it and I will certainly raise it at that forum, perhaps in six months time.</P>
      <P>Amendment, by leave, withdrawn.</P>
      <P>Amendment No. 12 not moved.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelFerris" hpid="Mr. Ferris Mr. Ferris">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Ferris</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 13:</P>
      <P>In page 4, between lines 42 and 43, to insert a new subsection as follows:</P>
      <P>&ldquo;(3)  If at any time during the detention of a person pursuant to this section there are no longer reasonable grounds for detention under this section, he shall be released from detention forthwith unless his detention is authorised apart from this Act.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>This is to protect the individual.  There are other Acts which give us widespread powers, the Offences Against the State Act and other Acts which are used regularly if there is any area of doubt about trying to detain somebody where conclusive evidence might not be readily available within the prescribed period of hours set down by legislation.  Apart from the widespread powers under the Prevention of Terrorism Act under which an officer would have certain powers to continue to detain a person I would not like an innocent person to be unduly detained if there were no grounds or no proof, if all the tests have proved negative and if the information that people had got was not up to standard.  A genuinely <Col N="1497" /> innocent person should not be kept for longer periods unless there are good grounds for doing so.  It is a reasonable section to include in the Bill in a progressive country where we have legislation dealing with people's rights as well as ensuring the security of the State and ensuring that innocent people are protected from people who import drugs illicity.</P>
    <Speaker pid="KatherineBulbulia" hpid="Mrs. Bulbulia Mrs. Bulbulia">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Bulbulia</NameTxt>
      <P>I second the amendment. It proposes a reasonable and sensible provision.  It is the sort of measure that is contained in the Criminal Justice Act, 1984.  It is a safeguard of the civil liberties of an individual.  It seems to me to be a logical provision and as such I second it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="NoelTracey" hpid="Mr. N. Treacy Mr. N. Treacy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. N. Treacy</NameTxt>
      <P>I have listened to the arguments put forward by Senators Ferris and Bulbulia and I accept the sincerity of the sentiments they have expressed. However, I want to state that section 2 merely provides for powers of search rather than detention.  I would emphasise that its net effect will be to enable customs officers to search meeters and greeters at airports, ports and land frontier.  At present the customs service has powers of personal search only in respect of travellers or in respect of persons genuinely suspected of an exportation offence.  Powers of search of travellers have existed without the need for a statutory safeguard in the terms of amendment No. 13 for more than a century, going back to the 1876 Act.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>It is invariably the practice that individuals who have been subject to a personal search are allowed to continue their journey immediately the search has been completed, provided, of course, that the search had proved fruitless.  I would be happy to bring forward such an amendment myself were it the case that evidence of abuse of powers by the customs service existed or that they were detaining people for longer than was necessary. We cannot constrain the judgment or the implementation and execution of their duties by the customs officers in their implementation of the laws of the land <Col N="1498" /><i>vis-à-vis</i> the customs service.  This section would put a constraint and a time limit on them.  We must be guided by their judgment and have confidence in their administration of the law.  I believe that this amendment to section 2 is unnecessary and therefore I regret that I have to oppose it.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelFerris" hpid="Mr. Ferris Mr. Ferris">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Ferris</NameTxt>
      <P>It would be ungrateful of me if I pressed this amendment in view of what the Minister has just said.  He has been very forthcoming with us today and what we have been trying to do here.  I accept his suggestion that if he felt this was necessary he would have brought in such an amendment himself.  He considers that it is unnecessary and that it might put an unreasonable demand on Customs and Excise officers and restrain them in some way.  For that reason I will not press the amendment.  I am glad of the Minister's assurances that there will not be any undue delay.  If there is an undue delay, the person has the right in law to take the appropriate action, if they feel that their rights and ordinary common freedom were impeded in any way.  I accept that there is an existing common law to protect that.  I just wanted to be sure that people's rights and privileges were respected.</P>
      <P>Amendment, by leave, withdrawn.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JackDaly" hpid="Mr. Daly Mr. Daly">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Daly</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 14:</P>
      <P>In page 12, line 46, to delete &ldquo;one half thereof&rdquo; and substitute &ldquo;one hundred and fifty pounds&rdquo;.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I want to ask the Minister to continue to be the reasonable man he has been all day.  I hope he does not stop now when I start because he has been very good to all the other parties.  I hope it will continue. It will not cost him as much in effort to do this for me as for the others. The position is that the fine was increased from £6 to £500 and from £200 to £1,000. I have no objection to the increase from £200 to £1,000 because that could be for somebody who is in high production of poteen and offering it for sale.  What I <Col N="1499" /> am talking about is the person a lot of people talk about, the small farmer.  The small farmer would need this kind of embrocation for his cattle and it is good for human beings, too, which is more important.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PadraicMcCormack" hpid="Mr. McCormack Mr. McCormack">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McCormack</NameTxt>
      <P>There is plenty of it in Galway.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JackDaly" hpid="Mr. Daly Mr. Daly">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Daly</NameTxt>
      <P>It is very good for medicinal purposes.  The person I wish to protect is the person who is making poteen for his own use and on a small scale.  A district justice will also have jurisdiction to increase the fine but if we tie his hands he has no chance.  I would remind the Minister that there is a precedent set for this is so far as in the case of the Abattoirs Bill under which people had to kill in licensed places and the meat had to be stamped the Minister agreed that where a man was killing livestock for his own use he got an exemption to kill without stamping and without reporting to the vet.</P>
      <P>The Minister may say that poteen could be sold by the man I am talking about, the small producer, that it would not be for medicinal purposes.  There is a simple answer to that.  Again there is a precedent because you have red diesel and white diesel.  The diesel exempt from duty can be used in tractors and for farm use and there is the white diesel for the cars.  Red diesel may not be used in cars. The Minister, if he wishes, can get the poteen coloured by a dye or by any other means.  I would ask him to allow for tolerance, leeway and flexibility on the part of district justices in this matter.  He will have no flexibility if the minimum fine is £500.  It would be crazy.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I will not go into the question of the great value this will become to the country some day when somebody realises the potential and the value of it worldwide as in the case of the bottled water of Ballygowan and Tipperary.  They laughed at the gentleman on &ldquo;The Late Late Show&rdquo; when he was talking about the water and now Budweiser are distributing it all over the United States.  Budweiser <Col N="1500" /> could be distributing this too.  I am really dealing with the small man and am only concerned with the small man and all I ask the Minister to do is to reduce this in order that the district justice will have flexibility.  He will have no flexibility if the Minister sets a minimum fine of £500. The previous fine was £6.  I think £500 would be crazy and whoever calculated that, the battery must have gone in the calculator midway.  Something happened anyway.  I appeal to the good sense and fair play of the Minister and his flexibility and the good mood he is in, because he has proved that he is in a good mood by the way in which he has treated the House all morning.</P>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="A Senator A Senator">
      <NameTxt>A Senator</NameTxt>
      <P>It must be the pioneer pin.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JackDaly" hpid="Mr. J. Daly Mr. J. Daly">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J. Daly</NameTxt>
      <P>I have already said that. I said it was one pioneer to another.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Is the amendment seconded?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PadraicMcCormack" hpid="Mr. McCormack Mr. McCormack">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McCormack</NameTxt>
      <P>I support the amendment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="NoelTracey" hpid="Mr. N. Treacy Mr. N. Treacy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. N. Treacy</NameTxt>
      <P>I listened with great interest to Senator Daly's contribution today and on Committee Stage about the medical characteristics of poteen and I appreciate his concern about the small man.  But the difficulty is that if the law is to be specific in accommodating the small man, the small man could become a big man and the law would be laughing at itself or, as they say, the law would be an ass.  I sympathise with him and appreciate the painful effects of maladies such as arthritis but I cannot condone any illegal acts particularly those which have potential to produce great suffering and even death.  Penalties must be realistic to deal with the problem of illegal distillation. It is the Government's view that a penalty of £1,000 which may be mitigated to not less than £500 is appropriate. The mitigation to 50 per cent of the penalty brings such offences into line with the general practice in relation to the mitigation of Customs and Excise penalties. Despite that very strong language, <Col N="1501" /> if you like, I want to further assure the House and Senator Daly that after the decision is made by the court and the justice on a fine of £500, the Minister for Justice, on appeal to him, may open a petition in any case and on the grounds of hardship or whatever he may decide to mitigate that figure to whatever figure he so wishes taking into account all the information available to him on any given case.  The person has the opportunity of appealing to the court, appealing to the Minister and ultimately of getting a reduction made by the Minister.  Unless we ensure that the law is consistent right across the board in all the Customs and Excise areas, that the mitigation is 50 per cent, we will be creating a situation of imbalance.  I would not like a situation to occur that people operating in the production of and commercial exploitation of illicit spirits would make a lot of money at the expense of not alone human beings but also the State, while I do accept that a small production may be of benefit medically to people and also as a veterinary contribution in an amateur fashion to alleviating the ailments of animals. I appreciate the concern and objectivity of Senator Daly but I regret I cannot accept his very moving and passionate plea.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JackDaly" hpid="Mr. J. Daly Mr. J. Daly">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J. Daly</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister says that he cannot make an ass of the law and, of course, the world knows the law is an ass anyway.  In this particular case I was giving the Minister an example of a precedent. I do not know whether he was the Minister dealing with the Abattoirs Bill, but it is on the record.  It is only a couple of weeks back.  In the case of that penalty for slaughtering animals without stamping and without notifying a vet the small farmer was exempt if he was doing it for his own use.  The small farmer could equally go into the commercial field.  He might kill an animal for his own use, sell it and having sold that he might kill another one and sell that.  That could happen. Those things will always happen.  But the fact that the exemption was given already and the precedent is there I again appeal to the Minister to have a look at that and <Col N="1502" /> see if he can deal with it as it was dealt with in the Abattoirs Bill.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="NoelTracey" hpid="Mr. N. Treacy Mr. N. Treacy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. N. Treacy</NameTxt>
      <P>I cannot accept it here today but as I gave a commitment on Committee Stage to be objective and as I have been fairly forthcoming in amending the Bill today, I will have a further look at this situation before the Bill goes to the Dáil.  If I find that there is some opportunity to have a further reduction, I will give it consideration.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JackDaly" hpid="Mr. J. Daly Mr. J. Daly">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J. Daly</NameTxt>
      <P>I thank the Minister.  I know he is a man of his word and he will do his best.</P>
      <P>Amendment, by leave, withdrawn.</P>
      <P>Bill received for final consideration.</P>
      <P>Agreed to take remaining Stage today.</P>
      <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That the Bill do now pass.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="NoelTracey" hpid="Minister of State at the Department of Finance (Mr. N. Treacy) Noel Treacy">
      <NameTxt>Minister of State at the Department of Finance (Mr. N. Treacy)</NameTxt>
      <P>I sincerely thank you, a Leas-Chathaoirligh, and the Members of the House for the excellent, very positive and informed contributions that they have made.  I hope that together the House and I have restrengthened this Bill and that Dáil Éireann will now give it a speedy passage to ensure that we will be able to further apprehend and control those trying to destroy our great, young developing nation by peddling drugs.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>May I ask the Acting Leader of the House if it is intended to have a sos?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFallon" hpid="Mr. Fallon Mr. Fallon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Fallon</NameTxt>
      <P>It is not intended to have a sos.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Shipping Investment Grants Bill, 1987" RHead=": Second Stage">
    <Title>Shipping Investment Grants Bill, 1987    [Certified Money Bill]:    Second Stage.</Title>
    <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That the Bill be now read a Second Time.&rdquo;</P>
    <Col N="1503" />
    <Speaker pid="PatTheCope" hpid="Minister of State at the Department of the Marine (Mr. P. Gallagher) Minister of State at the Department of the Marine (Mr. P. Gallagher)">
      <NameTxt>Minister of State at the Department of the Marine (Mr. P. Gallagher)</NameTxt>
      <P>The purpose of the Bill is to provide a statutory basis for a scheme of investment grants for ships.  Under the proposed scheme, grants of up to 25 per cent may be paid to Irish shipowners in respect of approved capital expenditure incurred in the purchase of new ships or second-hand ships which are not more than seven years old.</P>
      <P>In 1985, the Committee on Strategic Shipping Requirements was established to carry out a review of the country's strategic shipping needs.  In its report, the committee concluded that there was an overwhelming case on strategic grounds for the provision of incentives to encourage the maintenance and development of the Irish merchant fleet.</P>
      <P>The Committee recommended, <i>inter alia,</i> that the appropriate Departments consider what measures could be introduced to provide an effective stimulus to existing Irish shipowners and to encourage new investment in the industry.  A package of incentives, including the grants scheme for which this Bill provides a statutory basis, was announced earlier this year.  In addition to the grant scheme fiscal incentives were introduced under the 1987 Finance Act.  The corporation tax rate payable by shipping companies has been reduced from 50 per cent to 10 per cent.  This will allow shipowners to channel profits into the expansion and development of their services.  Shipping project which have been deemed eligible for grant aid will have access to the business expansion scheme under which private investment in designated projects is allowable against tax liabilities.  The interest shown to date in this regard has indicated that this could become an important source of finance for the industry. In addition, the way is now open for shipowners to approach the National Development Corporation for investment support in projects which are likely to yield a satisfactory return.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>These incentives, together with the Bill now before us, should be seen as part of <Col N="1504" /> an overall policy of support for the Irish merchant shipping industry.  The Bill is designed to provide a stimulus to Irish shipowners to acquire additional tonnage in the face of a worldwide recession and highly competitive conditions within the shipping industry.</P>
    <P>In the past decade we have witnessed a significant reduction in the size of both the EC and OECD's share of the world fleet.  OECD member countries, which include the EC member states, have pursued a policy based on the principle of free circulation of shipping in conditions of fair competition.  On the other hand, some countries through unilateral or bilateral agreements have excluded, either partially or wholly, the shipping from third countries from their trades.</P>
    <P>Irish Governments have chosen to promote a policy of full commercial freedom of shipping on the principle that, as an island State, it best serves Irish economic interests.  However, positive measures are now required so as to ensure that ships on the Irish register will not move away from the Irish flag to more accommodating administrations.  This would have serious strategic and economic consequences for the country as a whole as well as for our exporters who would find themselves in an extremely vulnerable position, despite efforts in the past to increase the share of our trade carried in Irish ships, the proportion is still less than 20 per cent of total trade.</P>
    <P>At present, partly because of the recession which I mentioned, a considerable supply of good quality secondhand ships in the five to seven year range has come on the market.  The provision of grants for vessels of this type will enable Irish shipowners to avail of the opportunity to acquire additional good quality ships at reasonable prices.</P>
    <P>The proposed grants scheme will have a number of restrictions which are intended to ensure that the object of the exercise, that is, the expansion of the Irish fleet, is achieved.  Grants may only be payable to individuals who are both citizens of and resident in the State, or to bodies corporate which are incorporated in the State, or to partnerships whose <Col N="1505" /> members are qualifying individuals or bodies corporate.</P>
    <P>Grants may only be paid in respect of ships which are registered in the State and which are in excess of 1,000 tons deadweight.  Since the scheme is aimed solely at the merchant shipping industry, fishing vessels, tugs, dredgers or offshore supply vessels are excluded from its application. In addition, the grant-aiding of the same vessel more than once is prohibited.</P>
    <P>Additional conditions may be imposed with the concurrence of the Minister for Finance so as to ensure that grant-aided vessels are employed in the applicant's business and will continue to be of practical benefit to the economy as part of the national fleet.  The Bill also provides for repayment of grants, in part or in full, in the event that the vessel ceases, within a specified time, through loss, transfer or other disposal, to fulfil the purposes which rendered it eligible for aid.</P>
    <P>As regards the question of loss, I should perhaps make it clear that all vessels which are grant-aided will be required to be insured to the extent that compensation payable will meet full replacement costs.  This will safeguard the State's investment as well as the ship-owner's. I would add that under section 6(2) of the Bill the discretionary powers available to the Minister are sufficiently broad to deal with the problems which might arise in the event of a grand-aided vessel being lost.  It should be remembered that the conditions of the scheme, including the repayment in certain circumstances, are designed to ensure that grant-aided vessels will make real contributions to our shipping industry.</P>
    <P>The Bill includes provisions in relation to offences and penalties for contravention of the Act, including the giving of false information, failure to comply with the administrative conditions and fraudulent application for grants.  Further provisions empower authorised persons to enter and inspect ships or premises in connection with the administration of the scheme.</P>
    <P>The scheme will have retrospective effect to 1 April 1987.  Following the <Col N="1506" /> announcement earlier this year of the decision in principle to introduce the scheme, certain Irish shipowners undertook investment in anticipation of its early implementation.  In giving this legislation retrospective effect, eligible ships purchased since 1 April may qualify for grant-aid.</P>
    <P>In framing the terms of the scheme, employment has been a central consideration. The benefits in terms of jobs created will be a crucial factor in deciding on which projects will receive grant-aid. Inquirers have been left in no doubt that they will have to come through on jobs for Irish personnel and the same will apply to formal applicants.  Grantees will have to comply with the manning regulations for registry which require Irish certificates of competency.</P>
    <P>The cost of the scheme, subject to an aggregate amount of £7.5 million, will depend on the response of the industry. There is, however, strong indication that shipowners will not be slow to seize the opportunities which the scheme affords. It is anticipated that approximately £500,000 will be paid in grant-aid during 1987.  Subject to budgetary constraints, it is expected that at least £1.03 million will be available in the first full year of the scheme's operation in 1988.</P>
    <P>The Government, in creating the Department of the Marine, have made clear their commitment to the development of our marine resources.  As the first legislation to be introduced under the aegis of the new Department this Bill represents a milestone in its brief history. The Shipping Investment Grants Bill is a progressive measure which it is hoped will provide a much needed boost for the Irish shipping industry.</P>
    <P>This country depends heavily on its rising level of exports and upon the importation of vital raw materials for its industry.  As a consequence, our economic prosperity relies largely on the shipping services available.  It makes sense in that case that we should endeavour to ensure that as much of our trade as possible is carried in Irish-owned ships.  The grant scheme for which this Bill provides a statutory basis, together with the fiscal <Col N="1507" /> incentives mentioned earlier, will make a significant contribution towards the achievement of this objective.</P>
    <P>I recommend the Bill to the House.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PadraicMcCormack" hpid="Mr. McCormack Mr. McCormack">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McCormack</NameTxt>
      <P>I welcome the Minister of State, Deputy Gallagher, to the House to take this Bill.  The purpose of the Bill is to provide a grant scheme to maintain and develop an Irish merchant shipping fleet for economic reasons and this is particularly necessary in the wake of the Irish Shipping liquidation.  If there is one good thing which the liquidation of Irish Shipping did, it was that it led to a review of shipping policy.  My colleague in the Dáil, Deputy Mitchell, as Minister for Communications, immediately set up a committee on strategic shipping requirements to investigate and report on current and future shipping needs.  The Bill before us now and part of the Finance Act, 1987, reducing corporation profit tax on shipping to 10 per cent are a direct result of the proposals of that committee.</P>
      <P>This Bill is largely the same as Deputy Mitchell's Bill.  It is the same Bill with small alterations.  The age of ships has been extended from five years to seven years and I welcome that.  In peace time it is sometimes hard to realise the importance of the strategic fleet particularly for essential supplies.  However, we must realise that over 90 per cent of our merchandise trade is carried out by sea and 80 per cent of this is done by foreign shipowners.  Persistent and current problems in shipping worldwide have made it difficult for shipping in recent years. Despite those difficulties I believe that if our industry here could compete on equal footing with its main competitors, then the relative advantage which we as an island people with long tradition in maritime trading have, will ensure us an adequate share of the international shipping market, irrespective of conditions prevailing there.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The Irish shipping industry has tremendous potential which I am confident will be realised to the benefit of our economy and our citizens.  The shipping industry <Col N="1508" /> worldwide is still reeling from the worst depression in 40 years.  Despite intensified voluntary reductions in tonnage, the huge surplus in all shipping markets has led to a continued excess of supply over demand, resulting in artificially low freight rates.  Recent years in particular have seen heavy losses by shipowners, bankruptcy of shipping companies, date rescheduling, deferred delivery on used ships and more and more ships being laid up.</P>
    <P>Despite all this there is still considerable over-capacity in the industry which will persist for some time.  Within this overall picture of surplus capacity the European Community share of world tonnage continues to decline in relation to other fleets.  Most member states have experienced a severe reduction in fleet size and are currently reviewing their maritime policies, both individually and collectively, as the Community works towards a maritime policy.</P>
    <P>We must compliment our own small private shipping sector which has shown great resilience in the face of worldwide depression.  However, recent low profitability has threatened the industry's very survival and prevented expansion.  I am, therefore, pleased to welcome this Bill which, subject to certain conditions, will allow grant-aid up to 25 per cent for the purchase of new or secondhand ships by Irish shipowners from 1 April this year. The good news is that at least five vessels are awaiting passage of this legislation to obtain the benefits, I sincerely hope that the list will grow.</P>
    <P>While £1.5 million has been provided this year for grants, the recently published Estimates for next year show a reduction to just over £1 million.  In section 2 (3), the amount of grant made available by the Minister shall not exceed an aggregate of £7.5 million.  I am a bit concerned about that and I am not clear on how this £7.5 million will be allocated. I would like clarification of that from the Minister because if this year we allocate £1.5 million and if next year we reduce it to £1 million and we continue on reducing it by approximately one-third or 33 per cent every year, we would never spend <Col N="1509" /> the £7.5 million.  I am not clear on how it is proposed to get to the figure of £7.5 million.  We could continue, for example, reducing it by a third of the Estimate provided for that every year and after about 20 to 21 years, according to my arithmetic, we would be down at an allocation of hundreds of pounds.  How is it proposed to reach the figure if we only provide £1.5 million this year and £1 million next year?</P>
    <P>I would like to draw some other matters to the Minister's attention.  My first concerns cross-reference from the Finance Act, 1987, to this Bill, section 8 (a). This section deals with qualification of shipping for the business expansion scheme, that it is a designated industry and qualifying for 10 per cent corporation tax.  One of the conditions for such a qualification, according to this section, is that:</P>
    <P>It shall include a certificate by the Minister for the Marine certifying that the purchase of a ship was, is, or would be eligible to be grant-aided under a statutory scheme of assistance for the purpose of ships administered by the Department of the Marine.</P>
    <P>In other words, it appears that to be eligible for inclusion in the business expansion scheme the ship has to be eligible for grant-aid under this Shipping Investment Bill and to be eligible under the terms of the Bill before us today a ship has got to be less than seven years old at the date of its purchase.</P>
    <P>The Minister said there were many good, second-hand ships from five to seven years old coming on the market. That may or may not be so but I believe the seven year limit on second-hand ships for the purpose of this Bill is correct but I have to reconcile that with a seven year limit for the purposes of the business expansion scheme.  The reason for this, contrary to what the Minister said, is that excellent, second-hand ships, often up to ten years old are bought, for example, from the Dutch and Germans.  Their ships do not come on the market until they are at least eight years old and that <Col N="1510" /> is in order to comply with grant conditions in these countries.  Perhaps the Minister will clarify in his reply how we might get over that crux.  This dilemma caused by the requirement that for the business expansion scheme a ship must be eligible for a grant under the Shipping Investment Bill must be clarified.  Perhaps this could be more properly corrected by an amendment in next year's Finance Bill and if that is so I will await the Minister's response.</P>
    <P>I would like the Minister to clarify those points I have raised.  May I ask the Minister if parts of the shipping grants included in the Finance Act work in conjunction with this Bill?  Of major importance to me in the Minister's reply would be information as to what is the period of time over which the £7.5 million will be paid out in view of my observations on the Estimates of about £1.5 million this year and £1 million next year.  Would that go on indefinitely?</P>
    <P>Before I conclude I wish to take this opportunity to thank my colleague, Deputy Mitchell, for his early work in assembling this Bill thus ensuring that it came before the Houses of the Oireachtas.</P>
    <Speaker pid="TomFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Fitzgerald Mr. Fitzgerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Fitzgerald</NameTxt>
      <P>First, I would like to welcome to the House the Minister of State at the Department of the Marine. This is my first opportunity to welcome him.  I also welcome the Bill.  To go back briefly in time, Irish Shipping was founded after the Second World War.  It was founded because we had learned by our mistakes of the past.  An island people just cannot do without their own boats to transport essential goods into this country in times of war and also to export our own goods.  It was unfortunate, a few years ago, that Irish Shipping went into liquidation and it was unfortunate in the way it was done at the time because it is my belief that Ireland's name was possibly smeared slightly throughout the world due to the manner in which it was done.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Nevertheless, that is behind us and there is now a positive effort to get Irish <Col N="1511" /> people or companies under Irish management, citizens of this State, to invest and make an investment in cargo boats, new or secondhand.  There is a golden opportunity here with the back-up of the Government in the provision of grants up to 25 per cent.  These grants are payable for new or secondhand boats.  As a fisherman who has seen a great amount of the sea, and who has watched cargo boats go up and down our coast, I saw very few of these cargo boats carrying Irish names or being registered in Ireland.  It was interesting to learn from what the Minister said that despite efforts to increase the share of our trade carried by Irish ships the proportion is still less than 20 per cent.</P>
    <P>Ireland, as an island, has a history of association with the sea and ships.  There must be great room for improvement in this area.  If I were to complain about the Bill, which I welcome, I might say that it possibly does not go far enough.  Perhaps in view of the amount of capital to buy some of these boats the Government should consider at another time a loan of some type to help out in buying them.</P>
    <P>We are nearly solely dependent at this point in time on ships that are owned by companies and people from outside this country and if there was a crisis of some nature, like war, we would be basically cut off.  The amount of goods being transported by sea in and out of this country is huge and proper investment in a proper shipping fleet is most welcome at this time.  There is a great potential there and I am sure that businessmen who are already, in a small way, owners of cargo vessels will jump to the opportunity provided by this Bill.  We do need the additional investment in the industry. There is, of course another aspect to it. Irish owned ships will carry Irish crews and there is this employment factor also.</P>
    <P>Perhaps the Minister could say if the Government have in mind making finance available possibly on short term loan to help out.  The 25 per cent is a most welcome and generous grant but the provision of the other 75 per cent might prove difficult.  Perhaps the Government <Col N="1512" /> would look again at this, seeing that the industry is in its infancy so that there would be an opportunity for starting off and money would be more freely available for these ships.</P>
    <P>I know that a boat of 1,000 tons is a very small boat but if we are to get the full potential out of the sea and the cargoes which can be transported on it, we must consider the amount of small ports around our coast which in the past accommodated boats of just less than 1,000 tons.  These would be nearly border line cases.  I do not want to be parochial about it but in my own town boats of 150 ft. to 200 ft. which are relatively small have been coming in there over the years with fertiliser, timber and coal.  To the best of my knowledge their tonnage would be somewhere round 700 or 800 tons.  There must be a number of small ports similar to Dingle around our coast which could still do business by sea in isolated places like Dingle.  Only a year ago, fish was being exported out of Dingle again in boats of under 1,000 tons.  It is only a small thing but perhaps the Minister would comment on it and also on the provision of finance by way of loan.</P>
    <P>I welcome this Bill wholeheartedly because we have been out on a limb since Irish Shipping went into liquidation.  I felt at the time it was a disgrace because of the way it was done.  This Bill must surely be welcomed right across the board by everybody.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatTheCope" hpid="Minister of State at the Department of the Marine (Mr. P. Gallagher) Minister of State at the Department of the Marine (Mr. P. Gallagher)">
      <NameTxt>Minister of State at the Department of the Marine (Mr. P. Gallagher)</NameTxt>
      <P>Ar dtús, ba mhaith liom mo bhuíochas a ghabháil leis na Seanadóirí McCormack agus Fitzgerald as ucht teacht isteach anseo inniu agus a thaispeáint dúinn an oiread suime atá acu san mBille seo.  Ba mhaith liom mo bhuíochas a ghabhaíl leis an mbeirt acu as ucht an fáiltiú a chuireadh roimh an mBille seo.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I would like to thank both Senator McCormack and Senator Fitzgerald for their wholehearted welcome.  Of course all have reservations and in the course of my reply I hope to deal with those.  I would like to thank them for their contributions and for their particular interest in this Shipping Investment Grants Bill. <Col N="1513" /> I would like to thank them for the encouraging and supportive contributions they made to the debate on this very important legislation.  Shipping services represent an area with huge potential for development and this Bill is progressive legislation designed to exploit that potential.</P>
    <P>At present less than 20 per cent of our total trade is carried on Irish registered vessels given that 95 per cent of our trade is seaborne and it is clear that there is scope for substantial expansion in domestic shipping services.  An expansion in the quality and capacity of our national shipping fleet would have significant and beneficial effects in terms of employment and of import substitution.  While we tend to think of import substitution in terms of manufactured goods, over the past number of years the importance of service industries, such as shipping, has increased and it is vital that where possible the use of domestic carriers is maximised. I am sure that both our exporters and those engaged in the importation of vital raw materials will not now be slow to realise the significant contribution they can make in this regard.</P>
    <P>The world recession in shipping has reduced employment opportunities for seafarers in all countries and for that reason it is the wish of the Government that the grants scheme should yield significant benefits in this area.  As I emphasised when introducing the Bill, the number of jobs which eligible projects will create will be a basic consideration in dealing with projects receiving grant aid.</P>
    <P>The combined effects of the grants scheme and the fiscal incentives introduced under this year's Finance Act create a more favourable environment for shipowners.  The development and expansion of our shipping services will mean that the industry can sustain a higher level of employment, thereby ensuring that we will continue to have at our disposal the traditional seafaring skills so vital to an island State.</P>
    <P>The £7.5 million which will be made available represents a potential of £30 million investment in the industry.  This <Col N="1514" /> will provide the necessary stimulus for further investment and will help to secure our basic strategic shipping needs.</P>
    <P>Senator McCormack referred to the £1.03 million available this year and to the question of the £7.5 million available overall.  It was absolutely necessary to put a ceiling on this.  Of course the ceiling may be changed at a later stage if we find that necessary but it is important to have a ceiling and not have the sort of situation that arose last year and prior to that in regard to the introduction of home improvement grants without any ceiling. If that were to happen in this case, it could be so open ended as to leave us with a fleet much greater than the capacity we would require.  It is accepted, from a financial and monetary point of view, that we have to have a ceiling.</P>
    <P>Senator McCormack referred also to the business expansion scheme and the access linked to grant eligibility.  If one is to avail of the business expansion scheme one does not have to have been paid a grant.  As long as one is eligible for a grant, one can avail of the business expansion scheme.  I was pleased that Senator McCormack referred to and accepted the seven year period rather than a longer one which was suggested by some Members of the other House. That is an increase on the five years which was intended previously.  However, we will ask the Minister for Finance to consider a 12 year period for the business expansion scheme but not for the grant aid.  However, to avail of the business expansion scheme we will have to vet applications and our Department will have to give approval before they can be considered for the business expansion scheme.  The Senator's comments will be taken very seriously and will be taken into account when framing the Finance Bill for 1988.</P>
    <P>Senator McCormack referred also to the reduction in the allocation.  I have already touched on that.  The timescale for grant payments under the scheme is open-ended to the ceiling of £7.5 million and it will be available subject to budgetary constraints.  I would like to think that there would be much more available but <Col N="1515" /> all Departments must accept that we have serious financial problems, not necessarily all of our own doing, but the problems are there and we must now try to rectify and resolve them.  Moneys will be available subject to budgetary constraints. The £7.5 million of course represents a total investment of £30 million.</P>
    <P>Senator Fitzgerald referred to the question of loans.  The financial institutions should look very favourably at any application which is vetted by our Department and I have already pointed out that moneys will be available from the NDC.  I believe that moneys will be forthcoming from them and, indeed, from other financial institutions.  There should not be an onus on the State to provide loans.</P>
    <P>The point raised by Senator Fitzgerald in relation to the limit of 1,000 dead tons varies somewhat from the previous Act which had a lower limit of some 100 tons. But the scheme is aimed at cargo-carrying vessels and of course the dead weight tonnage is less than the gross tonnage. Coastal trading is not very important in strategic terms.</P>
    <P>As Minister of State at the Department of the Marine, I would like to suggest to those who may be applying that this Department will be the nucleus of the industry and will be depending on the fishing industry but we do not have a reefer boat.  We are shipping out by way of refrigerated containers from the west and all other areas to all parts of Europe and even further afield.  Those involved in the industry and, indeed, those who want to become involved in the shipping industry should look at the question of a reefer container.</P>
    <P>In relation to the seven year age limit, we should note that ships built after May 1980, when the Safety of Life at Sea Convention came into force, were constructed in accordance with international safety standards adopted under that Convention. Any ships we would be grant aiding would have been built in accordance with the standards under that Convention. Vessels up to seven years old comply with these standards and are <Col N="1516" /> consequently more desirable additions to our fleet.</P>
    <P>I hope I have answered the questions posed by the Senators.  If there is any further information I can give I will certainly do so on Committee Stage.</P>
    <P>Very briefly, I would like to summarise and to refer to the principal benefits to the economy of the shipping incentives. I am confident that the package of incentives will result in benefits to the economy. The strategic fleet would be increased in line with the recommendations of the Committee on Strategic Shipping Requirements to approximately 158,000 dead weight tons. The income earned by the expanded fleet would result in a net balance of payments, improvements in foreign earnings and important import substitution which I referred to earlier.  Employment prospects for seamen and shore-based personnel would be improved.</P>
    <P>The necessary marine training facilities including access to sea time experience will continue to be available to seagoing cadets, thereby ensuring the continuation in Ireland of the necessary marine skills for the future.  The shipping industry would receive a stimulus to further expansion of both the size and scope of their services.</P>
    <P>A Chathaoirligh, arís gabhaim mo bhuíochas leis na Seanadóirí as ucht an fáilte a chuir siad roimh an mBille seo agus mar atá a fhios acu tá an Bille tríd an Dáil anois agus tá súil agam, roimh an tráthnóna go mbeidh sé tríd an Teach seo ionas go mbeimid ábalta cuidiú leo siúd a bhfuil iarratais istigh acu agus go mbeimid ábalta an cuidiú sin a chur ar fáil roimh dheireadh na bliana seo.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PadraicMcCormack" hpid="Mr. McCormack Mr. McCormack">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McCormack</NameTxt>
      <P>Gabh mo leithscéal, an feidir liom ceist a chur ar an Aire?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Acting Chairman Acting Chairman">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman</NameTxt>
      <P>It is not usual but the Senator did ask for clarification.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PadraicMcCormack" hpid="Mr. McCormack Mr. McCormack">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McCormack</NameTxt>
      <P>I did not even get it from the Minister's reply.  I understand that there had to be a maximum grant.  I was not referring to that at all.  I have no quibble with the maximum grant.  I know <Col N="1517" /> it is subject to budgetary restraints but if we continue with £1.5 million this year and £1 million next year, according to my sums if you keep reducing it by one-third in the Estimates every year it would take 20 years or more to spend £7.5 million. That would be my concern.  I hope I interpret the Minister correctly when I say people can still qualify for the business expansion scheme provided the applicant is qualified, not necessarily the age of the ship.  It does not necessarily have to have got a grant under this Bill to qualify for the business expansion scheme.  Does that mean the ship could be more than seven years old, and the person would not get a grant but would qualify for the business expansion scheme?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatTheCope" hpid="Mr. P. Gallagher Mr. P. Gallagher">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P. Gallagher</NameTxt>
      <P>I am sorry if I did not make myself clear enough for Senator McCormack.  The first point I would like to make is that mathematics are factual and not a matter of opinion, the Senator and I cannot disagree.  If we have a reduction of 10 per cent each year, the Senator's mathematics are right but his mathematics is based on assumptions.  If the logic of what he is saying were reversed, that there is £500,000 this year and £1.03 million next year, it would imply that we were progressing each year rather than regressing.  We could argue about that all day.  We are giving as much money as possible subject to budgetary controls, I cannot dispute the mathematics of it with the Senator but I think he will accept my point that it is a hypothetical question.  We will just have to wait and see.  The commitment of the Government is there.  The commitment of the new Department of the Marine is there.  The necessity to have a strategic fleet is there.  I think Senators will agree that we wasted no time bringing this Bill before the House.  I could agree with the Senator's mathematics but I certainly could not agree with his assumptions.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>My second point is in regard to the business expansion scheme.  To qualify for the business expansion scheme &mdash; I am glad the Senator raised the question if there is any ambiguity about this &mdash; one <Col N="1518" /> applies to our Department.  The application is scrutinised and processed to the full there.  If one is eligible for grant-aid and the applicant and the particular boat fulfil all of the conditions, the applicant would qualify for the business expansion scheme.  The age would still be seven years as of now.  The point raised by the Senator about an increase on that will be brought to the attention of the Minister for Finance, in that business expansion scheme incentives might be made available for boats between seven and, for example, ten and 12 years old.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PadraicMcCormack" hpid="Mr. McCormack Mr. McCormack">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McCormack</NameTxt>
      <P>I am glad to have had the opportunity to have that clarified.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>Agreed to take remaining Stages today.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Shipping Investment Grants Bill, 1987 [Certified" RHead="Money Bill]: Committee and Final Stages">
    <Title>Shipping Investment Grants Bill, 1987    [Certified Money Bill]:    Committee and Final Stages.</Title>
    <P>Section 1 agreed to.</P>
    <P Just="Center">SECTION 2.</P>
    <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That section 2 stand part of the Bill.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="PadraicMcCormack" hpid="Mr. McCormack Mr. McCormack">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McCormack</NameTxt>
      <P>I did not realise we were coming to Committee Stage and I apologise.  My question would have been more relevant on Committee Stage.  I accept the Minister's clarification on how the £7.5 million will be spent.  I am still concerned that no money can be spent, as the Minister has acknowledged, unless it is provided for in the Estimates.  I know the mechanics of spending £500,000 this year.  There was £1.5 million provided in the Estimates this year.  In next year's Estimates there is £1 million provided. We all acknowledge the financial restraints the Government or any Government in office are under.  There should have been a period of time included in the Bill, whether two, three or four years &mdash; perhaps two years would be too short &mdash; in which there could be <Col N="1519" /> grant-aiding up to the tune of £7.5 million.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P Just="Center">SECTION 3.</P>
      <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That section 3 stand part of the Bill.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PadraicMcCormack" hpid="Mr. McCormack Mr. McCormack">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McCormack</NameTxt>
      <P>Section 3 (d), line 16, says &ldquo;not more than seven years old.&rdquo; I accept the Minister's assurance on that. There may be something introduced which will allow ships of over seven years of age to qualify for the business expansion scheme.  Such provision should be incorporated.  A lot of good ships between eight and ten years old come on the market because of restrictions in the countries of origin.  If a provision could be written in whereby ships of up to ten or 12 years of age, where every other qualifying aspect was met, could qualify for the business expansion scheme, I would be happy with that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatTheCope" hpid="Minister of State at the Department of the Marine (Mr. P. Gallagher) Minister of State at the Department of the Marine (Mr. P. Gallagher)">
      <NameTxt>Minister of State at the Department of the Marine (Mr. P. Gallagher)</NameTxt>
      <P>This is something which may be a matter for the Minister for Finance.  We have already brought the views of Deputies to the Minister and will bring the views of Senators to the Minister in regard to introducing a period between seven and ten years for the business expansion scheme.  I can certainly say that anything over seven years will not be considered for grant-aid.  I think it is important that I should refer again to the SOLAS Convention.  Ships built after May 1980 when the Safety of Life at Sea Convention came into force, were constructed in accordance with international safety standards.  We would be responsible if it is decided in the 1988 Finance Act that boats between seven and 12 years would qualify for the business expansion scheme.  Those applications would be processed and scrutinised as would a boat under seven years.  It is vitally important that they comply with all of the conditions.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PadraicMcCormack" hpid="Mr. McCormack Mr. McCormack">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McCormack</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister accepts <Col N="1520" /> my point that Dutch and German ships come on the market and they are not in second-hand condition.  Because of conditions in their respective countries they have to hold a ship for eight years according to the grants they have obtained. After eight years some of those ships which are in very good condition come on the market and it would be a pity if Irish companies or Irish people buying those ships were excluded from the business expansion scheme because there was a criterion that they had to be first qualified for aid under this Bill.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatTheCope" hpid="Mr. P. Gallagher Mr. P. Gallagher">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P. Gallagher</NameTxt>
      <P>The point has been taken by me and we will discuss it with our counterparts in the Department of Finance.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>Section 4 agreed to.</P>
      <P Just="Center">SECTION 5.</P>
      <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That section 5 stand part of the Bill.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PadraicMcCormack" hpid="Mr. McCormack Mr. McCormack">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McCormack</NameTxt>
      <P>A grant under this Act may be made towards proved capital expenditure which is incurred on or after 1 April 1987.  Can the Minister give us an assurance that people who have entered into contracts since 1 April 1987 and may have been in contract situations before this Bill becomes law are eligible for grant-aid under this scheme.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatTheCope" hpid="Mr. P. Gallagher Mr. P. Gallagher">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P. Gallagher</NameTxt>
      <P>The legislation would be retrospective to 1 April.  Applications can only be processed when the Bill is enacted.  Anyone who applies will be given every consideration.  Anyone in business would be foolish to have entered into a binding contract on the assumption that this Bill would be passed and money would be made available.  We will look at all of the conditions and, as I pointed out on section 1, the employment condition will be a vital one.  All of the applications will be considered and prioritised.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PadraicMcCormack" hpid="Mr. McCormack Mr. McCormack">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McCormack</NameTxt>
      <P>Will a person who <Col N="1521" /> has entered into a contract and who meets all the other qualifying conditions be eligible for aid under this Bill?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatTheCope" hpid="Mr. P. Gallagher Mr. P. Gallagher">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P. Gallagher</NameTxt>
      <P>Subject to finance being available.  The point which I made earlier is that what the Senator is suggesting is that this would be similar to the home improvement grant scheme which was open ended and caused so many problems.  There is a limit of £515,000 available this year.  If the Bill is not enacted that money will not be available this year.  All of these will be processed and decisions will be taken by the Department. Grant-aid will be available subject to the financial position.  That is a limitation of £515,000 which would represent an investment this year of some £2 million and odd.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PadraicMcCormack" hpid="Mr. McCormack Mr. McCormack">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McCormack</NameTxt>
      <P>If there is an over demand on grants in the first year, which might happen because it is from 1 April, and there is only £515,000 available, can those applications be passed on to next year, or what kind of system would be envisaged for sorting out the applications? Where there are several qualified applicants, what system would be envisaged for sorting out the applications, and can an application then be passed on to the following year?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatTheCope" hpid="Mr. P. Gallagher Mr. P. Gallagher">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P. Gallagher</NameTxt>
      <P>If there is a greater demand for grant finance then finance available there will be an overrun into next year.  Conditions, obviously, must be a question of labour; the question of the quality of the vessel and the professional advice which we will receive.  I can assure the House every application will be treated the same.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PadraicMcCormack" hpid="Mr. McCormack Mr. McCormack">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McCormack</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister will accept that having regard to the cost of ships and with grant-aid of up to 25 per cent of the cost one application could eat up the entire £515,000 provided this year.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatTheCope" hpid="Mr. P. Gallagher Mr. P. Gallagher">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P. Gallagher</NameTxt>
      <P>I have no doubt.  I would be well aware of the cost of vessels. But, we are dealing with a factual situation and that is the amount that is <Col N="1522" /> available.  There are conditions.  I have spelt them out, perhaps not clearly enough.  It will be a question of the quality of the ships, the labour and the professional advice which we will receive. These conditions will be no different from similar type applications in any other Department.  I can assure the Senator that every one of these will be treated sympathetically and these factors will be taken into consideration.  If the Senator has any fears about applications which will be with us before the end of the year, if finance is not available, then there will be an overrun into next year.</P>
      <P>I would also like to point out that there may be companies who will take advantage of the business expansion scheme, which is a £25,000 investment per person which can run into quite a substantial amount of money, who may qualify for this without qualifying for grant-aid. Eligibility for grant-aid will entitle them to qualify for the business expansion scheme.  But undoubtedly it is a question of financial constraints.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P Just="Center">SECTION 6.</P>
      <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That section 6 stand part of the Bill.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PadraicMcCormack" hpid="Mr. McCormack Mr. McCormack">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McCormack</NameTxt>
      <P>Section 6 (a) provides &ldquo;securing that the ship in respect of which a grant has been or is proposed to be made shall continue to be used as required by those conditions.&rdquo;  What kind of monitoring system will there be to ensure that section 6 (a) is enforced?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatTheCope" hpid="Mr. P. Gallagher Mr. P. Gallagher">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P. Gallagher</NameTxt>
      <P>The provision in section 6 gives power to the Minister to impose conditions to ensure that a ship for which a grant has been made continues to be used as envisaged by the conditions of the grant.  The grant will become repayable in whole or in part if within a stated period the ship ceases to be used in the applicant's business or the applicant ceases to be eligible for a grant. This period will be at least five years and will be a condition laid down in the <Col N="1523" /> administration of the scheme.  The Minister's approval will be required for the chartering of a grant-aided ship for more than a single vessel.  We will have within the Department a number of officers, harbour masters, fishery officers, officers appointed by the Minister, who will closely monitor the situation.  Also, we have the marine surveyors; the harbour authorities.  We have the question of crew agreements lodged with the Mercantile Marine Office.</P>
      <P>All of these people will make information available to the Minister and ensure that the owner of the boat, whether it be an individual or a company, will comply very rigidly with the conditions laid down.  There will be a question of insurance which will be vitally important.  We will have to ensure that the Minister's interest is taken into consideration when a boat is being insured and inspections will be carried out periodically. All of these officers will bring this information to our attention and will monitor it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PadraicMcCormack" hpid="Mr. McCormack Mr. McCormack">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McCormack</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister has anticipated my next question because I was going to ask under section 6 (3) what would happen if a ship was destroyed or lost.  The Minister has anticipated that by saying that the Minister's interest would be covered by insurance.  That would be a necessary part of the allocation of a grant.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatTheCope" hpid="Mr. P. Gallagher Mr. P. Gallagher">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P. Gallagher</NameTxt>
      <P>For the benefit of the House we could elaborate somewhat on that and I will try to give as much information as possible.  Not alone is it in the interest of the Minister but it is also in the interest of the owner that any ship which would be grant-aided would be required in advance of payment of the grant to produce documentary evidence to show that the vessel had been fully insured.  The insurance will cover the vessel against all eventualities including its total loss and its replacement cost including the portion of its cost which was met by the State's investment and that is the grant.  It should be remembered that <Col N="1524" /> the principal purpose of the grant scheme will be to increase the size of the Irish registered fleet.  It is of overriding importance and must be safeguarded under the terms of the enabling legislation.  I am pleased that the Senator has asked for this information.  I am glad to be in a position to give this information.  Not alone is it in the interests of the Minister but it is very much in the interests of the industry as a whole that the insurance will cover the replacement costs of the vessel, not the original cost and will include the&mdash;&mdash;</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>Section 7 agreed to.</P>
      <P Just="Center">SECTION 8.</P>
      <P>Question proposed &ldquo;That section 8 stand part of the Bill&rdquo;.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PadraicMcCormack" hpid="Mr. McCormack Mr. McCormack">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McCormack</NameTxt>
      <P>Section 8 reads:</P>
      <P>(1) Any person who, for the purpose of obtaining a grant under the Act, knowingly or recklessly makes any statement, or who produces any document, which is false in any material particular shall be guilty of an offence and shall be liable&mdash;&mdash;</P>
      <P>(a) on summary conviction, to a fine not exceeding £1,000, or to imprisonment for any term not exceeding twelve months, or, at the discretion of the Court, to both such fine and such imprisonment,...</P>
      <P>Can a provision be written in that the grant would be refundable or that he would be liable in the first instance to pay back the grant if a person was convicted of such an offence?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatTheCope" hpid="Mr. P. Gallagher Mr. P. Gallagher">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P. Gallagher</NameTxt>
      <P>There are conditions attached to the grant whereby the Minister can insist that the grant, or a portion of the grant, will be repaid.  This section provides that on summary conviction a person shall be liable to a fine not exceeding £1,000, or to imprisonment.  The professional advice I have received has <Col N="1525" /> convinced me that this is adequate for a summary conviction and that the question of clawing back the grant, as suggested by the Senator, is covered under another section.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>Section 9 agreed to.</P>
      <P Just="Center">SECTION 10.</P>
      <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That section 10 stand part of the Bill.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PadraicMcCormack" hpid="Mr. McCormack Mr. McCormack">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McCormack</NameTxt>
      <P>Section 10 reads:</P>
      <P>The expenses incurred by the Minister in the administration of this Act shall, to such extent as may be sanctioned by the Minister for Finance, be paid out of moneys provided by the Oireachtas.</P>
      <P>Can administration costs eat into the funds provided for the grant?  That would be very wrong.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatTheCope" hpid="Mr. P. Gallagher Mr. P. Gallagher">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P. Gallagher</NameTxt>
      <P>This section is a normal provision to enable the Minister to incur expenditure on the administration of the grant schemes.  I can assure the Senator that the expenses will not reduce the grant allocation.  He need have no fears that the expenses will be such as to reduce the grant allocation.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PadraicMcCormack" hpid="Mr. McCormack Mr. McCormack">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McCormack</NameTxt>
      <P>I thank the Minister for his assurance.  I was concerned at some of the earlier provisions whereby the Minister or his agents would have authority to enter boats for inspection, which is necessary, and that could turn out to be very expensive and detailed work.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatTheCope" hpid="Mr. P. Gallagher Mr. P. Gallagher">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P. Gallagher</NameTxt>
      <P>This is normal practice and it is a normal provision to enable the Minister to incur this expenditure.  As I pointed out on an earlier section, we will have harbour masters, surveyors, fishery officers, but I do not anticipate the appointment of any further personnel. The officers who are already there would do this in the course of their normal <Col N="1526" /> duties.  Unfortunately, there is no question of 20 or 30 of these new ships arriving making it necessary to have an increase in the number of personnel.  As of now, I do not see this costing us any additional money.  I confirm that the expenses will not reduce the grant.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PadraicMcCormack" hpid="Mr. McCormack Mr. McCormack">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McCormack</NameTxt>
      <P>Has the Minister had discussions with some of the people he named, for example harbour masters, whom we would envisage carrying out those inspections?  Have any discussions taken place with people at that level?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatTheCope" hpid="Mr. P. Gallagher Mr. P. Gallagher">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P. Gallagher</NameTxt>
      <P>Could I say to the Senator that I have full confidence in the officials in my Department and if there is to be any delegation of authority it will be a matter for the officials to have discussions with the officers.  I do not think the Senator would expect that I would enter into discussions; I certainly would if it was necessary but this is the normal course.  Unfortunately, ten, 20 or 30 of these cargo vessels are not going to arrive in our ports tomorrow morning so it will not create any great difficulty.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>Sections 11 and 12 agreed to.</P>
      <P>Title agreed to.</P>
      <P>Bill reported without recommendation, received for final consideration and ordered to be returned to the Dáil.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Acting Chairman Acting Chairman">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman</NameTxt>
      <P>I thank the Minister and the Senators for their co-operation in finalising the Bill.</P>
      <P>
        <i>Sitting suspended at 2.40 p.m. and resumed at 2.50 p.m.</i>
      </P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Oil Pollution of the Sea (Civil Liability and" RHead="Compensation) Bill, 1987: Committee and Final Stages">
    <Title>Oil Pollution of the Sea (Civil Liability and Compensation) Bill, 1987: Committee and Final Stages.</Title>
    <P>Sections 1 and 2 agreed to.</P>
    <P Just="Center">
      <Col N="1527" /> SECTION 3.</P>
    <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That section 3 stand part of the Bill.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="PadraicMcCormack" hpid="Mr. McCormack Mr. McCormack">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McCormack</NameTxt>
      <P>Does &ldquo;compensation&rdquo; take into account, apart from the obvious damage and the cost to local authorities or to the State of having to clear an oil spill, all the work done by voluntary organisations in the clean up of the environment after an oil spill such as the cleaning of birds, sea shore, beaches etc?  Will &ldquo;compensation&rdquo; cover that as well as the actual compensation?  Will it take account of actions of voluntary bodies?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatTheCope" hpid="Minister of State at the Department of the Marine (Mr. P. Gallagher) Minister of State at the Department of the Marine (Mr. P. Gallagher)">
      <NameTxt>Minister of State at the Department of the Marine (Mr. P. Gallagher)</NameTxt>
      <P>Section 3 defines terms which are of general application throughout the Bill.  In the unfortunate event of an oil spillage all of the claims would be lodged and then it would be a matter for the legal people to decide, and for the conventions themselves to decide, the precise sum we should receive.  We would certainly insist on a total claim being presented to the insurers and we would have discussions with the other relevant bodies such as the local authority.  We would, on their behalf or in conjunction with them, lodge a claim.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PadraicMcCormack" hpid="Mr. McCormack Mr. McCormack">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McCormack</NameTxt>
      <P>Subsection (1) reads:</P>
      <P>&ldquo;crude oil&rdquo; has the meaning specified in section 19;</P>
      <P>&ldquo;discharge&rdquo;, in relation to oil, means any discharge or escape of oil however caused;</P>
      <P>Does the Bill relate only to a ship carrying a cargo of oil or does it relate to a spillage of engine oil from another type of cargo ship?  As we are all aware this Bill was introduced following the discovery of deficiencies in the existing law as revealed by the famous <i>Kowloon Bridge</i> disaster last year.  That was a big disaster but the <i>Kowloon Bridge</i> was carrying a cargo of ore and it was the engine oil that caused the pollution.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="1528" /> At that time off the Cork coast there was another incident involving an oil carrying cargo ship and if there had been a disaster with that, bad and all as the <i>Kowloon Bridge</i> was, it would have been a lot worse.  When the section says &ldquo;discharge&rdquo; of oil, does it mean discharge of oil as a cargo or will it also include compensation for the discharge of engine oil as in the case of the <i>Kowloon Bridge?</i></P>
    <Speaker pid="PatTheCope" hpid="Mr. P. Gallagher Mr. P. Gallagher">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P. Gallagher</NameTxt>
      <P>We will be dealing with that on section 7.  In relation to the questions the Senator has raised, and which are very appropriate, this Bill covers liability and compensation for oil pollution damage from laden oil tankers, tankers carrying oil as cargo, irrespective of their size, and irrespective of whether the spillage is from cargo or from bunker oil.  In relation to the case of the <i>Kowloon Bridge</i> when damage was caused by its own fuel oil while it was carrying another type of cargo, there is other legislation which will be updated to cover that.  We are considering strengthening the existing powers of the Merchant Shipping (Emergency Powers) Act to deal with contingencies such as the <i>Kowloon Bridge.</i>  To answer directly the Senator's question, this section covers the damage from laden oil tankers, irrespective of size and irrespective of whether the spillage is from cargo or bunker oil.  It does not cover a vessel carrying other types of material; as cargo there is other legislation to cover that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PadraicMcCormack" hpid="Mr. McCormack Mr. McCormack">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McCormack</NameTxt>
      <P>Notwithstanding what is in section 7, would it not have been appropriate in this Bill, seeing that it is dealing with oil pollution of the sea, to cover any type of oil pollution of the sea, apart from oil cargo ships polluting the sea?  The other ship I was trying to think of was the <i>Capo Emma</i>, which, as the Minister will be aware, was thought might go aground at the time of the <i>Kowloon Bridge.</i>  This legislation does not cover problems like those that arose at the time of the <i>Kowloon Bridge</i> disaster but covers pollution caused by ships like the <i>Capo Emma.</i>  As this is an oil pollution of the sea Bill and as serious oil <Col N="1529" /> pollution of the sea was caused by the <i>Kowloon Bridge</i> should this Bill not cover that aspect also?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatTheCope" hpid="Mr. P. Gallagher Mr. P. Gallagher">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P. Gallagher</NameTxt>
      <P>That may seem to be the obvious thing to do but the professional advice available to us is that we have to adhere to the two Conventions, the civil liability and the fund Conventions. The advice available to us is that we must bring in this legislation.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PadraicMcCormack" hpid="Mr. McCormack Mr. McCormack">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McCormack</NameTxt>
      <P>That seems strange because we know that the <i>Kowloon Bridge</i> clean-up operation cost the Department of the Environment £991,000, plus other costs, and that the Government are claiming £1.743 million in compensation in that case from the owners of the ship but we do not know if that money will be paid.  We know the direct cost of the pollution in the case of the <i>Kowloon Bridge</i> but can we say what the hidden costs were arising out of damage to fish and marine life, to tourism and allied interests, to farming, the environment, wildlife, animals and birds?  Can the Minister say what loss was caused to the fishing industry and what will be the long term effects of that leak?  I am posing those questions because it is not just good enough to say that we should wait for further legislation to deal with such problems. This Bill arose because of the public outcry and public alarm after the <i>Kowloon Bridge</i> incident.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatTheCope" hpid="Mr. P. Gallagher Mr. P. Gallagher">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P. Gallagher</NameTxt>
      <P>A number of the points made by Senator McCormack were also made in the Second Stage speech of Senator de Búitléar when he referred to the hidden costs and the hidden damage to wildlife and the sea.  It is almost impossible to quantify those costs.  We have submitted a claim for £1.743 million which we feel will cover all costs.  I do not want to give the impression, and I do not think anybody in the Department does, that we can quantify this.  I would say, with respect to the House, that this is a claim we feel will cover us.  I respectfully suggest that any elaboration, or the extraction of any further information from me in relation <Col N="1530" /> to this, may not be helpful to the country and to the Department.  I take the Senator's point about the hidden factors which were referred to by Senator de Buitléar, and other Senators, on Second Stage.  The Senator will appreciate that the reason we did not take Committee Stage on that day was because of the Senator's absence, through no fault of his own.  We appreciated his position as spokesman for the Marine and decided to hold it over until now.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PadraicMcCormack" hpid="Mr. McCormack Mr. McCormack">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McCormack</NameTxt>
      <P>I want to take this opportunity of publicly thanking the Minister and other Members of the Seanad who co-operated with him in doing that.  I am glad to have the opportunity today to have an input.  The Seanad met on a Tuesday which was unusual and I could not be there at short notice.  I thank the Minister for giving me this opportunity to be here for Committee Stage.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>Sections 4 to 6, inclusive, agreed to.</P>
      <P Just="Center">SECTION 7.</P>
      <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That section 7 stand part of the Bill.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TomFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Fitzgerald Mr. Fitzgerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Fitzgerald</NameTxt>
      <P>Ba mhaith liom ceist a chur ar an Aire mar gheall ar alt a seacht. I want to find out what happens if a ship is within or outside the State.  How far out to sea does our jurisdiction extend regarding oil pollution?  Have we a limit? The point I am making is that there could be a major disaster off our coast, maybe 200 miles out at sea, which would affect our shores.  Could the Minister tell me where the liability starts?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatTheCope" hpid="Mr. P. Gallagher Mr. P. Gallagher">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P. Gallagher</NameTxt>
      <P>Déanfaidh mé mo dhícheall freagra a thabhairt do Seanadóir Mac Gearailt.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The liability would cover the area out to 200 miles.  However, if there is a spillage outside 200 miles and it has an effect inside the 200-mile zone, then we will lodge a claim.  If it happens far out to <Col N="1531" /> sea it could well have detrimental effects inside our 200-mile economic zone and we will be in a position to lodge a claim. Subsection (1) determines the liability for pollution damage in the State caused by a ship carrying oil in bulk as cargo, whether such a ship is within or outside the State. The second subsection provides that any right of action of an owner of a ship regarding an incident against a third party may not be prejudiced by anything in this Act.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PadraicMcCormack" hpid="Mr. McCormack Mr. McCormack">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McCormack</NameTxt>
      <P>Section 7 states:</P>
      <P>The following provisions shall, subject to section 8, have effect in relation to pollution damage in the State which is caused by a ship carrying oil in bulk in cargo, whether the ship is within or without the State,...</P>
      <P>We are all aware that this Bill is necessary so that we can subscribe to the Convention of 1969, but with oil tankers getting bigger and bigger and passing near our coastline, is there any limit, apart from the compensation limit, to the size of ships carrying oil as bulk cargo?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatTheCope" hpid="Mr. P. Gallagher Mr. P. Gallagher">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P. Gallagher</NameTxt>
      <P>There is no limit to the size of the cargo but I would like to point out to the House that the compensation fund is being increased from 1 December.  The limitation fund increase would possibly be a <i>pro rata</i> increase.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PadraicMcCormack" hpid="Mr. McCormack Mr. McCormack">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McCormack</NameTxt>
      <P>This brings us back to the comparison cases.  I do not think people realise that if a bulk oil carrying tanker went aground &mdash; compare it to the other case where the engine oil of the <i>Kowloon Bridge</i> caused so much pollution &mdash; the type of pollution caused would be unbelievable.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatTheCope" hpid="Mr. P. Gallagher Mr. P. Gallagher">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P. Gallagher</NameTxt>
      <P>The purpose of this legislation is to relate to the two Conventions. It is vitally important that both of these Conventions are ratified &mdash; the Fund Convention of 1971 and the Civil Liability Convention of 1969.  It has taken far too long to have these Conventions ratified.  We are very much bound by the <Col N="1532" /> terms of both Conventions.  The Fund Convention provides for the establishment of a fund financed by oil companies for repayment of compensation for oil pollution where ship owners' liabilities exceed up to a current overall maximum of £46 million approximately. The figure in the Bill is the equivalent of £52 million approximately and the new limit will apply from 1 December next.  In short, the answer to the Senator's initial question in regard to limitations as to size, is that there is no limitation.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>Section 8 agreed to.</P>
      <P Just="Center">SECTION 9.</P>
      <P>Government amendment No. 1:</P>
      <P>In page 8, line 10, to delete &ldquo;or&rdquo; and substitute &ldquo;and&rdquo;.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatTheCope" hpid="Mr. P. Gallagher Mr. P. Gallagher">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P. Gallagher</NameTxt>
      <P>This is a technical amendment which I am bringing forward on the advice of the Attorney General.</P>
      <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
      <P>Section 9, as amended, agreed to.</P>
      <P Just="Center">SECTION 10.</P>
      <P>Government amendment No. 2:</P>
      <P>In page 8, between lines 34 and 35, to insert the following paragraph:</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>&ldquo;(e) Where, in accordance with the law of a Convention Country, an owner has limited his liability, the court, tribunal or administrative authority in that Convention Country that has the jurisdiction or power to determine liability for pollution damage and to award compensation therefor shall be exclusively competent to determine all matters relating to the appointment and distribution of any monies lodged with the court, tribunal or administrative authority, as the case may <Col N="1533" /> be, in respect of the owner's liability.&rdquo;.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatTheCope" hpid="Mr. P. Gallagher Mr. P. Gallagher">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P. Gallagher</NameTxt>
      <P>The intention of this amendment is to provide that where the owner of the ship is liable for pollution damage caused by a discharge of oil which occurred without his actual fault and when he has claimed his liability in a Convention country, the court in that country shall be exclusively competent to distribute any moneys lodged with the court.</P>
      <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
      <P>Section 10, as amended, agreed to.</P>
      <P>Section 11 agreed to.</P>
      <P Just="Center">SECTION 12.</P>
      <P>Government amendment No. 3:</P>
      <P>In page 9, between lines 37 and 38, to insert the following subsection:</P>
      <P>&ldquo;(3) Whenever the Court, on an application under subsection (1), orders the payment into court of any amount, the applicant shall comply with the order.&rdquo;.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatTheCope" hpid="Mr. P. Gallagher Mr. P. Gallagher">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P. Gallagher</NameTxt>
      <P>The purpose of this amendment is to provide that where the High Court determines the limit of the liability of the owner of a ship which has or is alleged to have incurred liability for pollution damage and orders the payment into court of an amount of money, the owner concerned must pay that sum into the court.</P>
      <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Acting Chairman Acting Chairman">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman</NameTxt>
      <P>Amendments Nos. 4, 5, 6 and 8 are related and may be discussed together.</P>
      <P>Government amendment No. 4:</P>
      <P>In page 10, line 32, to delete &ldquo;subsection (4)&rdquo; and substitute &ldquo;subsection (2)&rdquo;.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1534" />
    <Speaker pid="PatTheCope" hpid="Mr. P. Gallagher Mr. P. Gallagher">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P. Gallagher</NameTxt>
      <P>Since the Bill was published I have discovered some minor textual references in it which need to be amended.  This is the explanation for bringing forward these amendments.</P>
      <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
      <P>Government amendment No. 5:</P>
      <P>In page 10, line 40, to delete &ldquo;subsection (4)&rdquo; and substitute &ldquo;subsection (2)&rdquo;.</P>
      <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
      <P>Government amendment No. 6:</P>
      <P>In page 10, line 44, to delete &ldquo;subsection (4)&rdquo; and substitute &ldquo;subsection (2)&rdquo;.</P>
      <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
      <P>Government amendment No. 7:</P>
      <P>In page 10, line 47, to delete &ldquo;any country other than the State&rdquo;, and substitute &ldquo;a Convention Country&rdquo;.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatTheCope" hpid="Mr. P. Gallagher Mr. P. Gallagher">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P. Gallagher</NameTxt>
      <P>This is another technical amendment which I bring forward on the advice of the Attorney General.</P>
      <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
      <P>Government Amendment No. 8:</P>
      <P>In page 11, line 4, to delete &ldquo;subsection (4)&rdquo; and substitute &ldquo;subsection (2)&rdquo;.</P>
      <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
      <P>Section 12, as amended, agreed to.</P>
      <P Just="Center">SECTION 13.</P>
      <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That section 13 stand part of the Bill&rdquo;.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PadraicMcCormack" hpid="Mr. McCormack Mr. McCormack">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McCormack</NameTxt>
      <P>Section 13 (1) reads:</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Without prejudice to any power to detain a ship contained in any enactment, an inspector may stop or detain <Col N="1535" /> a ship in any harbour or a harbour-master may detain a ship in his harbour, in the State or wherever such ship may be in the State, if it appears to the inspector or, as the case may be, the harbour-master, that the owner of that ship has incurred a liability under section 7 for pollution damage caused by any ship which he owns.</P>
    <P>In other words, that ship could be detained. I would like to ask the Minister what affect this Bill would have on the Merchant Shipping Act, 1906, which was an amendment to the 1894 Act?  Under marine law this Act allowed ships under distress to come into ports to shelter or repair, other than the port of destination of the ship.  What effect will this Bill have on the provision in the amended 1906 Shipping Act?  Can ships that so come into ports according to the provisions of that Act, leave again at their will, or would this regulation abolish, contravene or in any way affect the amended 1906 Act in that regard?</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatTheCope" hpid="Mr. P. Gallagher Mr. P. Gallagher">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P. Gallagher</NameTxt>
      <P>First, I will refer to the actual section.  While this section would seem somewhat complicated, subsection (1) provides that an inspector may stop or detain a ship in any harbour or that a harbourmaster may detain a ship in his harbour if it appears to either of them that the owner of the ship has incurred a liability for pollution damage by any ship he owns.  Subsection (2) relates to the power of the court to release any ship detained if the person who has incurred a liability for pollution damage and is entitled to limit his liability has paid into court the amount determined to his liability.  We propose updating the Merchant Shipping Act, 1987. This, I hope, would strengthen the existing powers to deal with emergencies particularly those threatening pollution. I would hope measures would be included in the Bill to update the powers regarding exclusion zones, referred to earlier, around marine casualties, establishment of a vessel reporting system for the Irish coast and the provision of adequate <Col N="1536" /> powers to arrest in relation to vessels breaking the law.  That is what we propose to do in relation to the Merchant Shipping Act.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PadraicMcCormack" hpid="Mr. McCormack Mr. McCormack">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McCormack</NameTxt>
      <P>Subsection (3) reads:</P>
      <P>If a ship which has been detained pursuant to this section leaves, or attempts to leave, any harbour, terminal installation, offshore terminal or any other place in the State otherwise than in the accordance with the provisions of this Act, the master of the ship shall be guilty of an offence.</P>
      <P>I am afraid that inclusion in the new Bill would deter ships from coming into ports other than the ports of destination to shelter or for repair, and that worse damage could be caused to the ship by remaining on the open seas during a storm if repair was necessary.  I am afraid this provision would discourage ships from coming into ports or harbours under distress or for repair.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatTheCope" hpid="Mr. P. Gallagher Mr. P. Gallagher">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P. Gallagher</NameTxt>
      <P>It is a question of which is the better of two evils &mdash; whether they pollute the high seas or pollute the bay in which they have come to shelter. It is a very difficult question.  If a ship is in distress it will come into the bay and if there is damage caused we can detain it.  It is a matter of differentiating and deciding.  We have the example of the <i>Kowloon Bridge.</i>  What was the right thing to have done at that stage?  We are all very wise after the event.  As I said earlier, there is an insurance claim in at the moment and I appreciate that Senators do not want to pursue this while the claim is not settled because we would not want to prejudice our case in any way.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>Sections 14 and 15 agreed to.</P>
      <P Just="Center">SECTION 16.</P>
      <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That section 16 stand part of the Bill.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1537" />
    <Speaker pid="PadraicMcCormack" hpid="Mr. McCormack Mr. McCormack">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McCormack</NameTxt>
      <P>Is it the custom for the Chair to read out each section on Committee Stage?  At the rate we are passing sections we could miss something we would want to bring up, but maybe it is up to Senators to be vigilant.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatTheCope" hpid="Mr. P. Gallagher Mr. P. Gallagher">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P. Gallagher</NameTxt>
      <P>I appreciate that it is very difficult to understand the terminology of this legislation.  Section 16 is very long and if it was helpful, I could bring Senators through it subsection by subsection.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PadraicMcCormack" hpid="Mr. McCormack Mr. McCormack">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McCormack</NameTxt>
      <P>I would appreciate that.  This section mentions that a ship registered in the State shall not carry in bulk a cargo of more than 2,000 tonnes of oil unless there is in force in respect of the ship a contract of insurance, or other financial security, satisfying such requirements as may be prescribed.  In the case of a ship registered in the State, there is a limit on the cargo, but apparently there is no limit on the cargo of a ship not registered in the State but that might be passing near our shores.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatTheCope" hpid="Mr. P. Gallagher Mr. P. Gallagher">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P. Gallagher</NameTxt>
      <P>The quick answer to that is that that is done in their own country of registry.  This section provides that a ship registered in the State shall not carry in bulk a cargo of 2,000 tonnes or more of oil and must have a contract of insurance or other financial security in respect of such cargo.  That is done in the country of registry.  If there is any other section the Senators want me to bring them through, I will certainly do so.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TomFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Fitzgerald Mr. Fitzgerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Fitzgerald</NameTxt>
      <P>I want clarification on this small point: it is basically the cargo of these ships that is covered, not the fuel they carry for use on the oil tankers.  Is the fuel for its own use covered by the insurance if something happens?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatTheCope" hpid="Mr. P. Gallagher Mr. P. Gallagher">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P. Gallagher</NameTxt>
      <P>This question raises its head very frequently and I will give a very definite answer so that there can be absolutely no ambiguity.  There may be a misconception that this Bill only covers boats carrying oil as cargo, and I am pleased to have the opportunity of <Col N="1538" /> informing the House that the Bill covers liability and compensation for oil pollution damage from laden oil tankers, irrespective of size &mdash; Senator McCormack asked earlier about the size &mdash; and irrespective of whether the spillage is from the cargo oil or bunker oil.  So whether it is either or both, it is covered under this section.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>Section 17 agreed to.</P>
      <P Just="Center">SECTION 18.</P>
      <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That section 18 stand part of the Bill.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PadraicMcCormack" hpid="Mr. McCormack Mr. McCormack">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McCormack</NameTxt>
      <P>This section reads:</P>
      <P>The provisions of section 503 (1) (d) of the Merchant Shipping Act 1894 shall be deemed to apply to any liability for cost of preventing or mitigating pollution damage which is not covered by this Act.</P>
      <P>This refers again to the pollution damage to which Senator de Buitléar referred in his contribution on Second Stage.  How do we determine pollution damage not covered in this measure?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatTheCope" hpid="Mr. P. Gallagher Mr. P. Gallagher">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P. Gallagher</NameTxt>
      <P>This section provides that section 503 (1) (d) of the Merchant Shipping Act, 1894, applies to any liability relating to the cost of preventing or mitigating pollution damage which is not covered by this Act.  In short, it is a catch-all one in order to ensure that everything is covered.  It was necessary to go back to the Merchant Shipping Act of 1894, section 503 (1) (d) which reads:</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Where any loss or damage is caused to any other vessel, or to any goods, merchandise, or other things whatsoever on board any other vessel, by reason of the improper navigation of the ship; be liable to damages beyond the following amounts; (that is to say), (i) In respect of loss of life or personal injury, either alone or together with loss of or damage to vessels, goods, <Col N="1539" /> merchandise, or other things, an aggregate amount not exceeding fifteen pounds for each ton of their ship's tonnage and in respect of loss of or damage to vessels, goods, merchandise or other things whether there be in addition loss of life or person injury or not, an aggregate amount not exceeding eight pounds for each ton of their ship's tonnage....</P>
    <P>We wanted to include in section 18 a provision relating to section 503, which I referred to, of the Shipping Act.  In short, it is a catch-all to ensure that everything is absolutely covered.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PadraicMcCormack" hpid="Mr. McCormack Mr. McCormack">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McCormack</NameTxt>
      <P>The figures the Minister gave of £15 and £8 per ton seem very small.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatTheCope" hpid="Mr. P. Gallagher Mr. P. Gallagher">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P. Gallagher</NameTxt>
      <P>They are very small by today's standards but I am referring to 1894 and I can assure the Senator that there will be a <i>pro rata</i> increase and those will be up-dated.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PadraicMcCormack" hpid="Mr. McCormack Mr. McCormack">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McCormack</NameTxt>
      <P>Will that <i>pro rata</i> increase become part of the Bill then? We accept that they refer to an 1894 Bill which is nearly 100 years old now but where do we get those increased <i>pro rata</i>?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatTheCope" hpid="Mr. P. Gallagher Mr. P. Gallagher">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P. Gallagher</NameTxt>
      <P>There is pressure on our Department and the Government have a lot of legislation coming before both Houses.  One of the Bills at the end of the pipeline at the moment is the Bill up-dating the Merchant Shipping Act of 1894.  When we have the opportunity of bringing that Bill before the House we will have the up-dated figures.  They are not in this Bill because it is a matter for the up-dating of the Merchant Shipping Act, 1894.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P Just="Center">SECTION 19.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Amendments Nos. 9, 10 and 11 are related and may be discussed together.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="1540" /> Government amendment No. 9:</P>
    <P>In page 13, line 38, to delete &ldquo;as may be calculated in accordance with&rdquo; and substitute &ldquo;as may be determined by the Assembly of the Fund Convention and certified by the Director of the Fund, any such sum to be determined in accordance with&rdquo;.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatTheCope" hpid="Mr. P. Gallagher Mr. P. Gallagher">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P. Gallagher</NameTxt>
      <P>Following the publication of the Bill, the secretariat of the International Oil Pollution Compensation Fund wrote to me and suggested that I might consider making some minor changes in the Bill and, having carefully considered the matter, I have decided to bring forward amendment Nos. 9, 10 and 11 to section 19.</P>
      <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
      <P>Government amendment No. 10:</P>
      <P>In page 13, line 47, after &ldquo;payable&rdquo; to insert the following &ldquo;,such interest to be at such rate as may, from time to time, be determined by the Assembly of the Fund Convention&rdquo;.</P>
      <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
      <P>Government amendment No. 11:</P>
      <P>In page 14, between lines 5 and 6, to insert the following definition:</P>
      <P>&ldquo; `the Assembly of the Fund Convention' means the Assembly specified in Article 17 of the Fund Convention.&rdquo;.</P>
      <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
      <P>Section 19, as amended, agreed to.</P>
      <P Just="Center">SECTION 20.</P>
      <P>Government amendment No. 12:</P>
      <P>In page 14, to delete lines 34 to 47, and substitute the following subsections:</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>&ldquo;(4) The Fund shall not be liable for pollution damage if it is proved that the discharge of oil which caused the <Col N="1541" /> pollution damage resulted from an act of war, hostilities, civil war or insurrection or was caused by oil which has escaped or been discharged from a warship or other ship owned or operated by the State or by a Convention Country and used, at the time of the incident, only on government noncommercial service.</P>
    <P>(5)  The Fund may be wholly or partly relieved from liability for pollution damage if it is established that the discharge of oil which caused the pollution damage was due wholly or partly to&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    <P>(a)  anything done or left undone by the person who suffered the pollution damage with intent to cause damage;</P>
    <P>or</P>
    <P>(b)  the negligence of the person who suffered the pollution damage:</P>
    <P>Provided that this subsection shall not apply to the cost of any reasonable measures taken after an incident has occured to prevent or to minimise pollution damage.&rdquo;.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatTheCope" hpid="Mr. P. Gallagher Mr. P. Gallagher">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P. Gallagher</NameTxt>
      <P>The purpose of this amendment is to provide that the International Oil Pollution Compensation Fund may be wholly or partially relieved from liability for pollution damage in certain circumstances.  Under the Bill as published the fund was wholly relieved from such liability in stated circumstances. In considering this amendment Senators may wish to know that subsection (4) in this amendment is indentical to the first two lines at paragraph (a) of subsection (4) of the Bill as published except at &ldquo;operated by the State or by a Convention Country&rdquo; which has been inserted instead of &ldquo;operated by a State&rdquo;.</P>
      <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Acting Chairman Acting Chairman">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman</NameTxt>
      <P>Amendments Nos. 13 and 14 are related and may be discussed together.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="1542" /> Government amendment No. 13:</P>
    <P>In page 15, to delete lines 1 to 12, and substitute the following subsections:</P>
    <P>&ldquo;(5) Subject to subsections (6) and (7), the Fund shall, in accordance with the provisions of this Act, indemnify the owner of a ship or his guarantor against this liability under section 7 or 10.</P>
    <P>(6) A liability shall not be imposed on the Fund under subsection (5) in any case where it is established that the pollution damage resulted from the wilful misconduct of the owner of the ship.</P>
    <P>(7) The Fund may be wholly or partly relieved from its liability under subsection (5) if it is established that, because of the actual fault or privity of the owner of the ship, the pollution damage was wholly or partly occasioned by the non-compliance with the provisions of any Convention in relation to&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    <P>(a)  Safety at Sea, or</P>
    <P>(b)  Pollution of the Sea,</P>
    <P>which may be specified by, or in accordance with, the Fund Convention.&rdquo;.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatTheCope" hpid="Mr. P. Gallagher Mr. P. Gallagher">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P. Gallagher</NameTxt>
      <P>The intention of amendments Nos. 13 and 14 is to bring the text of certain subsections of the Bill closer in line with the wording used in corresponding articles and conventions setting up the International Oil Compensation Fund.</P>
      <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
      <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That section 20, as amended, stand part of the Bill.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PadraicMcCormack" hpid="Mr. McCormack Mr. McCormack">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McCormack</NameTxt>
      <P>Can the Minister clarify the meaning of &ldquo;the Fund&rdquo; in the phrase &ldquo;the Fund shall be liable for pollution damage in the State&rdquo;?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatTheCope" hpid="Mr. P. Gallagher Mr. P. Gallagher">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P. Gallagher</NameTxt>
      <P>The fund is defined <Col N="1543" /> in the earlier sections of the Bill.  We placed a copy of the International Oil Pollution Compensation Fund in the Library of the House for the benefit of Senators.  The fund is known as the Compensation Fund and prior to the enactment of this Bill voluntary subscriptions were made to it.  Now there will be a statutory obligation to subscribe to this fund.  One may pose the question of the statutory position and whether this will increase the price of oil.  I am quite satisfied that the majority of vessels carrying oil as cargo were covered under the voluntary fund and the fact that it is now statutory to subscribe to this fund will not in any way increase the price of oil overall.  I may have expanded there a little but, in short, the fund referred to is the International Oil Pollution Compensation Fund and a copy of this is available in the Library to Members of the House.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PadraicMcCormack" hpid="Mr. McCormack Mr. McCormack">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McCormack</NameTxt>
      <P>Have all oil and cargo owners to subscribe to that fund?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatTheCope" hpid="Mr. P. Gallagher Mr. P. Gallagher">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P. Gallagher</NameTxt>
      <P>As far as I understand, all cargo and shipping owners have subscribed to that fund.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="VivianOCallaghan" hpid="Mr. O'Callaghan Mr. O'Callaghan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Callaghan</NameTxt>
      <P>The timing of the disbursement of the fund is a problem.  I am aware of the complex nature of the fund but could the Minister tell us whether, if somebody qualifies to claim, there is a timescale involved under the Convention in the disbursement of the fund?  It may not relate to this question.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatTheCope" hpid="Mr. P. Gallagher Mr. P. Gallagher">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P. Gallagher</NameTxt>
      <P>It is fortunate possibly that there is not a timescale involved in this.  There would be a preliminary claim as is normal in all insurances and then there would be the factual one. There is no cut off point in relation to this.  For the benefit of Senator McCormack, the matter of the International Oil Pollution Compensation Fund is set out clearly in section 19 of the Bill.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P Just="Center">
      <Col N="1544" /> SECTION 21.</P>
    <P>Government amendment No. 14:</P>
    <P>In page 15, to delete lines 18 to 21, and substitute the following:</P>
    <P>(2)  Where the Fund in accordance with section 20 (5) indemnifies the owner of a ship or his guarantor, any such indemnity shall not exceed that part of such owner's, or his guarantor's, liability under this Act which is&mdash;&mdash;&rdquo;.</P>
    <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
    <P>Government amendment No. 15:</P>
    <P>In page 15, to delete lines 30 to 41, and substitute the following subsection:</P>
    <P>(3)  For the purposes of this section &ldquo;the aggregate amount of compensation&rdquo; means the maximum amount of compensation payable by the Fund by reason of pollution damage occasioned by any one incident whether such compensation is payable by reason of any one or more of the following, that is to say&mdash;</P>
    <P>(a)  the provisions of this Act,</P>
    <P>(b)  the provisions of any law in any Convention Country, or</P>
    <P>(c)  the provisions of the Fund Convention.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatTheCope" hpid="Mr. P. Gallagher Mr. P. Gallagher">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P. Gallagher</NameTxt>
      <P>The purpose of this amendment is to extend what constitutes the aggregate amount of compensation in section 21.</P>
      <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
      <P>Section 21, as amended, agreed to.</P>
      <P Just="Center">SECTION 22.</P>
      <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That section 22 stand part of the Bill.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PadraicMcCormack" hpid="Mr. McCormack Mr. McCormack">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McCormack</NameTxt>
      <P>I would like to ask the Minister for clarification on the following wording in subsection (1):</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="1545" /> After three years from the date on which the pollution damage occurred unless an action for compensation has already been commenced under this Act, the owner of a ship or his guarantor and the Fund has been notified pursuant to rules of court of the action by any party thereto, or after six years...</P>
    <P>I would like further clarification of the necessity for three and six years in those cases.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatTheCope" hpid="Mr. P. Gallagher Mr. P. Gallagher">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P. Gallagher</NameTxt>
      <P>What we are doing is ratifying both Conventions.  We are very much bound by the terms of those Conventions.  This section would be the converse of the question asked by Senator O'Callaghan.  This sets out the time limits which must be met when bringing an action against the fund.  It sets out the time limit which must be met by the owner of a ship or his guarantor when seeking indemnification from the fund pursuant to section 20 (5).</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P Just="Center">SECTION 23.</P>
      <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That section 23 stand part of the Bill.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatTheCope" hpid="Mr. P. Gallagher Mr. P. Gallagher">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P. Gallagher</NameTxt>
      <P>To clear something for the Senators, there is a time limit on claims but not on disbursement.  There is a difference and I think this section spells it out.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PadraicMcCormack" hpid="Mr. McCormack Mr. McCormack">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McCormack</NameTxt>
      <P>Section 23 reads:</P>
      <P>Where an incident which results in the Funds being liable for compensation or indemnity under section 20 occasions pollution damage in the State or in one or more other Convention Countries, proceedings under this Act may be taken, and the incidents may for all incidental purposes be treated as having occurred, in any place in the State.</P>
      <P>How would you cover incidents that do not occur in State waters for example?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1546" />
    <Speaker pid="PatTheCope" hpid="Mr. P. Gallagher Mr. P. Gallagher">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P. Gallagher</NameTxt>
      <P>Let us take an example.  If it happens in the Irish Sea it can be prosecuted in either or both jurisdictions.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TomFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Fitzgerald Mr. Fitzgerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Fitzgerald</NameTxt>
      <P>If it happened in a harbour or pier in Ireland and the pollution travelled to England or <i>vice versa</i>, who would take the action and how would you go about it?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatTheCope" hpid="Mr. P. Gallagher Mr. P. Gallagher">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P. Gallagher</NameTxt>
      <P>I can assure the House that if it happens outside the economic zone, some 200 miles from this coast or if it happens off the coast of France or the coast of England, we will not be found wanting as far as action is concerned. There will be no question of any ambiguity there.  We would take the action first and find out afterwards.  I am quite happy that we could be in the position that we could take the action.  It can be done in either or both counties where there is common damage.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PadraicMcCormack" hpid="Mr. McCormack Mr. McCormack">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McCormack</NameTxt>
      <P>It reminds me of another reported incident recently where somebody was trying to dump sewage waste or talking about dumping sewage waste off the Porcupine Bank.  Does this Bill only relate to pollution of the seas by oil as the Title of the Bill suggests?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatTheCope" hpid="Mr. P. Gallagher Mr. P. Gallagher">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P. Gallagher</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes, it is the Oil Pollution of the Sea (Civil Liability and Compensation) Bill.  That would cover cargo vessels only carrying oil as cargo. It would also cover a ship carrying oil as cargo.  If it has a spillage from its bunker oil it is also included in this Bill.  But if a cargo ship carrying grain or any other materials or products has a spillage from its bunker then that is covered on a separate list.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>Sections 24 to 26, inclusive, agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P Just="Center">
      <Col N="1547" /> SECTION 27.</P>
    <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That section 27 stand part of the Bill.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="PadraicMcCormack" hpid="Mr. McCormack Mr. McCormack">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McCormack</NameTxt>
      <P>Section 27 (2) reads:</P>
      <P>Whenever the Court makes an order on foot of an application made persuant to section 26 for the enforcement of a determination, the order may provide for the payment of the reasonable costs of and incidental to the application and such costs shall be recoverable as if they were sums recoverable under the determination.</P>
      <P>I would like further clarification of that. Does that mean after an offender would be taken to court that such costs should be recoverable?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatTheCope" hpid="Mr. P. Gallagher Mr. P. Gallagher">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P. Gallagher</NameTxt>
      <P>This provides that the High Court makes an order relating to an application for the enforcement of a determination.  The High Court order can allow for the payment of the costs of the application.  These costs can be recovered as if they were recoverable under the determination.  This is basically to cover the costs, which in cases such as these could be very substantial, in addition to any other damage.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="VivianOCallaghan" hpid="Mr. O'Callaghan Mr. O'Callaghan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Callaghan</NameTxt>
      <P>Is that to cover the cost of the agency operating on behalf of the State.  Take for example a county council pollution team.  Are they the costs the Minister is referring to?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatTheCope" hpid="Mr. P. Gallagher Mr. P. Gallagher">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P. Gallagher</NameTxt>
      <P>No.  It is the cost of the application to the court.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="VivianOCallaghan" hpid="Mr. O'Callaghan Mr. O'Callaghan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Callaghan</NameTxt>
      <P>The actual legal proceedings?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatTheCope" hpid="Mr. P. Gallagher Mr. P. Gallagher">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P. Gallagher</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P Just="Center">SECTION 28.</P>
      <P>Government amendment No. 16:</P>
      <P>In page 18, to delete lines 11 and 12.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1548" />
    <Speaker pid="PatTheCope" hpid="Mr. P. Gallagher Mr. P. Gallagher">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P. Gallagher</NameTxt>
      <P>The thinking behind this amendment is to permit proceedings to be taken in several Convention countries which apply to the same incident. This is in line with the provisions of both the Liability Convention and the Fund Convention and brings us back to questions which were posed earlier.  This will cover that eventually.</P>
      <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
      <P>Section 28, as amended, agreed to.</P>
      <P>Section 29 agreed to.</P>
      <P Just="Center">SECTION 30.</P>
      <P>Government amendment No. 17:</P>
      <P>In page 20, to delete lines 16 to 20, and substitute the following:</P>
      <P>&ldquo;(3) The Court may relieve the owner of a ship, his guarantor or the Fund wholly or partially from liability to a person for pollution damage if it is proved that the damage resulted wholly or partially from the negligence of that person or that the damage was contributed to by any act or omission of such person which was calculated to cause damage.&rdquo;.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="VivianOCallaghan" hpid="Mr. O'Callaghan Mr. O'Callaghan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Callaghan</NameTxt>
      <P>In relation to relieving the owner of a ship I take it that relates solely to a court action, in other words, in the absence of the ability of the owner to pay his compensation the ship will be taken.  It does not relate to relieving the master of a ship in the course of the crisis itself.  Does that section have any relevance in that department? During the <i>Kowloon Bridge</i> saga there were suggestions subsequent to the disaster that it might have been more opportune for the State agencies involved, or the Navy, to take possession of the ship during the crisis.  I take it that this section could not be used as a device in that crisis. I accept that it is intended to serve a different purpose, but could we use it as a device to take possession of a ship in such eventuality?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1549" />
    <Speaker pid="PatTheCope" hpid="Mr. P. Gallagher Mr. P. Gallagher">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P. Gallagher</NameTxt>
      <P>There is provision in legislation in the event of a cargo vessel polluting that that vessel can be detained. Furthermore, we will have the powers under the proposed Act to detain any other vessels owned by that individual or company.  There is ample cover for eventualities.</P>
      <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
      <P>Section 30, as amended, agreed to.</P>
      <P>Sections 31 to 33, inclusive, agreed to.</P>
      <P Just="Center">SECTION 34.</P>
      <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That section 34 stand part of the Bill.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PadraicMcCormack" hpid="Mr. McCormack Mr. McCormack">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McCormack</NameTxt>
      <P>Under the powers of detention in section 34 what is the situation if a ship should break up when detained?  What is the position there <i>vis-à-vis</i> the 1894 Act and the 1906 (Amendment) Act if a ship under detention should break up or cause pollution?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatTheCope" hpid="Mr. P. Gallagher Mr. P. Gallagher">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P. Gallagher</NameTxt>
      <P>This section provides for certain powers and the inspector, harbour master or the official appointed by the Minister for the Marine would obtain an order from a district justice allowing the ship to be detained for 48 hours.  Where proceedings are pending against the master of a ship the district justice may require the inspector or the harbour master to detain the ship until the proceedings are completed. There need not necessarily be any pollution damage.  If the vessel is suspected and if all the conditions are not complied with, it can be detained for this time.  An example would be the insurance certificate.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>In the case of pollution being caused while the ship is detained then the ship has polluted and we would lodge our claim to the fund.  I do not know if that answers the Senator's question.  Is he suggesting that as a result of detention the pollution would take place?  Every ship is detained.  It is taken into port and detained there.  It is very difficult to <Col N="1550" /> comprehend how this could happen deliberately or as a result of its detention by the harbour master who would obtain an order from the District Court.  It is very difficult to understand how that could happen but if it did happen there is cover under the legislation to claim against the fund.  Of course, there is also provision in the legislation that, if damage is done deliberately and in other ways, we would not receive compensation.</P>
    <Speaker pid="VivianOCallaghan" hpid="Mr. O'Callaghan Mr. O'Callaghan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Callaghan</NameTxt>
      <P>In relation to the status of the inspector, I am aware that in some cases in the appointment of harbour masters certain certificates are required in relation to their ability and experience to handle certain types of vessels referred to normally in the oil business as VLCCs. I understand that there are certain sizes of ships of which certain inspectors would not be deemed sufficiently well qualified to take possession.  Is the Minister happy that there is adequate provision in this section whereby such an inspector would have the status required to take possession of the ship in the circumstances outlined in the Bill.  I understand a foreign going master's ticket is the normal requirement to take possession of a super tanker.  I am aware that in some of the bigger ports on the Continent, to qualify for a harbour master post one has to have this adequacy of certification to handle VLCCs.  Is the Minister happy that the inspector would always have such a qualification?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatTheCope" hpid="Mr. P. Gallagher Mr. P. Gallagher">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P. Gallagher</NameTxt>
      <P>Under earlier sections of the Bill when we referred to the inspector, the inspector would mean a person appointed to be an inspector by warrant of the Minister, or a person appointed to be a surveyor of ships by warrant of the Minister under sections 7 to 24 of the Merchant Shipping Act, 1894, or a sea fisheries protection officer.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I fully appreciate the point made by Senator O'Callaghan that there may be inspectors who would not be qualified to carry out an inspection of one of these super tankers.  All harbour masters at the major harbour ports are all qualified and <Col N="1551" /> many of them have experience on board. May I go from the sublime to the ridiculous and say that I do not anticipate that one of the super tankers which Senator O'Callaghan refers to would be going into Dingle?</P>
    <P>I am quite satisfied that the legislation adequately covers this.  From discussions I have had with my officials I am quite satisfied that there is ample cover.</P>
    <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
    <P>Sections 35 to 39, inclusive, agreed to.</P>
    <P Just="Center">SECTION 40.</P>
    <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That section 40 stand part of the Bill.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="PadraicMcCormack" hpid="Mr. McCormack Mr. McCormack">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McCormack</NameTxt>
      <P>Section 40 reads:</P>
      <P>Where it appears to the court imposing a fine for an offence under this Act that a person has incurred, or will incur, expense in removing any pollution or making good any damage attributable to the offence, the court may order that the whole or part of the fine be paid to that person for, or towards, defraying that expense.</P>
      <P>I would like further clarification on that from the point of view of where the court imposes a fine for an offence under this Act.  Would a local authority, for example, who would incur expenses in having pollution cleared up on their coastline be likely to be compensated in that regard from that source?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatTheCope" hpid="Mr. P. Gallagher Mr. P. Gallagher">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P. Gallagher</NameTxt>
      <P>The section provides that the court may order the payment of a fine or part of same to a person who will incur expenses in making good the pollution damage.  That, of course, will cover any person or local authority.  It would be a catch-all provision.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PadraicMcCormack" hpid="Mr. McCormack Mr. McCormack">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McCormack</NameTxt>
      <P>Or any person?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatTheCope" hpid="Mr. P. Gallagher Mr. P. Gallagher">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P. Gallagher</NameTxt>
      <P>Or any person. Under the wording in that section, line <Col N="1552" /> 49 of section 40, says that the court may do this.  It covers any person or local authority.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PadraicMcCormack" hpid="Mr. McCormack Mr. McCormack">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McCormack</NameTxt>
      <P>Does that become a matter for the court to order or would there have to be a claim from any person or local authority or voluntary body or whatever to seek compensation for the expenses incurred in the clearing of pollution?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatTheCope" hpid="Mr. P. Gallagher Mr. P. Gallagher">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P. Gallagher</NameTxt>
      <P>That section would be a matter for the courts.  There is discretion there; it might cover it.  It is a question for the courts.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>Section 41 agreed to.</P>
      <P Just="Center">SECTION 42.</P>
      <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That section 42 stand part of the Bill.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PadraicMcCormack" hpid="Mr. McCormack Mr. McCormack">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McCormack</NameTxt>
      <P>This section says the Act shall not apply to any warship or any ship for the time being used by the Government for purposes other than for commercial purposes.  What would happen if one of those vessels caused pollution?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatTheCope" hpid="Mr. P. Gallagher Mr. P. Gallagher">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P. Gallagher</NameTxt>
      <P>Subsection (1) is self-explanatory but subsection 2 provides that the Minister can grant exemption from the Act to a ship or class of ships where he is satisfied the exemptions would not lead to reduced liability for pollution or in reduced means for meeting some of the liability.  In a situation like this, the Minister where he is satisfied that the exemption would not result in reduced liability for pollution or indeed means for meeting such liability could exempt any ship registered in the State or any class of ship so registered from all or any of the provisions of the Act.  This section, like many other sections is very much dependent on the fund conventions, the conventions of 1969 and 1971 and the protocols of 1976.  We are <Col N="1553" /> very much bound by those conventions. The wording here is almost imposed upon us.  Since we are accepting the conventions, if there is pollution as a result of a warship or by any ship for the time being used by the Government of the State, then there would be no cover there, there would be exemption from the Act.  This has been thought out not just by ourselves but prior to the fund conventions those involved in the drafting of it said that it would be in very exceptional circumstances and there would need to be extenuating circumstances. It goes so far to say a &ldquo;warship&rdquo;, I hope that in an eventuality such as that we will be around to claim.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="VivianOCallaghan" hpid="Mr. O'Callaghan Mr. O'Callaghan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Callaghan</NameTxt>
      <P>Just a clarification on section 42 (1) and (2), I note that the Bill relates to warships, the property of the State.  I wonder what is the situation in relation to warships that visit the State on courtesy visits.  We are aware of the ongoing confrontation between various groups, for example, Greenpeace groups in other countries where they have effectively confronted visiting warships, have boarded these ships and so on and have caused considerable embarrassment to various Governments, fortunately not here.  I wonder whether there is a provision in the Act to cover this?  Obviously, the visiting ship would not be deemed to be a commercial ship; it is a warship but it is not a warship belonging to the State. If there was pollution &mdash; which would be most unusual in relation to a warship on a courtesy call to this State &mdash; would it fall into any particular category embraced in this Act?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatTheCope" hpid="Mr. P. Gallagher Mr. P. Gallagher">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P. Gallagher</NameTxt>
      <P>I would expect that any warship would not be an oil tanker so, obviously, even if it was here on a courtesy call and caused pollution the pollution would be from the bunkers or from its own fuel oil which would be covered under separate legislation.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PadraicMcCormack" hpid="Mr. McCormack Mr. McCormack">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McCormack</NameTxt>
      <P>On that matter, the Minister mentioned a few times during the course of his replies today, and perhaps before he finishes he will give this <Col N="1554" /> House an idea of when that separate legislation may be introduced.  While all the Senators are satisfied with this Bill, and we welcome it in itself, we might get the false impression that the Bill caters for all the likely pollution.  We know from the Minister's clarifications and the proper manner in which he answered all the questions that it does not cater for all the likely causes of pollution.  I would like to ask the Minister for clarification on the effect of this Bill.  It covers oil tankers but it has no effect on cargo ships.  It would not even cover the <i>Kowloon Bridge</i> case referred to earlier.</P>
      <P>I thought this Bill did not go far enough but having accepted the Minister's response to that I would have to ask when it is proposed to have legislation that will cover the other types of pollution, apart from pollution from oil tankers &mdash; which would be a major pollutant if it happened &mdash; pollution from cargo ships and other pollution.  When is it expected that that legislation will be introduced because people might get the false impression that now that the Houses of the Oireachtas have dealt with the Oil Pollution of the Sea Bill we are covered to deal with all oil pollution.  It is quite clear we would not be covered in respect of oil pollution from the engine oil of a ship.  I anticipate the other legislation with interest and hope it will come very soon.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatTheCope" hpid="Mr. P. Gallagher Mr. P. Gallagher">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P. Gallagher</NameTxt>
      <P>The position is that we are covered for pollution.  That was proven in the <i>Kowloon Bridge</i> situation. The Senator asks what would be the the situation if we had another <i>Kowloon Bridge</i> incident in the morning.  I do not want to sound arlarmist and I do not think the Senator wants to sound alarm bells, but if it happens we will know and we will be better able to deal with it in practice.  The legislation is there and we have a claim for £1.743 million with the fund convention.  I may have given a wrong impression but we are strengthening the legislation for the <i>Kowloon Bridge</i> situation.  Possibly the fact that this Bill is almost through this House &mdash; and I hope will go through the Dáil as quickly as it has gone through here &mdash;<Col N="1555" /> and that the other legislation will be introduced as quickly as possible may give the wrong impression.  I think Senators will appreciate this.  I do not think that any Government &mdash; I am not being political; I am being factual &mdash; over the past decades have had as much legislation and as many Bills ready for the House.  My difficulty is finding time to get into both Houses with these Bills.  They are almost ready and as soon as we can get them through the Houses we will have them enacted.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="VivianOCallaghan" hpid="Mr. O'Callaghan Mr. O'Callaghan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Callaghan</NameTxt>
      <P>I welcome the Minister's comments in this regard because it is important that we would, to some degree, explode this myth that nothing has been done in relation to the <i>Kowloon Bridge.</i>  It should be remembered that in actual fact it was this day 12 months ago that the <i>Kowloon Bridge</i> went on the rocks in west Cork and did all the damage.  It should also be said that less than six months after that devastation took place the beaches of west Cork were usable.  I live in that area and am aware of the fact.  That should have been said at the outset.  Unfortunately, I was not here for the initial debate on this Bill to record my appreciation of the Department of Communications officials particularly.  I had occasion to be very close to the operations on that occasion, given it was based in my own town.  It was most gratifying to see that we had officials of the competence and calibre of the people who were in evidence in Bantry and west Cork in November and December last year.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>This was a matter that was commented on by people who came from all over the world to observe the crisis.  The competence, the expedition, and the controlling influence in evidence from the all-party steering group who were on the site within six or eight hours of the crisis occurring impressed everybody.  It was most gratifying for me, as a public representative, to see that we had within our Departments people with sufficient expertise and competence to handle a crisis such as that.  We should also be mindful of the fact that less than 12 months after the crisis occurred we have <Col N="1556" /> our very sizeable and substantial compensation claim submitted to this international convention.</P>
    <P>I should also say, as a member of Cork County Council, that substantial compensation has already been paid to the county council in Cork to offset the substantial costs they incurred having an anti-pollution group in place for virtually six or seven months of last year.  It is important that we should record the Minister's undertaking here that in actual fact we already have almost sufficient legislation on the Statute Book.  The way this affair developed over the past year is proof positive that this legislation is in place.  We now have our compensation claims submitted.  I would hope that, on the basis of what the Minister said here this afternoon, we could expect a fairly expeditious conclusion to this claim.</P>
    <P>There is one other point I would like to touch on for the Minister's consideration. It is in relation to private claims.  I accept that this is not within the brief of the Minister.  A considerable amount of foot-dragging is quite often done by the insurance group covering the <i>Kowloon Bridge</i>, as is referred to in the Minister's earlier remarks.  There is an amount of foot dragging going on from time to time in relation to the settlement of smaller claims on the ground.  I am aware, for example, that a sizeable pollution took place in Bantry Bay in 1976 from the <i>Universe Leader.</i>  Some of those claims have not yet been paid after 11 years because of a line-by-line examination of every aspect of the submissions made by the solicitors on behalf of the claimants.  I know that it is not a matter of responsibility for the Minister but I should say that people are concerned lest the impression be given that all is well. While the Government can proceed and resolve their compensation claims &mdash; and it is evident here today that the Minister is doing that &mdash; in relation to the claims against the <i>Kowloon Bridge</i>, the people on the ground, local fishermen and so on have not found their problems so easily redressed.  I welcome the Minister's comments here this afternoon and I support his point that there is a substantial <Col N="1557" /> amount of legislation quite suitable to process these claims in place at present. It is evident here this afternoon that we are pursuing those claims through the proper channels.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PadraicMcCormack" hpid="Mr. McCormack Mr. McCormack">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McCormack</NameTxt>
      <P>I would like to join with Senator Callaghan in complimenting the Department of the Environment officials and Minister Mitchell on the quick and thorough action that was taken in the <i>Kowloon Bridge</i> case.  I did not wish to imply anything to the contrary.  I understand from the Minister's reply that the amount of Bills now going through the Seanad seems to show an increase on previous occasions.  I am only speaking from my short experience in the Seanad. In fact, this Bill itself was introduced in the Seanad.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>Sections 43 and 44 agreed to.</P>
      <P>Title agreed to.</P>
      <P>Bill reported with amendments and received for final consideration.</P>
      <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That the Bill do now pass.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonDeBuitlear" hpid="Eamon de Buitléar Eamon de Buitléar">
      <NameTxt>Eamon de Buitléar</NameTxt>
      <P>Níl le rá agamsa ach gur mhaith liom mo bheannacht a thabhairt don Bhille seo agus mo bhuíochas a ghabháil leis An Aire as ucht an Bille a thabhairt chomh fada seo.  Ba mhaith liom freisin ag an bpointe seo tréaslú don Rialtas as ucht Roinn na Mara a bhunú.  B'aisteach nár bunaíodh a leithéid seo de Roinn i bhfad ó shin.  Ach ar chaoi ar bith, is comhartha é seo go bhfuilimid ag dúiseacht suas faoi dheireadh thiar thall agus go dtuigeann an Rialtas an tábhacht a bhaineann le fairrgí na tíre seo.  Tuigeann an tAire go maith a bhfuil ráite agam ach ar eagla nach dtuigeann roinnt des na Seanadóirí mo chuid cainte, déarfaidh mé arís é, agus b'fhéidir níos mó, i dteanga a thuigeann chuile dhuine.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I would like to congratulate again the Minister and all those concerned in taking <Col N="1558" /> the Bill to this stage.  I would also like to take this opportunity to congratulate the Government on forming a Department of the Marine.  Strange to say that we have not had such a Department up to now.  I take it as a sign of the Government's realisation of just how important our seas are and that they are very much a part of our environment and indeed of our whole economy.  Only a year or two ago we had the amazing situation that the only research vessel we had was about to be taken out of the water for good because it was said at the time that we could not afford the cost of keeping it on the ocean.  How we are to value our environment or to know what it has to offer if we do not carry out research is beyond me.</P>
    <P>I would like to emphasise once again what I said on the last occasion when this Bill was before the House, that is that we must do our utmost to prevent these incidences of oil pollution by having proper inspections and where these incidences do occur we must be prepared to act with all possible speed and with proper equipment.  It will save the country a tremendous amount of money and in the long run protect our environment.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatTheCope" hpid="Minister of State at the Department of the Marine (Mr. P. Gallagher) Minister of State at the Department of the Marine (Mr. P. Gallagher)">
      <NameTxt>Minister of State at the Department of the Marine (Mr. P. Gallagher)</NameTxt>
      <P>Ba mhaith liom mo bhuíochas a ghabháil leis na Seanadóirí go léir a thaispeáin inniu an oiread sin suime atá acu san Bhille seo agus san fhairrge agus an timpeallacht. B'fhéidir nach bhfaighimid an oiread sin airgid agus ba ghnách agus a bheas de dhíth orainn ach bí cinnte, am ar bith a tharlós rud mar seo, go gcuirfimid chuige agus go bhfaighimid gach cineál eolais gur féidir a fháil ionas go mbeidh an t-iarratas a bheas a chur isteach chuig na funds nó chuig na comhlachtaí árachais ar mhaithe na tíre seo agus ar mhaithe na ndaoine a chaillfidh.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I would like to thank all Senators who participated in the Second Stage and, indeed, in the Committee Stage of this Oil Pollution of the Sea (Civil Liability and Compensation) Bill, 1987, for their interest in this important Bill.  I hope this Bill will receive a speedy passage through <Col N="1559" /> the Dáil and that we can have it enacted at the earliest possible date.</P>
    <P>Lest there be any misconception I would like to point out that the claim of £1.743 million which we have lodged is not to the fund; it is to the insurers in this case as far as the <i>Kowloon Bridge</i> is concerned.  Again, I thank Senators most sincerely for their contributions here today.  I hope this Bill will be enacted quickly and that before too long, either myself or the Minister will be back in the House with further legislation which will help to strengthen existing legislation.</P>
    <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Business" RHead="of Seanad">
    <Title>Business of Seanad.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Acting Chairman Acting Chairman">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman</NameTxt>
      <P>I understand from the Leader of the House that because of the limitation of time, we are unable to take Item No. 4.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TomFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Fitzgerald Mr. Fitzgerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Fitzgerald</NameTxt>
      <P>I propose that we adjourn now until Wednesday, 18 November 1987 at 2.30 p.m.</P>
      <P>Agreed.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Adjournment Matter. - National" RHead="Social Service Board">
    <Title>Adjournment Matter. - National Social Service Board.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Acting Chairman Acting Chairman">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman</NameTxt>
      <P>I understand that Senator O'Toole was given permission to raise on the Adjournment the proposed closure of the National Social Service Board.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeOToole" hpid="Mr. J. O'Toole Mr. J. O'Toole">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J. O'Toole</NameTxt>
      <P>I thank the Minister for making himself available to discuss this matter.  Of all the various cuts that have been talked about and all the various cuts that have been looked at over the past couple of weeks &mdash; indeed there has been plenty of discussion about them &mdash; this underlines, in one sense, all that was wrong and all that was bad about cuts in the Estimates.  I have taken the view that many of the cuts are not in any sense cost-effective.  We are looking at the National Social Service Board.  I do <Col N="1560" /> not believe that the proposed closure of the National Social Service Board will save the State one penny.  I think, in fact, that it will be worse than that; it will cost the State.</P>
      <P>The National Social Service Board are operating since 1971.  They co-ordinated social services for people throughout the country.  At the moment they maintain 80 community and information centres and give them the information and backup service they need so badly.  At the moment they have a grant of approximately £0.5 million per year.  The Government are shutting them down and putting forward the view that this will save money for the State.  The figures do not add up.  If 52 per cent of the total grant goes on salaries and all the personnel of the board have been guaranteed deployment or other work within the Department of Health, on 52 per cent of the total grant there will be no saving whatsoever.  Another standing cost is the cost of renting their premises.  The rental of their premises is tied up in a five year lease.  They attempted to get out of that lease 18 months ago and were unable to do so on legal grounds.  The State is committed to the payment of that rent for the next number of years, up to five years &mdash; I am not sure of the exact number of years.  More than that, they have dealt with over 100,000 queries per year.</P>
      <P>The Minister maintains that this work will be taken over by the Department of Health.  I fail to understand how the costing on that was done.  I ask the Minister to explain to me the average cost per query as worked out by the Minister for Health because it seems that whatever the cost, it will now cost an awful lot more to maintain this service than it did heretofore when it was being run and maintained under the structure of the National Social Service Board.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>There is also, to me, a very dangerous position in that I have heard it said that there are many politicians who were not too enamoured with the work of the National Social Service Board and their network of satellite services around the country because many politicians felt that <Col N="1561" /> ordinary people were getting information from the different clinics and centres which were working under the aegis of the National Social Service Board, information that the politicians would prefer to be giving out in their own clinics.  I have no hard and fast information on that but it has certainly been said to me and I certainly responded to the point.  Politicians more than anybody else recognise that information is power and that very often giving is telling even if giving is only giving information.</P>
    <P>Therefore, I put it to the Minister that this proposal to close down the National Social Service Board is not cost effective that, in fact, it is a cut that will cost the State money, that it hurts the least protected groups in our society and that it is a politically suspect move.  I ask him to explain to me how we are going to continue this service without spending more money on it and to assure me that the rumour I heard, that one particular health board was going to be asked to coordinate and take over the work that was at present being undertaken by the National Social Service Board, is not true.  I would ask him to explain to me how this can be justified either socially, economically or financially.  Finally, I would like the Minister to also assure me that this proposal will not be implemented.</P>
    <Speaker pid="TerryLeyden" hpid="Minister of State at the Department of Health (Mr. Leyden) Terry Leyden">
      <NameTxt>Minister of State at the Department of Health (Mr. Leyden)</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister for Health, Deputy O'Hanlon, made it clear at the press conference that the services at present provided under the auspices of the National Social Service Board will be continued.  There is no question that the community information centres will be allowed to suffer neglect.  In fact, it is the intention to review the public information services generally and, in the context of this new plan, we hope useful proposals for the enhancement of the services to the community information services will emerge.  I might say that the Department of Social Welfare, notwithstanding that they have a network of local offices of their own and an information service are concerned that the <Col N="1562" /> community information centres should continue to function because of their irreplaceable function in helping individuals with their problems about entitlements. At least 50 per cent of the work of the community information centres is about social welfare matters.  It is therefore appropriate that the Department of Social Welfare should be the channel for grants of public money for the maintenance of these centres.  The Department are considering what arrangement would be best for ensuring that the kind of information to which the centres have been accustomed in relation not only to social welfare matters but to a range of other problems which most public representatives are also aware of, in relation to my own Department, the Department of Health, the Department of the Environment, local authorities, income tax and such like.  If the public come to the centres the information will continue to be available.  The information bulletins and other publications relevant to the work of the centres will also be maintained.  I will not anticipate the precise form of these revised arrangements as they are still being worked out.  I can say there will be a public announcement about them very shortly.  Certain proposals are before the Government just now.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>These new and I hope enhanced information and training arrangements will take place within a broader framework of community development.  Certain suggestions are being put to health boards about an extension of their assistance to local social service councils and similar co-ordinated bodies at local level.  The encouragement of the formation and growth of local voluntary effort involves direct touch with local opinion and closer relationship between health boards and the voluntary sector.  While the decision in relation to the National Social Service Board was based on the need for rationalisation and streamlining, it is fundamentally in pursuance of a policy of development of community services. When the final arrangements are made, Senator O'Toole and others who have expressed concern in relation to the type of work the National Social Service <Col N="1563" /> Board were carrying out, will be very satisfied with the arrangements the Government are proposing.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JoeOToole" hpid="Mr. J. O'Toole Mr. J. O'Toole">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J. O'Toole</NameTxt>
      <P>On the basis that the Minister's answer concerns service improvement, is he confirming that there is no financial or economic advantage to the State in closing down the National Social Service Board, that there is, in fact, no financial gain or economic advantage to the State in shutting down this board?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1564" />
    <Speaker pid="TerryLeyden" hpid="Mr. Leyden Mr. Leyden">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Leyden</NameTxt>
      <P>The situation is that all rationalisation which is to take place at the moment would have ultimately some type of saving.  Nevertheless, in the circumstances we hope that the service will be provided at the most economical rate.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeOToole" hpid="Mr. J. O'Toole Mr. J. O'Toole">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J. O'Toole</NameTxt>
      <P>I think the Minister has answered my question.</P>
      <P>The Seanad adjourned at 4.35 p.m. until 2.30 p.m. on Wednesday, 18 November 1987.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
</Debate>