<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE Debate SYSTEM "../Debate.dtd"[]>
<Debate DocTitle="Seanad Debate" Day="Thu" Date="21" Month="May" Year="1987" Vol="116" No="3" DateIrish="Déardaoin, 21 Bealtaine 1987" DateEnglish="Thursday, 21 May 1987" House="S" CommitteeEng="" CommitteeIr="" SubNameEng="" cnum="393">
  <MainHeading Type="Prelude" LHead="" RHead="">
    <Title>
    </Title>
    <P>
      <Col N="393" /> Chuaigh an Cathaoirleach i gceannas ar 10.30 a.m.</P>
    <P Just="Center">
      <i>Paidir.</i>
    </P>
    <P Just="Center">
      <i>Prayer.</i>
    </P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Business" RHead="of Seanad">
    <Title>Business of Seanad.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="TrasHonan" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I have notice from Senator John A. Murphy that, on the motion for the Adjournment of the House today, he proposes to raise the following matter:</P>
      <P>The pressure extended by the Government on the national broadcasting service to change the balance of its coverage on the present Referendum campaign.</P>
      <P>I regret that I have to rule that this matter is not suitable for discussion on the Adjournment on the grounds of lack of ministerial responsibility.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnMurphy2" hpid="Professor Murphy Professor Murphy">
      <NameTxt>Professor Murphy</NameTxt>
      <P>I regret that I find your decision extraordinary because I have some experience of raising matters on the Adjournment and I have come to know the kind of matters that are not regarded as suitable.  In this instance a matter of grave public concern has not been given the discussion it deserves.  It seems to me that ministerial responsibility is absolutely crystal clear.  I find your judgment extraordinary and, with great respect, politically suspect.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TrasHonan" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator Murphy, if this is going to be your attitude to me as <Col N="394" /> Cathaoirleach during this term of this Seanad, my only immediate comment on your last remark is that it is sad, that is the only word I should use.  As regards my ruling, as Cathaoirleach of a former Seanad and four years as Leas-Chathaoirleach when my esteemed predecessor was ill I acted as Cathaoirleach and never was I accused of taking sides with any political party on the floor of this Seanad.</P>
      <P>I have made my ruling and you can speak again &mdash; which you should not be allowed to do &mdash; when I have just explained to you why my ruling was made.  The ruling was not made on political grounds or to protect any Minister of any Cabinet.  Everyone has the right to object to any broadcast of anything on our broadcasting system as individuals and that was all that Minister did.  The authority has the full responsibility.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnMurphy2" hpid="Professor Murphy Professor Murphy">
      <NameTxt>Professor Murphy</NameTxt>
      <P>They thought it was ignored in this instance.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TrasHonan" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>And I have made my ruling now.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnMurphy2" hpid="Professor Murphy Professor Murphy">
      <NameTxt>Professor Murphy</NameTxt>
      <P>If he called in the RTE executives, how much clearer could you get a case of ministerial responsibility and therefore suitability of this motion for discussion?  I must say, with respect, that this Chamber is not a mutual congratulation society as it seems to have been since we convened on the first day. This is a serious Chamber where I have every right to bring up these matters.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Order of" RHead="Business">
    <Title>Order of Business.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="MickLanigan" hpid="Mr. Lanigan Mr. Lanigan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lanigan</NameTxt>
      <P>It is intended to take items Nos. 1, 2 and 3 today.  It is intended to take all stages of Nos. 2 and 3.</P>
      <P>Order of Business agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Committee of" RHead="Selection">
    <Title>Committee of Selection.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="MickLanigan" hpid="Mr. Lanigan Mr. Lanigan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lanigan</NameTxt>
      <P>I move:</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>That, in pursuance of Standing Order No. 68 of the Standing Orders <Col N="395" /> relative to Public Business, the Committee of Selection be appointed and do consist of the following members:&mdash;</P>
    <P>The Leas-Chathaoirleach, Senators Denis Cregan, Jack Daly, Willie Farreil, Tom Fitzgerald, Jack Fitzsimons, John Harte, Seán F. Haughey, Tom McEllistrim, Joe O'Toole and William Ryan.</P>
    <Speaker pid="TrasHonan" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I would like to make a short comment on the first item on the Clár here this morning because of a comment yesterday.  I think every Senator here witnessed eight to ten Senators standing against the back wall of this room.  I only refer to this room as a room because I never approved of it as suitable for a Seanad Chamber.  I understand that alternative accommodation is being looked at and because of the feeling that Senators may not know what was going on, I say that anything that I am aware of as Cathaoirleach will be made known.  The Committee on Procedure and Privileges, in which we all have a say, will only do the right thing for the Seanad to ensure a proper Chamber.  I think the former Seanad never really approved of this room and indeed the new Seanad saw the situation here yesterday.  All I can say is that we will try to get a proper alternative Chamber for this Seanad as soon as possible.  This follows other little upsets regarding accommodation, etc. That will also be dealt with.  It is only in everybody's interest to try to have a proper Chamber for the Upper House.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelFerris" hpid="Mr. Ferris Mr. Ferris">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Ferris</NameTxt>
      <P>In view of your remarks I think in fairness the Leader of the House yesterday said that he was not dealing with rumours, only with facts.  We were concerned yesterday about the rumours and written rumours about decisions that were being made about where the Seanad should sit and you have rightly pointed out that the committee which would normally decide and bring back its decision here has not met.  That was the objection of the people who raised the matter yesterday initially that decisions seem to have been made about where the Seanad <Col N="396" /> would sit without the Seanad itself and its Procedure and Privileges Committee making such a decision formally.  I accepted the assurance of the Leader of the House yesterday that he was not interested in rumour or newspaper articles about this, and that it should be dealt with properly.  I look forward to it being dealt with properly because, like yourself, we all have a say in where this House should sit.  Where the rumours emanated from is another question.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MickLanigan" hpid="Mr. Lanigan Mr. Lanigan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lanigan</NameTxt>
      <P>To accelerate or attempt to accelerate the business which has been mentioned, I suggest that the Whips could get together today to try to have the Committee of Selection meet today. If they can meet today we can get down to the selection of the Committee or Procedure and Privileges which we would hope could then meet early next week.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="An Bille um Údarás na Gaeltachta (Leasú), 1987 [ Bille Airgid" RHead="Deimhnithe ] &mdash;An Dara Céim agus na Céimeanna Eile">
    <Title>An Bille um Údarás na Gaeltachta (Leasú), 1987  [  Bille Airgid Deimhnithe ]  &mdash;An Dara Céim agus na Céimeanna Eile.</Title>
    <P>Tairgeadh an cheist: &ldquo;Go léifear an Bille an Dara hUair.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="DenisGallagher" hpid="Aire Stáit ag Roinn na Gaeltachta (Mr. D. Gallagher) Aire Stáit ag Roinn na Gaeltachta (Mr. D. Gallagher)">
      <NameTxt>Aire Stáit ag Roinn na Gaeltachta (Mr. D. Gallagher)</NameTxt>
      <P>Is Bille é seo chun an uasteorainn do na hairleacain as an bPríomh-Chiste chuig Údarás na Gaeltachta a mhéadú ó £50 milliún go dtí £60 milliún. Teorainn £50 milliún a leagadh síos san Acht um Údarás na Gaeltachta, 1979 &mdash; an tAcht faoinar bunaíodh an tÚdarás. Tá an tsuim sin faighte ag an Údarás ó mhí na Nollag seo caite agus tá sé riachtanach an teorainn a mhéadú anois le go bhféadfar tuilleadh airleacan a chur ar fáil don eagraíocht chun a chur ar a cumas brú ar aghaidh leis an obair thábhachtach atá ar siúl aici ar mhaithe le forbairt na Gaeltachta agus cur chun cinn na Gaeilge.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Is ar mhonarchana le cur ar cíos do thionscail agus ar scaireanna i gcuideachtaí is mó a chaitear na hairleacain &mdash; nó caipiteal neamhvótáilte mar a thugtar orthu.  Ar ndóigh, ní hionann uasteorainn reachtúil a ardú agus airgead a íoc <Col N="397" /> amach: is amhlaidh a eiseofar airleacain de réir mar a bheidh caiteachas caipitil den saghas atá luaite agam le glanadh agus faoi réir na suime bliantúla a bheidh údaraithe ag an Rialtas.  Soláthar £5 mhilliún atá ann don bhliain reatha.  Ní miste a rá nach mbaineann an Bille le caipiteal vótáilte an Údaráis, is é sin, an caiteachas caipitil le haghaidh na ndeontas a thugann an tÚdarás do thionscail: cuirtear an t-airgead sin ar fáil trí Vóta Roinn na Gaeltachta gach bliain.  Suim £8.52 mhilliún atá i Leabhar na Meastachán don bhliain reatha.</P>
    <P>Faoi mar is eol don Seanad foilsíodh tuarascáil thábhachtach Chomhchoiste an Oireachtais um Chomhiachtaí Státtionscanta Tráchtála ar an Údarás anuraidh.  Tá na moltaí sa tuarascáil chuimsitheach sin á scrúdú go fóill.</P>
    <P>Faoi mar a dúirt mé sa Dáil nuair a bhí an Dara Céim den Bhille seo á phlé tá sé thar a bheith tábhachtach go mbeadh sochar maith le fáil as an airgead Stáit a chuirtear ar fáil don Údarás mar airleacain &mdash; agus go deimhin mar dheontais-i-gcabhair freisin &mdash; agus chuige sin tá iarrtha ar an Údarás scrúdú iomlán a dhéanamh ar a chuid socmhainní le cinntiú go mbeidh an sochar is fearr is féidir le gnóth astu agus trí chritéir dhaingne a leagan síos go mbeidh luach a chuid airgid le fáil ag an Stát as chaiteachas ar airleacain.</P>
    <P>De réir Tuarascáil agus Cuntais na heagraíochta don bhliain 1985 atá leagtha faoi bhráid an tSeanaid bhí 4,659 nduine ag obair go lánaimseartha ar 31 Nollaig 1985 sna tionscail uile a fuair cúnamh ó Ghaeltarra/ón Údarás.  Ba é sin an ceathrú bliain as a chéile a d'éirigh leis an Údarás an fhostaíocht i dtionscail faoina scáth a mhéadú agus tréaslaím a saothar leo.  Ag deireadh na bliana 1985 bhí 254 dhuine breise fostaithe go lánaimseartha i dtionscail faoi choimirce an Údaráis i gcomparáid leis an líon a bhí fostaithe i dtús na bliana sin .i.e. méadú 5.7 faoin gcéad ar an bhfostaíocht lánaimseartha. Is dul chun cinn suntasach é sin nuair a smaoinítear ar an tionchar atá ag an gcúlú eacnamaíochta ar chúrsaí fostaíochta sa tír.  Níl figiúirí cruinne ar fáil go fóill faoin líon daoine a bhí fostaithe ag deireadh na bliana 1986 ach tuigim ón Údarás go <Col N="398" /> meastar go raibh líon beag daoine sa bhreis ag obair go lánaimseartha sna tionscail faoina scáth ar 31 Nollaig 1986 i gcomparáid leis an dáta céanna sa bhliain roimhe sin.</P>
    <P>Is d'fhonn fostaíocht a chur ar fáil do mhuintir na Gaeltachta a théann an tÚdarás faoi chaiteachas caipitil.  Tá béim ar leith á cur ag an eagraíocht ar fhorbairt acmhainní nádúrtha na Gaeltachta agus tá dul chun cinn maith déanta ach go háirithe maidir leis an tionscal fheirmeoireacht éisc.  Tá an tÚdarás sásta go bhfuil fás mór i ndán don tionscal sin sa Ghaeltacht &mdash; áit a bhfuil suímh oiriúnacha ar fáil, go príomha ar chósta an iarthair.  Tuigtear ón Údarás go bhfuil breis is 100 duine fostaithe go lánaimseartha agus timpeall 40 duine go páirtaimseartha ar fud na Gaeltachta faoi láthair sa tionscal fheirmeoireacht éisc agus meastar go bhféadfar suas le 500 post lánaimseartha ar a laghad a chruthú sa tionscal sin sa Ghaeltacht thar tréimhse 10-15 bliana.</P>
    <P>Faoi mar is eol do Sheanadóirí bíonn sé riachtanach dul faoi chaiteachas ar thaighde chun táirgí nua a fhorbairt.  Bhí an tÚdarás mar cheannródaí sa tír seo maidir le saothrú na mara a chur chun cinn le deich mbliana anuas agus caitheadh roinnt mhaith airgid ar obair thaighde agus forbartha &mdash; saothar a ndeachaigh chun leas na tíre cheana féin agus a rachaidh tuilleadh sna blianta atá romh ainn.  Mar léiriú ar an dul chun cinn atá déanta is i gcomhlachtaí a fuair cúnamh ón Údarás a tháirgítear suas le 70 faoin gcéad de na bradáin a thagann ó fheirmeacha éisc sa tír seo faoi láthair.  Tá mé dóchasach go mbeifear in ann cur leis an bhforbairt sin le deiseanna fostaíochta breise a sholáthar do mhuintir na Gaeltachta.</P>
    <P>Tá mé cinnte nach miste bheith ag brath ar an Údarás brú ar aghaidh go tréan leis an obair chun poist bhreise a chruthú sa Ghaeltacht agus is mar chabhair chuige sin atáim ag iarraidh ar an Seanad glacadh leis an mBille gairid seo.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PeterKelleher" hpid="Mr. Kelleher Mr. Kelleher">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Kelleher</NameTxt>
      <P>Maidir le hoibriú Údarás na Gaeltachta caithfidh mé ar an gcéad dul síos moladh a thabhairt dóibh as an obair atá ar siúl acu do mhuintir na Gaeltachta. <Col N="399" /> Tá roint mhaith airgid curtha ar fáil acu do fhostóirí na Gaeltachta chun postanna a chur ar fáil do mhuintir na Gaeltachta.  Sa bhliain 1985 is cúis sásaimh don Údarás gur éirigh leis an fhostaíocht faoin a scáth sa Ghaeltacht a mhéadú don ceathrú bliain as a chéile agus lena chois sin infheistíocht thabhachtach bhreise a thabhairt isteach.  Trí fhiontair nua i rith na bliana 1985 tháinig méadú 254 ar líon na ndaoine a bhí ag obair go lánaimsearach.  Fostaíocht 4,659 a bhí sa tionscal i ndeireadh 1985 i gcomparáid le 4,405 i dtús na bliana.  Is ionann é sin agus méadú 5.7 faoin gcéad ar an bhfostaíocht lánaimseartha.  Is méad suntasach é sin i gcomparáid leis na torthaí náisiúnta agus go háirithe nuair a thógtar san áireamh na deacrachtaí ar leith a bhíonn le sáru sa Ghaeltacht.</P>
      <P>Údarás na Gaeltachta have an outstanding record of success in attracting industrial enterprise to Gaeltacht regions.  Since 1981 industrial employment has risen in Gaeltacht areas.  From January 1981 to year end 1985 full time employment in the industries promoted by Údarás na Gaeltachta has risen from 4,011 to 4,659.  One must remember that the authority serves an area with a population of approximately only 80,000 people.  The increase occurred at a time when unemployment was rising in the rest of the country.</P>
      <P>I live in a Gaeltacht area in Ballyvourney, County Cork, where we have a number of small industries set up with the help of grant-aid from Údarás na Gaeltachta.  I am glad to say that we have very little unemployment in this area and again that is thanks to the direct involvement of Údarás na Gaeltachta.  Údarás na Gaeltachta have a part time office in this region which is manned for two days a week by their representative and he is there to assist and give advice on any project which one might have or to help with the preparation of an application for grant-aid for the setting up of any viable industrial project within the Muskerry Gaeltacht.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>There are now very strict criteria in order to qualify for grant-aid and the average cost per job is in the region of <Col N="400" /> £5,000 compared with the IDA who have an average cost per job ranging from between £7,000 to £20,000.  It is also true that Údarás na Gaeltachta projects are generally of higher risk in that the high technology projects go to the IDA and SFADCo regions principally due to their location advantages.  It is obvious that any foreign industrialist, if offered an advance factory in the Limerick region of SFADCo convenient to Shannon Airport or to the Limerick dock area, will settle there rather than take a factory in Gweedore, County Donegal, where he is approximately 200 miles from Dublin Airport.  His transport costs from Donegal would be massive in relation to other locations around the country.  This is one of the reasons there is a higher percentage of grant-aid for those starting up projects in the Gaeltacht areas.</P>
    <P>The following incentives are provided by Údarás na Gaeltachta for those industries. They give a capital grant of up to 60 per cent of the cost of new buildings, machinery and equipment or 66? per cent in the case of projects promoted by native Irish speakers, by co-operatives and industries located in Gaeltacht areas; training grants of up to 100 per cent of the actual training costs and approximately 50 per cent of this is refunded by the European Communities Social Fund; in the case of small industries, an interest subsidy grant on loan finance subject to a maximum loan of 20 per cent; the rate of subsidy is scaled down from 100 per cent in year one, 75 per cent in year two, 50 per cent in year three and 25 per cent in year four; in certain development grants up to 60 per cent of the agreed cost subject to a maximum of £50,000 in any one case and a further £50,000 with the permission of the Minister for the Gaeltacht; feasibility study grants up to 50 per cent of accepted costs subject to a maximum of £5,000 in any one case and rent subsidies payable for up to a period of 15 years.</P>
    <P>In addition to the above grants Údarás na Gaeltachta may under certain conditions acquire a majority or minority equity shareholding in companies as part of their industrial development activities.</P>
    <P>In relation to item 4 reference is made <Col N="401" /> to R and D grants.  I am not satisfied that Údarás na Gaeltachta are carrying out this function properly.  I have had the experience recently of a security company which spent in excess of £25,000 on research and development in the production of a prototype safe used by CIE on their one-man bus.  Because it did not meet all the requirements set by CIE, it was decided not to develop it further. Údarás na Gaeltachta have said they cannot pay for a product which is not being produced.  Surely research and development on any product carries a huge risk of failure.  Once the money is spent by a small rural company they are entitled to reimbursement of the grant element or part of the expenditure.  The research and development is there surely to cover the risk of failure.</P>
    <P>Údarás na Gaeltachta are falling down in the area of support for small industries by their non-commitment to marketing aid.  There is no grant or assistance to help small companies to market their products.  Everybody knows at this stage that good marketing is critical to survival. I have mentioned this to management within An tÚdarás on many occasions without success to date.</P>
    <P>An tÚdarás administers FEOGA grants which are available for marketing and processing of fish and fish products and mariculture.  FEOGA grants are available at up to 50 per cent of eligible costs and Údarás na Gaeltachta may further grant-aid these projects up to a further 25 per cent.  But in general manufacturing or service industries there are no marketing grants from Údarás na Gaeltachta.  This will have to change if the increase in employment in the Gaeltacht areas is to be continued.</P>
    <P>I support the Bill before us in this House today and I approve of the amendment to section 23 of the Údarás na Gaeltachta Act, 1979 by the substitution in subsection 4 of £60 million instead of £50 million.  I wish to state categorically that I respect Údarás na Gaeltachta, their members, their workers and the people of the Gaeltacht.  I want to see the Gaeltacht developed to the fullest extent possible. I want to see a love generated for the <Col N="402" /> Irish language, ár dteanga ar ndúchas, in a realistic manner and not just lip service paid to it by adopting the hypocritical attitude which has been shown to it down through the years by different people in Government.  The survival of the Gaeltacht rests with the Minister of the day. For that reason I was very disappointed that the Taoiseach did not see fit to appoint a full time Cabinet Minister responsible for Gaeltacht affairs.  I do not believe that, as Taoiseach, with the added responsibility for Gaeltacht affairs, Mr. Haughey can give enough commitment to the Gaeltacht.  As a result it will be grossly neglected under this Government.</P>
    <P>Initially, the Commission for the Gaeltacht was set up by the late Mr. Cosgrave in 1926.  From then until 1956, when the Department of the Gaeltacht was founded, nothing of real advantage or progress took place in Gaeltacht areas. It was not until 1973 that the Coalition Government saw fit to appoint a fulltime Cabinet Minister for the Gaeltacht, Tomás O Dómhnaill a bhí ina Aire le ceithre bhliana go leith.  When he was appointed Minister he brought a new image to the ministry of the Gaeltacht and increased his workforce from approximately 1,800 to 4,000 people. Industries were set up which were not successful but, by and large, he brought a new awareness of the Gaeltacht areas and the Irish language to our people.</P>
    <P>In December 1979 the residents of the different Gaeltachta went to the polls. The election which took place was democratic in so far as the members of Údarás na Gaeltachta going forward for election were returned to their various positions. The Minister of the day made appointments and the people on the board were very hard working and were genuinely aware of the needs and problems of the different Gaeltachta throughout the country.  The board of Údarás na Gaeltachta is made up of 13 members, including the chairman.  I congratulate the present chairman who is from Donegal, Pádraig O'Doherty, on his commitment to Gaeltacht affairs.  I had the pleasure of meeting the board members recently in Ballyvourney when they did a fact <Col N="403" /> finding tour of all the Gaeltacht areas to familiarise themselves with the problems which arise in those areas.</P>
    <P>Údarás na Gaeltachta must be seen as a step in the right direction, and one that is being watched with extreme interest in other parts of the country.  It provided the first opportunity for development to be initiated by elected people from the Gaeltacht.  I want to see Údarás na Gaeltachta as an effective body, able to promote the cultural, social and linguistic development of our Gaeltacht areas, as well as solving the unemployment problems. For this reason I support the Bill.</P>
    <Speaker pid="NicholasOConnor" hpid="Mr. O'Connor Mr. O'Connor">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Connor</NameTxt>
      <P>A Chathaoirligh, is onóir mhór dom labhairt anseo sa Seanad don chéad uair, go mórmhór mar dhuine a rugadh agus a tógadh sa Ghaeltacht. Freisin cuireann sé áthas orm go bhfuil an Taoiseach é féin mar Aire Ghaeltachta agus go bhfuil fear a rugadh agus a tógadh sa nGaeltacht, An Teachta Denis Gallagher, mar Aire Stáit.  Tá mé ag ceapadh go bhfuil an triúr againn mar an gcéanna ar bhealaí &mdash; is oileánach é, is oileánach mé féin agus déarfainn gur oileánach é an Taoiseach é féin cuid mhaith den am.  Cuirim fáilte roimh an Bhille seo chun airgead breise a thabhairt do Údarás na Gaeltachta, sé sin ardú ó £50,000,000 go dtí £60,000,000 in am go bhfuil airgead thar a bheith gann, agus cinnte beidh fáilte mór ag muintir na Gaeltachta roimhe seo.  Ó 1982 d'éirigh le Údarás na Gaeltachta méadú mór a chur le cúrsaí fostaíochta sa Ghaeltacht agus i rith na tréimhse sin tháinig méadú 16 faoin gcéad i bhfostaíocht san tionscal déantúsaíochta.  Is suntasach an rud é seo, mar tháinig laghdú mór san tionscal déantúsaíochta ar fúd na tíre i gcoitinne. I rith na tréimhse céanna ardaíodh cuid den mhéanchostas san chuid eile den tír post a chruthú agus sin ag tógáil san áireamh na deacrachtaí móra atá ag an Gaeltacht féin maidir le infrastructúr agus go hiondúil go bhfuil cuid do na Gaeltachtaí i bhfad ó chalafoirt agus ó aerfoirt.  Tá go leor ráite maidir le deacrachtaí atá luaite agus maidir le infrastructúir.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Ba mhaith liom rud amháin a rá, ná <Col N="404" /> gur tháinig Údarás na Gaeltachta tríd an tréimhse is crua agus is deacra a tháinig aon eagras stáit trid le linn Paddy O'Toole mar Aire Ghaeltachta.  Is cinnte go ndearna sé rudaí thar a bheith deacair ag an am sin do Bhord an Údaráis agus do na daoine a bhí ag obair istigh san Údarás féin, go mór mhór do dhaoine a rugadh agus a tógadh sa Ghaeltacht.  Ní raibh aon tuiscint acu cén fáth go raibh dochar á dhéanamh don Údarás nó, bhféidir, ag an am, ag iarraidh deireadh a chur leo.  Níl ciall nó réasún bheith ag iarraidh ag an am seo, uaireanta, leanúint ar aghaidh chun tionscail a mhealladh isteach go dtí na háiteacha iargúlta mar tá sé thar a bheith deacair forbairt a dhéanamh sna háiteacha seo, mar adúirt mé, mar gheall ar an infrastructúr.  Tóg mar shampla, an infheistíocht mhór atá déanta ag an Údarás sa feilméireacht éisc le ceithre bliain anuas.</P>
    <P>Tá infheistíocht mhór déanta acu. D'fhéadfaí a rá go bhfuil suas le 70 faoin gcéad de na feirmeacha bradán bunaithe sa Ghaeltacht féin a thug Údarás na Gaeltachta cabhair agus tacaíocht dóibh.  Freisin tá forbairt taighde ar bun maidir le sliogéisc, agus ba cheart chuile chúnamh a thabhairt chuig Comharchumann Sliogéisc Chonamara agus do fhiontair na noileán atá i mbun forbartha faoi láthair, go mór mhór nuair is achmhainní nádúrtha atá i gceist agus leas mhuintir na Gaeltachta.</P>
    <P>Bhí an tÚdarás in ann comhlacht mór fheilméireacht éisc a mhealladh isteach agus tá fostaíocht mhór á cur ar fáil ag Carrolls faoi láthair i gceantar Ghaeltacht Chonamara.  Ní ceart dearmad a dhéanamh ach an oiread ar mhuintir na Gaeltachta iad féin.  Mar atá a fhios ag gach éinne cosnaíonn sé an t-uafás airgid infheistíocht a dhéanamh sna feirmeacha seo.  Tá an tÚdarás ag tabhairt cúnaimh don ghnáth dhuine leanúint ar aghaidh leis na feirmeacha seo, go mór mhór na feirmeacha bradán satailíte, is é sin go bhfaigheann siad cead oibriú lámh le láimh leis na comhlachtaí móra.</P>
    <P>Tá mé ag iarraidh ar an Aire teacht i gcabhair ar an scéim seo mar tá cuid den scéim seo coinnithe siar faoi láthair idir Roinn na Gaeltachta agus an Roinn Iascaigh.  Scéim thar a bheith tábhachtach <Col N="405" /> í do mhuintir na Gaeltachta.  Ba chóir go mbeadh chuile cheart acu i leith na n-achmhainní nádúrtha seo.  D'fhág na céadta daoine ceantar Chonamara ó 1981 agus caithfimid a rá go bhfuil chuile iarracht déanta ag an Udarás chun forbairt na Gaeltachta a chinntu í go mór mhór i leith achmhainní nádúrtha.</P>
    <P>Tá stáisin i gCarna faoí láthair a bhfuil baint ag Ollscoil na Gaillimhe leithe ach ní bhfuaireadar aon airgead ón Rialtas le roinnt blianta anuas.  Tá sé thar a bheith tábhachtach go gcoinneofaí oscailte an stáisiún mar gan an stáisiún ann ní bheidh na trialacha ag dul ar aghaidh chun a chinntiú go mbeidh na sliogéisc agus a leithéid ag leanúint ar aghaidh.  Níl mórán fostaoíchta nó forbairt déanta i bhfeilmóireacht éisc.  Ba cheart iarracht a dhéanamh an próiseál éisc a thabhairt chun cinn.  Tá na mílte jobanna anseo ach leagadh amach ceart dó.  Ceapaim féin gur cheart na hachmhainní nádúrtha a úsáid ionnas go mbeimid in ann an próiseál éisc a dhéanamh taobh istigh de na Gaeltachtaí féin.  Tá súil agam go mbeidh Roinn na Mara in ann teacht i gcabhair chun a lán de na deacrachtaí seo, go mórmhór maidir leis an sliogéisc, a réiteach. Ba cheart na deontais seirbhisí a chur ar fáil arís, sé sin deontais do ghnáthdhaoine chun seans a thabhairt dóibh laistigh de na Gaeltachtaí féin chun cupla jobanna breise a chur ar fáil.  Chuir an Rialtas deireadh stop leis seo agus iarraim ar an Aire tabhairt chuige arís.</P>
    <P>Tharla an rud céanna le forbairt na bportach, achmhainní nádúrtha eile istigh de Ghealtacht Chonamara go mórmhór.  Cuireadh deireadh leis sin, agus anois níl aon dream sásta aon fhorbairt a dhéanamh ar phortaigh i gceanntar Chonamara.  Maidir leis na comhairchumann, tá sé in am iad a bheith faoi aon stiúr amháin faoin Údarás nó faoi Roinn na Gaeltachta.  Tá freastal á dhéanamh orthu trí go leor lán Ranna Stáit.  Tá mé ag ceapadh go bhfuil 12 dóibh i gceist agus ní aon chomh-oibriú ceart ann; tá daoine ag dul treasna ar a chéile agus cothaíonn sé seo deacrachtaí áirithe i measc an phobail anois agus arís.</P>
    <P>Tarlaíonn sé go minic go dtagann na comharchumainn treasna ar ghnótha príomháideacha, agus déanann sé sin <Col N="406" /> dochar dóibh.  Tá sé crúthaithe ag oibrithe na Gaeltachta go bhfúil siad chomh maith agus níos fearr uaireanta ná aon dream eile sa tír.  Ba mhaith liom comhgháirdeas a dhéanamh le Telemara Teoranta ar an gCeathrú Rua agus leis an Údarás mar gheall ar an aitheantas a fuair siad ón IIRS, agus go mórmhór mar gheall ar an ghnó mór a dhéanann siad le IBM, cómhlacht idirnáisiúnta.  Cruthúntas é seo go bhfuil caighdeán an-mhór ag muintir na Gaeltachta ag dul i mbun a gcuid oibre féin ag aon uair agus ag aon am.</P>
    <P>Tuigtear dom go bhfuil scéim thurasóireacht leagtha amach ag an Údarás agus nach bhfuil aon chinneadh déanta faoi seo fós.  Creidim nach bhfuil tuiscint na Gaeltachta ag Bord Fáilte nó ag Ireland West chun spreagadh a dhéanamh ar na hachmhainní nádúrtha seo.  Ní bhéadh costas mór airgid i gceist chun cur leis an obair thógála i dtaobh tí ósta agus go mormhór chun cúnamh a thabhairt don ghnáth dhuine agus dá chlann.</P>
    <P>Maidir leis na coláistí Gaeilge, níl an oiread céanna daltaí ag freastal anois ar an Ghaeltacht agus a bhíodh.  De bharr céimeanna eacnamaíochta agus ganntanas airgid breathnaíonn sé nach bhfuil an tsuim chéanna san Ghaeilge agus a bhíodh.  Ba chóir chuile chabhair a thabhairt do na mná tí agus na coláistí Gaeilge, agus is trua go bhfuil laige ag teacht ar theanga na Gaeilge.  Ba cheart do Roinn na Gaeltachta agus an tÚdarás cinntiú nach dtarlóidh sé seo.  Cé nach bhfuil cuid mhór de mhuintir Chathair na Gaillimhe an-báiúil le teanga na Gaeilge nó le Gaeltacht Chonamara, caitear níos mó na £20 milliún istigh sa chathair sin dé bharr seirbhísí a chuirtear ar fáil do mhuintir nGhaeltacht Chonamara agus mhuintir Oileán Arainn.</P>
    <P>Is cinnte go bhfuil an-tionchar ag Raidió na Gaeltachta i saol muintir na Gaeltachta agus Gaelgeóirí ar fud na tíre freisin.  Daoine ón Ghaeltacht atá anoís ag rith seirbhís an raidió seo chomh fada agus is féidir, agus ó táimid anois ag tarraingt chuig deireadh na n-ochtóidí tá sé thar a bheith molta go leathnófaí an tseirbhís seo ní hé amháin go Sasana ach go dtí Meiriceá.  Ceapaim nach bhfuil sé seo do-dhéanta ag an am seo de bharr <Col N="407" /> an córas saitilíte agus bealaí eile.  Is fiú staidéar a dhéanamh ar seo mar d'imigh an oiread sin daoine ó na Gaeltachtaí le blianta anuas go mbeidís in ann téangmháil len a muintir sa mbaile agus len a gcáirde.</P>
    <P>Tá súil agam nach fada uainn Teilifís na Gaeltachta sa lá atá againn inniu ann, tá sé thar a bheith tábhachtach é seo a chur ar fáil chomh luath agus is féidir.  Is cinnte go bhfuil an Ghaeilge agus muintir na nGaeltachtaí dá bplúcadh ag an brú isteach ag an BBC agus teilifísí saitilíte ó chuile aird den domhan.  Níl sé seo sách maith, agus táim cinnte go ndéanfaidh an Rialtas cinneadh faoi seo chomh luath agus is féidir ar mhaithe leis an teanga.</P>
    <P>Molaim gur ceart ar a laghad deich faoin gcéad den chrannchur náisiúnta a chur ar fáil chun an Ghaeilge a spreagadh a thuilleadh.  Maidir le tógraí an Údaráis, tá méad tagtha air i rith 1987-88.  I rith 1986, leagadh amach níos mó oibrithe agus tá contúirt ann go leagfar amach níos mó dóibh.  Iarraim ar an Aire dul chuige seo ionnas nach dtárlódh sé agus táim cinnte ón bhreis airgid atá faighte aige sa Bhille seo go mbeidh an tÚdarás in ann na hoibrithe atá ann a choinneáil ag obair ar mhaithe le forbairt.  Freisin, ba cheart cabhair deontais a cheadú maidir leis an scéim fostaíochta.  Tá sin faighte ag an IDA cheana féin le haghaidh scéimeanna éagsla agus ba cheart go mbeadh an rud céanna á chur ar fáil don Údarás.</P>
    <P>Ní ceart dearmad a dhéanamh de na hOileáin Árainn agus an córas farantóracht atá á iarradh acu leis na blianta.  Is iad muintir Inis Oirr na daoine is measa atá thios leis faoí láthair.  Níl sé sách maith i 1987 go gcaithfidh daoine dul amach i gcurrachaí canbháis go dtí na báid mhóra ag iarraidh a gcuid earraí a fháil i gContae na Gaillimhe.  Ba cheart an saol a dhéanamh níos compóirdí do na daoine seo más féidir, mar tá chuile iarracht déanta ag an gcomharchumann áitiúil an scéim seo a chur chun cinn.  Tuigim go bhfuil plé á dhéanamh faoí sa Roinn faoí láthair.  Cé go dtuigim go bhfuil deacrachtaí airgid sa tír, ag an am céanna ba cheart go mbeadh réiteach déanta ar an scéal i rith trí nó ceithre blian ionas nach mbeadh an costas <Col N="408" /> ro-throm ar an Stát.  Ba cheart dul ar aghaidh leis an forbairt a bhí ceapaithe do Ros a' Mhíl.  Is cinnte go bhfuil deacrachtaí airgid i dtaobh scéim uisce i Gleanach an Mhuireann, scéim atá curtha siar san Roinn Comhshaoil le blianta fada.  Ní féidir dul ar aghaidh leis an monarchan próiseal éisc de bharr ganntanas uisce sa cheantar.  Scéim réigiúnach atá sa scéim seo agus iarraim ar an Aire féachaint chuige.</P>
    <P>Tá brón orm gur labhraíos níos mó faoi Ghaeltacht Chonamara, ach mhínigh mé sin cheana.  Ba mhaith liom chuile deághuí a rá faoín fhoireann in Údarás na Gaeltachta.  Tá cuid mhaith acu sa Ghaeltacht féin agus tá a ndícheall déanta acu leis na blianta anuas, go mórmhór leis na ceithre bliain atá imithe, amanntaí crua, amanntaí gránna nach ndearna aon mhaitheas don Údarás ná do mhuintir na Gaeltachta.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JohnMurphy2" hpid="Professor Murphy Professor Murphy">
      <NameTxt>Professor Murphy</NameTxt>
      <P>Tá náire orm a rá nach raibh an seans agam mé féin a ullmhú don Bhille seo toisc cúrsaí práinneacha eile, ach le cúnamh Dé beidh seans eile chun ceist na Gaeltachtá agus ceist an Údaráis a phlé.  Toisc nach raibh an t-eolas agam, chuir mé an-spéis sa mhéid a bhí le rá ag an Seanadóir Kelleher agus an Seanadóir O'Connor mar is léir go bhfuil siad eolgaiseach sna cúrsaí seo.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Ba bhreá liom a chlos go bhfuil an fhostaíocht ag dul i méid i gcónaí faoi choimirce an Údaráis, rud nach dtuigeann an gnáth-phobal.  Is í tuairim an gnáth-dhuine lasmuigh den Ghaeltacht, is dócha, nach bhfuil á dhéanamh ach airgead a chaitheamh isteach chucu sna Gaeltachtaí i bhfoirm deontais agus nach bhfuil aon fhostaíocht ar siúl i ndairíre. Mheabhródh sé sin dúinn, b'fhéidir, a mholadh nár miste tuilleadh poiblíochta a chur os comhair an phobail ar obair an Údaráis mar tar éis an tsaoll, ó thaobh Béarlóirí na tíre, níl san Údarás ach saghas Údaráis a bhaineann le geiteó agus níl aon tuiscint nó aon spéis ag Béarlóirí san saothar fíorthábhachtach seo.  Mar sin, b'fhéidir mar a deirim, gur mó ba chóir a mholadh don Údarás go gcuirfeadh siad feachtas éigin poiblíochta ar siúl.  Is é an fáth go bhfuil an tÚdarás ann in aon chor, agus go bhfuil an iarracht <Col N="409" /> seo á dhéanamh ar fostaíocht a chur ar fáil ná chun an saol Gaelach agus cultúr na Gaeilge a chothú.  Agus fiú, dá mbeadh ag éirí go geal leis an Údarás, ó thaobh fostaíochta dhe, agus fiú brabús á dhéanamh ar na tionscail seo, bheadh sé fánach ag deireach an lae, bheadh aon dul ar aghaidh cacnamaíochta fánach muna mbeadh an cultúr á neartú ag an am céanna.</P>
    <P>Sin í an cheist atá agamsa, an bhfuil obair thionsclaíoch an Údaráis ag cabhrú leis an gcultúr nó ag cur isteach ar an gcultúr?  An bhfuil aon taighde déanta ag an Údarás ar an gceist tábhachtach seo? An dtarlódh sé, cuirim i gcás, go mbíonn saghasanna áirithe tionsclaíochta sa Ghaeltacht atá ag déanamh dochair don Ghaeilge agus tionsclaíocht eile atá ag cabhrú leis an nGaeilge?  Níl a fhios agam ach ba chóir na ceisteanna seo a chur agus níor mhiste, b'fhéidir, taighde éigin a dhéanamh fúthu.</P>
    <P>Dúirt an Seanadóir Kelleher gur céim síos don Ghaeilge agus don Ghaeltacht nár ceapadh Aire Rialtais don Ghaeltacht an babhta seo, agus aontaím leis. Agus mhol sé Comhrialtas '73/'77 toisc gur cheapadar an Teachta Tomás Ó Domhnaill don chéad uair mar Aire Ghaeltachta.  Ach mo léan, caithfear cuimhneamh chomh maith, gurb é an Comhrialtas deireanach a chaith Aireacht na Gaeltachta i leataobh nó a cheap Aire go raibh mar chúram air cúraimí eile Stáit seachas an Ghaeltacht agus céim síos ab, ea an ceapachán sin chomh maith.  Aontaím, ag an am céanna leis an Seanadóir. Kelleher nach bhfuil sé sásúil go bhfuil obair na Gaeltachta in ainm bheith faoi Roinn an Taoisigh, mar tá a fhios againn go léir go bhfuil an Taoiseach ró-ghnóthach chun obair na Gaeltachta a láimhseáil. Agus an méid sin á rá agam ba mhaith liom fáilte a chur roimh an Aire Stáit anseo, an tUasal Denis Gallagher. Tá tamall fada anois imithe ó bhíos anseo agus ó bhí sé sa chathaoir sin ach táimid arís sa Seanad agus táim an-sásta é a fheiscint arís mar bhí meas agam air i gcónaí mar Aire Ghaeltachta.  Mar sin, fáiltím roimh an mBille go croíúil.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PadraicMcCormack" hpid="Mr. McCormack Mr. McCormack">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McCormack</NameTxt>
      <P>Níor rugadh mé sa <Col N="410" /> Ghaeltacht ach, mar sin féin, ba mhaith liom cupla focal a rá ar an mBille seo.</P>
      <P>As a person from Galway, the largest part of the Gaeltacht in our county, I should contribute to this debate.  I would like to welcome the Bill.  The Department of the Gaeltacht were the only Department who succeeded in having an increased Estimate this year and that is a factor to be welcomed.  We pay tribute to the Minister for the Gaeltacht, the Taoiseach, in providing that extra money and I would also like to take this opportunity to pay tribute to the former Minister for the Gaeltacht, Mr. Paddy O'Toole, no longer a Member of the House.  He succeeded over the past four years in having an increased Estimate for Údarás.  Having provided an increased Estimate from £50 million to £60 million is only part of what is necessary.  I believe the essential thing is how this Estimate will be spent and the use to which it will be put is a matter we should be addressing now.  In that regard I would like to address a few remarks to the Minister of State, Deputy Gallagher, who is sitting in on the debate.</P>
      <P>I urge the Údarás officials to work more closely with the local people in general in the creation of jobs based in the Gaeltacht.  I do not mean by that the creation of foreign-based industries.  I mean the development of native-based jobs in the Gaeltacht in forestry, fishing, farming, tourism and peat development maintaining employment in using the natural resources already there and keeping people at home in this gainful employment, thus revitalising the life of the Gaeltacht and avoiding the workforce there having to emigrate.  It is only in this way we can preserve the language and the culture of the Gaeltacht.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I would like to ask if the Taoiseach is ready to announce plans for the extension of the pier on Inis Oirr and development of the harbour there.  The local people through the efforts of the local co-op have produced plans for a £1.6 million job on the pier and harbour at Inis Oirr, this money to be spent over four years.  They are seeking £800,000 a year over four years and they hope, through the social employment scheme, to employ 45 <Col N="411" /> people, the full workforce on Inis Oirr. It would be a tremendous achievement even on Inis Oirr, one of our smaller islands, to have the full workforce employed.  I am asking the Minister is there any announcement due in that regard.</P>
    <P>I bring up another matter about which the person who was in the Chair before Senator Cregan took over, Senator Martin J. O'Toole, would have great knowledge and I have considerable knowledge of it myself because I am involved in this end of the livestock industry. Efforts are being made to provide a marketing livestock mart at Maam Cross, right in the centre of Connemara between the two major Gaeltacht areas in Connemara. I think it would be a very suitable project to be grant-aided in whatever way possible.  It seems all of the livestock of Connemara &mdash; and I am aware of this myself &mdash; are now going either directly or indirectly to marts in east Galway or Mayo; in other words, they are being marketed through the marts system. Connemara sheep and Connemara cattle are unique in their own right.  They are a much sought-after breed, either mountain ewes or store cattle, by midland feeders and feeders elsewhere when they go to the bigger marketing centres the 100 or 200 cattle from Connemara are mixed up in a sale of maybe 1,000 cattle or 1,500 cattle in a mart in east Galway.  They lose their identity immediately and they look worse in comparison to the cattle from the better lands of the adjoining counties. If they had a market of their own in Connemara where all the stock would be brought together in one unit, not alone would it be beneficial to the area in saving transport costs, it would also be beneficial because people would seek to buy a certain type of stock and would get it in one centre.  This would be beneficial both to the seller and to the buyer of stock.  I am asking the Minister if any part of the grant can be provided for that purpose?</P>
    <P>I welcome the overall increase in the grant.  I ask that Údarás na Gaeltachta officials enter into very close liaison and discussion with co-ops, community councils <Col N="412" /> and local people, in an organised or unorganised capacity, to work out how this money can be spent for the better overall development of the area.  In the long term developing the Gaeltacht area by using its natural resources will help those living there and will make the areas attractive to tourists.</P>
    <Speaker pid="DenisGallagher" hpid="Aire Stáit ag Roinn na Gaeltachta (Mr. D. Gallagher) Aire Stáit ag Roinn na Gaeltachta (Mr. D. Gallagher)">
      <NameTxt>Aire Stáit ag Roinn na Gaeltachta (Mr. D. Gallagher)</NameTxt>
      <P>A Chathaoirligh, ba mhaith liom mo bhuíochas a ghlacadh leis na daoine a labhair ar an mBille seo agus an chaoi ar fháiltigh siad roimh an airgead a bheas á chur ar fáil do Údarás na Gaeltachta. Anois, an chuid is mó den chaint bhain sé leis an Údarás, ar ndóigh, agus bhí tagairtí chomh maith do rudaí nár bhain go díreach leis an mBille seo.  Ach níl mé ag rá nach ceart é sin nuair atáimid ag caint faoi airgead don Údarás.  Baineann sé leis an nGaeltacht ar fad agus níl locht ar bith ar aon duine labhairt faoi chursaí atá taobh amuigh de chúrsaí an Údaráis.  Is deas an rud é bheith in ann a rá, mar adúirt mé nuair a bhí mé ag caint ar dtús, go bhfuil daoine sásta le hobair an Údarás i láthair na huaire.  Fuair sé cuid mhaith drochphoiblíocht le cúpla bliain agus níor chuidigh sé sin le obair an Údaráis agus níor chuidigh sé le lucht tionscail a thabhairt isteach chun na Gaeltachta.  Chuir sé isteach cuid mhaith ar an obair a bhí ar siúl acu.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Fad is a bhaineann sé liomsa, mar Aire Stáit &mdash; agus tá mé cinnte go bhfuil mé ag labhairt thar ceann an Taoisigh, atá ina Aire Ghaeltachta &mdash; ní bheidh aon troid nó achrann againne le baill an bhoird nó leis na daoine atá i mbun an Údaráis i láthair na huaire.  Ní raibh sé i gceist agamsa bheith polaiticiil anseo, ach, tharla go raibh daoine eile ag tarraingt na polaitíochta isteach sa rud, tharla sé cúpla mí roimh dul amach don Rialtas atá caite, gur toghadh baill den Údarás go polaitúil ar fad ó na Gaeltachtaí rud nár tharla nuair a bhí muidne i gcumhacht.  Thogh muid daoine a raibh taithí acu ar chéard a bheadh i gceist i gcomhlacht cosúil leis an Údarás agus sin é atá san Údarás ar bhealach, comhlacht a bhfuil sé mar churam orthu cúrsaí na Gaeltachta a chur chun tosaigh.  Tá anmhuinín agam féin as an Údarás atá ansin <Col N="413" /> i láthair na huaire.  Tá muinín agam as na baill tofa atá ar an Údarás agus tá mé cinnte go mbeidh lan-tacaíocht ar fáil ó na daoine eile a thogh an t-iar Aire, le cuidiú leo ina gcuid oibre.</P>
    <P>Aontaím leis an Seanadóir Kelleher nuair adeir sé go bhfuil margaíocht tábhachtach ó thaobh chuid mhaith de na comhlachtaí atá ag an Údarás.  Ach, mar adúirt me, tá an-mhuinín agam as an bpríomhfheidhmeanach atá ann i láthair na huaire.  Tuigeann sé na cúrsaí sin agus má fheiceann sé comhlacht ar bith atá i sáinn nó ag iarraidh cuidithe den chineál sin beidh sé sásta teacht i gcabhair ortha agus cuidiú leo ina n-iarrachtaí chun margaí a fháil.  Bhí sé ráite ag Seanadóirí go gcaillfeadh an tÚdarás agus an Ghaeltacht de bharr nár ainmníodh Aire faoi leith don Ghaeltacht.  Le bheith praiticiuil ní fheicim go bhfuil mórán difríochta sa scéal.  Bhí taithí agam féin ar bheith mar Aire Ghaeltachta agus le mo linn bhí mé in ann Bille faoin Údarás a chur os comhair na Dála.  Tuigim cúrsaí na Gaeltachta, mar rugadh agus tógadh mé féin sa Ghaeltacht agus beidh comhoibriú idir mé féin agus an Taoiseach, maidir leis na cúrsaí seo agus tá suim aige sa nGaeltacht. Cuirim i gcás an Luan seo chugainn tá sé ag tabhairt cuairt ar an nGaeltacht is mó atá againn, ag caitheamh laé iomlám ann, ag buaileadh le muintir na Gaeltachta agus leis an Údarás.  Sílim nach gá do Sheanadóirí ar bith imní ar bith a bheith air go ndéanfaí faillí ar bith ar an nGaeltacht toisc gur fágadh é gan Aireacht iomlán, mar adúradh anseo ó cianaibh.</P>
    <P>Luaigh an Seanadóir Nicholas O'Connor cuid mhaith rudaí a bhaineann lena Ghaeltacht féin, ar ndoigh, agus fáiltím roimh an chuid is mó dá ndúirt sé.  Tá tábhacht an-mhór ag baint le próiséail éisc i láthair na huaire agus nuair a fheiceann tú go bhfuil comhlachta móra a raibh suim acu in obair de chineál eile sásta teacht anois agus infheistíocht an-mhór a dhéanamh, cuirim i gcás, i bhfeilméireacht éisc, sílim go mbeidh an-bhuntáiste ann san am atá romhainn.  Ach, mar a luaigh an Seanadóir, cé go bhfuil sé sin tábhachtach, sílím nach mbeidh an tairbhe nó an buntáiste ceart ann do mhuintir na Gaeltachta mura mbíonn an <Col N="414" /> pobal áitiúil in ann teacht ar an eolas atá ag na comhlachtaí móra sin.  Ansan beidh siad féin, muintir na háite, in ann bheith páirteach sa bhfeilméireacht éisc. Bheadh sé an-tabhachtach go mbeadh siad in ann dul amach agus úsáid a bhaint as an fharraige atá buailte lena gcuid feirmeacha agus cuid den saibhreas atá ann a fháil dóibh féin.  Sin é an rud atá i gceist ag an Údarás&mdash;ní hé amháin go bhfuil siad ag teacht i gcabhair nó ag tabhairt deontas do na comhlachtaí móra atá ag tabhairt faoi fheilméireacht éisc ach tá siad sásta, chomh maith, cuidiú le comhlachtaí eile, cuid de mhuintir na háite, a chuirfeadh comharchumainn agus comhlachtaí ar bun le dul ar aghaidh leis an obair seo.</P>
    <P>Tá sé tábhachtach chomh maith go mbeadh uisce, bóithre agus cumarsáid cheart sa Ghaeltacht más mian linn tionscail a tharraingt isteach sa Ghaeltacht agus tá dul chun cinn á dhéanamh sna cúrsaí seo.  Luaigh an Seanadóir Ó Conchúir an córas uisce atá i Ros a' Mhíl.  Sin rud atá tábhachtach.  Ní féidir próiseáil ceart a dhéanamh ar éisc, ní féidir comhlachtaí breise a thabhairt isteach, mura mbíonn na seirbhísí sin ar fad sásúil. Rachaidh mé féin chun cainte leis an Aire Chomhshaoil go bhfeicimíd an mbeidh muid in ann cúrsaí a bhrostú i gcaoi is go mbeidh na seirbhísí sin ar fáil.</P>
    <P>Tá an-obair déanta ag na comharchumainn sna Gaeltachtaí, go mór mhór le misneach a thabhairt do mhuintir na Gaeltachtaí.  Níl a fhios agam an bhfuil na deacrachtaí atá luaite ag an Seandóir chomh mór sin maidir leis an Údarás agus Roinn na Gaeltachta a bheith ag teacht salach ar a chéile.  Má tá aon chás ar leith ar mhaith leis a lua linn, deacrachtaí a dtig linn teacht tharstu beimíd sásta an rud a scrúdú agus ár ndicheall a dhéanamh annsin.</P>
    <P>Luaigh an Seandaóir Ó Murchú ansin an chaoi a raibh cúrsaí maidir le tionscail sa Ghaeltacht, go raibh sé sásta go raibh dul chun cinn á dhéanamh agus chuir sé an cheist an raibh sé sin ag cur isteach ar an chultúr agus ar an nGaeilge sna Gaeltachtaí.  Is dócha go bhféadfaí a rá, i dtús ama nuair a tháinig tionscail, go mb'fhéidir go raibh tionchar aige sin ar an nGaeilge ach ins an chuid is mó de <Col N="415" /> na monarchana i láthair na huaire sna Gaeltachtaí is iad muintir na Gaeltachta iad féin atá i mbun na hoibre, i mbun bainistíochta agus ní fheicim go bhfuil aon dainséar ó thaobh na cúrsaí sin.  Thug mé turas ar Ghaeltacht Chonamara cúpla seachtain ó shin agus bhí an-áthas orm a fheiceáil go raibh an oiread sin de bhunadh na háite i mbun bainistíochta agus ag tabhairt faoi obair a chuirfeadh ionadh ar na ghnáth phobal.  Aontáim ar fad leis an Seanadóir nuair adéir sé go mba bhreá an rud é dá mbeadh an pobal ar fud na tíre i láthair na huaire in ann dul amach chuig na Gaeltachtaí agus na monarchana bréatha atá ansin a fheiceáil agus an obair theicniúil atá ar siúl iontu.  Tá ríomhairí i mórán de na monarchana agus daoine de bhunadh na háite ina mbun agus ba bhreá an rud é dá bhféadfadh daoine nuair a bheadh siad, b'fhéidir, ag turasóireacht nó ag tabhairt cuairte ar na nGaeltacht dul isteach chuig na monarchana agus a fheiceáil céard atá ar siúl ansin.  Tá mé cinnte go dtabharfadh an tÚdarás lántacaíocht dóibh agus go mbeadh siad in ann iad a threórú agus gach eolas a thabhairt dóibh.</P>
    <P>Tá rud eile atá ar siúl ag an Údarás i láthair na huaire agus sílim go bhfuil sé an-tábhachtach agus luaigh cuid de na Seanadóirí é anseo.  Tá siad ag cur béime níos mó ar fhorbairt ár n-achmhainní nádúrtha.  Luaigh mé an fheilméireacht éisc, turasóireacht, talmhaíocht agus luaigh an Seanadóir McCormack é seo, go gcuirfí ionadaíocht margaíochta ar siúl i gceantar Chonamara a chuideódh leis na feirmeóirí a gcuid bheithigh a dhíol ina n-áit féin, in áit a bheith ag dul go Gaillimh Thior nó Muigh Eo.  Níl aon mioneolas agam ar an rud a luaigh an Seanadóir ach déanfaidh mé an rud a scrúdú agus tá mé cinnte má bhaineann sé le muintir na Gaeltachta agus go dtig linne i Roinn na Gaeltachta aon chuidiú a thabhairt beimid lán sásta é sin a dhéanamh.</P>
    <P>Ní thuigim go bhfuil tada eile a dtig liom a rá ach mo bhuíochas a ghlacadh leis na daoine a labhair.  Tá sé go deas, go suimiúil agus tá mé buíoch de gach duine.  Nuair a thagann Aire isteach agus go bhfaigheann sé an comhoibriú a <Col N="416" /> fuair muid anseo inniú is maith é.  Ar ndóigh tá an Ghaeilge agus an Ghaeltacht tábhachtach dúinn ar fad.  Tá an tÚdarás ag iarraidh ár gcultúr a chosaint agus a chaomhnú.  Fhad is atá obair le fáil ag muintir na Gaeltachta beidh sé sin ag tarlú.  Ach tá brú mór ar mhuintir na Gaeltachta ó thaobh teilifíse agus cúrsaí mar sin i láthair na huaire.</P>
    <P>Beimid ag iarraidh teacht i gcabhair orthu, agus luaigh an Seanadóir O'Connor Raidió na Gaeltachta.  Sílim go bhfuil an-chreidiúint ag dul chucu.  Is breá an rud go bhfuil éisteacht mhór acu ar fud na tíre anois agus ba dheas an rud é, mar a luaigh sé, dá mbeadh an tseirbhís sin le fáil ag ár ndaoine féin i Sasana agus i Meiriceá.  Is fiú, cinnte, na rudaí sin ar fad a scrúdú agus féachaint leis an cultúr a chosaint agus a chaomhnú agus a neartú.</P>
    <P>Cuireadh agus aontaíodh an cheist.</P>
    <P>Aontaíodh na Céimeanna eile a thógáil inniu.</P>
    <P>Cuireadh an Bille tríd an Coiste, tuairiscíodh é gan mholadh, glacadh é chun an breithniú deiridh a dheanamh air agus ordaíodh an Bille a chur ar ais chun na Dála.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Defence (Amendment) Bill, 1986:" RHead="Second Stage">
    <Title>Defence (Amendment) Bill, 1986: Second Stage.</Title>
    <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That the Bill be now read a Second Time.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelJNoonan" hpid="Minister for Defence (Mr. Noonan, Limerick West) Michael J. (Limerick West) Noonan">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Defence (Mr. Noonan,</NameTxt>
      <P>
        <i>Limerick West</i>): Before proceeding to deal with the details of the Bill I should like to give the House the background to it.  This Bill was introduced in Dáil Éireann by my immediate predecessor during the life of the previous Dáil but was not taken beyond First Stage.  The Government, on taking office, decided that the Bill should be adopted and sought and obtained Dáil approval for its restoration to the Order Paper of that House.  As Senators will be aware, all Stages of the Bill have since been passed by the Dáil and I am now bringing it before this House to seek approval of the measure here.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The purpose of the Bill is to introduce certain reforms and updating into the <Col N="417" /> existing code of military law as contained in the Defence Acts.  The Principal Act &mdash; the Defence Act, 1954 &mdash; was enacted by the Oireachtas more than 30 years ago and the need for revision has become evident over the years since that Act became law.  In general, the existing legislation has stood the test of time but, inevitably, legislative provisions which were designed to meet the circumstances of a particular time will require amendment and will not remain adequate for the needs of more than 30 years later.</P>
    <P>A number of substantial amendments to the 1954 Act have been made in the intervening years.  In 1960 there was amending legislation which provided for overseas service with the United Nations on peacekeeping missions.</P>
    <P>The last major reform in the field of military law was introduced by the Courts Martial Appeals Act, 1983.  That Act provided for the establishment of a special court to hear appeals against the findings and sentences of courts martial by persons convicted of offences against military law.  Free legal aid was also provided for, at court martial hearings and hearings by the appeal court, on conditions similar to those applicable to the grant of free legal aid in the civil criminal courts.</P>
    <P>The Bill now before the House is the outcome of a further review of military law which has been under way for some time.  Section 1 deals with interpretation. Section 2 updates the level of maximum fines which may be imposed by the District Court for a variety of offences in relation to military affairs and service property; generally speaking such offences would be committed by persons not subject to military law and would be tried in the District Court.  Examples of such offences are inducing a member of the Defence Forces to desert and trespassing on military property.  Sections 3 and 4 provide for increases in the levels of the maximum fines which may be imposed at summary trials and by courts martial for offences against military law and in the maximum amounts which an offender may be ordered to pay by way of compensation where compensation is appropriate.  They also provide for the linking of those maximum amounts to the <Col N="418" /> daily rate of pay of the offender as defined in section 1.</P>
    <P>Because of the decline in the value of money over the years, the maximum financial penalties prescribed in the 1954 Act are now of nominal impact only and have little if any deterrent effect.  This, I understand, has given rise to a situation in which military tribunals have, for some time, been faced with difficulty in imposing appropriate punishments.  The revised penalties proposed are aimed at easing this difficulty.  I would like to stress, however, that the actual penalties to be imposed will be at the discretion of the relevant tribunal within the prescribed maxima.</P>
    <P>Section 4 also provides for &mdash; (i) the introduction of a new punishment of reduction in rank for commissioned officers.  This punishment already exists for non-commissioned officers and in the case of officers will provide courts martial and the appeal court with an alternative penalty in appropriate cases.  It will bridge the existing gap between the very severe punishment of dismissal and the lesser punishment of forfeiture of seniority; (ii) an alteration in the order of the punishments which may be imposed on men of the Defence Forces so as to make &ldquo;detention&rdquo; a lesser punishment than &ldquo;discharge&rdquo; or &ldquo;discharge with ignominy&rdquo;; and (iii) modification of the existing very harsh consequential penalty of disqualification for State employment which is suffered by persons dismissed or discharged with ignominy from the Defence Forces.  In future there would be a time limit of seven years in so far as civil employment is concerned and the Government would have power to lift this part of the disqualification at any time.</P>
    <P>These amendments are designed to modify the severity of existing punishments. In the first two instances it is proposed, in appropriate cases, to provide alternatives for dismissal or discharge and the third instance represents a relaxation of the present very severe and inflexible provision.</P>
    <P>Section 5 provides for the creation of a new offence against military law, namely that of being under the disabling influence <Col N="419" /> of any drug or volatile substance. The section includes a provision that it will be a defence to a charge to prove that the drug or substance was prescribed by a medical doctor or was used in good faith for medical reasons.  The need for providing for the offence arises from the fact that military personnel are armed, are liable for duty at all times and must be capable of undertaking such duty at any time.  Military personnel are, of course, at present amenable to the ordinary criminal law in relation to drug abuse and will remain so.</P>
    <P>Sections 6, 7, 9 and 14 deal with different safety aspects of the flying and navigation of service aircraft.  The new powers being sought are particularly relevant to the operation of the sophisticated aircraft and helicopters now available to the Air Corps and to the increased incidence of civilian passengers being carried in military aircraft.</P>
    <P>Section 6 provides express power for the captain of a service aircraft to take appropriate measures in relation to nonmilitary passengers who may jeopardise the safety of the aircraft or of other passengers or property on board the aircraft. The section reflects powers already in existence in relation to the safety of civilian aircraft.</P>
    <P>Section 7 provides power to lop, cut or remove any tree or shrub on land in the vicinity of a military aerodrome which obstructs the safe take-off or landing of aircraft.  It will be necessary to give not less than 21 days' notice of such intention to the occupier of the land concerned who will be entitled to undertake the work himself if he so wishes, and be paid his reasonable expenses for so doing. Power already exists in the Defence Act, 1954, to prohibit the erection of other possible hazards to aircraft, for example, buildings or aerials, in the vicinity of a military aerodrome.</P>
    <P>Section 9 provides for the extension of the existing powers to erect and maintain signalling apparatus on lands or buildings in the vicinity of a military aerodrome so as to enable such apparatus, if required for air navigation purposes, to be placed <Col N="420" /> on land or buildings in the vicinity of any military post, not necessarily an aerodrome. This requirement relates mainly to the use of helicopters which land and take off nowadays at various military barracks.</P>
    <P>Section 14 provides for the expansion of the existing powers to make regulations in relation to the flying of service aircraft and for the certification and maintenance of such aircraft and aircraft material.</P>
    <P>Section 8 provides for the production of documents by civilians who are witnesses before military tribunals.</P>
    <P>Section 10 restricts the protection from imprisonment for debt which has in the past had an adverse effect on the credit-rating of non-commissioned service personnel seeking facilities from banks and other financial institutions.  The protection against imprisonment for nonpayment of debt which section 107 of the Defence Act, 1954, gives at present to non-commissioned personnel and to reservists on permanent service is unrestricted. In future in the case of non-commissioned personnel of the Permanent Defence Force it will apply only while they are on active service.  It will continue to apply to reservists called out on permanent service.</P>
    <P>Section 12 regularises the procedure for the prosecution of civilian witnesses before courts martial who are charged with contempt.  The provisions of the Defence Act which now apply require to be brought into line with the provisions of the relevant civil law.</P>
    <P>Section 13 increases the penalty for wearing, without the Minister's permission, any uniform of the Defence Forces, including any distinctive part of a uniform.</P>
    <P>The remaining provisons in the Bill are self-explanatory.  We will go into these during the Committee Stage and I will be happy to reply to any points raised on Second Stage.</P>
    <P>In the Dáil on Committee Stage of the Bill, I undertook to examine further in consultation with the Attorney General an amendment which was proposed at short notice.  I had not an opportunity of looking into the legal aspect of it.  The <Col N="421" /> purpose of that amendment was to facilitate certain court proofs in the case of members of the Permanent Defence Force serving overseas with an armed international United Nations force. Having examined the proposal in consultation with the law officers I decided to accept the amendment as desirable and I propose that on Committee Stage it be included in the Bill.  I commend the Bill to the House.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MauriceManning" hpid="Mr. Manning Mr. Manning">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Manning</NameTxt>
      <P>Before turning to the Bill I take this opportunity of congratulating the Minister on his appointment as Minister for Defence.  This is the first occasion on which he has spoken to the Seanad in his ministerial capacity.  I would like to wish him well in his tenure of office.</P>
      <P>The Bill we have before us this morning is a very unremarkable piece of legislation. It is largely concerned with updating certain regulations and bringing them into line with contemporary developments. It is a Bill which has a number of disparate elements as if it was a good occasion to get together a number of fairly important odds and ends and put them together in one Bill.  It covers a number of disparate areas, largely designed to bring developments up to date.  It is over 30 years since many of the provisions in the last Defence Act have been looked at and it is inevitable that we are now looking at some of these here this morning.</P>
      <P>By and large I think the Bill does its job adequately.  I am very pleased that the Minister has taken on board the points made in the other House and that he is prepared this morning to accept the amendment which was proposed and which I think will improve the Bill.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Before looking at the various parts of the Bill I would like to say a few general words about the role of the Army today. In the other House the former Minister for Defence, Deputy Cooney, referred to the Army as the last true professionals in our society.  That is a very fair and accurate description of the role of the Army in Irish life today.  For over 60 years now we have had an Army which <Col N="422" /> has always put service to the State above all other considerations.  It is an Army which, though it was born out of bitter political conflict, has always scrupulously and rigorously avoided any involvement or connection with party politics.  The Army has been starved of adequate resources from its earliest days.  I often thought it was a good thing that in 1939 our Army was not put to the test of proving our neutrality, of having to actually defend ourselves against any invasion because the Governments of the twenties and thirties, while professing great belief in a strong Army, had in fact begun a tradition which all Governments have been guilty of, that of not providing the sort of resources which a modern Army needs.  Nonetheless our Army has always performed at the highest levels of professionalism, whether at home, or more spectacularly in recent years, in its peacekeeping role for which it has won praise and commendation from many quarters throughout the world.  This has done a great deal to improve the performance of the Army itself.</P>
    <P>We are very lucky in the calibre and dedication of our armed services.  It is a long time now since the early days of the State when people compared our Army with the departing forces of the Crown and were inclined to make comparisons which were not favourable to our Army. That day has long since gone, and among all people in this country I think there is a very quiet and justified pride in the Army and in the role it plays and in the quality of our armed forces.  We as politicians, and by extension the public generally, make very excessive demands on the armed forces without being willing to vote the resources needed.  It is an age old problem but it does bring into focus the question of our neutrality which I have no intention of elaborating on at this particular moment.  I would ask one question about neutrality which I believe concerns our sincerity as a people.  If we really want to be neutral we must be prepared to defend ourselves like the true neutrals, the neutrals of what I call the strict observance of Sweden, the Austrians and the Swiss.  We should be prepared <Col N="423" /> to spend far more of our GNP on Defence.  We do not do this and I am quite certain we are not going to do so in the foreseeable future.  In a sense we are getting the best of all possible worlds; we are neutral without having to pay the price which the other neutral countries are obliged to pay.</P>
    <P>Sections 3 and 4 of the Bill concerning increasing the level of fines make a lot of sense, especially in regard to fixing fines in terms of a day's pay.  This will eliminate the cumbersome need of having to go to the Oireachtas to update financial fines. It is perhaps interesting to recall under the old system where a fine could be fixed at £5 for a particular offence, those fixing it could rest assured that £5 would mean roughly the same in terms of <i>pro rata</i> 20 years on, that £5 fixed as a fine in 1930 would mean roughly the same in 1950. Unhappily those days have gone and the device the Minister has put into the Bill meets the need there.</P>
    <P>I am in general agreement with the other main proposals.  Section 6 which gives additional power to the captain of a service aircraft in relation to civilian passengers merely extends the same power as already exists in the case of civilian aircraft.  It is a valuable addition to section 154 of the Defence Act.</P>
    <P>Section 8 which makes an addition to the law governing the summoning of civilian witnesses before courts martial or other military or legal proceedings again makes sense and arises from the experience of cases in the past.</P>
    <P>The proposals in section 12 provide the law governing contempt of court martial. This is a necessary legal reform and one which perhaps should have taken place many years ago.</P>
    <P>I have doubts about the proposals in section 4 which provide for an additional form of punishment.  I am referring in particular to the section dealing with the reduction of an officer from a commissioned to a non-commissioned rank. In practice this could prove to be unworkable. There are many and sufficient forms of punishment at present for an officer who is found guilty and I doubt very much <Col N="424" /> the practicality of reducing an officer to the ranks.  The officer so reduced could probably find great difficulty in being accepted in the ranks where previously he had held command, his brother officers would have great difficulty in dealing with somebody who was a classmate of theirs in military college and who had been a comrade of theirs on equal terms for so long.  I suspect that the psychological damage inflicted on someone so reduced might very well make him unsuitable at any rank in the Army.  I doubt also whether this situation might arise very often and I wonder if the change is necessary, if it is helpful or if it meets any particular need.</P>
    <P>I welcome the proposal in section 4 which allows a relaxation of the prohibition against State employment in the case of persons sentenced to be discharged with ignominy.  In fact, I am not sure what the term &ldquo;ignominy&rdquo; means at present.  Neither am I sure that it adds a great deal.  Perhaps some other phrase would be more appropriate in present times.</P>
    <P>I welcome the provision whereby somebody who has been discharged from the Army will not be disbarred from State employment. There are many areas of State employment of a menial kind for which somebody who had been so discharged but who had mended his ways and sorted out whatever problem he had, might well be appropriate.  It might very well mean that somebody could begin to remake their lives at a more humble, more reduced level but nonetheless remake their lives.  I welcome the element of discretion which is brought into all of this, that there is a seven year disqualification period but that the Minister can, in certain cases, reduce that number of years.  It is something which I believe will not be abused.  I believe that the standard applied by the Department of Defence and Ministers over the years in all appointments has been above reproach.</P>
    <P>I should like to get further information on the thinking behind section 10 which exempts soldiers from imprisonment <Col N="425" /> under certain Acts.  I am thinking here in particular of the Finance Acts.  Some people believe this section does not confer any particular privilege on soldiers but that in certain cases it makes it more difficult for them to get house loans or hire purchase finance.  I am not clear on this section.  Perhaps the Minister might comment on it.</P>
    <P>Section 13 deals with the penalties for the wearing of uniforms.  Obviously the Minister is right in this section.  Clearly the wearing of Army uniforms by Paramilitaries, by gangsters, or by people in the execution of crime cannot be tolerated. We must be very careful that the use of these uniforms is confined exclusively to those who have taken the oath and who are properly and legally entitled to wear them.  I have a small worry about the £1,000 fine.  I would like to see a certain amount of discretion used in this regard because in recent times we have all seen a custom, or a fad, or a fashion grow up in relation to the wearing of disused Army greatcoats.  I suspect some surplus FCA stock may have found its way into some of the secondhand clothes shops around Dublin.  Among students especially this habit has arisen in recent years.  They may not be all Irish Army uniforms, but surplus US uniforms and so forth.  I hope students who indulge in this particular fashion will not find themselves facing a £1,000 fine in court. I expect it will not arise.</P>
    <P>The Bill goes a long way to remedy the deficiencies which have been found in practice arising from the legislation which, in some cases, was outdated.  I wonder if it goes far enough.  I wonder if the Department of Defence might, at some stage in the future, conduct a fairly root and branch examination both of Army regulations and of Defence law to see if, in fact, there could be a streamlining of the system.  Some of the archaic and pointless provisions which still exist might well be weeded out and we will get a more contemporary version of regulations and of law.  However, I have no difficulty in supporting the Bill. <Col N="426" /> I am glad that the Minister has accepted the amendment from the other House.</P>
    <P>Debate adjourned.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Report of Committee of Selection:" RHead="Motion">
    <Title>Report of Committee of Selection: Motion.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="CharlesBMcDonald" hpid="Mr. McDonald Mr. McDonald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McDonald</NameTxt>
      <P>The Committee of Selection reports that it has nominated the following Members to serve on the Committee on Procedure and Privileges: &mdash; Senators Daly, Fallon, Ferris, Hanafin, Lanigan, McGowan, Manning, J. O'Toole, M. O'Toole and W. Ryan, together with the Cathaoirleach and Leas-Chathaoirleach, according to Standing Order No. 69.</P>
      <P>I move: &ldquo;That the report be laid before the Seanad.&rdquo;</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Defence (Amendment) Bill, 1986:" RHead="Second Stage (Resumed)">
    <Title>Defence (Amendment) Bill, 1986: Second Stage (Resumed).</Title>
    <P>Question again proposed: &ldquo;That the Bill be now read a Second Time.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="MickLanigan" hpid="Mr. Lanigan Mr. Lanigan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lanigan</NameTxt>
      <P>First, may I welcome the Minister on his first occasion in this House as Minister for Defence?  I wish him well in his new duties.  The role of the Minister for Defence has changed considerably over the past number of years.  I have absolutely no doubt that the Minister will bring to the job the type of expertise necessary in the ever changing role which is required of a Minister for Defence.  It is not often that we in this House get an opportunity to discuss matters relating to the Department of Defence and, in particular, the Army.  It is regrettable that we do not have more changes in legislative matters which would afford Members of the Oireachtas an opportunity to speak about the Army and their role at present.  The last substantial change was made in 1954, the Bill giving us the right to send peacekeeping troops overseas was introduced in 1960. Much has happened since 1954 within <Col N="427" /> Army circles and, indeed, quite a considerable amount has happened since 1960.</P>
      <P>The role of the Army in Irish life is a quiet one and too often we tend to forget about them.  We are not tardy about calling on them when we feel it is necessary for them to come to the aid of the civil powers.  On a day to day basis people see the Army as protectors of money going around the country.  The Army are more visible outside banks and post offices than in other areas of life in Ireland.  However, the role of the Army is not just a protective role of money.  Over the past number of years they have played a major part in peacekeeping abroad.  I have seen at first hand the excellence of their contribution to peacekeeping forces, particularly in the Lebanon.  Anybody who has had any contact with the Army abroad would have to say that they are the most professional of the armies involved in United Nations peacekeeping duties. Their conduct is exemplary.  They are welcomed by the residents of the countries where they play a peacekeeping role.  As members of the observer corps of the United Nations they go about their business in areas which are extremely difficult.  The fact that we have observer corps people in the city of Beirut shows that they are willing to go to areas where many others are not prepared to go.</P>
      <P>The role of the Army is a quiet one in cities and towns where we have an army presence.  The Army are respected and they play a major role in the social and cultural life where they are stationed.  It is very often forgotten that the Army presence in a city or town brings many benefits to the area.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The Bill before us is an accommodating Bill to update certain procedures within the Army particularly the upgrading of fines which were set in 1954.  It is not before its time that there should be this type of upgrading.  It seems ludicrous that fines imposed in 1954 should not have been changed until 1987.  I am glad that, even though there will be an increase in fines, such things as service pay and overseas allowance will not be taken into <Col N="428" /> account when a day's pay is the fine. Indeed, relating fines to a day's pay is probably a reasonable way to go about it.  The protection and supervisory role of the Army in our prisons plays a major part in ensuring that the gardaí and the prison officers and people working in prisons are protected to the maximum.  It is a bit incongruous that the Army personnel who are guarding these institutions are the worst paid of all the people involved in the protection and regulation of these places.  There is no doubt that the duty moneys paid to Army personnel for attendance at prisons is not sufficient. Indeed when one considers the overtime rates prison officers get for attendance at prisons, it is ludicrously low in comparison with payments to the gardaí and prison officers.</P>
    <P>The question was raised by Senator Manning of the new imposition of a reduction in rank of a commissioned officer.  I think that he is under a misapprehension here.  I do not think any consideration is being given to the reduction of a commissioned officer to a non-commissioned rank.  I do not think that would be practical but the introduction of a new clause whereby an officer could be demoted in rank among the commissioned ranks is probably an innovation.  The provision is there already for the non-commissioned ranks. I do not think it has ever stopped anybody from being promoted again to the rank from which he was demoted or indeed to get promotion over and above the rank from which he was demoted provided he has worked within the rules and regulations of the Army and has operated as best he could within the new arrangements for him.</P>
    <P>There is no doubt that the ignominy of a forced resignation of an officer, has created enormous difficulties for a number of people.  While at a certain stage, particularly in young officers' careers, they may have done things which they would not do in hindsight, the fact that they were thrown out of the Army puts a pall over their lives.  Indeed, I had a letter from America recently from one such person.  He feels he was denied the <Col N="429" /> rights he should have been afforded because he was thrown out of the Army under particular conditions.  He regrets what he did and, equally, he regrets the fact that he was thrown out of the Army and that he could never again get a post of any responsibility in the State services, and indeed he was precluded from ever again getting a job in the State services. I am glad there is a change in the regulations, in that a time limit is being put on, so that within a reasonably short time after conviction a person will again be eligible for employment in the State sector.</P>
    <P>I am not in total agreement with the fine of £100 for a witness who does not agree to pass over documentation to a court martial.  The fine is as out-of-line with today's conditions as was the £5 fine which was the maximum that could be imposed as a day's pay in the past.  I would like the Minister to see if the fines could be increased substantially if civilian witnesses do not pass documentation over to a court martial.</P>
    <P>As regards section 5, I totally agree there must be up-to-date regulations brought in regarding the abuse of drugs. We are extremely glad there has not been any drug-taking in the Army.  I am not saying there have not been isolated instances but in any real terms there has not been the incidence of drug-taking we have seen in many armies around the world.  The very existence of some armies is threatened because of the fact that drug-taking has become an epidemic. Whatever can be done must be done to protect the Army from the great problems that could arise if there was any increase in drug-taking.  The need for providing for the offence arises as the Minister said from the fact that military personnel are armed and are liable for duty at all times.  In this regard there should be a possibility of having intensive courses on drugs so that Army officers will be capable of recognising the results of drug-taking among personnel.  People who are not well versed in the effects of drug-taking may not realise that others are on drugs.</P>
    <P>As regards the new powers concerning <Col N="430" /> aircraft and navigation, it may be essential for owners of lands close by a military establishment to cut down a certain number of trees.  I do not want to see trees cut down anywhere but from a safety point of view it may be necessary that this should happen.</P>
    <P>Has any thought been given to the fact that around our coast at present naval personnel are coming under increasing harassment from locals in areas where there may be a conflict about fishing rights or about illegal fishing.  In quite a number of the seaports, naval personnel have been set upon.  In fact, the Garda and the civilian courts have dealt with the perpetrators of these particular instances but too often the fines imposed have been too small.  Our naval personnel play a major role for this country and I think that they should have more adequate protection when they come into ports.</P>
    <P>The Bill deals with uniforms.  We have seen in the past how Army uniforms and Garda uniforms have been worn to perpetrate crimes of an horrendous nature. Steps should be taken to ensure that people who wear these uniforms for such reasons are dealt with in as harsh a manner as possible.</P>
    <P>The Bill is relatively non-controversial. It is about time that the Bill came before the House.  I commend the Minister for bringing it in so soon at the start of this session of the Oireachtas.  I think it goes a long way to bring up-to-date many of the penalties for offences against the military law.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JohnMurphy2" hpid="Professor Murphy Professor Murphy">
      <NameTxt>Professor Murphy</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not think the Seanad will have any difficulty in accepting the Bill.  Since it purports to introduce certain reforms and updating &mdash; to quote the Minister's speech &mdash; the trouble is that it does not go far enough in that perhaps this is an appropriate time for the Government to ask themselves what is the purpose of the Army.  We are talking here about measures that have not been amended since the fifties and, as Senator Lanigan said, life and the world has changed very much since then.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I suggest that the role of the Army in this State is no longer what it was when <Col N="431" /> the Army was founded and, indeed, when the Army was expanded to its maximum point during The Emergency.  It was then taken for granted that the business of the Army was to defend the State against any aggression, against any invasion though if an invasion had happened during The Emergency it is very problematical as to whether the Army would have been successful.  However, this was its purpose as founded and as it has remained. Though the whole scene has changed with the development of nuclear strategy, our Army has in a sense, stood still.  There are very few of us now who could envisage a situation where the Army would go into combat to defend the State against hostile forces.  It seems that one of the two main functions of the Army now is the absolutely essential one of providing a reservoir of power to the civil Government. I cannot understand the views of some pacifists who dismiss the need altogether for the Army.  To avoid chaos it is absolutely essential to have this fall back sanction and, indeed, in the state of semicrisis in which we have been living for much of the State's existence and certainly in the past 17 or 18 years, the Army is absolutely essential.  The other main purpose is one that was not even dreamt of in 1954 and to which Senator Lanigan had paid a very complimentary tribute, namely, its role as a peacekeeping force internationally.</P>
    <P>Let me say that internally the Army is accepted by the citizens and respected by them but had a struggle to establish itself, if you like, because it was part of the Irish Free State which took a long time to gain complete acceptance and consensus.  Our Army had to contend with the existence of another and illegal army which referred to it right throughout the thirties and forties contemptuously as &ldquo;as the army of chocolate soldiers&rdquo;.  We know by now which is the real Army.  The role of the Army as a peace keeping force is an important service to the State internationally. If we have a certain status abroad, much of it is due, as Senator Lanigan said, to the admirable way in which the Army discharges its duty.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="432" /> I am glad the Army is properly subordinate to the civil power and that the Army is non-political.  The civil power should be always watchful in this regard. We went through a very bloody experience in this country in order to let the Army know where its place was; it must remember to keep its place.  I say this because one hears from time to time talk of Army interest in the North Atlantic Treaty Organisation and bodies like that and the possibilities of our Army becoming perhaps a component for some other larger defence grouping.  We must be extremely watchful about that.  In fact, I suggest that the great respect our forces have won abroad as international peacekeepers would be severely damaged should our Army come at any stage to be part of a war machine.  I hope, indeed, it will always be our Army, that there will be no other army on the territory of this State.  I know these are large matters to discuss in what is a fairly mundane Bill, but the principle remains that it is time for the Government to radically reconsider the role of the Army in this State.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PaulBradford" hpid="Mr. Bradford Mr. Bradford">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Bradford</NameTxt>
      <P>First, I congratulate the Minister on his appointment to his new role.  He comes from a neighbouring constituency to mine and I hope that some of his success may rub off down my way. I am sure he is in the envious position at the moment of being perhaps the only Minister in the Government who does not have to implement these dreadful things called cutbacks.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I am glad to have been afforded the opportunity to speak on this Bill this morning because it will allow me, at least for a few minutes, to comment on what I would see as the role of our Defence Force in the Ireland of today.  To some it may seem that a discussion on a Bill such as this which, in fairness, is not too far-reaching, may be relatively unimportant particularly when you consider the fact that our Army and its military capability, is quite small and, considering the nuclear age in which we live, not very important. While we cannot but admit that the might of our Army will not frighten away the military superpowers of the world, I think <Col N="433" /> we can be quite proud of the fact that since the foundation of this State our Army, in times of peace and trouble, particularly during what we call The Emergency &mdash; what other people call World War II &mdash; has served us well.  As ambassadors of peace, in troubled spots throughout the world, they have been very proud advocates of the Irish path of peaceful progress instead of war and strife.  Accordingly, we owe today to our Permanent Defence Force, not just a slap on the back, &ldquo;a thank you very much Captain&rdquo; approach, but a full commitment to their future, an offer of the best possible equipment to suit their needs and, most important, whatever is deemed necessary to provide them with the best possible working conditions.</P>
    <P>There is no doubt that despite our political role and our military or, more appropriately perhaps, our non-military role remaining the same in world affairs for many decades, our Permanent Defence Force has undergone profound change.  Despite our low GNP we have provided our military forces with sufficient funds to enable them to run a very well-equipped, superbly trained force which is perhaps very suitable to the limited military needs of the Irish people. As I have said already, the Army is an outstanding ambassador abroad of our desire for peace in the troubled spots throughout the globe.  Despite these unquestioned and unquestionable facts, despite the achievements of other sections of the defence forces, in particular, the Army Equitation School which has brought honour and glory to this country and which I believe was the first body to raise the Irish Tricolour outside of this State, and even the Army Band, the Army has become very well known and famous throughout the world, but there are still many people in this State who would question seriously the role of our Irish Army today and ask whether we need it at all.</P>
    <P>The point can be made quite validly that our Army could never hope to stop an invading horde of reds or blues or invaders of whatever colour from wherever they may come.  Unfortunately, the <Col N="434" /> size of the budget available to this country and to the Army will never allow us to compete with the military might of some of these countries but even if the budget would allow us to do so I would hope we would not go down that path towards military madness.</P>
    <P>The most disappointing comments in regard to our Army, however, come from those who would question the ability and commitment of those who serve within the Defence Forces.  In particular, it is very sad to hear comments which would indicate that the Army is really nothing but the last outpost for those who cannot find a job elsewhere.  Not only is this very far removed from the truth but it is a gross insult to all those who are prepared to put service to the nation and to peace throughout the world before their own personal safety.</P>
    <P>I admit that many of those who are serving as privates in the Army came into that position after being unemployed for quite some time.  Many people on the present unemployment register are hoping to &mdash; and will &mdash; get into the Army at some stage.  Qualities such as courage, strength, bravery, determination and discipline which are necessary for a person to serve in the Defence Forces, are at a premium in the Ireland of today. There may be no guarantee of a job for a person having these qualities in some of our more sedate positions so, therefore, let us not question the ability or the commitment of those in our Defence Forces.  As was said in the Dáil, they are the supreme professionals, putting their country and others before themselves. How many other so-called professionals would be prepared to do that in the Ireland of today?  I do not think there are very many.</P>
    <P>I am sure the changes proposed in the Bill are not sending shock waves throughout the Army.  In a sense they are quite limited.  To the general public they may not even be noticed or commented on. Those of us whose slight worry about our Defence Forces is their seemingly total independent form of judiciary and punishment, we must at least question the need for and the extent of these changes. <Col N="435" /> In general the question must be asked whether the need to increase military fines is an indication of a greater level of petty crime within the ranks.  Perhaps the Minister may set that record straight at some stage.</P>
    <P>I would be the first to admit that the fines were so small as to render them almost meaningless.  While it is welcome that the new range of fines are linked to the level of pay within the forces the new maximum fines could be very harsh in some cases, on those on lower salary scales.  However, the new maximum fines need not be implemented; they will only be implemented at the discretion of the judiciary in charge.  That is welcome because I presume they will use their commonsense on that matter.</P>
    <P>I welcome the provision in section 4 which will allow those dismissed from the forces to at least apply later on for employment in some other State quarter. Ruling these people out totally was very discriminatory.</P>
    <P>Section 5 deals with drug related matters and is, I suppose, a reaction to the change of environment in which we live today.  We see and hear much on a daily basis about the threat of drug abuse.  This problem threatens every group within society, from the poorest to the wealthiest. While this is not a major problem in our Army I am sure other armies throughout the world are finding it a problem.  This section will help ensure that where this problem exists it will be stamped out at an early stage.  While I am on the question of drug abuse, what is the position regarding alcohol?  In fairness, the Army were never considered to be the second Father Matthew Brigade. If there is a problem with regard to alcohol what is the Minister's position on it?  Will there be restrictions regarding alcohol?  Admittedly, drugs such as cannibis and heroin are more spectacular by name at least and would render quite poor the operations of an Army officer if he were under such an influence but as we know, alcohol could also do the same. I would like clarification on that matter.</P>
    <P>Section 7 deals with the need to remove <Col N="436" /> or change any structures causing obstruction, for instance, to army airfields, bases etc.  That is very welcome.  I hope that any changes taking place or any moves being made by Army personnel as a result of this section will be done so only after full consultation with the people involved.  There is no point in moving in on a person's property without full consultation.  It is very important that an organisation such as the Defence Forces maintain good relations with the general public.</P>
    <P>Section 10 is also very welcome because for far too long many ordinary members such as privates were disadvantaged due to the bad example of a few regarding debt repayments.  The regulation to allow for the imprisonment of a non-commissioned officer for non-repayment of a debt will help those who are genuinely committed to paying any debts they may incur and increase any chances they have of getting a loan whenever necessary.</P>
    <P>Section 13 which deals with military uniforms is quite brief but I presume it is quite important, particularly because of the position regarding subversives within the State.  During the past number of years subversives wearing uniforms that were taken from members of the Garda conducted their own form of checkpoints. The provision here in relation to military uniforms will help ensure that this will not happen with Army personnel, that we will not have any difficulty in sorting out who is who.</P>
    <P>The Bill is brief and the changes it proposes to introduce are not too far fetched or too drastic but I am sure they will help strengthen the resolve of the Army towards their work.  The Bill will help also to increase public awareness of the work the Army are doing.  For far too long we have taken the Army for granted and have not appreciated the position they hold in our system of democracy. As Senator Murphy said earlier, because of the Northern crisis, it is very important to keep an Army in position so that they can defend our democracy if required to do so.  That may sound like a slightly dramatic statement, and I hope it will not <Col N="437" /> come into being, but nevertheless it is good to know that we have people such as those in our Defence Forces to fall back on whenever they may be required. Down through the years history has shown that, if required they could do the job more than adequately.  I have every confidence in them today.  While this Bill will not change things too much, it will certainly help the Army to carry out their duties in a more professional and orderly manner.</P>
    <Speaker pid="VivianOCallaghan" hpid="Mr. O'Callaghan Mr. O'Callaghan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Callaghan</NameTxt>
      <P>I was not aware when this Bill was introduced this morning that Members would avail of the opportunity to make wide ranging comments on the activities of the Army.  I would like to be associated with the expressions of congratulations to the Minister on his new appointment.  I have no doubt that he will discharge his responsibilities in the very fine way he did as spokesman on agriculture for the then Opposition.</P>
      <P>I subscribe to almost everything that has been said this morning by way of praise for the Army.  We tend to take them for granted.  Perhaps that is a good thing because the profile of the Army is such that they are obliged &mdash; and do so quite happily &mdash; to take a backseat role in the general running of the country.</P>
      <P>We were all conscious of the debate in recent weeks during the power strike when the Minister was under pressure from various Deputies to say he was not in a position to put members of the armed forces into the various power stations. During various industrial crises, successive Ministers have consistently said they did not see the role of the army as that of strike breaking.  Notwithstanding that point of view, there is a responsibility on the Department of Defence to provide and devise some strategy whereby at least some minimal form of assistance can be forthcoming when the country is held up to ransom as happened in recent weeks during the ESB strike.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Even though we are looking forward to a period of peace in relation to the activities of our workers the subject needs to be addressed to some degree. <Col N="438" /> Army personnel in this city have been called out during refuse strikes, national bus strikes and so on.  If it is permissible to break strikes in some areas I do not see why it should not be permissible in others.  The Minister might look at that sometime in the future.</P>
    <P>Senator Bradford said the Minister was in the happy position that he did not have to bring down the axe, and did not have to initiate any cuts in his Department. However, I am aware that during the past number of years there has been a form of run down at least in the funding to the FCA.  We should never underscore the importance of the role of the FCA particularly in rural communities.  The FCA fill a vacuum for young people who might have an interest in military matters and who might be induced to join some other military grouping if their interest in military matters was not serviced by way of introduction to the FCA.  The FCA have provided a very useful escape valve for young people who have an interest in military matters and who have an interest in being in the Army in a peripheral way. I am aware of the fine work being done by the FCA in my own area.  It would be unfortunate if there was any run down of the FCA.  I am aware that some summer camps and so on are being curtailed. Young people look forward to going to these camps and it would be unfortunate if they were run down.  I ask the Minister to be mindful of that.</P>
    <P>Most of what I would like to say with regard to this Bill has been touched on by previous speakers.  Senator Lanigan referred to the difficulty in relation to our Naval personnel.  It is a bit disconcerting, to put it mildly, to see our Naval people being harassed on a regular basis in pursuit of what is their statutory obligation. This can be construed only as an attack on our military forces.  It is not good enough to try these cases in the local district court where fines of between £50 and £100 are imposed.  In the intervening period our Naval personnel are being subjected to the type of threat that unfortunately they cannot respond to and which no doubt, they are very often <Col N="439" /> anxious to respond to.  That is something the Minister should look at.</P>
    <P>I would like to refer to section 14 which deals with the activities of military aircraft. Now that we have at long last acquired night-flying aircraft and night-flying helicopters I hope we will see these in operation as quickly as possible.  A provision should be made to suppress the nonchalant attitude that some people have to calling out an aircraft or search craft at any time of the day or night.  A person may decide to go to sea without recognising the risk he is placing himself at but by virtue of his indifference he may also be placing at risk the lives of military personnel who may have to go out in the middle of the night to save him.  There are people who do not bother to ensure that their craft is seaworthy.  They may not listen to weather forecasts and so on. A few years ago the British RAF Services risked life and limb during the Fastnet race off the south coast when people went to sea in the knowledge that the forecast was such that it was quite dangerous to go.  But when they got into difficulties they had no reservations about calling out the RAF and thereby endangering their lives as well as their own.  The Minister should consider making some provision for that.  If people call out aircraft, especially at night and it is subsequently established that there was no need for them to be out there should be some provision in the Act whereby the people responsible would be prosecuted because apart from the danger to life the costs alone are quite great.</P>
    <P>I welcome the increase in fines in the area of misuse of military uniforms. Senator Manning quite rightly said that there is a great interest among young people in military uniforms; it is almost cult at this stage.  A fine line has to be drawn somewhere.  We have heard the disquiet being expressed by the Garda recently because the new Garda uniforms which are only about a month old have already been copied by some security companies.  It is mindboggling to think that the military can make provisions for this and yet the Department of Justice <Col N="440" /> cannot.  I find that difficult to reconcile. It is welcome that at least it has been addressed in this case.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelJNoonan" hpid="Minister for Defence (Mr. Noonan, Limerick West) Michael J. (Limerick West) Noonan">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Defence (Mr. Noonan,</NameTxt>
      <P>
        <i>Limerick West):</i> I thank the Senators for their interest in the Bill.  I appreciate the sentiments they expressed in regard to my appointment.  I thank them also for their good wishes in regard to my success in this position.</P>
      <P>The many items raised this morning will receive my attention.  In the course of my reply I hope to get the opportunity of referring to some of them.  I should like also to take this opportunity to wish the Seanad every success in its deliberations on the various matters that will come before it in the future.  I wish also to take this opportunity of acknowledging and endorsing the tributes paid by Senators to our Defence Force.</P>
      <P>The Bill is an important measure from a military point of view.  It contains a number of amendments which are of significance to the Army.  Many of the proposals incorporated in the Bill have come from the Army.  I would like to offer some further comments on the contents of the Bill and to touch on some points raised by Senators.</P>
      <P>As we know, the main objective of military law is to provide for the maintenance of good order and discipline among members of the Defence Force. These are essential attributes in any military force.  They are usually maintained by supplementing the ordinary criminal law and the ordinary judicial system with a special code of discipline and a special system for enforcing it.  It is, of course, necessary to maintain the operational efficiency of the armed forces.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Military law is contained in the Defence Act, 1954, in several amending Acts, including the Courts Martial Appeals Act, 1983, and the many statutory instruments such as the Defence Force regulations and the rules of procedure made under those Acts from time to time.  The Defence Act, 1954 creates a number of offences in relation to military affairs or property which are triable summarily in the District Court.  Examples of <Col N="441" /> such offences are, inducing members of the force to desert and the unlawful wearing of military uniform.  Such offences are punishable on conviction by the District Court by the imposition of a fine or imprisonment.  The less serious offences against military law committed by junior officers, NCOs and privates, is disposed of summarily by authorised officers, commanding officers and subordinate officers.  The range and severity of punishments awardable by such officers is strictly limited by law and falls far short of that available to a court martial.  Where a case is being dealt with summarily the offender may, if the punishment which the officer trying the charge proposes to impose is a fine or otherwise involves monetary loss, opt for trial by court martial. The options are there.</P>
    <P>Courts martial are the military tribunals provided by law for the trial by officers of the Defence Force of persons accused of offences against military law. The finding and sentence of a court martial are not valid unless confirmed by a confirming authority &mdash; an officer authorised by the Minister.  The provision in the Courts Martial Appeals Act, 1983, of a system of appeal to the court martial appeals court against the findings and sentence of a court martial, and of a scheme of free legal aid, represented a major reform of our system of military law.  Apart from the appeal process, a person convicted by a court martial has the right to petition against the sentence of the court martial, the authority to whom the petition is addressed and all petitions may, if the convicted person so wishes, be submitted to the Minister.  The Minister, therefore, is empowered to mitigate the punishment awarded or to remit it in whole or in part.</P>
    <P>Senator Manning made reference to fines and the increases in fines.  It is well to remember that the fines which may be imposed for offences against military law have been in force since 1955.  I am sure Senators will agree that there have been changes in the cost of living since then. These fines have become totally unrealistic having regard to the change in the value of money since 1955.  For example, <Col N="442" /> the amount of £5 which is the maximum fine which a court martial may impose on a private soldier represented about two weeks' pay in 1956.  The maximum fine proposed for a private under the Bill is six days' pay or about £130 in current terms.  Fixing fines, therefore, by reference to so many days' pay also means that the amount of the fines will be self-adjusting. The amounts being prescribed are maximum amounts and it will be a matter for the authority concerned to decide on the levels of the fine, etc., within the maximum amount being laid down.</P>
    <P>The abuse of drugs which has been referred to by many Senators is one of the scourges of modern society.  Thankfully we do not have a problem in this respect in the Defence Forces.  Considering that many military duties are performed under arms, the possible use of the drugs in the Defence Forces would be truly alarming and would have the most serious implications.  Therefore, it is proposed that the offence should be made a specific and clearly identifiable offence against military law.  I am sure the House will agree that this should be done in the context of the Bill and Members in their contributions said this.</P>
    <P>Reference was made by Senator Manning to punishment.  Punishment of reduction in rank at present may be imposed by a court-martial on a non-commissioned officer.  The introduction of a similar penalty in the case of an officer would provide a court-martial with an alternative to the severe punishment of dismissal or of the lesser punishment of forfeiture of seniority.  It was felt that there was a considerable gap between those two punishments and the new punishment is an appropriate means of filling this void.  In particular circumstances one of the punishments could be too lenient and perhaps the other too severe.  It is right that this type of punishment should be introduced.  An officer who was reduced in rank under the proposal would of course, continue to be an officer and would have an opportunity to rehabilitate himself.  Experience has <Col N="443" /> shown that reduction in rank happens in very exceptional circumstances only.</P>
    <P>Senator Manning referred to employment. Present disqualification from State employment arising from dismissal in certain circumstances lasts a lifetime.  This applies to employment with the State. In the case of employment in a civilian capacity with the State it is proposed that the disqualification should be modified to seven years and that the Government should have the necessary power to remove that disqualification at any time during the seven years.  No change is envisaged in the disqualification from employment in a military capacity. Having examined that aspect of it and discussed it with the relevant military and civil authorities, I have come to the conclusion that this bar should continue.</P>
    <P>Reference was made to the lopping of trees and so on.  When the Defence Act, 1954, was enacted the Defence Forces had no helicopters. Nowadays military helicopters land at and take off from military installations and other places.  Therefore, the necessity may arise to erect certain apparatus on lands or buildings adjacent to such installations to facilitate the helicopter operations.  Section 9 of the Bill provides power to do that.  Power already exists under section 35 of the 1954 Act to erect and maintain apparatus in the vicinity of military aerodromes.</P>
    <P>Senator Manning stated that it is being represented that protection against legal proceedings, which it contained in section 107 of the Defence Act, 1954, works to the disadvantage of members of the permanent Defence Forces in that their credit rating can be adversely affected. This protection is now being modified so as to be available in future to permanent defence personnel only when they are on active service.  That is the difference.  The protection applies at present to reserve Defence Forces personnel only when they are called out on permanent service. This is the equivalent of active service and no modification is required in this instance.</P>
    <P>As I have already stated, in recent <Col N="444" /> years we have had difficulties with regard to lopping of trees on private lands.  It is desirable that the Minister should have power to ensure that hazards of this type are removed as quickly as possible.  As I explained in my opening address, the landowner will be invited and given the opportunity to do the necessary work himself and will be compensated and paid reasonable expenses.  If he is not prepared to do that, the work will be carried out by the Department.</P>
    <P>Senator Manning also made reference to equipment.  Within the budgetary constraints and with the resources available to the Department, there is a continuous programme of improving the equipment of the Defence Forces and providing them, as far as possible, with up-to-date equipment.  This is being done on an ongoing basis.  The capability of the Defence Forces to discharge their roles is kept under constant review and changes are made as necessary.  For example, the helicopters purchased in recent years will be fully operational within the next six or seven months.  That is an example of the up-to-date position with regard to equipment.  It is constantly under review and will have to be kept under review because of the sensitive areas in which the Defence Forces are involved.</P>
    <P>Senator Lanigan raised the question of pay.  The pay of all ranks in the Defence Forces has, over the years, been increased in accordance with the terms of national and public service pay agreements. In addition, pay is increased from time to time in line with grade and special awards in certain areas of the Civil Service. The question of pay is constantly kept under review.  In line with national pay agreements, members of the permanent Defence Forces will be adequatley compensated.</P>
    <P>Senator Lanigan also mentioned the £100 fine.  It only relates to summary trials and not to courts martial.  Refusal to produce documents at a court martial puts a person in contempt and liable to a fine of £1,000 or 12 months imprisonment.</P>
    <P>Senator Lanigan also made reference to our troops serving with UNIFIL.  As I <Col N="445" /> said in the other House, the safety of our troops serving with the United Nations is a matter that is kept under constant review.  My Department are in daily contact through the military authorities with the situation in Lebanon and are kept abreast of the position on an ongoing basis.  I have asked to be fully appraised daily of the situation in Lebanon.  The troops selected for UNIFIL service undergo a very rigorous programme of training designed to assist them in carrying out their peace-keeping duties and to provide for their protection.  They are issued with a modern range of weapons and equipment.  Having reviewed the recent contingent which went to Lebanon, I am satisfied the training and the weapons and equipment are adequate to ensure their maximum safety consistent with the performance of their duties.  We must realise that no peace-keeping operation can be entirely without risk.  The Government are continuing to monitor the developments in south Lebanon with a view to taking whatever measures may be necessary at any time to ensure the safety and welfare of our troops.  Having met the troops after their recent tour of duty some couple of weeks ago, I know their commitment to peace-keeping operations is total.  They see it as a great challenge to their position as soldiers.  The role of the Irish Army is very acceptable to the local people in Lebanon.  The whole operation within UNIFIL and our peacekeeping operations overseas are matters that are kept under constant review.  I am in daily contact with the situation.  It will continue to be monitored on a daily basis and we will review the situation from time to time.</P>
    <P>Senator Murphy spoke about the role of the Army.  He is quite right in saying that the role of the Army is not the same now as it was many years ago.  Perhaps the time is now opportune to have a look at the whole Army operation and have a full review of its role in its totality and the place of the Army because the situation is changing.  This is something which will be receiving my attention over the next number of months.  Senator Murphy outlined his views.  I would like to point <Col N="446" /> out that basically the role of the Army is to defend the State.  There are other roles which the Army can adopt time to time. Aid to the civil power has assumed a major importance over the past 18 years. Peace-keeping duties have an important place in Army life.  There are other areas which I will be looking at.  We will have a full review of the role of the Army.</P>
    <P>I want to thank Senator Bradford and all the other Senators for their compliments and good wishes to me.  Senator Bradford and I come from neighbouring constituencies.  I hope we can contribute in whatever way we can.  I would be very glad to do what the Senator wants if I were the only Minister not to be subject to cutbacks but unfortunately that is not the case.  Senator Bradford also mentioned the reason for the increase in fines. It has nothing at all to do with the level of offences in the Army.  It is just that the level of the fines is out-of-date.  The Senator also made reference to drunkenness. That is already an offence against military law under section 142 of the 1954 Act.</P>
    <P>I share the views of Senator O'Callaghan in regard to the importance of the FCA which has a major role to play in the military context.  Unfortunately, due to financial constraints it has been necessary to curtail the period of annual training in recent years.  I see the role of the FCA as very important.  I will do everything possible to enhance their reputation and their position.  I will have an opportunity in coming weeks to visit their summer camps and see the situation myself at first hand.</P>
    <P>Senator O'Callaghan also raised the issue of serious attacks on Naval service personnel in the context of fishery protection. These attacks are to be deplored. The punishment is a matter for the ordinary criminal law and I hope that will be attended to.</P>
    <P>There were a number of other matters raised during the course of the debate and these will be receiving my attention. Indeed many of them are already receiving my attention.  I would like to thank <Col N="447" /> Senators for their expression of appreciation of our Defence Forces whose service at home and indeed abroad is so highly regarded.  It is important that we acknowledge that fact publicly when the opportunity arises.  I welcome and unreservedly endorse the generous tributes paid to the Defence Forces in this House.</P>
    <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
    <P>Agreed to take remaining Stages today.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Defence (Amendment) Bill, 1986:" RHead="Committee and Final Stages">
    <Title>Defence (Amendment) Bill, 1986: Committee and Final Stages.</Title>
    <P>Sections 1 to 12, inclusive, agreed to.</P>
    <P Just="Center">NEW SECTION.</P>
    <P>Government amendment No. 1:</P>
    <P>In page 11, before section 13, to insert the following section:</P>
    <P>&ldquo;Section 248 of the Principal Act is hereby amended by the insertion in paragraph (a) after subparagraph (ii) of the following subparagraph:</P>
    <P>&lsquo;(iiA) having, or not having, at any specified time or times, served outside the State as a member of the Permanent Defence Force with an armed International United Nations Force, or&rsquo;.&rdquo;.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelJNoonan" hpid="Minister for Defence (Mr. Noonan, Limerick West) Michael J. (Limerick West) Noonan">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Defence (Mr. Noonan,</NameTxt>
      <P>
        <i>Limerick West):</i> The purpose of this amendment is to facilitate certain matters in the case of a member of the Permanent Defence Force who was serving overseas with an armed international United Nations Force at the time of the alleged offence.  As I have already mentioned an amendment with a similar purpose was <Col N="448" /> moved at short notice when the Bill was being debated at Committee Stage in Dáil Eireann.  While it was not possible for me to accept the amendment proposed without having had the opportunity of giving the proposal a detailed examination I undertook that following full consideration of the matter, if such a provision was found to be desirable, I would introduce a suitable amendment to the Bill.  The amendment now before the House is designed to provide a simple and straightforward means of proving, in effect, that the accused person was, in fact, on active service when the offence was committed, a position that would arise in the case of overseas service with an armed United Nations force.  I commend the amendment to the House.</P>
      <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
      <P>Sections 13 to 16, inclusive, agreed to.</P>
      <P>Title agreed to.</P>
      <P>Bill reported with amendment, received for final consideration and passed.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Business" RHead="of Seanad">
    <Title>Business of Seanad.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="MickLanigan" hpid="Mr. Lanigan Mr. Lanigan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lanigan</NameTxt>
      <P>It is intended that we sit next Wednesday at 2.30 p.m.  The main business on that day will be a continuation of the Companies (No. 2) Bill, 1987, and it is intended to spend one and a half hours on the Fine Gael motion on budgetary proposals in relation to the health services.</P>
      <P>The Seanad adjourned at 1.15 p.m. until 2.30 p.m. on Wednesday, 27 May 1987.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
</Debate>