<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE Debate SYSTEM "../Debate.dtd"[]>
<Debate DocTitle="D&aacute;il Debate" Day="Fri" Date="5" Month="Apr" Year="1974" Vol="271" No="12" DateIrish="Dé hAoine, 5 Aibreán 1974" DateEnglish="Friday, 5 April 1974" House="D" CommitteeEng="" CommitteeIr="" SubNameEng="" cnum="0">
  <MainHeading Type="Prelude" LHead="" RHead="">
    <Title>
    </Title>
    <P>
      <Col N="1765" /> Chuaigh an Ceann Comhairle i gceannas ar 10.30 a.m.</P>
    <P Just="Center">
      <i>Paidir.</i>
    </P>
    <P Just="Center">
      <i>Prayer.</i>
    </P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Order of" RHead="Business">
    <Title>Order of Business.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickSDonegan" hpid="Minister for Defence (Mr. Donegan) Patrick S. Donegan">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Defence (Mr. Donegan)</NameTxt>
      <P>It is proposed to take business in the following order: No. 1 and No. 11 (resumed).</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Local Elections (Petitions and" RHead="Disqualifications) Bill, 1974: First Stage">
    <Title>Local Elections (Petitions and Disqualifications) Bill, 1974: First Stage.</Title>
    <P>Leave granted to introduce a Bill entitled an Act to make provision in relation to local election petitions, to make provision in relation to membership disqualifications with regard to local authorities, to enable certain restrictions on holding office under or being employed by a local authority to be modified, to repeal certain enactments relating to local elections and to make other provisions connected with the foregoing.</P>
    <P Just="Right">&mdash;(Minister for Local Government.)</P>
    <Speaker pid="SeanTreacy" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Seán Treacy">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>Next Stage?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JosephBrennan" hpid="Mr. Brennan Mr. Brennan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Brennan</NameTxt>
      <P>When will the Bill be circulated?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesTully" hpid="Mr. Tully Mr. Tully">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Tully</NameTxt>
      <P>During the recess.  I should be grateful if the Opposition would arrange to discuss this measure very early after the recess because I should like to have it enacted before mid-May.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JosephBrennan" hpid="Mr. Brennan Mr. Brennan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Brennan</NameTxt>
      <P>We will have to have a look at it first.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesTully" hpid="Mr. Tully Mr. Tully">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Tully</NameTxt>
      <P>It is non-contentious. Could we say 24th April?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickJLalor" hpid="Mr. Lalor Mr. Lalor">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lalor</NameTxt>
      <P>It would be no use ordering it for the 24th April because our principal spokesman would not be <Col N="1766" /> able to take it before 30th May at the earliest.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesTully" hpid="Mr. Tully Mr. Tully">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Tully</NameTxt>
      <P>Could we order it for the 24th of this month?  As I say, it is not a contentious measure and someone else might be able to deal with it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanTreacy" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Seán Treacy">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>There would be no obligation to take it on 24th April.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickJLalor" hpid="Mr. Lalor Mr. Lalor">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lalor</NameTxt>
      <P>Very good.  Then it can be ordered.</P>
      <P>Second Stage ordered for Wednesday, April 24th, 1974.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Financial Statement, 1974:" RHead="Motion (Resumed)">
    <Title>Financial Statement, 1974: Motion (Resumed).</Title>
    <P>Debate resumed on the following motion:</P>
    <P>That Dáil Éireann takes note of the Financial Statement made by the Minister for Finance on 3rd April 1974.</P>
    <P Just="Right">&mdash;(Minister for Finance.)</P>
    <Speaker pid="FrankCluskey" hpid="Parliamentary Secretary to the Minister for Social Welfare (Mr. Cluskey) Frank Cluskey">
      <NameTxt>Parliamentary Secretary to the Minister for Social Welfare (Mr. Cluskey)</NameTxt>
      <P>Last night I dealt in a somewhat limited way with what this budget is all about and I said that the best word to describe the budget, as far as we are concerned, is the word &ldquo;concern&rdquo;.  Looking at the provisions in the budget one sees immediately that it does not slavishly follow the pattern of previous budgets where social welfare recipients are concerned, the pattern of adding small sums to benefits, but illustrates rather that considerable thought which has gone into new areas of need in our community.  When I say &ldquo;new areas&rdquo; I do not mean that these social problems have only recently been visited upon some of our people.  I mean new areas from the point of view of assistance and help to people in particular categories.  It is fair to say, I think, that Fianna Fáil priorities were somewhat different.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I said last night that the people in this House are seasoned politicians. They are able to guage where the <Col N="1767" /> voting power is and I believe that Fianna Fáil had come to the conclusion, and rightly so, that innovations in the field of social security were not the best way in which to attract votes.  The main difference between this Administration and the last Administration is clearly demonstrated in this.  There are certain areas in which the number of votes is not and cannot be the main criteria for a Government because there is a responsibility on a Government to ensure that social justice is clearly demonstrated by the Government on behalf of all the people.  That to me is the main difference between the last Administration and the present Government.</P>
    <P>Last night I spoke about a particular problem we have in our society, the problem of poverty.  No extensive research into this particular area was engaged in by the previous Administration and the only figure we have, although some people have doubted its accuracy, is that 20 per cent of our people live in poverty&mdash; 20 per cent of the people in our society live in poverty.  I am not talking about relative poverty, I am talking about basic poverty.  I am talking about not having enough to eat, not having sufficient clothing and not having a roof over one's head.  I understand that 215,000 children are born and live in these circumstances.</P>
    <P>What this budget meant to me and what the fact that 20 per cent of our society live in poverty meant to me was brought home very forcibly when I read yesterday's edition of the <i>Irish Independent.</i> That newspaper carried a photograph of a lady of 82 years of age and she was asked what the budget meant to her and what the increase in pension meant to her. When she was asked what she would do with the extra money she replied that she was badly in need of underwear and the extra money would also help her save up for a new pair of shoes.  Asked if she would be able to spend more on food she replied that with eggs a shilling each she had not been able to afford them but that now she might be able to get an odd egg, <Col N="1768" /> or a rasher or a bit of cheese.  That old lady told the interviewer that she eats very simply but only because she has to.</P>
    <P>These comments, as far as I am concerned, are the greatest indictment that could possibly be made against the political party who have held power in this country for practically four-fifths of the time since we gained independence.  That was the concern and that is the result of the concern that was shown by the Fianna Fáil Governments for the people in this category.  We know, just as the Deputies opposite know, that there is no great organisation amongst old age pensioners and that no great political pressure can be brought on Governments to give them some measure of justice.  If one feels that they do not figure in their sense of priorities one can politically afford to ignore them to some extent.</P>
    <P>We did not choose to do that and I am proud to be a member of a Government that did not choose to do that.  I am sure there are many members of the Fianna Fáil Party who have seen over the last 13 months what it is possible to do in this area and who must now be wondering&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    <Speaker pid="CharlesJHaughey" hpid="Mr. Haughey Mr. Haughey">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Haughey</NameTxt>
      <P>Did I ignore them?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrankCluskey" hpid="Mr. Cluskey Mr. Cluskey">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cluskey</NameTxt>
      <P>The Deputy was for a long number of years a prominent member of the Cabinet of Fianna Fáil Governments and I will give the Deputy a statistic which will answer his question.  Of the last ten budgets, eight were introduced by Fianna Fáil and in those eight the total amount allocated to social welfare by Fianna Fáil was £54 million. In the two budgets which our Minister for Finance, Deputy Richie Ryan, introduced in this House on behalf of the National Coalition £88 million has been allocated to social welfare. In my view that answers the Deputy's question.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="CharlesJHaughey" hpid="Mr. Haughey Mr. Haughey">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Haughey</NameTxt>
      <P>I asked if I ignored old age pensioners when I was Minister for Finance.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrankCluskey" hpid="Mr. Cluskey Mr. Cluskey">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cluskey</NameTxt>
      <P>With respect, I am not here to have a personal exposure <Col N="1769" /> of conscience with any Deputy, including Deputy Haughey, but the fact remains that Deputy Haughey was a prominent influential member of Fianna Fáil Governments.  In fact, Deputy Haughey was Minister for Finance.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="CharlesJHaughey" hpid="Mr. Haughey Mr. Haughey">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Haughey</NameTxt>
      <P>The Parliamentary Secretary was in this House to hear several of the budgets I introduced and, therefore, should be able to answer my question.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrankCluskey" hpid="Mr. Cluskey Mr. Cluskey">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cluskey</NameTxt>
      <P>If one averages out the figure I have given one will find that over the eight years it averages out at approximately £7 million per year by Fianna Fáil to social welfare while the two budgets introduced by the present Minister for Finance average out at £44 million per year. That is the answer to Deputy Haughey's question.</P>
      <P>While I believe I was right in putting that on the record I feel the responsibility of a Government is not just to indulge in exposing the lack of social conscience on behalf of a previous Administration irrespective of the magnitude of the problem in a particular area which they have been presented with through years of neglect. In that army of 20 per cent in the poverty category Fianna Fáil was the recruiting sergeant.  The Fianna Fáil policy on social welfare was the recruiting sergent that brought that figure to 20 per cent of our population. It is the intention, and the commitment, of this Government eventually to eliminate that category from our society, and that can be done; there is no question about that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>However, it cannot be done overnight and it cannot be done without sacrifice.  It means a contribution from the other 80 per cent of our population. There is a notion in some quarters that 5 per cent of our population are very rich and that if we concentrated all our efforts on extracting money from them we would solve all our ills.  That is a very silly notion and one which would not work.  Every member of our community has a responsibility to contribute a fair proportion within reasonable bounds, within his or her ability, to solving these ills.  It should be <Col N="1770" /> clearly understood that concentrating solely on the 5 per cent and trying to transfer the 5 per cent to the 20 per cent while at the same time ignoring the 75 per cent will not work.  The 75 per cent also have a responsibility in this area.  It is on all our consciences that we have 20 per cent of our people who have not enough to eat, whose ambition after 80 odd years helping to build up the relative affluence we have in this society is, as with the poor unfortunate lady in our capital city, to be able to buy a set of underwear. These, then, are the facts.</P>
    <P>In this budget the Minister has allocated £100,000 towards combating poverty.  This Administration are convinced that the handing out of money alone will not solve the problem of poverty because we know that certain side effects result when families have to live in poverty for a prolonged period and these side effects must be tackled as part of any attempt to solve the poverty problem.  It is our intention to set up in the immediate future a committee of experts in this field to advise us on the operation of pilot schemes, the purpose of which will be to rehabilitate into the main stream of our society families who are in the poverty category.  It is our hope that after a limited period of operation these pilot schemes will indicate what should be the proper means of eliminating poverty.  In our 14-point programme we gave a commitment to alleviate and, eventually, to eliminate poverty.  Unfortunately, poverty cannot be eliminated overnight but we can take immediate steps towards alleviating the problem.  Undoubtedly this Administration have taken such steps both in this budget and in the last one.</P>
    <P>It was rather pathetic to sit here on Wednesday last after the Minister had concluded his statement and to watch Deputy Colley search frantically for some grounds on which to attack the budget.  Apparently, to attack is the mentality of the Opposition.  Their approach seems to be to cut the head off anything that shows itself.</P>
    <Speaker pid="CharlesJHaughey" hpid="Mr. Haughey Mr. Haughey">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Haughey</NameTxt>
      <P>The Parliamentary Secretary is not a bad hand at that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1771" />
    <Speaker pid="FrankCluskey" hpid="Mr. Cluskey Mr. Cluskey">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cluskey</NameTxt>
      <P>But I am usually constructive.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="CharlesJHaughey" hpid="Mr. Haughey Mr. Haughey">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Haughey</NameTxt>
      <P>He is not a bad protagonist.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrankCluskey" hpid="Mr. Cluskey Mr. Cluskey">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cluskey</NameTxt>
      <P>We have not heard very much constructive comment from the Opposition benches since March, 1973.  Indeed, occasions come to mind readily on which we had what was bordering on the irresponsible from the people opposite.  For example not very long ago we had a situation in which the junior hospital doctors were on strike.  Consequently, the people whom we were elected to represent were seriously concerned not only for their health but for the lives of those who were ill.  The point I want to make is that the comment made at the time by the spokesman on health for the Opposition could only be described as being irresponsible.</P>
      <P>I confess to having had some sympathy for Deputy Colley on Wednesday last.  I was in Opposition for a number of years and I know the difficulties of being in that situation but I know also the tactics of being in Opposition.  I know that it is a legitimate tactic for an Opposition immediately before a budget to begin demanding improvements which, in their opinion, cannot possibly be made. The people expect that from an Opposition.  They can read between the lines but on this occasion we witnessed Deputy Colley standing up to oppose the budget against the background of a speech made a week previously outside this House by the Leader of his party who called on the Government to grant a 25 per cent increase in social welfare benefits.  Deputy Lynch never found it possible to grant any such increase so I suppose it was reasonable that he would assume that no one else could either.  He was calling for something which, in his private opinion, could not possibly be done.  But, unfortunate Deputy Colley had to criticise a budget which, to all intents and purposes, had achieved what the Leader of the Opposition had called for in respect of social welfare benefits.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>In this budget there is an across-the-board increase of 18 per cent for a <Col N="1772" /> nine-month period and, if one calculates that increase for a 12-month period, the figure is slightly more than 24 per cent.  One must have sympathy for any Opposition spokesman on finance whose task is to criticise any such budget.  As has been indicated again clearly by the Leader of the Opposition, Fianna Fáil in Opposition, could not even adjust their thinking towards something constructive and just so far as people on social welfare benefits or assistance are concerned.</P>
    <P>There are many difficulties involved in the whole area of social welfare and there is yet a long way to go.  Nobody on this side of the House from the Taoiseach down, would suggest for a moment that, despite what has been achieved&mdash;and this has been considerable&mdash;enough has been done or that people in this category are receiving what could be described as an adequate amount of money on which to live.</P>
    <P>There is a long way ahead but we have started and made substantial progress in 13 months.  What the present Administration thought and did in this area is on record.  What the last Administration thought is not on record.  What they did is but what they thought nobody knows because they have never produced it in a written policy in the history of their political life.  All their actions and pronouncements have been activated by political expediency.</P>
    <P>I should like briefly to illustrate what has been done not in a haphazard way but with the intention of doing something to ensure that a completely comprehensive social security system will operate in this country. Our approach was not just to stick on something here, put 2p on that and 10p on this.  What we have done in our 13 months of office bears out what I said earlier this morning, that the word which best describes this budget is &ldquo;concern&rdquo;.  Since this Government came into being they have introduced a pay-related benefit scheme, the abolition of the £1,600 income limit, a system of payments to deserted wives, a system of financial help to enable unmarried mothers to keep their children.  In this budget we <Col N="1773" /> have removed a glaring injustice that has existed during the years by giving the non-contributory old-age pensioners' dependants an allowance, an increase involving £3.65 per week.  We have introduced a prisoners' dependants allowance and a scheme for single ladies of more than 58 years in certain circumstances.</P>
    <P>Look at all these things, particularly at the last four.  The problems involved are not new.  Like any other society, we have had unmarried mothers.  They were not discovered until March, 1973.  We have had families of long-term prisoners suffering in some cases more than the prisoners who were supposed to be paying debts to society.  The prisoners knew they would have three square meals a day and a bed at night, but their families did not know that.  That is what we mean by concern.  There are not many people involved in these categories, not many votes, but it was still right to do it and it would have been as right for Fianna Fáil to have done it.  However, there were no votes.</P>
    <Speaker pid="CharlesJHaughey" hpid="Mr. Haughey Mr. Haughey">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Haughey</NameTxt>
      <P>Full marks for it, full credit.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrankCluskey" hpid="Mr. Cluskey Mr. Cluskey">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cluskey</NameTxt>
      <P>Single ladies in certain circumstances&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="CharlesJHaughey" hpid="Mr. Haughey Mr. Haughey">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Haughey</NameTxt>
      <P>Full credit for that too.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrankCluskey" hpid="Mr. Cluskey Mr. Cluskey">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cluskey</NameTxt>
      <P>Our provisions will relieve a tremendous amount of hidden hardship and suffering.  The majority of these single ladies&mdash;it is impossible to tell the exact number&mdash; who will benefit from this scheme in the main have come from relatively comfortable homes.  They were relatively comfortable in their childhood and young womanhood but a parent lived on, the rest of the family left to marry and they continued to look after these parents until they died. They had no qualifications to get employment. They were people who found it extremely hard to go seeking financial assistance, even if it was there by way of home assistance.  Suddenly they found themselves really up against it.  I am convinced that a tremendous amount of hidden suffering <Col N="1774" /> will be relieved by the introduction of this scheme.</P>
      <P>As I have said, these people have been with us during the years.  We did not discover them.  The National Coalition did not import them.  They have been here all along, but again the criterion of &ldquo;no votes, no help&rdquo; was applied by the last Administration.</P>
      <P>I will not detain the House much longer but I should like to give a brief idea of the difficulties we have faced and the advances that have been made in spite of these difficulties.  We listened to the bursts of hysteria from the Opposition benches after they had heard the provisions of this budget. They said that the social welfare benefits would not mean anything because of the eroding influence of inflation&mdash;that the effect of these increased benefits would be lost because of inflation.  Undoubtedly, there has been inflation and it presented tough problems to this Government as it did to every Government in Europe and beyond it.  However, thanks be to God we have managed to weather that storm better than most in Europe.  We were supposed to get panic-stricken and the Irish people were supposed to look back and say: &ldquo;Dear God, in our hour of need where are Fianna Fail?&rdquo; I think the people are looking back at this moment and saying: &ldquo;Thanks be to God&rdquo; period.  Deputy Haughey is reasonably good at figures, better than I am&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="CharlesJHaughey" hpid="Mr. Haughey Mr. Haughey">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Haughey</NameTxt>
      <P>I am amused at the way the Deputy has been invoking God so frequently.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrankCluskey" hpid="Mr. Cluskey Mr. Cluskey">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cluskey</NameTxt>
      <P>Why not?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="CharlesJHaughey" hpid="Mr. Haughey Mr. Haughey">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Haughey</NameTxt>
      <P>There is no reason why the Deputy should not but I thought he would be attributing the thanks to his own economics.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrankCluskey" hpid="Mr. Cluskey Mr. Cluskey">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cluskey</NameTxt>
      <P>The people were supposed to thank Fianna Fáil.  Personally I would sooner thank God, along with the Irish electors, especially for the removal of Fianna Fáil.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>In the period from the third quarter of 1972 to the third quarter of <Col N="1775" /> 1974 the most pessimistic estimate of the rise in the consumer price index would be 28 per cent.  Even an outrageous Fianna Fáil spokesman would find it difficult to go over that figure. Between March, 1973 when this Government came into office, and July, 1974, we will have increased by 37 per cent the pension of a single contributory pensioner.  The increase will be 45 per cent for a couple over 68 years of age on contributory pension, 39 per cent for a widow on contributory pension, 40 per cent for a person on unemployment benefit, 42 per cent for a non-contributory pensioner and 42 per cent for a deserted wife.  Child dependant allowance will have risen by 70 per cent for widows on contributory pensions. There will be an increase of from 60 to 80 per cent for other recipients of benefit, 78 per cent for widows and deserted wives on non-contributory schemes and 70 to 100 per cent for other assistance categories. Those figures are published.  They are available.  They are not speculation, they are fact.  Deputy Haughey can check them, the House can check them, the Press can check them.  They are on public record.</P>
    <P>That is the difference.  All the whining, all the distortion, all the inaccuracy, will not take away from that fact.  When this poor unfortunate lady next July opens her purse on pension day she will know that it is a fact She will know it is not enough, we will know it is not enough but she will know that it is a fact.</P>
    <Speaker pid="CharlesJHaughey" hpid="Mr. Haughey Mr. Haughey">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Haughey</NameTxt>
      <P>Mícheál Mac Liammoir could not do better.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrankCluskey" hpid="Mr. Cluskey Mr. Cluskey">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cluskey</NameTxt>
      <P>I know the Deputy is a patron of the Arts but I think it would have been far more beneficial to the people of this nation if, as Minister for Finance, he had been a patron&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="CharlesJHaughey" hpid="Mr. Haughey Mr. Haughey">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Haughey</NameTxt>
      <P>I did more for the old age pensioners than you have done and they know it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrankCluskey" hpid="Mr. Cluskey Mr. Cluskey">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cluskey</NameTxt>
      <P>&mdash;&mdash;of the people in this category.  It might have been far <Col N="1776" /> more beneficial if he had given a little more time to studying the plight of those people in the 20 per cent poverty category&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="CharlesJHaughey" hpid="Mr. Haughey Mr. Haughey">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Haughey</NameTxt>
      <P>I looked after the old age pensioners and they know it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrankCluskey" hpid="Mr. Cluskey Mr. Cluskey">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cluskey</NameTxt>
      <P>&mdash;&mdash;which his Government made possible and paid less attention to the paintings and the plays and the rest.</P>
      <P>We made a public commitment in the 14-point programme.  We have heard from across the House that we have broken promises.  The commitment on which we were elected was for a five-year period.  Thirteen months of that time have gone by and very substantial progress has been made in honouring that commitment in the area on which I have concentrated.  I have no doubt that despite the difficulties that exist in this area we will by pursuance of this policy alleviate in the short term and eliminate in the long term that 20 per cent which is the result of Fianna Fáil's lack of concern about other than the Taca belt.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="CharlesJHaughey" hpid="Mr. Haughey Mr. Haughey">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Haughey</NameTxt>
      <P>A budget can be many things.  Ideally, of course, it should be a blueprint for the management of our economic and social affairs at least for the period of one year but, if possible, with indications for a much longer period than the year immediately concerned.  The purpose of a good budget should be to set down the economic and social pattern for the year, to endeavour to chart the progress both of the economy and, indeed, of the social system of the community. Public attention is, very naturally, in regard to any budget focussed on what is in the budget&mdash;the taxation measures, the tax reliefs, the social welfare benefits and so on&mdash;but the really important and significant aspect of this budget is what is not in it.  I think what is in it is fairly predictable. Through the efficient operation of the Government Information Service the territory which the Minister was to traverse in his budget was fairly well outlined for us in advance of it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>My general criticism of the budget, as distinct from any particular aspects <Col N="1777" /> of it with which I will deal later, is that it makes no attempt whatever to deal with the many large, formidable economic problems which confront us today in this community.  It does not attempt to come to grips with these problems.  Neither does it make any attempt to promote or even outline the steps that might be taken to promote economic and social development in the medium term apart altogether from the long term.  I would mention just a few of the particularly significant, major problems which seem to me to confront this Administration.</P>
    <P>First of all of course there is the problem of prices.  There is the very threatening situation which is developing in regard to our membership of the European Communities.  There seem to be very serious doubts and misgivings as to the continued existence of the Community as such and, in addition, even if the Community continues to exist as we know it there are the lines along which its policies seem likely to develop.  There is, of course, the ever present driving, urgent need for economic development.  We are inclined to forget from time to time that we still have in the region of 70,000 people unemployed.  There is the problem of the development of the western seaboard counties and the question of implementing a regional policy in this area.</P>
    <P>We might have expected the Minister to make some reference to these and to the various other major economic problems which confront us.  His review of our economic situation in general and the prospects for the future, was pathetically inadequate. For instance, under the heading of international monetary developments he treats us to a string of meaningless platitudes.  He has nothing to say on the vital question of the value and the parity of our Irish pound.  This is a matter which must be engaging the attention of our financial authorities. Are we going to continue our parity with sterling?  Are we going to maintain our reserves largely in their present form?  These are vital and urgent financial questions and the Minister has almost completely <Col N="1778" /> ignored them in what purports to be his review of the economic situation.</P>
    <P>On the question of interest rates, a matter of fundamental importance which dominates the entire business scene today, the Minister only produces the following gem of jargon:</P>
    <P>The desirability of keeping interest rates here as low as possible is fully recognised and the position is being kept under constant review.</P>
    <P>I think for the businessman attempting to plan his operations or for the hard-pressed householder with a mortgage who is attempting to pay exorbitant rates of interest it will be a source of great consolation to them to know that somewhere in the Department of Finance somebody was keeping the situation under constant review.  Under the heading &ldquo;Use of credit&rdquo; we find this particular nugget:</P>
    <P>...capital is as basic and fundamental a necessity for economic development as oil or electricity. Industry and agriculture will have problems enough in financing essential investment without the community adding to the difficulties by improvident expenditure on luxuries and speculation.</P>
    <P>That, I am sure the House will agree, is a very penetrating comment on the whole credit situation and it comes by the way from a Minister who, by the very publication of his White Paper on Capital Taxation, has completely distorted the entire investment climate in this country.  All he can find to say about credit policy is in effect that it is as important as oil or electricity and we must eschew improvident spending on luxuries and speculation.</P>
    <P>I submit that the Minister's review of our economic situation and our prospects for the future is a litany of banalities which a leader writer of a minor provincial newspaper with a hangover could easily improve upon. The management, for instance, of our capital investment programme is dealt with by a page of trivialities.  The Minister makes no attempt whatsoever to deal with the very major issues which confront us in this area.  I believe <Col N="1779" /> it to be a key area and that on the success with which we handle our capital investment programme will depend very largely the success or failure of all our economic efforts.</P>
    <P>The financing of this year's capital programme in itself seems to me to present the Minister with very considerable problems and difficulties. Apart from the expanded capital investment programme in the public sector he has to find an additional £76 million to finance the budget deficit. As the Leader of the Opposition pointed out, there is a formidable task of considerable magnitude facing the economy in providing the resources to meet these commitments.  The Minister has not given us any satisfactory outline of the manner in which he will cope with this problem. He has given no indication whatever of how he hopes to provide the necessary capital involved.</P>
    <P>Some years ago in the Department of Finance a scheme of long-term capital budgeting was initiated.  The Minister has made no mention whatsoever of this in his budget speech. This is becoming one of the most important areas in economic programming and economic planning. The idea that one can put forward a capital budget for a period of 12 months on its own is now hopelessly out of date.  Any sensible approach to economic planning must, I think it is generally agreed, be based on long-term budgeted capital investment. Increasingly our capital programmes must be looked at over five or even ten-year periods.  The amounts involved are becoming enormous, and the period of years involved in capital investment is also becoming very considerably extended. For instance, we have on the stocks at the moment a proposal for a nuclear reactor.  The capital involved in this is of substantial proportions and the period over which that capital will be extended will be many years.  There is also looming up the problem of the exploration of our offshore oil.  The Minister for Local Government has brought in a Bill to provide him with the necessary <Col N="1780" /> statutory authority to build motorways. In every area of the economy massive capital expenditures are looming up.</P>
    <P>In these circumstances the idea of bringing forward a budget for a capital programme for 12 months is almost meaningless, and I want to criticise the Minister for this short term approach, for completely ignoring in his budget speech, what are the long-term capital commitments of the economy, how they will be met and what has become of the scheme of long-term capital programme budgeting which was initiated in the Department some years ago.</P>
    <P>It is becoming increasingly clear, too, that the new industries which are being established are of a size and scale completely different from those to which we have been accustomed in the past.  The sort of industries we want now are large-scale, sophisticated technological complexes.  In some cases I understand that their current day-to-day needs are in the region of £10 million or more.  Many of these are giant operations, and their day-to-day requirements, apart altogether from the capital investment involved, are of great magnitude indeed.  Is the Irish banking system expected to cope with these needs out of their own domestic resources?  As I understand the operations of many of these multinational corporations, they are prepared to provide long-term capital investment from outside, but they expect the domestic institutions to provide their day-to-day working requirements.</P>
    <P>In that connection, I want to ask the Minister would he, for heaven's sake, review this idiotic stance by the Central Bank in regard to borrowing from outside by Irish financial institutions. According to the directive, if an Irish financial institution raises money outside the country, it must deposit half the amount involved at a penal rate with the Central Bank.  This, in effect, prohibits Irish financial institutions going abroad and securing funds which they could use very satisfactorily in the domestic market.  In view of the large-scale requirements of many of these new industries, it seems <Col N="1781" /> to me that this directive is outmoded and should be rescinded.  I suppose the basis for it is that the Central Bank wishes to prevent the importation of inflation in this way.  However, in that regard the situation is absurd because I understand State bodies can go abroad and borrow what they like.  In the present climate everything points to our Irish financial institutions having access to the international monetary markets and availing of their resources for the benefit of industrial development here.</P>
    <P>I am very concerned about the situation in regard to agricultural credit.  In the context of the Minister's capital programme agricultural credit and, in particular, the Agricultural Credit Corporation, seem to be the poor relation.  There are now 75,000 to 80,000 farmers who are embarked, to a greater or lesser degree depending on their individual competence, on expansion programmes.  Many of them have committed themselves to development programmes and there is going to be an avid demand in the next five, six or even ten years for agricultural credit.  In that sort of situation it is very disappointing to see that in regard to the Agricultural Credit Corporation the Minister has eliminated the £8 million provided in last year's capital programme, and that the total resources available to the Agricultural Credit Corporation will be increased by a mere £4,500,000. That seems to be a pathetically inadequate increase, particularly when it is related to increases under other headings in the capital programme.</P>
    <P>The Agricultural Credit Corporation's programme is restricted to £15 million to be provided from its own resources and £19 million from external resources.  I understand that &ldquo;external resources&rdquo; in this context does not really mean external resources; it simply means resources outside the public sector.  The Agricultural Credit Corporation will have to carry on its operations with £15 million provided from its own internal resources and £19 million raised on the domestic market.  Apart altogether from the inadequacy of the overall total of £34 million to which that <Col N="1782" /> amounts, the fact that the corporation will have to go on to the domestic market to raise £19 million in competition with other institutions will seriously impede the efficacy of its operations.</P>
    <P>I should very much like to hear something on this whole situation from the Minister.  We have about 80,000 farmers who are now gearing themselves to meet the challenge of the EEC market and there will be competition for a share of that market.  It is quite clear that British agriculture is expanding; so is Danish agriculture.  Our competitors in the Community are preparing to win for themselves a larger section of the expanding Community market.  The efficacy of our attempt to take part in this competitive process will be very largely determined by the capital&mdash;first, the amount of it and, secondly, the rate of interest at which it is obtainable&mdash;that we make available to our farmers.  Against this background of farmers attempting to re-equip and stock their holdings for this necessary expansion, the proposal by the Minister to introduce tax on farmers becomes slightly bizarre.</P>
    <P>It is very difficult to ascertain from the Minister's speech what exactly is the situation in regard to economic planning or programming.  One would have thought that an economic plan or programme of some sort was a <i>sine qua non</i> for a modern developing economy.  When we in Fianna Fáil were in office we were continually berated by the Opposition of the day, led usually by Deputy FitzGerald on the grounds that our plans and programmes were inadequate and unsatisfactory, but we now have the situation where there is no plan or programme of any sort.</P>
    <P>I find the Minister's statement contradictory in this regard.  On one hand he says quite clearly that the Government have decided that it would not be possible to publish a meaningful programme.  Later, referring to the establishment of the National Economic and Social Council he said: &ldquo;I shall be consulting the council in the course of the preparatory <Col N="1783" /> work on the new programme for economic and social development.&rdquo; It seems to me that there exists a very clear contradiction between these two statements and I should like the Minister to state what is the situation.  Admittedly, the economic climate is uncertain; nevertheless, I believe it is almost essential for any consistent, coherent attempt at economic development that we should have an overall plan of some sort for some period.  This is a very real and particular criticism which can be levelled against the Government's approach to our economic affairs in general&mdash;the fact that they have not prepared and put before the country a coherent economic plan to which all can relate their own efforts and plan their own development.</P>
    <P>On the taxation side the most significant thing in the budget is the Minister's proposal to introduce income tax for the farming community.  Apart from any other consideration the timing of this proposal is ill-advised. If the Minister feels that there are some overwhelming reasons why farming as such should be brought within the income tax provisions, I should have thought that a statement of intent in this regard with a period in which the farming community could prepare for the eventuality would have been the proper approach.  It is iniquitous for the Minister to introduce income tax on farming and at the same time retain local rates.  This is entirely indefensible.  If this major and significant change were to be made in regard to the farming community, they were at least entitled to have their overall situation examined and the introduction, if it was necessary, of income tax related in some way to a gradual elimination of rates.  It is grossly unfair, even iniquitous, simply to provide for a system of income taxation on top of the already unsatisfactory system of taxation of farming by local rates.</P>
    <P>There is another aspect of the matter to which it is important to draw attention here.  The Minister in his budget address suggested that the changes we were making would involve <Col N="1784" /> only 9,000 farmers out of a total of 170,000.  It seems to me that a far greater number will, in fact, be involved. I refer in particular to the fact that the Minister intends to make new provisions in regard to the income tax allowances to which farmers are entitled. In his statement the Minister said:</P>
    <P>The same issue arises where the farmer, whether married or single, has non-farming income of his own. To deal with such cases, it is proposed that, in the case of farmers not now being brought within the scope of income taxation, only one-half of the appropriate personal allowances will be set off against non-farming income, whether of the farmer or of his wife.  This restriction will apply as from 6th April, 1974.</P>
    <P>This is a very serious proposal and I doubt very much if the farming community as yet have realised fully what is involved in it.  I am totally opposed to this.  Whatever about the figure of 9,000 farmers who will be affected by the new proposals in regard to income tax as such, there will be anything up to 40,000 or 50,000 farmers affected by this particular provision.  What is involved here is that where a farmer or his wife has income other than that provided by the farm, he will be allowed claim only one-half of his personal allowances against the non-farming income.</P>
    <P>One of the emerging features of rural Ireland is the situation of the small farmer on the uneconomic holding finding off-farm employment, in industry, forestry or elsewhere to make ends meet.  This section of farmers will be savagely penalised by this provision.  I cannot see any justification whatever for it.  In fact, many people who are concerned with the small farm problem, particularly in the western countries, hoped that one possible solution would be that the family farm would be maintained as a domestic base while members of the family would find employment in local industry and in other branches of economic activity.  That was regarded by everybody concerned as a welcome <Col N="1785" /> development.  No matter how efficiently or well they are managed, many small farms are quite incapable of providing satisfactory standards of living for the farm family.  One solution to the problem which this presented to maintaining the level of rural population in the small farm counties was that the farmer or members of his family would find off-farm employment. That will now be specifically penalised by this provision proposed by the Minister.  Whatever about the broader provision, unjustifiable as it is because of its failure to recognise the fact that the farmer is already paying local rates, this proposal particularly seems to me to represent a major injustice to the small farming community.  I hope the Minister will have a second look at this provision with a view to abandoning it altogether because I cannot find any justification for it on any basis whatsoever.</P>
    <P>To a great extent this year's budget is overshadowed by the proposals in the Government's White Paper on Capital Taxation.  Compared with the far-reaching fundamental implications of that particular package of proposals and their effect on the ownership of property, business, investment, employment and on our whole approach to economic affairs, what is contained in the budget itself is of comparatively minor significance.  It is the duty of Deputies on this side of the House to direct the attention of the public in this debate to these proposals and in particular to their implications.  We must endeavour to secure a full understanding of precisely what is involved in the Government's proposals as outlined in this White Paper.  I am convinced that public relation to this White Paper has been much less vigorous than it would otherwise have been if the full implications of these proposals were realised.  The reaction of a considerable number of people has been passive either because they do not think they will be affected by them, or, alternatively, because in some vague way they feel they will find a way around them.  I believe that directly or indirectly these proposals will affect every single member of our community.  Anybody in the community who feels that they are just another <Col N="1786" /> series of taxation proposals which can be either evaded or avoided is in for a very rude awakening.  If there is one thing that can be said about these proposals it is that they are total and complete in their proposed application.</P>
    <P>We in this House must be very honest and forthcoming with people in regard to what is in store for them in this package.  This package will overnight transform this community into the most comprehensively and heavily taxed community in western Europe.  I challenge contradiction on that statement.  If the proposals as outlined in the White Paper are implemented then we will become, without any doubt, the most comprehensively taxed community not only in western Europe but, indeed, in the developed world.  I do not believe that that is the sort of situation into which we should be committing ourselves at this time.  It is economic madness.  We have an urgent, continuing need for economic development and for a country like ours whose primary requirement is economic development to transform itself into a highly-taxed community of this sort is a negation of common sense.  Socialism may be a suitable system for dividing up a rich, prosperous national cake if the cake exists, but it will not provide or enlarge it.  I make no apology for stating here that only a private enterprise system can provide us with the economic development which we need to procure any worthwhile social progress.</P>
    <P>The Minister for Finance recognised that fundamental truth when he said recently that he would do all he could to encourage men of enterprise who are prepared to take risks and to make intelligent use of capital and that they add to the community's store of assets.  I do not believe that statement can be reconciled with the approach in the White Paper.  I challenge the Minister, when he comes to reply to this debate, to try to reconcile that statement of his, which I believe to be correct, with the whole philosophy and approach outlined in the White Paper.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="1787" /> I believe from my own observations and from what I hear that a very significant outflow of capital has been triggered off by the very publication of the White Paper.  The implications of the publication of those proposals is twofold.  First of all, it generates an outflow of capital from this country. We are not in a position to measure the extent of that outflow at this time. If one is to believe even one-half of what one hears that outflow is of considerable significance.  Perhaps more important however than the outflow of capital is the generation of a climate which will discourage the inflow of investment.</P>
    <P>We need industrial development in this country.  I know there is general agreement on that.  To a large extent, because of our historic situation, that industrial development can only come through the encouragement of external investment, particularly external investment of a sophisticated, technological kind.  We in Fianna Fáil want an equitable tax system.  We want that equitable tax system as a basis for social justice.  As we said recently in a statement we have always sought to preserve a balance between the redistribution which is required in the interests of social justice on the one hand and the need to encourage economic development on the other.  That is the real problem which confronts the administrator in this country today and the real problem which has confronted him for many decades.</P>
    <P>We want to ensure economic development and at the same time to ensure, to the greatest extent possible, that social justice will prevail between the different sections of the community. The important and delicate task of the economic administration of this country is to try to preserve a reasonable balance between these two demands.  Over the years we in Fianna Fáil succeeded in doing that.  It was recognised internationally that we had succeeded in creating here the sort of economic, social complex in which these two conflicting demands were reasonably reconciled and because we were able to do that we were able to <Col N="1788" /> attract here the sort of development that we wanted.</P>
    <P>We had so successfully created the type of climate necessary that we were able to pick and choose between types of development.  I genuinely believe that the Minister's proposals in regard to capital taxation will shatter that climate irretrievably.  That climate was built up painfully and assiduously over many years.  I believe it was successful in assuring international investors that the circumstances and climate in this country made it suitable as a place in which to invest.  I feel that this aspect has not been adverted to by this Government in bringing forward these proposals.</P>
    <P>Yesterday the Parliamentary Secretary to the Taoiseach attacked me, I understand, for stating that the proposals will mean the end of private property.  He suggested that I would have to backtrack on that statement. I have no intention of backtracking on it.  I want to reaffirm emphatically that it is so.  Ultimately, if these proposals go through in their entirely as outlined in the White Paper, it will mean the abolition of ownership of private property in this country.  If there is a taxation mechanism which is designed to annex 2½ per cent of the property of every member of the community every year surely it is a simple mathematical calculation to project that after 40 years the entire property of each individual member of the community will have been appropriated.</P>
    <P>I want also to point out that the process will in fact in the event be a great deal more accelerated.  It is specifically stated in the White Paper that there will be no upper limit on the proportion of a taxpayer's income which can be taken by the combined taxes in any one year.  It is quite clear from that, that in order to pay particularly the wealth tax, the taxpayer will have no alternative but to sell off year by year portion after portion of his property to meet the tax burden imposed upon him.</P>
    <P>It will not be simply a matter of selling off each year the amount of property necessary to pay the tax imposed, because inflation will ensure <Col N="1789" /> that almost every sale, if not every sale, will attract capital gains, so that the very proceeds of the sale which the taxpayer will make in order to pay the wealth tax will themselves be subject to capital gains and will be taken from the taxpayer to the extent of up to 35 per cent.  So the taxpayer, the owner of property, will be forced into an ever-decreasing vicious circle.  The simple mathematics of the situation are that, at least in a 40-year period, and more likely than not in a much shorter period, the total property of a taxpayer will be annexed by the Revenue authorities.</P>
    <P>There is one particular provision in this proposal which I regard as especially pernicious.  It is the simple stark statement that a compulsory acquisition will be regarded as a sale for the purposes of the capital gains tax.  There are and there will be differing opinions legitimately and sincerely held by different people as to the appropriateness of a capital gains tax in our circumstances.  There will also be different opinions equally sincerely and legitimately held by different people as to the level at which a capital gains tax should be imposed, if it is to be imposed.</P>
    <P>It seems to me, however, morally indefensible, where property is compulsorily acquired from an individual citizen, that compulsory acquisition should result in his having to pay capital gains on the proceeds.  Whatever about paying capital gains on the proceeds of a transaction voluntarily entered into by an individual, it seems to me to be utterly wrong to apply capital gains in the case of a transfer of property over which an individual private citizen has no control whatsoever and into which he is forced by the operation of some compulsory acquisition machinery.</P>
    <P>Yesterday the Parliamentary Secretary referred to the legislation which I introduced in this House to reform the law governing the disposition of property on death.  He said that I brought that piece of legislation into the House without having read it.  If that is the sort of accuracy which we can expect from the Parliamentary Secretary I would be very apprehensive <Col N="1790" /> for his academic reputation.  I doubt that there is anything else I ever attempted to do in public life to which I gave more thought than that piece of legislation.  I studied every aspect of it.  I personally researched the systems in operation in other countries.  I consulted, among others, Glanville Williams, the renowned authority in this area.  I spoke to him personally.  I familiarised myself with every aspect of that piece of legislation and I published it with a full knowledge of every single implication and every single thing involved in it.</P>
    <P>For the Parliamentary Secretary at this stage to come in and say I brought that piece of legislation into the House carelessly and without having read it is a travesty, and I hope he will have the decency to withdraw.  That piece of legislation in no way interfered with the right to the ownership of private property.  It dealt with the manner in which property should be dealt with on the death of the individual concerned.</P>
    <P>I believe this White Paper is a document which was thrown together hurriedly to beat a deadline.  I feel that the Government did not carefully and thoroughly consider its implications.  The sensible thing for them to do is to take it away and throw it back to whatever doctrinaire egghead produced it in the first instance and come forward with a completely different set of proposals. I would urge the Government in this area to resist the temptation to curry favour on the basis of a soak-the-rich campaign.  Any such popularity is totally ephemeral.</P>
    <P>What we are concerned with here and should be concerned with is long-term sound economic development and not with temporary political expediency. The fundamental economic interests of this country require that this set of proposals should be taken away and thoroughly re-examined by the more sensible members of the Government.</P>
    <P>The Government have at last brought forward their proposals for the taxation of mining.  I personally awaited the publication of these proposals <Col N="1791" /> with very great interest because it was I, as Minister for Finance, who brought in the original proposals which exempted profits from mining from income tax for a 20-year period.  I was interested to read in the Minister's speech the grudging statement, referring to the 20-year tax-free period, &ldquo;whatever the reasons underlying the introduction...&rdquo; It seems to me that with those words he acknowledges the fact that there may have been justification at that time for introducing that provision.</P>
    <P>I do not want to go over the ground in that regard.  I will just say that I think the introduction of that 20-year period at that time was justified as seems to me to be implied in what the Minister said in his statement.</P>
    <Speaker pid="RichieRyan" hpid="Minister for Finance (Mr. R. Ryan) Richie Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Finance (Mr. R. Ryan)</NameTxt>
      <P>I did call them prodigal incentives.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="CharlesJHaughey" hpid="Mr. Haughey Mr. Haughey">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Haughey</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister is inclined occasionally to use an exaggerated phrase and I would not take any great exception to that description.  But I do think they succeeded in their objective.  I think it is perfectly legitimate for the Government to re-examine the situation at this stage.  What intrigues me is that in the piece of legislation which the Government are now bringing forward I find all the proposals, solemnly set out, with which I was confronted at that time.  I am quite prepared to speculate that the result of this piece of legislation ultimately will be almost exactly the same as mine and that when all the allowances set out in the Bill are given effect to no income tax will in effect be payable by most mining concerns.  At the time it seemed to me that, rather than invoke this whole complicated apparatus of income tax allowances, the simpler thing to do was to exempt mining, as such, from the income tax code and to procure the proportion to which the community was entitled by means of royalties.  I still have not found any satisfactory rebuttal of my approach.  The royalty mechanism enables the Minister for Finance, the <Col N="1792" /> Minister for Industry and Commerce, or whichever Minister is concerned, to procure for the community in a definite, clear cut, way whatever proportion of the minerals he thinks should accrue to them.</P>
      <P>I do not intend to quarrel with the introduction of this measure.  I have the feeling it was brought in in response to political pressure rather than in response to the realities of the situation, but I do not think it is worth having a great political battle about.  In effect, I think, when these provisions come into operation, they are going to have the same effect in the ultimate as my provision of a 20 year tax-free period.  In that connection I cannot but think of the different approach of the Minister's predecessor, Deputy Sweetman, in regard to matters of this sort.  He made a very important and significant contribution to the development of our taxation system in the manner in which that taxation system can be used to promote economic development. I should not like this opportunity to pass&mdash;when this provision is coming in without paying that tribute to his memory and to the contribution he made.  He was a doughty opponent, a hard-hitting one, but he was a very great realist.  To my mind, he knew what economic development was all about.  The present Minister for Finance might give more attention to the approach and philosophy of Deputy Sweetman than to some of the rigid doctrinaire socialists who seem to have his ear these days.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>There is another aspect of the Government's activities in this field of taxation to which I should like to draw the attention of the House.  This is something quite separate from the social and economic implications of the measures involved.  It is something of serious import and I hope the Minister will advert to it at some stage during this debate.  I am concerned about the capacity of the Revenue administrative machine to cope with this very considerable mass of complicated taxation measures which the Government are proposing to feed into it.  In this country since the State was established we have <Col N="1793" /> been particularly fortunate in the manner in which the community has been served by its Revenue Commissioners. Of course in the nature of things it is inevitable that the Revenue Commissioners, as a body, will attract to themselves a great deal of the unpopularity and dislike which belongs properly to the taxation measures themselves and indeed to us parliamentarians who enact those measures. They are, however, a very mature institution and have always resisted the natural temptation to resent the unpopularity mistakenly directed at them as distinct from us parliamentarians to whom it properly belongs.</P>
    <P>The result of that was that the Oireachtas could always be assured that whatever measures we wished to introduce, whether on the taxation or customs side, these would be effectively, impartially and efficiently implemented by the Revenue Commissioners. I should like to be assured that that situation will continue.  I want the Minister to tell us if he is completely satisfied that this very competent, capable machine will be able to cope with this very considerable volume of new taxation measures he is bringing forward.  This is a vital question.  It is something which is of great significance to the fundamental administration of the State.  As I have indicated, I have great faith in the Revenue Commissioners, as a body, and in their competence, efficiency and organisation.  Over the last decade they have demonstrated an admirable capacity to adjust to and cope with new taxation.  In particular they have coped with the introduction of PAYE, turnover tax and value-added tax.  To their credit, let me say, they were amongst the first major institutions in this country to go over to computerisation. But I would be concerned that the Minister should not overload that machine with all the proposals he is bringing forward.  I hope he will deal with that aspect of the matter in his reply to this debate.  Perhaps he would be able to tell us whether he has consulted seriously with the Revenue Commissioners as to their capacity in this regard and whether they have expressed any doubt whatsoever about <Col N="1794" /> their capacity to take on this entire new load of tax legislation.</P>
    <P>Government spokesmen have made a great deal of play about the increase in social welfare benefits provided for in this budget.  I do not think the debate on the budget should be an occasion on which we should parade our social consciences in front of one another.  The Fianna Fáil Government of which I was a member&mdash;indeed, all Fianna Fáil Governments in my time&mdash;were alert to the need for improvements in the social welfare structure and, in so far as the resources were available to them, they made whatever improvements they could.</P>
    <P>I should like to look for a moment now at what the Minister has achieved this year by way of improvements in social welfare benefits. By and large, he has improved these benefits by 18 per cent but, on his own admission, prices will rise during the year by at least 14 per cent so that the improvement does not seem to me to provide in any way for a significant improvement in the standard of living of the recipients of these benefits.  At 18 per cent the Minister is just about keeping pace with inflationary pressures and, on this occasion, he had to do at least that.</P>
    <P>I should like to look now, and this is the real test, at what the Minister has been able to do in the fields of social welfare benefits and income tax reliefs in relation to the resources at his disposal.  Improvements in social welfare benefits is a well-established factor in modern budgetary policy.  Indeed, the policy can be regarded as a bi-partisan one.  No Minister for Finance today would attempt to come in here with a budget in which at the very least social welfare benefits were not improved to the extent necessary to keep pace with the cost of living.  It is, however, relevant this year to relate what the Minister has done in regard to benefits and income tax reliefs to the resources at his disposal.  For simplicity sake, I would regard these resources as being, on the one hand, the buoyancy of revenue and, on the <Col N="1795" /> other hand, the budget deficit for which he has planned.</P>
    <P>I calculate that buoyancy of revenue at £93 million.  With no changes in taxation buoyancy over the 12-month period would have brought in an extra £126 million.  Relating that to the 9-month period for which the Minister is budgeting the figure is £93 million.  In addition to that the Minister has budgeted for a deficit of £76 million.  Between these two sources, buoyancy of revenue and the budget deficit for which he has planned, the Minister had at his disposal £169 million extra this year with which to cater for social welfare benefits and income tax reliefs.  Out of that £169 million he has only dispensed £34 million&mdash;£17 million for increased social welfare benefits and £17 million for income tax reliefs and public service pensions and, looking at what the Minister has done in the light of these two sets of figures, his achievement is not all that significant.</P>
    <P>It is perfectly legitimate to look at what he has done in these two areas in relation to what was at his disposal from revenue buoyancy and his budget deficit.  Both of these can be regarded as windfalls.  He does not have to put on one extra penny in taxation to procure either of them.  Revenue buoyancy happens automatically and the budget deficit planned for involves no taxation whatsoever because the money in question is borrowed. Taking then the figure of £169 million and the actual cost of the benefits provided, it seems to me that the Minister could have done five times better than he has actually done.  Out of the total of £169 million at his disposal he has given out a mere £34 million and that is the way in which his achievement in this regard should be measured.</P>
    <P>I congratulate the Minister on some of the things he has introduced in the Social Welfare area.  Social assistance for wives of long-term prisoners is highly commendable; so is his scheme of assistance for unmarried women. This is very welcome indeed.  The Minister deserves to be congratulated <Col N="1796" /> on these very meritorious social advances.</P>
    <P>I want to correct now an inadvertent misquotation.  I welcome particularly the Minister's intention to provide £100,000 for pilot schemes into the investigation of poverty.  This is very necessary.  In this modern community of ours it is important that we should try to ascertain exactly where poverty really exists so that we can frame out social welfare and other policies directly towards eradicating or alleviating that poverty.  The Minister's proposal is very commendable.  I hope it will be successful in identifying for him and for all of us the directions in which our policies should be channelled in the future.  In so far as there was a quotation in one newspaper which seemed to indicate that I was critical of this proposal, I want now to correct that impression.  I welcome it and I believe it can be very useful. Indeed I hope the Minister will later give a more detailed indication of what precisely he has in mind in this regard.</P>
    <P>I do not know if the Minister, and his advisers, have given sufficient attention to the desirability of deficit budgeting this year.  The figure concerned is of staggering proportions, £76 million in the nine-month period. Because of the combination of circumstances the budget deficit which the Minister planned for last year was very considerably reduced and it came out at £10 million.  That, however, is still £10 million to be added to our national debt, the public debt, and it is of some significance that in this year's figures the amount needed to finance that national debt is up by more than £30 million.</P>
    <P>I am not at all averse to deficit budgeting when the economic situation demands it but in any reasonable approach to our financial administration one must be somewhat concerned at the fact that we have been incurring budget deficits for some years now and that we intend for this year to go for a budget deficit to the extent of £76 million or £66 million depending on what period one takes.  It is all very well to dismiss that particular figure as a mere budget deficit and to <Col N="1797" /> look upon it as good economic planning and the sort of thing that is dictated by the economic circumstances of the time but we must realise that it goes on to the national debt and, ultimately, has to be recouped out of current taxation at some stage.</P>
    <P>I suspect that the Minister is hoping, as happened last year, that the £76 million deficit will not come out at anything like that figure and that because of, perhaps, further inflation or other developments, it will be very considerably reduced.  We all hope that will be so but we must face up to it that at the moment the likelihood, the probability, is that on top of the deficit of £10 million last year we are going to add another £66 or £76 million this year.  We must be conscious of the implications of that on the long-term national debt financial provisions.</P>
    <P>I do not know whether it would have been wiser for the Minister on this occasion to attempt to reduce that deficit either by increased taxation or by a reduction in his expenditure estimates.  I presume he has taken all the various factors into account in deciding to plan for a deficit of this size.  We should be very conscious, however, of the fact that we must not come to accept budgets which are, as a matter of course, going to finish up with a deficit which has to be borrowed.</P>
    <P>I know that the Minister in his outline of his budget strategy has indicated that in his view the increase in prices with which the economy would have to contend was serious enough without his adding to them by increases in taxation and, therefore, he went for a budget deficit rather than attempting to balance the budget by the necessary taxes.  I suppose that at this stage we have no option but to accept that fundamental decision by the Minister in his approach to the budget this year but it is as well on this side of the House that we should indicate our apprehension about the Minister continuing with deficit budgeting of this sort.</P>
    <P>To sum up, to my mind this budget does not make any attempt to face up to the very real formidable economic problems with which the country is <Col N="1798" /> confronted today nor is there contained anywhere in the budget any specific proposals designed to promote economic development in industry or in agriculture.  There is not one specific measure in all the budgetary proposals to which he Minister can point and say that that particular proposal will encourage investment, employment or economic development. I believe in his approach to the matter of social welfare benefits and income tax reliefs the Minister has not been anything like as generous as the resources at his disposal in the circumstances of this year could have enabled him to be.</P>
    <P>I do not think that any objective assessment of what he has done in relation to what was required and the resources at his disposal could regard his efforts as satisfactory.  On the whole I commend the Minister for what he has done in regard to income tax reliefs and social welfare benefits but I suggest that in the circumstances of today, and with the inflationary pressures which are crowding in upon us, they are not as satisfactory or as adequate as they might have been.  On the whole, the budget does not meet the requirements of the economic and social situation of today.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MylesStaunton" hpid="Mr. Staunton Mr. Staunton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Staunton</NameTxt>
      <P>I rise to support this budget and I am pleased to be in the position of speaking immediately after Deputy Haughey because, having been here to listen to him, I shall be able to make a few general comments regarding his remarks. Deputy Haughey spoke well and in a low key.  This was entirely in contrast with the strident approach of spokesmen in the Opposition who used such unacceptable terminology as &ldquo;fraudulent&rdquo; to describe the budget.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Having said that, I shall address myself to the budget and to our economy.  In saying that we should be concerned with having an equitable tax system as a basis for social justice, Deputy Haughey is merely reiterating the remarks and comments of members of the National Coalition Government because we would suggest that what we are about is the development of an equitable tax system as the basis for social justice.  There is the necessity within our country for social justice.  Our people, as a whole, <Col N="1799" /> support the view that there must be social justice but, perhaps, the major area of disagreement at present relates to the measures by which we shall pursue this objective.  Much of the debate regarding our economy and regarding the mining legislation which the Government propose to introduce has revolved around these factors and the opponents of the measures which the Government propose to introduce have been attempting to tell us that the implementation of these new policies would spell economic disaster for the country.  In other words, many of these opponents of ours would admit the necessity for reform and for social justice but would suggest that the measures we are adopting, while of short-term benefit, would, in the long-term result in the ruination of the economy.</P>
    <P>Taking into account the fact that we need these improvements in social welfare and in the social area in general, I would address myself to the tax system, to the economics of the situation, to the position of this country in the economic world and I would argue that the development of the policies of the Government in this area would not in any sense lead to a reduction in the economic development of our country.</P>
    <P>Deputy Lynch referred to what he termed the present outflow of funds from this country.  Similar references were made by other Opposition Deputies but from the information available to us it would seem that there are no grounds on which to base a statement to the effect that the balance is on capital flowing from this country.  On the contrary, there have been suggestions recently, even since the introduction of the White Paper on capital taxation and since the initiatives taken last year by the Government, that the balance has been to this country rather than from it. This is entirely in contrast with the suggestions made by the economic spokesmen of the Opposition and by certain financial journalists.  I am sure that the Minister for Finance, together with his advisers in the Central <Col N="1800" /> Bank, are keeping the situation under review because, obviously, it would be undesirable that there should be a trend such as that suggested by Deputy Lynch.  In a relative sense, if we are comparing the Irish economy, we must compare it with other economies; we must compare it internationally.  In Britain today there is an estate duty tax to which Irish funds invested will be subject.  We find that the Government there are implementing tougher taxation measures than we have been implementing here so that, relatively, our position has not in any sense been eroded.  To bring that point up-to-date and, again, arguing entirely from the economic standpoint, if one were to listen entirely to the remarks of the Opposition spokesmen, the budget would seem to be spelling economic disaster yet in the financial pages of <i>The Irish Times</i> of yesterday we read that the budget is likely to aid share values. This is the evidence to which I am pointing to show that the economic situation is healthy.  The financial journalist who wrote the article I am referring to goes on to say that the proposed deficit should boost growth by more than 4 per cent while no specific tax impost has been put on companies.  He states further that the general increase in purchasing power which can be anticipated both as a result of the budget and of the national wage agreement should help retailers of non-durable goods.  Therefore, it would appear that this budget is acceptable to financial interests.</P>
    <P>To indicate further the degree to which that journalist was prophetic, I would refer to the financial press pages of two of our national newspapers this morning.  In one there is a headline which states that the market is better after the budget and the article goes on to state that the Irish stock market yesterday showed an improvement.  In another national newspaper this morning we read a statement which tells us that the market responded favourably to the budget and with broad gain and it goes on to state that the upsurge of business continued to have a steady effect on the market yesterday after a <Col N="1801" /> milder budget than was anticipated. The article goes on to say that equities throughout the list showed good advances. In other words, the budget has been accepted broadly so far as economic and financial interests are concerned. When the chips are down we must judge not from the use of such terminology as &ldquo;fraudulent&rdquo; but from the volume of the investment of funds and the movement of funds on the stock exchange.  In a sense the present position is analagous with the position that prevailed after the Government announced the introduction of measures relating to the mining industry. For a few days after that announcement we had the same strident noises and the same comments, mostly from vested interests, as we are having now.  We had suggestions that the bottom would fall out of the mining industry.  Yet although there was a temporary falling off in mining share values, we are now back on an even keel so that the economic indicators are there to suggest that what the Government did was acceptable ultimately to the interests involved.  In terms of the degree to which the nation will benefit from mining profits the Government's action was acceptable generally to the country.</P>
    <P>The budget is orthodox and in addition to being adventurous it is prudent.  It is interesting to note that it was produced after the two months of the greatest crisis to befall the western world since World War II.</P>
    <P>The energy crisis of last autumn had a catastrophic affect in Japan, North America and all of Western Europe. That was followed by a series of major crises in Britain, politically and economically, economically to the degree that the working week was cut to three days.  Traditionally our economy has been dependent to an extraordinary degree on the British economy.  However the prudence, the adventurous spirit and the stability of the budget of this week are a tremendous achievement in this age of rampant global inflation, especially taking into account the particular difficulties of our neighbouring island.</P>
    <P>I would hope that the eventual deficit will follow the pattern of last <Col N="1802" /> year's budget.  Last year the Minister had a nominal current deficit of £39 million which resulted in an actual deficit of only £10 million, a quarter of the budgeted nominal current deficit.  I would hope the bouyancy in the economy and the spending which will be generated by the initiatives of this week will also result in a comparable actual deficit.</P>
    <P>There is a background for this deficit budget in that the National Economic and Social Council suggested that 1974 would not warrant the application of restrictive monetary and fiscal policies to dampen development.  They suggested that curbing gross domestic output could raise rather than lower unit costs.  There is a point there that if one were unduly conservative in approaching this budget in present economic circumstances the result might be to increase rather than to lower costs.</P>
    <P>In addition, the recent OECD Report gives <i>carte blanche</i> to the Minister to act as he has done.  They state that 1973 was a particularly successful year here as a result of an expansionist budgetary stance and a rapid growth in output.  As well, they expressed the belief that it is necessary that there should be policy action to &ldquo;stimulate demand and output&rdquo;. They say this would seem desirable and add:</P>
    <P>Nor should an increased deficit on current Government budget deficit be considered undesirable.</P>
    <P>They follow by saying that such a policy would represent a positive response to the threat to domestic output and employment as a result of the oil crisis.  In other words, there is established opinion to reinforce the action of the Minister for Finance in producing a budget which has been vindicated by the results on the Irish stock market in the past few days.</P>
    <P>I would tend to be more optimistic than some people regarding our international trade position.  Here we are extremely conscious of inflation and the extent to which the cost of living has risen in the past few years.  We have to bear in mind that this is a global phenomenon.  Those of us who have recently travelled in other countries are extremely conscious of the degree to which there has been rampant <Col N="1803" /> inflation in Western Europe. Recently a publication suggested that in the past 12 months the relative increase in wage rates here and in Britain was lower than in any of the other countries in the EEC.</P>
    <P>I shall revert briefly to the economic background of this budget and to some remarks made by Deputy Colley in his speech on Wednesday. Probably through lack of anything credible to state, he suggested there had been serious consequences in the industrial development field as a result of the announcement of a mining tax. He was challenged on that by the Minister for Industry and Commerce, who was then in the House, and he could not produce a reply.  I now challenge any Opposition spokesman to point to any area in which there have been problems in industrial development consequent on the announcement of the mining plans.  At the time Government spokesmen gave a solemn assurance that the tax incentives which had been given to manufacturing industry and which relieved them from tax on exports was a complete guarantee.  There is no question of the erosion of that position or of weakening on the commitment to such companies.</P>
    <P>In Fine Gael we have a problem to a degree in explaining ourselves at times to the electorate in the sense that Deputy Meaney in his speech suggested the Government had failed to bring in a socialist budget whereas other people, Deputy Power in particular, said that Fine Gael had been swamped by Labour in this respect. The Parliamentary Secretary to the Taoiseach referred to the contra position adopted by Senator Noel Browne and Mr. Maher of the IFA.  Therefore we are constantly in this middle ground, being accused by both sides of wearing two kinds of hat.</P>
    <P>There is no conflict whatever within the National Coalition Government in the formulation of policies.  The reason is simple.  Whereas some people among the electorate, and some of our journalist friends, tend to categorise our party as representing certain vested interests rather than a broad <Col N="1804" /> spectrum of opinion, the policies adopted over a number of years by Fine Gael were entirely progressive in approach and attitude and were most democratic.  The result is that there has been a dovetailing of minds and opinions; and I respectfully suggest that in the various areas where legislation has been produced Fine Gael policy has been merely seen to be consistent with the attitudes expressed in policy documents over a number of years.</P>
    <P>I shall continue by discussing the background to our economy and suggest that at the root of it is the fact that, as a relatively underdeveloped nation, in recent years we have had to develop policies that were completely liberal in approach to investment, particularly to foreign investment. There were liberals who would agree that our policies were more liberal than the attitudes adopted by any other country in Western Europe or North America.  Because of dependence on the development of industrial employment which was essential to our economy, because of the extremely large numbers of unemployed in our primary area of agriculture, we allowed a situation to develop in which we allowed total ownership to foreign interests.  We allowed 100 per cent relief from taxes on export sales, we allowed a completely free hand for management and on the boards of such companies we allowed complete repatriation of profits built up in this country by foreign facilities.  This is entirely in contrast with the position, for example in Japan, where the nation insists that foreign enterprise establishing interests in Japan can only be on a joint venture basis and in circumstances in which the Japanese insist on a measure of control by Japanese nationals or by the Japanese Government in such developments. Midway between the policy we have adopted and that of Japan are the attitudes of other European countries.</P>
    <P>What I am trying to say is that there has been enormous latitude where investment, production and management are concerned.  It is against this background that the policy statements and the White Paper on <Col N="1805" /> Capital Taxation have been produced. I would respectfully submit that what is happening is merely a tiny erosion of what had been a completely liberal attitude.  It seems to me that as we develop as a nation, as our economy improves, as we create conditions of fuller employment, it will be the duty of Government to review the extent to which we have control of our economy and from time to time, dependent on the degree to which the economy can stand it, it will be necessary for us to take a closer look at some of these situations.</P>
    <P>I shall refer briefly to the White Paper on Capital Taxation dealing with a capital gains tax and a wealth tax.  The point, to a degree, has been missed.  It was stressed by the Minister for Foreign Affairs last night when he pointed to two articles written by financial journalists shortly after the publication of the White Paper and in neither of those articles was there a line suggesting that the basis of it was the abolition of estate duty.  It is important, in considering the White Paper, to point out that the positive aspect of it is the commitment of this Government to the total abolition of estate duty from April of next year.  Consequent on that decision, which had been made as a result of intense pressure from many interests over the past few years, was the necessity to gather the funds from another source.  There were certain areas to which one could look.  Obviously, in the light of speculative gains in the country in more recent years, it was deemed generally that an equitable approach to the position would be to arrange for a capital gains tax.  I am certain in regard to that and in regard to the wealth tax that the Minister will listen with respect to the representations that will be made to him over the next two or three months before legislation is effected in that regard.</P>
    <P>I support the publication of the White Paper, I support the philosophy of the Government but I should like to see a reduction, to a degree, in the percentage of tax suggested in the capital gains area and one or two changes in the wealth tax <Col N="1806" /> area, if possible, where private houses of people are concerned.</P>
    <P>Deputy Colley posed the question as to what we are as a Government, whether we could decide if we are a private enterprise party or a socialist party.  I do not believe that the answer to that question is entirely simple.  I should like to throw it back at him and at the Opposition in general and to ask them to decide where they stand, whether they are private enterprise or socialist.  One can get too bound up in words and jargon and such phraseology.  Obviously in recent years we have had the enormous development of State involvement in the economy.  We have had the direct investment of the State through semi-State companies in the development of aspects of our economy.</P>
    <P>Because of the fact that the Industrial Revolution had by-passed us and that our level of economic development was much less than that of other countries in the developed world and because our resources as individuals were fairly thin, it was obviously necessary to support this type of development.  But if we have a country in which the State plays such a major role and has done under successive Governments, what do we call this type of State?  Do we call it a socialist State or do we call it a private enterprise system?  I think our policy is adequate in that there is a twin approach.  There are areas where the State should certainly become involved in the development of the economy, especially areas where private enterprise has not taken up the options.  Equally, I believe it to be terribly important to ensure that an economic climate prevails in which private enterprise is encouraged and I believe latitude should be given in this area.  I would suggest that this is the policy of the present Government in that there is considerable latitude and room for initiative.</P>
    <P>I shall refer briefly to what is obviously the controversial introduction of taxation where the farming community is concerned.  I should like to point to the background.  In 1960 the committee on income tax stated that they believed that the exemption <Col N="1807" /> of certain farmers from the tax net was inequitable.  In 1967 the committee on State expenditure on agriculture recommended that taxation should be introduced.  Taxation on farmers exists in eight other EEC countries.  We are speaking against a background in which there was a growth rate in the particular industry of 32 per cent in 1973.  I come from a farming constituency.  Having said that, I agree with the introduction of this taxation.  It is possible that I am prejudiced in the sense that the constituency I represent contains the most enormous number of small farmers and I know that their interests are not affected by this measure.  But from travelling through the country, in the east and in the south, and looking at the general picture of our economy it would seem to me that where very large farms are concerned, in this case we are talking of merely 9,000 out of 170,000, and it is equitable to introduce a measure of taxation. I choose my words carefully.  I know the problems the agricultural industry has had in building itself up in the past few years but I know also that there has been considerable discontent in urban areas about what they believe to be a most inequitable situation where lower paid workers are paying their full share of tax through PAYE.  I know that throughout the country there has been a measure of discontent with the situation in which agricultural labourers, earning relatively small sums, have been paying their full rate of tax on their slim wages while those who employed them have had the benefits of an expanding economy both in terms of output, profits and capital appreciation.  I believe the country will accept this measure as being entirely just.</P>
    <P>Regarding the social welfare benefits, I support the initiatives of the Minister and I compliment the Government on the further rates of increase which at the very least are going to match the extent of inflation over the next 12 months.  I would like to refer briefly to the west in this regard because, coming from a constituency <Col N="1808" /> which has had the most extraordinary level of emigration and where, due to economic circumstances, we have many people living in our county who unfortunately, whilst most hard-working people with a solid background, are not in a position to earn incomes comparable with those earned by people in the large towns or in the rest of the country naturally I welcome the increase in social welfare benefits.  As far as this part of the country is concerned the economy depends on them. The fact that certain people are staying there is entirely because such benefits exist.  The net effect, if they were abolished in the morning, would be the denuding of much of this country.  Business also tends to benefit when increased social welfare benefits are given because the business people are entirely dependent on the money people have to spend.</P>
    <P>I should like to make a few general comments about the economic development of the west against this background. Social welfare benefits are acceptable at a high level and are very necessary in this area.  It is even more desirable that the Government should produce initiatives to implement policies which will reduce rather than increase the necessity for large scale social welfare activities.  It has been fashionable in some areas to suggest that people in the west do not want to work, that they are lazy and have the ambition to live on the dole.  This is completely fallacious.  A large number of people from Mayo go to work in Britain and the United States.  If you go to any of the building sites in Britain and ask them where the hardest working people come from they will tell you they come from the west of Ireland.  The same can be said of any of the people from the west who are working in the United States or in Dublin.  The spirit is there and they have the will to work.</P>
    <P>It is too scathing to suggest when due to particular circumstances some of the people from the west, stay at home on a 15-acre patch, that they should get busy as bees on such a patch.  Obviously, if one opts to stay at home in such circumstances one <Col N="1809" /> takes an easy way out.  I do not condemn them for doing that.  We want to see the development of policies which will result in the creation of industrial employment in the western towns, the development of our land resources to a greater degree, the division of our commonages to allow the land to be fertilised to a greater degree, so that we have the economic conditions prevailing in the western area which will not necessitate our people depending on social welfare benefits to the degree to which, unfortunately, they are at present dependent.</P>
    <P>I represent these people and that is all they seek.  It is an appalling statement to suggest that the people of the west have this dole mentality.  This statement does not bear any relevance to the facts.  There are major problems in the west at the moment.  Our entry into the EEC was hailed as a possible salvation of the country and particularly of the western area.  It was suggested that the commitment to the common agricultural policy and the development of a regional policy would help that area.  We have been members of the EEC for some time now and there is considerable disillusionment among the people because they find that the approach in the agricultural area is that of a substantial commitment to farms over a certain level.  Unfortunately, due to the farm size in many counties of the west many of these farmers will not have the opportunity to participate in the farm development programmes, the farm modernisation schemes and the schemes which require a minimum income level, so there is disillusionment there.</P>
    <P>When we go into the area of regional policy we find that such a policy has not emerged from the EEC. I hope, despite the conflict at present, the problems in Great Britain and France and the disagreement there is about this matter, that a regional policy will emerge.  I believe it is one of the pillars of the European Communities to arrange that those areas of the Community which are neglected and less developed than the more populated areas will be supported by subsidies which will come principally through this particular fund.  In this <Col N="1810" /> country the wealthy farmlands of the east and south have benefited greatly from EEC involvement through the common agricultural policy.  I hope when the EEC regional fund emerges the Government will ensure that the interests of the west of Ireland are looked at as far as the spending of this fund is concerned.</P>
    <P>It is on funds going into the infrastructures, the building up of roads, water and sewerage schemes, the development of our harbours and grants for industrial development that we will depend.  For a number of years many of us have been very dissatisfied with the policies relating to the development of the west.  Many of us believe, due to what we term the most centralised policy of any country in Europe, that in the remote parts of the country we have been entirely dependent on decision making in central Government Departments and semi-State agencies in Dublin.  We believe that fundamental to the problem of the west is the development of adequate structures, through the development of regional development boards consisting largely of people from the region, with funds voted annually by the Government to allow people to work within the province and planning what they see is of interest in the province.  They should be able to do this with a measure of independence.</P>
    <P>I would like to compliment the Minister for Finance on a speech which he made in Cork about two months ago when he stated that he was having examined the general question of organisations and structures that should exist if there is to be effective regional development. The 14-point plan produced by the National Coalition parties expressed commitment to the western areas.  I know from discussions with the Minister that the Government are very concerned about this matter and that a particular examination is being made of western areas where such regional development is concerned within the context of the Minister's Cork speech.  I hope certain structures will emerge in that area for which, when they emerge, <Col N="1811" /> the Government will be commended. We can go back over the last decade and see where enormous pressures were exerted on the then Government from vocational interests and from those of us who were politically opposed to the Government, and yet nothing happened.  I know from the prevailing attitude that good news will emerge in this area before too long.</P>
    <P>At an earlier stage I was dealing with aspects of the taxation policy&mdash; the incentives, the disincentives, the White Paper, the capital gains tax, estate duty taxation, the grants available for industrial development and taxation policy.  I want briefly to refer again to a matter I think I mentioned a year ago.  There has been discussion about the extent to which grants were available or income tax concessions were available for manufacturing industry set up in Ireland related to the profits on exports.  The present position is that grants are given to such industries all over the country with the exception of Dublin, and it is suggested that the fact that such grants are not given in Dublin is a disincentive to industrial development in Dublin.</P>
    <P>However I should like to point out that the other major incentive which was given to manufacturing industry is complete relief from taxation on exports of manufactured goods. While the benefit of grants is not available in Dublin, when we look at the tax concessions on export sales we find this applies to the entire country, including Dublin.  Multinational companies, in particular, are not very much concerned about finding funds.  Generally they can do this without too much difficulty.  The yardstick which they would largely employ to assess an investment is return on investment.  If we combine the grant concessions which exists in the rest of the country with the tax concession which exists there and make a comparison with the returns that may be obtained from investments in industrial development in Dublin city, we find the differential is merely marginal and not what it <Col N="1812" /> seems in the first instance.</P>
    <P>One of the reasons for this, and the public do not seem to be aware of this fact, is that we tend to read only about the grant picture and the extent to which we take big wallops of money and hand them out to individual companies.  Obviously if you read statistics in which you see that all of the money has been spread around the country and that nothing has been given to Dublin, you may get the picture that Dublin is not within the area of incentives.  The facts point to an entirely different position, because half of the entire manufacturing industry is in Dublin city.  As a Deputy coming from the west of the country I regard this as an undesirable situation.  Dublin has been expanding.  For many people in Dublin it has been expanding too rapidly.  There are many opportunities for employment in a vast range of services which are provided in offices, hotels, cafes and other business premises.  In addition to that, if we are to encourage, as we have been doing through this tax concession, industrial development in Dublin, I do not believe this to be in the national interest.</P>
    <P>I want to give a tiny illustration of return on investment which will point to this fact.  Take a simple facility in which there is a capital investment of £100,000.  Let us presuppose that in rural Ireland the grant level is 30 per cent.  This means that the net investment in rural Ireland in a particular industry is £70,000 whereas in Dublin the initial investment is £100,000, because no grant is available.  Let us assume that the profit before tax on the facility is £10,000.  The Dublin profit before tax is £10,000; that is also the net profit because there is no tax picture.  Therefore there is a return on investment in the facility in Dublin of 10 per cent, whereas in rural Ireland the same facility getting a 30 per cent grant would have a profit of £10,000 on £70,000, which would be a return on investment of 14 per cent.  The comparison on the return of investment basis is merely the difference between 10 per cent and 14 per cent, <Col N="1813" /> which narrows it somewhat and gives the reasons why there is still major industrial development taking place in the city.</P>
    <P>The gap is even narrower than that, because this nominal difference in return on investment between 10 per cent and 14 per cent in this test case is not even taking into account the natural disadvantages of industry established in the south-west, the west and the north-west, the natural disadvantages of being removed from the centre, from services and from facilities, the natural disadvantages in relation to the cost of transport of imported goods and export of finished products.</P>
    <P>If people want to establish industry in Dublin let them do so, but I do not think it should be done at the expense of State incentives.  Having said that, I do not believe for an instant that the Government should renege on the incentives granted to existing manufacturing industries.  Rather do I think that over the next year or two they should have a look at the position for future projections in order to arrange a more equitable distribution of industry throughout the country.</P>
    <P>I referred earlier to the necessity for the creation of certain development boards in western areas.  Recently in that regard the Minister for the Gaeltacht, Deputy Tom O'Donnell, has announced certain initiatives where Gaeltacht areas are concerned through Údarás na Gaeltachta. I commend the Minister for his initiative since his appointment as Minister for the Gaeltacht.  I believe he has given that part of the country an attention which it had not received for many years, because of his special interest and sole responsibility.  Under the previous Government the Gaeltacht was incorporated in the Department of Finance, which was probably the busiest Ministry of the State, and consequently it was neglected.  However I would draw this analogy: if it is necessary and desirable that there should be certain organisations and a certain approach in Gaeltacht areas for economic development, I would suggest that there is an equal necessity, as I pointed out earlier, for such <Col N="1814" /> an approach to those parts of our country which are underdeveloped but which are not in the Gaeltacht.</P>
    <P>I know of a case recently where a particular town in Mayo sought inclusion in the Gaeltacht.  We have reached an unacceptable stage when any town or village would seek inclusion in the Gaeltacht, not because they would claim their area is an Irish speaking area but because they believe they should be entitled to the grants, facilities, and State investment which are available to Gaeltacht areas.  If the policies that have been adopted over a number of years are producing this appalling attitude, where people must get in under the umbrella for economic purposes only, I believe a policy should emerge which will provide equal incentives and opportunities in underdeveloped areas.  I certainly support the viewpoint that there should be a separate policy for the Gaeltacht, especially in the area of culture, language and identity. But, as I say, there should be a similar approach to underprivileged areas regardless of whether or not they are Gaeltacht areas.</P>
    <P>I should like to refer briefly to the energy crisis and the consequences for Ireland.  Unfortunately statistics suggest to us that we are more dependent, in a relative sense, on oil than many of our partners in Europe. In industry, for example, we seem to be dependent to the extent of 68 per cent of our requirements on oil as an energy source, whereas the average in EEC countries is 35 per cent.  This poses the considerable problem we have at present.  Part of the reason for this is that we do not have the energy resources of other countries. It has been suggested by OECD that it will increase gross domestic product by between 3½ and 4 per cent which would be the largest in any of the countries for which OECD has responsibility.  Consequent on that I should like to see the Government vigorously pursuing the development of offshore oil activity in those areas where we have a responsibility and a function.  We have seen the developments in Norway and in Scotland.  We read of the extraordinary degree to <Col N="1815" /> which the development of offshore oil can contribute to the economies of Britain and Norway.  It seems that our country is so very dependent on resources and so underdeveloped compared with other countries that this offshore oil could provide for us an equal contribution and, in relative terms, a greatly increased contribution.</P>
    <P>I welcome the recent statement of the Minister for Industry and Commerce that he has this matter under active review at present and that he sees a future where there will be an amalgamation of private and public interests in such development and I shall listen with interest to his further comments in this area which I think we should exploit as rapidly as possible.</P>
    <P>Associated with the energy question, we had to some extent been given to understand that our peat resources were exhausted.  Yet, suddenly when the energy crisis blew up we found that Bord na Móna were in a position to announce a programme for the spending of £20 million on the development of such peat resources.  I welcome this announcement because it concerns a prime resource the net effect of the development of which will be the creation of employment and the reduction of our dependence on sources of imported energy such as oil.</P>
    <P>The only adverse comment I would like to make in regard to this statement is that it seemed to be concerned to a very large extent with bog development in the midlands.  I should like to see the board coming to my part of the country where we have substantial peat resources which I should like to have examined as a matter of urgency, particularly in North Mayo where there is a vast acreage available and where the labour force is there to help in doing the job and where there is an ESB generating station to absorb some of the peat which would be produced. There have been suggestions that the deposit is limited.  This is controversial and is generally not accepted by local interests.  I would welcome a thorough investigation of the position with a view to the development of the bog in Mayo.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="1816" /> To summarise, I support the budget: I believe it will continue our progress. I believe that deficit budgeting in present circumstances is justified, not necessarily to be repeated every year. This approach was vindicated last year and I think it will be vindicated to an even greater extent this year.  Any other policy adopted by the Minister might have led to stagnation in the present very difficult circumstances.  I congratulate the Minister.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JosephDowling" hpid="Mr. Dowling Mr. Dowling">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dowling</NameTxt>
      <P>I welcome any changes that would assist the needy sections of the community.  Social justice and an equitable tax system are ideals we all desire to see implemented. We are not against a change in the tax system provided it gives an equitable system.  Speakers on our side have clearly indicated their views in regard to the improvements introduced by the budget and the changes in the tax system.  The changes that have taken place in the social field are probably best summed up in the words of a leading article in <i>The Irish Press</i> of April 4th which referred to the Minister for Finance as being like a log-hopper on the St. Lawrence.  It referred to the commitment to deliver the income tax rebate as being given small changes in very bulky packets.  It went on to analyse the problems and the promises in connection with the budget. While we agree with the social improvements and advances that have taken place, it must be remembered that we are living in an enlightened world of ever-changing conditions and circumstances of which we must keep abreast.  Some of the credit the Government have endeavoured to take should be analysed in depth.  We know that the EEC have set standards to which this country must conform and some of the improvements tend to go in that direction but all the improvements indicated in the budget do not go far enough. That may be said by Oppositions at all times and, indeed, by members of the Government parties.  In our view they have fallen far short of what the Minister could have done for the weaker sections of the community.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Throughout the budget speech the Minister gave no indication of any economic programme which the Government <Col N="1817" /> will pursue.  He has not stated their long term aims; he has not indicated the growth rate to be expected in any detail nor the employment progress that might be achieved. These are important factors on which the public and the workers need Government guidance.  To my mind this budget fits the terms used in the leading article in <i>The Irish Press</i> of Wednesday last.</P>
    <P>It was interesting to hear the Parliamentary Secretary to the Minister for Social Welfare speak this morning and I should like to comment at some length on his statements. This budget could be described as a streaker's budget.  The Minister has fiddled the till in relation to the Central Bank from where he has, under extraordinary circumstances, obtained £20 million.  I should like an explanation as to which Departmental funds were attacked.  When the Coalition were in power previously they drew money from the widows' and orphans' fund.  Where is the money coming from on this occasion? Is it from the Department of Finance, the Department of Local Government, the Department of Social Welfare or has the Post Office been raided?  These factors need to be explained fully and without ambiguity. The public demand to know and I trust the Minister will indicate in his reply where the funds are coming from.  Will services be affected?  Is this a gambler's budget?  Is the Minister taking a gamble and putting sections of the community at risk?  If this is so, we demand a clear and comprehensive statement from him.</P>
    <P>The Minister is budgeting for a deficit in the region of £76 million plus buoyancy of revenue of £93 million which gives him £169 million. I want to deal in some detail with the pittance which he has given to the weaker sections of the community who are the real victims of this budget. In his budget speech 16th May, 1973 the Minister said that that specific financial resolution related only to ensuring that children's allowance would go to the more necessitous people in the community and that it could be refunded by persons whose <Col N="1818" /> nett incomes exceeded £2,500.  The Minister's attitude on this occasion is inconsistent with his attitude last year. What brought about this change of heart?  Was it because of the distress caused to many people in that income bracket?  Was it because Members of the Oireachtas complained because of the problems in industry where distress funds had to be set up to assist workers whose pay packets were attacked on the direction of the Department of Finance?  Those workers received very little to bring home when the direction was issued to clawback children's allowances. What changed the Minister's mind? He and the Government were very strong on the issue that necessitous persons should get the bulk of social welfare benefits.  I am in favour of that.  But on this occasion the Minister has not gone far enough.</P>
    <P>This means that a man with £2,500 and five children will get an extra £108 a year.  The lower-paid workers will receive an extra £18 a year.  The Parliamentary Secretary indicated that there were several thousand children who lived below the poverty line and the miserable assistance given to the weaker sections of the community amounted to only £18 a year.  This works out at 7½p per week and if one is lucky enough to have twins, 15p per week.</P>
    <Speaker pid="FergusOBrien" hpid="Mr. O'Brien Mr. O'Brien">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Brien</NameTxt>
      <P>What about triplets?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JosephDowling" hpid="Mr. Dowling Mr. Dowling">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dowling</NameTxt>
      <P>The Tánaiste, the Minister for Finance and the Parliamentary Secretary have spoken about the weaker sections of the community and the vast numbers who are living below the poverty line but they are still only getting an increase of 7½p in children's allowances.  This budget was meant to help these people.  It does not do so.  When the time comes, people will speak loud and clear.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The Labour Party issued a statement saying that 640,000 people lived below the poverty line.  Notwithstanding the fact that the Minister had a considerable amount of money at his disposal, it was decided that there would be an extra 30p per month for each child.  There is no <Col N="1819" /> need for me to go into further detail about children's allowances.  This is one of the benefits of which&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    <Speaker pid="FergusOBrien" hpid="Mr. O'Brien Mr. O'Brien">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Brien</NameTxt>
      <P>We can be proud.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JosephDowling" hpid="Mr. Dowling Mr. Dowling">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dowling</NameTxt>
      <P>&mdash;&mdash;that has been paraded in this House from time to time as being the means of assisting the lower-paid workers.  This 30p per month was the sole contribution to the 640,000 who are in great need and distress.  This 7½p per week is meant to ensure that these people will have the necessities of life.  The Minister has failed miserably to provide for the weaker sections of the community.</P>
      <P>It was stated in the Press and elsewhere that this is a rich man's budget because it tends to assist the rich man as against the poor man.  Further thought will have to be given to the subject.  Every community has its weaker sections.  In every community there is poverty of some kind.  If that poverty extends to the degree indicated by the Parliamentary Secretary, surely we are under an obligation to ensure that those people get the bulk of advantage from the budget.  What did they get?  A mere 30p per month. The lowest type of advance&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FergusOBrien" hpid="Mr. O'Brien Mr. O'Brien">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Brien</NameTxt>
      <P>What did Fianna Fáil do for the children's allowance?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JosephDowling" hpid="Mr. Dowling Mr. Dowling">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dowling</NameTxt>
      <P>We brought it in and increased it time and time again. Deputy O'Brien should go back to see the advances made in social welfare by Fianna Fáil over the years and how many schemes were introduced. The children's allowances scheme was introduced and improved upon on many occasions even before we joined the EEC.  If it was necessary to give greater assistance to the weaker sections of the community now it would have been mainly to demand taxes to ensure that those on the poverty line would be assisted by the Government.  This would have been a responsible action.  The Government have failed miserably by leaving this section the same as they were before the budget in spite of the fact that <Col N="1820" /> they have statistics which were mentioned this morning.</P>
      <P>It is unfortunate that Deputy O'Brien was not here to listen to the Parliamentary Secretary, Deputy Cluskey, and did not hear the Tánaiste on television.  He should have listened to the other speakers in Fine Gael and Labour who have spoken about this particular section of the community.  They will suffer viciously under this budget.  They will pay more than the 30p per month for each child.</P>
      <P>If Deputy O'Brien believes that 7½p per child per week is sufficient to assist a child in the category mentioned he is indicating that he too is a 7½p socialist.  The Government did not measure up to their responsibilities. We must highlight the needs of the weaker sections so that they will know that the Government have failed miserably to alleviate their situation. They have worsened the conditions of the lower-paid worker, the unemployed and the man with a large family.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GarrettFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. G. Fitzgerald Mr. G. Fitzgerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. G. Fitzgerald</NameTxt>
      <P>What about the mortgage payers of Dublin and Cork?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JosephDowling" hpid="Mr. Dowling Mr. Dowling">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dowling</NameTxt>
      <P>This budget operates viciously against the poor.  The people at the level of Deputy O'Brien will be satisfied with the budget&mdash;&mdash;</P>
      <P>
        <i>(Interruptions.)</i>
      </P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DenisJones" hpid="An Leas-Cheann Comhairle Denis Francis Jones">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Cheann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>Deputy Dowling, without interruption.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JosephDowling" hpid="Mr. Dowling Mr. Dowling">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dowling</NameTxt>
      <P>Deputy Cluskey indicated that there were 215,000 children living on the poverty line or below it.  The sole contribution to alleviate their distress was the 30p per child per month.  No responsible Deputy on the other side of the House&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMoore" hpid="Mr. Moore Mr. Moore">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Moore</NameTxt>
      <P>Are there any?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JosephDowling" hpid="Mr. Dowling Mr. Dowling">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dowling</NameTxt>
      <P>&mdash;&mdash;will agree that any assistance has been given to them. They are even worse off than they were.  I hope that the Members on the benches opposite will become aware of the necessity of providing assistance for the weaker sections of the community.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="1821" /> Last year there was a clawback in children's allowances from the people earning more than £2,500.  The inconsistency is that this time these people are getting £109 as against £19.  On the last occasion I felt the clawback was unfair and that the application of the means test in the manner in which it was applied was unfair.  Despite the fact that these people are now getting a considerable sum of money a new clawback will come into force.  Prior to the Presidential election advertising was used to explain away the clawback. There is a new clawback which affects the lower-paid workers more viciously than the children's allowance clawback did.  It relates to the advantages which the Minister outlined in his budget speech.  In the yellow-page document issued by the Minister in relation to the various aspects he explains that he has set aside £100,000 for investigation into poverty.</P>
    <Speaker pid="FergusOBrien" hpid="Mr. O'Brien Mr. O'Brien">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Brien</NameTxt>
      <P>What about the £100,000 lost by Fianna Fáil?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMoore" hpid="Mr. Moore Mr. Moore">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Moore</NameTxt>
      <P>You were not here at the time.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JosephDowling" hpid="Mr. Dowling Mr. Dowling">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dowling</NameTxt>
      <P>I want to deal with another aspect of the much publicised income tax assistance which the Minister claims is given to the workers. Perhaps Deputy O'Brien will be able to explain why the weakest section of the community did not get assistance. We hear much talk about large families.  On this occasion the large family has little to be enthusiastic about.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FergusOBrien" hpid="Mr. O'Brien Mr. O'Brien">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Brien</NameTxt>
      <P>The widow has.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JosephDowling" hpid="Mr. Dowling Mr. Dowling">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dowling</NameTxt>
      <P>Let us examine the document which the Minister had prepared.  The figures show how the budget affects the workers of this city. There was much talk about the national pay agreement.  If that agreement was to be ratified now what would happen?  I am positive it would be rejected, and rightly so.  I was in favour of a national pay agreement because I believe that is what is in the best interests of the community. Promises were given to Congress and to the workers that substantial tax reliefs would be forthcoming.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="1822" /> This document indicates the old system, the new system, the earnings and the percentages.  A person with £900 last year will earn more this year.  The tax saving is £27.60 for a single person earning £900 per year. If we turn to page 11 we see that the tax saving of a married person earning £900 a year is £28.60.  That is £1 more for a married couple than for a single person.  Is that social justice?  Is that the type of social justice the Labour Party stand for? Is that the type of social justice the Fine Gael Party stand for?  That is the justice which is indicated clearly in this Yellow Paper issued by the Minister for Finance and all the interruptions in the world from Deputy O'Brien will not erase the facts set out here. The difference in the tax saving for a single man earning £900 a year and a married man earning £900 a year is one miserable pound.</P>
    <Speaker pid="FergusOBrien" hpid="Mr. O'Brien Mr. O'Brien">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Brien</NameTxt>
      <P>What is miserable about £1?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JosephDowling" hpid="Mr. Dowling Mr. Dowling">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dowling</NameTxt>
      <P>Deputy O'Brien agrees that this is adequate for a husband and wife.  He agrees that a difference of £1 is sufficient.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FergusOBrien" hpid="Mr. O'Brien Mr. O'Brien">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Brien</NameTxt>
      <P>What did you give them.  You voted against the widows getting the pension.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMoore" hpid="Mr. Moore Mr. Moore">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Moore</NameTxt>
      <P>That is on the record now and we will quote you.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DenisJones" hpid="An Leas-Cheann Comhairle Denis Francis Jones">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Cheann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>Deputy Dowling without interruption.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JosephDowling" hpid="Mr. Dowling Mr. Dowling">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dowling</NameTxt>
      <P>We have now established the mind of the Fine Gael back benchers&mdash;a difference of £1 is sufficient in the tax saving between a married man and a single man.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMoore" hpid="Mr. Moore Mr. Moore">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Moore</NameTxt>
      <P>According to Deputy O'Brien.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DenisJones" hpid="An Leas-Cheann Comhairle Denis Francis Jones">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Cheann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>Deputy Dowling should address the Chair.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JosephDowling" hpid="Mr. Dowling Mr. Dowling">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dowling</NameTxt>
      <P>It is very difficult when there are interruptions from&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMoore" hpid="Mr. Moore Mr. Moore">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Moore</NameTxt>
      <P>Callous Deputies.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FergusOBrien" hpid="Mr. O'Brien Mr. O'Brien">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Brien</NameTxt>
      <P>You are very concerned. <Col N="1823" /> You voted against pensions for widows.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMoore" hpid="Mr. Moore Mr. Moore">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Moore</NameTxt>
      <P>According to Deputy O'Brien £1 is good enough.  He is sorry he interrupted.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JosephDowling" hpid="Mr. Dowling Mr. Dowling">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dowling</NameTxt>
      <P>Deputies can read the Official Report to become familiar with what has been termed a social budget.  A married person without children with £2,000 a year has a tax saving of £40.10, and the tax saving for a man with three children earning £2,000 is £41.40, a difference of £1.30.  That is what they call socialism. Now we have a clear indication of the type of Government we have who consider that that is adequate. A person with no children earning £2,100 per year has a tax saving of £49.10 and a person with three children earning £2,100 per year has a tax saving of £50.40, a difference of £1.30 only.  Again we have a clear indication of their type of socialist approach.</P>
      <P>It has been said that the Labour Party are dragging Fine Gael to the left.  This document speaks for itself. I do not think the Labour Party will want to be associated with this budget when we have dealt with a few more items in depth and in detail.  A man with no children earning £2,200 a year has a tax saving of £58.10 and a man with three children earning £2,200 a year has a tax saving of £59.40, a difference of £1.30.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesCTunney" hpid="Mr. Tunney Mr. Tunney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Tunney</NameTxt>
      <P>It is a contraceptive budget.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JosephDowling" hpid="Mr. Dowling Mr. Dowling">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dowling</NameTxt>
      <P>This is not the type of budget I should like to be associated with in any way whatsoever, because it tends to victimise the worker in this manner.  The Minister and other speakers talked about the wonderful manipulation of the income tax system which has brought about such glorious reliefs, but we now find how they equate money to families.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>A man with no children earning £2,300 a year has a tax saving of £67.10 and a man with three children earning the same salary has a tax <Col N="1824" /> saving of £68.40, again a difference of £1.30.  Surely the married man with three children is entitled to a far greater concession than £1.30. The difference in tax saving between a man with no children earning £2,500 a year and the man with three children earning the same figure is £4.80.  At the £2,500 bracket they get a little more, notwithstanding the fact that the weaker sections of the community need more.  As we go up the scale we find that this budget is loaded in favour of the man with the greater salary.</P>
    <P>I already dealt with how the children's allowances operated last year and the miserable concession given to the weaker section of the community. Now in this income tax reform we have a system which operates against the lower paid worker. A man with three children earning £3,000 a year gets a tax saving of £179.40 so he is substantially better off notwithstanding the fact that he gets £109 for children's allowances this year as against the £19 for the lower paid worker.  We now see how this budget is weighted.</P>
    <P>When we go to the £5,000 bracket we find socialism in the extreme. The difference in the tax saving between a man with no children earning £5,000 a year and the man with three children earning £5,000 a year is £106.90.  The difference in the tax saving between a man with no children earning £7,000 a year and the man with three children earning the same figure is £130.60.  If you are earning £7,000 a year and there is no clawback on your children's allowances, despite what the Minister said last year and despite the fact that he said the weaker section should get the advantage&mdash;and I believe they should&mdash;the difference in your tax saving is £130.60.  Does it cost a man with £7,000 a year more to keep his children than it costs the man who is living at subsistence level?</P>
    <P>The difference in the tax saving between a man with no children earning £9,000 a year and a man with three children earning £9,000 a year is £154.30.  The difference in the tax saving between a man with no children <Col N="1825" /> earning £10,000 a year and the man with three children earning £10,000 is £178.90.  This is the pushing to the left of the Fine Gael Party. I should not like to be associated with being pushed on that basis.  I should like the figures to be reversed.</P>
    <P>We have it clearly outlined in the Minister's brief here&mdash;that we have a situation loaded in favour of the higher paid worker, the man with £10,000 or £5,000 a year who is getting all the advantages and the person we really want to help is getting 7½p per week per child.  Of course if he has three children, he gets another £140.  This is supposed to take families off the poverty line, as indicated by Deputy Cluskey, the Parliamentary Secretary to the Minister for Social Welfare.  He is a man who should know.  He is the man who spoke about the wonderful social welfare assistance that had been given in this budget.  He did not give it any thought or go into it in any great detail.  It is quite obvious that somebody has presented this and he has accepted it.  I do not believe that any true socialist&mdash;if there is such a thing in this House&mdash;would stand for this type of treatment of the weaker sections of the community.  The lower-paid worker has been forgotten about completely and neglected in this budget.  So far as the lower-paid worker is concerned, this budget is a heap of rubbish.</P>
    <P>We can see too clearly outlined in this document a vicious attack on the weaker section of the community, the lower-paid worker and the lower-paid worker with a large family.  If we go into it in greater depth and detail we find that, as the family expands, the greater will be the assistance to the man with £10,000 or £5,000 a year or the man with £3,000 a year as against the man with £40 a week or less.  He is the victim on this occasion.  Not alone is he a victim in regard to children's allowances but it would have been far better had the Government offered nothing than offer 7½ per child per week.</P>
    <P>If we take the other side of the story&mdash;the clawback of the worker's increase, as I said a few moments ago, the position in relation to the national <Col N="1826" /> pay agreement was a very important one.  It is a matter with which I should like to deal in some depth here. Again it affects workers who earn from £16 to £20 a week.  Let us examine exactly how this Government have treated the workers despite the fact that they clearly indicated there would be substantial tax reductions to offset the situation occasioned by higher prices and the other factors affecting the workers of this State. We find, instead of the promises of the present Government that there would be granted substantial increases in the tax allowance system, a complete betrayal of Irish workers by the Labour and Fine Gael Parties.  This is something that will never be forgotten.</P>
    <P>I would say that if in another 12 months' time another national wage agreement is suggested, the Government will have to tell the workers beforehand what they are going to give them because nobody would take the word of the Minister for Finance, the Taoiseach, the Tánaiste or any other member of that Government in relation to concessions that might be available.  On this occasion I feel the workers were blackmailed into acceptance. I want to prove that this is so. A married man with £40 a week&mdash;in relation to the national pay agreement &mdash;during the first year of the agreement will get £176 under the first phase; £55 under the second; £30 on the escalator clause, a total of £261. Out of this extra £261 the Minister for Finance will clawback&mdash;and this was a phrase he used last year&mdash;£68 by way of income tax.  He has put his hand into the worker's pocket and taken, in the case of a married man with £40 a week, £68.  Therefore the wage agreement was nullified to a large extent by the action of the Minister for Finance, ably supported and abetted by the Labour Party on this occasion, by allowing him put his hand into the worker's pay packet and take out £68 to which the worker felt he was entitled and expected he would have to spend on himself and his family.</P>
    <P>If we take a single man on £20 a week&mdash;and he could not be regarded <Col N="1827" /> as a very highly paid individual; as a matter of fact, to offer a man £20 a week at this stage is an insult&mdash; in the first year of the agreement he would earn £159 extra, £104 under the first phase; £40 under the second and £15 on the escalator clause.  From this man, the Minister&mdash;ably supported and abetted by the Labour Party&mdash; will clawback £40.  Under the national pay agreement there is no way in which he can recoup the £40 or, in the case of the married man, the £68. The cost of living index is the basis on which additional moneys can be granted and on that basis only.  A married man earning £30 a week would earn during the first year of the agreement £207 extra.  Of course £30 is not a very high figure but the Minister will put his hand in that man's pay packet and clawback £54.  The workers of this country have been betrayed by the Minister for Finance, by the Taoiseach, by the Leader of the Labour Party&mdash;in fact by every single Member of the Fine Gael and Labour Parties.</P>
    <P>While we on this side of the House worked to ensure that the national wage agreement would be carried in the interests of this nation, I have second thoughts about believing anything the Minister would say or any promises given to workers in this country by any person on the Government benches.  They have broken their word completely about the substantial tax increases they were giving, while at the same time the Minister for Finance was devising a scheme whereby he could rob the worker of that to which he was rightly entitled under the national pay agreement. The Parliamentary Secretary to the Minister for Agriculture knows full well that when a man makes a claim for a wage increase it is on the basis of that which he requires to make up for the defects and deficiencies and for the increases that have taken place. He knows that to plunder a man's pay packet is completely wrong.  I hope some member of the Labour Party will stand up and tell the Minister for Finance that he has robbed these workers and broken his word to them.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="1828" /> I am appalled that the Irish Congress of Trade Unions did not come out in defence of the workers on this occasion.  Perhaps they have not examined in any great detail the various aspects of the budget affecting those workers.  If they did, they would see clearly that the pay packets have been plundered, that the workers have been misled and that they themselves have been misled grossly by the Government. How many members of that Government met the workers, the trade unionists and gave them solemn promises that there would be adequate provision in the budget to offset increases? I wonder where are the Deputies now who support this type of tactic and attitude&mdash;of the plundering of the worker's pay packet?  To my mind this is robbery with violence. Having given a solemn undertaking, they have broken their word and then robbed the worker.  What could be worse than that?  These are the facts of the situation.</P>
    <P>Again, that might not have been too bad if that were the end of the line, but we see now that a single person earning £2,000 per annum, with the reduction in income tax here, would require a reduction of £70 and not just £25 if he were to be restored to the position he was in in 1972 when Fianna Fáil were in office.  Not alone is he not brought back to that position, but the Minister has worsened his position and robbed his pay packet.</P>
    <P>We have been told that the Labour Party pushed Fine Gael to the left. They must have done some pushing and, if that is their contribution to socialism, we can see exactly where the country is heading and how the weaker sections will be affected.</P>
    <P>If we take our calculations a little further we find that the married man with £2,000 a year will get £38; to restore him to the position in which he was after the 1972 budget he should get a reduction of £87.  Right through there is a worsening of the position of the worker.  No wonder workers rebel against governments when they are treated in a savage manner like this. If we take the married man then with £2,000 a year and two children, he is <Col N="1829" /> getting £37 in tax reliefs; if he were to be reinstated to the position in which he was in 1972 he would need £114.  Right through there is this cutting down and we have this dreadful situation in which the weaker sections are being severely victimised and their pay packets plundered, and they are being insulted into the bargain.</P>
    <P>Let us examine this now from another direction.  This document relates to £1,500 or £1,700.  We all know that the situation this year is not what it was last year and, next year, there will be still further increases so these figures cannot be trusted except for an examination of the situation on a very narrow basis.  Let us take the position of a single man earning £20 a week last year.  He paid £168 tax.  This year, allowing for the increase, he will earn £1,199 and he will pay £182 tax. Would the Minister explain in what way is he giving this man a tax concession? How can an increase from £168 tax to £182 be regarded as a tax reduction?  One must, of course, take into consideration the pay increases that will be granted and equate one with the other to find out what the exact amount will be.  As I say, this budget is an insult to the workers, to those on low incomes and those with large families.</P>
    <P>Take the married man with £40 a week.  Last year he paid £448 tax. This year he will earn £2,341 and he will pay £481 tax.  Is this a tax reduction? The Minister talks about tax reductions but, when one examines the position in depth, one finds that not alone has the Minister plundered the pay packets of the workers but he is actually misleading them.  The married man with two children, earning £30 a week, or £1,560 a year, paid £128 tax; this year he will earn £1,767 and he will pay £147 tax.  There is no tax reduction here.  There is an increase. The Minister is clawing back £54.</P>
    <P>The term &ldquo;clawback&rdquo; was regarded as an objectionable one at one time. This budget is full of clawbacks.  I have shown that the alleged tax concessions are nothing but tax manipulations. Add this to the trail of broken promises and we can be certain that the workers will never again trust this <Col N="1830" /> Minister or this Government.  If the Labour Party have accepted this kind of social policy, and this is supposed to be extreme Labour Party social policy, then it is a poor lookout for the workers.</P>
    <P>I am glad the Minister is here. I indicated earlier the pathetic state of the lower paid worker.  I have listened with interest to statements made by members of the Labour Party who claimed there were a great many people on the poverty line and a great many children living below that line.  The Minister is giving the latter, in his generosity, with the assistance of the Labour Party 7½p per week per child and, if the family are lucky enough to have twins, they will get 15p.  That is the Minister's contribution to people living below the poverty line.  It would have been better had the Minister come in here and taxed some commodity, any commodity, and said he wanted to give the weaker sections of the community in such dire need&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    <Speaker pid="SeanTreacy" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Seán Treacy">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>I must remind the Deputy that it is not in order to indulge in repetition.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JosephDowling" hpid="Mr. Dowling Mr. Dowling">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dowling</NameTxt>
      <P>Unfortunately the Minister was not here.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanTreacy" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Seán Treacy">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>That is no justification for repetition.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JosephDowling" hpid="Mr. Dowling Mr. Dowling">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dowling</NameTxt>
      <P>Families are being victimised in this budget in many ways.  The Parliamentary Secretary to the Minister for Social Welfare last night shed crocodile tears about a particular section of which he was aware because he had not done something to twist the Minister's arm and ensure they would get assistance.  I am sure the Minister agrees that 7½p a week for each child will in no way compensate&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanTreacy" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Seán Treacy">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>The Deputy has already said that.  He must not repeat.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JosephDowling" hpid="Mr. Dowling Mr. Dowling">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dowling</NameTxt>
      <P>I will, every time I come in here.  In due course, when the Minister examines his conscience and his colleagues examine theirs, I hope they will take a look at the <Col N="1831" /> figures I have detailed here.  I have shown that the difference between a married man and a married man with three children is a tax saving of £140 or £130 in the case of a man earning £2,000 and £2,500 respectively.  The person who earns £10,000 per year gets a substantial increase of £178.</P>
      <P>We have a lot of ground to make up in relation to benefits and there are pressures from workers and enlightened trade unionists to bring us in line with the social advances that have taken place elsewhere.  If this budget is an indication of future Government activity then those people who had some confidence in the present Government will be feeling very depressed.  I am sure that the weaker sections of the community are also feeling depressed.  I wonder if this will set in train the feeling that the conditions which are applicable in the EEC will never be realised here.  It is not lip service we want; we want active service to ensure that what we say is done and that we will protect, to the best of our ability, those sections of the community who are deserving of protection.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>We have a long way to go to meet some of the requirements needed.  I accept that we have gone some of the way, assisted by the funds available to us by the EEC, and we have done this particularly in relation to social welfare benefits.  Listening to Deputies on the Government side one would think that it was not the contribution from the EEC that assisted the Government in increasing social welfare benefits last year.  The Minister has taken last year's social welfare benefits and this year's and combined them to make an average for the two years, but last year the Minister had available a substantial sum of money for social welfare benefits.  This did not arise from any action the Minister took but because of the decision made by the people to join the EEC.  The people who were crying loudest yesterday and today about the substantial increases in benefits are the very people who opposed our entry into the EEC.  If they had their way we <Col N="1832" /> would not have had the finances available to ensure that the social benefits were paid out last year.  We would be worse off if this had not been done.</P>
    <P>I hope that the confidence of many people which has been shattered in the past will not take a further shattering. We have already seen the shattering blow to this Government when they sought a national loan.  We know exactly how the people of the nation responded to the loan and the confidence they have in the National Coalition.</P>
    <P>I do not want to go into any detail about the assurances given to the people in the stockbroker and banker belt prior to the general election by the present Ministers for Foreign Affairs and Finance because this has been dealt with already in an issue of <i>Hibernia.</i> The lack of confidence of the same people was evident in the fact that the national loan was the greatest disaster that this country has ever witnessed.  The Minister is only too well aware of the lack of confidence the people have in him and his Government.</P>
    <P>This budget may be an effort to arrest the situation whereby the people with substantial finance come out best. It is clear that they have come out best on this occasion.  When we look at the situation in relation to social welfare we find in the OECD Report that EEC funds to the extent of £60 million were available while the Minister says this figure was £24½ million. Where did the other money go?  Why was more money not made available when the Minister had this substantial amount at his disposal?  The Minister could have assisted a section of the community which he ignored, something for which he will never be forgiven.</P>
    <P>The Minister, in the course of his statement, told the House that the consumer price index rose on average by 11.4 per cent in 1973 as compared with 8.6 per cent in 1972.  He also told us that there was a distinct improvement in the trend of food prices during the second half of the year.  That is a joke.  The OECD Report tells us that the retail food prices increased <Col N="1833" /> by 13.4 per cent.  The Minister indicated that there was a distinct improvement in the trend of food prices during the second half of the year.  I should like to refer to the National Prices Commission Report No. 26 of February, 1974.  I wonder if it was the Minister who published that report. This report tells us that bread, batch loaf, sliced and wrapped, white, any brand, 2 lb., cost in Dublin in February, 1973, 13p, while in February, 1974, it cost 12½p.  According to this report the price of bread went down. Bolands Harvest Brown, sliced and wrapped, in February, 1973, cost 7.5p and reduced to 7p in February, 1974. Hovis reduced from 8.5p in 1973 to 7p in 1974.  Cabbage, carrots, cooking apples, eating apples, onions, tomatoes, coffee, flour, tinned soups, castor sugar, Anadin tablets and cold cream were all down.  I can understand Anadin tablets being decreased because of the number of headaches the housewives of the city had.</P>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMoore" hpid="Mr. Moore Mr. Moore">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Moore</NameTxt>
      <P>They should be subsidised.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JosephDowling" hpid="Mr. Dowling Mr. Dowling">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dowling</NameTxt>
      <P>In February, 1973, they were 10p while in February, 1974, they were 9½p.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. Ryan Mr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>It shows that the demand was falling and they had to boost their sales by reducing the price.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JosephDowling" hpid="Mr. Dowling Mr. Dowling">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dowling</NameTxt>
      <P>They were probably able to reduce them at a lower cost because of the volume.  There must have been a substantial demand for Anadin to cure all those headaches. I am positive that the housewives of the city would not agree that the commodities I have indicated decreased in cost between February, 1973, to February, 1974.  Price rises during the past 12 months have been so great that apart from the hardship they have caused in the ordinary way they have wrecked families.  There has been much confusion in homes because of the cost of living especially where one spouse voted differently from the other in the general election.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I wonder who supplies the National Prices Commission with their information. I have asked a number of <Col N="1834" /> housewives if they would agree with the indications published in the NPC's document but not one could think of any commodity which had been reduced in price.  Some months ago I asked the Taoiseach for information on the number of items of foodstuffs that had been either reduced in price or had remained static.  I was informed by the Taoiseach's Parliamentary Secretary that the prices of neck mutton, of black-and-white film and of toothpaste had been reduced.  Can anyone imagine a housewife offering her husband two black-and-white films, a tube of toothpaste and a bit of neck mutton?  I wonder what any husband would have to say to that?  In this document published in February, 1974, we are told that a variety of items have been reduced in price.  This is not the case.  The price of every commodity has increased&mdash;I shall question the cost of Anadins.</P>
    <P>In his statement the Minister told us that the removal of VAT from foodstuffs was a major factor in the slowing down rate of the increase in meat and vegetable prices.  He tells us that the removal of VAT from foodstuffs as and from 3rd September last was part of the Government's social and economic policy.  Every housewife knows of the substantial increase that occurred on all foodstuffs if not on the date of the coming into effect of the removal of VAT, in the days and weeks preceding that date.  The Minister cannot fool the people by saying that the reduction in food prices resulted from the removal of VAT. No effort was made by the Government to stop the upward spiral in prices that took place prior to September 3rd.  Instead, they ensured by their inaction that pockets would be well padded before the operative date.  We should be influenced by the commonsense of the ordinary housewife. Therefore, I would advise the Minister to consult the housewife as to what is her opinion in relation to the effect of the removal of VAT from foodstuffs.</P>
    <P>The Government took no action to curb the increases in prices before September 3rd and any action they <Col N="1835" /> have taken since then has been ineffective despite the fact that prior to the general election we were told that every effort would be made to control prices.  We have seen how miserably they have failed in this regard.  In August the food index price was 244. In November it was 251 and it is continuing to rise.  Last night the Minister for Foreign Affairs indicated that substantial increases are to take place. He quoted a well-informed sources as forecasting an increase in the region of 14 per cent.  I should like to know a little more about these well-informed sources.</P>
    <P>On the occasion of the previous budget every commodity, other than foodstuffs, was increased in price.  It is clear now that the removal of VAT from foodstuffs was nothing more than an election gimmick and that the people were fooled by the Coalition spokesman.  Footwear, clothing, medical appliances and disabled persons' requisities were all increased in price as a result of the excessive rate of VAT that was applied to them.  The Minister now tries to compensate those families hit hardest by those increases by giving them an extra 7½p per week.  This is the type of social conscience that pervades the Government. Are we to take it that all the increases in prices and that the attacks on the pay packet are being offset by what we are told are wonderful contributions in children's allowances? It is very heartening for the housewife, no doubt, to know that in his statement the Minister said that the impact of imported prices on the cost of living will be even greater in 1974 than in 1973 because of the widespread repercussions of imported prices throughout the economy.  The situation was had enough in 1973. The Minister went on to tell us that the very big increases in incomes at home have been an additional factor in the fuelling of the fires of inflation during the past year.  Who got the big increases?  Certainly, the lower paid workers who have been trounced in this budget did not get them.  I am concerned for the weaker section of the community.  These people got no <Col N="1836" /> more than that to which they were entitled.  Is it the Minister's opinion that any increases they received were too great?  Is he referring to that section of the community which the Parliamentary Secretary to the Minister for Social Welfare said are living below the poverty line?</P>
    <P>The Minister will have to rethink this situation.  He will have to do something to bridge the gap between the lower paid workers and others in the economy.  He will have to do it in a substantial way and not by any gimmicks.  He will have to improve social welfare benefits in a real way for a start. He will have to ensure that the present wages of lower paid workers will be increased to a level that will provide at least a minimum standard of living for them.</P>
    <P>In his speech the Minister mentioned the period since 1969 and said that employee incomes have accounted for between one-third and one-half of the rise in consumer prices.  He did not tell us that in many cases the increases to workers were not adequate to meet the increase in consumer prices.</P>
    <Speaker pid="SeanTreacy" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Seán Treacy">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>The Deputy has gone over that ground already.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JosephDowling" hpid="Mr. Dowling Mr. Dowling">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dowling</NameTxt>
      <P>This is the first time I have dealt with consumer prices. The Minister has been attempting to blame the workers without saying that there are workers and their families who have not the necessaries of life.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanTreacy" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Seán Treacy">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>We have heard all that before.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JosephDowling" hpid="Mr. Dowling Mr. Dowling">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dowling</NameTxt>
      <P>You have heard it all before.  Yes, we heard it all during the election campaign and after the election campaign but nothing has been done about it.  The Minister said in his speech:</P>
      <P>Most economic commentators agree that the average rise in consumer prices this year will not be less than 14 per cent.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Is he now relying on commentators? He did not do so before the last general election.  That is no way to bring <Col N="1837" /> in a budget.  We should have had an authoritative assessment, an expert one, from the Minister so that he could indicate as clearly as possible what the increases will amount to. The figure of 14 per cent was given by the Minister to indicate the level which wage earners could expect in their claims.  One day we are told by the Government that economic commentators cannot be trusted and the next day they are quoted in the Financial Statement of the Minister for Finance.  The Minister for Industry and Commerce spoke here yesterday about a friendly Press and a hostile Press.  Were the commentators cited by the Minister for Finance from the friendly Press?  They must be very friendly if he can include them in his Financial Statement.  The Minister went on in his speech:</P>
    <P>Price rises of this order, whatever their source, pose grave economic and social problems for our community and the way in which we react to them is a clear test of our personal wisdom and of our sense of national responsibility.</P>
    <P>The Minister spoke about inflationary spirals.  I can assure him that the Opposition will support any responsible Government action to combat inflation and to achieve social and economic progress but we will not be satisfied with gimmicks or with being told what commentators think unless they are backed up by expert advice. Any responsible action by the Government to ensure price control will be fully supported by this side of the House.</P>
    <P>From the way the present Minister for Industry and Commerce used to speak when in Opposition about measures to control prices one would have thought that in his present position he would have ensured there would not be any price rises.  I agree he has had problems but we all know there is power there to control prices. If they were not sufficient he should have introduced further power.</P>
    <P>In his speech, the Minister for Finance went into great detail on the national pay agreement.  He referred to a period of industrial peace and <Col N="1838" /> the role to be played by workers. Notwithstanding the many promises given about closing the gap in so far as the lower paid workers are concerned, that gap has been steadily increasing.  I hope the Government will take immediate action to see that that gap is closed as quickly as possible.  We all know there is conflict in many ways and places within the Labour Party and in the trade union movement and these create problems.  The other day Deputy Colley, as quoted in the <i>Irish Independent</i> of 4th April, said:</P>
    <P>There were serious consequences in the industrial field flowing from the announcement of the Government on mining taxation and the Government was trying to cover up this.  During the long silence regarding the Government's intentions on mining, a large foreign corporation had made an offer for shares in Tara, substantially higher than the quoted prices of the shares.  There were many people in this country and outside it who wanted to know how such an offer could be made in the absence of precise knowledge of the Government's intentions regarding taxation and royalties from Tara Mines.</P>
    <P>Unless the Government showed clearly that it had no contact direct or indirect with that foreign corporation during the period in question, a very serious situation would arise and one that would call for a public sworn inquiry.</P>
    <P>I agree with what Deputy Colley stated.  This is a very serious situation and one which has disturbed the minds of many people.  Information of this type can only come from within the Government.  There may have been people who were advising the Government and advising Ministers who could carry information but, nevertheless, the Ministers themselves must bear responsibility.  There was certainly a leakage of information somewhere along the line.  I understand that discussions were taking place between interested parties and the Minister for Finance and the Minister for Foreign Affairs.  We want to know exactly how the leakage came <Col N="1839" /> about.  The Government will have to spell out in detail what led up to this situation.  This calls for an inquiry. It would be interesting to hear whether it came from a Minister or Ministers, because there were a number of Ministers involved, but the information leaked in some way and created a very serious situation.  The Government Information Service has been very active on many occasions in the past in repudiating statements and making statements.  It has been silent on this occasion.  I wonder what happened.  Were they instructed to be silent?  This is a major matter, of great importance nationally and internationally. One would have hoped for some explanation.  I should like to add my voice to that of Deputy Colley in calling for a public sworn inquiry.  We do not want to be fobbed off because this is a serious matter and the Government Information Service and the Ministers concerned have been silent.  We want to know who sold out, at what cost and how.  The only way this can be cleared up is by an inquiry in which people inside and outside this House can have a say and some of them want to have a say because there are other aspects that will arise from this problem that probably will affect other industries.</P>
    <P>I should like some clarification from the Minister in regard to the wife's allowance.  It is not very clear from his speech.  At what rate will this be taxed?  Will it be 26 per cent or 35 per cent or will it be added to the husband's income?  I have been asked to seek clarification on this.</P>
    <P>A speaker yesterday referred to the pay-related benefits scheme as a scheme introduced by the Coalition Government.  This is not so.  This is our scheme and was piloted through this House by Deputy Brennan.</P>
    <P>The Minister indicated that 60,000 people will be released from the tax net on Wednesday.  I wonder how many more will be in it on Monday? Many of the workers who have been released from the tax net will come back into it immediately the first stage of the national pay agreement <Col N="1840" /> has been paid.  The fact that 60,000 people will be out of the tax net was shown fairly effectively on television but the other side of the coin was not.</P>
    <P>I should like to make a few comments in relation to statements that have been made by the Minister and by other Members of the Government. In <i>The Irish Times</i> on the Monday prior to the budget the Minister for Finance was reported as saying that the Government inherited a sluggish economy.  This is not true.  Industrial output for the first quarter of the year was 13½ per cent.  In the second quarter it began to slide and in the last quarter it was away down.  The Minister can blame whatever factors he likes but it is quite clear that when this Government took office the economy was in a sound position. The facts show that the decline started when they took office and that we had this decline ever since.  Whatever social advances have been made are welcome but the Minister has failed miserably in relation to the vital problem of the lower paid workers, the people in distress, the people who need budgets.  It would be much more honourable for the Minister to have imposed taxation. The Tánaiste used this new word &ldquo;concern&rdquo; that we have heard from the Parliamentary Secretary to the Minister for Social Welfare.  There is no concern here for the section that requires attention, the lower paid workers.  I hope those people will get a better deal in the next budget than they got on this occasion.</P>
    <Speaker pid="BrendanToal" hpid="Mr. Toal Mr. Toal">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Toal</NameTxt>
      <P>I am a new Member of the Dáil and this is the first budget I have seen passing through the House.  To my mind, whether you are budgeting for a town, a county or a country the guideline of the blueprint should be fair play.  The hallmark of this budget is fair play.  This Government or any Government who have a genuine concern for the socially deprived and the disadvantaged in society must embark on a programme of care for the old and the poor.  That was enshrined in the preelection manifesto of the National <Col N="1841" /> Coalition.  Shortly after they went into office they reduced the qualifying age for the old age pension from 70 to 69. That was the first time in over 50 years in this State that was done. In this budget the age limit has been futher reduced.  The Government intend to go on reducing it until the qualifying age is 65.</P>
      <P>The old age pensioners, the widows, the orphans and the disabled are getting increases in this year's budget. Almost all our social welfare payments are now on a par with those in Northern Ireland.  Some of them are in excess of their payments.  As well as increasing the existing social welfare schemes, the Government have brought in some new schemes. One of the most important is the allowance given to the wife of an old age pensioner or some other dependant under 68 years of age who lives with him.  Instead of that person getting £6.15 he now gets £10.95.  There is a new scheme coming in under social assistance for single women aged 58 and over.  The payment in this scheme will be £6.35. This shows that the Government are genuinely concerned with the disadvantaged in our society.  Those social welfare payments are not a handout by the Government.  They belong to those people as their right and in the interests of fair play.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The Minister said that it is his policy in the interests of fair play to take firm action against tax avoiders and evaders and to ensure a more equitable tax system.  He has done that in the budget.  He has closed the loopholes which existed in relation to tax avoiders and evaders.  Who would not agree with that?  He has also helped those who pay their income tax in that he has increased the personal income tax allowances for them.  A single person formerly had an allowance of £299 but he will now have a new allowance of £500.  A married person who had an allowance of £494 will now have an allowance of £800. As a result of these allowances 60,000 people, the less well off members of society in this country, will be free from the income tax net.  That will mean more money in their pockets and more money to spend.  It will <Col N="1842" /> mean more business and a greater stimulus to growth in our economy.</P>
    <P>The Minister also stated that the economy is likely to grow by 3¾ per cent this year.  In order to give a further boost to the economy he said he will not increase taxation this year. The taxation system in this country, which is under review at the moment, crawled cumbersomely along when the Fianna Fáil Government were in power.  Everybody gave out about it. Most people complained about it but nothing was done.  The previous Government shied away from it.  They did nothing about it and it was left to this Government to face the music, to bring justice into the system and to bring equity to bear so that those best able to pay will carry the tax burden.</P>
    <P>A White Paper on capital taxation was brought out by the Minister for Finance.  We had some scare tactics from the people on the Opposition benches and people shouting emotive phrases about it.  The Minister said he wanted all interested parties to come along to him and discuss this White Paper and that his door was open to them.  He said it was only after full consultation that an equitable taxation system would be brought in.</P>
    <P>There were shouts from the Opposition about the taxation system but when it came to the poor law valuation in relation to farms and the Government decided to impose tax on farms of £100 poor law valuation or over, the Opposition speakers said that the farmers were on the road to ruin.  Those are the very people who not so long ago went around saying that something would have to be done and that taxation for farmers would have to come sooner or later.  However, they left the matter as it was and it was left to this Government to bring some justice into the taxation system.</P>
    <P>I do not believe that any farmer with £100 poor law valuation or over would object to paying income tax if he was making a decent profit.  It is only after due deductions are made that he will be taxed.  The farmers got a 32 per cent increase in the cost of living last year.  Towards the end of the year they had a hard time of <Col N="1843" /> it with bad weather, shortage of feeding and depressed prices but the recent negotiations by the Minister for Agriculture and Fisheries in Brussels ensure that farmers are on the road to recovery and back on the road to prosperity.  The tide has again turned in their favour.</P>
    <P>I look forward to the emergence of the EEC regional fund.  I hope it will be directed especially to the border counties as they need help badly. Dublin is bursting at the seams and should not need any help.  I would like to see tax-free incentives given to industry and also transport allowances to prevent Dublin being pushed further out into the country.  The border constituency which I represent needs industry badly.  I have received private assurances that compensation will be paid soon for the bomb damage inflicted on the unfortunate towns of Clones and Belturbet. That compensation could not come soon enough because the people in both those towns lost their homes.  It is a long time since the damage was done and those people have been waiting for compensation.</P>
    <P>I came into this House shortly before Christmas.  Most of the time before Christmas and in the present session up to the night before the budget was given over to the Constituencies Bill.  While I sat on these benches I looked at Deputies opposite lashing abuse across the floor of the House.  I do not believe in the politics of abuse.  I do not think the people of Monaghan sent me to this House to indulge in the politics of abuse.  The only brand of politics which the people of my constituency are interested in is the politics of performance.  This budget is the embodiment of that; this is the politics of performance.  I congratulate the Minister on it, and I wish him very well in the financial year ahead.</P>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMoore" hpid="Mr. Moore Mr. Moore">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Moore</NameTxt>
      <P>First of all, I want to make it quite clear that I have no intention of starting a knocking campaign on the budget.  That does not mean that I do not see weaknesses in it which I shall criticise, as is my duty. I could have gone through quite a lot <Col N="1844" /> of it, even perhaps with a congratulatory note on one or two points in it, but the Minister for Industry and Commerce, when he was speaking, struck a petulant note at the very idea that the Opposition should criticise what he considered to be a work of financial art.  One of his phrases was that if the Opposition could not rule the economy they would proceed to wreck it.  That is absolutely wild talk by the Minister. It does not do any credit to himself or any good to the country.  I am not suggesting that many people take heed of his remarks, but just in case there are a few people in the community who might be misled by him, let us just mention that the Minister is under great strain at the moment as long as he is in his present office, because he is a man who has to battle with rising prices all the time.</P>
      <P>I often said when Fianna Fáil were in Government that it was very difficult for any Irish Minister to control prices effectively, because we imported such a huge amount of our raw material that because we had such little control over external prices, we were bound to have this continual battle against rising prices.  Having said that, I have to point out that before Deputy Keating became a Minister he promised the people that the Coalition Government would effectively control prices.  If people feel betrayed on the price issue and if they become cynical, we must place the blame on the Government in general and on the Minister for Industry and Commerce in particular.</P>
      <P>Prices are rising all the time and eroding any benefits, whether they be social welfare benefits or wage increases paid to workers in a factory or office.  Therefore, we must see how far this budget goes as an instrument for the stabilisation of the economy and for the effective control of prices.  We must examine in detail the Government's whole history of the handling of prices, of the handling of the national pay agreements, and of the amount of revenue given from the Exchequer to recipients of social welfare or as relief to taxpayers.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The budget, in that respect, does not make a pretty picture.  I see three good things in the budget.  First, there <Col N="1845" /> is the general social welfare increases, even though they are not adequate to meet the erosion of incomes caused by rising prices.  Secondly, there is this payment to unmarried women over 58 years of age.  Because of our history and because, up to recent years, of our very low marriage rate, we have a very high percentage of unmarried women in the community.  I would like to pay a tribute to many of them who have sacrificed their lives and their careers to care for an aged relative or an invalid relative.  The State has not been particularly generous in recognising this service, but I am glad to note this innovation. Thirdly, there is a payment to the wives and families of long-term prisoners.  In recent years there has been a tendency to think we should enlarge the State's allocation of money to cover categories like unmarried mothers, to provide increased welfare benefits and so on.  There has been greater concern&mdash;the word used so often this morning by the Parliamentary Secretary, Deputy Cluskey. As our society progresses and as the economy becomes more buoyant, we can become more generous to the most needy sections of our community. Over the years we have greatly expanded our social welfare services. This is to the credit of successive Governments and to people who have shown growing awareness of the need to help the less well-off members of our society.</P>
    <P>There is one section of the community that we have neglected and taken for granted.  I refer to the wife and mother.  It may be pointed out that in our income tax code we do make certain allowances for the wife as a dependent relative.  The time has come now, when we see the family under attack from all sides, to assess, if that is possible, the worth of a mother and wife to our society. If this value can be assessed, the State should recognise that worth to our society and ensure that the mother and wife should be repaid with the utmost generosity for her contribution to society.</P>
    <P>If we follow the example of other societies and allow the family to be <Col N="1846" /> wrecked by the pressures which are on it at the moment, we shall reap the harvest of that neglect by producing or emulating the sick societies of our modern states.  Affluence, instead of being a benefit to the people, seems to destroy all idealism and brings out the most selfish aspects in a people.  This may well be because of the false standards society in all these developed countries has accepted.</P>
    <P>The Minister for Finance has, I am sure, done his best with the budget, but on the basic matter of the whole and long-term planning.  On this financing of a State, I would like to ask the Minister: are we carrying on a kind of Victorian practice in having a yearly budget which must be balanced to the last penny?  This year it is really for only nine months.  Therefore I would urge, as Deputy Haughey did this morning, that there should be benefits and a stop-go pattern in the economy.  This requires very brave long term planning.</P>
    <P>I think it was Sir Boyle Roche who said: &ldquo;Let posterity pay for it.  What did they ever do for us?&rdquo; I do not go all the way with that saying.  I suggest we must have a sane approach to the development and expansion of the economy for the benefit of the people striving earnestly to rear their families today and of the children who will succeed them.  A Government should be brave and accept that we have problems today and shall have more tomorrow but with proper planning we should ensure that we shall not just have an annual exercise of doling out to the neglect of such citizens as mothers and, indeed, fathers who are to be good citizens.</P>
    <P>occasion when the economic situation was quite good and when the Minister had quite a lot of money we could have a really expansionary budget. While the budget has done some good in the three sectors I have mentioned and, perhaps, in others, I think it will bring a tale of woe towards the end of this year.  The pattern set for future budgets is made no easier by the document we are now discussing.</P>
    <P>Lest I forget, I noticed that Deputy Toal in his maiden speech mentioned that the Minister had promised that <Col N="1847" /> he would pay for the bomb damage in Clones out of State funds.  I welcome this and I hope the Minister will do the same for Dublin which suffered so much damage.  In fact I do not think the victims have yet been compensated.</P>
    <P>In laying the foundation for any budget we should have expert planing and be honest in our approach. This is where I take the Government to task in their handling of the recent national pay agreement.  The first attempt at agreement was rejected by all the workers involved.  At the time it was suggested that the Government would give some indication of what income tax relief they proposed to give in the present budget.  This may well have influenced a sufficient number of workers to vote for the national pay agreement and avoid industrial chaos which might have followed rejection.  The good sense of the workers and the employers prevailed and after the initial set-back and rejection of the first attempt, they came together again and hammered out an agreement.  On the first occasion the Government said they could not indicate what income tax relief would be given because this would mean giving away budget secrets.  The workers seemed to see sense in that at the time; they thought the Government should not be asked to commit themselves months before the budget as to what relief they would give. Then a strange thing happened.  After the failure of the first attempt at a national pay agreement there was consultation between the Congress of Trade Unions and the Government&mdash; a very laudable attempt to smooth out difficulties.  We then had a statement from the Taoiseach that certain income tax relief would be given in the budget.</P>
    <P>I was one of those who voted for the national pay agreement.  I am always in favour in principle of a national pay agreement, if not of the actual content, because I feel that unless we have a national agreement the lower-paid workers and the weaker section of the community would suffer in the free-for-all which would follow <Col N="1848" /> rejection of a proposed agreement. I could well see that key workers would be able to wield tremendous power on their own behalf and that thousands of semi-skilled and unskilled workers would have to take their places at the very end of the queue and would, therefore, lose.  In common, I suppose, with most members I believe that some day we shall have to examine how we can permanently help the lower-paid workers because it is human nature that the higher-paid workers will always strive to maintain the differential between themselves and the lower-paid workers.  I suppose they cannot be blamed for this but it will happen in any case.</P>
    <P>If you give the lower-paid workers an increase the higher-paid workers will claim that they must maintain the differential and must get a corresponding increase.  I suggest that the Minister might consider that lower-paid workers&mdash;I do not know what figure would be appropriate for this category but this could be worked out between the unions and the Government&mdash;should not have to pay for social welfare stamps?  They would at least save that amount weekly. Higher-paid workers would not be put at a disadvantage because they are paying in any case.  This would help the lower-paid groups considerably. I welcome the national pay agreement because it gives some protection to lower-paid workers but the Minister in the coming year might well consider this problem and, perhaps, in his plan to probe poverty&mdash; that is a very good idea&mdash;and establish what real poverty is he might well find that the lower-paid worker with four, five or six children is a man who requires help.</P>
    <P>The definition of poverty will depend on the area in which you are defining it.  For instance, in a wealthy nation like the US you might find the general level of poverty would be a level of comparative wealth somewhere in the third world.  In Ireland any politician who does his work will know where the pockets of poverty are in his own constituency.  Those representing Dublin city will be pretty well aware of what is happening in housing <Col N="1849" /> estates, old or new, local authority or private.  In the south-east area my own party organisation recently carried out a survey during the fuel crisis to see how many old people were short of fuel.  The result was astounding.  Strangely, they were not all poor people.  I recall one case of an elderly couple.  The man had a pension from his firm and also enjoyed a State pension and was by no means poor but they had no fuel in the house at the time when the coal merchants could not deliver it.  That was a case where they had the money but there was no fuel available.  That old couple had to sit in a very cold house in February.</P>
    <P>When the Parliamentary Secretary asks for suggestions to deal with poverty we will be delighted to give him examples of the poverty which exists.  Has any society ever abolished poverty?  It has been the bane of politicians and humanitarians since the beginning of time.  We never seem to be able to ensure that every family has a proper house, sufficient food and clothing.  We may talk about a standard of living but we should talk about the quality of living. I take the Government spokesmen to task for their patronising attitudes to old age pensioners and social welfare recipients.  It has been said that here is a benevolent Government distributing largesse, as if it came from their own party funds. They are doing great things for the aged and the handicapped.</P>
    <P>The social thinking behind the budget seems to be that the Government have effected certain changes in income tax and even the financing of the total indebtedness of the nation, and now they are going to distribute the benefits.  We must then listen to the cries of gratitude from the widows or old age pensioners because &ldquo;Big Brother&rdquo; gave them a pittance of an increase in their pensions.  They should go down on their knees and thank the benevolent State, which spent almost £1,000 million on running the State, because they are getting an increase of £1.50 a week or 7p a day.  We should train these people to stand up and be proud citizens of the State.  We are <Col N="1850" /> treating them as if they should be delighted that the State, in its generosity, has decided to give them an increase.  With respect to the Minister, I suggest that if he is presenting the budget next year he should try to get away from this patronising attitude.  When he comes in here with his brief, the backbenchers should sit in awe and hope that he will do something original.  The new payments to women over 58, the long-term prisoners' family allowances and the probe into poverty are original.</P>
    <P>Pensioners should not have to thank the State for what is being done for them.  These people are over 68 years of age and have worked all their lives, have created wealth and made others very wealthy.  The wealthy do not need to wait for the Minister's generosity in increasing their pensions. They live in affluent areas and could not care less whether pension increases are given.  I am not suggesting that they are unconcerned about the poorer pensioners because many are. I am talking about the poorer old age pensioners who, in the autumn of their lives, are given this increase.</P>
    <P>If the national economy had been better managed they could have been given more.  That is an argument which cannot be refuted and the accusation can be made against any Government.  In our economic and social planning, pensioners should come first on our list.  If this is done our society will not be a replica of some other modern States.  We should examine the ills of our society and bring original thinking to bear on the matter.  If we do that I will not feel like squirming as I did the other day when the Minister's colleagues stood and applauded the increases in the budget.  From the remarks they shouted across at Fianna Fáil one would think that the Government which were spending almost £1,000 million on running the State had created a new social charter to help the weaker sections of our people. From the applause from the Government benches one would think that a new Messiah had arrived on the financial scene with the horn of plenty from which he would dispense largesse and never again would these <Col N="1851" /> people be in want.  Of course they will be in want.  With the world in which we live today and the increases which are being passed by the Dáil, if I were an economist I could probably work out how much of an increase has been eroded by the increase in the price of commodities bought by those people.</P>
    <P>The Minister had at his disposal £93 million from revenue buoyancy and an overdraft of £76 million and this gave him £169 million.  Yet, the total distribution for social welfare was £34 million.  This was a glorious chance for the Minister to create a social welfare code of which we could be proud.</P>
    <P>I am not one of those people who say that our social welfare payments should be on a par with those paid in the Six-County area.  A person is worthy of an increase whether or not we have a united country.  This increase should be given as a matter of social justice and not for political advantage.  Any politician who believes that politics is a noble science must reach the stage where he says &ldquo;Even if this move costs me votes, I will do it&rdquo;.  It is not an easy thing for a politician to do and I am not saying that I would be brave enough to do it.  If politicians generally wish to keep their self-respect a stage must be reached when unpopular decisions must be taken.  Occasionally they must do something which they believe should be done even though they may not gain personally or politically from doing it.</P>
    <P>The Parliamentary Secretary to the Minister for Social Welfare said last night that he felt proud of what the Government had done for the social welfare recipients.  One cannot blame him for that.  He stressed that there was an idea of concern behind the budget.  I do not disbelieve him but I challenge him on that and on the degree of concern.  It would be wrong of me to suggest that I have more concern or feel more deeply than the Minister for Finance or the Parliamentary Secretary.  I have no right to claim that.  I am not an economist but I must ask why when £169 million was <Col N="1852" /> available such small amounts were given to social welfare beneficiaries. Perhaps some economist can explain this to me.  To my untutored mind, where a Minister has £93 million from revenue buoyancy and £76 million from budget overdraft, more should have been given to these people.  Not every Minister for Finance would be in such a favourable position of having the money at his disposal.</P>
    <P>The demands on the Minister's money are great.  The Government have increased this year the money for housing.  That is satisfactory.  We are trying to build 25,000 dwellings this year in the country.  I believe this can be done because of the achievements of the Fianna Fáil Government in regard to housing.  It will not be an easy task for the present Government but it is one that can be done and must be done, despite the setbacks following the three-day week in Britain which slowed up the housing drive because we could not obtain certain materials.  Most of our housing materials are now made here.  I see no reason why we should not exceed the target of 25,000 dwellings.  Any help which we can give towards achieving that target will be forthcoming.</P>
    <P>Our population is increasing.  Emigration is practically non-existent.  We must budget for a growing population which will demand higher standards of living.  Housing is very important in this context.  It is a costly item but it is the best social investment we can make.  We must invest in the efforts of our craftsmen.  Our architects and our surveyors must effect a great push forward in the housing drive, so that some day in this city we will be able to say that at last substandard housing is gone.  Those of us who remember Dublin in the 1930s will remember the frightful housing of that time. There was dreadful poverty.  We have striven to provide proper housing, to build up our economy and to ensure that our people are given a high standard of living.  Steps were taken by successive Fianna Fáil Governments to develop and expand our economy. We thought about the social improvements needed by our people.  We felt <Col N="1853" /> that the national wealth should be distributed on as wide a base as possible and that the weakest member of our community should have our first consideration.</P>
    <P>In my time we have seen a great revolution in housing conditions in the city.  One dare not become complacent now, although most of the substandard dwellings have gone.  Dublin, which at one time had the worst housing in Europe, is now reaching the stage where we can say that we have the best housing standards in Europe.  We realise however the suffering of many young couples who cannot get proper houses and must live with their in-laws. The houses they live in were never designed for two families. Human nature being what it is, this often results in great unhappiness for both families.  The old couple, having reared their children, are looking forward to some rest and comfort; but they feel they must take in a son or daughter who cannot get accommodation. There are young couples trying to obtain mortgages at a high rate of interest.  They must try to pay off the mortgage while rearing a family.  In these circumstances it is mockery to suggest to them that they should be good citizens.</P>
    <P>I realise that only living communities have housing problems.  Living cities will always have housing problems.  A dying city has no housing problem because the people are leaving it.  In the 1950s we did not have a great housing problem.  In some cases Dublin Corporation found it difficult to let their dwellings, particularly those in the outer suburbs.  That was because emigration was bleeding the nation. The demand for housing fell off and for the first time in many years the population of Dublin dropped.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JohnMKelly" hpid="Mr. Kelly Mr. Kelly">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Kelly</NameTxt>
      <P>I am not aware that the population of Dublin city ever dropped, whatever about the rest of the country. This is raised continually and if there were vacant corporation dwellings in those years, as there were, it was because the second Coalition broke all records in their housing programme.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMoore" hpid="Mr. Moore Mr. Moore">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Moore</NameTxt>
      <P>The Parliamentary Secretary has interrupted me on this point again.  He is implying that we <Col N="1854" /> had too many houses.  The point is that we had too few people.  Our people were being housed in Birmingham, Coventry and London.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnMKelly" hpid="Mr. Kelly Mr. Kelly">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Kelly</NameTxt>
      <P>I concede that there was severe emigration in the fifties as there was in the forties, the thirties and the twenties, but the population of Dublin city rose continuously.  The period about which Deputy Moore is talking was one in which the publicly paid for housing supply exceeded, for a while, the demand.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMoore" hpid="Mr. Moore Mr. Moore">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Moore</NameTxt>
      <P>That is my argument. The supply exceeded the demand.  The position is being reversed completely today and we have not got enough houses.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnMKelly" hpid="Mr. Kelly Mr. Kelly">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Kelly</NameTxt>
      <P>Because the figures achieved in municipal building under the second Coalition were never subsequently achieved.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMoore" hpid="Mr. Moore Mr. Moore">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Moore</NameTxt>
      <P>I did not want to go back to just after the last war but now I must do so.  In the war years materials could not be obtained. Dublin Corporation set out to preserve the Georgian buildings in Gardiner Street and Summerhill not because they wanted to preserve them but because they had no dwellings. They decided to preserve the old dwellings for families because they could not get the materials.  They preserved them at a cost of £1,000 per room. That was 30 years ago.  A frightful price was paid to maintain a Georgian facade.  It was not done for preservation but to house families.  The corporation decided to prepare for the housing drive which would come after the war when materials became available. The Coalition used what had been done and decided to build houses and roads quickly.  A Fianna Fáil Government had prepared the sites for the new houses and all the first Coalition had to do was&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnMKelly" hpid="Mr. Kelly Mr. Kelly">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Kelly</NameTxt>
      <P>To build them.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMoore" hpid="Mr. Moore Mr. Moore">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Moore</NameTxt>
      <P>The difference was that they then had the materials.  The war was over and we were getting back to normal times.  We should adopt a bipartisan approach to housing and social welfare.  Saying that Fianna Fáil <Col N="1855" /> did more than Fine Gael or Labour does not do any good.  We still have a big problem on hand.  If the Government do not take all positive steps to solve this problem we will have to be very severe on them.  I am not suggesting that we will demonstrate in the streets but we will demonstrate to the people that if they had a Fianna Fáil Government back in power we would continue the onward march towards self-sufficiency in housing.</P>
      <P>I do not deny that this year the Government have increased the amount of money for housing, but have they increased it enough to offset the eroding effect of the rampant inflation we have at the moment?  I do not think they have.  Despite the three good things which I saw in this budget&mdash;and I have mentioned them &mdash;it will cause a lot of problems.  It is suggested that a pensioner has got an 18 per cent increase but it is admitted that there will be a 14 per cent increase in inflation.  I cannot see the Government increasing further the social welfare payments and, therefore, there could be a total erosion of the increases given in the budget by the Government.  They may not be able to control inflation even with the best will in the world because there are outside influences at work.</P>
      <P>The Minister's budget was hailed by a clapping multitude on that side of the House as the greatest social charter ever.  Somebody described it as the greatest budget ever.  Perhaps it is, on paper.  It sounded very well the other day but I suggest that it is a gamble, and gamblers do not always win.  I do not think the nation's finances should be gambled with.  The Government did not face up to one financial aspect on which I am sure the Parliamentary Secretary is much better versed than I am.  It often worries me that if we go on borrowing money and have to pay interest on it, we could reach a time when we had borrowed so much money that we could not service the debt.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnMKelly" hpid="Mr. Kelly Mr. Kelly">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Kelly</NameTxt>
      <P>I share the Deputy's amazement at the growth in the national debt.  It was ten times greater <Col N="1856" /> at this time last year than it was in 1948 when the first Coalition took office.  It has been growing by enormous leaps and bounds.  I am not a financial expert and I do not pretend to be able to explain how that can be defended. It is a problem which has not raised its head this year for the first time. Long before the change of Government I was wondering about this colossal national debt which was eating up a very large proportion of the annual budget for the payment of interest.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TomJFitzpatrick" hpid="Mr. T.J. Fitzpatrick (Dublin Central) Mr. T.J. Fitzpatrick (Dublin Central)">
      <NameTxt>Mr. T.J. Fitzpatrick</NameTxt>
      <P>
        <i>(Dublin Central):</i> We were getting our money from national loans and it was going back into the economy.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMoore" hpid="Mr. Moore Mr. Moore">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Moore</NameTxt>
      <P>The two Deputies are disappointing me again.  They are engaging in one-upmanship on finance.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnMKelly" hpid="Mr. Kelly Mr. Kelly">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Kelly</NameTxt>
      <P>I did not mean it that way.  I recognise that Deputy Moore does not mean to be cantankerous.  In referring to the national debt we are referring to something which has been growing at an enormous rate for a very long time.  It was not this year or last year that it began to take off through the ceiling.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMoore" hpid="Mr. Moore Mr. Moore">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Moore</NameTxt>
      <P>This Government made many blunders but I do not suggest that they created the national debt which has been growing for many years.  They played their part.  Some economists might say that is a good thing in a way.  We could not stop borrowing anyway, even if we wanted to.  I wonder will civilisation ever reach the stage when it will not be able to service its debts.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnMKelly" hpid="Mr. Kelly Mr. Kelly">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Kelly</NameTxt>
      <P>If I heard him correctly, Deputy Fitzpatrick put his finger on one aspect of it which is really important. The interest payments on money raised inside the country on loans go back into the economy and end up being taxed again by the State in some shape or form.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMoore" hpid="Mr. Moore Mr. Moore">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Moore</NameTxt>
      <P>Money which has been borrowed on the Continent even at fairly low rates has to be paid back not into our economy but to the German bankers or some of those people.  What we are borrowing must be repaid and I am not one to say &ldquo;stop borrowing&rdquo;.  As I have said <Col N="1857" /> before, posterity must pay for some of the things we are doing.  As Deputy Haughey mentioned this morning, the Government intend buying a nuclear reactor.  That is a good thing but why should this generation pay for it?  We continue to build up our national debts.  The point I am making and I am not making political capital out of this&mdash;is how does one service those debts eventually?  Will some Minister for Finance, some day, sit down and say: &ldquo;Here is my plan for doing this&rdquo;?  Perhaps by then we will have reached such a stage of affluence that we will not have to borrow any more but that is hardly possible.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnMKelly" hpid="Mr. Kelly Mr. Kelly">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Kelly</NameTxt>
      <P>There was a time when the party to which I belong took the view that one ought to balance a budget, in the way that one tries to meet household expenses.  In order to do that, a shilling was taken off the old age pension and we never heard the last of it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMoore" hpid="Mr. Moore Mr. Moore">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Moore</NameTxt>
      <P>Now I shall really put the knife in.  The Parliamentary Secretary said: &ldquo;Take it off the old age pensioners&rdquo; but why not take it from the people who can afford it?  That is what we criticise the Government for.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnMKelly" hpid="Mr. Kelly Mr. Kelly">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Kelly</NameTxt>
      <P>That criticism was justified 40 years ago; that was what put the Deputy's party in and kept them there for a long time but the rules have changed now in a big way.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMoore" hpid="Mr. Moore Mr. Moore">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Moore</NameTxt>
      <P>Well, the Parliamentary Secretary is penitent for having done that, is he not?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnMKelly" hpid="Mr. Kelly Mr. Kelly">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Kelly</NameTxt>
      <P>I concede; I think they made a mistake in taking a shilling off the old age pension.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMoore" hpid="Mr. Moore Mr. Moore">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Moore</NameTxt>
      <P>I will give the Parliamentary Secretary absolution if he promises not to do it again.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>We are talking about housing, house finances and can we ever reach a full solution of these problems. I do not think one can in a growing society.  For example, in our city here, we shall have one million people very shortly.  Therefore, we shall require more houses for them. Not alone that, but people today demand a better type of house and <Col N="1858" /> these demands continue to grow all the time.  The same can be said of the general increase in the standard of living; people demand more and perhaps rightly so.  As long as we can fashion our economic assets or machinery in a way that builds up a worthwhile society, then we shall all enjoy being politicians, despite the fact that at times it is not a very easy calling.  But if we accept that politics is the science of Government and try and keep it at that high level, then the people will never desert the democratic ideal.</P>
    <P>I started off earlier by pointing out that the Government must be blamed for creating a great degree of cynicism in the minds of people in relation to their promises with regard to prices. During the election campaign&mdash;foolishly, I thought&mdash;they made several promises which some people seemed to believe and voted for them.  But those same people, now put to the pin of their collar to live, will not forget that.  When the drafting of the next national pay agreement comes about, the Government will have to spell out how much tax remission they will give to the craftsmen and workers generally.  Here is an instance where we could help to offset inflation and increase wages and standards at the same time, by the State joining in the deliberations of the national wage negotiations.  That is not an original thought of mine.  It came from a man whose name I cannot remember now and who said that the State must not stand aside any longer; indeed, the State should be the third force in planning a national wage agreement.  If one got together the employers, the trade unions and the State and the unions said: &ldquo;We want a certain amount, certain conditions,&rdquo; they are the people best able to speak for the workers because they know their aspirations and are engaged in furthering their interest all the time. I suppose the basic means of achieving a good standard of living is to have a good income.  Therefore, the trade unions are quite right in demanding a fair share of the national welfare for their members.  Of course, the employers will always say: &ldquo;We <Col N="1859" /> cannot afford that amount&rdquo;; the wrangling goes on then and sometimes ends in industrial strife.  But it is amazing that while today we may hear employers saying they cannot afford it, next week they grant it and it is all over.</P>
    <P>In future negotiations I suggest that the State must become a partner in the negotiations, that the Minister for Finance would be present as a partner at the conference or would inform the conference that if £X increase is to be given to the workers &mdash;whether in wage, salary or social welfare payments&mdash;the State would say then what part it could play.  This may be a sort of merry-go-round of taxation of income where we might have the State saying: &ldquo;There are £X towards the workers' claim.&rdquo; Of course, the worker will pay income tax anyway.  This is where we have to call on the income tax experts and see what they can do to ensure that all workers have a proper standard of living.</P>
    <P>I have not much more to say but I do want to praise the Government for three things in the budget.  One was the general social welfare payment increases which I think are inadequate but, at least, are an increase. Secondly, it probes into poverty which is a most interesting thing and I am sure we should all be very glad to help in any way we can on this matter. The third is the payment to women over 58 years of age.  As I said earlier, many of these women have given their entire lives to caring for an aged relative and we have always treated them in the most horrible manner possible.  Those are three good points. But the matters on which I criticise the Government&mdash;from the background of my amatuer financial or economic knowledge&mdash;are that though they had almost £170 million to give away they gave a mere £34 million to social welfare payments and the fact that they have not kept faith, on the basis of the national pay agreement, with the income tax relief given. There is a little touch of effrontery here when the Minister says that the old age pensioners and other categories <Col N="1860" /> of pensioners have received an 18 per cent increase while we will have a 14 per cent increase in the cost of living.  That is estimated on the Government's own goods which go on to the index for assessing the cost of living.  But there is always, in any Government's index, other articles which people use and which are not considered to be part of our needs for living.  Therefore, we can see very well that the increases granted in the budget will be eroded by spiralling inflation and the failure of the Government to check that inflation.  I think the Government will stand on trial towards the end of the year in relation to this budget.  I hope it works out; perhaps the Minister intends it will but I do not think that is likely.</P>
    <P>There has been talk of parties going right and going left.  In my day if a person spoke of a right wing person I was so naïve I thought he was talking about a footballer or a hurler.  In our more sophisticated age, with the influence of the French Assembly, its left wing, right wing and centre people, we are told that Fine Gael have gone left or that the Labour Party have gone right.  I do not think they have gone anywhere; they have remained stationary.  People may say that the influence of the Labour Party on Fine Gael has been tremendous. Perhaps it has been, I do not know, but it was the Fianna Fáil Party who set the pattern here of seeking social justice.  If we have dragged the Labour and Fine Gael Parties into 20th century thinking on social justice, we have done a good job.  I remember the time when it was not popular to enunciate the policy of the Fianna Fáil Party as regards sharing national wealth.  If we have succeeded in getting the Fine Gael Party to think of distributing the national cake on a more equitable basis, then we shall have succeeded.</P>
    <P>All the talk about socialism is so much poppycock.  I remember a Labour Party document called <i>The New Republic</i> issued in 1969.  I read it and I was amazed at the time that any modern political party could go for the kind of socialism portrayed in that booklet because at that time <Col N="1861" /> France, Western Germany and the other Community countries had rejected the out-of-date socialism propounded by the Labour Party in that booklet.  That was just prior to the 1969 General Election, an election in which they took such a beating at the polls.  The old republic was not so bad after all and we heard no more about the &ldquo;New Republic&rdquo;.</P>
    <P>If by their association with the Fine Gael Party they have now evolved between them some kind of secret republic, a republic in which they give a slight increase to the old age pensioners, and this represents their brand of socialism, I shudder to think what the early socialists would have thought of them.  James Connolly, James Larkin and all the others would feel themselves maligned; they certainly would not feel very happy.  Both the Labour Party and the Fine Gael Party are, in my opinion, very conservative in their outlook and I would appeal to them now, for the sake of the country, to drop their alleged rows over their ideologies and get down to running the country properly. I do not care whether they do it by socialist or capitalist means.  All I ask is that they control prices and give people a chance to live.  Would they, for heaven's sake, do something positive? Otherwise, I can well see the people rising in anger and throwing the Government out for their broken and their unfulfilled promises and their posturing as a benevolent Government.</P>
    <Speaker pid="FergusOBrien" hpid="Mr. O'Brien Mr. O'Brien">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Brien</NameTxt>
      <P>I have great pleasure in supporting this very fine budget. The last two budgets introduced here are memorable for their social content. We recall Deputy Colley describing this budget as a &ldquo;fraudulent&rdquo; budget.  He did not make sense because there is nothing fraudulent in this budget.  He was utterly disillusioned because for the second year in succession the National Coalition Government brought in yet another fine budget designed to meet the needs of our society.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Last year the budget was described as an inflationary budget, a budget which would cause a rundown in the economy with resultant unemployment. <Col N="1862" /> They really were dismal Jimmies.  What happened as a result of last year's budget?  GNP rose and unemployment fell; there were more people working as a result of a courageous budget.</P>
    <P>I am not an economist but I know that in these modern times one has to budget for a deficit in order to bring about expansion.  If the Opposition object to deficit budgeting from whom would they have taken the money to avoid that deficit?  Would they have taken it from the widows, from the old age pensioners, from the deserted wives?  Or would they have gone for economic stagnation?  Would they have cut back on expenditure? They should tell us what they would have done.</P>
    <P>We are quite clear about what we want.  One of our priorities in our 14-point programme was the tackling of poverty.  In this budget the Minister is allocating £100,000 for an investigation into poverty.  This is the first time such a step has been taken. We know the budget will not eradicate poverty, but it is a step in the right direction.  Before poverty can be eradicated an in-depth investigation is essential and we propose to carry out such an investigation.</P>
    <P>It was very important that a national wage agreement should have been drawn up.  It has been drawn up and great credit is due to the workers and trade unions for the responsible way in which they went about their task.  The agreement ensures a peaceful climate in industry. This is very important.</P>
    <P>The Government had to surmount certain difficulties in the last year.  It is hardly necessary to mention the oil crisis and the very high prices that had to be paid for imports.  Across the water they had to cut back to a three-day working week.  We did not take such drastic action.  We were able to operate in such a way that people could continue working.  I believe we have now got over the hump and we can look forward to a slow upward climb.  The growth in our economy will be slow.  This is understandable because of the high prices we will have to pay for oil and imported commodities. Some of the affluent nations in <Col N="1863" /> Europe are struggling to hold their own while a small country on the periphery actually makes economic progress. This budget augurs well for our economic expansion in the future.  We must have courage and I believe that next year when the budget comes before the House we will find the same satisfactory trend in our economic growth.</P>
    <P>In this budget we have had first class increases in our social welfare payments.  I am glad that, for the first time, they have been based on percentage increases because for years the only time such people received anything was in election years. If it was not an election year such recipients did badly.  We have got to rid ourselves of this kind of attitude and base increases on percentages, and the economic growth of the nation. The nation that neglects its aged, its sick and its deserted wives is not a progressive nation.</P>
    <P>This budget, and this Government make it clear that it is not intended to neglect those less well off in our society.  People in the Opposition have stated that Fine Gael are going socialist, that they are being dragged along by the Labour Party, but if improving the lot of our old age pensioners, the widow, the orphan or the deserted wife is socialist, so be it; but it is also Christian and that, in my view, is the important thing.  People have described this as a budget of concern.</P>
    <P>Deputy Colley was rather crestfallen as the news came to him and hit him about this budget.  He could not understand how a Government could look after the social welfare recipients so well and not tax the community in return.  That was something new to him and he could not understand it but he will be on that side of the House long enough to learn further lessons on how to produce a good budget.  We did not tax because we knew if we taxed commodities or other items it would lead to a rise in the cost of living.  We are committed to keeping down the cost of living where possible and we will not increase the cost.</P>
    <Col N="1864" />
    <Speaker pid="TomJFitzpatrick" hpid="Mr. T.J. Fitzpatrick (Dublin Central) Mr. T.J. Fitzpatrick (Dublin Central)">
      <NameTxt>Mr. T.J. Fitzpatrick</NameTxt>
      <P>
        <i>(Dublin Central):</i> Any business that runs itself excessively into debt usually goes broke.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FergusOBrien" hpid="Mr. O'Brien Mr. O'Brien">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Brien</NameTxt>
      <P>We are running a nation.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TomJFitzpatrick" hpid="Mr. T.J. Fitzpatrick (Dublin Central) Mr. T.J. Fitzpatrick (Dublin Central)">
      <NameTxt>Mr. T.J. Fitzpatrick</NameTxt>
      <P>
        <i>(Dublin Central):</i> There is no difference.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FergusOBrien" hpid="Mr. O'Brien Mr. O'Brien">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Brien</NameTxt>
      <P>The Deputy's party borrowed over a number of years and as a result of that borrowing we have a large national debt.  That is a debt which Fianna Fáil imposed on the nation.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TomJFitzpatrick" hpid="Mr. T.J. Fitzpatrick (Dublin Central) Mr. T.J. Fitzpatrick (Dublin Central)">
      <NameTxt>Mr. T.J. Fitzpatrick</NameTxt>
      <P>
        <i>(Dublin Central):</i> The assets are Aer Lingus, housing, schools and hospitals and that is what national debt means.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FergusOBrien" hpid="Mr. O'Brien Mr. O'Brien">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Brien</NameTxt>
      <P>Fianna Fáil imposed a national debt but we are budgeting for a deficit because we want to expand the economy, because we want to build a nuclear station, to develop more factories and build more houses.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TomJFitzpatrick" hpid="Mr. T.J. Fitzpatrick (Dublin Central) Mr. T.J. Fitzpatrick (Dublin Central)">
      <NameTxt>Mr. T.J. Fitzpatrick</NameTxt>
      <P>
        <i>(Dublin Central):</i> That has nothing to do with the current budget.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FergusOBrien" hpid="Mr. O'Brien Mr. O'Brien">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Brien</NameTxt>
      <P>It is expansion within the economic situation.  Last year the Opposition said the same thing would happen but during 1973 our production increased, the job rate increased by 9,000 and our percentage increase was 7 per cent, the highest for years. Under the Fianna Fáil Governments we had been dragging along with no real leap forward at all but a stop-go budget hoping something would happen next year.  We are concerned for next year and that is what this budget is concerned about.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>We will come back next year with an equally good budget because it is the duty of Government to provide and expand.  We are providing for this and we are going to expand.  The approach towards some innovations in the social welfare system is to be welcomed.  Now if a single girl spends her life looking after an aged parent she will have an income at the age of 58.  This is very important because it has been one of the anomalies that has existed in our society and about which the Opposition <Col N="1865" /> did precious little.  They had not the mind, the will or the energy to implement anything new.  They kept on with the old three and four pence all the time.</P>
    <P>In the case of a man serving a prison term his wife and family will now be looked after.  For too long this was one of the injustices in our society. While the husband was serving a jail term he was guaranteed meals and a bed while the people who were not responsible, his family, were the real sufferers.  This is a first step towards improving this position.  This, coupled with the increases in the social welfare payments, clearly illustrates the difference between the Opposition and the present Government.</P>
    <P>We have seen their attitude towards capital gains.  How any political party in 1974 can oppose capital gains is something beyond my comprehension. They opposed it at the Ard Fheis and subsequently when the White Paper was introduced.</P>
    <Speaker pid="TomJFitzpatrick" hpid="Mr. T.J. Fitzpatrick (Dublin Central) Mr. T.J. Fitzpatrick (Dublin Central)">
      <NameTxt>Mr. T.J. Fitzpatrick</NameTxt>
      <P>
        <i>(Dublin Central):</i> It was the new wealth tax.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FergusOBrien" hpid="Mr. O'Brien Mr. O'Brien">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Brien</NameTxt>
      <P>Fianna Fáil put forward no ideas.  I was looking at the Ard Fheis which is no longer a secret session because it is televised.  It was made quite clear then when Fianna Fáil were playing to their rich friends that they were not going to impose capital gains on them.  I have not seen anybody rushing to say that Fianna Fáil would be in favour of capital gains.  Fianna Fáil, apparently, are opposed to any type of tax reform in our society.  Over the years they have seen the speculators stripping companies, developing land, selling land and making vast profits overnight but not paying a penny tax. That is going to stop and any society that allows it happen is asking for trouble and would not be representative of the people.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I welcome the White Paper on tax reform.  It is desirable and necessary that the tax systems of any country are revised from time to time.  Unfortunately for 16 years Fianna Fáil took no action in this sphere except to bring within the income tax net <Col N="1866" /> the lower-paid worker thereby ensuring that, for instance, the typist earning £12 or £15 per week, out of which she had to pay a room rent of £5 or £6, would also have to pay income tax.  The number of surtax payers seems to have reduced during the Fianna Fáil regime.  Of course under that Administration, too, the speculator was exempt entirely.  Can anybody on the other side of the House tell us that that was social justice?</P>
    <P>Fianna Fáil have lost their political soul.  They try to tell us that they represent the working man and the small farmer.  Perhaps in the early years and long before I was involved in politics they were justified in making that claim but that is no longer the case.  They were in office too long and the party are now in the hands of what I referred to the other evening at a branch meeting as elitist groups who use the party for their own purpose.</P>
    <Speaker pid="TomJFitzpatrick" hpid="Mr. T.J. Fitzpatrick (Dublin Central) Mr. T.J. Fitzpatrick (Dublin Central)">
      <NameTxt>Mr. T.J. Fitzpatrick</NameTxt>
      <P>
        <i>(Dublin Central):</i> The Deputy should consult the IDA in relation to the wealth tax.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FergusOBrien" hpid="Mr. O'Brien Mr. O'Brien">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Brien</NameTxt>
      <P>We will consult everybody who should be consulted in this regard.  We are not a party to make decisions without first consulting those interests that should be consulted.  The document that has been issued is a discussion document.  The IDA, as well as chartered accountants and all other sections of society, will be encouraged to make submissions in relation to the document before June next.  These submissions will be examined in the light of the needs of our community generally and not in the light of the needs only of any sectional group or groups.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TomJFitzpatrick" hpid="Mr. T.J. Fitzpatrick (Dublin Central) Mr. T.J. Fitzpatrick (Dublin Central)">
      <NameTxt>Mr. T.J. Fitzpatrick</NameTxt>
      <P>
        <i>(Dublin Central):</i> Let the Deputy read the remarks that have been made already.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FergusOBrien" hpid="Mr. O'Brien Mr. O'Brien">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Brien</NameTxt>
      <P>Any group who wish their remarks to be heeded must make representations in the proper way.  Let not the Opposition pin their hopes on the possibility of these tax reforms having adverse effects on our economy.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TomJFitzpatrick" hpid="Mr. T.J. Fitzpatrick (Dublin Central) Mr. T.J. Fitzpatrick (Dublin Central)">
      <NameTxt>Mr. T.J. Fitzpatrick</NameTxt>
      <P>
        <i>(Dublin Central):</i> I hope sincerely that they will not have adverse effects.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1867" />
    <Speaker pid="FergusOBrien" hpid="Mr. O'Brien Mr. O'Brien">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Brien</NameTxt>
      <P>The reforms are being introduced for the purpose of streamlining our economy and of updating our tax system so as to bring it in line with most of the EEC countries which have a wealth tax.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TomJFitzpatrick" hpid="Mr. T.J. Fitzpatrick (Dublin Central) Mr. T.J. Fitzpatrick (Dublin Central)">
      <NameTxt>Mr. T.J. Fitzpatrick</NameTxt>
      <P>
        <i>(Dublin Central):</i> Not all of them have a wealth tax.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FergusOBrien" hpid="Mr. O'Brien Mr. O'Brien">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Brien</NameTxt>
      <P>They have a capital gains tax.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ConorCruiseOBrien" hpid="Minister for Posts and Telegraphs (Dr. Cruise-O'Brien) Minister for Posts and Telegraphs (Dr. Cruise-O'Brien)">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Posts and Telegraphs (Dr. Cruise-O'Brien)</NameTxt>
      <P>Some of them have a wealth tax.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FergusOBrien" hpid="Mr. O'Brien Mr. O'Brien">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Brien</NameTxt>
      <P>It is our aim to ensure that there is a fair spread of taxation.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TomJFitzpatrick" hpid="Mr. T.J. Fitzpatrick (Dublin Central) Mr. T.J. Fitzpatrick (Dublin Central)">
      <NameTxt>Mr. T.J. Fitzpatrick</NameTxt>
      <P>
        <i>(Dublin Central):</i> I agree that the system is wrong but the task of bringing about reform is not being approached by the Government in the right way.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FergusOBrien" hpid="Mr. O'Brien Mr. O'Brien">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Brien</NameTxt>
      <P>What we are doing will ensure a fair spread.  During Fianna Fáil's term in office they did no more than tax the working people. The PAYE system was the lazy way out.  It took effort and imagination to produce this White Paper.  We will sell the idea because the people want tax reform.  There are tax reliefs in the budget.  When did the party opposite give any tax reliefs?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TomJFitzpatrick" hpid="Mr. T.J. Fitzpatrick (Dublin Central) Mr. T.J. Fitzpatrick (Dublin Central)">
      <NameTxt>Mr. T.J. Fitzpatrick</NameTxt>
      <P>
        <i>(Dublin Central):</i> Two years ago.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FergusOBrien" hpid="Mr. O'Brien Mr. O'Brien">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Brien</NameTxt>
      <P>They did not.  The tax system has not been looked at since the time of the last Coalition in 1957. I am glad that Deputy Fitzpatrick is concerned with changing the system but he should inform his party of the need for change so that they might participate in that change rather than merely have articles in the newspapers, such as one I read last week in which it is stated that Fianna Fáil are opposed to the White Paper because it will spell ruination for the country because it will result in a flow outwards of wealth.  That is dangerous talk and talk that should not come from any responsible Opposition.  If they have comments to make on the question of capital taxation they should make them in a constructive <Col N="1868" /> and not in a mischievous way.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TomJFitzpatrick" hpid="Mr. T.J. Fitzpatrick (Dublin Central) Mr. T.J. Fitzpatrick (Dublin Central)">
      <NameTxt>Mr. T.J. Fitzpatrick</NameTxt>
      <P>
        <i>(Dublin Central):</i> We are being constructive.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FergusOBrien" hpid="Mr. O'Brien Mr. O'Brien">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Brien</NameTxt>
      <P>Fianna Fáil are hoping that we will run into trouble.  This Government are not running into trouble.  We are on a course on which we intend to remain.  Apparently the only concern of the Opposition is to look for cracks in the Government.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ConorCruiseOBrien" hpid="Dr. Cruise-O'Brien Dr. Cruise-O'Brien">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Cruise-O'Brien</NameTxt>
      <P>They will be looking for a long time.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FergusOBrien" hpid="Mr. O'Brien Mr. O'Brien">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Brien</NameTxt>
      <P>Would it not be much better if they cemented the cracks in their own party and organised themselves in a way that would allow them to oppose in a constructive manner? We would welcome a good Opposition because such an Opposition is good in a democracy but we do not want what we have now&mdash;an Opposition sitting and waiting for a breakdown in the Coalition.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DenisJones" hpid="An Leas-Cheann Comhairle Denis Francis Jones">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Cheann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>We are on the Financial Resolution.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FergusOBrien" hpid="Mr. O'Brien Mr. O'Brien">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Brien</NameTxt>
      <P>I have heard Deputies from the benches opposite describe this as an election budget. They seem to think that improvements in social welfare benefits are linked with the probability of an election. They cannot accept the concept that people must be given what is their entitlement.  As an economy develops and expands it is only just that social welfare recipients get their share of the cake.  In this case they are getting 18 per cent.  We would all like to see them being given more.  We reckon that the cost of living rise will be in the order of 14 per cent.  Therefore the category to which I am referring will benefit in real terms to the extent of 4 per cent in their standard of living.  Old-age pensioners and social welfare recipients living in local authority dwellings are now paying a rent of only 5p.  That in effect is another increase for them.</P>
      <P>Debate adjourned.</P>
      <P>The Dáil adjourned at 5 p.m. until 3 p.m. on Wednesday, 24th April, 1974.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
</Debate>