<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE Debate SYSTEM "../Debate.dtd"[]>
<Debate DocTitle="Seanad Debate" Day="Thu" Date="25" Month="Jan" Year="1923" Vol="1" No="8" DateIrish="Déardaoin, 25 Eanáir 1923" DateEnglish="Thursday, 25 January 1923" House="S" CommitteeEng="" CommitteeIr="" SubNameEng="" cnum="175">
  <MainHeading Type="Prelude" LHead="" RHead="">
    <Title>
    </Title>
    <P>
      <Col N="175" /> Cromadh ar obair an lae ar 3.5 p.m. Bhí an Cathaoirleach an Tiarna Lann Abhaigh, 'sa Chathaoir.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="IRISHMEN IN THE GREAT" RHead="WAR.(HOUSING SCHEME)">
    <Title>IRISHMEN IN THE GREAT WAR.(HOUSING SCHEME).</Title>
    <Speaker pid="EarlofMayo" hpid="The EARL of MAYO The EARL of MAYO">
      <NameTxt>The EARL of MAYO</NameTxt>
      <P>With the leave of the Seanad, I should like to draw attention to a fact of pressing interest&mdash; that is, that a large tract of land has been bought and paid for in the county of Kildare, on which it is proposed to settle Irishmen who fought in the Great War.  The object of this scheme is the same as that of several other schemes in various parts of Ireland which have been carried out successfully.  Houses are to be built for these men, and they are each to have a certain amount of land.  Now, I am not going to make a speech.  I only wish to say that in these times it is very difficult to deal with such a large scheme. In one or two cases the schemes have been eminently successful, but I know that in my own county some irresponsible people, when houses were built, came forward and broke the windows.  We are, of course, accustomed to that sort of thing in this country.  Now, this is a very large scheme, and I only wish to draw the attention of the Seanad to it in order to enable the Government, if possible, to deal with this matter.  I will bring it forward later on, when I have, if possible, consulted with the Minister or Ministers that have to deal with the matter.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="INTERNED EMPLOYEES OF DUBLIN" RHead="CORPORATION.(HOUSING SCHEME GRANT)">
    <Title>INTERNED EMPLOYEES OF DUBLIN CORPORATION.(HOUSING SCHEME GRANT).</Title>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasFarren" hpid="Mr. THOMAS FARREN Mr. THOMAS FARREN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. THOMAS FARREN</NameTxt>
      <P>In accordance with the Standing Orders, I wish to ask the permission of the Seanad to move a motion of urgency, also dealing with the question of housing.  The motion I wish to move is in connection with the decision of the Government to withdraw the Housing Grant from the Dublin Corporation. It is a matter of great urgency, and I wish the permission of the Seanad to move it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="176" />
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="AN CATHAOIRLEACH AN CATHAOIRLEACH">
      <NameTxt>AN CATHAOIRLEACH</NameTxt>
      <P>The Standing Order dealing with this matter has already been adopted.  I will read it:&mdash;&ldquo;Provided that, by permission of An Cathaoirleach, and by leave of the House, urgent motions may be discussed on shorter notice.&rdquo;  That is to say, we could dispense with notice altogether.  It would be sufficient compliance, for instance, if notice were given by a Senator to the effect that at the end of the business he would move this motion.  The question now before us is one that I will not take the responsibility of ruling out, but I will leave it to the Seanad, and the motion is whether it is the wish of the Seanad that leave be given to Senator Farren to move the motion which he has just read, and I will ask Senators in favour of that to say &ldquo;Tá,&rdquo; and of the contrary opinion &ldquo;Nil.&rdquo;</P>
      <P>The question having been put,</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="AN CATHAOIRLEACH AN CATHAOIRLEACH">
      <NameTxt>AN CATHAOIRLEACH</NameTxt>
      <P>I really cannot myself say where the majority lies, and there is rather a difficulty in consequence arising out of a point to which we have come now.  This point arises for the first time, and it is whether the leave of the Seanad means the unanimous permission or the permission by a majority. I should be myself inclined to hold that it means a majority.  If Senator Farren wishes, I will take a division.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasFarren" hpid="Mr. FARREN Mr. FARREN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. FARREN</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes, if I do not get unanimous permission, I will call for a division.  It is a matter of public urgency.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="AN CATHAOIRLEACH AN CATHAOIRLEACH">
      <NameTxt>AN CATHAOIRLEACH</NameTxt>
      <P>The Senators will understand now that a vote is being taken on the question whether leave is to be given to discuss this matter on notice shorter than would be required by the Standing Orders.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MartinFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. MARTIN FITZGERALD Mr. MARTIN FITZGERALD">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MARTIN FITZGERALD</NameTxt>
      <P>I think there are several members of the Seanad who do not realise what the motion is. Some have come in late, and if the motion were explained I think it would be enlightening.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="AN CATHAOIRLEACH AN CATHAOIRLEACH">
      <NameTxt>AN CATHAOIRLEACH</NameTxt>
      <P>The motion speaks for itself.  The object of it is to ask the Government to reconsider the decision with which we must assume we are all familiar, because it was published in the daily Press, <i>i.e.</i>, that in view of the action of the Corporation in voting half wages to their workpeople who are at present interned <Col N="177" /> in prison by order of the Free State, the Government has declared that it will withhold, so long as they maintain this attitude, the housing grant.  The object of Senator Farren's motion is to reconsider and rescind that resolution.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="178" />
    <Speaker pid="MartinFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. MARTIN FITZGERALD Mr. MARTIN FITZGERALD">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MARTIN FITZGERALD</NameTxt>
      <P>It is perfectly clear now.  I notice that several of the Senators did not realise what the motion was.  It has not been printed or given to them, and so has been sprung on them.</P>
      <P Just="Center">The Seanad divided: Tá, 12; Níl, 24.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <table pgwide="1">
      <tgroup cols="2">
        <colspec colname="1" colnum="1" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <colspec colname="2" colnum="2" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry rowsep="1">Tá.<br />T.W. Bennett.<br />J.G. Douglas.<br />E.W. Eyre.<br />Thos. Farren.<br />Mrs. Alice Stopford Green.<br />H. Seymour Guinness.<br />E. MacLysaght.<br />Thos. McPartlin.<br />Sir Bryan Mahon.<br />Colonel Moore.<br />Michael O'Dea.<br />J.T. O'Farrell.</entry>
            <entry rowsep="1">Níl.<br />John Bagwell, D.L.<br />Wm. Barrington.<br />Mrs. E. Costelloe.<br />John C. Counihan.<br />Sir Nugent Everard.<br />Martin Fitzgerald.<br />J.P. Goodbody.<br />Sir John Purser Griffith.<br />C.J. Irwin.<br />A. Jackson.<br />Sir John Keane.<br />P.W. Kenny.<br />Clayton Joseph Love.<br />John McLoughlin.<br />Lord Mayo.<br />T. Linehan.<br />B. O'Rourke.<br />J. J. Parkinson.<br />Col. Sir Hutcheson Poe.<br />Mrs. Wyse Power.<br />Dr. G. Sigerson.<br />The Earl of Wicklow.<br />W.B. Yeats.<br />Ed. McEvoy.</entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="THE STANDING" RHead="ORDERS">
    <Title>THE STANDING ORDERS.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="AN CATHAOIRLEACH AN CATHAOIRLEACH">
      <NameTxt>AN CATHAOIRLEACH</NameTxt>
      <P>The first business on the agenda is the resumed consideration of the Standing Orders.  It is the recollection of the Seanad that we reached No. 38 before the adjournment took place.  We will now proceed to consider the others consecutively.</P>
      <P>Standing Orders Nos. 39, 40, 41, 42, 43, 44, 45, and 46 were adopted.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EarlofWicklow" hpid="THE EARL of WICKLOW THE EARL of WICKLOW">
      <NameTxt>THE EARL of WICKLOW</NameTxt>
      <P>May I ask a question with regard to No. 47?  I see it appears that if a Senator introduces a Bill, he himself will move its passage in its various stages through the Seanad. What will happen where a Bill comes from Dáil Eireann which has no representative in this Seanad, and at present no arrangement that I am aware of exists whereby a member of the Seanad shall act as Government representative and pilot a Bill through its various stages?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="AN CATHAOIRLEACH AN CATHAOIRLEACH">
      <NameTxt>AN CATHAOIRLEACH</NameTxt>
      <P>That difficulty has been in my mind, and in that of some of my colleagues from the very start, owing to the fact that there is no provision that makes it compulsory for a Minister to attend here during the passage of Bills.  They have the right to attend, but we have no power to compel them to do so.  It is for themselves whether they do it or not, and I think they will find it to their own convenience in the case of a Bill which they have to discuss to provide that some Minister in charge will be in attendance here.  I should mention in addition that this Committee on Standing Orders hope to be able to arrive at some mutual arrangement between this Seanad and the Dáil by which mutual facilities will be afforded in the first instance to members of the Government during the passage of Bills here, and a corresponding privilege, or permission, to members of the Seanad who are interested in Bills originating in this House and under discussion in the other, and nothing definite has been arrived at, but I will assure the Senator we have not overlooked the matter, and will do our best to provide mutual facilities to deal with the matter he mentioned.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDouglas" hpid="Mr. J.G. DOUGLAS Mr. J.G. DOUGLAS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J.G. DOUGLAS</NameTxt>
      <P>May I mention that Standing Order No. 59 also provides for that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="179" />
    <Speaker pid="MauriceMoore" hpid="Colonel MAURICE MOORE Colonel MAURICE MOORE">
      <NameTxt>Colonel MAURICE MOORE</NameTxt>
      <P>A great many Senators were embarrassed by the position they were in owing to the absence of a Minister here to explain their point of view.</P>
      <P>Standing Orders 48 to 64 were then adopted without discussion.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="AN CATHAOIRLEACH AN CATHAOIRLEACH">
      <NameTxt>AN CATHAOIRLEACH</NameTxt>
      <P>We now come to a series of clauses from 65 to 71, which proposes the method of election in the case of casual vacancies caused by death or resignation of a member and perhaps as Chairman of the Committee appointed to draft these Standing Orders I might mention that I am responsible primarily for these particular Orders, having drawn them up, though they were, of course, subject to be approved by other members of the Committee, as they were.  I should like shortly to explain what the system is. On receiving notice or knowledge of the fact that there is a vacancy the Draft Orders provide that the Chairman shall at the next meeting of the Seanad have a notice on the Agenda informing the Seanad that the vacancy has taken place. At that meeting the Seanad is then to fix a day for an election to fill the vacancy, and that date is not to happen for a shorter interval than a fortnight from the date of notice.  That is to say a fortnight at least must elapse from the date on which notice is given of the holding of an election.  During the first week of that fortnight any member of this Seanad may nominate a candidate for the vacancy, the nomination to contain the full name, address, and qualifications of the candidate proposed.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EarlofMayo" hpid="The EARL of MAYO The EARL of MAYO">
      <NameTxt>The EARL of MAYO</NameTxt>
      <P>Is there to be a seconder?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="AN CATHAOIRLEACH AN CATHAOIRLEACH">
      <NameTxt>AN CATHAOIRLEACH</NameTxt>
      <P>Not neces&mdash; sarily.  Such nomination to be accompanied by a consent in writing from the person nominated that he will serve if elected.  On the date fixed for the election the Draft Orders propose that in the event&mdash;an unlikely event, I should think&mdash;of candidates nominated exceeding five in number the first vote shall be taken for a select list of three out of the total number, and the three who obtain the highest votes are to be put on the select list.  Then a further ballot is to be taken to select two out of the three, and after the two have been <Col N="180" /> selected there shall be a further ballot as between these two.  If, on the ballot as between the two one candidate obtains a majority of 3/5ths of the members present and voting he is to be declared elected.  If he does not get a majority of 3/5ths his name is to be put forward to the Seanad again, and if he again fails to get the requisite majority the election is to be treated as abortive.  On the other hand if the number of candidates does not exceed five, but is more than two the first ballot is to be for two only.  Then there is to be a second ballot as between the two, and the rest of the proceedings is as in the previous case.  If only two are nominated, then, of course, the first and second ballots are to be dispensed with, and a ballot is taken between the two, and if either obtains the necessary 3/5ths majority he becomes duly elected. If he fails to get the 3/5ths his name is again submitted, and if he again fails the election is abortive.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="A SENATOR A SENATOR">
      <NameTxt>A SENATOR.</NameTxt>
      <P>What about a tie?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="AN CATHAOIRLEACH AN CATHAOIRLEACH">
      <NameTxt>AN CATHAOIRLEACH</NameTxt>
      <P>The Chairman has a casting vote.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MartinFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. MARTIN FITZGERALD Mr. MARTIN FITZGERALD">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MARTIN FITZGERALD</NameTxt>
      <P>You cannot have a tie if there is to be a 3/5ths majority.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="AN CATHAOIRLEACH AN CATHAOIRLEACH">
      <NameTxt>AN CATHAOIRLEACH</NameTxt>
      <P>If there is only one candidate proposed, then the Standing Orders provide that his name should be submitted to a ballot, and if he obtains 3/5ths of a majority of the members present and voting he is to be declared elected.  If he fails to get the 3/5ths majority the election is abortive. Then there is a proviso for the purposes of this election, that the quorum is to be not less than thirty members.  I want the Seanad to understand that this means that no person can be elected to fill a casual vacancy unless he has the support of at least 18 members.  I do not think that that is an extravagant number and I think that the Seanad may, perhaps, agree that no person ought to be elected to a responsible position of this kind, unless he can command the votes of 18 members of the Seanad.  If you made it a bare majority the result would be that a candidate who only obtained 15 votes out of 60 members of the Seanad might possibly be returned.  These are the draft proposals, and I shall now ask Senator Linehan to propose his alternative <Col N="181" /> Standing Orders, of which he has given notice.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasLinehan" hpid="Mr. THOMAS LINEHAN Mr. THOMAS LINEHAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. THOMAS LINEHAN.</NameTxt>
      <P>As far as Rules 65 and 66 are concerned, I have no objection to them, but I have to the others, which are very complicated as regards procedure in the case of an election.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="AN CATHAOIRLEACH AN CATHAOIRLEACH">
      <NameTxt>AN CATHAOIRLEACH</NameTxt>
      <P>What are the other rules?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasLinehan" hpid="Mr. LINEHAN Mr. LINEHAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. LINEHAN</NameTxt>
      <P>67, 68, 69 and 70.  I propose we omit these four rules and proceed to formulate rules which will be more simple and will be better understood by the members of the Seanad.  According to these rules, where it is necessary to have a 3/5ths majority at the end of a poll, it may happen that several times we might not be able to elect a Senator at all.  I do not see why an ordinary majority of the Senators would not do.  It is necessary, by the rules, to have a 3/5ths majority to ensure that an election will be valid.  Now, it might happen that after several polls no candidate will be able to secure that majority, so that the election will be abortive and have to be gone over again.  I think it will be quite sufficient for a candidate to secure a majority of the votes of the Senators, and that should be sufficient to secure his election.  I sent in draft alternative rules for filling a vacancy, which were circulated.  The amendment I propose is: &ldquo;To omit Rules 67, 68, 69, and 70, and substitute:&mdash;</P>
      <P>&lsquo;Upon the appointed day the Seanad shall proceed to elect by ballot a Senator to fill the vacancy, and if there are more than two candidates proposed, the name of the candidate who receives the smallest number of votes as a result of the first ballot shall be eliminated, and further ballots between the remaining candidates shall be taken, always after each ballot striking off the name of the candidate having the smallest number of votes, till the number of candidates be reduced to two, when a final vote by ballot shall be taken, and the candidate who received the majority of the votes shall be declared elected.&rsquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>&lsquo;If two or more candidates having the smallest number of votes as the result of any ballot have obtained an equal number of votes, the Cathaoirleach shall <Col N="182" /> decide which of them shall have his name eliminated.&rdquo;&rsquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="AN CATHAOIRLEACH AN CATHAOIRLEACH">
      <NameTxt>AN CATHAOIRLEACH</NameTxt>
      <P>It will be more in order if I put rule 65 to the Seanad as you do not quarrel with any rule until you come to 67.  When we come to that I will put your amendment.</P>
      <P>Standing Orders 65 and 66 were then adopted without discussion.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="AN CATHAOIRLEACH AN CATHAOIRLEACH">
      <NameTxt>AN CATHAOIRLEACH</NameTxt>
      <P>As regards Rules 67, 68, 69 and 70, Senator Linehan moves as an amendment the deletion of these four and the substitution in their place of the above amendment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MartinFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. MARTIN FITZGERALD Mr. MARTIN FITZGERALD">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MARTIN FITZGERALD</NameTxt>
      <P>I think on the basis of the proposed voting the election would carry on for a very long time.  It seems to me that the rules are not framed at all on democratic principles. On the rules framed, if five or six go up, and one candidate secures say 45 votes he must go up repeatedly for election.  As he has got a majority of the Seanad I do not think he should have to go up again and again.  If on the first voting any person nominated secures a majority of those present, a majority in excess of the other candidates combined, it does not appear to me that there is any sense in further voting.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="AN CATHAOIRLEACH AN CATHAOIRLEACH">
      <NameTxt>AN CATHAOIRLEACH</NameTxt>
      <P>I understand you to suggest that if there were 5 candidates the whole thing is to depend on one vote.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MartinFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. FITZGERALD Mr. FITZGERALD">
      <NameTxt>Mr. FITZGERALD.</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes, if one candidate gets the majority of the Senators on the first count.  Otherwise it is simply putting the election back and back.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="AN CATHAOIRLEACH AN CATHAOIRLEACH">
      <NameTxt>AN CATHAOIRLEACH</NameTxt>
      <P>You are not supporting the amendment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MartinFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. FITZGERALD Mr. FITZGERALD">
      <NameTxt>Mr. FITZGERALD</NameTxt>
      <P>No.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="AN CATHAOIRLEACH AN CATHAOIRLEACH">
      <NameTxt>AN CATHAOIRLEACH</NameTxt>
      <P>Well, you are out of order for the present as the amendment has not been seconded.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MartinFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. FITZGERALD Mr. FITZGERALD">
      <NameTxt>Mr. FITZGERALD</NameTxt>
      <P>We have not had the amendment before us in its full form.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="AN CATHAOIRLEACH AN CATHAOIRLEACH">
      <NameTxt>AN CATHAOIRLEACH</NameTxt>
      <P>That is true, but Mr. Linehan is now in possession.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MartinFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. FITZGERALD Mr. FITZGERALD">
      <NameTxt>Mr. FITZGERALD</NameTxt>
      <P>But none of us have a copy of the amendment, and some of us do not know what is in it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="183" />
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="AN CATHAOIRLEACH AN CATHAOIRLEACH">
      <NameTxt>AN CATHAOIRLEACH</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not understand how that is so as it was circulated.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MartinFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. FITZGERALD Mr. FITZGERALD">
      <NameTxt>Mr. FITZGERALD</NameTxt>
      <P>No one here has a copy of it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="AN CATHAOIRLEACH AN CATHAOIRLEACH">
      <NameTxt>AN CATHAOIRLEACH</NameTxt>
      <P>It proposes that no matter what number of candidates might go forward they would be weeded out one by one, according to the percentage of votes for the various candidates. That is to say on the first ballot the candidate who gets the least number of votes his name is weeded out. Then you have another ballot to weed out the next name, until only two are left.  Whichever of these get the majority, and if there is no tie, will be elected automatically.  I am a good deal impressed by Senator Linehan's amendment, which seems to me to have many points of advantage over Articles 68, 69 and 70, but it differs in one very important respect, which is that it does not provide for a 3/5ths majority.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasBennett" hpid="Mr. T. BENNETT Mr. T. BENNETT">
      <NameTxt>Mr. T. BENNETT</NameTxt>
      <P>rose to speak.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="AN CATHAOIRLEACH AN CATHAOIRLEACH">
      <NameTxt>AN CATHAOIRLEACH</NameTxt>
      <P>Are you seconding his amendment?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasBennett" hpid="Mr. T. BENNETT Mr. T. BENNETT">
      <NameTxt>Mr. T. BENNETT.</NameTxt>
      <P>I am prepared to second his amendment, but I should like, before doing so, to have some information, which I think you could give us from the Chair, as to what was in the minds of the Committee who prepared the Standing Orders providing for a 3/5ths majority.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="AN CATHAOIRLEACH AN CATHAOIRLEACH">
      <NameTxt>AN CATHAOIRLEACH</NameTxt>
      <P>I thought I made that clear.  The idea the Committee had was this, that it would be a mistake, if you had a very meagre attendance in the Seanad, if a candidate obtained, we will say, only 12, 13, or 14 votes for a position of the kind, and that matter should be one in which each Senator will recognise his own responsibility, and will do his best to attend on the occasion.  And, therefore, we wanted to avoid any person being elected to the position unless he had at least the support in the Seanad of 18 members.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasBennett" hpid="Mr. T. BENNETT Mr. T. BENNETT">
      <NameTxt>Mr. T. BENNETT</NameTxt>
      <P>If Senator Linehan would alter that amendment to provide for a 3/5ths majority I would second it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasLinehan" hpid="Mr. LINEHAN Mr. LINEHAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. LINEHAN</NameTxt>
      <P>That is one of the points I object to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="184" />
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="AN CATHAOIRLEACH AN CATHAOIRLEACH">
      <NameTxt>AN CATHAOIRLEACH</NameTxt>
      <P>Then I must bring the point back to regulate it.  Does anyone second it?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnKeaneBart" hpid="Sir J. KEANE Sir J. KEANE">
      <NameTxt>Sir J. KEANE</NameTxt>
      <P>I second it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="AN CATHAOIRLEACH AN CATHAOIRLEACH">
      <NameTxt>AN CATHAOIRLEACH</NameTxt>
      <P>Now the amendment is open for discussion.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MartinFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. M. FITZGERALD Mr. M. FITZGERALD">
      <NameTxt>Mr. M. FITZGERALD</NameTxt>
      <P>I think, Sir, the first draft of the rules was left very wide.  Three-fifths of a majority should not be essential for election.  A majority should be quite sufficient, provided that a certain number&mdash;we call it a quorum&mdash; forms the House&mdash;that is, that no rushing might be done by a small number. You suggest that 18 should be the minimum votes for an elected Senator.  I think that is very moderate.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="AN CATHAOIRLEACH AN CATHAOIRLEACH">
      <NameTxt>AN CATHAOIRLEACH</NameTxt>
      <P>Then may I point out to you, Senator Fitzgerald, that unless you put the quorum at 30, on your suggestion of a bare majority 15 or 16 would be enough.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MartinFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. M. FITZGERALD Mr. M. FITZGERALD">
      <NameTxt>Mr. M. FITZGERALD</NameTxt>
      <P>I fully realise that, and that is the reason why I go a little further than you and say 18.  I even go further, and say the number who will vote for a Senator should not be under 20 or 25, if you like, for the election of a Senator.  I certainly say that the idea of a two-thirds majority is not by any means reasonable or democratic.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="AN CATHAOIRLEACH AN CATHAOIRLEACH">
      <NameTxt>AN CATHAOIRLEACH</NameTxt>
      <P>Three-fifths.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MartinFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. M. FITZGERALD Mr. M. FITZGERALD">
      <NameTxt>Mr. M. FITZGERALD</NameTxt>
      <P>Three-fifths and two-fifths, I think, is altogether out of proportion.  I think the majority of an Assembly like this ought to be quite sufficient for the election of a member. If, on the first ballot, the candidate nominated, secures the majority of this Assembly&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="AN CATHAOIRLEACH AN CATHAOIRLEACH">
      <NameTxt>AN CATHAOIRLEACH</NameTxt>
      <P>Are you proposing that now as an amendment?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MartinFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. M. FITZGERALD Mr. M. FITZGERALD">
      <NameTxt>Mr. M. FITZGERALD</NameTxt>
      <P>I propose that as an amendment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasFarren" hpid="Mr. FARREN Mr. FARREN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. FARREN</NameTxt>
      <P>On a point of order, can you have two amendments before the Seanad at one time?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="AN CATHAOIRLEACH AN CATHAOIRLEACH">
      <NameTxt>AN CATHAOIRLEACH.</NameTxt>
      <P>Oh, yes; they are not before the Seanad at the one time.  If Senator Martin.  Fitzgerald moves an amendment, and it is seconded, I shall take that first, because, if that <Col N="185" /> were carried, of course it would dispose of Senator Linehan's amendment and would dispose of the draft proposals of the Committee.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasFarren" hpid="Mr. FARREN Mr. FARREN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. FARREN</NameTxt>
      <P>With all respect the amendment proposed by Senator Linehan must take precedence over any other amendment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="AN CATHAOIRLEACH AN CATHAOIRLEACH">
      <NameTxt>AN CATHAOIRLEACH</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not agree with that, for this obvious reason, that if Senator Martin Fitzgerald's amendment commends itself to the good-sense of the majority of the Seanad, it disposes not only of the draft proposals of the Committee, but of the amendment proposed by Senator Linehan.  Is Senator Martin Fitzgerald's amendment seconded?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MauriceMoore" hpid="Colonel M. MOORE Colonel M. MOORE">
      <NameTxt>Colonel M. MOORE</NameTxt>
      <P>Would not Senator Fitzgerald's amendment be an amendment to the other amendment?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="AN CATHAOIRLEACH AN CATHAOIRLEACH">
      <NameTxt>AN CATHAOIRLEACH</NameTxt>
      <P>That is the reason why I am taking it now.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOFarrell" hpid="Mr. J.T. O'FARRELL Mr. J.T. O'FARRELL">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J.T. O'FARRELL</NameTxt>
      <P>I would respectfully submit that the business before the Seanad is the Report of the Committee on Standing Orders.  Senator Linehan has moved an amendment to this original motion, and I cannot convince myself how you can accept another amendment to that amendment before you deal with the amendment to the original motion.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="AN CATHAOIRLEACH AN CATHAOIRLEACH">
      <NameTxt>AN CATHAOIRLEACH</NameTxt>
      <P>Cannot the Senator see the absurd position the Seanad will be placed in if I were to allow a discussion to continue on Senator Linehan's motion?  That motion might be carried, and then Senator Martin Fitzgerald might move his amendment, the effect of which would be to destroy altogether Senator Linehan's amendment, and consequently the more convenient course is to proceed with Senator Fitzgerald's amendment after it is seconded.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMacPartlin" hpid="Mr. T. McPARTLIN Mr. T. McPARTLIN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. T. McPARTLIN</NameTxt>
      <P>In that event will we be allowed to propose the amendment which will abolish both the other amendments?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="AN CATHAOIRLEACH AN CATHAOIRLEACH">
      <NameTxt>AN CATHAOIRLEACH</NameTxt>
      <P>Certainly, but I do not think that will happen.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EarlofMayo" hpid="The EARL of MAYO The EARL of MAYO">
      <NameTxt>The EARL of MAYO</NameTxt>
      <P>I am afraid I <Col N="186" /> am more democratic than the Committee, Mr. Linehan and Mr. Fitzgerald&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="AN CATHAOIRLEACH AN CATHAOIRLEACH">
      <NameTxt>AN CATHAOIRLEACH</NameTxt>
      <P>One moment. Are you seconding Senator Martin Fitzgerald's amendment?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EarlofMayo" hpid="The EARL of MAYO The EARL of MAYO">
      <NameTxt>The EARL of MAYO.</NameTxt>
      <P>No, I am not. I am speaking generally.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="AN CATHAOIRLEACH AN CATHAOIRLEACH">
      <NameTxt>AN CATHAOIRLEACH</NameTxt>
      <P>Then I must ask you to wait.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasBennett" hpid="Mr. T. BENNETT Mr. T. BENNETT">
      <NameTxt>Mr. T. BENNETT</NameTxt>
      <P>I beg to second Senator Fitzgerald's amendment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="AN CATHAOIRLEACH AN CATHAOIRLEACH">
      <NameTxt>AN CATHAOIRLEACH</NameTxt>
      <P>I want the Seanad to understand the position before them.  First of all, there was a motion to approve of the Draft Proposals of the Committee.  To that Senator Linehan has moved a series of clauses, which would delete 67, 68, 69, and 70, and it is proposed to draft Orders to substitute in their place the method of election that I have mentioned.  Senator Martin Fitzgerald has proposed as an alternative, by amendment, a different method of selection, which, if adopted, would rule out both the proposals of the Committee and Senator Linehan's proposed amendment. And now, if anybody wishes to speak upon the amendment moved by Senator Martin Fitzgerald, of course he is at liberty to do so.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMacPartlin" hpid="Mr. McPARTLIN Mr. McPARTLIN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McPARTLIN</NameTxt>
      <P>What is the amendment?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="AN CATHAOIRLEACH AN CATHAOIRLEACH">
      <NameTxt>AN CATHAOIRLEACH</NameTxt>
      <P>The amendment is&mdash;if any candidate proposed, no matter what the number of candidates may be, obtains a majority of the members present and voting, he is to be there and then declared to be elected a Senator.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EarlofMayo" hpid="The EARL of MAYO The EARL of MAYO">
      <NameTxt>The EARL of MAYO</NameTxt>
      <P>As I said before, I am rather more democratic than the Committee, or Senator Linehan and Senator Fitzgerald.  My opinion is this, and you may take it how you like, surely if there is to be a Senator elected to this Seanad, that is a very important matter. If people do not attend here to elect that Senator, I am of opinion that the majority of the Seanad should decide who is to be their Senator.  We, as a body, have been chosen, nominated, and elected.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasFarren" hpid="Mr. FARREN Mr. FARREN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. FARREN</NameTxt>
      <P>No.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="187" />
    <Speaker pid="EarlofMayo" hpid="The EARL of MAYO The EARL of MAYO">
      <NameTxt>The EARL of MAYO</NameTxt>
      <P>Well, I allow the correction.  Surely, in times like these, there is a certain dignity allowed to this Assembly, and if people do not come to elect a man to this body when a vacancy occurs that is their fault, and this arrangement suggested both by the Committee and by the amendments, I say with all due respect to the movers of each amendment, I think, is very complicated. A fortnight's notice of the death or resignation of a member will be given, and then there is seven days more for a proposal to be brought forward for the election of a member to fill the vacancy, and there is plenty time for people to come forward here and elect a Senator.  Let the man who gets the biggest majority be a member of the Seanad.  That does away with all this 3/5ths or one-half arrangement.  Members of the Seanad have got to come here and do their duty, that is my opinion.  I disapprove entirely of this mixed-up sort of arrangement for the election of a Senator in a body like this, especially as it is the first time there has been a Seanad in Ireland.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasBennett" hpid="Mr. WESTROPP BENNETT Mr. WESTROPP BENNETT">
      <NameTxt>Mr. WESTROPP BENNETT</NameTxt>
      <P>I wish to support the amendment.  I think where a member has the majority of the Seanad he should command the respect of the Seanad.  Under the proposal of Senator Fitzgerald, if a man comes here and there are 30 Senators, and if he has the support of 16 of these he is elected, because he has a clear majority of the Seanad.  It seems the simplest arrangement, and far less complicated than the other one of eliminating one after the other. That in my experience in other places led to a good deal of finesse.  I have seen men who had not a chance brought from the bottom of the poll and competing with the last candidate, thereby eliminating useful candidates. In my opinion, if a man comes here and commands the respect of the Seanad, so as to secure a majority, then he should be entitled to the respect shown to him by the Seanad, and be thereby elected. I feel that strongly.  I do not suppose the occasion will ever arise, but if this Seanad will ever arrive at a stage in which they might resolve themselves into a clique that clique might so arrange that the man with the second or third majority might be ruled out of all subsequent <Col N="188" /> voting.  I feel strongly Senator Fitzgerald's proposal is a wiser one, and for that reason I would like to suggest, from the little experience I have had, that it might work better.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="AN CATHAOIRLEACH AN CATHAOIRLEACH">
      <NameTxt>AN CATHAOIRLEACH</NameTxt>
      <P>May I point out that there is a misapprehension in your mind, that the adoption of this amendment by Senator Fitzgerald might lead to the very danger and difficulty you yourselves anticipate, <i>i.e.</i>, that a certain section of the Seanad might vote solidly for one candidate and thereby exclude better men who came No. 2 or No. 3. That is the very thing I am afraid is likely to happen if you adopt this idea of having but one vote and giving the election to the candidate who secures the majority on the one large ballot.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasBennett" hpid="Mr. WESTROPP BENNETT Mr. WESTROPP BENNETT">
      <NameTxt>Mr. WESTROPP BENNETT</NameTxt>
      <P>Surely if a man commands the respect of the Seanad, sufficient to get the majority of the votes, he ought to be entitled to be elected a member of the Seanad.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="AN CATHAOIRLEACH AN CATHAOIRLEACH">
      <NameTxt>AN CATHAOIRLEACH.</NameTxt>
      <P>That is an obvious truism, but how are we to arrive at the result?  What I mean, Senator, is that the very evil you anticipate, that is to say a particular section of the Seanad might vote solidly for one man, and might exclude better candidates who are lower down on the list.  That is the very danger that is likely to happen if you decide the whole thing on one ballot.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MartinFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. FITZGERALD Mr. FITZGERALD">
      <NameTxt>Mr. FITZGERALD</NameTxt>
      <P>I think you misinterpret my amendment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="AN CATHAOIRLEACH AN CATHAOIRLEACH">
      <NameTxt>AN CATHAOIRLEACH</NameTxt>
      <P>We will hear you when the debate on your amendment is finished.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMacPartlin" hpid="Mr. McPARTLIN Mr. McPARTLIN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McPARTLIN</NameTxt>
      <P>I feel that I must vote against this amendment, and the reason I vote against it is that while I am in favour of the idea of the majority carrying the Senator to the Seanad, there appears to me to be underlying the discussion all along the fact that there must be 16 or 17, or 18 members voting in favour before any Senator is elected. That underlies Senator Fitzgerald's motion.  I do not see why, if all the important business of this Seanad can be carried by seven Senators, there must be 18 to vote for one Senator, who may be a dummy Senator.  Surely it is not altogether <Col N="189" /> so important that we should have the whole lot here.  It appears to me that a great number of the Senators look upon this as a spare time job&mdash;that they can come here when they like and stay away when they like, and that the elections will be kept over until they can come, when their own business allows them. Some of us look upon it as a duty to be here at every meeting, and I think this should be the outlook of all the Senators &mdash;that they should be here, especially at the present time.  It is not a question of delaying a meeting until you get eighteen of the people you like best to turn up to elect your man.  I think a majority vote is all right in so far as it goes, but underlying Senator Fitzgerald's idea, I think, is sixteen or eighteen of his own sort. Despite an anti-party vote here yesterday, one can see the party here just the same, though they do not wear the label up. That is really what is behind the whole thing&mdash;to ensure that if their business will not permit them to be here, that there will be a sufficient number here to carry one of their own party.  It is about time that we said that the opinion voiced yesterday is going to hold&mdash;that is, about the abolition of parties.  It is about time that an opportunity was taken to try and abolish parties, and to try and do the thing in a proper manner.  The country expects you to do it in a proper manner.  You are expected to be here at all times to do the nation's work in a proper manner, and not to come here when your business suits.  And the election of a Senator here is just as much the nation's work as anything else that takes place here.  If Senator Fitzgerald will qualify his amendment by saying he does not confine it to any number we may be able to vote for it; but if underlying the amendment is the idea of having fifteen or thirty of his own people to elect a man, then we will vote against it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EdwardMacLysaght" hpid="Mr. MacLYSAGHT Mr. MacLYSAGHT">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacLYSAGHT</NameTxt>
      <P>That will come up under 71.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMacPartlin" hpid="Mr. McPARTLIN Mr. McPARTLIN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McPARTLIN</NameTxt>
      <P>But it will be brushed over if you allow this to go.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOFarrell" hpid="Mr. J.T. O'FARRELL Mr. J.T. O'FARRELL">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J.T. O'FARRELL</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not know that we are particularly clear as to the procedure that Senator Fitzgerald proposes.  I think the procedure outlined in these Clauses 67, 68, and 69 is quite all right, with the exception of the <Col N="190" /> provision regarding the necessary three-fifths majority.  I think there can be general agreement in letting this clause stand, with that exception.  As has been pointed out already, far more important decisions than the election of a Senator to fill a vacancy can be carried by seven votes, and there is, moreover, the question of the quorum of thirty for such an election. That leaves the question open to considerable abuse.  Can you not conceive a few men, seeing that there would not be much chance of having their nominee carried on a particular occasion, walking out of the Chamber and leaving less than thirty people inside, and thereby postponing the election to another day?  Twenty-nine senators may stay here; and although twenty-nine, or five-sixths, might be in favour of the election of a particular nominee, the election might become inoperative because four or five Senators were smoking in the Lobby.  As has been pointed out, they get fourteen days' notice, and there are equal facilities for all to attend here on an occasion of that kind, and if somebody is elected by a majority of those present who may not command the support of three-fifths of thirty or three-fifths of those who should be here, the responsibility lies with the people who are not here and should be here if they possibly could.  Consequently I would support the amendment provided it means that the procedure outlined in this report is adhered to, and that the three-fifths majority and the thirty of a quorum be abolished, and that the bare majority should be sufficient to elect a Senator, in view of the complicated procedure outlined, and in view of the fact that fourteen days' notice has to be given.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="AN CATHAOIRLEACH AN CATHAOIRLEACH">
      <NameTxt>AN CATHAOIRLEACH</NameTxt>
      <P>Might I point out that Senator McPartlin is not really supporting the amendment.  The amendment of Senator Martin Fitzgerald is very plain and simple&mdash;that there should be one ballot and one ballot only, and that the candidate elected&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MartinFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. FITZGERALD Mr. FITZGERALD">
      <NameTxt>Mr. FITZGERALD</NameTxt>
      <P>No, no; that is what I wanted to question.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MauriceMoore" hpid="Colonel MOORE Colonel MOORE">
      <NameTxt>Colonel MOORE</NameTxt>
      <P>I think there is a misunderstanding.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="AN CATHAOIRLEACH AN CATHAOIRLEACH">
      <NameTxt>AN CATHAOIRLEACH</NameTxt>
      <P>Will Senator Martin Fitzgerald put his amendment in writing, before we discuss it any further <Col N="191" /> I certainly understood that that was what it meant.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MartinFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. FITZGERALD Mr. FITZGERALD">
      <NameTxt>Mr. FITZGERALD</NameTxt>
      <P>handed in his amendment in writing.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="AN CATHAOIRLEACH AN CATHAOIRLEACH">
      <NameTxt>AN CATHAOIRLEACH.</NameTxt>
      <P>I will read this to the Seanad.  It is not quite clear to me.  Perhaps the Seanad will understand it.  I can only say that I think it shows the importance in a matter of this kind&mdash;a matter of serious importance&mdash; that amendments should be put down in writing:&mdash;</P>
      <P>&ldquo;That in the case of the election of a Senator to the Seanad, in case of more than one nomination, should any nomination for the Senatorship secure a clear majority of those present that he be elected.  In the case of more than two nominees and a clear majority not being given to one, the nominee who gets the smallest number of votes be eliminated, and that the election proceed on the same basis for the other nominees.&rdquo;</P>
      <P>If the Senators understand that they will be in a position to vote upon it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMacPartlin" hpid="Mr. McPARTLIN Mr. McPARTLIN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McPARTLIN</NameTxt>
      <P>Might I suggest that Senator Fitzgerald&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="AN CATHAOIRLEACH AN CATHAOIRLEACH">
      <NameTxt>AN CATHAOIRLEACH</NameTxt>
      <P>One moment. In view of what Senator McPartlin has said, it is only right that Senator Martin Fitzgerald should tell the Seanad does he propose to support or amend Clause 71?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MartinFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. FITZGERALD Mr. FITZGERALD">
      <NameTxt>Mr. FITZGERALD</NameTxt>
      <P>In view of the remarks made by our friend of the Labour Party, and by our friend, the Earl of Mayo, I think I simply stand by the amendment I place before you.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="AN CATHAOIRLEACH AN CATHAOIRLEACH">
      <NameTxt>AN CATHAOIRLEACH</NameTxt>
      <P>Do you propose to amend Clause 71?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MartinFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. FITZGERALD Mr. FITZGERALD">
      <NameTxt>Mr. FITZGERALD</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes&mdash;that a quorum of the Seanad simply fills the vacancy.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="AN CATHAOIRLEACH AN CATHAOIRLEACH">
      <NameTxt>AN CATHAOIRLEACH</NameTxt>
      <P>In other words, your amendment is to take the place of not only 67, 68, 69 and 70, but also of 71.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MartinFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. FITZGERALD Mr. FITZGERALD">
      <NameTxt>Mr. FITZGERALD</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="AN CATHAOIRLEACH AN CATHAOIRLEACH">
      <NameTxt>AN CATHAOIRLEACH</NameTxt>
      <P>Now I understand.  I think we had better take a vote on that, if no other Senator wishes to speak.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDouglas" hpid="Mr. DOUGLAS Mr. DOUGLAS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. DOUGLAS</NameTxt>
      <P>It would make it <Col N="192" /> more clear to members if you would read the amendment a second time.</P>
      <P>Amendment read again.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="AN CATHAOIRLEACH AN CATHAOIRLEACH">
      <NameTxt>AN CATHAOIRLEACH</NameTxt>
      <P>I have read it as it has been handed to me.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamYeats" hpid="Mr. YEATS Mr. YEATS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. YEATS</NameTxt>
      <P>Are the names of the candidates to be one after the other in voting?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="AN CATHAOIRLEACH AN CATHAOIRLEACH">
      <NameTxt>AN CATHAOIRLEACH</NameTxt>
      <P>I am not very sanguine, but if I am right, as I understand it, it means this,&mdash;that on the first election no matter how many candidates there are, if one of the candidates secures a clear majority of the members present and voting he is to be elected as the result of that first vote.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamYeats" hpid="Mr. YEATS Mr. YEATS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. YEATS</NameTxt>
      <P>Who is to decide what name is to be put first?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="AN CATHAOIRLEACH AN CATHAOIRLEACH">
      <NameTxt>AN CATHAOIRLEACH</NameTxt>
      <P>I think what the Senator means is that no matter how many candidates there will be the Seanad will be asked in the first instance to vote, each member voting for any cadidate he likes.  I presume he intends to confine the right of voting to one candidate only no matter how many there may be, and apparently he contemplates that as a result of that first vote any one candidate who obtains a clear majority of the Senators present is to be declared elected.  But if he fails to get that majority then there is to be another vote, and the one who receives the smallest number of votes on the second ballot is to be eliminated.  I should have thought that what should have happened would be that if in the second ballot any candidate gets a clear majority he should be elected.  This means that the whole thing should be re-drafted because it is unworkable at present.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MartinFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. FITZGERALD Mr. FITZGERALD">
      <NameTxt>Mr. FITZGERALD</NameTxt>
      <P>The whole thing has been sprung upon us.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="AN CATHAOIRLEACH AN CATHAOIRLEACH">
      <NameTxt>AN CATHAOIRLEACH</NameTxt>
      <P>I am told you were asked, a considerable time ago, to put this into writing.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MartinFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. FITZGERALD Mr. FITZGERALD">
      <NameTxt>Mr. FITZGERALD</NameTxt>
      <P>No, it was only a while ago, and, of course, I had to listen to the discussion.  I could not write and listen to the discussion at the same time.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="HenryGuinness2" hpid="Mr. GUINNESS Mr. GUINNESS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. GUINNESS</NameTxt>
      <P>I suggest that Senator Fitzgerald adds to the end <Col N="193" /> of his amendment that the voting then proceeds until one of the candidates secures a majority of those present.  I think that would cover the point.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="AN CATHAOIRLEACH AN CATHAOIRLEACH">
      <NameTxt>AN CATHAOIRLEACH</NameTxt>
      <P>He would also have to provide as to what the voting powers of the members of the Seanad on the first ballot are.  Does he intend to confine each Senator to a vote for one candidate only?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MartinFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. FITZGERALD Mr. FITZGERALD">
      <NameTxt>Mr. FITZGERALD</NameTxt>
      <P>Naturally this is not Proportional Representation.  The whole difficulty is met by saying that if on the first vote a person receives a clear majority, or on the second vote he receives a clear majority, he is elected.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="AN CATHAOIRLEACH AN CATHAOIRLEACH">
      <NameTxt>AN CATHAOIRLEACH</NameTxt>
      <P>If there are five candidates&mdash;do you propose when the first vote is taken amongst the five that each member of the Seanad is only to vote for one.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MartinFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. FITZGERALD Mr. FITZGERALD">
      <NameTxt>Mr. FITZGERALD</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes, certainly.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnKeaneBart" hpid="Sir JOHN KEANE Sir JOHN KEANE">
      <NameTxt>Sir JOHN KEANE</NameTxt>
      <P>Before we vote I think if this is carried it will go in as a Standing Order, and the wording of it could be vastly improved.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EarlofMayo" hpid="The EARL of MAYO The EARL of MAYO">
      <NameTxt>The EARL of MAYO</NameTxt>
      <P>May I point out that the question of the deletion of Orders 67 to 72 should be voted upon first. If this amendment is carried it would absolutely delete all these clauses.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="AN CATHAOIRLEACH AN CATHAOIRLEACH">
      <NameTxt>AN CATHAOIRLEACH</NameTxt>
      <P>You cannot move anything at present, because we are debating this amendment.  If this amendment is carried Rules 67, 68, 69, 70 and 71 should go out.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOFarrell" hpid="Mr. J.T. O'FARRELL Mr. J.T. O'FARRELL">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J.T. O'FARRELL</NameTxt>
      <P>If this amendment is moved, can we move a subsequent amendment?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="AN CATHAOIRLEACH AN CATHAOIRLEACH">
      <NameTxt>AN CATHAOIRLEACH</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes.  I will have the roll called on the amendment moved by Senator Fitzgerald.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesGoodbody" hpid="Mr. GOODBODY Mr. GOODBODY">
      <NameTxt>Mr. GOODBODY</NameTxt>
      <P>I feel unable to vote upon the amendment unless it is properly worded.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="AN CATHAOIRLEACH AN CATHAOIRLEACH">
      <NameTxt>AN CATHAOIRLEACH</NameTxt>
      <P>If the Seanad will bear with me for a couple of minutes I will try and put it clearly.  I presume that Senator Fitzgerald intends that the vote is to be by ballot.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MartinFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. FITZGERALD Mr. FITZGERALD">
      <NameTxt>Mr. FITZGERALD</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="AN CATHAOIRLEACH AN CATHAOIRLEACH">
      <NameTxt>AN CATHAOIRLEACH</NameTxt>
      <P>I will put <Col N="194" /> the amendment then in this form:&mdash;&ldquo;That a vote by ballot shall be taken as between persons nominated, each Senator voting for one name only, and if upon such vote the candidate at the head of the poll obtains a clear majority of the members present and voting, he shall be declared elected.  Otherwise further ballots shall be taken until a candidate has obtained this majority the candidate who at each of these further ballots obtains the smallest number of votes being eliminated.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasLinehan" hpid="Mr. LINEHAN Mr. LINEHAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. LINEHAN</NameTxt>
      <P>There is little difference in principle between what is now proposed and the amendment which I proposed.  I think I will save the time of the Seanad by withdrawing my amendment and accepting this instead.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="NugentEverardBart" hpid="Sir NUGENT EVERARD Sir NUGENT EVERARD">
      <NameTxt>Sir NUGENT EVERARD</NameTxt>
      <P>I think there is one important difference.  I did not understand that Senator Linehan intended that Clause 71 should be eliminated.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="AN CATHAOIRLEACH AN CATHAOIRLEACH">
      <NameTxt>AN CATHAOIRLEACH</NameTxt>
      <P>His amendment did not propose that.  Let the Seanad clearly understand that this amendment of Senator Martin Fitzgerald is in lieu not only of four clauses, but of five.  In other words, if it is carried, Rules 67, 68, 69, 70, and 71 go out.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="HenryGuinness2" hpid="Mr. GUINNESS Mr. GUINNESS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. GUINNESS</NameTxt>
      <P>What is a clear majority?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="AN CATHAOIRLEACH AN CATHAOIRLEACH">
      <NameTxt>AN CATHAOIRLEACH</NameTxt>
      <P>If there were 41 voting, 21 would be a clear majority. In other words, it is a bare majority.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelODea" hpid="Mr. O'DEA Mr. O'DEA">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'DEA</NameTxt>
      <P>If there should be two or three or more vacancies, will the same machinery apply?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="AN CATHAOIRLEACH AN CATHAOIRLEACH">
      <NameTxt>AN CATHAOIRLEACH</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes; the same machinery will apply, certainly.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="HonJameson" hpid="Mr. ANDREW JAMESON Mr. ANDREW JAMESON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. ANDREW JAMESON</NameTxt>
      <P>I think we are not showing a great deal of courtesy to the Committee who drew up these Standing Orders.  We are trying to get a very democratic method of election, but we must not ignore the fact that in Rules 67, 68, and 69 the Committee have taken very elaborate precautions to prevent any rushing of a vote, and I take it for granted that our Committee have considered these things very carefully, and if we adopt Senator Fitzgerald's <Col N="195" /> amendment now we will be sweeping away all these things.  I do not think that many of us realise what we are sweeping away.  The Committee very elaborately considered these matters, and it seems to me to be wrong to sweep away a lot of things to obtain one.  The quorum is to be the same as is necessary for the rest of the business of the House, because you are doing away with clause 71.  The amendment wants a majority of the Senators present to vote, and the numbers present should be sufficient to form a quorum to carry on an election; but to secure that object, which many of us may think quite right, we are doing away with clauses that must have been put forward for some reason by the Committee, and I think before we do that we ought to hear some members of the Committee, to tell us what value there is in these, and what parts we might sweep away without doing any harm.  There is a good deal to be said for the real gist of Senator Fitzgerald's amendment, because I doubt if it was wise to alter the quorum.  We should trust our Senators to attend in sufficient numbers to enable a proper vote to be taken.  I should vote probably in favour of not altering the quorum, but I do not think that, in order to secure that result, we should do away with all the other recommendations in Rules 67, 68, and 69 made by the Committee.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="AN CATHAOIRLEACH AN CATHAOIRLEACH">
      <NameTxt>AN CATHAOIRLEACH</NameTxt>
      <P>If it would meet the views of the Senators perhaps Rules 67, 68, 69 and 70 could be allowed to stand with &lsquo;3/5ths&rdquo; altered to a bare majority and rule 71 deleted.  Perhaps that would meet the view of the majority of the Senators.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MauriceMoore" hpid="Colonel MOORE Colonel MOORE">
      <NameTxt>Colonel MOORE</NameTxt>
      <P>It is possible that through some calamity or other Senators might not be able to attend.  There might be a breakdown on the railways and Senators might not be able to turn up, and in that case would not 5 or 6 have the right if they turned up to insist on a vote?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOFarrell" hpid="Mr. J.T. O'FARRELL Mr. J.T. O'FARRELL">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J.T. O'FARRELL</NameTxt>
      <P>You should have 12, and I had intended to move something on the lines the Cathaoirleach suggested.  I suggest that we should now leave the Standing Orders as they are, only deleting the words &ldquo;3/5th&rdquo; in Orders 68 and 70, and deleting rule 71. <Col N="196" /> You will then have left what I will describe as considerable machinery and you will have done away with the 3/5ths and the 30 as a quorum.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDouglas" hpid="Mr. J.G. DOUGLAS Mr. J.G. DOUGLAS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J.G. DOUGLAS</NameTxt>
      <P>I entirely agree with the last Senator.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="AN CATHAOIRLEACH AN CATHAOIRLEACH">
      <NameTxt>AN CATHAOIRLEACH</NameTxt>
      <P>I think that I will see that those Clauses are amended to fall in with that view because I think it is an advantage to have a weeding out of the candidates.  I think these rules are wiser in that respect, and if you provide this weeding-out, then it meets the very point that Senator Linehan is anxious to bring about, and if the Seanad leave it to me, I will try to meet their view and do away with the quorum of 30 as distinct from a quorum of 12.  I think it would be desirable that the Committee be appointed and I think Senator Douglas is prepared to move the appointment of such a Committee.</P>
      <P>Amendment by leave withdrawn.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamBarrington" hpid="Mr. BARRINGTON Mr. BARRINGTON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. BARRINGTON</NameTxt>
      <P>I think that any important Committee that is appointed should have power to deal with further Standing Orders that will be necessary in relation to Private Bill legislation. Anybody at all familiar with the Private Bill legislation in the Houses of Parliament at Westminister, knows that very careful and very minute Standing Orders are required for the purpose of Private Bill Legislation, and these Orders provide for the payment of fees.  I have frequently heard that the expenses of the Houses of Parliament at Westminster are largely met by fees paid upon Private Bill legislation.  It would be a very desirable thing if the Committee would bear these points in mind when considering the new Standing Orders.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="SUGGESTED" RHead="OPENING PRAYER">
    <Title>SUGGESTED OPENING PRAYER.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="AN CATHAOIRLEACH AN CATHAOIRLEACH">
      <NameTxt>AN CATHAOIRLEACH</NameTxt>
      <P>We will pass from that and take up the next business on the agenda.  The Earl of Wicklow has asked permission to draw attention of the Seanad to a matter to which he attaches importance.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EarlofWicklow" hpid="EARL of WICKLOW EARL of WICKLOW">
      <NameTxt>EARL of WICKLOW</NameTxt>
      <P>It has occurred to me, and to a number of Senators, and I have seen references to it, and a suggestion made in the public Press, that it seems almost improper that we should begin our proceedings daily without any <Col N="197" /> form whatever of public prayer, and no reference whatever to Almighty God. Surely there has seidom been a Parliament in the history of the world that finds itself more in need of Divine guidance than ours, and it seems wrong that we do not ask for it.  It is quite immaterial to me whether any prayers that might be said are said in Irish or English, or in Latin, and it is equally immaterial if they are said according to the rites of the Roman Catholic Church, or the rites of the various denominations which exist in this country.  I am only concerned that some sort of reference should be made at the opening of our proceedings to the God whom we all worship.  I have been speaking to you, sir, about this, and you were good enough to think that if a minute's silence was observed, every Senator standing, might meet the case. Personally I would prefer a more definite form of prayer, and if that is so, I would most thankfully agree with it as something of a compromise.  I think every House of Parliament, certainly in England, has definite forms of prayer, and actually has a chaplain, and I really do not see why in this country we should not be able to do ourselves just as well in this respect as the others.  I do not propose any motion on the subject, but wish to get the sense of the Seanad upon my suggestion.  If it is the desire that something of the kind should be instituted, I would be very glad to put down a motion later.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="AN CATHAOIRLEACH AN CATHAOIRLEACH">
      <NameTxt>AN CATHAOIRLEACH</NameTxt>
      <P>The matter to which Senator the Earl of Wicklow has called attention is one that has already occupied attention.  The Speaker of the Dáil and I had a conversation on the subject. Senators will appreciate that this is a delicate and a difficult subject.  Questions of this kind are always delicate questions amongst us.  It was thought by him, and by myself, that perhaps the simplest and most dignified solution would be, if the Dáil and the Seanad were to arrange that at the beginning of business, all members standing up, there should be a moment's silence, and then each member could make what prayer he thought fit, according to his own belief. Otherwise, it might be difficult, and, as I say, delicate, to frame any sort of procedure that would receive universal acceptance.  As to the institution of chaplains for the purpose, I <Col N="198" /> am afraid, apart from the question of expense, that would also be a matter of very great difficulty.  I think there might be a simple and dignified solution if, as I say, the Seanad at the beginning of the sitting, those present, were to stand up in reverential attitude, each individual taking advantage of the interval for any particular form of prayer he preferred.  Perhaps it is better to leave the matter over, but it has not been overlooked, and probably, having regard to the attention that has been called to it, some definite course will be taken.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EarlofWicklow" hpid="EARL of WICKLOW EARL of WICKLOW">
      <NameTxt>EARL of WICKLOW</NameTxt>
      <P>I am perfectly satisfied, and if Senators will be good enough to consider the proposal, at a future sitting we can again refer to the matter.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MauriceMoore" hpid="Colonel MOORE Colonel MOORE">
      <NameTxt>Colonel MOORE</NameTxt>
      <P>I am inclined to agree with the proposal, but I think it may be left for the Standing Orders Committee to discuss.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BenjaminHaughton" hpid="Mr. BENJAMIN HAUGHTON Mr. BENJAMIN HAUGHTON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. BENJAMIN HAUGHTON</NameTxt>
      <P>On behalf of several other Senators and myself, may I say we are greatly pleased that Lord Wicklow brought this matter up, as it has been in the minds of many of us.  I hope some step such as has been indicated by An Cathaoirleach will be taken.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="AN CATHAOIRLEACH AN CATHAOIRLEACH">
      <NameTxt>AN CATHAOIRLEACH</NameTxt>
      <P>It is eminently desirable that whatever course is adopted should be one of universal agreement, and if Senators would talk about it amongst themselves and see what the prevailing idea is, we might do something useful in that connection.  I want to mention that a meeting of the Committee appointed on the motion of Colonel Moore, and which consisted of a very large number of members of the Seanad, will be held to-morrow at 12.  I now ask Senator Barrington to move his motion.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="ATLANTIC SERVICE" RHead="COMMISSION">
    <Title>ATLANTIC SERVICE COMMISSION.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamBarrington" hpid="Mr. WILLIAM BARRINGTON Mr. WILLIAM BARRINGTON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. WILLIAM BARRINGTON.</NameTxt>
      <P>I desire to move the following motion:&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <i>(a)</i>  That the Seanad requests the Government to appoint a Joint Commission from both Houses, of not more than seven members, to report upon the most practical means of establishing a regular line of Transatlantic steamers between Ireland and America, <Col N="199" /> with a terminal port in the Free State.</P>
    <P>
      <i>(b)</i>  Upon the most suitable ports for this purpose upon both sides of the Atlantic, having regard</P>
    <P>(1)  To their natural advantages;</P>
    <P>(2)  To the existing or prospective facilities they possess;</P>
    <P>(3)  To the cost of adapting them to the objects in view.</P>
    <P>
      <i>(c)</i>  That this Commission be authorised to negotiate with railway or steamship companies, harbour authorities, landowners, or others in a position to forward the above objects, with a view to obtaining reliable data as to costs, etc., for submission to Parliament.</P>
    <P>
      <i>(d)</i>  That this Commission be empowered, if they consider it desirable, to co-opt an additional member with special technical knowledge who is not a member of either Seanad or Dáil.</P>
    <P>
      <i>(e)</i>  That the Ministry be requested to make such provision as may be required to meet the necessary expenses of this Commission.</P>
    <P>In introducing the resolution to this Seanad which appears on the Order Paper, I feel at a great disadvantage owing to the death of a valuable colleague to whom I am indebted for much of the information I propose to lay before you.  I refer to the late Mr. Morley of Liverpool and Limerick, whose knowledge of shipping matters and position as a ship owner opened sources of information which would otherwise have been unavailable.  We have spent hours in working out the problem, and hours grew to days, weeks, and months, and we have travelled thousands of miles, in interviewing Under-Secretaries and Chief Secretaries.  Ministers and Prime Ministers of some of the Colonies interested, as well as shipping and railroad magnates from both sides of the Atlantic. When prospects were at last improving, the Great War extinguished all hopes of success, for a time at all events, and then Mr. Morley was called away by an inscrutable Providence, and I am left alone to carry on the work to which so much time and thought has been devoted. Lest any misconception should arise as to this resolution, if carried, involving this country in heavy, premature, <Col N="200" /> and consequently unwise expenditure, I want to impress upon this Seanad that the object of this motion is exactly the reverse.  It is to prevent the loss, failure, and discouragement sure to arise later, from the forcing of ill-considered, immature, or defective proposals upon the Government and the country by the force of public opinion.  The country has been led to expect that one of the first results of self-government will be the development of its natural resources, and it undoubtedly expects the redemption of these pledges at the earliest possible moment, and if it sees no steps being taken will be apt to become impatient of delay.</P>
    <P>Ireland possesses one obvious natural advantage of which no one can deprive her.  She is the nearest point in Europe to the continent of North America.  Her western and southern seaboard contains numerous safe and commodious natural harbours, as good as are to be found in the world.  The approximate distance from any of these western Irish ports to the nearest port of the North American continent, Cape Breton, is 2,050 nautical miles.  Halifax, Nova Scotia, owing to the excellence of its ice-free harbour, and the existing railway facilities is generally taken as a standard for calculation, and the distance of Halifax from the western Irish harbours is, approximately, 2,150 knots.  There are, however, in Nova Scotia, several other excellent ice-free ports&mdash;Country Harbour, Sidney Harbour, which lie from 100 to 150 nautical miles nearer to us. Accepting Halifax, however, an Atlantic liner of the same, or, perhaps, lower speed, than most of the newer boats&mdash;24 knots&mdash;would make the voyage in 93½ hours, or 3¾ days.</P>
    <P>Such a vessel leaving a western Irish port at 4 a.m. on Sunday morning&mdash;West European time&mdash;would reach Halifax at 9.30 p.m., same time or 5.30 p.m. local time the following Wednesday.  She could be ready to sail from Halifax the following Sunday, and arrive back at her port of departure in Ireland the following Wednesday, thus making a voyage across the Atlantic each week.  By any of the routes at present in use this would be an impossibility.  From Liverpool or Southampton to New York the quickest steamers occupy from 5½ to 7 days on the voyage and they only make one <Col N="201" /> journey out and one home each lunar month.  From this it is evident: (1) that only half the number of vessels would be required to give the same service from a western Irish port to Halifax as are needed from Liverpool to New York; (2) half the capital would be involved: (3) less than half the working expenses for the same service, because the expense of feeding passengers, and fuel and oil consumption, wear and tear, etc., for from 2½ to 3 days would be saved.  Some idea of what this saving would amount to can be gained by a consideration of the following pre-war figures:&mdash; The Chairman of the Transit Commission of Canada has placed the cost of working a bi-weekly line of steamers between Liverpool and New York at £1,804,400 per annum, and the cost of operating a similar line, between a western Irish port and Nova Scotia, at £600,000 per annum &mdash;a saving of upwards of a million pounds a year.  The saving would obviously be far greater now.  At first sight this might seem a somewhat startling statement to make, but the figures were prepared by gentlemen of great experience, well qualified to do so, and whose official positions should vouch for their accuracy. In considering this question, it will be necessary to dismiss from the mind all preconceived ideas based upon the usage of an Irish harbour as a port of call.  The fundamental principle underlying this suggestion is that an Irish harbour shall be the terminal port of the line.  With a port of call only, Ireland would lose most of the substantial advantages which have gone to the building up of such cities as New York, Boston, Liverpool, etc., into the important centres of commerce and population which they have become.  When dealing with this proposal I have frequently been told, &ldquo;Oh, but Ireland does not possess sufficient traffic to support such a line of steamers.&rdquo;  At present probably not, but it must be borne in mind that neither Liverpool, Southampton, nor New York in themselves possess the traffic to support the numerous vessels which frequent their harbours.  These towns and ports are simply the necks of the bottles through which the traffic flows; its final destination is somewhere else.  And if we can devise methods by which the traffic, of every kind, can be more economically and more expeditiously conveyed <Col N="202" /> to its final destination through our Western Irish port, and persuade it to come by that route we will have done a good day's work for Ireland, and one the beneficial effects of which can scarcely be overrated.</P>
    <P>What inducements can we offer to passengers and mails?  We must not ignore the fact that most of these are coming through or from London, and that many of these passengers are bad sailors, anxious to get to their destination as quickly as possible, and to be exposed to the torments of sea-sickness for as short a time as they can.</P>
    <P>A Western Irish port can be reached from London in 12 hours.</P>
    <table pgwide="1">
      <tgroup cols="4">
        <colspec colname="1" colnum="1" colwidth="26*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <colspec colname="2" colnum="2" colwidth="8*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <colspec colname="3" colnum="3" colwidth="8*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <colspec colname="4" colnum="4" colwidth="8*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <thead>
          <row>
            <entry rowsep="1">
            </entry>
            <entry rowsep="1">Days.</entry>
            <entry rowsep="1">Hrs.</entry>
            <entry rowsep="1">Mins.</entry>
          </row>
        </thead>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry>Ireland to Halifax</entry>
            <entry>3</entry>
            <entry>18</entry>
            <entry>&mdash;</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>Allow for transhipment of mails, etc.</entry>
            <entry>&mdash;</entry>
            <entry>2</entry>
            <entry>&mdash;</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>Train Halifax to New York</entry>
            <entry>1</entry>
            <entry>4</entry>
            <entry>&mdash;</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>Total via Ireland</entry>
            <entry>5</entry>
            <entry>12</entry>
            <entry>&mdash;</entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
    <P>
    </P>
    <table pgwide="1">
      <tgroup cols="4">
        <colspec colname="1" colnum="1" colwidth="26*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <colspec colname="2" colnum="2" colwidth="8*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <colspec colname="3" colnum="3" colwidth="8*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <colspec colname="4" colnum="4" colwidth="8*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <thead>
          <row>
            <entry rowsep="1">Record official time, G.P.O., London to New York, via South- ampton</entry>
            <entry rowsep="1">6</entry>
            <entry rowsep="1">22</entry>
            <entry rowsep="1">33</entry>
          </row>
        </thead>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry>Saving in favour of Irish port</entry>
            <entry>1</entry>
            <entry>10</entry>
            <entry>33</entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
    <P>If we can beat all other routes to New York itself by 34½ hours, or in round numbers a day and a half, what will the saving be to other places?</P>
    <P>Many passengers and much mail matter would be going to other places beyond New York, and which would be as speedily reached from Halifax over the Canadian railways as New York itself, such as Quebec.  Montreal, Toronto and Chicago.  So that in addition to saving one and a half days to New York the time would also be saved of the journey from thence to the destination of from two to two and a half days.  And this will hold good for all places further West and for Trans-Pacific mails, which must form a great inducement to Companies competing for such traffic to cast in their lot with us.  Much heavy cargo is now carried at unremunerative rates as filling-up stuff, because all freight paid for is so much money saved.  Why, however, carry it further than can be helped in these costly vessels, at a high rate of speed, which it is expensive to maintain? <Col N="203" /> Liverpool is not the final destination of the great bulk of cargo landed there.  It is simply a distributing centre. Such bulky low-freighted cargo could be much more economically distributed by inexpensive coasting steamers from the western Irish port which could, in most instances, carry it direct to its destination with no extra handling.  These coasters would bring back the low-freighted outgoing cargo, and such coal for the liners as it was necessary to import. It must be borne in mind that there is transhipment at present in Liverpool for all goods consigned elsewhere, as the bulk of them must be.  It may be asked why select a harbour in the West of Ireland for a terminal port instead of one nearer to the final destination of the goods.  And why, if the advantages previously referred to are so apparent, should the Government of the Irish Free State be asked to intervene. The answers to both are plain, and they are two-fold.  Such a route as has been outlined is not likely to be inaugurated by the enterprise of one Company or one State alone.  It can only be made a success by the co-operation of several Companies (Railway and Steamship), and probably States who are in a position largely to control and direct the commerce.</P>
    <P>
      <i>(a)</i>  On the Pacific Ocean;</P>
    <P>
      <i>(b)</i>  In America (both United States and Canada);</P>
    <P>
      <i>(c)</i>  And on the Atlantic.</P>
    <P>The tendency seems to be for the control of ports and shipping lines to fall more and more into the hands of the larger railway companies, and of the latter into that of the various States in which they lie.  As it is unlikely that one single company can be found in a position to comply with the conditions I have indicated as essential some inducements must be offered to the various States and companies which would be affected to get them to combine and cooperate. Such inducements in this case might be:&mdash;</P>
    <P>The guaranteed co-operation and assistance of the Irish Free State.</P>
    <P>2. The control of thoroughly suitable ports on both sides of the Atlantic which offer the shortest sea-route.</P>
    <P>I know from experience that it would <Col N="204" /> be idle to endeavour to get such a combination together unless one was in a position to assure them that the Government of the Irish Free State regarded the proposal with approval, and were prepared to do everything in their power to make the working a success.  In the long run nothing can deprive places of the geographical and natural advantages nature has bestowed upon them.  The West of Ireland and Nova Scotia are the nearest points in the two hemispheres where suitable harbour and railway connections are already in existence.  Between no other two such harbours would a weekly journey across the Atlantic by the same ship be possible for any steamers at present afloat.  The combination which first realises these facts and secures their position in the most suitable harbour on both sides will secure a grip of the trade of three Continents, of which no rivals can in future deprive them.  The further answer to the second part of this question &mdash;&ldquo;Why should the Government of Irish Free State intervene?&rdquo; is necessary; it is obvious that the people expect their Government to do everything in its power to foster Irish development along the lines of least resistance which nature has already provided; that the soundest way of doing so is to foster the creation of a number of thriving communities, especially in those parts of the country where at present they do not exist; that the assured success of the project I have outlined would, with absolute certainty, result in the founding of at least one prosperous city and centre of population; that such success can only be assured by the co-operation of several large companies in close alliance with their respective States.  The growth of such alliances and co-operation is like that of a tender plant, which cannot be hastened without injury to the plant itself, and largely depends upon the atmosphere.  I submit that we should endeavour to create or foster such an atmosphere with as little delay as possible, and it is to prevent the forcing upon the Government of spurious weeds whose growth is sure to lead to failure, disappointment, and discouragement that I have put forward the Resolution which I now beg to propose.</P>
    <Speaker pid="ArthurJackson" hpid="Mr. ARTHUR JACKSON Mr. ARTHUR JACKSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. ARTHUR JACKSON</NameTxt>
      <P>I wish to second the motion, and I do so with great pleasure.  I think probably the opening up of the West of Ireland should <Col N="205" /> be one of the most important matters connected with our harbours when it is borne in mind that in the twenty-six counties in the Free State we are mainly dependent upon agriculture, as I might say, the sole industry.  I know from my own experience that anyone who has had anything to do with shipping, or who has been connected with harbours, that any improvement of a harbour leads to increased industry.  I have known of expenditures of £5,000, £10,000, or £15,000 enabling larger vessels to be brought in, and they were no sooner able to come in from foreign ports than some enterprising people started new industries. Therefore, I support this proposal that lines of steamers might be brought to any port in the West of Ireland, and if it is to receive any support from this Seanad it should not be done in any parochial manner, but the whole Western seaboard should be considered as to what would be likely to be more successful, and, what is more important, what would be likely to prove most remunerative for those who would invest their money in it.  I think, on the whole, this matter has been kept back fifty years by promoters and people, in many cases with the best intentions, putting forward companies and schemes that had no earthly chance of ever seeing fruition.  Therefore, although I am not myself much in favour of Committees and Commissions &mdash;Ireland has had too many of them, and I think the results have not been commensurate with the time that has been spent on them and the Blue Books that have been issued&mdash;I think we have passed all that now, and that the Seanad will support something that will be practical and can be carried out.  While I hope it will receive support, we are not asking you to commit yourselves very much.  If it is not possible to get a line of steamers into the West of Ireland, we can, at least, do this much.  Some steps might be taken to improve some of the ports which are badly in need of capital to make them available for large steamers from abroad. That would undoubtedly give very much increased employment, would probably start new industries that would go on and succeed, and would be an enormous benefit to the agricultural interests, because if you have a port where there are proper harbour facilities the population begins to increase, and the farmers and <Col N="206" /> people living round about such a port derive benefit from that increased population. It would also mean improved means of transit for their products and for cattle feeding stuffs.  If you can bring in a steamer of 5,000 tons its cargo would be distributed within 50 miles of that place, and the farmer will get these products ever so much cheaper than if he had to pay the original cargo charges, that is, to pay the transit charges to Liverpool, and from there to some other port to the West of Ireland.  I feel the matter very keenly; it is one at least which deserves every consideration, and I believe that if it is taken up in the proper spirit of the times it might mean the transformation of the West coast of Ireland and of the people who live there under very hard conditions.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnBagwell" hpid="Mr. JOHN BAGWELL Mr. JOHN BAGWELL">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHN BAGWELL</NameTxt>
      <P>While in full sympathy with the objective which lies behind this motion I cannot vote for it, and I hope to give the Seanad some reasons why they should not do so.  I think that this Seanad as a Second Chamber should be exceptionally careful, especially at the inception of its career, not to originate any proposals which are not likely to have some practical results fairly soon.  Now, it seems to me that the particular line of action which is suggested in this Motion would only lead to the expenditure of a great deal of time on the part of the Commissioners, and of a certain amount of public money in defraying their expenses.  I have no firsthand knowledge of ocean steamship business or Transatlantic trade, but I have considerable experience of transportation business, and transportation ventures are subject to certain common rules.  This Motion aims at bringing a line of regular Transatlantic steamers with a terminal port in the Free State.  What is necessary for the success of such a venture? The first thing is that there should be sufficient traffic.  That traffic must be goods, passengers, or mails, or any or all of these.  Take goods, in the first instance; in my opinion they must be goods to and from Ireland only, because I do not believe in any proposition as being a practical one which involves the breaking of bulk more frequently than would be the case if the goods went direct to their destination on the Continent or in Great Britain.  Now, considered <Col N="207" /> by itself, goods trade between Ireland and North America requires a special line of steamers.  The steamers need not be very large or fast.  The harbours of Dublin, Cork, and Limerick are all suitable for steamers capable of dealing with the trade which exists.  We have the Head Line, The Moore-McCormack Line, and, I believe, two others, all serving the direct trade in goods between North America and this country. I have not had any communication with any representatives of those lines, but I hazard a guess that if I were to approach them they would tell me they are in a position to handle all traffic that offers, and if their traffic were very largely increased they would have no difficulty in dealing with it, but would be very glad to see it.  This motion, however, aims quite clearly, as has been explained by both the proposer and seconder, at something more ambitious than that.  It means steamers to take passengers and mails, and to compete for the world's traffic in passenger business.  There I see a great difficulty.  Both the proposer and the seconder, as a matter of fact, did not suggest that there is sufficient passenger traffic between this country and America to make such steamers pay. They merely contemplate a share in the very much larger traffic with Europe generally.  But in that direction great difficulties appear.  The Transatlantic lines of late years have aimed more and more directly at the great centres of population.  Liverpool has declined in favour of Southampton and Cherbourg, Southampton for London and for traffic to Great Britain, and Cherbourg for the Continent.  Now, the only gain in coming to an Irish port would be the saving of time, and, no doubt, as the proposer explained to us, if different ports were used to those now being used, and if Halifax or some other far-Northern port were selected there might be some saving in time, but I do not believe that the inducements which we offer would cause people to take very long train journeys, which they do not now have to take.  I believe that people in New York, which is the natural gathering point for the bulk of the population of North America, wish to sail to and from New York.  Now, if you take New York, the distance, you will find, from New York to London <i>via</i><Col N="208" /> Southampton is 3,205 miles; New York to London <i>via</i> Galway&mdash;I have taken Galway as being obviously the proper point for making the shortest possible journey to New York and Europe&mdash;the distance is 3,153 miles.  Therefore, the journey <i>via</i> Galway is 52 miles shorter. But then you have to break the journey twice more than is now, the case if the steamer goes direct to Southampton, and I doubt if the travelling public would put up with that.  All the tendency of late years and during our lifetime has been in favour of the steamer as against the steamer and train.  There was a time when people dreaded ocean voyages. Most people do not dread them at all now.  Steamers have grown enormously in size, and have very much improved in comparison with trains.  Therefore, people are quite content to spend a day or two longer on a journey if they save themselves the disturbance of having to change in and out of a steamer, with all its attendant inconveniences.  If we take from New York to Paris <i>via</i> Cherbourg the distance is 100 miles shorter than by Galway, so that that Continental business will be still less likely to use a Western Irish port.  In addition to that the present is hardly the time for the establishment of fast train services across Ireland. I need not enlarge upon that, but I do not suppose there has been a time during the past generation which has been so unfavourable for development of this kind, and I think to fail now in an endeavour of this kind would prejudice success in the future.  It would tend also, in my opinion, to discredit this Seanad as a practical body.  The present is not a time in which a venture of this kind has much chance of success.  It may have a much better chance of success some time in the future, and I suggest that it would be much better to postpone action in favour of a venture of this kind.  If times improve, as we hope they will, you can take it up later on.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JosephLove" hpid="Mr. CLAYTON JOSEPH LOVE Mr. CLAYTON JOSEPH LOVE">
      <NameTxt>Mr. CLAYTON JOSEPH LOVE</NameTxt>
      <P>There is a port pre-eminently best situated for the purpose of an Irish Transatlantic Terminal.  This is sustained substantially when the natural advantages of the port are considered.  So far back as 1602 Elizabeth's naval advisers occupied it for Admiralty purposes, and it was again requisitioned in 1641, 1649, and 1690, and <Col N="209" /> from then onward even up to our own time.</P>
      <P>In 1805 the Navy Victualling and Ordnance Departments built magnificent stores in cut limestone, and they were so splendidly constructed that they (5 storeys high) still exist in a perfect state of preservation, and are capable of warehousing thousands of tons of cargo.</P>
      <P>It is in the direct route of all steamers making for the Mersey or Bristol Channel, Cork or Dublin, and has deep water quayage capable of accommodating the largest liners using those ports.  It has railway siding laid, running to the water's edge, connecting with the G.S. &amp; W. R. system.</P>
      <P>A very fine railway station with up-to-date refreshment rooms, Custom examination departments capable of dealing with hundreds of passengers, and all modern lavatory and toilet accessories. Large parcels and baggage stores accommodation and telegraph office, numerous hotels.  The moment steam replaced sail in Transatlantic liners Cobh was instantly selected as the port of call.</P>
      <P>So from the middle of the 18th century onwards various lines sprung into existence, to rise, to fall, and to survive.  The steamers of those lines have come and departed, but those surviving, and they are many, much improved, some magnificent, all, or nearly all, still use Cobh, one of the world's finest waterways, out and home, to and from American ports, New York, Boston, Philadelphia, and Canadian ports, Halifax, Montreal.  The largest triple screw steamer in the world, the s.s. Olympic, has frequently anchored there.  In the inner harbour, with her 857ft. of length and anchor cable, she would require a diameter of 2,000ft. for her swinging circle in a depth of 36ft. of water.  This in perfectly calm and sheltered waters the port of Cobh affords.  I have seen three large liners, 20,000 ton ships, such as the Baltic, anchored at one and the same time within the inner harbour, together with a dozen warships&mdash; two large liners alongside the deep water quay at the railway station&mdash;yet room for more.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Every navigator seeking the Mersey or Bristol Channel, and coming from an American port, is anxiously looking out for the Fastnet or Old Head.  They are respectively about 60 and 12 miles from Cobh.  He is in foggy weather reduced <Col N="210" /> to the necessity of taking soundings, and is mindful of the ocean current setting from 20" to 25" west in an easterly direction.  This current divides itself, and sets north part of it, and the rest into the Bay of Biscay, I am informed.</P>
    <P>Such soundings, taken on the South coast of Ireland, give clear indication of a ship approaching the land, and danger consequently.</P>
    <P>On the West coast of Ireland deep ocean depths are carried to within a few miles of the land.  Soundings, then, are comparatively of much less or slight value.  The danger is very great, consequently, in thick and foggy weather for a ship approaching the land on the West coast of Ireland.</P>
    <P>The distance from Cobh to Ushant is 240 miles; Cobh to Glasgow 335 miles; Cobh to Liverpool (rivers) 255 miles, and to bar about 240 miles; Cobh to London 500 miles; Cobh to Waterford 50 miles.</P>
    <P>The distance Cobh to Londonderry is 329 miles; Cobh to Dublin 178 miles; Cobh to Belfast 264 miles; Cobh to Cardiff 215 miles; Cobh to Milford Haven 145 miles; Cobh to Swansea 190 miles; Cobh to Dundee 820 miles.</P>
    <P>The port is entered by two channels, the east entrance being most favoured by liners.</P>
    <P>It accommodates vessels drawing 33ft., and has been frequently used by such for the past fifteen years.</P>
    <P>Most of the largest battleships of the British Navy have frequently anchored there, as units and as fleets.</P>
    <P>Nowhere in the 26 counties do the same docking facilities occur.  There are four graving docks, ranging from 600 feet and 540 feet downwards, with the most up-to-date machine shops.  Sheer legs capable of lifting up to 80 tons, and a deep water basin with cassion attached to one, capable of giving any required additional length when pumped dry, and when in flood accommodating alongside its quays three or four battle cruisers, huge vessels.</P>
    <P>£640,000 has been expended on two of those docks within recent years, and the capital involved in all of them would run to millions.</P>
    <P>The channel from Roche's Point to Cork quays is lighted all the way by the most modern gas buoys, a distance of about 14 miles.  The most powerful tugs and tenders, salvage vessels and plant on <Col N="211" /> the Irish coast are, and have been, stationed there for the past 50 years.</P>
    <P>I therefore respectfully submit that either as a good port of call, refuge, or terminal, the port of Cobh (Cork) has no rival in Ireland, and few anywhere else.</P>
    <P>With the wisdom of imposing a consideration of the question at issue presently on the Government I am not so agreed.  I would respectfully suggest that the Government appoint a Commission, not composed of well-meaning amateurs, but of thoroughly practical men, fully qualified to speak, and representing every branch of Irish shipping interests. Let them give their experiences and offer their suggestions.  This is the way to get the truth as to the real extent and effect of foreign competition, and how to counter it.  It is the way to learn just why our shipping has languished and been allowed to slip out of our control.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JohnGriffith" hpid="Sir JOHN PURSER GRIFFITH Sir JOHN PURSER GRIFFITH">
      <NameTxt>Sir JOHN PURSER GRIFFITH</NameTxt>
      <P>I shall not keep you very long on this very important question, although it is one that has interested me for the last thirty years&mdash;I may say all my life.  I may say at once that I am a great believer in the proposition, but we are not here to argue as to the merits of one port or another. We have only come to determine whether we shall ask the Government to institute an inquiry which will consolidate our ideas, and, after hearing all sides, come to a sound and firm judgment.  I am sorry Senator Bagwell has gone, because I disagreed with his views very materially. It is no secret that I have taken a very active part during the last twenty years in endeavouring to bring this problem before the English Government Now that the English have departed I think it is time that our present Government should really study the problem. It will not be done during the time of this disturbance.  As Senator Bagwell suggested, it will take years to prepare, and anything that will further it, I believe, must prove of material benefit to this land.  Of late years the view I have taken in discussing it is that the service must be a high speed mail and passenger service.  The state of affairs is this, that the class of vessel you are driving now at 24 knots an hour cannot afford time in port to load a cargo.  It was forecasted <Col N="212" /> some years ago by one of our shipbuilders that the time would come when the time in port would form such an important item in the cost of a ship that it would not pay you to be carrying any cargo beyond the fuel to carry the vessel across the Atlantic.  Recent practice has shown that that distinguished shipbuilder was right, and anything that can be done in the way Senator Barrington has pointed out to-night in shortening the time of these vessels in port and in passage means an overwhelming advantage from the financial point of view.  I have turned these matters into figures, but I am not going to weary you to-night with them.  They are matters which should go before this Commission that is suggested. I have the greatest possible pleasure in supporting Senator Barrington's views that the matter should be referred to a Commission set up by the Government.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BenjaminHaughton" hpid="Mr. BENJAMIN HAUGHTON Mr. BENJAMIN HAUGHTON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. BENJAMIN HAUGHTON</NameTxt>
      <P>The interest that has been displayed thus early in the Seanad proceedings in the different parts of Ireland is natural enough, and I am glad that Senator Barrington has brought this matter up on behalf of the West of Ireland.  We would all like to see the West of Ireland prosper.  However that part of our country prospers it affects the whole land.  I am glad to say that I noticed in recent months, in fact for more than a year, that the increase in the trade coming into our port of Cork is very encouraging. There are several liners, as Senator Bagwell has brought under our notice, coming to our harbour, and I heard to-day before I left Cork that vessels are coming over with full cargoes, which is a very encouraging matter.  I believe that the great majority of the people of the territory covered by the Free State Government are optimistic with regard to the future of our country.  We have at no time been pessimistic in Cork.  We are optimists in Cork, and we are optimistic about the magnificent harbour we have in the South of Ireland, than which there are few in the entire world to surpass. So much do we believe in the future of Cork and its harbour and its wonderful possibilities that within the last year and a half or two years we went to a very considerable expense in bringing from Seattle, on the Pacific slope of America, <Col N="213" /> officials to advise us with regard to the alterations that would be necessary in order to place the harbour of Cork in an unrivalled position on the Continent of Europe.  We have those plans, and they are at the disposal of the Seanad or any other body that would like to see them, and we look forward to the Seanad lending its sympathy to us in our proposals, and we hope giving practical support to Cork, whatever other part of the country it may also lend its support to.  The late General Michael Collins, whose death was so universally deplored, knew what was passing through the minds of many of us.  I have had the honour of sitting in the Cork Harbour Board for a great many years, and it is due largely to the energy and ability of our present Chairman and some of his colleagues that these things were brought about, and that we had reason to think that something practical would be done on behalf of the South of Ireland. I am glad the discussion has taken place, but I think it would be premature for us to appoint any Committee, at the present time, in the state of things that surround us.  I would much prefer that the matter should be postponed for the present.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BrianORourke" hpid="Mr. BERNARD O'ROURKE Mr. BERNARD O'ROURKE">
      <NameTxt>Mr. BERNARD O'ROURKE</NameTxt>
      <P>I rise to oppose this from another point of view altogether.  Is it wise for us to subsidise ships to take in the produce of American trusts to this country?  Could we not do something to help employment and the industries of this country?  At present we have two companies&mdash;the Head Line and the Moore-McCormick Line-both able to deal with traffic of this kind, and the other little traffic that might be sent from Ireland would not fill one-tenth of the boats going back.  What benefit is it to Ireland or to the rest of the country to have those passengers coming to Galway and being transhipped and sent across Ireland to Paris or London.  I say we want to do something to help on the industrial revival of the country, and the way to do that is to put up a tariff wall to prevent Uncle Sam dumping his stuff here, instead of subsidising ships to help him to send across the stuff here.  If you go into the shops of Dublin you will find that nine-tenths of the articles displayed there are manufactured outside Ireland. If you go to the West it is just the same. Go into any Galway or Mayo shoemaker <Col N="214" /> and you will find him mending a pair of American boots with leather tanned in England and rivets manufactured in some part of the United States.  If you go into a blacksmith you will find him shoeing a horse with American nails and putting on American shoes.  I am sure that when this scheme is in proper shape we will be able to send a horse across to America, get him shod there, and have him back by the next boat.  That is the way we are drifting, assisting the foreigner, and preventing working men getting employment at home.  I oppose this because I think it is not right to spend the money of the State on matters of this kind.  The way to give employment is by putting up a tariff wall and keeping out the produce of the States of America.  At present an American farmer living five or six hundred miles up the St. Lawrence can land his stock at the North Wall more cheaply than a Louth farmer can land his barley at Guinness', of Dublin.  I think that so long as that is feasible shipping is well organised, and we should not appoint a Commission to see that these farmers and industrialists and trusts of America should get their stock landed in Ireland. The idea is that boats coming over here should be full of highly manufactured stock, boots, bicycles, and curry-combs, and articles of that kind.  I say that we should put up a wall to keep these things out.  We should let nothing in except raw material.  We should manufacture everything that is required in the shops in Dublin if we were a properly organised industrial nation.  We can do that if our new Parliament follows on the old lines of Grattan's Parliament.  On these grounds I oppose this scheme.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnMacLoughlin" hpid="Mr. J. McLOUGHLIN Mr. J. McLOUGHLIN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J. McLOUGHLIN</NameTxt>
      <P>I also oppose on the grounds that this discussion and this scheme are altogether too premature. While opening up the West of Ireland and shortening the Transatlantic passage is very important, it is still more important that disorder should be put down in the West of Ireland, and that the reign of anarchy should be shortened there.  I am surprised that Senators should come from the West of Ireland at a time when railways and bridges are being blown up and places burned, and that they should come in here, and instead of asking the Government for more adequate <Col N="215" /> protection for railways, they proceed to spend their time in discussing a scheme, one of the advantages of which I understand is that it will reduce the amount of sea sickness amongst Transatlantic trippers.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="HonJameson" hpid="Mr. ANDREW JAMESON Mr. ANDREW JAMESON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. ANDREW JAMESON</NameTxt>
      <P>I was going to remark that I quite agreed with a great deal of what Senator Bagwell has said.  There is no doubt that his criticism of the great scheme of fast steamers from here with passengers and mails alone is very sound from a great many points of view, and the point of view opposite to it of Sir John Purser Griffith has also a great deal to be said for it. There are two entirely antagonistic points of view, and for a Commission, appointed as it is proposed here, to deal alone with that part of the matter, we know that it could do no good at all. There are a great many harbours of ours around Ireland that want attention. There is not the slightest doubt of that, and if a Commission were appointed to consider the harbours of Ireland and their possibilities, and how they can be improved, we could get ordinary practical benefits without being committed for enormous lines of steamers to run across the Atlantic, which is, considering the present state of the country, a scheme which is a little bit too previous.  I do believe that there is a crying need for Irishmen to consider the conditions of our harbours, how they are going to be improved, not only for cross-Atlantic traffic, but for traffic going from here to Great Britain.  I know something of one or two harbours in the West, and a great deal of business has been built up by efforts to improve those harbours, and they will not compete by bringing in foreign goods, for, I suppose, even our protectionist Senators will admit we must carry on some traffic with Great Britain. We may be able to keep out other countries' goods, but if we attack America we may find that out that a small island like Ireland can hardly set up a wall and exist inside the wall.  We can undoubtedly improve our own harbours, and it were well to set up a Commission to see what could be done in that way, and it were well not to limit the whole of the action of this Commission to one consideration, namely, the establishment of a regular <Col N="216" /> line of Transatlantic steamers between Ireland and America.  I believe if we appoint a Committee to inquire into the harbours of Ireland and the possibilities of traffic, not only across the Atlantic, but with Great Britain; we may easily find a way of doing a great deal of good to the country.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMoran" hpid="Mr. JAMES MORAN Mr. JAMES MORAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JAMES MORAN</NameTxt>
      <P>Arising out of Senator Jameson's remark, I may remind him that there is a Commission being formed, if it is not already formed, which would have powers under the usual terms of reference to inquire into the matter he mentioned.  I think Sir John Griffith is Chairman of the Committee, and if the powers are not sufficient already I suppose they would get their terms of reference widened to include their taking up the matter mentioned by the Senator.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamBarrington" hpid="Mr. WILLIAM BARRINGTON Mr. WILLIAM BARRINGTON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. WILLIAM BARRINGTON</NameTxt>
      <P>The only remark I feel obliged to make is that all the Senators have fallen under the impression that what I was suggesting was the immediate establishment of a line of steamers and the immediate incurring of a large amount of liability and tremendous responsibility on the part of the Free State.  I had hoped I had made it quite clear that the object I had in bringing forward this proposal was exactly the reverse.  Anyone with any experience knows quite well that you cannot get these things up in a moment. It requires a long time, probably years of negotiation.  You have to handle them with the greatest judiciousness, and the very idea expressed here is the thing I was trying to pour cold water on, namely. the immediate establishment of a line of steamers.  That is a thing I believe neither possible nor desirable.  What I suggested was the establishment of a Commission to see how a reasonable scheme could be brought forward.  What Senator Bagwell really said amounts to this, that we have been living under certain circumstances in the past on all sides and we cannot improve them. There may be something to be said for that from some peoples' point of view, but I do not think it is any argument why we should not attempt to get something that we have not had in the past, why we should not try to develop the resources of the country which have not been done in the past.  There have been <Col N="217" /> many powerful interests competing with us in the past, and naturally the British Government did not look with favourable eyes on anything competing with them. We have now a Government of our own for the first time, and it seems to me that the country was led to believe that one of the main reasons for the establishment of that Government was the fostering of our own industries, and that they will consider it an extraordinary thing if the Government does nothing to fulfil the pledge they gave.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMacPartlin" hpid="Mr. THOMAS McPARTLIN Mr. THOMAS McPARTLIN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. THOMAS McPARTLIN</NameTxt>
      <P>Would I be in order in making a suggestion in regard to this particular question?  The division of opinion resolves itself into a question of ports and harbours more than into one of principle in regard to this matter.  We have heard more about Cobh, its beauties and its ugliness and its probabilities than we anticipated.  Would it not be better that we should ask Senator Barrington to refer this matter to the Committee, which will meet to-morrow, instead of having a division on it now?  I do not think we should take a vote on the matter.  Some of us might require to know a great deal more about it before giving a vote upon it.  I submit the Senator should withdraw his motion, and submit the whole thing to the Committee.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDouglas" hpid="Mr. DOUGLAS Mr. DOUGLAS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. DOUGLAS</NameTxt>
      <P>I was going to make a similar suggestion.  I did not speak upon the motion because I do not know anything about it.  It is in the power of the Seanad to set up Committees as is done in Canada, where we know that Seanad Committees are most important. They arrange with the other House in matters of business, and we hope that will be repeated here between a Committee of our Seanad and a Committee of the Dáil.  I think it would be wise, as suggested by Senator McPartlin, that Senator Barrington should withdraw his motion and submit the matter to the Committee.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MauriceMoore" hpid="Colonel MOORE Colonel MOORE">
      <NameTxt>Colonel MOORE</NameTxt>
      <P>I suggest that Senator Barrington's name be added to the Committee.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="NugentEverardBart" hpid="Sir NUGENT EVERARD Sir NUGENT EVERARD">
      <NameTxt>Sir NUGENT EVERARD</NameTxt>
      <P>I should like to say a few words with reference to the appeal to Senator Barrington to withdraw his resolution.  I had a great deal to do with the question of a short <Col N="218" /> passage to America.  Mr. Worthington, lately deceased, and I worked as far as we possibly could to try and get a concession from the British Parliament.  We attended on several deputations over there.  Therefore I am not absolutely ignorant as to the schemes that have been on foot, but, unfortunately, there had always been a difference of opinion as to which is the best port in the West. I think this matter has been well ventilated to-day.  These are certainly very unsuitable times to bring forward such large projects.  I do not think that the public mind is in a position to grasp them now.  If Senator Barrington withdraws his motion and brings it up at a more favourable time he would do a great service, and he would get the support of everyone here.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamBarrington" hpid="Mr. BARRINGTON Mr. BARRINGTON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. BARRINGTON</NameTxt>
      <P>I have very much pleasure in falling in with the suggestion made by Senator McPartlin and Senator Douglas to submit the question to a Committee that is set up instead of submitting it to a vote of the Seanad now.  There is a great deal to be said for that proposal, and I agree to it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="AN CATHAOIRLEACH AN CATHAOIRLEACH">
      <NameTxt>AN CATHAOIRLEACH</NameTxt>
      <P>Have you any objection to having your name added to the Committee?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamBarrington" hpid="Mr. BARRINGTON Mr. BARRINGTON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. BARRINGTON</NameTxt>
      <P>I am afraid that living at such a distance as I do, and having regard to the difficulties of transit, I would not be able to attend.  I am sure the Committee is quite capable of dealing with the matter without me.</P>
      <P>Motion, by leave, withdrawn.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="COMMITTEE ON" RHead="STANDING ORDERS">
    <Title>COMMITTEE ON STANDING ORDERS.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="AN CATHAOIRLEACH AN CATHAOIRLEACH">
      <NameTxt>AN CATHAOIRLEACH</NameTxt>
      <P>The Committee itself, originally appointed, was fairly large, but substantially only four of us gave anything like regular attendance, and I wish particularly to acknowledge how much we are indebted to Senators O'Farrell and Kenny because they attended every meeting, and showed the keenest interest and intelligence with regard to those Standing Orders.  The new Committee consists of six members, and if the Seanad agrees, I would suggest we add to those the Chairman, the Deputy Chairman, as well as Senators O'Farrell and Kenny, and to add Senator Jameson and Sir John Keane to that <Col N="219" /> Committee, if they consent to act if nominated.  The Committee would then consist of:&mdash;Senators O'Farrell, Kenny, and Jameson, and Sir John Keane, together with An Cathaoirleach and An Leas-Chathaoirleach.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="BUSINESS FOR" RHead="THE SEANAD">
    <Title>BUSINESS FOR THE SEANAD.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="AN CATHAOIRLEACH AN CATHAOIRLEACH">
      <NameTxt>AN CATHAOIRLEACH.</NameTxt>
      <P>Before we adjourn I wish to say I have made enquiries, and so far as I can ascertain <Col N="220" /> from the Government, they will have no work ready for us until the week after next, and accordingly it will not be necessary for me to ask you to meet until Wednesday week, and you will only attend then if you get notice, and I shall see that you get notice.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDouglas" hpid="Mr. J. DOUGLAS Mr. J. DOUGLAS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J. DOUGLAS</NameTxt>
      <P>I formally move that the Seanad adjourns.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesGoodbody" hpid="Mr. J.P. GOODBODY Mr. J.P. GOODBODY">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J.P. GOODBODY</NameTxt>
      <P>I second</P>
      <P>The Seanad adjourned at 5.35 to Wednesday, 7th Feb., 1923.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
</Debate>