<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE Debate SYSTEM "../Debate.dtd"[]>
<Debate DocTitle="Seanad Debate" Day="Wed" Date="16" Month="Feb" Year="1994" Vol="139" No="5" DateIrish="Dé Céadaoin, 16 Feabhra 1994" DateEnglish="Wednesday, 16 February 1994" House="S" CommitteeEng="" CommitteeIr="" SubNameEng="" cnum="0">
  <MainHeading Type="Prelude" LHead="" RHead="">
    <Title>
    </Title>
    <P>
      <Col N="413" /> Chuaigh an Cathaoirleach i gceannas ar 2.30 p.m.</P>
    <P Just="Center">
      <i>Paidir.</i>
    </P>
    <P Just="Center">
      <i>Prayer.</i>
    </P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Business" RHead="of Seanad">
    <Title>Business of Seanad.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFallon" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I have notice from Senator O'Kennedy that, on the motion for the Adjournment of the House today he proposes to raise the following matter:</P>
      <P>The need for the Minister for Enterprise and Employment to investigate the failure of petrol companies to make standard or premium grade unleaded petrol widely available to the public.</P>
      <P>I have also received notice from Senator Ormonde of the following matter:</P>
      <P>The need for the Minister for Education to urge the UCD authorities to redress the situation regarding exemptions for Business and Legal Studies in Blackhall Place and the King's Inns, as the students involved undertook this course on the understanding that the exemptions were or would be available.</P>
      <P>I have also received notice from Senator Fahey of the following matter:</P>
      <P>The need for the Minister for Health to outline the deliberations of the joint working group, comprised of representatives of the Western Health Board and his Department, to consider the short and medium-term development requirements for all services at University College Hospital, Galway.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="414" /> I regard the matters raised as suitable for discussion on the Adjournment.  I have selected Senators O'Kennedy's and Ormonde's matters and they will be taken at the conclusion of business. Senator Fahey may give notice on another day of the matter he wishes to raise.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Expression" RHead="of Sympathy">
    <Title>Expression of Sympathy.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="GVWright" hpid="Mr. Wright Mr. Wright">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Wright</NameTxt>
      <P>On behalf of Members, I extend the sympathy of the House to our colleague, Senator Joe Lee, on the death of his mother, Mrs. Catherine Lee.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFallon" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>We will stand for a prayer.</P>
      <P>
        <i>Members rose in their places.</i>
      </P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Order of" RHead="Business">
    <Title>Order of Business.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="GVWright" hpid="Mr. Wright Mr. Wright">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Wright</NameTxt>
      <P>Today's Order of Business is Item 1, Committee Stage of the National Monuments (Amendment) Bill, 1993, until 6 p.m.; Item 32 will be taken from 6 p.m. to 8 p.m.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MauriceManning" hpid="Mr. Manning Mr. Manning">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Manning</NameTxt>
      <P>I wish to raise a matter with the Leader of the House which was raised last week arising from a judgment made by you, a Chathaoirligh, which disallowed discussion on certain aspects of the road transport network.  I accept that ruling but arising from it there has been considerable concern in my party, and in all parties, about the situation in local government at present.  The financing of certain authorities is under question, powers of members have been eroded and there is a clear absence of any sense of clarity about the future of local government. I ask the Leader of the House to provide time over the next two or three weeks for a lengthy debate on all aspects of local authorities.  It is a matter of serious concern to a large number of Members of this House and all parties would welcome an opportunity to discuss it.</P>
      <P>I ask the Leader of the House to report any progress on his attempts to restart the debate on Northern Ireland.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="415" />
    <Speaker pid="JohnDardis" hpid="Mr. Dardis Mr. Dardis">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dardis</NameTxt>
      <P>I support the comments made by Senator Manning and I add to them in that there is a lack of clarity in central Government also.</P>
      <P>When is it intended to debate the <i>Programme for Competitiveness and Work</i>, which was launched in Dublin Castle? Perhaps it is a throwback on the part of the Government but it seems that an increasing number of decisions and announcements are made in Dublin Castle rather than in the Houses of the Oireachtas.  There is something curious about that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidNorris" hpid="Mr. Norris Mr. Norris">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norris</NameTxt>
      <P>Back to the empire.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnDardis" hpid="Mr. Dardis Mr. Dardis">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dardis</NameTxt>
      <P>This is the place where these matters should be debated and everything up to now has excluded the Oireachtas from debate.  It is a matter of some urgency that we debate that particular document in the House.  I ask the Leader to make time available at the earliest opportunity so that this can be done.</P>
      <P>Also, I ask the Leader to confirm that the arrangements which were made last week in respect of the time allocation during Private Members' Business will operate again this week.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryKelly" hpid="Ms Kelly Ms Kelly">
      <NameTxt>Ms Kelly</NameTxt>
      <P>I ask the Leader to provide time for a debate on the problem of waste management and disposal.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PaddyMcGowan" hpid="Mr. McGowan Mr. McGowan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGowan</NameTxt>
      <P>I welcome the opportunity for Statements on the Developing the West Together report, entitled <i>A Crusade for Survival</i>, which hopefully will be taken tomorrow.  I ask the Leader if he would consider widening the debate to include a similar subject, the working arrangements for county enterprise partnership boards and consider providing more time so that both items could be taken together.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BrianCrowley" hpid="Mr. Crowley Mr. Crowley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Crowley</NameTxt>
      <P>I again call for time for a debate on the fishing industry and the impact of EU policy on it.  I also request the Leader of the House to ask the Minister for Foreign Affairs to come to the House to discuss a matter which was <Col N="416" /> recently brought to my attention, that is, that somebody over 65 years of age can get a passport for three years only.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFallon" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator, is this not a more suitable matter for the Adjournment?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BrianCrowley" hpid="Mr. Crowley Mr. Crowley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Crowley</NameTxt>
      <P>It impacts directly because of the age discrimination aspect of the issue.  It is a wider issue than one for the Adjournment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PaschalMooney" hpid="Mr. Mooney Mr. Mooney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Mooney</NameTxt>
      <P>Most Members of the House will have received the latest report of the International Fund for Ireland. This is a matter which impinges on my own part of the country.  It also has wider implications in a cross Border context and in the context of the international dimensions that are attached to the funding of the International Fund for Ireland. In view of this, would the Leader of the House make time available this session to debate this report?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelFinneranFF" hpid="Mr. Finneran Mr. Finneran">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Finneran</NameTxt>
      <P>I support the call for a debate on local authorities provided it is a broad debate which would include the topical issue of urban extension which affects local authorities.  As far as this House is concerned, the legislation is clear but it has connotations which have a national context.  In view of this I would like to see a debate on this issue.</P>
      <P>I also support the call by Senator McGowan for a debate on the county enterprise boards.  At this early stage, these boards should be identified as the vehicle by which applications for development take place rather than through a series of bodies.  I would welcome a debate on this issue.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeSherlock" hpid="Mr. Sherlock Mr. Sherlock">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Sherlock</NameTxt>
      <P>I support the call for a debate on local government.  If a debate is allowed, would the Leader of the House be in a position to state the Government's intention regarding the European charter of local self-government? The UK and Ireland are the only two states that have not signed this charter. As there is evidence that a subtle effort is being made to phase out local <Col N="417" /> authorities, such a debate should take place as quickly as possible.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WillieFarrell" hpid="Mr. Farrell Mr. Farrell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Farrell</NameTxt>
      <P>I support Senator Crowley's remarks on the passport issue. Recently I could only get my driving licence renewed for eight years because after the age of 70, one can only renew a licence yearly.  This is age discrimination. The youth and senior citizens of this country are being discriminated against regarding driving licences and insurance. May I remind the House that many Members will be coming into this age bracket when they renew their licences. It is important that Members should not support discrimination of this kind. Insurance companies are also discriminating against senior citizens.  It is something we must try and protect ourselves against, if possible.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PaddyBurke" hpid="Mr. Burke Mr. Burke">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Burke</NameTxt>
      <P>I support the call by Senator Manning for a debate on local authorities.  Such a debate should include the role and funding of local authorities and the role of public representatives because our powers as public representatives are being diminished every day.  This was evident from the speech made by the Minister for the Environment in this House last week.</P>
      <P>The Government should notify local authorities immediately of their funding for 1994.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidNorris" hpid="Mr. Norris Mr. Norris">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norris</NameTxt>
      <P>I am happy to support a debate on all the problems experienced by local government but I do not share the general grief that potholes will no longer be one of the predominant preoccupations of this House.  I found it an almighty yawn.  It is ridiculous that the Upper House of a Parliament should spend so much time drivelling on about potholes.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PaschalMooney" hpid="Mr. Mooney Mr. Mooney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Mooney</NameTxt>
      <P>May I remind the Senator that there are enough potholes on North Great Georges Street?</P>
      <P>
        <i>(Interruptions.)</i>
      </P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="418" />
    <Speaker pid="DavidNorris" hpid="Mr. Norris Mr. Norris">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norris</NameTxt>
      <P>There is a forum to raise these issues.  Most Members of the House are members of local authorities and this matter should be dealt with there rather than in the Upper House.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PaschalMooney" hpid="Mr. Mooney Mr. Mooney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Mooney</NameTxt>
      <P>There are a few potholes on North Great Georges Street which the Senator, as a local representative, could look after.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFallon" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator Norris, do you have a question for the Leader of the House?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidNorris" hpid="Mr. Norris Mr. Norris">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norris</NameTxt>
      <P>I give my support to a wide ranging discussion on this important subject relating to local authorities.  No doubt all Members will contribute to the debate.  As I said, there is a forum where Members can raise the issue of potholes but it is not here.</P>
      <P>Regarding a debate on Bosnia which we asked for last week and which is still relevant, although the Leader took the matter seriously he indicated there may be a problem about the availability of the Tánaiste.  As the proposer of the motion, I would welcome the presence of the Tánaiste, but it is not absolutely necessary; a Minister of State would suffice.  It is important that we discuss this issue.</P>
      <P>Finally, I raise a matter about which many people are concerned &mdash; the drug problem in our inner cities.  I ask that a date be set for a debate on this issue.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TomEnright" hpid="Mr. Enright Mr. Enright">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Enright</NameTxt>
      <P>I join with Members who requested a debate on local authority funding for roads, etc.  Senator Burke spoke about the powers of local representatives; I am sure Senator Norris will agree they are the representatives of the people at that level.  It is important to have a debate on this issue because the powers of local authorities are being drawn into a central area.  Most of the powers of local representatives are now being discharged from Dublin Castle in the form of different three year agreements, programmes for economic expansion and different <i>Programme for Economic and Social Progress</i> programmes.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="419" /> I ask the Leader of the House if there will be a time limit on the debate on the report, <i>A Crusade for Survival</i>?  Will it take place tomorrow?  Will it be a two hour debate?  Although I am not looking forward to it, when will Committee Stage of the Road Traffic Bill, 1993, be resumed?</P>
    <Speaker pid="MadeleineTaylorQuinn" hpid="Mrs. Taylor-Quinn Mrs. Taylor-Quinn">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Taylor-Quinn</NameTxt>
      <P>I support Senator Manning and other speakers who called for a debate on local authorities.  Senator Norris mentioned the drug problem.  This important issue should be discussed in this House.  Will the Leader ensure the Minister for Justice, Deputy Geoghegan-Quinn, and the Minister for Health, Deputy Howlin, attend?  Like Senator Norris, I believe this is not only a city problem, it affects the entire country, including the most remote parts.  This matter should be publicly addressed and the public should be alert to what is happening throughout the country.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GVWright" hpid="Mr. Wright Mr. Wright">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Wright</NameTxt>
      <P>I sympathise with the desire for a debate on local authorities. Perhaps the Whips could formulate a way in which we could have a wide ranging debate on the issues raised today.  The Minister for the Environment, Deputy Smith, will bring forward legislation dealing with the June elections; Senator Ross should not look so worried, they are only urban elections.  That would give us the opportunity to debate these issues.  I believe we could formulate a way of ensuring a wide ranging debate on local authorities.  The expertise in this House would be invaluable to the Minister.</P>
      <P>Regarding Northern Ireland, Bosnia and other issues which are being actively pursued at present, I hope to have more information on those issues.  I would like to inform Senator Dardis as regards item 4 on the Order Paper &mdash; the <i>Programme for Competitiveness and Work</i>&mdash; we will discuss that document as soon as possible.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The new time allocations are now in place for Private Members' Business. Senator Kelly raised the issue of waste management.  Legislation has been promised <Col N="420" /> on this and it should be introduced soon.  Item 3 &mdash; the Developing the West Together Report entitled Statements on <i>A Crusade for Survival</i>&mdash; will be taken tomorrow.  There will be no time restriction on any Senators who wish to speak on this important issue.  We will see how the debate progresses before we decide to bring in other issues.  The debate will not be concluded tomorrow but will be left on the Order Paper.</P>
    <P>There will definitely be a debate on the fishing industry within a month.  This will give all Senators a chance to make their views known.  I will make note of Item 9, which relates to the International Fund. Other issues are being actively pursued. The Road Traffic Bill will be taken in the first week of March.</P>
    <P>Order of Business agreed to.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="National Monuments (Amendment)" RHead="Bill, 1993: Committee Stage">
    <Title>National Monuments (Amendment) Bill, 1993: Committee Stage.</Title>
    <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That section 1 stand part of the Bill.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="TomEnright" hpid="Mr. Enright Mr. Enright">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Enright</NameTxt>
      <P>Line 23 of section 1 states that &ldquo;&lsquo;the Minister&rsquo; means the Minister for Arts, Culture and the Gaeltacht;&rdquo; As the Minister is aware, changes are sometimes made to the titles of Departments when Taoisigh appoint Ministers. Does the Minister want to change this line?  The Bill refers to the current title of the Minister responsible for this area but what would be the position in the event of a change?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatTheCope" hpid="Minister of State at the Department of Arts, Culture and the Gaeltacht (Mr. Gallagher, Donegal South-West) Minister of State at the Department of Arts, Culture and the Gaeltacht (Mr. Gallagher, Donegal South-West)">
      <NameTxt>Minister of State at the Department of Arts, Culture and the Gaeltacht (Mr. Gallagher,</NameTxt>
      <P>
        <i>Donegal South-West</i>): This is a reasonable question.  A change would involve a change of functions.  This situation arises often and questions such as this are asked.  There is no difficulty.  We do not envisage any change of functions but in the event of such a change the Bill will apply to the Minister with responsibility for this area.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="421" /> Question put and agreed to.</P>
    <P Just="Center">SECTION 2.</P>
    <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That section 2 stand part of the Bill.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="JohnDardis" hpid="Mr. Dardis Mr. Dardis">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dardis</NameTxt>
      <P>May I refer the Minister to section 2 (2) which refers to the ownership of archaeological objects?  It defines &ldquo;owner&rdquo; as &ldquo;the person for the time being having such estate or interest in the archaeological object as entitles him to the actual possession thereof.&rdquo;  What rights does this give to the person who owns the property or the land where the object is found?  It seems to me that it suggests that if somebody finds the archaeological object, he or she becomes the owner rather than the property or land owner having rights to it.  Perhaps the Minister could clarify that for me.  I apologise to him for landing it on his lap, so to speak, without notice.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatTheCope" hpid="Mr. Gallagher (Donegal South-West) Mr. Gallagher (Donegal South-West)">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Gallagher</NameTxt>
      <P>
        <i>(Donegal South-West):</i> It will not be a question of just rewarding the land owner who may not be the finder.  It is a question of rewarding the finder and the owner of the land.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnDardis" hpid="Mr. Dardis Mr. Dardis">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dardis</NameTxt>
      <P>Am I correct in saying that the owner of the property or land on which the object is found has rights attaching to the object although he might not be the person to discover or find it?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatTheCope" hpid="Mr. Gallagher (Donegal South-West) Mr. Gallagher (Donegal South-West)">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Gallagher</NameTxt>
      <P>
        <i>(Donegal South-West):</i> We have to differentiate because when it is an archaeological item it is owned by the State.  However, there would be a reward for both the finder and the land owner.  Of course, we would need proof of ownership, it is a question of title.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TomEnright" hpid="Mr. Enright Mr. Enright">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Enright</NameTxt>
      <P>If an archaeological object is vested in the State and the State is paying a reward, I presume that the reward would be placed in trust or on deposit while the persons involved prove their title and the true owners are established.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="422" />
    <Speaker pid="PatTheCope" hpid="Mr. Gallagher (Donegal South-West) Mr. Gallagher (Donegal South-West)">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Gallagher</NameTxt>
      <P>
        <i>(Donegal South-West):</i> To qualify for a reward we must have proof that there is no known owner.  It is important for this to be defined because the owner at all times of the archaeological object is the State.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TomEnright" hpid="Mr. Enright Mr. Enright">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Enright</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister is saying that the owner is the State but the section states: &ldquo;the person for the time being having such estate or interest in the archaeological object as entitles him to the actual possession thereof&rdquo;.  Is the finder entitled to the reward?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatTheCope" hpid="Mr. Gallagher (Donegal South-West) Mr. Gallagher (Donegal South-West)">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Gallagher</NameTxt>
      <P>
        <i>(Donegal South-West):</i> The finder would be entitled to the reward, there is also the possibility of the owner of the land being rewarded.  As there is no known owner, ownership is vested in the State.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="AnnOrmonde" hpid="Miss Ormonde Miss Ormonde">
      <NameTxt>Miss Ormonde</NameTxt>
      <P>Does section 2 deal with the reward?  I thought that the issue of the reward would come up under section 10.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFallon" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes, the reward is dealt with in a subsequent section.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="AnnOrmonde" hpid="Miss Ormonde Miss Ormonde">
      <NameTxt>Miss Ormonde</NameTxt>
      <P>There is obviously an overlap here.  I will wait until we come to section 10.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnDardis" hpid="Mr. Dardis Mr. Dardis">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dardis</NameTxt>
      <P>I think I understand what the Minister said, I just need some clarification. For example, in a hypothetical situation of a man working in a field whose JCB unearths an archaeological object which he takes home, given that the ownership will be eventually vested in the State but that there are parties who would claim to be owners, the land owner and the owner of the JCB, who will get the money?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatTheCope" hpid="Mr. Gallagher (Donegal South-West) Mr. Gallagher (Donegal South-West)">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Gallagher</NameTxt>
      <P>
        <i>(Donegal South-West):</i> Ownership of the item would be immediately vested in the State.  It is not a hypothetical situation but a real one.  A JCB driver could unearth an object, his helper could find it while they are working on land they do not own.  All those people could at least have discussions with us <Col N="423" /> in relation to the reward.  There is no entitlement, a point I want to underline. There is only one owner, in this case the State.  However, when a number of parties are involved, all of them may be entitled to a reward.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P Just="Center">SECTION 3.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TomEnright" hpid="Mr. Enright Mr. Enright">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Enright</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 1:</P>
      <P>In page 4, line 18, after &ldquo;object&rdquo; to insert &ldquo;and ensure its return to the owner&rdquo;.</P>
      <P>When an archaeological object becomes the property of the State, the Minister, on the advice of the director of the museum, may occasionally waive the State's ownership of that object.  I have known of people who gave items of major historical importance to the National Museum.  They later sought the return of these items but have not got them back for one reason or another.  They thought these objects were on display but they were not.  They were not aware of what use, if any, was being made of them.</P>
      <P>One may meet many well-meaning citizens who will present artefacts to the State without seeking any reward but, as Senator Dardis said, people with bulldozers may unearth an ancient historical item or archaeological object which would be vested in the State; they would generously give it to the director.  He will hold it until the matter is fully investigated. By that time, however, many of the finders may have died or have left the country.  There should be a specific inclusion in the Bill to return the object to the owner, their predecessors in title or other relevant beneficiaries.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>My amendment was put down to encourage people who find such objects to turn them over to the State.  If the item is retained by the State, they may be seeking a reward, and well and good if they get one.  However, if the object is <Col N="424" /> not of significant value to the State and the finder wants to retain it, care should be taken to return it to its owner rather than what is happening at the present time.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatTheCope" hpid="Mr. Gallagher (Donegal South-West) Mr. Gallagher (Donegal South-West)">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Gallagher</NameTxt>
      <P>
        <i>(Donegal South-West):</i> Senator Enright will be aware from section 2 of the Bill that the State's right to ownership has been extended to include archaeological objects found in the State after the coming into operation of the legislation where there is no known owner at the time of discovery.  Therefore, any object coming within the scope of this section will have no known owner other than the State.  Senator Enright's amendment would place an impossible burden on the Director of the National Museum.</P>
      <P>Where it is decided that an object coming within the scope of sections 2 and 3 of the Bill is not to be retained by the State, it is likely that it could be returned to the person who reported the finding of the object to the director.  If there is any dispute as to the ownership of the object at that stage, it will be a matter for the individuals concerned or, if necessary, for the courts to decide upon.</P>
      <P>I regret I am not able to support this amendment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TomEnright" hpid="Mr. Enright Mr. Enright">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Enright</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not intend to push my amendment to a vote.  I appreciate what the Minister said but my point is that the Minister can waive ownership of the object after getting advice from the Director of the National Museum.  The State may not be as interested in the object as the person who originally gave it to the State.  My amendment is designed to ensure that finders would be encouraged to come forward with these items.  They may have a personal, family or local interest in the object and they may give it to the State for those reasons. This amendment would encourage them to come forward with these objects.  I hoped the amendment would be accepted thereby facilitating the retention of an object pending a decision on the person to whom it should be returned.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="425" />
    <Speaker pid="PatTheCope" hpid="Mr. Gallagher (Donegal South-West) Mr. Gallagher (Donegal South-West)">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Gallagher</NameTxt>
      <P>
        <i>(Donegal South-West):</i> The Senator possibly appreciates the difficulties that could arise if we were to provide for the return of objects to owners.  If an object is of no value and there are a number of such objects in the possession of the State it might be an example of where it would be returned to the finders.  It is a matter for those who sighted and found it and those who own the land to decide to whom it should be returned.  We would be put in an impossible position if we were to enshrine this in legislation.</P>
      <P>Amendment, by leave, withdrawn.</P>
      <P>Section 3 agreed to.</P>
      <P>Section 4 agreed to.</P>
      <P Just="Center">SECTION 5.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFallon" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Amendment No. 2 is out of order as it involves a potential charge on the Revenue.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnDardis" hpid="Mr. Dardis Mr. Dardis">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dardis</NameTxt>
      <P>May I make a comment?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFallon" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I have ruled as you know.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnDardis" hpid="Mr. Dardis Mr. Dardis">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dardis</NameTxt>
      <P>I accept your ruling although the amendment involves a very minor charge on the State.  I intended here to try to devise a system whereby people would not have to pay the cost of postage.  It is a minor point but everything should be done to facilitate people who must return documents to the State and the onus should be on the State to look after them.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I made inquiries of An Post and I understand that in the case of the Department of Education in certain circumstances, when documents are being posted to Athlone, one has to pay the registration fee on the letter but not the postage.  The Bill explicitly says at the outset that there will not be a charge, nevertheless I ask the Minister to ensure that people are facilitated when returning these documents so if they find objects <Col N="426" /> there are no impediments to their notifying the State.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatTheCope" hpid="Mr. Gallagher (Donegal South-West) Mr. Gallagher (Donegal South-West)">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Gallagher</NameTxt>
      <P>
        <i>(Donegal South-West):</i> I accept the point made by Senator Dardis.  We want to ensure that those who find such objects will not be burdened with any cost.  If there is a reward to an individual those costs will be taken into consideration.  I assure the House that the director will be more than anxious to facilitate such people and if we are serious about our archaeological objects then we should facilitate them.  I accept the point but I do not think it necessary to enshrine it in legislation.  It will, however, be brought to the attention of the director.</P>
      <P>Amendment No. 2 not moved.</P>
      <P>Government amendment No. 3:</P>
      <P>In page 6, between lines 26 and 27, to insert the following subsection:</P>
      <P>&ldquo;(12)  This section shall not apply to any archaeological object which has been imported into the State for a period not exceeding two years for the purpose of exhibition, research or restoration, in pursuance of an agreement made between a person outside the State who claims to be the owner of the object and a person in the State who intends to exhibit, carry out research in respect of, or restore the object:</P>
      <P>Provided, however, that no such contract may be performed in the State in relation to any object to which this section would otherwise apply unless the terms and conditions of that contract have been approved of in writing by the Director.&rdquo;.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatTheCope" hpid="Mr. Gallagher (Donegal South-West) Mr. Gallagher (Donegal South-West)">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Gallagher</NameTxt>
      <P>
        <i>(Donegal South-West):</i> The purpose of the amendment is to provide the Director of the National Museum with flexibility by the inclusion of an option to waive the reporting requirements of section 5 in the interest of facilitating at least the temporary return to this State of archaeological objects situated outside the State and which may have been found in the State <Col N="427" /> after the passing of the Principal Act. Although such an object may have been illegally exported in the past any possibility of proceedings might well have been exhausted at this stage and there would no longer be any other method open to the director to obtain the return of the object.  As drafted, section 5 could be a deterrent to the return of such an object on any basis.</P>
      <P>The section also has the effect of creating a mechanism whereby the director may be made aware at the earliest juncture of action being contemplated by any person in the State to have an archaeological object returned to it.  The mechanism is also designed to counter a potential defence which might be made by a person to explain non-compliance with the reporting requirements set out in section 5.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TomEnright" hpid="Mr. Enright Mr. Enright">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Enright</NameTxt>
      <P>The second part of the Minister's amendment reads: &ldquo;Provided, however, that no such contract may be performed in the State...&rdquo;.  Does this relate to an exhibition and to a contract relating to the exhibition?  Will the Minister clarify that?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatTheCope" hpid="Mr. Gallagher (Donegal South-West) Mr. Gallagher (Donegal South-West)">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Gallagher</NameTxt>
      <P>
        <i>(Donegal South-West):</i> The best explanation is that if an object has been brought back for an exhibition the director must be informed in advance.  If he is not it could create a difficulty.</P>
      <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
      <P>Section 5, as amended, agreed to.</P>
      <P>Section 6 agreed to.</P>
      <P Just="Center">SECTION 7.</P>
      <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That section 7 stand part of the Bill.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="AnnOrmonde" hpid="Miss Ormonde Miss Ormonde">
      <NameTxt>Miss Ormonde</NameTxt>
      <P>I would like the Minister to re-examine section 7 which states:</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>A member of the Garda Síochána may without warrant seize and detain <Col N="428" /> ... [and then we come down to subsection (b)] ...any diving equipment which he reasonably believes is about to be used or has been used in any waters protected by underwater heritage order made under section 3 (1) of the Act of 1987.</P>
    <P>The sub aqua and diving clubs throughout the country do great work and give great service to the community.  I am concerned that this measure is draconian and I would like the Minister to re-examine it.  The divers are doing great work in our area, they are a very responsible body.  This measure is analogous to any of us going out to look at our heritage and being stopped because we were seen to be threatening the area we were looking at.  This section gives too much power in this regard.  If we move into this area we will alienate the whole sub aqua community. We should try to bring them onside as they do a lot of work.</P>
    <Speaker pid="TomEnright" hpid="Mr. Enright Mr. Enright">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Enright</NameTxt>
      <P>I agree with Senator Ormonde's comments in regard to this section.  The thrust of her argument should be considered by the Minister at this early stage in the debate.  This Bill will go to Report Stage and then to the other House and the Minister will have adequate opportunity to research the matter.  The section states&rdquo; ...may without warrant seize and detain a detection device&rdquo;.  If this equipment is found near some of these archaeological sites the section is understandable, but the Bill also states that diving equipment which the garda has reason to believe is about to be used in any water protected by an underwater heritage order may be seized. I see why the Minister has included this provision where the area is protected, nevertheless as there is no necessity for a warrant and as the garda may seize and detain the diving equipment, this provision is excessive.  Why was it inserted? I would also like to know the position in regard to people who may not be fully aware that a heritage order has been served in a particular area.  I know that many people swim off Clonmacnoise on the Shannon and that a diving group swim <Col N="429" /> there.  They would be aggrieved if because of this amendment their diving equipment, which they use for rescuing people in difficulties and water safety activities, was seized.  Perhaps the Minister would look into that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryKelly" hpid="Ms Kelly Ms Kelly">
      <NameTxt>Ms Kelly</NameTxt>
      <P>I agree with Senator Ormonde and Senator Enright.  The section as phrased would give gardaí the power to come to one's house if they had reason to believe a person had been in Clonmacnoise.  The section gives the gardaí wide powers.  The intention to protect our underwater heritage in the same way as our land heritage is a good one, but the section does not give the diver sufficient protection; it treats everyone who engages in sub-aqua diving as a potential criminal.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatTheCope" hpid="Mr. Gallagher (Donegal South-West) Mr. Gallagher (Donegal South-West)">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Gallagher</NameTxt>
      <P>
        <i>(Donegal South-West):</i> Perhaps we are thinking the same way, but when I first read the Bill I raised the same point.  The explanation I was given, which I hope will be acceptable to the Senators, was that the seizure would not be permanent.  This would be a matter for the courts, and it is explained later in the section.  The equipment is only seized for evidence.  We are referring to underwater heritage areas, and the only one of concern in the country is in County Leitrim where there are two crannógs. The equipment would only be seized for evidence because it would take time to obtain warrants and then it could be too late.  It would have to refer to the responsible attitude of our divers who would be aware of important underwater heritage areas.  We are only talking about one specific area and the seizure for the purpose of evidence.  The responsibility of the divers is important and this should be taken into consideration.</P>
      <P>At first reading it would appear that the tactic is to seize the equipment permanently but that is not the case.  At present, we have jurisdiction only in County Leitrim where there are two crannógs.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P Just="Center">
      <Col N="430" /> SECTION 8.</P>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFallon" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Amendment No. 5 is an alternative to amendment No. 4 and both may be discussed together.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnDardis" hpid="Mr. Dardis Mr. Dardis">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dardis</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 4:</P>
      <P>In page 7, subsection (2), line 28, after &ldquo;person&rdquo; to insert &ldquo;on giving seven days notice in writing to the owner,&rdquo;.</P>
      <P>The object of this amendment is to ensure that the director or a designated person cannot decide willy-nilly to enter lands or premises to do whatever is necessary to protect the archaeological object.  This is a dangerous area in terms of rights to property; from a constitutional point of view I could raise questions about section 8 (2).  I do not know of any circumstances where people can enter land without due notice.  In relation to compulsory acquisition for motorways or roadways, one is served with a notice to treat, then one is given the day and people enter.  This amendment states that notice in writing must be given to the owner that the director or designated person will enter lands.</P>
      <P>I can give a practical reason for this, other than the more serious legal or constitutional reasons, and it relates to farming. There could be a standing crop of wheat in a field which is worth a lot of money, and the director arrives with his Land Rover and 40 foot articulated lorry to remove the boat which has been uncovered by the JCB we were talking about earlier.  This section gives them extraordinary powers to plough on, so to speak, through the land.  I can accept there is an obligation to protect the artefact or archaeological object, but I do not see that it requires somebody to trundle in immediately to achieve that objective. This is to do with the rights or property and the individual.  Even the Garda do not have a right to enter without due cause.  If they suspect a crime has been committed they have to get a warrant.  To give the director that type of discretion is not acceptable and that is why the amendment is proposed.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="431" />
    <Speaker pid="TomEnright" hpid="Mr. Enright Mr. Enright">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Enright</NameTxt>
      <P>A number of people who had been looking over this Bill with me were concerned about the wording of this section.  Section 7 states that the Garda will have power to seize equipment without a warrant and under the provisions of this section, somebody can enter your lands and property without notice.</P>
      <P>Section 8 (1) states:</P>
      <P>Where the finding of an archaeological object has been reported to the Director or a designated person under the provisions of the National Monuments Acts, 1930 to 1993, the Director may inspect, or cause to be inspected by a designated person, the land or premises under which or in the vicinity of which the said object has been found.</P>
      <P>Section 8 (2) states that:</P>
      <P>The Director or a designated person may enter on any lands or premises and there do all such things as may be reasonably necessary for performing his functions under the National Monuments Acts, 1930 to 1993, including carrying out an inspection or excavation.</P>
      <P>These are quite wide-ranging powers. It would be wrong to grant such powers to the director to enter a person's land without the landowner having the opportunity of knowing beforehand.  The director or his representative should also see if the landowner is agreeable to the visit. Unless this section is amended it could lead to problems in the future.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>A garda cannot enter your house without a warrant, or enter your lands or property without a good and substantial reason such as the suspected commission of a crime or other serious offence.  In this instance a person, because he believes you have an archaeological object, may enter your lands.  Senator Dardis's amendment seeks to insert the words &ldquo;on giving seven days' notice in writing to the owner.&rdquo;  My own amendment is similar and seeks to insert the words &ldquo;after service of adequate notice in writing on the owners or occupiers.&rdquo; At least they would then know someone <Col N="432" /> is coming from the director's office and I am quite certain that most people would give full co-operation.  I do not think it is wise to proceed in this way.  This matter could be better dealt with by adopting a carrot rather than a stick approach to get people's co-operation.  It is essential to have the co-operation of farmers, landowners and others where the item is found.  Otherwise I am quite certain there will be widespread problems.</P>
    <P>Senator Dardis mentioned a field of wheat.  Many other areas could also be affected and, for many reasons, someone might not want the director to enter their land.  There would be widespread objections from members of the farming community as well as private individuals who may have a small portion of land &mdash; a house on two or three acres &mdash; for sporting purposes.  They would not be aware that any archaeological importance was attached to it, and might find excavations being carried out which are totally unsuitable for them at a particular time.  They may wish to vary the time and I am sure they would give assurances of co-operation. However, notice must be given in writing.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatTheCope" hpid="Mr. Gallagher (Donegal South-West) Mr. Gallagher (Donegal South-West)">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Gallagher</NameTxt>
      <P>
        <i>(Donegal South-West):</i> The purpose of section 8 of the Bill is to enable immediate action &mdash; and I emphasise &ldquo;immediate&rdquo;&mdash; by the director, or a designated person, on the site where an archaeological object is found.  The physical context of a find of this nature is often more important than the object itself and it is vital that action be taken quickly to preserve the site from damage. Other objects or fragments may be nearby or the finding of one object may indicate a site of immense importance. To require seven days or any period of notice would defeat the purpose of the section and increase the possibility of irrevocable damage to a potentially important site through, for example, weather, vandalism or natural deterioration of ancient objects exposed to the elements due to the delay.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I emphasise that one would expect these powers to be exercised with sensitivity and the co-operation of the land-Quinn <Col N="433" /> owner or occupier would be sought in all cases.  I expect that such co-operation would be given in the vast majority of cases.  However, the power to conduct an immediate investigation is essential. Under section 8 of the 1987 Act, the Commissioners of Public Works already have the power to enter land to inspect monuments.  The important aspects of this are immediate inspection, consultation, sensitivity and a reasonable attitude on the part of all parties.  I hope that if a field of wheat was involved there would be no question of arriving overnight without consultation with the farmer or occupier.</P>
    <P>I regret I cannot accept the amendments.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JohnDardis" hpid="Mr. Dardis Mr. Dardis">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dardis</NameTxt>
      <P>I accept the degree of urgency that would be required in the need to protect a find of substantial archaeological or historical significance. However, the Minister has expressed the hope that there would be consultation. The difficulty is that there is nothing in the legislation to give effect to that hope. It is open to the director to do whatever he or she considers fit without consultation or co-operation.  That is the central point of the argument.</P>
      <P>I can give an example to illustrate the point.  There is a major historical site called Connellmor Abbey close to my home in County Kildare.  It was an important monastery but is now almost entirely covered by grassland.  That grassland is prime stud farming land.  Let us assume that something is found on that land and a thoroughbred stallion worth between £6 million or £7 million is kept in the field.  I can guarantee the Minister that the owner of that land will not be very pleased if somebody arrives at the gate to enter that field without consultation.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>There is no onus on the director, under this legislation, to enter into the type of consultation which I and the Minister would expect.  It is not enshrined in the law.  The director can enter the land without reference to such consultation or co-operation. That is not acceptable.  We may be dealing with people who have <Col N="434" /> absolutely no knowledge of the countryside or farming and who do not understand animals, crops or farmers.  In their enthusiasm to protect what they regard as an artefact of supreme archaeological significance, they may get carried away to the point where conflict could arise. Subsection (3) states:</P>
    <P>No person shall impede the Director or a designated person in the exercise of his functions under this section.</P>
    <P>They should not be able to impede the director provided they are given adequate notice.  This provision does not give them adequate notice.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatTheCope" hpid="Mr. Gallagher (Donegal South-West) Mr. Gallagher (Donegal South-West)">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Gallagher</NameTxt>
      <P>
        <i>(Donegal South-West):</i> I will refer to the necessity for the immediate inspection of the objects which might be in the area to which Senator Dardis refers.  It is vital that action is taken quickly to preserve the site from any damage.  That necessity could be enshrined in legislation but we have an obligation to our own &mdash; and future generations &mdash; to look after our archaeological objects.  We expect people to behave reasonably.  We are dealing with archaeologists who should fully understand the problems raised by Senator Dardis and that the co-operation of the landowners is vital.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>As I said, and the Minister referred to it in his speech on Second Stage, the area in which the object is found may be equally &mdash; or more &mdash; important than the object itself.  Co-operation is necessary, if the object is taken away it does not mean that the object itself is all important, the area may be important.  Co-operation with the landowners at all times is essential and the co-operation of the owners is necessary if we are to succeed. As I said earlier, this is new and section 8 of the 1987 Act says that the Commissioners of Public Works have power to enter land to inspect monuments. Immediate inspection is necessary.  The object itself could be damaged and irrevocable damage might be caused to a potentially important site by weather, vandalism or natural deterioration of the <Col N="435" /> object or objects concerned.  I regret I cannot accept either amendment.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JohnDardis" hpid="Mr. Dardis Mr. Dardis">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dardis</NameTxt>
      <P>I accept that co-operation is necessary, that is my point.  The way in which this legislation is framed is guaranteed to ensure that there will not be co-operation. If it comes to a point where the director informs the owner that he is coming and the owner objects, the owner's reaction will be negative to the point, in the extreme, where action might be taken to damage the artefact.  I accept what the Minister says about the need to protect the archaeological object and quick action.  However, one cannot achieve that on the one hand and infringe upon the rights of the property owner on the other.  It comes to a point where the two are irreconcilable.  The owner should have an absolute right to be consulted before somebody enters property or land.  I raised the point earlier about the constitutionality of the matter with regard to property and I think there is a difficulty there.  I hope this is not another Bill which will have to be referred to the Supreme Court.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TomEnright" hpid="Mr. Enright Mr. Enright">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Enright</NameTxt>
      <P>There is a difference between this Bill and the National Monuments (Amendment) Act, 1987 which deals with the inspection of historic monuments.  Section 8 states:</P>
      <P>The Commissioners may cause such inspections, investigations and reports as they may direct (either generally or particularly) to be made by their officers, services, agents or other persons duly authorised by them in that behalf in regard to&mdash;&mdash;</P>
      <P>(a)  historic monuments and places where the Commissioners have reason to believe that historic monuments may exist, and</P>
      <P>(b)  restricted areas...&rdquo;</P>
      <P>That refers to inspection.  However, in this Bill we are dealing with inspection and excavation.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="436" /> While people might have agreed to the site being inspected, this Bill will permit excavations.  On occasion I have seen excavations, they can be quite extensive and entail a lot of disruption of normal farming practices.  There is a definite constitutional problem, not alone with the inspection but with the inspection and the excavation &mdash; which is a considerable power to give to anybody &mdash; without notice.  Somebody can enter property, inspect and excavate it.  These are extreme powers and, coupled with section 7, will cause problems in future.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatTheCope" hpid="Mr. Gallagher (Donegal South-West) Mr. Gallagher (Donegal South-West)">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Gallagher</NameTxt>
      <P>
        <i>(Donegal South-West):</i> I refer the House to section 8 (2) which states: &ldquo;The Director or a designated person may enter on any lands or premises and there do all such things as may be reasonably necessary for performing his functions.&rdquo;  Senator Dardis suggested notice of seven days and Senator Enright left it open, but if a warrant is challenged in the courts and goes through the system it could take much longer than a number of days.  Damage could be caused to the site or the object.  This is a matter where there should be co-operation and consultation and I refer again to the words &ldquo;reasonably necessary for performing his functions&rdquo; under this Bill.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TomEnright" hpid="Mr. Enright Mr. Enright">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Enright</NameTxt>
      <P>Because of the importance of this matter it will arise again and I will be pressing for a vote on my amendment.</P>
      <P>Amendment, by leave, withdrawn.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TomEnright" hpid="Mr. Enright Mr. Enright">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Enright</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 5:</P>
      <P>In page 7, subsection (2), line 28, after &ldquo;may&rdquo; to insert&rdquo;, after service of adequate notice in writing on the owners or occupiers,&rdquo;.</P>
      <P>Amendment put.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P Just="Center">
      <Col N="437" />
      <Col N="438" /> The Committee divided: Tá, 13; Níl, 31.</P>
    <P Just="Center">Tá</P>
    <table pgwide="1">
      <tgroup cols="2">
        <colspec colname="1" colnum="1" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <colspec colname="2" colnum="2" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry rowsep="1">Belton, Louis J.<br />Burke, Paddy.<br />Cregan, Denis (Dino).<br />Dardis, John.<br />Enright, Thomas W.<br />Farrelly, John V.<br /></entry>
            <entry rowsep="1">Honan, Cathy.<br />McDonagh, Jarlath.<br />Manning, Maurice.<br />Naughten, Liam.<br />Neville, Daniel.<br />Ross, Shane P.N.<br />Sherlock, Joe.</entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
    <P Just="Center">Níl</P>
    <table pgwide="1">
      <tgroup cols="2">
        <colspec colname="1" colnum="1" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <colspec colname="2" colnum="2" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry rowsep="1">Bohan, Eddie.<br />Byrne, Seán.<br />Calnan, Michael.<br />Cashin, Bill.<br />Cassidy, Donie.<br />Crowley, Brian.<br />Daly, Brendan.<br />Fahey, Frank.<br />Farrell, Willie.<br />Finneran, Michael.<br />Fitzgerald, Tom.<br />Gallagher, Ann.<br />Henry, Mary.<br />Hillery, Brian.<br />Kelly, Mary.<br /></entry>
            <entry rowsep="1">Kiely, Dan.<br />Lanigan, Mick.<br />Lydon, Don.<br />McGennis, Marian.<br />McGowan, Paddy.<br />Maloney, Sean.<br />Mooney, Paschal.<br />Mullooly, Brian.<br />Norris, David.<br />O'Brien, Francis.<br />O'Sullivan, Jan.<br />Ormonde, Ann.<br />Quinn, Feargal.<br />Townsend, Jim.<br />Wall, Jack.<br />Wright, G.V.</entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
    <P Just="Center">Tellers: Tá, Senators Burke and Cregan; Níl, Senators Mullooly and Wall.</P>
    <P>Amendment declared lost.</P>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFallon" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Amendment No. 6 is out of order as it involves a potential charge on the Revenue.  I am sorry about that, Senator Dardis.</P>
      <P>Amendment No. 6 not moved.</P>
      <P>Section 8 agreed to.</P>
      <P Just="Center">SECTION 9.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnDardis" hpid="Mr. Dardis Mr. Dardis">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dardis</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 7:</P>
      <P>In page 7, subsection (2), line 41, after &ldquo;Director&rdquo; to insert &ldquo;and the Board of Visitors of the National Museum of Ireland&rdquo;.</P>
      <P>This comes back to the question of the powers of the director and giving the director as one individual such extensive powers.  It is important that there should be consultation and co-operation as the Minister said.  Section 9 (2) states:</P>
      <P>This section shall not apply to an archaeological object which, in the opinion of the Director, is not of sufficient archaeological or historical interest to justify its retention by the State.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I propose to extend that discretion to include the Board of Visitors of the National Museum.  One might say that this is not a statutory body but there are plenty of precedents in legislation where interested bodies have been included in legislation.  One example is An Bord Glas where different farming and trade organisations were given rights to be on the consultative board.  Therefore, I argue that there is precedent for a provision such as this.  I would like it extended beyond just the director.  I take the point that the director would, in normal circumstances, probably consult with experts in the field.  However, under the <Col N="439" /> legislation, the director can decide unilaterally; there should be more people involved in decisions on such matters.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatTheCope" hpid="Mr. Gallagher (Donegal South-West) Mr. Gallagher (Donegal South-West)">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Gallagher</NameTxt>
      <P>
        <i>(Donegal South-West):</i> The National Museum was established under the provisions of the Dublin Science and Art Museum Act, 1877.  The terms of an agreement in 1881, by virtue of an enabling provision contained in section 16 of the 1877 Act, provided for a board of visitors for the National Museum, and, incidentally, the Botanic Gardens.  The 1881 agreement, which was between the Royal Irish Academy and Royal Dublin Society on the one hand and the then Department of Arts and Sciences and the Office of Public Works on the other, limited the role of the board of visitors to making annual reports on the condition, management and requirements of the museum and to giving advice on points affecting administration. The board of visitors has no day to day administrative functions.  Accordingly, it would be most inappropriate to place the responsibility envisaged by this amendment on the board.  One would have to unravel an agreement which is over a century old.</P>
      <P>The Minister is responsible for the administration of the museum and these functions are exercised through the director. The function of deciding whether an object is of such national significance as to warrant its retention by the State is best exercised through the director. Apart from his competence, he will have a wide range of advice available to him from many interested parties, including his own specialist staff of which many are distinguished academics.</P>
      <P>The Minister has signalled his intention to bring forward legislation to establish an autonomous board of management for the National Museum and has recently circulated proposals to his Cabinet colleagues for comment.  Any statutory powers given to the director by virtue of the provisions of the Bill before the House will be exercised under the general authority of that board.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="440" /> I regret that I cannot support this amendment.  The board of visitors has defined functions and it has no day to day administrative role.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JohnDardis" hpid="Mr. Dardis Mr. Dardis">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dardis</NameTxt>
      <P>It is not my intention to press this matter but the Minister said that this function would be exercised through the director rather than by the director and I take this as a distinction. I am sure the Minister will give us an assurance that the director would consult these competent people.  If an object is found and there is an expert on the era relevant to that artefact, I am sure, in the normal way, they will be consulted by the director.  Can the Minister say it would be the intention of his Department and of the director to consult with these people before reaching a decision?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatTheCope" hpid="Mr. Gallagher (Donegal South-West) Mr. Gallagher (Donegal South-West)">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Gallagher</NameTxt>
      <P>
        <i>(Donegal South-West):</i> In his initial contribution Senator Dardis referred to the advice that is available to the director.  I assure the House that the director will draw on the wide range of advice available to him from many interested parties and from his own staff who are specialists in that field, many of whom are distinguished academics.</P>
      <P>Amendment, by leave, withdrawn.</P>
      <P>Section 9 agreed to.</P>
      <P Just="Center">SECTION 10.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeSherlock" hpid="Acting Chairman (Mr. Sherlock) Acting Chairman (Mr. Sherlock)">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman (Mr. Sherlock)</NameTxt>
      <P>Amendment No. 8 is out of order as it involves a potential charge on the Revenue.</P>
      <P>Amendment No. 8 not moved.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TomEnright" hpid="Mr. Enright Mr. Enright">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Enright</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 9:</P>
      <P>In page 8, between lines 18 and 19, to insert the following subsection:</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>&ldquo;(6)  The owner of the land and the occupier of the land on or under which an archaeological object was found shall have the right to appeal to a court of competent jurisdiction <Col N="441" /> any decision taken in accordance with subsection 1 of this section.&rdquo;.</P>
    <P>The director should have authority to reward the relevant owner or occupier of the land in some way.  This amendment seeks to incorporate an arrangement to this effect.  As worded, section 10 (1) of the Bill states: &ldquo;The Director may, following consultation with the Minister and the Minister for Finance and with their consent given in writing, pay to each or any of the following...&rdquo;.  In the event of the director and the Minister not making any payment, this amendment provides for the right of appeal to a court of competent jurisdiction.  A person may feel aggrieved if there was an archaeological object found on his land and no reward of any kind was made.  In such circumstances this amendment would provide that person with the opportunity of going to a court of competent jurisdiction to obtain payment.</P>
    <P>Given the powers set out in the Bill, such as the power to take items without warrant and powers of inspection and excavation without any real authority or notice, it is important that the Bill includes incentives to encourage people to co-operate and for the director to obtain their good will.</P>
    <P>At present there is a danger of creating conflict.  Points of agreement should be settled before addressing points of disagreement. In this instance the cart is being put before the horse.  In view of this, some kind of safeguard should be provided which would be effective, given goodwill and co-operation.  Since the director and other officials and groups working for the National Museum are held in high esteem throughout the country, when drafting legislation it is important to ensure that this goodwill is not only retained but extended and expanded.</P>
    <Speaker pid="AnnOrmonde" hpid="Miss Ormonde Miss Ormonde">
      <NameTxt>Miss Ormonde</NameTxt>
      <P>I expressed concern about this aspect of the Bill on Second Stage as I was unable to ascertain if there was a framework for assessing the circumstances in which rewards may be <Col N="442" /> made, the intrinsic value of the objects and the kind of people qualified to make such assessments.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Acting Chairman Acting Chairman">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator, you may comment on the section when all amendments have been addressed.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="AnnOrmonde" hpid="Miss Ormonde Miss Ormonde">
      <NameTxt>Miss Ormonde</NameTxt>
      <P>Perhaps the framework in amendment No. 9 should be included in the legislation for assessing rewards.  I mentioned on Second Stage that such a framework did not appear to be in evidence in the legislation.  If it were incorporated into the legislation this would address the concerns raised by Senator Enright.  With such a framework the right of appeal would be granted.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnDardis" hpid="Mr. Dardis Mr. Dardis">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dardis</NameTxt>
      <P>I am tempted to get into a procedural wrangle over amendment No. 8 which has been ruled out of order, because it appears to me that if the director may, following consultation, award compensation, then, by definition, there is a charge on the Revenue.  I am proposing that this same charge should be &ldquo;definite&rdquo; rather &ldquo;probable&rdquo;.</P>
      <P>Section 10(4) states: &ldquo;Nothing in this section shall impose an obligation on the Director to pay a reward unless he is satisfied that it is in the public interest to do so.&rdquo;.  This again raises the aspect of discretionary behaviour on the part of one individual.  Surely there must be some objective criteria by which the object is valued?</P>
      <P>In addition &mdash; and returning to the amendment dealing with disturbance and excavation which was ruled out of order &mdash; I cannot envisage any circumstances where the director, not having given any notice to the individual who owns the land, trundles across it, digs it up and then advises that some compensation may be awarded.  That is unacceptable. For instance, there are statutory obligations which must be adhered to if the land was being used to build a roadway.</P>
      <P>There is an element in this legislation suggesting that the State owns everything under the ground and has the right, irrespective of what others may decide, to attach those objects.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="443" />
    <Speaker pid="DenisDinoCregan" hpid="Mr. Cregan Mr. Cregan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cregan</NameTxt>
      <P>I support this amendment. Under section 10 there could be aggravated behaviour on the part of those who own land where there is a find made. This amendment provides an admirable addition to this section as it protects both the director and the individuals on whose land a find is made.</P>
      <P>Section 10 (4) states: &ldquo;Nothing in this section shall impose an obligation on the Director to pay a reward unless he is satisfied that it is in the public interest to do so.&rdquo;  Section 10(1) states: &ldquo;The Director may, following consultation with the Minister and the Minister for Finance...&rdquo;.  The Director does not have to consult with the Minister for Finance under the provisions of section 10(4). This is contradictory.  Senator Enright and other Senators have commented on this.</P>
      <P>Amendment No. 9 seeks to address the matter by stipulating: &ldquo;The owner of the land and the occupier of the land on or under which an archaeological object was found shall have the right to appeal to a court of competent jurisdiction...&rdquo;.  Is an opportunity being created to make people aware of the fact that there is a method of appeal which will be fair to all parties involved, including the State and those on whose land a find has been made?  What kind of appeal system should be created to deal with this matter?</P>
      <P>If it is decided that the director will make the final decisions, can he do so without reference to the Minister for Finance? By inserting the word &ldquo;shall&rdquo;, and requiring consultation with the Minister for Finance under section 10 (1), while not requiring such consultation under section 10 (4), the proposed legislation is unfair.  We are creating situations where finds will be made but not declared.  The opportunity must be created for those with an interest to declare finds because many valuable objects have been found and not declared or have entailed legal battles in the High Court or the Supreme Court.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The addition to the Bill afforded by this amendment creates a fair opportunity for <Col N="444" /> all and I see no reason for not considering a compromise.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MaryKelly" hpid="Ms Kelly Ms Kelly">
      <NameTxt>Ms Kelly</NameTxt>
      <P>I would not be happy with the insertion of this new subsection because it gives the impression that every archaeological object has monetary value and it would raise the expectations of many people beyond its value.  The value of an object found on an archaeological site is in the amount of information it gives about the site, era or epoch in our history.  Often an object's value has nothing to do with its value on the open market.  If people are given the right to take the National Museum to court, there is a danger that a plethora of cases would be taken.  It would be costly for the State to appeal each case and would raise expectations beyond belief.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatTheCope" hpid="Mr. Gallagher (Donegal South-West) Mr. Gallagher (Donegal South-West)">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Gallagher</NameTxt>
      <P>
        <i>(Donegal South-West):</i> Subsection 3 sets out the criteria whereby the Director of the National Museum may evaluate whether a reward should be paid, namely the intrinsic value and importance of an object, the circumstances of its finding and amounts paid in other comparable cases.  The amount paid would vary according to the different factors involved.  Apart from the celebrated Derrynaflan court case &mdash; the problems arising from it are dealt with in the Bill &mdash; in virtually all other instances there has been little difficulty in reaching reasonable and amicable conclusions with finders when the question arises.</P>
      <P>Section 4 expressly states that there is no obligation on the Director to pay a reward unless it is in the public interest. For example, it would be in the public interest to pay a reward to a person who legitimately finds an object and who otherwise behaves responsibly.  In such instances, a reward would encourage people to declare a find.  It would not be in the public interest to pay a reward to a person who has been convicted for using a metal detector in contravention of metal detector licensing provisions in the National Monuments Act, 1987, or a person who has been warned not to engage in unlawful metal detecting.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="445" /> We should differentiate between a reward and compensation.  This is not a question of compensation, but a reward. The object is owned by the State, not by the person who detects it, the owner or, indeed, the occupier of the land.  The amendment tabled by Senator Enright would be more appropriate in a situation where some form of compensation was made rather than a reward.  However, this is not the case in section 10 which provides a mechanism to allow the rewarding of responsible citizenship, rather than payment for an archaeological object.  The reward is not designed as an entitlement or a right.  To make such a provision would encourage professional treasure hunters who seek such objects without regard for the context in which they are found.  Regardless of whether a reward is paid, such objects are the property of the State and it should not have to negotiate with the finder for their surrender.</P>
    <P>A section of the Bill states that a reward can only be paid with the agreement of the Minister and the Minister for Finance.  This ensures that a decision is not in the hands of one person.  While there is no <i>modus operandi</i> where one may have a right of appeal, it does not prevent an individual from instituting proceedings and taking a case to court where it would be decided.  It would be wrong to include a provision to give that right of appeal and we should differentiate clearly between the question of reward and compensation.  I cannot accept the inclusion of subsection 6 tabled by Senator Enright.</P>
    <Speaker pid="TomEnright" hpid="Mr. Enright Mr. Enright">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Enright</NameTxt>
      <P>It is not our intention to put this to a vote.  However, will the Minister consider it on Report Stage?  My amendment states: &ldquo;any decision taken in accordance with subsection 1 of this section&rdquo;; it specifically refers to a reward, not compensation.  I couched it in that manner because I did not want people using metal detectors and other equipment and seeking a reward.  People will usually hand over objects of importance but, of course, some will try to take them out of the country.  In the midlands there <Col N="446" /> are valuable objects which may be put in the boot of a car or station wagon and taken out of the country.  In these instances, it might be in everybody's interest for a court to decide.  I would have been happy to go along with the Minister in framing changes to my amendment to bring it into the ambit of what I am trying to do.  It is important that there is a mechanism whereby people who find objects are provided for and that there is a basis for them to obtain a reward.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnDardis" hpid="Mr. Dardis Mr. Dardis">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dardis</NameTxt>
      <P>I accept most of what the Minister said.  The question of a reward for an object is one aspect of the argument. Where an object is legitimately found, there should be a responsibility to pay for that object on the basis that it has an intrinsic value.  The Minister said there was no question of compensation, I understand that is in relation to an object. However, it is inconceivable the State should enter property and possibly do damage, dig holes or tear up the ground without compensating the owner for the damage.  When a motorway was going through my land, Kildare County Council dug test holes and for each one a payment was made, which is proper.  I cannot conceive a situation were the Director may come at his discretion and do what he likes without providing compensation.</P>
      <P>I am prepared to accept that when the Minister spoke about compensation he was referring to the artefact rather than damage.  I accept the State should be in a position to acquire these objects and that it should be an absolute right. However, there must be safeguards to protect those affected by the State's right to acquire those objects.  There are not adequate safeguards in this Bill.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>May I add to what Senator Enright said?  The Minister makes the argument about compensation.  I agree the word &ldquo;compensation&rdquo; never arose.  However, the impression might be that we should compensate people for what they have handed over.  There is no great difference between a reward and compensation, both involve a payment.  The Minister <Col N="447" /> said the person would have the right to put his case before a court and allow it to decide the issue.  However, it would be better for such issues to be decided by a person or persons appointed by the Government under this Bill rather than in the courts.  Legal costs are also faced by the State if people go to court.  Instead of spending money on compensation and rewards, I would prefer to devise the structure under this section, about which Senator Enright spoke, so that disputes between the director or the Minister for Finance and the person who makes a find can be settled without going to court. There are too many situations where the State is in conflict with people.</P>
    <P>I would not allow anyone on my land given that they can do what they like on it and are not liable to compensate me for any damage they do.  I see no mention in the Bill of awards for damage caused. Is there such a provision?  If not, there should be, otherwise, when people find objects they will bring them elsewhere.  I do not want any valuable objects still under the ground in many parts of Ireland to be lost to the State.  Senator Enright's argument is fair.  The Minister readily admitted that people have the right to go to court.  If people do not have this right, they are in big trouble.  We should encourage people to come forward with finds.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatTheCope" hpid="Mr. Gallagher (Donegal South-West) Mr. Gallagher (Donegal South-West)">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Gallagher</NameTxt>
      <P>
        <i>(Donegal South-West):</i> Senators referred to the damage which may be done.  Amendment No. 4 refers to the giving of notice to landowners. Amendment No. 9 refers specifically to a reward in respect of the object.  I believe that if a <i>modus operandi</i> giving this right were in place, this would encourage professional treasure hunters to seek out these objects.  If they are unhappy the right is there under general law for people to proceed through the courts.  The Department and the director will not take the initiative in this respect.  We have made an advance in that at present the payment of rewards is discretionary whereas the Bill now puts this on a statutory footing.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="448" /> Section 10 (3) lists the criteria in deciding whether to pay a reward: these are the intrinsic value and the general historical and archaeological importance of the object found, the circumstances of the finding of the object and the amount of the rewards paid in the State in respect of the finding of other comparable archaeological objects.  I am happy that the legislation will deter professional treasure hunters from seeking such objects. There is a recourse available to individuals who wish to pursue this.</P>
    <P>Amendment, by leave, withdrawn.</P>
    <P>Section 10 agreed to.</P>
    <P Just="Center">SECTION 11.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JohnDardis" hpid="Mr. Dardis Mr. Dardis">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dardis</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 10:</P>
      <P>In page 8, subsection (1), lines 25 to 33, to delete paragraphs (c), (d) and (e).</P>
      <P>This is one of the most important matters in the Bill.  Section 11 allows the commissioners to acquire land and monuments. I am most concerned about section 11 (1) (c) which refers to &ldquo;any land that is in the vicinity of such a monument and is intended to be used by them [the commissioners] for the provision of facilities for persons having access to the monument under the National Monuments Acts, 1930 to 1993.&rdquo;.</P>
      <P>I would be interested to know what &ldquo;in the vicinity&rdquo; means.  Does paragraph (c) mean that if a field or a building is within a short distance of a national monument we will have an interpretative centre, a coffee bar or some other edifice not in keeping with the monument?  We are again into the subjective definition of taste and what should or should not be allowed.  In my view this gives far too much power to the commissioners.  They should be forced under the Bill to seek planning permission in the event of their providing such facilities on adjacent land. It is very difficult to see how these paragraphs can be amended and that is why I am proposing their deletion.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="449" /> We are back again to property rights. Paragraph (d) refers to &ldquo;any right, easement, title or interest of any kind in, over or in respect of such a monument or land.&rdquo;  This gives the commissioners wide powers.  I accept there is an onus on the commissioners to protect monuments and ensure they are left in as pristine a condition as possible for the benefit of subsequent generations.  However, I am not prepared to accept that the commissioners should have powers which would allow them to decide arbitrarily what they consider to be in the best interests of society and the country in areas not directly related to the condition of the monument.  This is the difficulty I have with paragraphs (c), (d) and (e). Section 11 (1) says they &ldquo;...may so acquire any such monument or land whether they or a local authority are or are not the guardians of the monument and whether a preservation order is or is not in force in regard thereto.&rdquo;.  This seems to give them very wide powers.  I am questioning the powers given to the commissioners and the degree to which we can be confident, having framed the law, that they will exercise them with the discretion we believe is required.</P>
    <Speaker pid="TomEnright" hpid="Mr. Enright Mr. Enright">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Enright</NameTxt>
      <P>I support this amendment. The powers set out in paragraphs (c), (d) and (e) are extensive.  The section states that the commissioners may</P>
      <P>acquire by agreement or compulsorily in accordance with the Schedule to this Act all or any of the following...any land that is in the vicinity of such a monument and is intended to be used by them for the provision of facilities for persons having access to the monument under the National Monuments Acts, 1930 to 1993.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>This does not refer only to the land on which the monument is sited but to land in the vicinity.  Who will decide how far the vicinity extends because there is no definition of &ldquo;vicinity&rdquo;?  It sounds extreme but a large number of acres of land could be acquired, perhaps an entire <Col N="450" /> farm.  I am concerned about the powers contained in these paragraphs.</P>
    <P>Section 11 (1) (c) states: &ldquo;for the provision of facilities for persons having access&rdquo;.  If there were a considerable number of tourists coming on to the land on a continuous basis it would change a person's standard of living and way of life.  For example, buildings could be erected on 30 acres of a 50 acre farm for the benefit of tourists.  A person can appeal if they are not satisfied with the compensation being offered if this is being done by compulsory purchase but that is not good enough.  This is a particularly draconian subsection.</P>
    <P>Section 11 (1) (d) states &ldquo;any right, easement, title or interest of any kind in, over or in respect of such a monument or land&rdquo;.  Improvements have been made to a considerable number of our monuments. The commissioners and the State have great powers but what powers does an individual have if the commissioners fail to make repairs?  We have been lucky in parts of Offaly.  A tremendous amount of money has been spent on Clonmacnoise and its restoration and development is an excellent achievement.</P>
    <P>However, in other areas the commissioners have decided that certain monuments are national ones and have stuck black or green signs on them to signify this.  Everybody can see that these monuments are falling into a state of disrepair but nothing is being done about them.  Many people who would welcome the right to take action if a monument is falling into disrepair.  People are aghast at the neglect of some of these sites.  We should give individuals the right where they feel action is necessary to report it to the commissioners.  Then, if the commissioners fail to take action, the individual should be able to do so if they own the land.  As it is phrased in the Bill, the owner of the land in the vicinity of such a monument has no rights &mdash; or very restricted rights &mdash; and it can be acquired from him.  However, he cannot compel the commissioners to carry out work on these monuments.  I support the amendment.</P>
    <Col N="451" />
    <Speaker pid="MaryHenry" hpid="Dr. Henry Dr. Henry">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Henry</NameTxt>
      <P>I share Senator Dardis's concern.  On Second Stage I referred to our lack of concern about the scale or size of facilities which we put up around various monuments and important archaeological sites.  I pointed out to the Minister who was in the House that I had recently visited Filatosa, the most important megalithic site in Corsica, and the facilities which had been provided there appeared to be housed in a building about 30 feet by 15 feet.  They were perfectly adequate and in keeping with the scale of the site.  I also referred to the nuraghe in Sardinia where facilities were provided in a very small area.  We, in contrast, have recently developed an unfortunate tendency for overkill at many of our archaeological sites.</P>
      <P>There seems to be little concern about the feelings of the local people when it comes to the size of the facilities.  There seems to be no concern that facilities may be put up where satisfactory facilities are already available locally.  This is a heavy handed approach and could lead to an overkill on these sites.  Facilities which have been considered adequate may be superseded by new ones with little consultation with the local people.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="AnnOrmonde" hpid="Miss Ormonde Miss Ormonde">
      <NameTxt>Miss Ormonde</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not agree with this amendment.  I welcome the Minister's integrated approach to the local planning authorities.  The functions of the Office of Public Works and the local authorities should complement each other.  The local authorities have extended their role to include the preservation of amenities. Any buildings or archaeological objects of note will have to be looked at in the context of the overall setting.  We need to consult with local authorities and note what they say about any archaeological sites in their area.  For example, if there is a linear parkway leading from a town or village which incorporates a historical site of note, the local authorities will have to play a role in its development.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The Minister has gone a long way with this integrated approach and such a consultative procedure would overcome these problems.  There will then be local democracy in relation to these sites.  I <Col N="452" /> would not be in favour of deleting any of these paragraphs.  I would favour a consultative procedure with the local planning authority which I think would be sufficient.</P>
    <Speaker pid="BrendanDaly" hpid="Mr. Daly Mr. Daly">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Daly</NameTxt>
      <P>My understanding was that the Minister already has this power and that it would be unnecessary to include it in new legislation.  However, deleting these paragraphs would leave the Commissioners of Public Works in an almost impossible position.  For example, two of the biggest issues which have arisen in the Burren have been in connection with the closing off of national monuments. Access to Leamanagh Castle, one of the most historic sites in Ireland, has been denied because of difficulties of acquisition of access.  The castle and the adjoining lands are privately owned and if the owner chose to fence off the castle the deletion of these subsections would mean that the Minister would have no power to intervene.  The same can be said about the Poulnabrone Dolmen which is probably one of the most written about and photographed historical sites in Europe and we have had terrible difficulty in regard to it.  The owner of the lands adjacent to and surrounding the site is anxious to make an arrangement allowing access to it but his worry is that, in doing so, people who injure or harm themselves on it can take him to court and get compensation for damages.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I appreciate what Senator Dardis is trying to do.  However, one should not confuse what is happening in Mullaghmore with the Minister's statements. The lands for the interpretative centre at Mullaghmore were acquired by negotiation from a local landowner a long time ago and the Commission of Public Works can continue to do this, regardless of its size.  However, if one closes off this power to the Minister, he would be precluded from intervening in places like Leamanagh Castle and the Poulnabrone Dolmen.  The only access to Quin Abbey, for instance, is through private property.  The landowners involved are keen to negotiate with the Minister, but if he does not have any right to do that, <Col N="453" /> effectively many of our important sites and monuments would close.  I referred to those two examples because I am familiar with them but there are thousands of others.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JohnDardis" hpid="Mr. Dardis Mr. Dardis">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dardis</NameTxt>
      <P>The question of Mullaghmore should be separated from this matter because it is not the same as discussing land adjacent to a monument.  I am aware of the castle in County Clare, but what arises here is the fundamental right under our Constitution to property. To bring this argument to its logical conclusion, one can conclude that a site like Castletown House, in private ownership, should be automatically open to the public and become the property of the State because of its international importance. This provision in the Bill does not provide an integrated planning approach with the local authorities.  It says that &ldquo;the Commissioners may so acquire any such monument or land whether they or a local authority are or are not the guardians of the monument.&rdquo;  There will not be much consultation if the local authority decides it does not want to release the land.  The commissioners are in a strong position to do what they like, irrespective of whether the site has a preservation order on it.  The powers here are draconian.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The Minister, by becoming involved in this area, is interfering with the rights to private property.  One must strike a balance between this right and that of the State to acquire and maintain the monuments, which are enshrined in section 11 (1) (a) and (b).  Where does &ldquo;the vicinity&rdquo; end?  That question has been raised and needs to be answered. What does &ldquo;the vicinity&rdquo; mean?  At what point does it get to the stage where one can take a whole townland because it happens to coincide with an interest which has nothing to do with the preservation of the monument, but with putting up an interpretative centre or &ldquo;facilities&rdquo;.  What does &ldquo;facilities&rdquo; mean?  Giving the commissioners that type of discretion is the major difficulty with the proposal.  We have already given the Director of the National Museum <Col N="454" /> tremendous discretion.  Now the commissioners will have the same discretion.</P>
    <Speaker pid="DenisDinoCregan" hpid="Mr. Cregan Mr. Cregan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cregan</NameTxt>
      <P>The question of shipwrecks off our coasts was referred to some time ago.  There was a similar argument about insurance claims in relation to passing through private property to get to them.  This matter is similar in nature.</P>
      <P>Under these provisions, the Minister has the right to purchase land on any site or side of a national monument, such as the Burren, for example.  If one wants to provide facilities such as toilets for people visiting national monuments, they will have to be built a good distance from the site so as not to spoil it.  Land will have to be purchased to provide these facilities. How will that be done?  Facilities should not be built within a three mile radius of the site of a national monument.  No individual should have the right to damage a family who have held that land for the last 300 years.  It is the same for any person owning a private building. The Minister may feel it should belong to the State and demand that it must be handed over.  Indeed, the entrance, which could be as much as five miles long, would be also purchased.</P>
      <P>Senator Daly's argument regarding compensation for covering landowners is not adequately explained in the Bill.  We may never, because of financial shortages, purchase these lands but the general public will still be using them.  How will we cover the landowners?  The Minister says that all these lands will be bought, but that will not happen.  How will Senator Daly's point be covered?  In parts of the country, many farmers will not even let fishermen on their land because of compensation claims.</P>
      <P>Although I agree the wording of the amendment may be too extreme, it raises a point.  Will the Minister define &ldquo;vicinity&rdquo;? It could mean 12 miles from the monument.  At the end of the day, this wording may be tested in court. However, it is too easy to say that the courts will decide the matter, they will only make a decision on what we produce.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="455" />
    <Speaker pid="PatTheCope" hpid="Mr. Gallagher (Donegal South-West) Mr. Gallagher (Donegal South-West)">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Gallagher</NameTxt>
      <P>
        <i>(Donegal South-West):</i> This section has aroused a lot of interest, judging by the many contributions from the Senators.  I will first refer to section 11 in general terms.</P>
      <P>This section updates the provision in section 6 of the National Monuments (Amendment) Act, 1987, for the acquisition, either by agreement or compulsory purchase, of national monuments, parts thereof, and lands in the vicinity by the Commissioners of Public Works, by making new provision for the acquisition by the Commissioners of rights of easements, titles or any other interest.  Provision is also made for a specific mechanism of compulsory purchase and calculation of compensation on the basis of set criteria.  Section 6 of the 1987 Act is lacking in this regard in that it does not set out the precise procedure to be gone through by the commissioners in the process of compulsory purchase.</P>
      <P>The Bill seeks to rectify this deficiency by setting out in the Schedule procedures similar to those in the Shannon Navigation Act, 1990.  As a result of this deficiency in the compulsory purchase aspect of section 6, it has not been invoked.  Even if the compulsory aspect had been operated, it has been and continues to be the policy of the commissioners that this power be used only as a last resort.</P>
      <P>The policy of the commissioners is to try to reach a voluntary, amicable arrangement with the land owner for maintenance of the site.  This policy has been successful in the main but, occasionally, problems have arisen and no doubt will arise, particularly in respect of rights of way to certain important sites.  Therefore, while it is anticipated that the compulsory aspect of the purchase would rarely be used to buy land outright or to purchase a right of way, the option the power represents is, nonetheless, considered an essential tool in the maintenance of the inherent right of people to visit, without unnecessary hindrance, physical manifestations of our national heritage.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Section 11 (1) provides that with the consent of the Minister for Arts, Culture <Col N="456" /> and the Gaeltacht and the Minister for Finance, the commissioners may acquire, by agreement or compulsorily, any monument that, in their opinion, is a national monument, a part of such a monument, land in the vicinity of such a monument for the provision of facilities for persons having access to the monument, rights, easements, titles or any other interest in respect of the land or monument being acquired and easement over land to provide access to or service for the monument being acquired.  The subsection also provides that the commissioners may acquire such monuments or lands regardless of whether they or a local authority are the guardians of the monument and whether there is a preservation order on it.</P>
    <P>Compulsory acquisitions of monuments or land must be carried out in accordance with the Schedule which sets out the procedures which must be adhered to by the commissioners when they propose to compulsorily acquire any monument or lands.  These include the publication of the intention to acquire the land and the notification of the owners and occupiers of the property to be acquired, the lodging of objections by the owner or occupier of the land or monument, the conditions which must be met before the consent of the Minister is given and the mechanism whereby the property is acquired.  The Schedule also provides for the payment of any outstanding debts to the State relating to the property being acquired, the calculation and payment of compensation in respect of rights associated with the property and the prescribing by regulation of vesting orders giving effect to acquisitions.</P>
    <P>With regard to the amendment tabled by Senators Dardis and Honan, the provisions in paragraph (c) are already in section 6 of the 1987 Act which is being repealed by this Bill.  It is clearly necessary that the State should have power to purchase lands in the vicinity of national monuments to provide necessary facilities such as car parking and toilets and an access pathway to the monument.  This should be provided in the vicinity and not, as suggested, three miles away.  Planning <Col N="457" /> permission would obviously be required and that was highlighted last year when matters relating to planning were brought before the courts.</P>
    <P>The procedure for the purchase of land is adequately covered in the Lands Clauses Acts.  Paragraphs (d) and (e) of section 11 (1) are merely technical provisions to enable the State to acquire clear possession of lands and to enable them to provide services and access to monuments in its care.  Section 11 provides the commissioners with the power to acquire property voluntarily or compulsorily and, without the provisions in (c), (d) and (e) of this subsection, they would be debarred from acquiring property around the monuments and property for a right of way.</P>
    <P>Compulsory powers are rarely used by the commissioners and it is not envisaged that they will be used in future.  It is, however, necessary to have them available for use as a last resort.  There are sufficient safeguards built into this section and the Schedule to ensure that the compulsory powers will not be used needlessly.  The approval of two Ministers is required for any purchase &mdash; the Minister for Arts, Culture and the Gaeltacht and the Minister for Finance &mdash; and where an owner or occupier objects to proposals to compulsorily acquire his property, the two Ministers must again give their consent before the compulsory purchase procedures can go ahead.</P>
    <P>I am convinced that paragraphs (c), (d) and (e) are essential and will enable the State to acquire clear possession of lands.  If paragraphs (c), (d) and (e) were to be deleted from section 11 it would cause insurmountable difficulties and I do not believe that is the intention of the Senators who tabled this amendment. Therefore, I am not in a position to accept amendment No. 10.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JohnDardis" hpid="Mr. Dardis Mr. Dardis">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dardis</NameTxt>
      <P>I am not sure that debarring commissioners from acquiring land would be unacceptable, that is part of my argument.  The argument is not about the procedures to be adopted, what is in the Schedule or how compensation would be paid.  The argument is about what we <Col N="458" /> acquire, not about how we acquire it.  It would be far more beneficial to compensate landowners whose land was being crossed by people going to national monuments for public liability insurance. That would do far more to allow access to national monuments than acquiring land and less expensive.</P>
      <P>Landowners are fearful about people climbing fences to cross their fields to get to a national monument and falling and breaking a leg, resulting in an occupier's liability claim.  That is the difficulty involved in access to national monuments. It is not about building nice gravelled pathways through farmland and acquiring lands to put up toilets and so on.</P>
      <P>The extent to which the public should have access to national monuments is a difficult question.  It is desirable that people have access but not at the expense of private property.  There is a constitutional issue here which will have to be addressed and it may well be addressed by people aggrieved by the provisions of this Bill.</P>
      <P>Unfortunately I was not a Senator when the 1987 Act was debated.  If I had been I might well have tried to amend it.  By adopting section 11(1) and (2) which provides for the repealing of section 6 of the 1987 Act would logically follow.  However, the question is why we need to change it.  The Minister has restated what is in the Bill.  We do not agree and we would like it improved.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BrendanDaly" hpid="Mr. Daly Mr. Daly">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Daly</NameTxt>
      <P>I support the view expressed by Senator Dardis that it is necessary to deal with the public liability issue.  There have been many reports and discussions on this issue but little action as a result. I support Senator Dardis and agree that it would, to a large extent, eliminate many of the problems.  In light of the additional powers being given to the Minister with regard to compulsory acquisition, I impress upon him the desirability of dealing with this in a sensitive way because it is a delicate issue.  Compulsory acquisition of what is to a large extent private property, but which is inside public places, will have to be dealt <Col N="459" /> with in a very sensitive and caring way by the Commissioners of Public Works.</P>
      <P>In relation to the Burren, it is important to underline the fact that all the land for the Burren national park, including Mullaghmore mountain, was purchased through negotiation with the farmers and landowners concerned. There was no element of compulsory acquisition in the acquisition of the land for the national park or of Mullaghmore mountain itself.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnDardis" hpid="Mr. Dardis Mr. Dardis">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dardis</NameTxt>
      <P>There is one very simple way to resolve this issue.  The Minister should bring in an amendment to delete the words &ldquo;or compulsorily&rdquo;, in other words, land must be purchased by agreement and not by compulsion.  Senator Daly is right.  That is the best way of doing things.  The State must have certain rights in respect of the monuments themselves but the degree to which it should be able to compulsorily acquire lands in their vicinity has to be open to question. It is a question of the use to which the land will be put.  The Minister said that planning permission would be needed.  I am very glad to hear that and I accept that assurance on that basis.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatTheCope" hpid="Mr. Gallagher (Donegal South-West) Mr. Gallagher (Donegal South-West)">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Gallagher</NameTxt>
      <P>
        <i>(Donegal South-West):</i> Following the passing of the Local Government (Planning and Development) Bill, State authorities, including the Commissioners of Public Works, require planning permission for any works they wish to carry out.  I cannot understand why Senator Dardis should say it might not be a bad thing if the Commissioners of Public Works were not in a position to acquire land.  I would remind Senator Dardis of a period when neither him nor I would have been here &mdash; 1930.  Section 16 of the 1930 Act&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnDardis" hpid="Mr. Dardis Mr. Dardis">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dardis</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not go back quite that far.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatTheCope" hpid="Mr. Gallagher (Donegal South-West) Mr. Gallagher (Donegal South-West)">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Gallagher</NameTxt>
      <P>
        <i>(Donegal South-West):</i> We have to go back to 1930 to fully understand the importance of this.  Under <Col N="460" /> section 16 of the 1930 Act, the public must have access to monuments.  The Act states that the Commissioners of Public Works shall admit the public to monuments. We have to live with that situation at the moment.  People may visit these monuments and public liability is a problem. Why should not the State acquire land in the vicinity of a monument to ensure access?  If that is the situation then the State is liable for any public liability. At present, individuals cannot be prevented from visiting our national monuments and since there is a public liability problem, why not acquire the land, voluntarily if possible?</P>
      <P>We have an obligation to ensure that if individuals are not prepared to negotiate on a voluntary basis the State can compulsorily acquire this land.  If we were to follow through the Opposition's logic if we wanted to build a road and the persons owning the land were not prepared to sell the land voluntarily, we could not acquire that land by compulsory purchase order.</P>
      <P>We have learned to live with compulsory purchase orders at local authority and national level.  I am convinced from my experience that the Commissioners of Public Works would not acquire land compulsorily unless they could not agree purchase with a land owner.  It is important to have that relief valve there in the best interests of the State, in the interest of protecting our national monuments and in the best interests of those who want to visit our national monuments.</P>
      <P>There was a question earlier about the definition of &ldquo;vicinity&rdquo; to which I did not reply.  &ldquo;Vicinity&rdquo; is very difficult to define.  It depends on the monument concerned and would be examined in relation to the individual monuments.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHoward" hpid="Mr. Howard Mr. Howard">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Howard</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister's explanation has given me cause for concern which I did not have during the debate. I listened to part of the debate on the monitor.  I can interpret what the Minister has said.  This provision is a substitute for the State facing up to its obligations in regard to the public liability of landowners. That issue is being avoided here. <Col N="461" /> As I understand it, the Minister says that under the 1930 legislation the public have a right of access to public monuments and the State is bound to uphold that right of access.</P>
      <P>Senator Daly referred earlier to developments in my county.  The dolmen in Poulnabrone is an example.  Barriers have been erected to prevent access to the monument because the ground over which the public would have to travel is rough stony ground and it is likely that members of the public would hurt themselves going to see that dolmen.  The easy way out of this problem is for the Government to face up to their responsibilities on the matter of public liability, which at present rests with the land owner.  If the Government is not prepared to face up to it &mdash; and this is what alarms me &mdash; what is proposed here is that the State compulsorily acquires a piece of land across that landowners farm, thereby interfering with the free use of that farm and causing considerable disruption to the operation of the farm itself.  There is a very simple way around this problem. The State should accept responsibility or put in place the necessary mechanism to cover public liability of landowners.  It is far easier than giving the State the authority to compulsorily acquire a piece of land across a farm, disrupting the operation of the entire farm and depriving the owner of the use and enjoyment of that land.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The Minister has also stated that the last thing the State will do is compulsorily acquire the property.  In my constituency &mdash; I do not know if Senator Daly will agree with me &mdash; there are examples where the State has been anything but sensitive in its dealings in regard to land. Because of that I want to warn the Minister who comes from a rural constituency that he is sowing seeds which will cause enormous dissension unless this matter is handled in a very sensitive way.  There is an easy way out of this and I have told the Minister what it is, but it worries me that by going down this road now he is implying, rightly or wrongly, that the State is more or less opting out of its obligation to look after the liability of the <Col N="462" /> landowner and using this legislation as a substitute for it.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatTheCope" hpid="Mr. Gallagher (Donegal South-West) Mr. Gallagher (Donegal South-West)">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Gallagher</NameTxt>
      <P>
        <i>(Donegal South-West):</i> I stated that as far as national monuments in State care were concerned, under the 1930 Act the public must have access to these monuments.  To follow Senator Howard's logic, is he suggesting that a member of the public visits one of those monuments and damage is caused or if the individual is hurt climbing over fences to get to the monument, that the State should accept public liability?  We are trying to regularise this to acquire the area of land that is necessary in the vicinity of the monument and to negotiate as far as possible with the land owner to acquire that land voluntarily if possible. However, if that is not possible, there is a compulsory aspect to this legislation. At all times the policy is to try to reach a voluntary and amicable agreement with the landowner.  We are regularising what was a serious situation so that one may gain access to a national monument in the State's care from any part of the circumference of the area around the monument.  That would regularise the situation to purchase an area of land around a monument and then the State would be responsible for public liability.  This should be a welcome development, but I understand the reference made by Senator Dardis to its compulsory aspect, which is still necessary.</P>
      <P>We, as local authority members, could not say that the local authority should not have the right to acquire land by compulsory purchase order to build a road through an area.  This compulsory clause must be included if such a development is necessary.  I assure the House that the State and the Commissioners of Public Works have at all times tried to acquire land on a voluntary basis.  I will not agree to amendment No. 10 because it would create a serious situation.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnDardis" hpid="Mr. Dardis Mr. Dardis">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dardis</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not want to discuss this matter interminably.  I am fascinated by the statement in the explanatory memorandum which says these proposals will not cost the Exchequer any money.  Some <Col N="463" /> of the amendments were ruled out of order because they might have posed a charge on the Exchequer.  It seems we are becoming involved in an area of substantial cost if the State intends to acquire land around these national monuments.</P>
      <P>If we read Lord Killanin's <i>Shell Guide to Ireland</i>, we will see that almost every townland has a national monument.  It is inconceivable that the State will acquire land around all these monuments to allow access to them.  We are talking about the primary national monuments which many people visit.  It would be cheaper and more effective in terms of allowing access if landowners were indemnified for public liability insurance.  As every rural Senator knows, this is a major bone of contention.  It has got to the point in Senator Daly's constituency where landowners will not allow people, irrespective of what it says in the 1930 Act, to cross their land to see these monuments because of the liability involved if someone falls and is injured.  That is the way to address this area and we are concentrating on this to the exclusion of the facilities.  This section gives the Commissioners of Public Works too much power in determining what they might consider to be desirable in the vicinity of a national monument and, as a result, some undesirable edifices could be placed around national monuments.  Therefore, I will press this amendment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DenisDinoCregan" hpid="Mr. Cregan Mr. Cregan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cregan</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister is giving the impression that this is not a question of finance.  Section 11 states that the &ldquo;Commissioners may, with the consent of the Minister and the Minister for Finance, acquire by agreement...&rdquo;, but one does not acquire something without purchasing or offering a reward or compensation. Everything in this section will involve a certain amount of expenditure and anyone who gives the impression that we cannot speak about money is crazy.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I cannot believe the Minister is giving the impression that the Department or the Commissioners of Public Works will not consider the idea of purchasing property &mdash; for example, a pathway.  The pathway <Col N="464" /> to a monument may be four miles long and providing a roadway may be in the interests of the common good.  I do not disagree with the Minister when he says we want people to look at our national monuments and if they cannot get to them we must use a compulsory purchase order.</P>
    <P>I cannot understand why the Government is not prepared to consider public liability for people who want to cross private land to get to a monument, this would be cheaper for the taxpayer.  What is wrong with this idea?  There is no reason it cannot be done.  We are prepared to spend millions of pounds to purchase land but we will not give a farmer public liability cover at a lower cost to the public.  I ask the Minister who is trying to fool whom?</P>
    <P>There are national monuments which are of educational benefit to our young people but they cannot visit them because the farmer will not let them cross his land in case they make a claim against him and try to get something which belongs to the country.  The farmer is right.  I would do the same if people were visiting a wreck on the shore and they had to cross my land because I am responsible while they are on my land.  Who is trying to fool whom?</P>
    <P>Surely the Government could cover people against public claims; it is only right to do so.  Why should we spend millions of pounds to purchase land to get from one part of a monument to another?  This is a serious argument and there is no logic in having wired fences which prevent people from crossing ditches. If people want to cross a ditch to see something on the other side of a farm and if they hurt themselves in the process, they should not be able to claim off a landowner.  We must provide a general policy which will cover the nation against any such claim.  The claim cannot be very big if people are crossing rough land but, if it is, we should be able to cover it with the number of people employed in the courts to defend the nation.  I see no reason there should not be private liability cover.  I cannot accept what is in this Bill because I hold the opposite view.</P>
    <Col N="465" />
    <Speaker pid="PatTheCope" hpid="Mr. Gallagher (Donegal South-West) Mr. Gallagher (Donegal South-West)">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Gallagher</NameTxt>
      <P>
        <i>(Donegal South-West):</i> We are trying to facilitate the people who want to visit national monuments in State care and to regularise the situation.  If, for example, there is a monument in the centre of ten or 20 acres, should we allow access from the entire circumference of that area and say the State is liable for any accident which takes place there, regardless of whether one is going up hills and down dales or trying to cross rivers? We are trying to allow access to monuments so that there will be no question of our landowners denying people the right of access, which they already have.</P>
      <P>We are trying to make entrances to our national monuments which will entice people to visit them.  We will be unable to entice people to visit these monuments if they must cross fields and hedges.  I put it to the House that we would be able to entice more people to visit our national monuments and to be proud of them if we had a walkway or drive to them with all the necessary facilities.  That is what we are trying to do and I am surprised to hear some Senators say the opposite.</P>
      <P>Public liability, to which Senator Dardis referred, is a serious matter.  The House will be aware that the Law Reform Commission produced a report on public liability.  The introduction of legislation to improve the position in relation to public liability is a matter for the Minister for Equality and Law Reform, Deputy Taylor, and I accept the necessity for this. I am not being difficult on this matter; in fact, I would be the most amicable person here if I thought we could improve the situation, but I do not believe this amendment will improve it and I ask the House to accept that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DenisDinoCregan" hpid="Mr. Cregan Mr. Cregan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cregan</NameTxt>
      <P>I understand what the Minister is saying.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryHenry" hpid="Dr. Henry Dr. Henry">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Henry</NameTxt>
      <P>Will we have to accept liability if we own these public pathways to the monuments?  Will this be less expensive than the liability suggested by Senator Cregan and Senator Dardis?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatTheCope" hpid="Mr. Gallagher (Donegal South-West) Mr. Gallagher (Donegal South-West)">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Gallagher</NameTxt>
      <P>
        <i>(Donegal South-West):</i> Yes, if there are pathways it will be the <Col N="466" /> responsibility of the commissioners to accept public liability but it would be much more structured and less chances of claims in that respect than if you were trying to scale ten-foot walls to get into areas.  Quite honestly, I believe that this is&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnDardis" hpid="Mr. Dardis Mr. Dardis">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dardis</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister is a fair man if he can scale that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatTheCope" hpid="Mr. Gallagher (Donegal South-West) Mr. Gallagher (Donegal South-West)">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Gallagher</NameTxt>
      <P>
        <i>(Donegal South-West):</i> I suppose if Senator Dardis thought there would be a vote in it he would do exactly the same.  I am not going from the sublime to the ridiculous, I am being realistic and practical about this.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DenisDinoCregan" hpid="Mr. Cregan Mr. Cregan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cregan</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister is not going from the sublime to the ridiculous but the Bill is.  While the Minister is being fair, the Bill is not and that is important because its provisions will be enshrined in law.  I agree with the Minister because he wants to create pathways through which people can walk.  Is the Minister prepared to say that there could be common law pathways, in other words rights of way?  There is no reason to destroy a whole area through which people want to walk on a Sunday to visit to a national monument, and which, for the rest of the week, nobody is using, yet it belongs to the State.  Why can the Minister not put in a provision to create a common right thus covering public liability? Of course we should have pathways but we should not make demands on a farmer or his family in whose name the farm has been owned for the last 300 or 400 years.</P>
      <P>The wording of section 11 (1) (c) which mentions &ldquo;any land that is in the vicinity of such a monument&rdquo; is very important because such land could be purchased. We could create an opportunity for people to say that they might as well take the lot because it is no good to him.  Could that happen?  The wording should be: &ldquo;any opportunity for pathways to be created between both parties, and public liability, should be covered by the State&rdquo;.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>There would be opportunities for the Government, commissioner or Ministers <Col N="467" /> for Finance to purchase enormous amounts of land irrelevant to national monuments.  That is the danger. However, it is clear that the Minister does not want that kind of opportunity to be given to a commissioner.  Neither do I.  Nevertheless, pathways should provide a common right for people to walk at weekends or in the summer and the State should cover public liability to make sure everybody has that right.</P>
    <P>Farmers and others living where national monuments are situated want to help in every possible way but we should also help them in every possible way.  We should not create a situation in this Bill where farmers' rights are infringed.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatTheCope" hpid="Mr. Gallagher (Donegal South-West) Mr. Gallagher (Donegal South-West)">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Gallagher</NameTxt>
      <P>
        <i>(Donegal South-West):</i> That may appear to be the situation but, looking back at the history of the commissioners of public works, practically all acquisition of land is as a result of negotiation on a voluntary basis.  Section 11 (1) provides that any of the following may be acquired by agreement or compulsorily: the monument itself; part of a monument and land in the vicinity of such a monument.  We might also negotiate in relation to rights of way, easements, titles or any other interests in respect of the land or monument being acquired.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Senator Cregan referred to the damage that could be caused and taking away rights.  Let us take a practical situation where thousands of people are crossing through a field.  Is he suggesting that wheat and potatoes will grow in <Col N="468" /> the area?  Damage will be caused there anyway.  We will compensate the farmer to acquire that land whether as a right of way or purchasing it outright.  We are being very reasonable and the views I express &mdash; those of the vast majority in the House &mdash; are reflected in the Bill. Negotiation will be extremely important. It would narrow down the question of public liability and, indeed, people visiting monuments would be covered by public liability which is not now the case. We are being reasonable, practical and realistic.</P>
    <P>I do not underestimate, or doubt the sincerity of Senators who contributed and who may have another view.  However, they should look at the practicalities.  We accept it being put to a vote but in future they may say I was right.  The consent of the Minister for Finance will be required before any compulsory acquisition. Given the responsibilities of the Minister for Finance of the day, it is unrealistic to expect him to preside over the unnecessary acquisition of vast tracts of land.  If we were to concede public liability cover in the vicinity of a national monument, I shudder to think of the result.  Claims could be quite expensive on the State, perhaps much more expensive than acquiring tracts of land.</P>
    <Speaker pid="WillieFarrell" hpid="Acting Chairman (Mr. Farrell) Acting Chairman (Mr. Farrell)">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman (Mr. Farrell)</NameTxt>
      <P>Is amendment No. 10 being pressed?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnDardis" hpid="Mr. Dardis Mr. Dardis">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dardis</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes.</P>
      <P>Question put: &ldquo;That the words proposed to be deleted stand.&rdquo;</P>
      <P Just="Center">The Committee divided: Tá, 29; Níl, 15.</P>
      <P Just="Center">Tá</P>
    </Speaker>
    <table pgwide="1">
      <tgroup cols="2">
        <colspec colname="1" colnum="1" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <colspec colname="2" colnum="2" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry rowsep="1">Byrne, Seán.<br />Calnan, Michael.<br />Cashin, Bill.<br />Daly, Brendan.<br />Farrell, Willie.<br />Finneran, Michael.<br />Fitzgerald, Tom.<br />Gallagher, Ann.<br />Hillery, Brian.<br />Kelleher, Billy.<br />Kelly, Mary.<br />Kiely, Dan.
<Col N="469" />Ormonde, Ann.<br />Roche, Dick.<br />Townsend, Jim.</entry>
            <entry rowsep="1">Kiely, Rory.<br />Lanigan, Mick.<br />Lydon, Don.<br />McGennis, Marian.<br />McGowan, Paddy.<br />Magner, Pat.<br />Maloney, Sean.<br />Mooney, Paschal.<br />Mullooly, Brian.<br />O'Brien, Francis.<br />O'Kennedy, Michael.<br />O'Sullivan, Jan.
<Col N="470" />Wall, Jack.<br />Wright, G. V.<br /></entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
    <P Just="Center">Níl</P>
    <table pgwide="1">
      <tgroup cols="2">
        <colspec colname="1" colnum="1" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <colspec colname="2" colnum="2" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry rowsep="1">Burke, Paddy.<br />Cotter, Bill.<br />Cregan, Denis (Dino).<br />D'Arcy, Michael.<br />Dardis, John.<br />Enright, Thomas W.<br />Farrelly, John V.<br />Henry, Mary.</entry>
            <entry rowsep="1">Honan, Cathy.<br />Howard, Michael.<br />Lee, Joe.<br />Manning, Maurice.<br />Naughten, Liam.<br />Neville, Daniel.<br />Ross, Shane P.N.<br /></entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
    <P Just="Center">Tellers: Tá, Senators Mullooly and Magner; Níl, Senators Dardis and Henry.</P>
    <P>Question declared carried.</P>
    <P>Amendment declared lost.</P>
    <P>Government amendment No. 11:</P>
    <P>In page 8, subsection (1) (e), line 32, to delete &ldquo;any such&rdquo; and substitute &ldquo;such a&rdquo;.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatTheCope" hpid="Mr. Gallagher (Donegal South-West) Mr. Gallagher (Donegal South-West)">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Gallagher</NameTxt>
      <P>
        <i>(Donegal South-West):</i> This is a technical amendment designed to clarify section 11 (1) (e): &ldquo;any easement over land to provide access to or service for a monument&rdquo; relates to any national monument or part thereof, regardless of whether the acquisition at issue takes place under section 11, including access to monuments already in State ownership or care.  It is a technical amendment.  In effect, it means that if we want to acquire easement over land to provide access and we do not have this amendment, we can only provide this to a monument acquired under section 11 after the enactment of this Bill.  We are anxious to ensure that this legislation will also cover monuments which were acquired prior to it.  A typical case in point would be Dún Aonghusa on the Aran Islands.  If we were anxious to acquire a stretch of land for entry to the monument and we did not insert these words in substitution it would create a problem.  The amendment is deleting &ldquo;any such&rdquo; and substituting &ldquo;such a&rdquo;.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BrendanDaly" hpid="Mr. Daly Mr. Daly">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Daly</NameTxt>
      <P>May I raise one point arising from section 11 of the 1987 Act which contains the definition of a national monument?  The definition excludes a building or a part of a building which would be used for ecclesiastical purposes. That section creates difficulties in many respects in relation to some of our most historic and important monuments, I refer in particular to monuments on Scattery Island in the Shannon Estuary and to St. Mary's Cathedral in Limerick, where the Commissioners of Public Works were excluded form providing assistance because ecclesiastical services were taking place in the building which was a national monument.</P>
      <P>I asked on Second Stage whether the Minister would put down an amendment to clarify this matter, by changing the definition under section 11 of the 1987 Act or by changing the Churches Act, or by bringing in some arrangement whereby buildings which are national monuments would not be excluded from financial support because ecclesiastical services were taking place there.  I am aware that this is a complicated issue and would need more detailed consideration by the Minister.  I raised it on Second Stage in the hope that on Committee Stage the Minister would find a way to deal with it.  There are constitutional and other issues involved.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I raise the matter again in the hope that the Minister might at a future date find a way to deal with it.  The issue <Col N="471" /> creates some anxiety in relation to Scattery Island in the sense that, if restoration takes place in some of the historic buildings on the island, because ecclesiastical services take place there, it could be excluded from support from the Commissioners of Public Works.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatTheCope" hpid="Mr. Gallagher (Donegal South-West) Mr. Gallagher (Donegal South-West)">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Gallagher</NameTxt>
      <P>
        <i>(Donegal South-West):</i> Senator Daly raised this matter on Second Stage.  Under the National Monuments Acts a building used habitually for ecclesiastical purposes cannot be a national monument.  This has consistently been the position since 1930 and it is too broad an issue to deal with under this Bill.  It could be considered in connection with future amendments to the National Monuments Acts.</P>
      <P>There is also a possibility of constitutional issues.  The Constitution provides that the State cannot subvert any religion and it might be unconstitutional to provide that the State could provide financial support for a church which is in use for religious purposes.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BrendanDaly" hpid="Mr. Daly Mr. Daly">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Daly</NameTxt>
      <P>I would accept that reply if we could be satisfied that it would not be put on the long finger and that we would not find ourselves in the same position when those amendments are being looked at.  This is a critical issue and is being followed closely by people involved in the historic and cultural organisations who are interested in the development and preservation of some of these important sites.  I refer again to Scattery Island which is being developed by the Kilrush Community Development Company and SFADCo in conjunction with the Commissioners of Public Works.  This provision may cause difficulty in undertaking important restoration and preservation work on the island buildings.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatTheCope" hpid="Mr. Gallagher (Donegal South-West) Mr. Gallagher (Donegal South-West)">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Gallagher</NameTxt>
      <P>
        <i>(Donegal South-West):</i> There are never any guarantees in life, but as far as possible I can assure the Senator that all Senators' views are taken on board and taken seriously by the Department.  I assure the Senator and the House that we will look at this matter but <Col N="472" /> without giving any guarantees.  We would have to look at the constitutional aspects and that would entail an in-depth study.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BrendanDaly" hpid="Mr. Daly Mr. Daly">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Daly</NameTxt>
      <P>I am sure that the Minister of State will come across some cases like this in his forthcoming campaign.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatTheCope" hpid="Mr. Gallagher (Donegal South-West) Mr. Gallagher (Donegal South-West)">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Gallagher</NameTxt>
      <P>
        <i>(Donegal South-West):</i> I am bigger than that now.  I would not want to focus in on specific areas.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnDardis" hpid="Mr. Dardis Mr. Dardis">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dardis</NameTxt>
      <P>Are we having an adjournment debate for the Minister of State?</P>
      <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
      <P>Section 11, as amended, agreed to.</P>
      <P Just="Center">SECTION 12.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnDardis" hpid="Mr. Dardis Mr. Dardis">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dardis</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 12:</P>
      <P>In page 8, subsection (1), line 40, to delete &ldquo;may&rdquo; and substitute &ldquo;shall, in consultation with such voluntary, scholarly and conservation bodies as the Minister shall from time to time appoint,&rdquo;.</P>
      <P>The genesis for this amendment is An Taisce who wrote to the Minister for Arts, Culture and the Gaeltacht, Deputy M. Higgins, in November.  That body asked that consideration be given to the establishment of a national register.  The Programme for a Partnership Government says the Government will undertake a full audit of national monument sites and that is why my amendment uses the word &ldquo;shall&rdquo; rather than &ldquo;may&rdquo;.  The Bill says the commissioners &ldquo;may&rdquo; establish and maintain a record of monuments and places.  The word &ldquo;shall&rdquo; confers a degree of compulsion consistent with the commitment in the programme for Government.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>While An Taisce welcomed the intention to put the record on a statutory basis it regards the Royal Society of Antiquarians as a body which could provide research facilities for those interested in historical and archaeological structures on a nationwide basis, similar to the Historic <Col N="473" /> Buildings and Ancient Monuments Council in Britain.  While welcoming the provision, An Taisce urged consideration of a national archive which could provide for input by voluntary, scholarly or conservation bodies.  That is why I tabled the amendment.  It is reasonable because bodies within the State are anxious to help in these matters and could make a valuable input, even at local level.  There are precedents in other legislation for allowing outside, non-statutory agencies to be involved with bodies established under law.  This would be a case where they might usefully be employed to assist the State in drawing up a record.  Perhaps the Minister could explain if there is a difference in law between maintaining a record of monuments and a register of monuments.  I recommend to the Minister that bodies expert in the field are consulted when making such a record.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MaryHenry" hpid="Dr. Henry Dr. Henry">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Henry</NameTxt>
      <P>I support this amendment because nothing can be more valuable than involving voluntary and local bodies.  Without their expertise and enthusiasm for what one wants to conserve and record, there can be difficulties. These bodies could be of assistance to the commissioners and they would provide expertise at little or no cost.  I would be glad if the Minister could accept the amendment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatTheCope" hpid="Mr. Gallagher (Donegal South-West) Mr. Gallagher (Donegal South-West)">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Gallagher</NameTxt>
      <P>
        <i>(Donegal South-West):</i> The intention to establish a statutory heritage council was announced in the programme for Government and it is hoped to bring the necessary legislation forward at an early date.  It is intended that the council will have broad ranging functions in relation to all aspects of heritage, including national monuments and that body will provide the type of advice sought by the Senator.  It would only lead to confusion and a waste of resources if a separate body was appointed to advise on this section of the Bill.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The substitution of the word &ldquo;shall&rdquo; for &ldquo;may&rdquo; could give rise to practical difficulties, particularly in maintenance of records.  It is expected the records which already exist will need to be revised <Col N="474" /> from time to time in the light of new knowledge; that is, as new monuments are discovered or perhaps when features now considered to be monuments are proven on closer inspection to be natural features.  This will inevitably cause delays in publishing revised maps, but in such understandable circumstances, the commissioners could be deemed to be in breach of their duties if the word &ldquo;shall&rdquo; is included in this section.</P>
    <P>The 1987 Act states that the owner of each monument must be notified before it is put in the register.  There are 150,000 such monuments so it would create practical difficulties for us.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JohnDardis" hpid="Mr. Dardis Mr. Dardis">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dardis</NameTxt>
      <P>I thought the Government was committed to openness.  If there are expert agencies in the country who are available and want to help, they would be allowed to make an input if there was a spirit of openness in Government.</P>
      <P>My point in using the word &ldquo;shall&rdquo; is precisely that it creates a compulsion to do what is stated in the Programme for a Partnership Government.  It is quite explicit; it says: &ldquo;We will undertake a full national audit of archaeological sites.&rdquo; Using &ldquo;shall&rdquo; involves a degree of compulsion and prevents it being discretionary. It will not let this provision lie in the legislation for years before the commissioners ultimately decide, at their discretion, to compile a record.  One distasteful aspect of this thinking is that it implies the repository of knowledge resides with the commissioners and that those in Government and outside that closed circuit have no input, no expertise and no legitimate view on how the monuments should be developed and registered.</P>
      <P>I will not reopen the debate on lands in the vicinity of monuments in section 11.  However, we have established that the Government will acquire lands in the vicinity of 150,000 monuments which reaffirms the point that dealing with public liability would have been much cheaper than putting footpaths into all these monuments.  That will not happen in practice but it is the scale involved.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>If we are serious about open Government, <Col N="475" /> consultation and subsidiarity, as it is described in Europe, there is no legitimate argument that bodies who have expertise and knowledge and wish to help should not be involved in this process.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatTheCope" hpid="Mr. Gallagher (Donegal South-West) Mr. Gallagher (Donegal South-West)">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Gallagher</NameTxt>
      <P>
        <i>(Donegal South-West):</i> A full record has already been completed. In keeping it up to date, there has been consultation between the Office of Public Works and other bodies.  All sources are used to keep our records up to date.  There is no need to put this in legislation because it is done as a matter of course.</P>
      <P>Over the past two decades &mdash; and especially the last ten years &mdash; a preliminary but comprehensive national record, detailing where it is believed monuments and monument places known as sites are located, has been compiled on survey maps by the Office of Public Works.  Those details are held on individual files located in its office.  The maps are constructed on a county by county basis and the nationwide survey was completed in 1992.  The detailed maps have been distributed to all local planning authorities and are already open for inspection to those who wish to know where monuments are located.</P>
      <P>These maps are known as sites and monuments records or SMRs.  About 150,000 such monuments are recorded and this section provides for a formal exhibition of the SMRs in each county in a manner to be prescribed by the Minister. This will provide landowners with the opportunity to establish if there are any monuments on their property.  This is transparent and reflects the openness of Government.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnDardis" hpid="Mr. Dardis Mr. Dardis">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dardis</NameTxt>
      <P>We now discover that we have already what we are seeking to establish in law.  The question arises why it is here in the first place if it is already established.  What is the point of that?  Subsection (2) states that &ldquo;The Commissioners shall cause...to be published&rdquo;. First they &ldquo;may&rdquo; decide and then <Col N="476" /> they &ldquo;shall publish&rdquo;.  If it is a commitment in the Programme for Government, the word &ldquo;shall&rdquo; should be there and it should be established in law.  In terms of consultation, we are now told that we have already consulted all these bodies. If we this has already been done, what is the danger of putting it into the legislation that we continue to consult them?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFallon" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Is the amendment being pressed?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnDardis" hpid="Mr. Dardis Mr. Dardis">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dardis</NameTxt>
      <P>No.</P>
      <P>Amendment, by leave, withdrawn.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFallon" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>It was agreed on the Order on the Business that we would adjourn Committee Stage debate at 6 p.m.  Minister, thank you for being with us.</P>
      <P>Progress reported; Committee to sit again.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Budget 1994:" RHead="Motion">
    <Title>Budget 1994: Motion.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFallon" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I welcome the Minister to the House.  Senator O'Sullivan has 12 minutes to propose the motion.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JanOSullivan" hpid="Ms O'Sullivan Ms O'Sullivan">
      <NameTxt>Ms O'Sullivan</NameTxt>
      <P>I move:</P>
      <P>That Seanad Éireann endorses the proposals in the 1994 budget and welcomes and supports the pro-jobs, pro-growth and pro-enterprise thrust of the budget, the significant improvements in take home pay that will arise from income tax reductions, the increases in social welfare payments and other measures contributing to economic and social progress in the budget.</P>
      <P>I have great pleasure in proposing this motion and in welcoming the Minister of State to the House.  I have no hesitation in saying that this is the best budget ever in terms of its focus on jobs and enterprise and this is the area on which I intend to concentrate.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>This budget tackled many of the root problems in relation to jobs, employment <Col N="477" /> and enterprise in our society that were not tackled before.  There are four specific areas to which I wish to refer.  The first relates to small businesses while the second is the identified need for a shift in taxation.  This has primarily been on work and income.  It was identified in the Culliton report, the NESC report, the report of the Commission on Taxation and many other reports that we needed to shift some of the emphasis of taxation from employment to other areas.  The third area I wish to address is the measures in relation to long term unemployment.  I particularly wish to refer to whole communities which are in crisis due to large percentages of the people living there who are long term unemployed.  My fourth point is the poverty trap which has been discussed in this House and in the other House on many occasions.  There is a sector of the population who appears to be stuck in a situation where, whether people are unemployed or have the opportunity to take up work, they seem to be unable to improve their position and in many cases these people felt they were worse off if they took jobs.  These four aspects are at the core of the budget. They are interrelated and aimed at directing this country towards methods and systems which will make it easier for people to create and take up work.  They also aim to create a general atmosphere and culture and facilities for employment.</P>
    <P>The first area relates to small businesses in particular.  The most important change in this area is in relation to the loan fund of £100 million where, at an interest rate of 6.75 per cent over ten years, small businesses can borrow.  It was identified over many years that there was a need for low interest loans for small businesses.  I note that the private banks are beginning to follow suit in this area. This is also to be welcomed and the initiative came from the budget through the ICC.  Many of the recommendations in relation to small businesses that are included in the budget were the result of the small business task force, which was set up by the Department of Enterprise and Employment.  It should be noted that <Col N="478" /> the people who are represented in this area were listened to because for many years they were not heard.</P>
    <P>I take issue with the amendment tabled by the Progressive Democrats because when that party was in Government, and its Minister was in that Department, there was little movement to deal with the problems of small businesses.  Many of these have now been addressed.  My colleagues will deal with that in more detail.  I want to refer to the reduction in employers' PRSI for incomes under £9,000 and increases in the VAT thresholds, which took many people out of the net.  Another important matter is the VAT on cash receipts rather than on invoices &mdash; this is of major importance in terms of cash flow for small industries &mdash; and there are many other matters which relate to small industries, such as the simplification of the forms that must be filled when they set up small businesses.</P>
    <P>There are approximately 100,000 family businesses and this is the year of the family.  The concessions in that area, especially where the sons and daughters of owners of small firms can qualify for the PAYE allowance, are very important for these family businesses.  These measures are designed to encourage the start up of businesses, to consolidate small businesses and to help in their expansion towards medium and big concerns.</P>
    <P>There have been many debates in this House on the service industries, the division of the former IDA and so on.  It has been said that many of these changes were needed and I am pleased to welcome them in the budget.</P>
    <P>Regarding the need to remove taxation to some extent from income, the Culliton report, reports by the Commission on Taxation and so on have made various proposals to this effect.  It was proposed in these reports, and expounded upon by many Members of the Opposition, that these changes were necessary yet, when the property tax, a tax which has been on the Statute Book for a long time, was widened the reaction was over the top. An individual earning £25,000 a year with a house valued at between £85,000 and <Col N="479" /> £90,000 and entering the property tax net for the first time will have to pay a maximum of £125 per year; that person gains £640 per year under the income tax changes announced in the budget.</P>
    <P>These new entrants to the property tax net are gaining.  I question whether the Opposition is serious when it advocates the need for tax reform because as soon as the Government starts moving in that direction there is an outcry over something which benefits rather than adversely affects many taxpayers.</P>
    <P>Regarding the long term unemployed, the budget provides for the community employment scheme which will offer employment opportunities to 40,000 people.  It will replace previous similar schemes, will be focused on the communities and will be closely allied to the local development programme within the national plan.</P>
    <P>It is important that we focus on local communities, that we listen to them and empower them, especially communities where there is chronic long term unemployment in a high percentage of families. Yesterday I met with a group of people from Northern Ireland, Limerick and Scotland who were involved in a three way project under the EU Poverty 3 programme.  They put a strong emphasis on the importance of consulting with people in local communities regarding community schemes.  There has been close consultation with local communities. In addition there has been consultation under the National Economic and Social Forum with the various interest groups in relation to these budget changes.</P>
    <P>I also note that the proposal by the Conference of Major Religious Superiors regarding community work in return for unemployment assistance has been taken on board in the budget with the establishment of a pilot scheme.  It is a proposal worth investigating and the appropriate way to do this is through such a scheme. There has been much discussion about it and the pilot scheme should identify the good points, and possibly the bad points, of the proposal.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="480" /> A sizeable section of the population is unemployed long term, that is over three years, and unfortunately such people have small chance of getting back into mainstream employment unless they have the opportunity of participation in community schemes to reactivate their skills, to train and to regain contacts with the labour market.  This will be possible through these schemes.  It is important that there be flexibility in these schemes and that there will be the opportunity for people to stay on longer than one year in certain cases.  It is also important that there be a link between these schemes and the possibility of further employment.</P>
    <P>The poverty trap, as it is commonly described, has been addressed in the budget in several ways.  For those with an income under £9,000 the levies have been abolished, that is the health levy, the youth employment levy and the income levy, which has been abolished for all taxpayers.  Exemptions for income tax liability have been raised, the tax bands have been broadened, personal allowances have been raised and the family income supplement has been increased by £6 per week.  These measures are geared to help people on low pay and who, in many cases, feel that they would lose out, or have lost out, by taking a job.  These measures are also designed to help many who are unemployed and who have the opportunity to get a job but feel that by doing so they would be worse off in terms of take home pay.</P>
    <P>These important measures are designed to address this problem.  In addition, the tax measures have a number of advantages for middle income earners in terms of raising allowances and widening the standard band.  There is a wide range of other measures in the budget in terms of health, education, the public house building programme and so on that address the need to benefit those people who are on low incomes and to stimulate the economy.  The public house building programme not only provides houses for the public but it stimulates and helps the building industry.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="481" /> The budget is focused on work, the protection of people on social welfare and on job and enterprise creation.  These are the constant points of reference throughout this budget, a budget which is turning the corner.  It is a new direction and it will stimulate the economy in Ireland in the ways that I have outlined.</P>
    <P>I have pleasure in proposing this motion.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelCalnan" hpid="Mr. Calnan Mr. Calnan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Calnan</NameTxt>
      <P>I welcome the Minister to the House.  I second the motion.  Many small aspects of the budget have been criticised.  In view of this, I will dwell on the positive aspects.  The motion mentions &ldquo;pro-jobs&rdquo;.  The Department of Enterprise and Employment will be assisting small businesses to a greater extent because of the provisions in the budget.  These include an interest subsidy of 3 per cent on the special loan fund of £100 million; the £800 PAYE allowance being made available to sons and daughters of owners of small firms who are working full time &mdash; this is important because this benefit was not available to young people who were employed by their parents in the family business, whereas it would have been available to any stranger employed by the parents; the reduction in employers' PRSI from 12.2 per cent down to 9 per cent on incomes up to £9,000, a positive move towards reducing PRSI contributions for employers.  Over the years, employers have been hit hard by PRSI and this move to reduce PRSI contributions will protect jobs, especially for those on low pay; the VAT thresholds have been increased to £40,000 and £20,000, thereby eliminating thousands of small businesses from the VAT net; VAT is to be compiled on a cash receipts basis rather than an invoice basis.  Often an invoice which included VAT meant that if the money was paid, it was out of circulation for the person in business, and consequently hindered the growth of the business.  Having VAT on cash receipts makes the system more equitable.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Another provision in the budget is the reduction in the revised capital gains tax from 40 to 27 per cent.  This 27 per cent <Col N="482" /> is important.  A 27 per cent rate across the board is the right amount to pay in tax.  When we speak about 40 or 50 per cent, we are going beyond the limit of the ordinary working person.  The £100 million granted to the health boards will provide jobs by speeding up payments to suppliers and, in addition, there will be a greater cash flow for smaller firms.  There are now single tax registration forms for all new businesses and single tax clearance certificates for all public bodies. Owners may invest in their business under the business expansion scheme.</P>
    <P>These are positive steps to develop small businesses.  If small businesses in rural areas could be developed, one, two or three jobs could be created and this would be of enormous value in a small village.  These jobs would provide money for those who would otherwise be unemployed or who would have to take the boat or the plane across the sea.</P>
    <P>As regards the reduction in income tax, this year the single and married allowances and the 27 and 48 per cent tax bands were substantially increased. Although we may criticise these measures because the increases are not large enough, people will only notice an increase in spending money when the budget comes into effect in the new tax year.  While people may be hyper-critical of certain issues at present, very often they are talking about future projections which may not come true, for example, the telephone débacle some months ago.</P>
    <P>I pay tribute to the Minister of State, Deputy Burton, on the social welfare aspects of the budget which have provided substantial gains for people on social welfare.  There was an increase in disability and unemployment benefits and a 3 per cent rise all round.  Last year's budget showed a substantial increase in child benefit which was further increased this year.  The family income supplement was also increased.  The carer's allowance is gradually coming in line with what may be regarded as a dependence allowance. In the past when a carer took over this job 24 hours a day &mdash; they are wonderful people who provide a social and caring service &mdash; and stayed in the house, the <Col N="483" /> pensioner often lost his or her free telephone, electricity, etc.  However, this is being corrected.  The carer should receive extra money and it should not be taken from the pensioner.  As far as social welfare is concerned, this measure is important.</P>
    <P>The provision of a contributory pension for widowers is also welcome.  In the past widowers were ignored.  Often those caring for children after a bereavement found it difficult to keep going.  The widower's allowance is of immense importance. I am glad the free schemes have been extended to widows over 60 years. Often a husband and wife had free electricity, television and telephone because the husband was over 66 years.  If the husband died at 70 years and his wife was not yet 66 years, she had to pay for electricity again.  This was a severe burden on someone with a reduced income.  The extension of the free schemes to widows is welcome.  Perhaps they could be extended further.</P>
    <P>People ranted and raved about the tax amnesty but we no longer hear anything about it because we see the work being done with the money collected.  The health agencies are getting £100 million, An Post and Telecom Éireann's pension funds are getting £71 million, county roads &mdash; we hear a lot about potholes, etc. &mdash; are getting £15 million and local authorities are getting £5 million to repay debts.  Many other areas have been included in the budget, such as local authority housing where remedial work on bathrooms and window replacement is necessary.  If we isolate parts of the budget and say they are bad, we are not doing justice to the good parts.  There are many good parts to this budget.</P>
    <Speaker pid="TomEnright" hpid="Mr. Enright Mr. Enright">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Enright</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 1:</P>
      <P>To delete all words after &ldquo;That&rdquo; and substitute the following:</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>&ldquo;Seanad Éireann deplores the attack on home owners and middle and lower income earners in the recent budget, as a result of the <Col N="484" /> reduction in mortgage and VHI tax relief, the increase in the residential property tax, the retention of the Probate Tax and the minimal increase in social welfare benefits; and while welcoming the PRSI relief for lower income earners, calls on the Government to introduce a further extension on a graduated level of PRSI payments.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>This budget contained a number of proposals which are welcome, but it contained others of which I would be critical. I welcome the abolition of the 1 per cent income levy imposed in last year's budget.  While it represents a distinct turnaround, it is welcome.  The allocation of £100 million to the health boards from the tax amnesty to reduce their overdraft is welcome.  The provision of an additional £10 million for the hospital waiting list initiative is also welcome. This is essential because many patients have waited up to four years for orthopaedic treatment.  I have evidence that this situation still exists.  The provision of subsidised loans to small businesses is welcome.  This money is coming from the European Union loan fund and is being administered by the European Investment Bank through the Associated Irish Banks.  The 6.5 per cent rate over a ten year period will be of benefit and it is welcome.</P>
    <P>Last year I strongly recommended a widower's pension.  I met an individual who experienced problems in this regard and the case was mentioned by Ms Nuala Ó Faoláin in <i>The Irish Times.</i>  I welcome the introduction of a widower's pension; I am pleased the Minister went along with this proposal.</P>
    <P>As regards means testing contributory widow's and widower's pensions, I am glad the Minister accepted the reasonable objections and reversed the original proposal. Deputy Gay Mitchell highlighted this on radio.  Irrespective of how this came about, this reversal is welcome.  If these changes had been made all contributory pensions in future would have been in danger of being means tested.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="485" /> I believe an anomaly exists in regard to means testing deserted wife's allowance which has not been publicly highlighted. The Minister, who is more of an expert on this.  Senator Calnan and others might be able to clarify this.  The deserted wife's allowance is based on the contribution of the husband up to the time of the breakup of the marriage.  A deserted wife is entitled to an allowance on the basis of his contributions.  If she draws deserted wife's allowance, under this proposal she will not be allowed to earn over £16,000. If this proposal is implemented, it will pose a threat to the introduction of means testing contributory benefits.  This proposal to means testing for the deserted wife's allowance must be withdrawn.  I ask the Minister to examine this because I believe it is a problem.  These are some of the positive proposals, but other areas of the budget are disappointing.</P>
    <P>While acknowledging the economy is in a stronger position than for some years, the Minister failed to take the initiative in this budget.  He was afforded a significant opportunity to improve the level of take home pay and to promote enterprise and job creation.  The revision of PAYE allowances is, at best, minimal and, in view of the reductions in tax relief in some areas, will not have much impact on disposable income.  Rather than pursuing policies of job creation, the extension of the residential property tax and the reduction in mortgage interest relief will adversely affect employment levels in the construction industry.</P>
    <P>The anomalies in the tax have been widely debated and I do not intend to discuss them in detail.  However, the Government has been singularly reluctant to specify measures to redress the anomalies which it admits are inherent in the tax.  A clear statement of its proposals is urgently required to justify the assurances. The Minister's first attempts at tax reform have been bungled and are not a source of hope for promised reforms.  He appears to be at odds with the IAVI and other interested bodies regarding the incidence and yield of this revised property tax.  Perhaps greater consideration should have been given to the proposal.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="486" /> The reduction in tax relief on VHI contributions and the projections for further reductions by 1996-97 will force many people to revert to the public health services, thereby providing an even greater drain on these services.  This reduction is short-sighted and will encourage people to become more dependent on State services.</P>
    <P>I welcome the moneys which the tax amnesty yielded.  Some of the items of expenditure provided for in the budget are financed from funds available on a once off basis from the tax amnesty. Instead of making proper planning provision for the development of the finances of the health boards, the Minister is operating on a safety net basis.  When major problems again arise in relation to health boards' finances, will a further tax amnesty be required to finance the next survival package?</P>
    <P>The revision of the probate tax is welcome but has not gone far enough because it is levied when people have suffered a bereavement.  It must be paid prior to the release of funds from the estate.  A grant of administration or probate cannot issue until the tax has been paid.  Accordingly, the tax must be paid prior to vesting the benefit in the beneficiary. I again state that this tax is a return to death duties.  In its new form it must be paid with capital acquisitions tax and is imposed at the rate of 2 per cent. It is easy to see this being increased to 4 per cent or higher.  The tax is inappropriate and dangerous and should never have been introduced.  I again call for its abolition.</P>
    <P>Non contributory old age pensions are to be increased by £1.80, a great deal has been said about this.  However, it is less than the price of a pint.  When people look at it in a realistic fashion, they will not think it is sufficient.  I looked at some of the increases in child benefits, one of which will be increased by 50p.  The reduction of 3.2 per cent in employers' PRSI and of 2.25 per cent in employees' health and employment levies, both of which apply to incomes up to £9,000 a year, are welcome.  However, the scale should be graduated to encompass <Col N="487" /> people earning between £9,000 and £12,000 a year because they are penalised. The reductions amount to 5.45 per cent.  It may benefit the Government, as well as employees and employers, to provide reductions of 3 per cent on incomes up to £12,000.</P>
    <Speaker pid="DenisDinoCregan" hpid="Mr. Cregan Mr. Cregan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cregan</NameTxt>
      <P>I support the amendment and I agree with Senator Enright in relation to the benefits to those earning £9,000.  In many areas people earning less than £9,000 are not considered.  I do not like people taking credit for measures before they are implemented.  The increases and the so-called schemes have not yet been implemented and the different names put on the same schemes time after time annoy me.  These schemes have been in place since the social employment scheme was introduced in 1985 by the last Fine Gael-Labour coalition.  They were introduced for the long term unemployed, not to take work from people already employed.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The Government in 1987 agreed with the social partners, the Irish Congress of Trade Unions and the employers, that there should be a major reduction in the numbers employed in the public sector. The impression was given that extra jobs would be created but since 1987 the unemployment rate has doubled.  People are still giving the impression that a great number of jobs are being created but I do not agree with these schemes as they give the impression that people are getting jobs and should consider themselves lucky.  This is demeaning because people should have full-time jobs.  We should not give a job to a person for 12 months and then give it to his neighbour for the next 12 months.  We should not give the impression these schemes are for trained people.  They are for general operatives with shovels in their hands.  I do not say this to demean the people engaged in these schemes, I do not like demeaning people or putting them on the side of a street and saying to them they should consider themselves lucky that the State is giving them a job for 12 months.  We give people work for 12 months and give <Col N="488" /> the impression that 40,000 jobs are being created but they are not.  The number of jobs lost in local authorities between 1987 and 1989 was over 40,000.</P>
    <P>I very much resent that the Minister for Finance and the Government give the impression that they are looking after the less well off because the opposite is the case.  Members should examine the facts before they put down motions saying that certain measures will be of benefit.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JanOSullivan" hpid="Ms O'Sullivan Ms O'Sullivan">
      <NameTxt>Ms O'Sullivan</NameTxt>
      <P>We gave the facts, Senator Cregan.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DenisDinoCregan" hpid="Mr. Cregan Mr. Cregan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cregan</NameTxt>
      <P>I did not interrupt anyone.  If this motion was put down in 12 months' time stating that some of the budget's proposals worked, I would give credit where it is due.  However, people should not seek glory before it is due. The proposals should be implemented before Members on the Government side come here and boast.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I now turn to taxation of unemployment benefit.  Have we any idea what will happen to people on unemployment benefit whose spouses are working? Their pay related benefit will be reduced, indeed the Labour Party agrees it should be eliminated.  I heard the Minister say on radio it is right that people who paid contributions towards, for example, widows' pensions should be assessed and means tested.  These contributions could have been paid by their husbands or themselves.  I have no doubt that during the period of this Government pensions and other social welfare payments will be assessed as in the case of unemployment benefit.  These people are now £16.80 a week worse off because of taxation of their basic benefit.  I do not want to give the impression I am against anybody doing something which would create a job.  However, I am talking about real jobs rather than telling people to pull weeds or cut hedges.  We must not forget that when the social employment schemes were first implemented, the Congress of Trade Unions demanded that under no circumstances was this to interfere with a full time job.  That was the agreement and this is a big turn about <Col N="489" /> by people who want to take credit for creating extra jobs when this is not the case.</P>
    <P>An extra 150,000 people are unemployed because of the policy pursued in 1987.  The congress is now given the impression that we can create 40,000 jobs every year.  The Taoiseach spoke yesterday about the creation of 60,000 jobs over a three year period by incoming plants.  I welcome that and hope it happens because that is real work.  Let a person pay real tax on real income.</P>
    <P>There has been a rapid deterioration in roads and urban areas in all local authority areas yet nobody is working.  For example, there are 550 fewer jobs in my local authority than in 1987.  If that figure is multiplied by all the local authorities, how many full time jobs would it create? A general operative in a local authority area is paid less than £9,000 &mdash; what is wrong with giving him full time employment and a pension in 20 years' time? Instead, we give him £9,000 for one year and nothing for the next.  He will then receive unemployment benefit and be credited with the stamps.  If his wife in the meantime does some work he can be taxed on that.</P>
    <P>With regard to the property tax, the Senator spoke about the income level being £25,000.  Let us not forget that it is not £25,000 earned by one person but £25,000 coming into the home which is taxed.  I have no objection to someone who earns £25,000 being taxed but this taxes everybody.  Three people in a house could each earn £8,500, which is nothing, and two of them might not contribute anything to the home.  A widower could earn £9,000 a year, his two children may each earn £8,000 and give their father £20 a week.  Do we really think they should pay such a tax?  There is no logic in it.  There should be only one tax of this type but other taxes are being collected at local government level.  If we are to have a property tax it should be given to local government, instead it goes to the Revenue Commissioner.</P>
    <P>Will the Minister reply to my question on taxing unemployment benefit paid to short term workers?  Such people lose a <Col N="490" /> great deal of money and I can give the Minister the information if she so wishes.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JoanBurtonLAB" hpid="Minister of State at the Department of Social Welfare (Ms Burton) Joan Burton">
      <NameTxt>Minister of State at the Department of Social Welfare (Ms Burton)</NameTxt>
      <P>I welcome this motion because it sums up very well the broad thrust of this year's budget.  I commend my colleagues in the Upper House for focusing attention on the important aspects of the budget which affect the vast majority.  It needs to be repeated that these important aspects are jobs, income tax improvements for the low paid and general social welfare improvements.</P>
      <P>This is a sharing budget founded on the twin pillars of economic growth and social justice.  It makes a series of bold and imaginative leaps into the whole area of tax reform and the integration of tax and social welfare.  I welcome the changes in relation to social welfare which seek to consolidate the concept of social protection. However, for somebody on a social welfare income the income element is only a part of the total services which they consume.  Everybody, including social welfare recipients and the so-called &ldquo;middle income group&rdquo;, benefits from the provisions in this budget on health, education and housing.</P>
      <P>A common theme of Fine Gael and Progressive Democrats' rhetoric in recent weeks is that Labour and Fianna Fáil are running a tax and spend Government. In spite of this, their Senators are here looking for further increases in spending and criticising some small increases in specific taxes.  In common with so much else which comes from these sources, the tax and spend claim is rooted more in wishful fantasy than reality.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Although this Government has boosted public spending in many sensitive social areas such as education and health, its overall fiscal approach is very cautious and it has shown determination to keep its annual spending firmly within the agreed European guidelines and to achieve a reduction in the overall national debt.  In fact, we are the only country in the EU to have stayed within the Maastricht guidelines while reducing <Col N="491" /> taxes at the same time.  Ireland now has the lowest public expenditure as a percentage of GDP in the EU.</P>
    <P>OECD figures published this week show that, contrary to general perceptions, Ireland is not a heavily taxed country.  In fact, total tax revenue as a proportion of GDP is lower in Ireland than in most EU countries.</P>
    <Speaker pid="DenisDinoCregan" hpid="Mr. Cregan Mr. Cregan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cregan</NameTxt>
      <P>Does that include excise taxes?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoanBurtonLAB" hpid="Ms Burton Ms Burton">
      <NameTxt>Ms Burton</NameTxt>
      <P>Its record in 1993 and its targets for 1994 put it in the top league of governments reaching the Maastricht standards.  The flow of foreign funds into our currency reflects the level of confidence in the stability of that policy. Every home owner and business is reaping a rich harvest of interest rate cuts which directly flow from it and it is universally recognised that mortgage holders are significantly better off this year than this time last year.  That is what counts in practical terms for many families.</P>
      <P>Another myth which we hear time and again from these sources is the allegation of the Labour Party's hostility to the self reliant middle income group.  It is a curious claim as Senators know that many Labour Party TDs and Senators are from this group &mdash; teachers, lawyers, an architect, a chartered accountant, professionals of various kinds.  We even have a psychiatrist.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TomEnright" hpid="Mr. Enright Mr. Enright">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Enright</NameTxt>
      <P>Full-time.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoanBurtonLAB" hpid="Ms Burton Ms Burton">
      <NameTxt>Ms Burton</NameTxt>
      <P>The Labour Party is an almost perfect microcosm of society.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DenisDinoCregan" hpid="Mr. Cregan Mr. Cregan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cregan</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister means smoked salmon socialists.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister, without interruption.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoanBurtonLAB" hpid="Ms Burton Ms Burton">
      <NameTxt>Ms Burton</NameTxt>
      <P>Many of its members have moved into the middle income group through education and the normal upward social mobility brought by economic <Col N="492" /> prosperity and personal ambition. Their political base is heavily rooted in middle class as well as working class votes and it is inconceivable that these TDs &mdash; Ministers or backbenchers &mdash; or Senators would countenance any policy which would suppress social or economic ambition.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DenisDinoCregan" hpid="Mr. Cregan Mr. Cregan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cregan</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister could have fooled me.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoanBurtonLAB" hpid="Ms Burton Ms Burton">
      <NameTxt>Ms Burton</NameTxt>
      <P>In recent weeks I have been infuriated by the vulgar repetition by Fine Gael and the Progressive Democrats of the myth that the middle income group is asked to pay for everything but gets nothing in return.  This is just a barefaced lie.  The tax take in a family with three children and a salary of £40,000 a year was reduced from 38 per cent of income in 1986-87 to 32 per cent in 1993-94. That hardly constitutes war on the middle income groups.  It is not only in take home pay that the middle income group has gained, but in State services generally.  Take education for example, which, understandably, is a subject of considerable concern for all groups in our society.  The overwhelming ambition of the middle income group is high standards in public education with affordable access to the highest levels.  This is the surest guarantee that their children will have the capacity to maintain and improve their standard of living.  The improved level of public spending devoted to education at every level reflects the commitment of the Labour Party in Government to this ambition. Every middle income taxpayer receives a top quality return from this investment in education which their taxes provides.</P>
      <P>While third level fees are a major drain on many such families, the tax relief provided through covenants has remained in place at the full rate.  There is also a review of the grants system currently taking place.  In any case, every individual third level place commands a substantial public subsidy and there can be no doubt that middle income taxpayers are the main beneficiaries, as indeed, they are entitled to be.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="493" /> Equally the health service uses up vast sums of public money.  While most middle income families are careful to take out VHI cover, there is still a large cost to the Exchequer for every treatment given.  The quality of the care on offer is the direct result of the taxes paid and invested in the health services.  It is nonsense to claim that no benefit comes to middle income taxpayers from the extra resources devoted.  Both this year&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    <Speaker pid="DenisDinoCregan" hpid="Mr. Cregan Mr. Cregan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cregan</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister is abusing them.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoanBurtonLAB" hpid="Ms Burton Ms Burton">
      <NameTxt>Ms Burton</NameTxt>
      <P>&mdash;&mdash;and last year, the elimination of hospital waiting lists has been of benefit to everybody using the health services.</P>
      <P>Housing subsidies are substantially aimed at owner occupiers.  All the studies of these subsidies show that middle and higher income groups gain disproportionately from them.  Virtually every home owner in the country has been helped to acquire that status by generous State subsidies.  Politicians who feed crude and ill-informed prejudices are beneath contempt.  Whatever discomfort the Government in general, and the Labour Party in particular, has experienced in the past two weeks, Ministers can derive some amusement at the sight of erstwhile tax reformers from right and left rushing to shred a decade of speeches and policy documents on calling for a widening of the tax base.  I believe the machines have been working overtime.</P>
      <P>They will not get away that easily.  The basic problem of excess tax on wages and salaries still remains.  Last April, a Fine Gael spokesman put a £500 million figure on the scale of the switch to new taxes he would propose to Fine Gael.  He highlighted VAT on food, books and medicines and additional local charges as possible sources of such revenue.  He referred to tough choices in the interview. I suspect Fine Gael is rather anxious to forget that now.  Are we to expect a shamefaced admission that these views, on mature reflection, are no longer operative?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="494" /> Tax reform comes with a price and Fine Gael's seems to be higher taxes on every family's bread and butter and on school books.  As the row over the residential property tax subsides, voters will be looking carefully at the tax options of other parties.  I suspect Fine Gael will not be in any rush to let them know too much about its policies.</P>
    <P>We must accept that high quality education, health and housing services cost money.  We cannot reasonably demand improved services and lower taxation at the same time.  We can, however, demand that taxation should be fair and that its impact on income should be consistent. Tax reform is not only tax reduction&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    <Speaker pid="DenisDinoCregan" hpid="Mr. Cregan Mr. Cregan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cregan</NameTxt>
      <P>Like the unemployed.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoanBurtonLAB" hpid="Ms Burton Ms Burton">
      <NameTxt>Ms Burton</NameTxt>
      <P>&mdash;&mdash;which is what the Opposition seek.</P>
      <P>The public discussion on the budget so far has been dominated by one issue.  I want to talk about the real issue, the unemployed and the lower paid.  The emphasis in this budget was far from being an attack on the middle income group.  Instead, it was designed to improve the climate for employment creation and give greater incentives to lower paid workers.  My colleague, the Minister for Enterprise and Employment, Deputy Quinn, announced major incentives for small businesses, which everyone has welcomed.  We have encouraged family businesses by changes in CGT and CAT.  We have reduced bureaucracy in small firms.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TomEnright" hpid="Mr. Enright Mr. Enright">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Enright</NameTxt>
      <P>The Government certainly expanded it in Dublin.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoanBurtonLAB" hpid="Ms Burton Ms Burton">
      <NameTxt>Ms Burton</NameTxt>
      <P>It is extraordinary that commentators can castigate the Labour Party for being anti-middle class when a Labour Party Minister is introducing the most significant encouragement for small and medium sized businesses.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>In the social welfare area, we have increased benefits by 3 per cent and the lower rates, such as unemployment benefit, by 10 per cent.  We have introduced <Col N="495" /> a number of other improvements.  Fine Gael is criticising what it apparently considers to be too low an increase in social welfare.  I looked at the names of the Members on the Fine Gael amendment and I saw Senator Ross's name.  I recall him writing in his column in the <i>Sunday Independent</i> less than a month ago about the social welfare monster.  Now he is asking the monster to grow by calling for an increase in social welfare benefits.  We need to ensure that&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    <Speaker pid="TomEnright" hpid="Mr. Enright Mr. Enright">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Enright</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator Ross will go along with what I said about the increase of £1.80.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoanBurtonLAB" hpid="Ms Burton Ms Burton">
      <NameTxt>Ms Burton</NameTxt>
      <P>&mdash;&mdash;taxation policy is pro-employment. As the House is aware, this means continuing the process of tax reform&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DenisDinoCregan" hpid="Mr. Cregan Mr. Cregan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cregan</NameTxt>
      <P>It is a failed speech.  The Minister is feeling the pressure.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoanBurtonLAB" hpid="Ms Burton Ms Burton">
      <NameTxt>Ms Burton</NameTxt>
      <P>&mdash;&mdash;now under way for a number of years, aimed especially at increasing the rewards and incentives for working and reducing the cost of employing workers.</P>
      <P>I accept that the proportion of all tax collected from incomes is high.  Furthermore, the burden of income tax bears heavily on those with modest incomes because of the speed at which individuals enter the tax net and, more importantly, the speed at which the higher rates of tax come into play.  In these respects our current tax system impacts negatively on enterprise and employment and significant changes are essential.  I was therefore, delighted that the Government was able to announce significant improvements in the income tax position of all earners in the budget.  I was particularly delighted that the focus of the benefits was on low and medium earners.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The budget reduced the overall take from income tax by almost £200 million in 1994 and by over £330 million in a full year.  We have removed the 1 per cent levy, significantly increased the personal allowances and widened the standard <Col N="496" /> rate band.  We have given the largest single increase in personal allowances since 1984.  These combined improvements will mean that the thresholds for the higher tax rate in the case of employees, before any allowance is included for discretionary reliefs, will be increased to £22,200 if married and to £11,600 if single.  These measures will help to reduce the tax burden on the low and middle income earners.  For example, a single person on £12,000 per year will have a total gain of £314, while a married couple on £22,000 will gain £569.  This will also result in over 40,000 fewer taxpayers being on the top rate of tax.  I need not of course remind the House that the top rate of tax is now 48 per cent compared to 58 per cent in 1987.</P>
    <P>The child addition to the income tax exemption thresholds is being increased by £100 per child.  The addition will now be £450 each for the first and second child and £650 each for the third and subsequent children.  For example, in future a married person with four children can earn up to £9,400 per annum, or slightly over £180 per week, without having to pay any income tax.  In addition, the marginal relief rate at which tax is charged on income slightly above the exemption threshold, is being reduced from 48 per cent to 40 per cent. This significant reduction in the marginal rate of tax faced by many low paid workers will alleviate the poverty trap and increase the incentive to work.  The improvements in this area will mean that 38,000 taxpayers will either benefit from marginal relief or be fully exempted. Moreover, the remainder of the 111,000 taxpayers currently on marginal relief will see their income tax bill considerably reduced.  Senator Cregan alluded to the fact that about 45 per cent of PAYE workers and 39 per cent of taxpayers earn less than £10,000, in other words, almost half a million people earn less than £10,000, and they are the people who will benefit significantly from this budget.</P>
    <P>Two measures are being introduced in the income tax area which are specifically aimed at business.  First, the PAYE allowance is being made available to children <Col N="497" /> of proprietary directors and the self-employed, including farmers, who are full time employees in their parents' business. Second, the company value limit for entrepreneurs' investment in their own company under the BES is being raised from the current £150,000 to £250,000. These are measures which have been welcomed on all sides.</P>
    <P>By any standards the reliefs in mainstream income taxation are substantial. The overall cost of these measures amounts to some £330 million in a full year. The extent of the relief is borne out by the fact that the total yield from income tax and the levies in 1994 is projected to be £20 million less than last year.  The net effect will be to substantially alleviate income taxation for all earners and thereby increase the share of the income available for use by them in the purchase of goods and services.</P>
    <P>In addition to the general income tax measures mentioned here, a number of other steps were taken to improve the position of the low paid and to help improve the competitive position of those industries which employ large numbers of low paid workers.  The Government has been convinced by the arguments of many employers and their representatives that a reduction in the overall burden of PRSI would assist them in maintaining or creating employment, especially in labour intensive sectors.  We have, therefore, introduced a differential employers PRSI contribution rate structure.</P>
    <P>From 6 April 1994 a reduced rate of 9 per cent will be levied on incomes up to £173 per week.  In addition an exemption from the health and employment and training levies is being introduced for those earning not more than £9,000 per annum.  The obligation for employers to pay the cost of these levies for those with medical cards is also being removed. These changes represent a major improvement for the cost structure of firms with large numbers of low paid employees and should improve significantly the competitive position of <Col N="498" /> these vulnerable firms, not least in the clothing sector.</P>
    <P>Lower paid workers are also being helped by the improvement in the family income supplement.  On a personal note, I am pleased that all the recommendations of the interim report of the working group on the integration of tax and social welfare which I established last year have been implemented and will help to improve the incentive to work for lower paid people.  I recall a newspaper article by Senator Ross which asked if anybody would ever read this report.  I am sorry he is not here.  The report had a target audience of one &mdash; the Minister for Finance.</P>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I ask the Minister to refrain from mentioning Members who are not here.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoanBurtonLAB" hpid="Ms Burton Ms Burton">
      <NameTxt>Ms Burton</NameTxt>
      <P>The report was targeted at the Minister for Finance and I am pleased to say he saw fit to implement all the recommendations in the report.  The report has had a short but successful shelf life and I am happy about that.  Lower paid workers will benefit substantially from this budget and I think there is general agreement in the House that this should be the principal target of relief in this budget.</P>
      <P>The Government's and my foremost concern at present is the need to create sustainable employment in Ireland.  With that objective in mind, supporting enterprise in the interest of employment has been a central theme of recent budgets. All the measures and initiatives which have been introduced, such as the changes in CAT, CGT and in the BES and the improvements for small and medium enterprises are aimed at making the economy more employment friendly through improving wage competitiveness and further tilting the balance between risk and reward in favour of business investment and entrepreneurial activity.  I trust that these measures will both promote employment and help the business community to thrive and expand in today's competitive market.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="499" /> The Government's economic strategy has at its core the fundamental reality that Ireland's capacity for sustainable growth ultimately depends on our ability to compete successfully in the global marketplace of which we are now a part. It proceeds from the conviction that to deliver sustainable economic and social progress there is only one sound approach and that is to improve the capacity of the economy to grow.  These are the policies which have enabled Ireland to perform particularly well while at the same time keeping Government borrowing and inflation well below the European Union average.</P>
    <P>Our task now is to build on this foundation and to maximise the growth potential of our economy to enable further progress in tackling the daunting problem of unemployment.  This year's budget has taken a major step in this direction.  We have clearly shown that responsible budgetary management will be continued in good times as well as bad, that our debt burden will continue to be reduced over the medium term to free more resources in support of growth and that tax reform will continue so as to maximise the employment dividend from growth.</P>
    <P>In conclusion, this motion recognises the crucial importance of our efforts to generate more jobs in the economy, to improve work incentives by increasing take home pay, to assist enterprise and investment and to ensure that the less well off in our society are catered for. Accordingly, I fully support the motion.</P>
    <Speaker pid="CathyHonan" hpid="Ms Honan Ms Honan">
      <NameTxt>Ms Honan</NameTxt>
      <P>I understand that I am unable to move my amendment as there is another amendment before the House but I would like to read it into the record. It states:</P>
      <P>To delete all words after &ldquo;Seanad Éireann&rdquo; and substitute the following:</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>&rdquo;, while welcoming the PRSI relief for lower-paid workers, deplores the budget's lack of a clear strategy for employment and self-reliance, and in particular denounces the anti family home <Col N="500" /> tax; the attack on employment through the £549 PRSI increase on middle incomes; and the paltry improvement in the standard income tax band.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>Scarcely has there been a budget in recent times that promised so much and delivered so little.  Far from being a pro-jobs budget, it lacks a clear strategy to tackle the unemployment crisis.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MaryKelly" hpid="Ms Kelly Ms Kelly">
      <NameTxt>Ms Kelly</NameTxt>
      <P>Unlike the Senator's party's policies of years gone by.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="CathyHonan" hpid="Ms Honan Ms Honan">
      <NameTxt>Ms Honan</NameTxt>
      <P>It reveals a continued fixation with borrowing; £800 million more is being added to the national debt of £25.8 billion.  That mountain of debt is consuming £2 out of every £3 in tax that is collected from the PAYE sector in annual interest payments.  While the improvement in the standard rate income tax band is welcome, it will be completely offset for most middle income earners by the increased cost of their mortgage, VHI, petrol and family home tax.</P>
      <P>If the purpose of this budget was to improve the climate for employment its effect will be negligible.  The effect of the budget's change in employer's PRSI was to add about £550 to the employer's cost of a skilled worker on £25,000 per annum and the employee will also be liable for a further £70 per annum.  This means that the great pro-employment budget has slapped an extra £620 in direct levies on employing many skilled and middle income workers.  The effect of this will be dramatic.</P>
      <P>Guinness in Dublin said that they would have to pay an extra £1.2 million in payroll costs this year because of this change in the budget.  If the management of that company decide to make more people redundant to keep their payroll costs down, the blame will fall fair and square on the shoulders of Labour and Fianna Fáil.  There are many other companies throughout the country, including many hi-tech companies, with skilled workers where the 1994 budget will do more to damage job prospects than any other budget in recent history.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="501" /> One of the most talked about features of this budget was the removal of the 1 per cent levy.  This was supposed to be a reforming measure.  With the greatest of respect, I think everybody accepts that the levy was wrong and anti-work.  It was imposed by this Government in their last budget and its removal was nothing more than the correction of a mistake that should never have been made.  While its removal is very welcome, the fact that an anti-work levy is imposed in year one and removed in year two cannot be seen as a reforming measure.  It once again demonstrates the Government's complete lack of strategy.</P>
    <P>In general terms the changes in allowances are not very radical.  It is not radical tax reform for a Minister to increase personal allowances in very favourable circumstances. Broadening the standard rate by 6 per cent is not radical tax reform.  These measures have been dressed up as major changes but disregarding the abolition of the 1 per cent levy, the real combined effect of the extra PRSI on many middle income workers will far outweigh the effect of the 3 per cent real change in tax bands, a 5 per cent change in allowances, once inflation is taken into account.</P>
    <P>Despite all the huffing and puffing in advance of the budget about the need to widen significantly the standard income tax band, what emerged has still left thousands of workers paying the top rate of tax on below average incomes.  It could be argued that had the Minister concentrated the resources he undoubtedly had this year and widened the standard tax band by three times the amount he did, and if he had done very little else in this budget, it would have had a far more positive impact on stimulating enterprise and employment in the economy.  The reduction in taxation for lower waged workers is a step in the right direction but here also is a lack of a coherent strategy.</P>
    <P>The employers PRSI and the employee's 2.5 per cent levy break up to £9,000 means that a new welfare poverty trap is being created at that level.  If a worker earns £1 above this threshold he <Col N="502" /> will pay the full levies and his wage attracts full employers PRSI on all the income, not simply on the amount of earnings above £9,000.  If the employer pays workers in this section an extra £500 or £1,000 it will cost employers a lot of money in payroll taxes.  If an employee in the hard pressed clothing sector is offered overtime next year, the cost for the employer could be enormous.  A new ceiling has been imposed on those at the bottom of the ladder.</P>
    <P>In view of that the Progressive Democrats proposal to exclude the first £3,000 of everyone's earnings from PRSI would be more balanced and equitable.  Real reform of PRSI would transform it into part of the general tax system.  If it applied to everyone, including the public sector, at the same rate, there would be an extra £400 million to use in introducing genuine tax reform to exempt low incomes.  There has been no hint of that from this Government.</P>
    <P>I now come to the infamous residential property tax.  It is necessary to put this in context because we have been accused by Fianna Fáil and Labour of being hypocritical on this issue.  In 1973 the national coalition parties offered to take the health charges off rates; Fianna Fáil promised to abolish rates completely.  In 1977 Fianna Fáil repeated that promise, accompanied by their infamous promise to abolish motor tax.  The Fine Gael-Labour alliance also said in 1977 that they would get rid of rates, but over four years.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelOKennedy" hpid="Mr. O'Kennedy Mr. O'Kennedy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Kennedy</NameTxt>
      <P>There was a certain PD man in that Government, if I recall, and I think he was responsible for a vote of&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator Honan without interruption, please.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelOKennedy" hpid="Mr. O'Kennedy Mr. O'Kennedy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Kennedy</NameTxt>
      <P>I may be wrong, but I remember him there.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="CathyHonan" hpid="Ms Honan Ms Honan">
      <NameTxt>Ms Honan</NameTxt>
      <P>Everyone wanted to shift the tax burden onto income tax, in other words onto employment.  In the next Fine Gael-Labour Government, between <Col N="503" /> 1983 and 1987, local charges were introduced and were fought tooth and nail by Fianna Fáil.  Residential property tax was introduced.  In 1991 both parties contested the local elections with a clear commitment to remove local charges. They both did very well out of that.  In 1992, the Government parties used property tax in a scandalous and cynical series of election advertisements.  The Taoiseach, Deputy Reynolds, chose to use the property tax scare to attempt to damage Labour, and the Tánaiste, Deputy Spring, denied any such intentions.</P>
      <P>The Progressive Democrats have been assailed by this Government for not supporting the extension of the residential property tax.  In 1986 at our first conference, we committed ourselves to its repeal.  In 1988 we published a tax reform document which again committed us to its abolition.  We made the case at all times for radically transforming local government&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JanOSullivan" hpid="Ms O'Sullivan Ms O'Sullivan">
      <NameTxt>Ms O'Sullivan</NameTxt>
      <P>You were in Government.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="CathyHonan" hpid="Ms Honan Ms Honan">
      <NameTxt>Ms Honan</NameTxt>
      <P>&mdash;&mdash;and shifting some of the costs to all non-agricultural property in the form of a charge that would go to local government.  In 1989 we proposed an all party committee of the Oireachtas to examine this issue but there was no appetite for that.  We opposed residential property tax because we thought it was arbitrary and unfair.  I now restate the reasons we oppose it.</P>
      <P>We have always opposed it.  It is not a local government tax.  It is an extra central Exchequer wealth tax on homes.  It is anti-family and anti-urban.  If the Government wished to take some of the load off income tax by funding local government differently, the Progressive Democrats will participate in and support that process, provided it is part of a downward shift in taxation and that every penny is used to directly reduce tax on work.  This is part of radical transformation and democratisation of local government.  This has been our consistent policy since we were founded.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="504" /> The recent comments of the Minister, Deputy Smith, on the issue of local government suggest that this Government has no intention of tackling the reform of local government funding which is so badly needed.  The Progressive Democrats voted last year and this year for aspects of the budget with which we were in agreement.  We got little thanks for that, but we will continue to support from our position that which we would do in government.  Residential property tax is unfair and arbitrary.  Its retention and extension is an error.</P>
    <P>In short, we believe that this budget is a missed opportunity.  If the Government had gone for radical change instead of the feeble changes we have seen, we would support it.  If allowances had been transformed into basic rate tax credit, if bands had been widened and rates cut, if the last two budgets had controlled public spending and kept it in line with inflation and if public sector pay had been controlled, this could have been a budget that was so badly needed, but sadly, none of that was done.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelOKennedy" hpid="Mr. O'Kennedy Mr. O'Kennedy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Kennedy</NameTxt>
      <P>I support the motion in the names of my Labour Party colleagues and to even more enthusiastically repudiate the motion in the name of Fine Gael and the Progressive Democrats. This budget has been made possible by good management of the economy and of the public finances going back to 1957. Far from being a tax and spend budget, as the Minister of State has rightly pointed out, the latest figures from the European Union support the Government's view.  These are objective figures.  Much else here, understandably, is argument.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The objective data from the European Union shows beyond any doubt that Ireland's public expenditure as a percentage of national output is the lowest in the European Union, and that is an extraordinary achievement.  I am glad to say, as the Minister of State has pointed out, that the policies now being pursued and the benefits we are enjoying from them are the policies which have enabled Ireland to out-perform our European partners over the last six years in terms <Col N="505" /> of growth and employment.  I am very happy and proud to have been part of the Government that made all this possible.</P>
    <P>The decisions we took were not easy. They were difficult decisions because a good Government is not one which takes easy decisions.  As a consequence of that we now find ourselves in the strong and healthy state unique in Europe in terms of the level of public expenditure as a percentage of national output.  When prudent policies like that are being pursued, priority areas must be targeted in terms of those most in need.  As my colleagues have already pointed out, this is precisely what the Government is doing in this budget &mdash; targeting within controlled public expenditure those most entitled to support from Government. For that reason I have to totally repudiate the hypocrisy and falsehood in the Fine Gael motion which &ldquo;deplores the attack on middle and lower income earners&rdquo; because they have been singled out for special protection and concern in this budget.</P>
    <P>Let me give a few examples.  Before this budget the existing tax allowance for the single person was £2,175; after the budget it is £2,350, an increase of £175; for married couples it is an increase at that low level of income of £350; and for widowed persons an increase of £175. That kind of social targeting is vitally important when prudent and sometimes restrictive policies in terms of public expenditure are being pursued.  That is why the Fine Gael statement about targeting the low income earners does not match the reality of this budget.  For example, there has been an increase of £175 in the one parent family allowance. This is evidence of the type of social targeting one would expect from a Government of this composition.</P>
    <P>I want to refer to a sector of our community which was not mentioned and with which I dealt for five years during which time I laid the basis for existing conditions.  The agricultural and farming community are an important part of this budget and of our socio-economic structure. They will benefit considerably from many of the measures announced in the <Col N="506" /> budget.  Additional resources are available to streamline payments of the common agricultural reform premiums and the other direct income supports which were introduced in my time.  The aids to farmers in less favoured areas is being increased by £40 million to £126 million.  One of the consequences of my work &mdash; I must be modest about this &mdash; was the extension of disadvantaged areas to cover 72 per cent of the country.  I am happy this is being maximised now to benefit low income farmers in particular.</P>
    <P>A new fund of £7 million, to be co-financed by the European Union, is provided for institutional research and development in the food sector.  This is vital to generate employment in our indigenous sector, and I also endorse the targeting of this area in the budget. Additional resources are provided for investment in dairy hygiene and animal welfare to meet European Union standards. This is the key to opening new markets and to maintaining our place in those enhanced areas and the continued high status of Irish agricultural produce. These things will not change overnight, but such actions and targets guarantee that the future employment prospects of those about whom we are concerned will be secured.</P>
    <P>In addition, there is a fund of £7.5 million and £10 million, respectively, for the new European Union assisted farm retirement and agri-environment programmes. Farm retirement schemes are essential to our agriculture sector because they allow our young people to accept the responsibility which older people pass on to them.  The agri-environment programmes are also essential and they are part of the agri-tourism programme which I introduced three years ago and which, I am told, is the most successful tourism programme in the country.  I would be greatly disappointed if this was not the case.  A sum of £2 million is being provided for small farm development services operated by Teagasc.</P>
    <P>Social welfare is targeted throughout this budget because the Government remains, committed to the further <Col N="507" /> development of the social welfare system.  I want to mention a few points which will highlight this fact.  There has been a general rise of 3 per cent in social welfare levels which, like last year and the year before, will be above the expected rate of inflation.  This is how one secures the position of the old, the sick and the disadvantaged.  By keeping their levels above inflation, we are continuing the policy of increasing lower payments to priority rates.  In addition, we are increasing the child benefit to £25 for the third and subsequent children.  The means test is being relaxed for carers and lone parent allowances.  I am only highlighting a selection of enlightened measures in a regulated public expenditure system.  This shows community awareness because lone parent and carers allowances will encourage people to look after their own people in their own homes.</P>
    <P>I want to talk about small businesses because my colleagues have dealt with this issue.  It is fair to say that this budget is a charter for small business.  There are so many elements in it that I will not have time to discuss them now but I understand they have been put on the record. Small businesses have been targeted in order to generate the employment opportunities we require.  Instead of attacking the lower paid, workers will gain most in this budget through exemption from employment and health levies on earnings of £9,000 or less.</P>
    <P>Priority is also being given to health boards and public voluntary hospitals, particularly those in debt, who are at risk of liquidation.  They will also gain from a £100 million contribution to help restore their finances.  This will be a once off payment.  A sum of £10 million will be made available to reduce hospital waiting lists.</P>
    <P>Two million pounds is being provided for handicapped children and £5 million for secondary school buildings, the base of any enlightened socio-economic policy.  This is what all sections of our community and all parties expect from this Government and it is being done. <Col N="508" /> There is evidence that those who have the greatest social need and claim on our resources are being given special support in this budget.  In relation to our housing programme, improvements have been made to substandard housing as a result of the work done by the task force for the elderly in particular.</P>
    <P>In relation to the infrastructural base of the overall economy, the additional £15 million from the tax amnesty, which is being provided for the maintenance of our non-national roads, is an essential element of enlightened policy.  I find it extraordinary to hear people say there is no targeting of priority groups.  There is no evidence to support that case made by the Opposition.  The elimination of the 1 per cent levy, the 7 per cent increase in the tax bands and the large increase in personal tax allowances represent a major reduction in taxation to one of the lowest levels in Europe.</P>
    <Speaker pid="LiamTCosgrave" hpid="Mr. Cosgrave Mr. Cosgrave">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cosgrave</NameTxt>
      <P>I welcome the Minister of State, Deputy Burton, to the House and I support the amendment which shows how this budget has and will affect so many people in the weeks and years ahead.</P>
      <P>Initially, I want to deal with the residential property tax and to point out the dishonesty of the party which promised to put trust in politics.  They seem to be the biggest tellers of untruths &mdash; I do not know if I am going too far to call them liars &mdash; in relation to what they said at the beginning of their term in office.  It is no harm to put on the record the message sent in those heady days in November when the Labour Party was doing reasonably well, when it conned a number of people some of the time, particularly during the weeks leading up to polling day.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaloney" hpid="Mr. Maloney Mr. Maloney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Maloney</NameTxt>
      <P>Is the Senator talking about yesterday?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LiamTCosgrave" hpid="Mr. Cosgrave Mr. Cosgrave">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cosgrave</NameTxt>
      <P>I want to put on the record what the Labour Party said in the heat of the campaign: the Labour Party <Col N="509" /> has no plans to introduce a new property or house tax&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JanOSullivan" hpid="Ms O'Sullivan Ms O'Sullivan">
      <NameTxt>Ms O'Sullivan</NameTxt>
      <P>It is not a new tax.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoanBurtonLAB" hpid="Ms Burton Ms Burton">
      <NameTxt>Ms Burton</NameTxt>
      <P>Fine Gael introduced it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LiamTCosgrave" hpid="Mr. Cosgrave Mr. Cosgrave">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cosgrave</NameTxt>
      <P>&mdash;&mdash;the Labour Party will not reduce mortgage interest relief &mdash; I will discuss the threshold later; the Labour Party will increase the relief while interest rates remain high, but it will not introduce a wealth tax or reduce VHI tax relief.  The residential property tax was brought in in the 1980s to deal with houses of reasonable size.  The plan was that the value of houses would increase in line with inflation and that the salaries of those affected would also increase so that people on a fairly good income, living in a reasonably priced house, would pay a certain amount of tax.  What happened?  I am sure the Minister is aware from her own area &mdash; as I am sure her colleagues Ministers Fitzgerald and Bhreathnach are aware from their areas &mdash; that this tax is now hitting ordinary two and three bedroom houses which were originally bought, perhaps 30 years ago, for relatively modest sums and which, because of their location, now fall into the tax bracket.  It also hits families where parents may be earning a fairly modest income but when their children's income is added to the total the household comes quite easily into the net.  The tax also operates where a mother or mother-in-law's pension brings the whole family's income over the threshold.  This measure was introduced by a party that made great play of trust and truth but it has been shown to be as bad, if not worse, than its colleagues in Fianna Fáil.  It has demonstrated that not only does it not tell the truth but that it told outright lies during the last election campaign.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I am glad that the Labour Party, despite other attractions in the last few days, brought this issue back to centre stage because it will continue to be centre stage, and even more so when people have to start finding considerable lump sums to pay the tax.  Average house prices in Dublin are quite high, even for people <Col N="510" /> trying to buy a new three-bedroom, semidetached property within a few miles of here.  People on modest incomes who decide to buy a house in a certain area will now be hit.  They will also be hit by the reduced mortgage interest relief.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JanOSullivan" hpid="Ms O'Sullivan Ms O'Sullivan">
      <NameTxt>Ms O'Sullivan</NameTxt>
      <P>They gain a lot more in income tax changes than they lose in either of those.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LiamTCosgrave" hpid="Mr. Cosgrave Mr. Cosgrave">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cosgrave</NameTxt>
      <P>They will be hit and I hope the Labour Party will be hit in June because people will not forget it, either this year or next.  Perhaps, eventually, council houses will be in the net.  I can see a gradual extension of the tax because already houses valued at £75,000 are included.  I am sure this Government will continue to reduce the house price and income thresholds so that, eventually everyone will be caught.  This is the start of the reintroduction of rates by the Government which will begin slowly and gradually increase.  This so-called &ldquo;caring&rdquo; Government which &mdash; if it is not going after hard-pressed young couples or people on modest incomes trying to raise their families &mdash; is telling people to throw out their mothers, mothers-in-law or other elderly relatives.  That is the action of the Government who promised to tell the truth and put truth back into politics.  It is important to point out, as the amendment tabled by our group does, that the effects of this budget will hit various people very hard.  It is important that the Minister and his colleagues remember this because the electorate certainly will remember it in the days to come.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JimTownsend" hpid="Mr. Townsend Mr. Townsend">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Townsend</NameTxt>
      <P>I would like to share my time with Senator Maloney.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Is that agreed?  Agreed.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JimTownsend" hpid="Mr. Townsend Mr. Townsend">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Townsend</NameTxt>
      <P>This is not just a good budget, it is a great budget, the best in many years.  It is good for the low-paid and for small business, people in receipt of social welfare and those on local authority housing lists, people on hospital <Col N="511" /> waiting lists as well as children attending primary school.  A lot of misrepresentation, gross hypocrisy and downright lies have been told about the property tax which I would like to counter. The property tax is not new, it has been there for ten years.  The most that any person, brought into the property tax net for the first time this year, will have to pay is £150.  A good number of people will hardly pay anything and I will give an example.  A person with a £90,000 house and an income of £27,000 will pay the enormous annual sum of £15 in property tax.  If that person has two children he or she will pay the enormous sum of £1.50 in a year.  That is hardly a crucifixion of the middle classes.</P>
      <P>I wish to discuss the question of people with mortgages, not just those with mortgages on large houses worth over £75,000 but the ordinary person with a £30,000 mortgage over 20 years.  If the interest rate in that case goes up 1 per cent repayments will increase by £19 a month or £225 in a full year.  If we are really concerned about mortgage holders then we must do our best to keep interest rates down by all possible means.  That is how we can help.  If someone has a 20-year mortgage at 8.5 per cent, then for every £1,000 that a house might increase &mdash; if someone enters into a new mortgage &mdash; they would pay £8.60 a month or £103 a year extra.  So, if we are worried about home-owners and mortgage holders we must try not to let house prices go wild, as well as trying to keep interest rates down.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Some 45 per cent of all PAYE workers earn less than £9,000 or £173 a week and will be substantially helped by this budget.  Social welfare increases, especially widowers' pensions, are welcome as is the provision whereby a widow under 66 years of age will now be allowed to keep her social welfare entitlement. Wonderful improvements have been brought about for the small business sector in this budget and I will list some of them.  The interest subsidy of £100 million, whereby people will be able to borrow money at a fixed interest rate of <Col N="512" /> 6.75 per cent for ten years, must be of great assistance to many small companies.</P>
    <P>The £800 PAYE allowance being made available to the sons and daughters of small firm owners and farmers brings justice to the system.  The reduction in employers' PRSI contributions from 12.2 per cent to 9 per cent on incomes up to £9,000 is of benefit and is a response to the complaints that it is too expensive to employ workers.  Increasing the VAT thresholds from £20,000 to £40,000 will take thousands of small businesses out of the VAT net and will help small business generally.  There are many other aspects of the budget which will help small business.</P>
    <P>The budget's strategy is already working in spite of comments to the contrary. The lending institutions are offering mortgages at fixed interest rates for up to ten years.  Bank of Ireland today announced that it, too, will provide money at long term fixed interest rates.</P>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaloney" hpid="Mr. Maloney Mr. Maloney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Maloney</NameTxt>
      <P>I thank Senator Townsend for sharing his time and I welcome the Minister to the House.  It must be a proud occasion for her as this budget has seen increases higher than the rate of inflation in social welfare which is her area of special interest.  There are increases of almost 10 per cent in some areas.  Disability benefit, unemployment benefit and child benefit have been increased.  I welcome those increases and I congratulate the Minister on her input to the budget.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>This motion is welcome.  As a trade union leader in the health services &mdash; a sector which has many low paid workers &mdash;I have attended union meetings where there has been an unbelievable reaction to the budget.  It is the first time I have attended meetings at which members no longer complain.  People used to talk about the &ldquo;lunatic left&rdquo;.  However, it is the lunatic right which has now gone mad in its rantings and ravings about the residential property tax.  An accountant in Letterkenny did some calculations on the tax for me.  For a family with two children, a house worth £90,000 and an <Col N="513" /> income of £30,000, the tax will amount to £15 per year.  We have definitely gone mad.  I received only one representation on the matter in Donegal.</P>
    <P>The Minister for Health, Deputy Howlin, has done sterling work in the health sector.  A total of 17,000 extra operations have been carried out due to the allocation of £20 million last year and £10 million is being provided this year for similar operations.  That showed the greed of the consultants who allowed the waiting lists to grow.  As a result of the attack on the waiting lists people are now getting what they paid for many years ago.  The Minister has also secured over £100 million to address the long running financial problems of health boards. Some health boards overran their budgets while others did not &mdash; I feel sorry for those that did not.  They probably would have been better off if they had because they would have got more money in the budget.</P>
    <P>A total of 3,500 houses were built last year and another 3,500 will be built this year.  This is a massive attack on the housing waiting lists.  Our party gave a commitment on going into Government that it would ensure that every local house in need of a bathroom would get one.  Progress has been made in that regard.  In addition, the Minister of State, Deputy Stagg, announced last week that weather-proof windows and central heating will be provided in new houses from this year forward.  That is a welcome announcement.  The commitment given by the Minister for Education to provide extra moneys for school extensions and new school buildings is welcome too.</P>
    <P>As the members of my union have said, this is one of the best budgets in years especially for the less well off and the low paid workers in our society.  I welcome and support the motion.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JoeOToole" hpid="Mr. O'Toole Mr. O'Toole">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Toole</NameTxt>
      <P>I worry when I hear about trade union meetings at which nobody complains and at which members praise the budget.  I do not know if the Senator is trying to talk us out of a job, but it is a new approach to trade unionism and I would be prepared to put up with <Col N="514" /> some of it for a while.  The Senator should video-tape those meetings and show us how some union meetings are conducted.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaloney" hpid="Mr. Maloney Mr. Maloney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Maloney</NameTxt>
      <P>The Senator's members are well off.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeOToole" hpid="Mr. O'Toole Mr. O'Toole">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Toole</NameTxt>
      <P>The Labour Party always stuns me.  I have to admire its audacity in moving a motion to congratulate the Government on its budget.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryKelly" hpid="Ms Kelly Ms Kelly">
      <NameTxt>Ms Kelly</NameTxt>
      <P>We have something to boast about.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeOToole" hpid="Mr. O'Toole Mr. O'Toole">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Toole</NameTxt>
      <P>I look at the budget from a balanced point of view.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaloney" hpid="Mr. Maloney Mr. Maloney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Maloney</NameTxt>
      <P>The Senator was on the radio recently and had nothing bad to say about it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeOToole" hpid="Mr. O'Toole Mr. O'Toole">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Toole</NameTxt>
      <P>I recognise that there are good and bad elements in the budget and there is not enough time to discuss all of them in detail.  However, my first comment is complimentary.  I compliment the Government on recognising its error in imposing the 1 per cent income levy last year and on abolishing the levy in this budget.  That was the most positive aspect of the budget and was a major move forward.</P>
      <P>I have reassessed my point of view on one issue since I commented on the budget.  At the time I thought the tax on unemployment benefit was a regressive move.  However, on reconsideration I believe it is a positive move.  It had to happen.  It will have a positive impact on the figures during the year.</P>
      <P>The property tax is a total mess.  Incidentally, I am not aware of a cap of £150 on property tax.  Perhaps the Government has made another decision and stepped further away from it.  The problem with the property tax has nothing to do with the amount of money involved; it has nothing to do with people's worry that it will be more next year.  The fact is it will affect the same people who are trying to pay their taxes all the time and it sparks a reaction of, they are at it again, they are hitting us in another way.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="515" /> I am not a county councillor and I am not a member of a political party so I can discuss the issue of rates in an objective way, unlike other Members of this House, with the exception of the Independent Senators.  Rates were abolished in the 1977 budget.  It was a disastrous error.  Members of local authorities recognise that.  Rates were abolished on the basis that the money would be provided out of taxation.  I regret that the Minister in his budget did not say he would reduce taxation by x per cent.  He could have told the taxpayers that they would not get that money back but would pay it through local charges or rates.  The money will come back one way or another. Only Independent politicians can say this because they are not seeking votes in local authorities.  What is happening in this area is disastrous.</P>
    <P>The property tax is unfair inasmuch as it hits the wrong people at this time.  I support the idea of a property tax.  Any country in Europe with a fair system of taxation must have a form of property tax in its tax system.  The way it was introduced and the pressures it puts on people have caused the current reaction. It was handled in a hamfisted way and the Government has paid, and will continue to pay, for that.  There must be some acceptable way of taxing property.</P>
    <P>I do not agree with those who think no tax is best.  There must be taxation.  A good budget does not necessarily mean a reduction in the amount of tax; it means a fairer system for the payment of tax. The Minister made every effort in this budget to spread the burden away from income taxation.  That approach must be welcomed.  However, it did not work. The idea of reducing VHI and mortgage interest reliefs would be fine if, at the same time, there was an extension of the 27 per cent tax band so that at least three-quarters of the taxpayers were paying at that rate.  People could not then argue about getting the kickback for the same amount.  However, there will be a problem until those two things happen.</P>
    <P>One matter is a cause of regret to me. I have seen its effects and have tried to <Col N="516" /> raise it with Ministers.  It is an issue that affects people with children in third level education and is, the threshold for qualification for third level grants.  The cost for parents of a child in third level education is approximately £4,000 per year: £2,000 for fees and £2,000 maintenance. For people like myself who might have to pay that three times in the year it represents a cost of £12,000 after tax.  For those who are paying it means a gross earning figure of £24,000 per year to have three children in third level college.</P>
    <P>I have come across cases of teachers and other taxpayers who retired early so that they would be out on pension and thereby qualify for the third level grants for their children.  Others have taken career breaks, stopped working in other words, when they could not afford to do so to let their children go through college. Worst of all, I have seen people gladly sell their retirement lump sum to pay for their children to go through college as it is an investment in their future and in the future of the country.</P>
    <P>However, the threshold can never be raised enough.  The policy of the two parties in Government is for access to third level education to be improved.  The reality is that it cannot be delivered overnight but surely we can take steps in that direction.  As well as increasing the threshold could we not extend the scope of covenants?  I accept that covenanting is a regressive form of tax relief inasmuch as the higher the income the more one can qualify.  If it is only 5 per cent of income then a person on £100,000 can claim £5,000 whereas somebody on £20,000 can claim only £1,000.  Therefore, it is not to be encouraged as a fair form of tax relief.</P>
    <P>However, instead of extending the percentage in covenant we could extend the scope and vouched third level fees could be offset against tax.  That would be fairer.  People like me, who are earning good salaries should not be able to demand that the State put our children through college if we can afford to pay for it &mdash; I can make the principled argument for and against &mdash; in practical terms. I resent that one is paying double the <Col N="517" /> amount in terms of one's gross salary and, therefore, covenanting should be extended to allow its scope to include vouched third level fees or costs.  That is within the Government's policies and would be welcomed on all sides.  It is the kind of tax break that is as good an investment as a BES scheme or any other investment.</P>
    <P>I know a parent who is not badly off, he earns nearly £30,000 &mdash; almost as much as a TD &mdash; and he has two children in college. He has told his third child that if she wants to go to college she will have to take two years off so that the others can finish.  He simply cannot afford it. There is something wrong with that and it could be addressed by extending the scope of covenants.</P>
    <P>The most significant statement in the budget was in the background to it and dealt with unemployment.  It gave an indication that this year the Government expects the unemployment figures to be reduced by 5,000.  I did not see that reported in any paper, and I can understand that the Government would not be jumping with joy at the idea as 5,000 is a drop in the ocean of the 300,000 unemployed. I look at it from the trade union point of view and if that marks a turnaround from annual increases in unemployment then it is a major move forward.  This budget is full of flaws and I have pointed out some of them, but there are also good things in it.  If at the end of this year we have turned the tide and unemployment starts to reduce by 5,000 this year and more next year, then the Government can take credit for it.  If not, they will get plenty of criticism from this side of the House.  I hope that the optimism of the Minister for Finance as indicated in the budget is justified.  The economic indicators at all levels are solid. The objective in income taxation has to be to get at least three quarters of our taxpayers into the 27 per cent band.</P>
    <Speaker pid="BrianJHillery" hpid="Professor Hillery Professor Hillery">
      <NameTxt>Professor Hillery</NameTxt>
      <P>I will focus on unemployment and highlight an aspect that has not emerged fully in the debate.  We are all agreed that unemployment is the main social and economic problem facing the <Col N="518" /> country.  The budget significantly addresses the question of job creation and shows a sensitivity in the provisions for the long term unemployed.  I welcome the community employment programme which will increase the places in the existing social employment scheme and the community employment development programme by 50 per cent, and they are to be replaced by the community employment programme.  These schemes provide valuable work experience and developmental training that should help people to integrate with the workforce.</P>
      <P>I specifically want to refer to work for the unemployed and the action proposed in the budget on the proposal of the Conference of Major Religious Superiors. This proposal was first enunciated by the Oireachtas Joint Committee on Employment, which I had the honour to chair, in 1992.  We came to an agreement at that time across party lines, with the exception of Fine Gael &mdash; every other party was on the Committee and a variety of interest groups from outside the Oireachtas on the subcommittees &mdash; that there had to be a better way than paying £1 billion a year to unemployed people who had to prove that they were doing nothing and that they were chashing nonexistent jobs to get that benefit.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>We got cross-party agreement to look at alternatives and one of those was the question of identifying work in local authorities and in community and voluntary organisations where the public funds paid out in benefit could be paid on an optional basis to people who would take up that work.  I stress the optional element.  This is an option to work as envisaged in the pilot scheme in the budget.  There is no question of compulsion, politicians know that literally thousands of people want to work and would welcome it tomorrow.  I do not see the need for compulsion in any case. Under the present system we are saying, in effect, here is the money but thou shalt not work.  I look forward to the 1,000 places in the pilot scheme where people would work for the unemployment benefit on a voluntary basis.  This should also <Col N="519" /> help to deal with the loss of dignity and self-worth that unemployed people face.</P>
    <P>The money pumped into education has been referred to on a broad level and I welcome the increases in the budget.  The vocational training opportunities scheme has proved a valuable exercise in getting long term unemployed people back into mainstream education with a view to increasing their job prospects.  There is a long established link between educational attainment and jobs.</P>
    <P>On the question of small businesses I am glad that the serious problem of access to capital has been addressed.  I welcome the assistance towards capital in the £100 million of cheap loans that are to be provided at 3 per cent below market rates.  I particularly welcome the reduction in administration for small businesses.  Excessive bureaucracy is the enemy of enterprise and any such measure within the control of Government should be simplified to facilitate firms who want to get on with the job of creating work and developing their businesses.</P>
    <P>The National Economic and Social Forum is the successor to the joint committee on employment and I am an Oireachtas Member of that body.  We are currently examining all the schemes for dealing with unemployment.  We are exploring new ideas, including international thinking in this area, and we plan to produce a report in May on the question of the long term unemployed with specific proposals for consideration by Government.  I hope that our report will be taken seriously and taken on board as a serious input to the formulation of Government policy.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMagner" hpid="Mr. Magner Mr. Magner">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Magner</NameTxt>
      <P>Time is short and I wager that by the time I get through listing the provisions in this budget which are in favour of business and the family the Cathaoirleach will call me to order because there will not be enough time to go through what is, without doubt, one <Col N="520" /> of the best budgets produced for many years.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PaddyBurke" hpid="Mr. Burke Mr. Burke">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Burke</NameTxt>
      <P>For tax.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMagner" hpid="Mr. Magner Mr. Magner">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Magner</NameTxt>
      <P>It is appropriate that this pro-family budget should be produced in the international year of the family.  Fine Gael and the Progressive Democrats must follow the Chinese calendar, under which this is the year of the dog, because they have taken a dog in the manger approach.  They said the budget is not good enough, that it is taking money from some people and not giving enough to others.</P>
      <P>Who agrees to tax property at a certain level?  Fianna Fáil and Labour do, so does Fine Gael because the former Minister, Deputy Dukes, introduced property tax.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DenisDinoCregan" hpid="Mr. Cregan Mr. Cregan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cregan</NameTxt>
      <P>With the Labour Party.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMagner" hpid="Mr. Magner Mr. Magner">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Magner</NameTxt>
      <P>Obviously, because Fine Gael would not have been in power without Labour.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TomEnright" hpid="Mr. Enright Mr. Enright">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Enright</NameTxt>
      <P>Labour also agreed to tax children's shoes.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMagner" hpid="Mr. Magner Mr. Magner">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Magner</NameTxt>
      <P>It has been a fundamental policy of those trapeze artists, the Progressive Democrats, since their inception.  It was also the policy of Sinn Féin The Workers' Party, which is now Democratic Left.  The opposition to this has been so fraudulent that Houdini or Richard Nixon should have signed the amendment to the motion.</P>
      <P>I quote from the <i>Sunday Business Post:</i></P>
      <P>Almost a dozen members of the Fine Gael front bench were at the gates of Leinster House last week to greet a delegation of modest men from ACRA, the householders defence group.  Whatever about John Bruton's concern for equity in taxation, it is clear the party is desperately seeking a political lifeline.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PaddyBurke" hpid="Mr. Burke Mr. Burke">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Burke</NameTxt>
      <P>What is the name of the paper?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="521" />
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMagner" hpid="Mr. Magner Mr. Magner">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Magner</NameTxt>
      <P>It continues: &ldquo;Within hours party deputies were summoning up the ghost of James Connolly in an effort to chastise the Labour Party over taxes and unemployment&mdash;&mdash;&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DenisDinoCregan" hpid="Mr. Cregan Mr. Cregan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cregan</NameTxt>
      <P>That reminds me of the Aer Lingus workers.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMagner" hpid="Mr. Magner Mr. Magner">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Magner</NameTxt>
      <P>&ldquo;&mdash;&mdash;while the Progressive Democrats and Fine Gael were whipping up middle class wrath over the adjustments to the residential property tax.&rdquo;  The leading article goes on:</P>
      <P>For voters to think clearly and dispassionately about what is proposed the Government proposes to impose the RPT on incomes in excess of £25,000 whose houses are worth £75,000.  Where incomes slightly exceed the threshold, marginal relief will apply.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TomEnright" hpid="Mr. Enright Mr. Enright">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Enright</NameTxt>
      <P>Can the Senator not write an original speech?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DenisDinoCregan" hpid="Mr. Cregan Mr. Cregan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cregan</NameTxt>
      <P>Too many papers are being read.  Deal with the facts.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMagner" hpid="Mr. Magner Mr. Magner">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Magner</NameTxt>
      <P>The article says:</P>
      <P>This is hardly the slaughter of the chattering classes and the Minister is likely to make sensible arrangements at the time of the Finance Bill.  But it is positively nauseating to see Mary Harney trying to make political capital out of this matter, given the Progressive Democrats' clamour for a general property tax in the past and their relentless demands for a broadening of the tax base.  The spectacle of General O'Duffy's followers promoting socialism on the floor of the Dáil, meanwhile, merely reinforces our belief that the difficulties faced by the Fine Gael party are deeper than was feared.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidNorris" hpid="Mr. Norris Mr. Norris">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norris</NameTxt>
      <P>On a point of order, a Chathaoirligh, is it in order to name Members of the other House?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DenisDinoCregan" hpid="Mr. Cregan Mr. Cregan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cregan</NameTxt>
      <P>God be with the red rose; smoked salmon socialists.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="522" />
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMagner" hpid="Mr. Magner Mr. Magner">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Magner</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not know what Senator Norris is talking about.  If there is a protected species in this country, it is university lecturers.  If there is a species to which the normal strictures on people's lives do not apply, it is within the hallowed walls of academia, to quote a member of the transport union.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidNorris" hpid="Mr. Norris Mr. Norris">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norris</NameTxt>
      <P>Quite right.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DenisDinoCregan" hpid="Mr. Cregan Mr. Cregan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cregan</NameTxt>
      <P>What transport union?  It no longer exists.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMagner" hpid="Mr. Magner Mr. Magner">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Magner</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator Norris might be affected by the property tax but he has a substantial property and I am sure he will not mind.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidNorris" hpid="Mr. Norris Mr. Norris">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norris</NameTxt>
      <P>I made sure I will not be affected.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMagner" hpid="Mr. Magner Mr. Magner">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Magner</NameTxt>
      <P>I hope Senator Norris is not considering dodging the property tax by renting half his house, a Chathaoirligh.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFallon" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I would not believe it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidNorris" hpid="Mr. Norris Mr. Norris">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norris</NameTxt>
      <P>I will pay only what is required by law.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DenisDinoCregan" hpid="Mr. Cregan Mr. Cregan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cregan</NameTxt>
      <P>Self-assessment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMagner" hpid="Mr. Magner Mr. Magner">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Magner</NameTxt>
      <P>In this budget the business community especially small businesses have benefited.  How could those who opposed this budget oppose the measures for small businesses announced by the Minister, Deputy Quinn?  In America, the amount of employment generated by small businesses supersedes that from major companies.  We must encourage small businesses.  I thought that was favoured by the Opposition but obviously it is not.  Its tactic is to oppose something with which they agree.  It is a difficult position.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DenisDinoCregan" hpid="Mr. Cregan Mr. Cregan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cregan</NameTxt>
      <P>Where is the opposition? There is nothing in the amendment about that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="523" />
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMagner" hpid="Mr. Magner Mr. Magner">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Magner</NameTxt>
      <P>I know that and it is because the Opposition has no point to make.  When it ran out of excuses it turned on Deputy Bruton.  The budget is relevant and contains more provisions for the welfare of people than any budget I can remember.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DenisDinoCregan" hpid="Mr. Cregan Mr. Cregan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cregan</NameTxt>
      <P>The Government is taxing the unemployed.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFallon" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator Magner, your time is up.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMagner" hpid="Mr. Magner Mr. Magner">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Magner</NameTxt>
      <P>In this House the Opposition got everything wrong so far this year.  It said we would close Aer Lingus down, we would not give the company money and that it would never fly a plane again.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TomEnright" hpid="Mr. Enright Mr. Enright">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Enright</NameTxt>
      <P>If Government Ministers were not flying around the world Aer Lingus would have gone out of business. The Government jet is extremely busy. The next Labour Party conference is in the Waldorf-Astoria Hotel in New York.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="524" />
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMagner" hpid="Mr. Magner Mr. Magner">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Magner</NameTxt>
      <P>We heard the same about Telecom Eireann.  We were told people would surrender their telephones and bills would increase by 700 per cent as a result of the actions of this Government.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DenisDinoCregan" hpid="Mr. Cregan Mr. Cregan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cregan</NameTxt>
      <P>The Government sold out Aer Lingus and Telecom Éireann.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMagner" hpid="Mr. Magner Mr. Magner">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Magner</NameTxt>
      <P>A Chathoirligh, I appeal for your protection.  This is a classic example of the mental agility of Fine Gael.  If we sold out Aer Lingus we did so with the assistance of its workers and management.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFallon" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator Magner, your time is up.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMagner" hpid="Mr. Magner Mr. Magner">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Magner</NameTxt>
      <P>I ask for another minute or two because of these interruptions. The Opposition was proved wrong on the 1 per cent levy.  Fine Gael would have gone to the gallows saying that levy would never been removed.  If one applied the Trades Description Act to this Opposition its Members would be put in gaol.</P>
      <P>Amendment put.</P>
      <P Just="Center">The Seanad divided: Tá, 16; Níl, 33.</P>
      <P Just="Center">Tá</P>
    </Speaker>
    <table pgwide="1">
      <tgroup cols="2">
        <colspec colname="1" colnum="1" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <colspec colname="2" colnum="2" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry rowsep="1">Belton, Louis J.<br />Burke, Paddy.<br />Cosgrave, Liam.<br />Cotter, Bill.<br />Cregan, Denis (Dino).<br />Dardis, John.<br />Enright, Thomas W.<br />Farrelly, John V.</entry>
            <entry rowsep="1">Honan, Cathy.<br />Howard, Michael.<br />McDonagh, Jarlath.<br />Naughten, Liam.<br />Neville, Daniel.<br />O'Toole, Joe.<br />Ross, Shane P.N.<br />Taylor-Quinn, Madeleine.</entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
    <P Just="Center">Níl</P>
    <table pgwide="1">
      <tgroup cols="2">
        <colspec colname="1" colnum="1" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <colspec colname="2" colnum="2" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry rowsep="1">Byrne, Seán.<br />Calnan, Michael.<br />Cashin, Bill.<br />Crowley, Brian.<br />Daly, Brendan.<br />Fahey, Frank.<br />Farrell, Willie.<br />Finneran, Michael.<br />Fitzgerald, Tom.<br />Gallagher, Ann.<br />Henry, Mary.<br />Hillery, Brian.<br />Kelleher, Billy.<br />Kelly, Mary.
<Col N="525" />Ormonde, Ann.<br />Roche, Dick.<br />Townsend, Jim.</entry>
            <entry rowsep="1">Kiely, Dan.<br />Kiely, Rory.<br />Lanigan, Mick.<br />Lydon, Don.<br />McGennis, Marian.<br />McGowan, Paddy.<br />Magner, Pat.<br />Maloney, Sean.<br />Mooney, Paschal.<br />Mullooly, Brian.<br />Norris, David.<br />O'Brien, Francis.<br />O'Kennedy, Michael.<br />O'Sullivan, Jan.
<Col N="526" />Wall, Jack.<br />Wright, G.V.<br /></entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
    <P Just="Center">Tellers: Tá, Senators Cosgrave and Burke; Níl, Senators Mullooly and Magner.</P>
    <P>Amendment declared lost.</P>
    <Speaker pid="CathyHonan" hpid="Senator Honan Senator Honan">
      <NameTxt>Senator Honan</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 2:</P>
      <P>To delete all words after &ldquo;Seanad Éireann&rdquo; and substitute the following:</P>
      <P>&rdquo;, while welcoming the PRSI relief for lower paid workers, deplores the budget's lack of a clear strategy for employment and self-reliance, and in particular denounces the anti-family home tax; the attack on employment through the £549 PRSI increase on middle incomes; and the paltry improvement in the standard income tax band.&rdquo;</P>
      <P>Amendment put and declared lost.</P>
      <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That the motion be agreed to.&rdquo;</P>
      <P Just="Center">The Seanad divided: Tá, 31; Níl, 16.</P>
      <P Just="Center">Tá</P>
    </Speaker>
    <table pgwide="1">
      <tgroup cols="2">
        <colspec colname="1" colnum="1" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <colspec colname="2" colnum="2" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry rowsep="1">Byrne, Seán.<br />Calnan, Michael.<br />Cashin, Bill.<br />Crowley, Brian.<br />Daly, Brendan.<br />Farrell, Willie.<br />Finneran, Michael.<br />Fitzgerald, Tom.<br />Gallagher, Ann.<br />Henry, Mary.<br />Hillery, Brian.<br />Kelleher, Billy.<br />Kiely, Dan.<br />Kiely, Rory.<br />Lanigan, Mick.<br /></entry>
            <entry rowsep="1">Lydon, Don.<br />McGennis, Marian.<br />McGowan, Paddy.<br />Magner, Pat.<br />Maloney, Sean.<br />Mooney, Paschal.<br />Mullooly, Brian.<br />O'Brien, Francis.<br />O'Kennedy, Michael.<br />O'Sullivan, Jan.<br />O'Toole, Joe.<br />Ormonde, Ann.<br />Roche, Dick.<br />Townsend, Jim.<br />Wall, Jack.<br />Wright, G.V.</entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
    <P Just="Center">Níl</P>
    <table pgwide="1">
      <tgroup cols="2">
        <colspec colname="1" colnum="1" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <colspec colname="2" colnum="2" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry rowsep="1">Belton, Louis J.<br />Burke, Paddy.<br />Cosgrave, Liam.<br />Cotter, Bill.<br />Cregan, Denis (Dino).<br />Dardis, John.<br />Enright, Thomas W.<br />Farrelly, John V.</entry>
            <entry rowsep="1">Honan, Cathy.<br />Howard, Michael.<br />McDonagh, Jarlath.<br />Naughten, Liam.<br />Neville, Daniel.<br />Norris, David.<br />Ross, Shane P.N.<br />Taylor-Quinn, Madeleine.</entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
    <P Just="Center">Tellers: Tá, Senators Mullooly and Magner; Níl, Senators Cosgrave and Burke.</P>
    <P>Question declared carried.</P>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFallon" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>When is it proposed to sit again?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GVWright" hpid="Mr. Wright Mr. Wright">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Wright</NameTxt>
      <P>It is proposed to sit again at 10.30 a.m. on Thursday, 17 February 1994.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Adjournment Matters. -" RHead="Availability of Unleaded Petrol">
    <Title>Adjournment Matters. - Availability of Unleaded Petrol.</Title>
    <Col N="527" />
    <Speaker pid="MichaelOKennedy" hpid="Mr. O'Kennedy Mr. O'Kennedy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Kennedy</NameTxt>
      <P>I thank the Minister for coming to the House.  I wish to draw attention to the present situation in relation to the price levels of unleaded petrol.  In view of the growing awareness of the effect of leaded petrol on health and the environment, the motoring public should be encouraged to use unleaded petrol.  There are two types of unleaded petrol available, Superplus unleaded which has an octane rating of 98 ron and Eurograde unleaded, also called premium or standard unleaded, which has an octane rating of 95 ron.  Almost all cars can use the lower grade of unleaded petrol without any significant difference in performance.</P>
      <P>When unleaded petrol was first introduced in 1986, many cars, particularly older models, needed a slight timing adjustment to take the cheaper fuel.  The Superplus grade did away the need for this and served a useful purpose in the transition to unleaded petrol.</P>
      <P>Since October 1990 it is compulsory for all cars sold in the European Union to be compatible with the 95 grade fuel, hence the term Eurograde.  The number of cars which need to use the enhanced grade has been falling and is now less than 5 per cent of the total.  It was reasonable, therefore, to expect petrol companies to encourage the use of the cheaper Eurograde and to ensure its availability at all outlets.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Since Government controls on petrol prices were lifted in 1990, consumer choice should have been encouraged by the petroleum companies.  Yet until July 1993, the supply of Eurograde had not changed, while the supply of Superplus increased.  The various oil companies cited difficulties in storage, market resistance and complaints about Eurograde as reasons for preferring to supply Superplus. While these may have been factors, it is hardly a coincidence that the fuel they chose to supply was more expensive.  In the second half of 1993 the <Col N="528" /> supply situation was ridiculous.  As few as one in four service stations stocked Eurograde; that figure was as low as one in five in rural areas.  Yet all service stations were stocking the more expensive fuel.</P>
    <P>Understandably, the Automobile Association embarked on a publicity campaign at that time in an attempt to improve things with two specific objectives. The first objective was to inform motorists about the differences and similarities between the two types of unleaded petrol and to advise them to buy the cheaper fuel, thereby saving them a considerable amount of money.  There is a misconception in the Irish market that Superplus was a better fuel because it was &ldquo;Superplus&rdquo; and was kinder to the engine.  There is no technical basis for this belief.  The second objective of the AA campaign was to bring pressure to bear on oil companies to improve the lamentable supply situation by publishing it and by encouraging motorists to complain on garage forecourts.</P>
    <P>An embarrassed oil industry has said little or nothing in response to this campaign. It has not yet taken the necessary steps to ensure cheaper Eurograde unleaded is available at all outlets.  Motorist have begun to insist on the lower grade fuel and its sale has increased dramatically.  By the end of 1993, three out of four outlets were supplying the cheaper fuel, but it must be available at all outlets.</P>
    <P>The breakdown of petrol sales in 1992 is as follows: leaded petrol, 65 per cent; Superplus unleaded, 28 per cent and Eurograde, 7 per cent.  By the end of 1993 the figures were as follows: leaded petrol, 58 per cent; Superplus unleaded, 21 per cent; and Eurograde, 21 per cent.  These figures are welcome and they show the awareness of the motoring public of the desirability of using unleaded petrol and the fact that Superplus unleaded does not add to the performance of a car.</P>
    <P>The consumer demand for Eurograde is growing and is, to a large extent, a <Col N="529" /> consequence of the publicity given to this issue by the Automobile Association. This trend also shows that the oil industry is capable of supplying the fuel.  Arguments about storage capacity and market resistance proved specious when motorists started to complain by taking their business elsewhere.  Within three months, companies which said people would not buy the cheaper fuel changed their stance in view of public demand and even offered incentives, such as 20p per gallon off 95 unleaded, although that was the price in any event.</P>
    <P>This begs the important question, why did they not supply it in the first place? Oil companies have a special and privileged role in this economy.  One must ask why they are not supplying this fuel to all rural and urban outlets at this stage.  It is clear the industry was content to allow motorists continue to believe Superplus was superior.  It may be unfair to say it created the misconception, but it did little to correct it.  It was prepared to go on indefinitely making considerable profits on the difference.</P>
    <P>Petroleum prices at consumer level have a considerable impact on the consumer price index and the Government is concerned to keep it below the level of inflation.  It is important, therefore, to keep pressure on petrol companies to ensure the motorist is offered a genuine choice in line with that available in all EU countries where the supply of higher grade fuel has become increasingly obsolete and the supply of Eurograde outstrips it.  It is important to maintain pressure on oil companies.  In some outlets Superplus unleaded is still supplied in preference to the standard grade and this costs motorist a considerable sum of money.</P>
    <P>Standard grade should be supplied universally and Superplus should, in time, be the exception.  Superplus is a super way to waste money.  Over 95 per cent of cars will run the same way on Eurograde unleaded.  A top of the range sports car may notice a marginal difference in performance, <Col N="530" /> but for everyone else the difference will be felt in the wallet.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MaryORourke" hpid="Minister of State at the Department of Enterprise and Employment (Mrs. O'Rourke) Minister of State at the Department of Enterprise and Employment (Mrs. O'Rourke)">
      <NameTxt>Minister of State at the Department of Enterprise and Employment (Mrs. O'Rourke)</NameTxt>
      <P>I thank Senator O'Kennedy for raising this important issue.  The consumer should have a wide choice; that is the essence of equity in the consumer market.  In October 1993, the Automobile Association issued details claiming only one in four petrol stations nationwide stock lower grade unleaded petrol.  I requested the Director of Consumer Affairs to look into the matter and inquiries were made.  As Senator O'Kennedy said, Irish consumers, unlike most of our European counterparts except for <i>la belle France</i>, have tended to purchase higher grade petrol in the belief they were doing better.  This tradition has extended to the newer unleaded petrols.  Because of this, smaller retail outlets, limited in the number of grades of fuel they can stock, have tended to sell the higher grades of petrol.</P>
      <P>However, the director's inquiries indicate that this situation is changing, as Senator O'Kennedy said, with more Irish consumers now moving towards the lower grades.  Petrol companies have reacted by making the cheaper grade of unleaded petrol more widely available, again showing that if the consumer presses, the market reacts.  The latest information available indicates that three out of four petrol stations nationwide are now stocking the lower grade unleaded petrol.  I very much welcome that the market has reacted to meet the change in consumer preference.  In saying that Irish motorists have tended to purchase higher grade petrol, the director informed me that when unleaded petrol was first introduced only the standard grade was available and motorists were very reluctant to purchase what was seen as an inferior product.  It was only when the higher grade of unleaded petrol was put on the market that motorists began to switch to unleaded.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="531" /> I am aware that the Automobile Association has for some time been expressing the view that almost all cars in this country can use the lower grade without noticing any difference in terms of performance or economy and that motorists in other European countries have been happy to use the lower grade. In this respect it is worth noting that in Ireland the higher grade accounts for 67 per cent of sales of unleaded petrol and the lower grade 33 per cent.  In the United Kingdom the higher grade accounts for 13 per cent and the lower grade for 87 per cent of sales.  In Germany the higher grade accounts for 8 per cent and the lower grade for 92 per cent of sales.  In Denmark the figures for the higher and lower grades are 33 per cent and 67 per cent respectively.  However, in France the preference is for higher grade which accounts for 91 per cent of sales.</P>
    <P>It is also worth pointing out there is a difference between the higher and lower grades of unleaded petrol in terms of octane content and that some consumers may have a preference for the higher grade.  It is essentially a matter of choice and my concern is that motorists should be free to exercise choice between the two grades.</P>
    <P>In an ideal world every petrol station would have the capacity to stock both grades.  However, the reality is that smaller stations, mainly rural ones, will be limited in the number of grades of fuel they can stock and the retailer may have to choose one over another.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelOKennedy" hpid="Mr. O'Kennedy Mr. O'Kennedy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Kennedy</NameTxt>
      <P>They will not be using racing cars.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryORourke" hpid="Mrs. O'Rourke Mrs. O'Rourke">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. O'Rourke</NameTxt>
      <P>As I indicated, the latest information available indicates that in making their choice an increasing number of retailers choose to stock lower grade unleaded petrol.  I am satisfied the market is functioning well in that oil companies and retailers have reacted positively to meet the shift in consumer <Col N="532" /> preference.  Why can retailers and providers not be ahead of what the consumer wants?  Why do they sit back and wait for pressure from consumers?  It is right that this pressure is exerted but a proper retailer or manufacturer of a product would ask what the consumer wants. Until we are ahead in terms of the wishes of consumers, we will not be in the race. I thank Senator O'Kennedy for his wisdom in raising this matter.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFallon" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>And saving us all money.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryORourke" hpid="Mrs. O'Rourke Mrs. O'Rourke">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. O'Rourke</NameTxt>
      <P>Consumers are dear to my heart.  The Senator has given me a chance to say things on their behalf.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelOKennedy" hpid="Mr. O'Kennedy Mr. O'Kennedy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Kennedy</NameTxt>
      <P>I thank the Minister. I am very conscious of her concern for consumers and I hope this will be a contribution to the very positive campaign in which she is engaged.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Adjournment Matters. - UCD Business" RHead="and Legal Studies Exemptions">
    <Title>Adjournment Matters. - UCD Business and Legal Studies Exemptions.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="AnnOrmonde" hpid="Miss Ormonde Miss Ormonde">
      <NameTxt>Miss Ormonde</NameTxt>
      <P>I am grateful for this opportunity to raise the issue of students in UCD who are taking the Legal and Business Studies course which started in 1991.  It was to be a two pronged course. Fifty per cent of the subjects were in the commerce and business area and 50 per cent in the legal area.  Parents and students were under the impression that when students pursued this course and entered UCD, they would be able to move into the legal area at the end of the BBLS degree.  Two years later they discovered this is not the case.  There are ongoing negotiations between the Dean of the Law Faculty in UCD and Blackhall Place and the King's Inns in relation to exemptions.  The parents are very concerned that this may not happen.  Will the Minister lend his support to obtaining exemptions for students who entered the course with the view that this would <Col N="533" /> happen?  The students have asked me to raise this for them.</P>
      <P>It is a pity UCD did not do its homework before putting on a course.  I now take off my Senator's hat and put on my guidance counsellor's one.  I have to deal with this problem.  When one looks at the books, the impression is given, although it is not in writing, that students will be entitled to exemptions.  They are following five of the same subjects which are part of the law degree, the BCL. Law degree students get exemptions to Blackhall Place.  I ask that students in the Business and Legal Studies be given exemptions in five of the eight subjects needed for the entrance exam to Blackhall Place as this would make it a little easier for them.</P>
      <P>UCD had the philosophy that one could do postgraduate work in business or pursue a law postgraduate course after the BBLS but this has not happened and I am very concerned about this.  We need the backing of the Minister for UCD to pursue this.  Students of similar new courses in Limerick and Galway are entitled to exemptions.  I do not know why UCD is dragging its heels at this stage.  I would like to think we would be in a position to say that if UCD put on a course they should follow it through.  The students are very upset.  Some of them will qualify in the next year or two, wondering whether they can pursue courses in Blackhall Place or whether they will have to repeat all these subjects from scratch.  This does not make sense.  The purpose of this course was to provide two career paths for these students.  This is why I am asking the Minister for his support.  I appreciate he has come here late at night to listen to me.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LiamAylward" hpid="Minister of State at the Department of Education (Mr. Aylward) Liam Aylward">
      <NameTxt>Minister of State at the Department of Education (Mr. Aylward)</NameTxt>
      <P>I thank Senator Ormonde for raising this matter. Being the excellent Senator she is, I appreciate her interest in this case as in many others.  Unfortunately, this is not a matter for which the Minister for Education <Col N="534" /> has direct or immediate responsibility.</P>
      <P>As the House may be aware, the Honourable Society of King's Inns is the body which governs entry to the profession of barrister-at-law.  The society provides courses of education and training for students, conducts examinations and confers on students who reach the appropriate standard in these examinations the degree of barrister-at-law. The Incorporated Law Society is the representative body of the solicitors' profession. It exercises statutory functions under the Solicitors' Acts in relation to the education and training of solicitors.</P>
      <P>Both the King's Inns and the Law Society are autonomous bodies and receive no State funding in respect of their educational activities.  Entry requirements to courses of education and training at these institutions are a matter for the authorities of the institution concerned.</P>
      <P>As a constituent college of the National University of Ireland, University College, Dublin, is an autonomous self-governing institution.  The Minister for Education has, accordingly, no function in its day-to-day operation.  Exemptions which professional bodies give in respect of degrees from the National University of Ireland would be a matter for private negotiation between either the university or college and the bodies concerned.</P>
      <P>I have, however, had the matter taken up with the UCD Law Faculty by the Higher Education Authority.  I understand the Business and Legal Studies degree course commenced in October 1991 and that the first students will graduate in the summer of 1995.  I have also been informed through the Higher Education Authority that the course was not designed to qualify people for the legal profession.  The intention, it seems, was that graduates with both business and some legal training would be useful to commercial companies.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The UCD Law Faculty has assured the Higher Education Authority that at no <Col N="535" /> stage were students given to understand that exemptions would be given in respect of this degree by either the Law Society or the King's Inns.</P>
    <P>I understand, however, that because of the extent to which legal matters are covered by the course, many students have decided their future lies in the legal profession rather than in the commercial world.  Accordingly, I am informed that the UCD authorities applied to the Incorporated Law Society for exemption from the legal elements of their courses and expect a response to their application in the near future.  I will have further inquiries made in relation to the position regarding exemptions for courses at the <Col N="536" /> King's Inns and I will communicate directly with the Senator in the matter.</P>
    <P>I trust the foregoing information has been helpful to Senator Ormonde and I hope that this matter will turn out satisfactorily for the students concerned.  I assure the Senator that the Department will lend its support to this matter.</P>
    <Speaker pid="AnnOrmonde" hpid="Miss Ormonde Miss Ormonde">
      <NameTxt>Miss Ormonde</NameTxt>
      <P>I thank the Minister for that information.  I appreciate there are ongoing discussions but the fact that it has been aired by the Minister will enhance the case and make it an important issue.  I appreciate his efforts.</P>
      <P>The Seanad adjourned at 8.55 p.m. until 10.30 a.m. on Thursday, 17 February 1994.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
</Debate>