<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE Debate SYSTEM "../Debate.dtd"[]>
<Debate DocTitle="Seanad Debate" Day="Wed" Date="26" Month="Oct" Year="1994" Vol="141" No="4" DateIrish="Dé Céadaoin, 26 Deireadh Fómhair 1994" DateEnglish="Wednesday, 26 October 1994" House="S" CommitteeEng="" CommitteeIr="" SubNameEng="" cnum="0">
  <MainHeading Type="Prelude" LHead="" RHead="">
    <Title>
    </Title>
    <P>
      <Col N="489" /> Chuaigh an Cathaoirleach i gceannas ar 2.30 p.m.</P>
    <P Just="Center">
      <i>Paidir.</i>
    </P>
    <P Just="Center">
      <i>Prayer.</i>
    </P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Business" RHead="of Seanad">
    <Title>Business of Seanad.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFallon" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I have notice from Senator Taylor-Quinn that, on the motion for the Adjournment of the House today, she proposes to raise the following matter:</P>
      <P>The need for the Minister for Transport, Energy and Communications to outline the action the Government proposes to take to rectify the reduction of 8 per cent in traffic through Shannon Airport in the first nine months of this year; and the Government's view of the economic impact of this trend in the west and mid-west region.</P>
      <P>I have also received notice from Senator Finneran of the following matter:</P>
      <P>The need for the Minister for Health to urgently clarify the situation regarding the provision of alternative accommodation in Castlerea, Country Roscommon, for the patients in St. Patrick's Hospital following the Government decision to locate a prison in that hospital.</P>
      <P>I have also received notice from Senator Honan of the following matter:</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The need for the Minister for Transport, Energy and Communications to clarify the present position <Col N="490" /> of the new peat fired station in the midlands as outlined in the national plan.</P>
    <P>I regard the matters raised as suitable for discussion on the Adjournment.  I have selected Senators Taylor-Quinn and Finneran's matters and they will be taken at the conclusion of business. Senator Honan may give notice on another day of the matter she wishes to raise.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Order of" RHead="Business">
    <Title>Order of Business.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="GVWright" hpid="Mr. Wright Mr. Wright">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Wright</NameTxt>
      <P>Today's Order of Business is Item 1, the ACC Bank Bill, 1994 &mdash; all Stages between now and 6 p.m. with the agreement of the House &mdash; and Item 24 from 6 p.m. to 8 p.m.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MauriceManning" hpid="Mr. Manning Mr. Manning">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Manning</NameTxt>
      <P>Last week I asked the Leader of the House if he would give us a list of legislation to be taken this session. I did not press the point last Thursday but I had hoped he would indicate today what legislation will be taken this session.</P>
      <P>At this early stage in the session I would like to raise a point which is of concern to Members on all sides.  The newly reformed Oireachtas committees are so structured that Members of this House are excluded from three of the four main committees.  Members are denied an opportunity to participate in the most satisfactory aspect of the work of Parliament.  The Leader should see if a way can be found for Members of all parties to attend and participate at these three committees from which, for understandable reasons, we are now excluded.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PaschalMooney" hpid="Mr. Mooney Mr. Mooney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Mooney</NameTxt>
      <P>I support Senator Manning and I am delighted he has raised this point.  I raised this matter on a debate on the reform of the Houses when the committees were being instituted.  It seemed to be the thin end of the wedge as far as this House was concerned.  While the reforms were welcome and certainly contributed to the improvement of the mechanics of legislation <Col N="491" /> in the other House, they had no positive impact on the affairs of this House.  Rather they had a negative aspect as regards this House which Senator Manning outlined.</P>
      <P>It is an important issue that needs to be addressed although I am not sure how we can address it as it is a matter for the other House how it conducts its business.  I raised the point before and I am pleased that the leader of the Opposition group has now taken it on board. I hope we can progress towards an equitable resolution of the matter.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BillCotter" hpid="Mr. Cotter Mr. Cotter">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cotter</NameTxt>
      <P>Would it be possible for the Minister for Education to make a statement regarding the report she has ordered and received on the Letterkenny regional technical college? There is a lot of speculation about it and the good name of the college and its teaching staff needs to be restored because&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFallon" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Have you a question for the Leader?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BillCotter" hpid="Mr. Cotter Mr. Cotter">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cotter</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister was correct and I congratulate her on the action she has taken but the job is unfinished.  The speculation should be ended and the Minister should take the next step of clarifying all matters regarding the administration and management of the college.  She should do so in the two Houses of the Oireachtas as many here would be interested in the system of regional technical colleges&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFallon" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator, you are going on at length.  Have you a question for the Leader?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LouisBelton" hpid="Mr. Belton Mr. Belton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Belton</NameTxt>
      <P>It is a long story.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BillCotter" hpid="Mr. Cotter Mr. Cotter">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cotter</NameTxt>
      <P>Can we offer the Minister an opportunity to come into the House, tomorrow perhaps, to clarify the issue as a matter of urgency?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PaddyMcGowan" hpid="Mr. McGowan Mr. McGowan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGowan</NameTxt>
      <P>I support Senator Manning's comments regarding the lack <Col N="492" /> of involvement of this House in a number of important committees.  However, the issue cannot be discussed on the Order of Business.  Could the Leader of the House arrange an early date for a debate on the matter?  The issue is much wider than has been suggested because elected Members of this House are precluded from being, for example, chairmen of county enterprise boards.  I was chairman of the board of management of Letterkenny regional technical college for five years but I was excluded from the formation of the recent board largely because I am a Member of this House.  I resent that very strongly.</P>
      <P>We cannot do justice to this subject without holding a proper debate in this House.  There has been a lot of innuendo that the Labour Party is writing the agenda.  We find it hard to accept many of the statements being made.  It would help to clear the air if we were given the opportunity to state in this House that we are dissatisfied with our exclusion from a number of committees. I believe it is unconstitutional to exclude elected public representatives such as you, a Chathaoirligh, or me from a committee. There is no good reason for it.  I am not far from pushing my protest to that point.  First, however, I ask the Leader of the House to take this matter on board and to facilitate a debate on it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DanNeville" hpid="Mr. Neville Mr. Neville">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Neville</NameTxt>
      <P>When the Leader of the House replies to Senator Manning's question regarding the legislative programme for this term would he deal with Item 3 &mdash; Adoptive Leave Bill, 1993 &mdash; which is two weeks short of being one year on the Order Paper?  It got much attention when it was introduced and we were assured that all Stages would be completed by the end of November last year.  What is happening with that Bill and why has it been delayed for so long?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LouisBelton" hpid="Mr. Belton Mr. Belton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Belton</NameTxt>
      <P>Last week I asked the Leader of the House about the prospect of having a debate on the Price Waterhouse report.  Since then there has been a television programme on it so the <Col N="493" /> report is in the public domain.  Heretofore, we were led to believe that that was not the case.  Many matters were raised on that television programme and I am sure you, a Chathaoirligh, have been approached&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFallon" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>It is a big issue in Athlone.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LouisBelton" hpid="Mr. Belton Mr. Belton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Belton</NameTxt>
      <P>Will you thank me for raising it for you?</P>
      <P>It is a big issue as the Cathaoirleach has agreed.  I hope the Leader of the House will arrange for a debate on the matter in the not too distant future because many people are anxious about it.  The report cost £0.25 million.  The initial reason for seeking the report was to save money and the fact that the report has cost that sum is all the more reason for it being debated in this House.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidNorris" hpid="Mr. Norris Mr. Norris">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norris</NameTxt>
      <P>When will the refugee Bill be put on the Order Paper?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GVWright" hpid="Mr. Wright Mr. Wright">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Wright</NameTxt>
      <P>Tomorrow morning I will have the list of legislation to be dealt with during this session.  The Adoptive Leave Bill will be taken next week.  I will bring the comments about committees to the attention of the Government Chief Whip.  The issue of public representatives on public bodies and so forth mentioned by Senator McGowan might be a topic we could debate.  With regard to Senator Belton's request, the Chief Whip will contact the relevant Minister.  The same will apply to Senator Cotter's request.</P>
      <P>The time limits on Item 1 are 20 minutes for each spokesperson and 15 minutes for other contributors.</P>
      <P>Order of Business agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="ACC Bank Bill, 1994:" RHead="Second and Subsequent Stages">
    <Title>ACC Bank Bill, 1994: Second and Subsequent Stages.</Title>
    <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That the Bill be now read a Second Time.&rdquo;</P>
    <Col N="494" />
    <Speaker pid="SeanFallon" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>There will be a slight delay before the Minister arrives.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnDardis" hpid="Mr. Dardis Mr. Dardis">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dardis</NameTxt>
      <P>I would have expected the Minister for Transport, Energy and Communication to be delayed rather than the Minister for Finance.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="Bertie" hpid="Minister for Finance (Mr. B. Ahern) Bertie Ahern">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Finance (Mr. B. Ahern)</NameTxt>
      <P>This is a simple technical Bill with just one section, the purpose of which is to raise the limit on the borrowings which ACC Bank is permitted to undertake. At present this limit stands at £1,000 million; I propose to raise it to £1,400 million.</P>
      <P>I should point out that as far as the balance sheets of banks are concerned, &ldquo;borrowing&rdquo; includes not only what we instinctively recognise as such &mdash; that is, loans raised on the interbank markets and bonds and other debt instruments issued &mdash; but also the deposits of customers. When a bank accepts a deposit from a customer it is increasing its borrowing. This enables the bank to increase its lending and thus to increase its business.  In the case of ACC Bank these customer deposits constitute the vast bulk of borrowings.</P>
      <P>ACC Bank's recent level of growth has been such that there is a real possibility that the existing limit will be reached in the near future, perhaps by the end of the year.  At the end of December 1993 actual borrowings stood at £882 million.  The bank's business has grown significantly this year and it is necessary to ensure its operations are not curtailed by the present ceiling.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Before I deal with the level of the ceiling itself and the basis for the increase I am proposing, I will put the Bill into context for Senators by referring to the history and development of ACC Bank and its performance in recent years.  Senators will be aware the Agricultural Credit Corporation, as it was then known, was established in 1927 to provide medium and long term finance for farmers and farming co-operatives. At that time both categories of borrower found it difficult to raise funding from other sources.  The original <Col N="495" /> legislation restricted the corporation's activities to the agricultural sector.</P>
    <P>However, growth was slow.  During the 1960s new legislation was introduced permitting the ACC to accept deposits as well as obtain advances from the State.  The ACC quickly built up a significant deposit base and in the 1970s developed a nationwide network of branches.  This wider funding base allowed the ACC to extend its lending activities in response to greater demand for agricultural credit, especially following Ireland's entry into the European Community in 1973 when the agricultural sector grew strongly.</P>
    <P>The economic difficulties of the early 1980s adversely affected the agricultural sector with serious consequences for the ACC.  Bad debts and increases in arrears reduced the corporation's profitability. The extent of these consequences, largely resulting from the corporation's confinement to agricultural lending, was apparent in the heavy losses sustained in 1987.  The Agricultural Credit Act, 1988, sought to help address these problems, in particular through granting of powers to the corporation to widen the base of its operations in accordance with modern banking practice.</P>
    <P>In the following years the ACC turned the corner and is now heading for its seventh successive year of increasing profitability.  This process of recovery was aided by the passage of the ACC Bank Act, 1992, which removed entirely the remaining restriction on lending outside the agriculture sector.  That Act also changed the name of the organisation to the ACC Bank plc to reflect the enhanced orientation to sectors of the economy other than agriculture and agri-business.  It also increased the authorised share capital from £35 million to £50 million, and raised the limit on borrowing from £800 million to £1,000 million.  Finally, the 1992 Act brought the ACC Bank within the prudential supervision of the Central Bank.  This means that the ACC Bank is now subject to the same rules <Col N="496" /> as apply to the other credit institutions supervised by the Central Bank.  These rules relate in the main to capital adequacy, liquidity, categories of exposure, permissible charges and deposit guarantee.</P>
    <P>As I have already indicated, an increase in the statutory borrowing limit of ACC Bank is required because without it the bank would have to cease increasing its deposits and adding to its other forms of borrowing.  This would correspondingly limit its capacity to increase lending to its customers.</P>
    <P>This impasse would obviously be unacceptable, as it would amount to imposing an unnecessary and discriminatory restriction on the bank's operations. That is why I am now proposing to raise the ceiling to accommodate the operational needs of the bank.</P>
    <P>The proposed increase in the limit is £400 million.  At the average rate of growth which has obtained in recent years, this should cover the bank's requirements for the next three or four years.  However, if recent trends are maintained, the new ceiling could be reached in as little as two years.</P>
    <P>This Bill addresses the needs of ACC Bank as they stand at present.  If there are any developments in the banking sector which involve or fundamentally affect the operation of the bank, appropriate measures, including the introduction of legislation, will be taken as the need arises.</P>
    <P>The present Bill is purely technical and is in no way related to the possible restructuring of the State banks.  There are no hidden links with or implications for the restructuring of the State banks. As Senators will be aware, I have received the report of the consultants whom I appointed to advise me on the options available in respect of the goals underpinning the Programme for a Partnership Government in relation to the development of the banking sector.  I am at present examining that report and hope to be in a position to bring the matter to Government at an early date.</P>
    <P>In the interim, I have to deal with the <i>status quo</i> and this dictates that if the <Col N="497" /> ACC Bank is not to be hampered in its development, it requires an immediate increase in its borrowing limit.  It is in any case highly unlikely that any change in the position of ACC Bank, if that were what the Government should decide, could be implemented in the short period between now and the end of this parliamentary session, by which time the increases in the borrowing limit will be required if present trends continue.</P>
    <P>This, then, is a technical Bill.  I commend it to the House.</P>
    <Speaker pid="ShaneRoss" hpid="Mr. Ross Mr. Ross">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Ross</NameTxt>
      <P>I am always very suspicious when a Minister comes to the House and emphasises that the Bill is technical. While it is strictly true that this Bill is only technical, it also has significance for the banking sector because this is the third time in the last six years that we have had an ACC Bill come before the House.  We should ask ourselves why we had to have at least two technical Bills and one more substantial one on the ACC.  A Bill in 1988 gave it fuller powers to expand outside the agriculture sector, a Bill in 1992 extended its borrowing limits and we now have a Bill to further extend these limits.</P>
      <P>The Minister should answer a number of questions.  Why is the limit being set at £1.4 billion?  Why is it not higher?  Is he likely to come back to the House, as he said in his speech, in two years time to ask us to extend this limit further?  It seems unnecessary for us to go through this procedure every two or three years. This indicates that the Government has a very piecemeal and temporary &mdash; pragmatic if you like &mdash; attitude to the State banks, ACC Bank and the ICC because it does not know what it wants to do with them.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>From time to time, the banks hit their ceiling on their borrowing limits and they tell the Department they must have a bigger borrowing limit, therefore a Bill must go through the House.  That means it is not a technical Bill but a serious one.  It also means there is serious mismanagement and lack of foresight in the Department and among <Col N="498" /> the Minister and politicians about what they intend to do with the State banks. If we knew what was going to happen with State banks, we would not have to rush through this Bill every two or three years so that the bank can operate under normal commercial criteria.</P>
    <P>Stokes Kennedy Crowley has looked at this problem and has sent a report to the Minister.  We are due &mdash; in the language we are used to in politics &mdash; an early decision on this.  In view of the history of this bank &mdash; it was founded in the 1920s and it had a difficult time because it lost a lot of money in the 1980s, after which it was subsidised by the Government, and then suddenly in 1988 it burst into profits &mdash; we are due an explanation about its new role.  The Minister should tell us if the bank was up for sale under the last Government, as was commonly believed.  Was it up for sale under the Fianna Fáil-Progressive Democrat Government, as was the ICC?  Because Fianna Fáil is in Government with someone else, is it no longer for sale but up for a type of merger?  It is a pity the opportunity was not taken by the Minister to tell us what is his thinking and that of the Government on this issue.  Can the bank be privatised or sold?  Will it not be part of this mythical and mysterious third force about which we hear so much?</P>
    <P>It would not be fair to be totally critical of ACC Bank today in a speech of this sort because ACC Bank, having been given an opportunity in 1988 to expand into the commercial industrial world and the restrictions having been lifted from it, took full advantage of that and has been successful in turning a loss into a profit.  As the Minister knows, ACC Bank returned a creditable profit last year of approximately £11 million. It has now approximately 3 per cent of the banking market share in Ireland.  It has a staff of approximately 800 people. It pays the Government £2 million a year in dividends and it has made a great investment in its staff.  Approximately £1,000 per member of staff per annum is made by ACC Bank in its future.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="499" /> We should acknowledge its performance, particularly as ACC Bank has got the State monkey on its back and it is not operating as a normal commercial bank.  Its board is appointed by the State and it has restrictions imposed on it because it is State owned both in the commercial and in the political world. In the circumstances in which it operates, ACC Bank has done well in recent years.</P>
    <P>Perhaps the Minister could answer a question about the £11 million profits last year.  According to its annual report, £1.6 million of the £11 million comes from trading investments.  I think it is correct to say that this is trading gilts in the gilt market.  In the normal commercial world, that is a great performance because it is an increase in profits from £500,000 to £1.6 million for ACC Bank, part of which it pays to the Government in the form of a dividend.  However, it is a little absurd for a State bank to be making some of its profits out of punting against the State from gilts owned by the State and then be paying some of that money back to the Government.  I would be interested to hear the Minister's comments.</P>
    <P>What is happening here is that ACC Bank is actually making direct money trading Government stock at the expense of the Government and the taxpayer, taking it on board as a profit for itself and then paying it back to the Government in the form of a dividend. It seems absurd that the State bank should be punting in State securities.  It is a circular movement which is utterly pointless because all of the money ends up in the same place.  It may be good training for the commercial world but it is one of the anomalies of the State banks that they should be indulging in this sort of activity.  I would be interested to hear the Minister's comments on that.</P>
    <P>The most important issue in the debate about the future of ACC Bank is on page 12 of its annual report.  The chairman of ACC Bank pays tribute to <Col N="500" /> all the staff by saying that &ldquo;All the employees of the Bank can take credit for these results and are to be congratulated for concentrating fully on the bank's business when other issues could have distracted their attention&rdquo;.  That is the sort of language chairmen and chief executives of semi-State banks always use when they are sending little hints of discontent to the Government but are frightened of saying they are fed up with what is going on.  They never say it in the outspoken language they might use in a private company.</P>
    <Speaker pid="Bertie" hpid="Mr. B. Ahern Mr. B. Ahern">
      <NameTxt>Mr. B. Ahern</NameTxt>
      <P>If that person was the chairman of a private company he would not say anything or he would lose his head.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ShaneRoss" hpid="Mr. Ross Mr. Ross">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Ross</NameTxt>
      <P>Is that a threat or is it a&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="Bertie" hpid="Mr. B. Ahern Mr. B. Ahern">
      <NameTxt>Mr. B. Ahern</NameTxt>
      <P>No, but the Senator should keep the balance&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ShaneRoss" hpid="Mr. Ross Mr. Ross">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Ross</NameTxt>
      <P>That is a statement of fact. However, this is the language he used and the Minister knows&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="Bertie" hpid="Mr. B. Ahern Mr. B. Ahern">
      <NameTxt>Mr. B. Ahern</NameTxt>
      <P>There is an element of democracy when one is dealing in the State sector.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ShaneRoss" hpid="Mr. Ross Mr. Ross">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Ross</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister knows what the chief executive meant by that comment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DickRoche" hpid="Mr. Roche Mr. Roche">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Roche</NameTxt>
      <P>The chief executive knows what the Minister meant.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ShaneRoss" hpid="Mr. Ross Mr. Ross">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Ross</NameTxt>
      <P>What the Minister meant was that the uncertainty surrounding the future of this and other State banks has made it more difficult for them to operate in the commercial world.  The chief executive is saying that the staff have done an extremely good job in the circumstances in which ACC Bank finds itself.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>ACC Bank has been lumbered with the threat of being shoved into a third force in banking against its will since the formation of this Government.  Everybody knows there was a commitment in <Col N="501" /> the Programme for a Partnership Government for a third force in banking, which is now causing extreme difficulty for the present Government because it knows that is not practical.  It also finds that ACC Bank does not want to be a part of it, the Fianna Fáil Party does not believe in it and the Labour Party does not really know what it wants.  In the middle is the poor ACC bank which is going to be kicked around from Billy to Jack.  Eventually, there will be some sort of political compromise, but the people who will not be considered will be the banks who are doing their best.  What the chief executive is saying is that it is difficult for the staff to operate when they could be distracted by other issues.</P>
    <P>Unfortunately, that particular artificial institution which the State is threatening to form, but which it cannot do because nobody really wants to be part of it, is causing great difficulties. What the Government has done is to ask for a report from Stokes Kennedy Crowley.  I do not quarrel with the fact that the Minister has done that because Stokes Kennedy Crowley is a reputable company and will no doubt produce a good report.  Perhaps he could tell us, however, what will be the cost of this report.  If any of the banks being considered &mdash; that is the TSB, ICC and ACC &mdash; wants to opt out of this extraordinary arrangement, which after all is only some sort of ideological nonsense invented by the Labour Party to put something in the Programme for a Partnership Government because they could not find anything else &mdash; perhaps he could tell us if they should get the option to do so.  Maybe the Minister could give a guarantee to ICC, which I understand wants to be part of this arrangement, and ACC that if they do not want to be part of this arrangement they will not be forced to.</P>
    <P>As the Minister will know, plenty of people are interested in buying, or merging with, ACC and ICC, but that is for very good reasons.  One of the reasons ACC does not wish to be part of this clumsy conglomerate is that they <Col N="502" /> see it as a mechanism for laying off staff. I find it strange that the Labour Party &mdash; the party that trumpets full employment, worries about people's jobs day and night, and wrings its hands about wages and salaries in the State sector &mdash; wants to rationalise all the State banks to such an extent that many people will be laid off and put on the dole queues. That is the only sense in rationalising TSB, ICC and ACC.  The effect of such a merger will be that where there is duplication, which there undoubtedly is, between the State-owned banks, it will be removed and so more people will be unemployed.</P>
    <P>What has happened here is an ill thought out conflict between those socialists who still remain in the Labour Party&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    <Speaker pid="LouisBelton" hpid="Mr. Belton Mr. Belton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Belton</NameTxt>
      <P>It is difficult to find them.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ShaneRoss" hpid="Mr. Ross Mr. Ross">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Ross</NameTxt>
      <P>It is difficult to find them, but you find them from time to time &mdash; on the back benches I hasten to add.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LouisBelton" hpid="Mr. Belton Mr. Belton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Belton</NameTxt>
      <P>In Wicklow.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ShaneRoss" hpid="Mr. Ross Mr. Ross">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Ross</NameTxt>
      <P>There is a conflict for those who ideologically hate all banks so much, and particularly the big banks, that they want to create a third force to compete with them and teach them manners, and the difficulties they find themselves in when creating this third force efficiently in that they are going to have to lay people off and create more unemployment.  It is a difficulty which Lenin, Trotsky, Marx and all the others found when they tried to create artificial State institutions.  That always happens. It cannot be done in practice.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>You will not create a third force in banking which will successfully compete with the banks if you do it artificially and this is what is happening here.  It has taken an extraordinarily long time for this ingredient of the ill-fated Programme for a Partnership Government to come into existence because it is not really going to happen the way they promised.  It sounded good at the time, and kept a few people happy on the <Col N="503" /> Labour Party back benches but in practice it does not work.</P>
    <P>The Minister will know that this bank, which is competing successfully in a small way with the major banks, not only does not want to go into a forced friendship with the other banks but it has been looked at, talked to, and examined by foreign banks.  A logical arrangement has been proposed whereby a European Bank, Crédit Agricole, which has looked at ACC Bank, would get involved in a joint venture. The great advantage of a joint venture with Crédit Agricole is that the real difficulty for ACC Bank, as the chief executive says in this report, is going to be raising capital in the near future.  It is difficult for a State bank to raise capital because it is hamstrung, but there is one way.  The bank can go back to the Government and ask it, as the 99 per cent shareholder, to give the bank the money required for expansion.  Even the Labour Party would not be able to give it any more capital.  If ACC Bank is to have any future, it must lie in its ability to increase its capital base.</P>
    <P>Crédit Agricole has offered to provide the necessary capital but the Labour Party has a terrible fear of foreigners, as they proved with Greencore and others, and is probably opposed to any such arrangement with a foreign bank.  They do not like foreign capital coming to this country; they prefer to keep banks here small, cosy and provincial. This xenophobia will block this arrangement and stop the progress of ACC Bank.</P>
    <P>That is a pity but the Minister may be able to enlighten us on pending progress. It is more likely he will say he is considering bringing that report to Government in the near future with recommendations and returning to us. maybe in two years time, looking for an extension of borrowings for ACC Bank.</P>
    <P>I have some specific questions about this bank.  The directors' fees in a State organisation of this type make it almost impossible for them to compete with the private sector.  It is a problem to which <Col N="504" /> nobody has produced a solution.  The chief executive of this bank is paid £58,000 per annum and the directors are paid £4,000 per annum.  This compares very unfavourably with the private sector. I believe the answer is to privatise this and other banks so they can compete without their hands tied behind their backs.</P>
    <P>The Irish Permanent Building Society will be a direct competitor of this bank. It is going public tomorrow with a new arrangement whereby its chief executive will be paid £201,000 per annum and its non-executive directors will be paid £20,000 per annum.  The Minister may reply by saying that these are unjustified fees and I would agree with him.</P>
    <Speaker pid="Bertie" hpid="Mr. B. Ahern Mr. B. Ahern">
      <NameTxt>Mr. B. Ahern</NameTxt>
      <P>One cannot do much about it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ShaneRoss" hpid="Mr. Ross Mr. Ross">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Ross</NameTxt>
      <P>Exactly.  However the Minister can release the directors of his own banks from the extraordinary yoke around their necks.  There is no way we will get seriously competent directors on terms which are about 25 per cent the value of the best paid people in the private sector unless they are very dedicated people, which I am sure they are. This is a serious problem.  I do not say it as a criticism of the Minister but as something which must be highlighted.</P>
      <P>Bonuses in the semi-State sector are also very small while in the private sector, and in the case of the Irish Permanent, they rise to 50 per cent of annual salaries.  Bonuses in the semi-State sector under the new system are in the region of 10 or 15 per cent.  There are other perks available in the private sector including options and medical insurance which may or may not be available in the public sector.</P>
      <P>All these factors act against the best interests of the State banks.  While they are supposed to be competing commercially, they are competing at an enormous disadvantage.  The logical answer is for the Minister to privatise or consider privatising these two banks and not continue State ownership.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="505" /> I would like to ask the Minister a specific question.  What instructions were given to State banks during the devaluation crisis?  Were they allowed or encouraged to act freely in selling Irish pounds during that period against the wishes of the Government?  I ask because at the time there was, and could be again, a difficulty for banks which were put under a great deal of moral pressure not to move against the Irish pound against their best commercial instincts.  Some banks did move while others did not and there was a certain amount of unpleasantness against those who sold Irish pounds &mdash; to my mind, it was justifiable.</P>
    <P>Presumably State banks come under a slightly different category in this case because they take direct instructions and it would be unusual for them to sell Irish pounds if the Government does not want them to do so.  If they do not do so, adverse restrictions and difficulties are imposed on them which means they are non-commercial when part of their profit comes from trading in the markets.  I would like the Minister to answer that question.  Will State banks deal in Irish currency as freely as other banks in the future?</P>
    <Speaker pid="DickRoche" hpid="Mr. Roche Mr. Roche">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Roche</NameTxt>
      <P>In the light of forthcoming legislation, it will not be too long before we must declare our interest when we listen to Senator Ross because, to say the least, he is amusing.  He did at least two full flips of the circuit because he went from attacking the Labour Party to concern for employees of ACC Bank and the horrific threat of privatisation to suggesting that it should immediately be privatised.  He is always great value and in a few years will have to declare that we had the privilege of listening to him and work out what financial value we could put on that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The Minister outlined the historical background to this Bill.  It is interesting to look at the history of the ACC, which was created in 1927 for precisely one of the reasons we should argue for a third force in banking.  This bank was created &mdash; as in the case of ICC &mdash; because the <Col N="506" /> then commercial banks were reluctant, in fact they refused downright in the case of ACC, to deal with agricultural enterprise.  The State created ACC and ICC in order to put some competition into the banking sector.  That is a historical fact and an interesting example of how we can move full circle.</P>
    <P>There are good and cogent reasons, not ideological ones, for the creation of a third force in banking.  Senator Ross and I would agree that if ideology and practicality were to compete, we would both support the practical rather than ideological approach to State enterprise. Arguments for and against the creation of the sustaining of State enterprise have never been informed by an ideological debate but by what is practical at the particular time.</P>
    <P>As the Minister said, ACC has had a long and chequered history since its foundation.  It was not until the 1970s that we saw any growth in the company. The company expanded its business dramatically in the 1970s, some would say imprudently.  Many public representatives like the Cathaoirleach and I came across the debris of that imprudent expansion.  Farmers and those in the agriculture business were encouraged by ACC to extend their credit and to behave in a manner which was imprudent. At the end of that period and into the 1980s, ACC found itself in a situation where, if it had been a private bank, it would not have been allowed to operate. It had exceeded every limitation placed on the private sector.  The ACC fell from grace at that time and it has taken them a long time to rebuild that trust, particularly in the agricultural community.</P>
    <P>The arrangements in this Bill are designed to rebuild the trust that the bank established in its 50 years of operation up to the mid-1970s.  In fairness to the company and to all concerned with the company, they have done that since the 1988 legislation.  Senator Ross mentioned three sets of legislation.  The 1988 legislation was successful in that it allowed the company to restructure and get back on to a prudent base.  Senator <Col N="507" /> Ross was not suggesting that the legislation itself was a failure, but he was questioning the need to come before the Oireachtas from time to time with legislation. He is wrong in that, and I will come back to that in a moment.</P>
    <P>The 1992 Act, which effectively restructured the company, made it more like a bank.  The legislation gave the corporation the right to call itself the ACC Bank and removed the restrictions then applying to lending outside the agricultural sector.  The bank was able to extend its portfolio and has done so prudently. It changed the organisation's name to ACC Bank, moving it psychologically away from agri-business or farming.  It provided that the bank would come under the prudential supervision of the Central Bank in view of the bank's own behaviour in the 1970s.  That was a warranted decision and a wise one.  The bank is profitable at present because there have been a number of legislative changes and because a number of Ministers in different administrations have forced the bank to rethink the whole way it operates.</P>
    <P>It would be wise at this stage in our development to look for a new role for the State banks.  It is no longer logical to argue that there should be a separate industrial credit bank and a separate agricultural credit bank, both owned by the State and both in effect competing with each other.  There is another course of action which could be taken now.  The way to look at it, not from an ideological but from a practical point of view, is to see if the three banks &mdash; ACC, ICC and TSB &mdash; perhaps in some partnership, could be built into a third banking force. This is not said for any ideological reasons &mdash; Senator Ross knows me well enough in that regard &mdash; but it seems to me that there is a need to create an additional force in banking in this State.</P>
    <P>Look at the issue of bank charges, for example.  Every Member of this House, every member of the community who has a bank account and who is not able to keep it continuously in the black knows that we are being raided continuously <Col N="508" /> by the major clearing banks. There needs to be some break in that cartel.  I accept &mdash; and Senator Ross made the point very validly &mdash; that it would be very difficult to construct a third force of sufficient size to break the cartel; but some competition, even from a relative minnow in that particular field, would be better than none.  The idea of a third banking force is a good idea and one which at least warrants exploration.  The creation of a corporation owned partly by the State and partly by the private sector would be very prudent.</P>
    <P>In his contribution, Senator Ross raised an issue that was raised in the other House.  That is the question of the limits that are being placed in this Bill. Why a limit of £1.4 billion, he asks.  Why have a limit at all?  The imposition of a limit is a very prudent course of action and the Bill gets it right.  It is impossible to know how many years it will take ACC to hit against the ceiling again, but I believe that it is better and more prudent, if the State is to stay in the public sector, to subject the bank to regular reviews in both Houses of the Oireachtas.  If we were to increase that borrowing requirement to £2 billion, for example &mdash; Senator Ross did not mention a figure of £2 billion but we will take that as an example, it is more or less double the present limit &mdash; it would mean that it would be a very long time before there would be any reason to bring this bank before the Houses of the Oireachtas to examine its operations in detail.  I accept, of course, that a committee of both Houses should be doing that, but we all know there are certain weaknesses there.</P>
    <P>The Minister holds 100 per cent of the shares in the bank at present and the arrangement whereby the ceiling forces the Minister, and the bank, to appear before the House is good and prudent. I hope the Minister will hold fast to this £1.4 billion borrowing ceiling if anybody makes any recommendations otherwise. If he were to do otherwise it would effectively mean that this bank would be placed outside the direct scrutiny of <Col N="509" /> both Houses for a long period of time. This would be a mistake, and if Senator Ross rethinks his contribution in this respect he will be aware of this.</P>
    <P>When he was quoting from page 12 of the last ACC annual report, it appeared that Senator Ross, uncharacteristically, was going to ditch his personal interest in privatisation.  If we are to go the privatisation route with this bank, something with which I would have no difficulty, and if it is able to make a positive contribution, the State should review its position from time to time, and the need for having the bank should be reviewed. If it is concluded that the bank has served its useful purpose within the public sector, that is, if it did all that it was set up to do in 1927 and subsequently, and if it would be regarded as prudent to release the funds by privatisation for other public investment, then I would not oppose this course of action. However, it would not be prudent &mdash; and in this I differ from Senator Ross &mdash; to sell off the ACC and the ICC to the best bidder, because in the longer term this would mean that such competition as they provide would effectively be taken out of the banking sector.</P>
    <P>This is a technical Bill and it requires a great deal of discussion.  In addition it raises other issues.  The issue of the third banking force is one which should be discussed, and it should be discussed in an environment removed as far as possible from pure ideology.  Our partners in Government and those who have argued for a third banking force have not done so purely as a piece of ideology, and it is unfair to suggest otherwise. As a proposition, it has many merits, and as a proposition it demands&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    <Speaker pid="ShaneRoss" hpid="Mr. Ross Mr. Ross">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Ross</NameTxt>
      <P>God forgive the Senator.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DickRoche" hpid="Mr. Roche Mr. Roche">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Roche</NameTxt>
      <P>It would appear that Senator Ross is having some kind of attack again.  The proposition in itself demands a little more rigorous examination than it has been subjected to in the House.  I commend the Bill.  The course of action taken by the Minister in the Bill is prudent.  I agree with the imposition <Col N="510" /> of a limitation or a ceiling which, if the company stays in the public sector, requires it and the Minister to return to this House and the other House for regular scrutiny.  The Bill should be supported by all sides of the House.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PaddyBurke" hpid="Mr. Burke Mr. Burke">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Burke</NameTxt>
      <P>Since 1927-28 the ACC has served the country well; it has served the farming community excellently since its establishment in the 1920s.  However, where does the future of the ACC lie now?  It is uncertain. How often will the Minister return to the House regarding matters such as this?</P>
      <P>Some may consider that the proposal to raise the limit to £1,400 million is a trivial matter to put before this House and the other House.  However, it is only right that such a proposal be put before the House, because in other instances the powers of public representatives have been eroded.  Indeed, Senator Mooney has remarked that the power of the local representative has been eroded substantially over the past number of years.</P>
      <P>This is one instance where the Minister and the ACC must appear before public representatives.  It is only right that they should do so, as we are answerable to the people.  In addition, too many agencies have been established over the past number of years which have not been answerable to anybody. Senator Mooney raised a very important matter recently, which should be debated in this House and brought to the attention of the relevant Ministers &mdash; that power should be handed back to public representatives and that we should have more powers.  The powers of public representatives have been eroded over the last number of years.  I am delighted that this Bill has come before us.  We are able to scrutinise the functions and dealings of ACC Bank and it is answerable to this House.  I concur with the Senator in this regard.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>There is no doubt that ACC Bank has provided an excellent service for the farming community in particular.  In 1988 its powers were expanded to areas <Col N="511" /> outside of farming, as the Minister stated.  I was delighted with that and it has given it the base to increase its profits and to stabilise it in the market place.  It has performed excellently over the last few years.  Perhaps we should give more powers to ACC Bank.  It does not want to be part of a third banking force.  It has performed excellently since 1988 and there is a valid reason why it should not form part of the third banking force.</P>
    <P>In relation to the third banking force, if the TSB, ACC and ICC merged, would they give us a competitive edge and would they be competitive enough to challenge the Bank of Ireland and the AIB?  I doubt it very much because they would still be a smaller banking force than the Ulster Bank.  In that regard, they still would not be a major force in Irish banking.</P>
    <P>While the programmes for competitiveness and for Government will cause some headaches if a third banking force is formed, if the ACC, ICC and TSB merge there will certainly be job losses. That, as Senator Ross pointed out, would be against all the principles of the Labour Party.  I would not want to see any reduction of the staff of the ACC or ICC.  Both have served the country excellently since they were formed.  The ACC, in particular, has gone through some very tough times in supporting the farming community when it was in serious disarray during the early to mid 1980s.  Its remit was widened in 1988 to give it extended powers and the basis to extend its banking facilities.  It has done that in an exceptional fashion, for which it should be complimented.</P>
    <P>The ICC has the facility to lend moneys to the small business community and new businesses at the reduced rate of 6 per cent in certain circumstances. I wish to ask the Minister if this facility is available to ACC Bank.  If it is not, it should be because otherwise ACC Bank is working at a disadvantage. The Bank of Ireland has introduced its own incentives where it can lend money to certain small businesses <Col N="512" /> and new businesses at the reduced rate of 6 per cent.  The ICC can do the same.</P>
    <P>I have no problem with granting the extra facility to increase the limits on ACC Bank's borrowings to £1,400 million. It has performed exceptionally over the last number of years and I have no doubt that it will continue to do so.  We should not hinder it in any way.  I wish ACC Bank the best in its efforts because I have no doubt that the functions with which we are empowering it are in good hands.  We have no need to worry about ACC Bank.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JimTownsend" hpid="Mr. Townsend Mr. Townsend">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Townsend</NameTxt>
      <P>I am sorry that Senator Ross has left because I note that he spent more of his time giving a lecture to the Labour Party and talking about the third banking force than on the Bill.  If Senator Ross started praising the Labour Party I would be really worried because he is the kind of person whom in the country we describe as an expert on everything who knows very little about anything.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFallon" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator McGowan has a name for a man like that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DickRoche" hpid="Mr. Roche Mr. Roche">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Roche</NameTxt>
      <P>A &ldquo;boxerologist&rdquo;.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JimTownsend" hpid="Mr. Townsend Mr. Townsend">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Townsend</NameTxt>
      <P>I will try to confine my comments to the Bill.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnDardis" hpid="Mr. Dardis Mr. Dardis">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dardis</NameTxt>
      <P>The Senator will not be speaking for long if that is the case.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JimTownsend" hpid="Mr. Townsend Mr. Townsend">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Townsend</NameTxt>
      <P>I welcome the proposal to increase the borrowings of ACC Bank from £1,000 million to £1,400 million.  It is a welcome sign that ACC Bank should be looking to do so. It is a sign that the economy, especially the agricultural sector, is on the way up. According to the Bill, the term &ldquo;borrowing&rdquo; means the sum total of deposits placed with ACC Bank and all other forms of borrowing.  If this Bill was not passed, ACC Bank would have to cease to increase its deposits and add further to its forms of borrowing.  In other words, people who wished to deposit <Col N="513" /> money with ACC Bank would not be able to do so.</P>
      <P>If the present borrowing level of £1,000 million was reached before the Bill became law it would place ACC Bank at a great disadvantage in comparison with the other banks.  It would also place people who have deposited their money there over the years at a great disadvantage.  If the Bill was not passed it would reduce competition between the banks, which would not be in the national interest.  More competition is required in the banking sector rather than less.</P>
      <P>ACC Bank has served this country well, especially the agricultural sector. The Minister said that this is a simple, technical Bill.  It is also a commonsense Bill, which has been brought forward by a commonsense Minister.  I particularly welcome the assurance given by the Minister today that:</P>
      <P>The present Bill is purely technical and is in no way related to the possible restructuring of the State banks. There are no hidden links with or implications for the restructuring of the State banks.</P>
      <P>I welcome this Bill.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnDardis" hpid="Mr. Dardis Mr. Dardis">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dardis</NameTxt>
      <P>I join in welcoming the Minister to the House.  The Bill is very straightforward and I welcome it.  I agree with the Minister's observations that there should not be a limit on ACC Bank's operations by virtue of the ceiling which is imposed.  I also do not see anything wrong with returning to the House on a regular basis to increase that ceiling rather than leaving it open ended, as some people have suggested.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>We owe a considerable debt of gratitude to ACC Bank.  I can say that on a personal level because I have been a client of that bank since the late 1960s. I know that my farming operation would not have received the necessary funding if ACC Bank had not been there, which I think is true for many farmers.  We do not have to go back very far to remember a time when farmers in <Col N="514" /> general were treated with extreme scepticism by the Associated Banks.  It is probable that they are still treated with extreme scepticism, but at one time it was almost the case that collateral was all that counted.  Now, thankfully, one must show some ability to repay.  I do not agree with a point made by Senator Roche that ACC Bank was introduced as a competitor to the Associated Banks.  I do not think that was the case. It was introduced for a different reason &mdash; to promote the growth of the industry. It was never of a scale that it could successfully compete on a commercial level with&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    <Speaker pid="DickRoche" hpid="Mr. Roche Mr. Roche">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Roche</NameTxt>
      <P>I think the Senator misheard me.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnDardis" hpid="Mr. Dardis Mr. Dardis">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dardis</NameTxt>
      <P>I apologise if that is so but I wrote down what I thought I heard.  It was not a competitor of the large Associated Banks, although it gingered them up.  It allowed Irish agriculture to develop and grow when Ireland joined the European Community by giving adequate funding to farmers for productive purposes.</P>
      <P>The Minister will correct me if I am wrong but I understand the bank enjoys approximately 2.5 per cent of the banking market and that it intends to increase its share to 4 per cent over the coming five years.  It has expanded into areas outside its traditional remit but I would not like it to expand to the extent where its agricultural ethos is abandoned. The agricultural ethos, which drove the bank and its staff over several decades, was a most positive influence for national change and investment and for the benefit of the company.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The Minister pointed out that this is the seventh successive year in which ACC Bank has returned a profit.  This is a welcome development for the Minister. There are other State bodies that could learn fruitful lessons from ACC Bank's management and way of operation, given that it turned itself around at a difficult time.  There was a hangover of bad debt from the end of the 1970s, when there was much injudicious borrowing <Col N="515" /> by farmers and others and interest rates increased to a particularly high level, and people had difficulty repaying those debts.  There was a significant overhang of bad debt which was dealt with effectively.  This a model in terms of looking at other State bodies.</P>
    <P>Reference was made to the large salaries paid to people in other areas of banking and building societies.  We are still entitled to expect that there are people who have enough patriotism and interest in the development of their country to make a significant input to the boards of companies, such as ACC Bank, for not a great deal of reward.  I am not sure it is necessary to have substantial sums of money available to people who are prepared to serve on these boards, although that is not to say they should not be rewarded.  They should be rewarded but I occasionally wonder about the extent of the reward that is required to reimburse people who should be there to work in the service of the country and help out the State.</P>
    <P>I am a little unclear about the State guarantee to borrowers.  I am sure the Minister will clarify the matter for me. How far does that guarantee to the borrowers extend?  Was it restricted to £800 million or is it in excess of that figure? Does it now become £1,400 million to the depositors in ACC Bank?</P>
    <P>It is unquestionable that the bank had to take the road it took, by diversifying into other areas, in order to survive and grow.  We are all aware of what has happened to Irish agriculture over the past 20 years in terms of the decline of the numbers on the land and the decline of the business of many of the people still on the land.  From that point of view, it was quite sensible that ACC Bank should look to other areas within the commercial banking sector to generate profits and create growth.  It was unquestionable that growth would not continue if agriculture remained its sole business.  However, I return to the point that agriculture should remain its core business rather than its sole business <Col N="516" /> and it should retain its agricultural ethos.</P>
    <P>It may be required to find a partner. I have no ideological problem with looking outside the country for a like-minded partner.  One can think of plenty of examples of suitable like-minded partners for ACC Bank, such as Crédit Agricole in France.  I noted a point made by the Minister in his speech.  I accept that there are no hidden links with or implications for the restructuring of the State banks in terms of this legislation.  The agricultural ethos is worth preserving.  If ACC Bank looks for a partner, the one to seek is probably one which shares something of the same ethos in Europe and one which is a credible partner.  Crédit Agricole is just one of that nature.</P>
    <P>I hope ACC Bank continues to grow and develop and that this legislation assists it to do so.  Regarding the third banking force, in the event that Ulster Bank or the National Australia Bank Group take over the TSB, there is obviously somebody left on the sideline who will be looking for a partner or who may have some predatory instincts.  Perhaps they will look to ACC Bank.  What are the Minister's views about linking up with partners of that nature or with partners outside the country?  Much has been said about the third banking force, much of which is ideologically driven.  If such a force developed I question whether it would be a significant competitor to the Associated Banks and put balance into the lending market, as we would hope.  It is questionable whether it will have that effect.  I welcome the legislation and it will not be obstructed on this side of the House.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PaddyMcGowan" hpid="Mr. McGowan Mr. McGowan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGowan</NameTxt>
      <P>I welcome this important Bill.  It is a pity that those who oppose the Government use every vehicle to knock, criticise and be destructive rather than supportive.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I come from a part of Ireland which depends largely on agriculture.  In that context, this is a healthy piece of legislation. If ACC Bank now finds it necessary to increase its capital provision, it <Col N="517" /> is a healthy signal to the farming community. I do not want to reflect on any bank but ACC Bank weathered the storm on behalf of farmers who were caught in a difficult period.  Twenty years ago people were urged to buy land at high prices.  ACC Bank was to the fore in supporting the development of farms through the merger of small farms.  It played a major role in that regard.  ACC Bank carried many farmers through the later recession and our thanks and gratitude should go to it.</P>
    <P>Most of us who are aware of the difficulties faced by farmers appreciate the contribution of ACC Bank down the years.  I particularly welcome the healthy picture presented by the Minister. All credit is due to the Minister for his response to ACC Bank's request. This is positive legislation and I am delighted to support it.  Whether one speculates that there will be a merger between ACC Bank and another bank or that ACC will be sold, everybody will want to see ACC Bank being strong enough to stand on its own and to be in a strong negotiating position.</P>
    <P>This measure indicates that ACC Bank will be able to negotiate should the need arise, and that it will also be able to survive and continue to support the agriculture industry.  This is important now as we will shortly reach a position where there will not be continuing support for agricultural development from Europe.  We need a bank that understands and will take into account the difficulties of the farming community, for example, in cases where plans do not work out due to weather conditions, price changes or other factors.</P>
    <P>It behoves all of us to be aware of the value of ACC Bank to the farming community. I am pleased with this Bill and I congratulate the Minister and the directors of the bank for their positive successful programme.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelCalnan" hpid="Mr. Calnan Mr. Calnan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Calnan</NameTxt>
      <P>I welcome this Bill to raise the borrowing limit from £1 billion to £1.4 billion, a substantial 40 per cent rise and I can see the bank making great <Col N="518" /> progress.  If the Minister came back to the House in 1995 to raise the figure to £2 billion I would welcome it because it would show the vibrancy of one of our State banks.</P>
      <P>It is a pity Senator Ross is not in the House but I was interested in his lecture on the Labour Party.  He sadly missed Senator Magner &mdash; who is no doubt in Cork for the by-elections &mdash; as there might have been a little of the banter or argy-bargy between them which they enjoy.  I did not indulge in that but I listened to his lecture, which took up quite an amount of his contribution, and I hope he was happy with it.</P>
      <P>I suspect that he suffers from &ldquo;Labour-itis&rdquo; or &ldquo;Labour-phobia&rdquo;; I hope he does not waken at night with Labour nightmares.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnDardis" hpid="Mr. Dardis Mr. Dardis">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dardis</NameTxt>
      <P>As long as Fianna Fáil do not get them the Senator need not worry.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelCalnan" hpid="Mr. Calnan Mr. Calnan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Calnan</NameTxt>
      <P>For a while I thought that, according to Senator Ross, the only party in Government was the Labour Party.  I am glad we have a Programme for Government until 1997 and if Senator Ross reads that&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator Ross is not here to defend himself.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelCalnan" hpid="Mr. Calnan Mr. Calnan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Calnan</NameTxt>
      <P>He might be listening on a monitor.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RoryKiely" hpid="Mr. R. Kiely Mr. R. Kiely">
      <NameTxt>Mr. R. Kiely</NameTxt>
      <P>He could come back quickly.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelCalnan" hpid="Mr. Calnan Mr. Calnan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Calnan</NameTxt>
      <P>It is important to open up further investment and lending in ACC Bank.  If we close the door on investors or borrowers at any time they will go else where and their business will be lost.  That is why I would welcome the Minister coming back here next year if he wanted to increase the amount to £2 billion because it would be a healthy sign for the bank.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The ACC, which was started in 1927 to help the farmers and the co-operatives, has done a tremendous job for the <Col N="519" /> agricultural sector, particularly for the co-operatives.  I come from an area where there are four co-operatives and the ACC must be praised for their help to the farmers and the farming co-operatives.</P>
    <P>A vibrant bank with a nationwide network is important to keep its staff working. I thought Senator Ross implied that the Labour Party was the only party looking after the workers in the bank. This increase in the borrowing limit will continue the work for the staff who are doing a good job.</P>
    <Speaker pid="RoryKiely" hpid="Mr. R. Kiely Mr. R. Kiely">
      <NameTxt>Mr. R. Kiely</NameTxt>
      <P>I welcome the Bill and congratulate the Minister on bringing it forward.  The ACC was set up in 1927 to provide medium and long-term finance for farmers and farming co-operatives and it has served the agriculture sector well.  At that time there was a stigma attached to borrowing money and people had to be acclimatised to it.  The services provided by the county committees of agriculture at the time encouraged farmers to develop their farms to their full potential and to borrow.  The ACC was helpful to the farming community in developing agriculture to its full potential.</P>
      <P>There were occasions when farmers found themselves in trouble with the ACC and the ACC was a little hard on them.  However, when one borrows money it must always be understood that one must have the capacity to pay it back.  The granting of future loans depends on the repayment of debts.  I know of farmers who found themselves in difficulty but the ACC was helpful and understood their position.  I welcome this Bill which ensures that ACC Bank will continue to widen its business in helping the agricultural community.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I may have a vested interest in this but I always found that the ACC was good to farmers who, in order to comply with European regulations, had to upgrade the hygiene level of their dairy facilities, for example, which was very expensive.  ACC Bank provides subsidised interest loans and I would like to <Col N="520" /> see this continue.  Subsided loans should be made available to farmers in depopulated areas so that they can get back into production and their cash flow improves.</P>
    <P>I do not mind about a third banking force but I would like to see ACC Bank continue to operate for the benefit of the agricultural community.  In 1992 it widened its operations to give finance to other sectors but it must be maintained for the farming community and the benefit of agriculture.</P>
    <Speaker pid="LouisBelton" hpid="Mr. Belton Mr. Belton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Belton</NameTxt>
      <P>I add my praise to the work done by the ACC since 1927.  It is one of the better establishments set up in the early days of the State.  We sometimes forget the contributions made at that time by people with a lot of foresight. It is always nice to be in a position to recall those days when things were not easy and there was a lot of criticism of the decisions to set up new State institutions.  I am glad the ACC has stood the test of time.</P>
      <P>It might be appropriate to pay tribute to the founding fathers.  Things have changed since then.  The financial world changes rapidly, and nobody knows that better than the Minister.  One week you can be up and the next week you can be down.  It is always advisable to keep your eye on the financial ball. ACC Bank has diversified into other areas of operation in addition to the agricultural sector.  Its business has improved since this change was made. Like other financial institutions its business suffered as a result of bad debts in the farming sector.  However, it appears to have weathered the storm and to be in a good trading position.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>This is a technical Bill but it offers us the opportunity to voice our opinions on the proposal regarding a third banking force which appears to have been put on the long finger.  It is enough for me to hear that there is a report on the issue. That is kicking for touch.  The Minister is a regular visitor to Croke Park and there is no better man to land a high ball across the stand because it takes <Col N="521" /> some time to find it.  Perhaps that is where the third banking force is at present.</P>
    <P>ACC Bank is, I gather from reports, quite satisfied with its activities and it is seeking wider parameters today.  I hope they are being granted those parameters for the right reasons.  I wish ACC Bank well.  It has done much for the farming sector and has spread its activities into other areas.  It employs 800 people and makes a major contribution to employment and to the financial well being of many of our citizens.</P>
    <Speaker pid="Bertie" hpid="Minister for Finance (Mr. B. Ahern) Bertie Ahern">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Finance (Mr. B. Ahern)</NameTxt>
      <P>I thank Senators for their contributions and for their overwhelming support for ACC Bank's work.  I also thank the Senators for their kind remarks about the legislative changes we have made regarding the involvement of the board, the executive and the staff of ACC Bank.  The latter, in their examination of these debates, will be pleased that the House takes such an interest in their affairs.  Senator Dardis, in particular, picked up on the point about introducing further legislation.</P>
      <P>The Houses of the Oireachtas cannot have it both ways.  We must decide if we want to have an involvement and a say in these matters or if we do not want to know anything.  We cannot say we do not want legislation introduced because we consider it too technical and nonsensical while at the same time demanding a say in these matters.  These technical Bills afford the House an opportunity within the rules of having a broad ranging debate.  I would have got support for setting the limit at £1.6 billion but it is better that Members should have the opportunity to discuss this within the term of at least every Dáil and if it occurs more quickly than that, so be it. That is an important point because it refers to the double-think of at least one Senator.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>We have different views about how the banking sector should be organised and how different banks should develop.  Senators have shown in this debate that we all share the same concern <Col N="522" /> to develop policy that will advance the national interest.  Senator Ross suggested that in requiring that this matter be returned to the Oireachtas every few years we are showing a lack of foresight and an <i>ad hoc</i> approach to policy.  I am surprised the Senator thinks we should not have a say or that the approval of the Oireachtas should not be sought by a body owned by the people when it proposes to assume very substantial liabilities.  I am sure he will explain that to the people.</P>
    <P>In my opening remarks I mentioned that the £400 million increment was designed to give an interval of between two and four years before we need to address the matter again.  The representative institutions of the people are entitled to have the opportunity at reasonable intervals to scrutinize and debate the activities of bodies established to carry on business in the name of the people.  During the debates on this Bill in this House and in the Lower House it was noticeable that Members have a great deal of knowledge about the activities of the bank.  They are familiar with what is happening and with the views of the public on the issue. That is a good thing.  As far as parliamentary accountability is concerned, we should look periodically at what these institutions are doing and I appreciate the well reasoned comments of Senator Roche and Senator Dardis in that regard.</P>
    <P>Senator Ross also referred to dealing in gilts.  ACC Bank deals in gilts in the same way as any other bank.  It would be wrong to restrict ACC Bank in a way other banks are not restricted.  Any profits it makes in such trading derive from the secondary market and are not made at the expense of the Exchequer. Senator Ross, by highlighting ACC Bank's independence, gives lie to his other arguments that the bank is unduly fettered by official restrictions.  This is another example of double-think.  If the bank was restricted it would be unable to operate in the gilt market but it is not restricted and operates in the gilt market. I am not sure what the Senator <Col N="523" /> wants because he changed his arguments so many times.  However, in this case ACC Bank is allowed to deal in the gilt market.  At the time of the currency crisis, to which Senator Ross referred, ACC Bank conducted its day-to-day treasury operations on an independent commercial basis.</P>
    <P>It worries me that Senator Ross misunderstands how commercially operated State companies work.  The Minister or the senior official from the Department does not run ACC Bank.  I do not decide whether a person may be given a loan.  The Senator appears to think that the bank is interfered with politically and that I am responsible for sanctioning the bank's loans.  The Minister of the day has no such say.  The Minister appoints the board and it runs the company on a commercial basis. The bank is successful and is making a good profit on that basis.  I realise that it is hard for somebody who is opposed to 100 per cent State ownership of any enterprise to admit that such enterprises are commercially run in an independent fashion and are successful.  That is very upsetting if one believes the State should own nothing.</P>
    <P>I agree with Senator Dardis.  If ACC Bank wishes to move into the agri-business or related sectors or is considering embarking on international joint ventures, that will probably be considered by the Government.  What the Government will or will not do is a matter for a future debate.  However, it is unfair to, on the one hand, nitpick at a successful, independent, commercial State company that is owned 100 per cent by the people just because one has an ideological view and, on the other hand, to spend the rest of one's time ideologically arguing against another party because it has a different ideological view.  Apparently, it is all right to have one ideological view but not any other.</P>
    <P>My view is probably between those two ideological views and is close to that of Senator Dardis in some of these matters. There is nothing wrong in combining the two viewpoints but that is something <Col N="524" /> we have to debate.  That is the third case where he is not clear in his mind about the issue.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JohnDardis" hpid="Mr. Dardis Mr. Dardis">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dardis</NameTxt>
      <P>I am glad to hear the Minister is a liberal.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="Bertie" hpid="Mr. B. Ahern Mr. B. Ahern">
      <NameTxt>Mr. B. Ahern</NameTxt>
      <P>Without naming a State company, I often believe the best way to resolve this question would be to put one of our notoriously unsuccessful State institutions into the private sector and place one of our successful private companies in public control and see how they have progressed ten years later.  I think we would be surprised, but perhaps that is another ideological view.  In any case it amuses me to listen to some people when they are confusing the issue.</P>
      <P>As regards the emoluments of directors, Senator Ross made an unjustified attack on the calibre and competence of ACC Bank directors.  He conceded that they are dedicated people and I am fully satisfied with their expertise.  The quality of directors of State bodies is very high, as Senator Ross could establish if he looked at the lists of people involved.</P>
      <P>I do not propose to give his remarks on this point too much credence but he is trying to say that if a person is not paid more than £100,000 per annum salary they are not able to do the job.  I wish we could convince the public of that fact when it comes to our own profession. All State salaries are related and the salaries of directors of commercial State companies are linked to salaries of other grades.</P>
      <P>Some State company directors have said to me the only way to escape the pay guidelines is to work in a company which is in great difficulty but if one is in a successful company one cannot breach them.  I do not mean that remark in an unfair way and I can understand that frustration but as Minister for Finance I cannot break the guidelines in every case.  Senator Ross is right to say there is a problem but paying everyone a huge salary is not the way to solve it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Senators mentioned the bank's capital requirements which is as significant <Col N="525" /> an issue for ACC Bank as any other. Capital is required by banks, first to enable them to satisfy the capital adequacy requirements laid down by the Central Bank in accordance with EU requirements and solvency ratio directives; and second to enable them to increase their business, which is the rationale for this Bill.  The capital required by ACC Bank to increase its balance sheet by the £400 million increment provided for in this Bill will depend on a number of factors, including profitability, market conditions, the board's dividend policy and the composition of the balance sheet.</P>
    <P>Several Senators referred to the future of the bank and of State banks in general.  Any commentary by me on this matter at this time would be premature and would amount to speculation.  We received the report to which Senator Ross referred on 10 October drawn up by Stokes Kennedy Crowley, Rothschilds and William Fry and Company, Solicitors, who were the consultants appointed to advise me on the available options for State banks in the context of Government policy on the banking sector.</P>
    <P>In the light of a recommendation from the trustees of the TSB which envisages the disposal of the State's interest in that bank, I am examining the report at present and expect to be in a position to put the matter before Government as soon as possible.  As I indicated on a number of occasions in recent weeks, until the Government has had the opportunity to consider the report in detail I cannot make any comment on how we will proceed in 1995 and beyond.  I will, therefore, not comment on the general points but I assure Senators I will take their views into account.</P>
    <P>In answer to Senator Ross, the chairman of ACC Bank has assured me that he and his board will accept and act upon whatever decisions the Government makes on the future of State banks.  There is no ambiguity in the bank's annual report on this issue.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="526" /> Senators referred to the widespread displeasure at the level of bank charges. This area is outside the remit of the Bill but Senators will be aware that the Taoiseach, other Ministers and myself have had meetings with the banks and have taken every possible opportunity to put the public's view to the chairmen and chief executives of the major banks. At one detailed meeting we discussed various aspects of the relationship between banks and their customers and how banks could best contribute to the development of the economy.  This initiative is ongoing and we have arranged to meet again and consult on a more regular basis.  This issue is also dealt with in the Consumer Credit Bill and I have taken note of the points made by Senators.</P>
    <P>Senator Burke referred to the small business expansion scheme which is administered by ICC.  That bank is administering the scheme because it submitted the cheapest tender and fulfilled the terms laid down by the Minister for Enterprise and Employment and myself.  This was a competitive tender, not a sweetheart deal.</P>
    <P>There was also general support for increased competition in the banking sector.  I think the desirability of competition goes without saying; it is a wider issue for another day.  The transparency of the bank's operation and accounting was also raised by Senators.</P>
    <P>Mention was made of State guarantees for deposits with ACC Bank.  It is true the bulk of the bank's deposits are guaranteed but in recent years ACC Bank has been successful in attracting deposits without guarantee cover.  This is a clear indication of the credibility of the bank with the investing public. Senator Dardis asked about the limit; ACC Bank has found no need to increase the level of State guarantee for deposits which remains at the level of £800 million set some years ago.</P>
    <P>Senator Townsend, Senator McGowan and others remarked positively on the efficiency and profitability of the bank and I thank them; that is gratifying for the bank and it shows a <Col N="527" /> State shareholding need not be such a bad thing, as I said earlier.  It also shows how positive management and a serious sense of purpose can turn around a business in difficulty and make it viable and profitable.</P>
    <P>ACC Bank has used imagination and innovation to get substantial footholds in sectors outside its traditional base in farming and agri-business.  The bank constantly states it has not abandoned agri-business; it wants to develop within that sector and in other sectors.  This helps its capital base and its business as a whole.  Its network has expanded and it has plans to move into other areas in the medium term, particularly technological development.  ACC Bank is a serious player in some of these sectors while remaining active and profitable in the agricultural sector.</P>
    <P>The importance of ACC in the history of Irish agriculture has been mentioned. Its presence in the sector today, while no longer as large as it was relative to other financial institutions, is still significant. The bank's ethos of personal service and its practice of tailoring schemes to individual needs has generated success and profitability.  I assure Senator Kiely that the board is conscious of its role in the agricultural community and intends to continue it, regardless of other developments.</P>
    <P>While the views of the ACC board and executive on the third banking force are well known, the board members do not want the bank to stay as it is.  If it did remain in its current status a Minister at a later date might have difficulties. The board has made a policy direction and has argued about how it wants to develop but it does not want to remain as it is now.  The board will continue with its plans; the Government may not agree totally with those plans and may give the board certain directions but the bank will keep agriculture as its core sector.  The board deserves our congratulations and to be allowed to proceed with its business.  This is precisely the purpose of this Bill.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="528" /> I trust that what I have said covered the specific points identified by Senators and I will take into account the more general points made.  I thank Senators from Fine Gael and the Progressive Democrats for their support of the Bill. I hope we can take the remaining Stages now because there is an urgency in allowing the bank proceed with its plans for the future.</P>
    <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
    <P>Agreed to take remaining Stages today.</P>
    <P>Bill put through Committee, reported without amendment, received for final consideration and passed.</P>
    <P>
      <i>Sitting suspended at 4.20 p.m. and resumed at 6 p.m.</i>
    </P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Cork City Coal Ban:" RHead="Motion">
    <Title>Cork City Coal Ban: Motion.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelFinneranFF" hpid="Mr. Finneran Mr. Finneran">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Finneran</NameTxt>
      <P>I move:</P>
      <P>That Seanad Éireann welcomes the decision of the Government to improve air quality in Cork by introducing a ban on bituminous coal in Cork city area; and to make available a special fuel allowance of £3 per week to facilitate full compliance with the new smoke control régime.</P>
      <P>I am pleased with the opportunity to contribute to this debate.  I welcome the Minister of State at the Department of the Environment, Deputy Brown <i>(Wexford)</i> the House and I compliment him on his activities to date, particularly the recent announcement by himself and the Minister for the Environment, Deputy M. Smith, on the prevention of smog in Cork city and its environs.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The Minister will be aware that the ban on the sale of bituminous coal will have a major beneficial effect on Cork city and, in particular, on the elderly, those with chest complaints and those who find smog a major interference in their lives.  A similar decision was taken about Dublin a few years ago and its <Col N="529" /> effects are clear today.  This was successful in Dublin because the public accepted and implemented it.  The introduction of bans on the sale of bituminous coal and other such measures are only as good as the public which implements them.  People are interested in such Government measures.  The proposal put forward by the Government and the Minister to ban the sale of bituminous coal in Cork is a correct one and will benefit that city and its environs in the future.</P>
    <P>The levels of smog in Cork city are not good.  My information suggests that the regulations have not been breached, but we are close to the top levels of smog.  It is therefore appropriate to introduce proper measures to eliminate that.  However, this Government could not bring in such measures without introducing compensatory allowances. The compensatory allowances, which will be paid over the winter months to allow people to buy smokeless fuel, is the proper way to implement this measure and to get public acceptance for it.  People today are on a tight budget and it is important for the Government to recognise this.  We must welcome the co-operation between the Department of the Environment and the Department of Social Welfare in this regard.  It is part and parcel of the overall package which allows this decision to be fully implemented early in the new year.  The decision can now be implemented in practice if people respond positively.</P>
    <P>I compliment the Minister on his wide-ranging discussions at local level in Cork.  He met all interested groups in Cork regarding the ban on the sale of bituminous coal.  He met Cork Corporation and Cork County Council, the coal and fuel suppliers and other interested groups in that area.  That is the proper way to implement such measures.  My information suggests he has received a positive response from the interested parties there.  This House hopes that the people of Cork will also respond in a positive manner, as the people of Dublin have done over the past number of years.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="530" /> The people of Cork city will benefit from the ban on the sale of bituminous coal over the next couple of years. People's health is important, particularly elderly people, who are often prisoners in their homes during the winter months when the burning of such fuels causes smog in the city and its environs.  A measure which allows them to travel from their homes without the fear of having to call into the nearest casualty unit because of the level of smog in their city is an important aspect of the ban on the sale of bituminous coal.  Young children with asthma and people with chest complaints will benefit from this important decision.</P>
    <P>The visual environment of Cork city and its environs will improve because the fall out from the burning of such fuels will not be the same.  This Government has taken a positive approach to matters of environmental importance. People are now conscious of the environment and of implementing measures which support and maintain a good clean environment.  It is important for the Government to respond.  The Government is responding and this measure is part and parcel of a number of measures.  This decision will have positive effects in Cork city and its environs.</P>
    <P>One needs a backup to the national fuel allowance scheme because it is no good to say we already have a scheme. The extra £3 per week to buy smokeless fuel, introduced by the Minister and the Minister for Social Welfare, is important to implement this.  The fact that this is available now to the people of Cork and not when the measure becomes fully implementable over the period of mid-October to mid-April allows people to be involved, to some extent on a voluntary basis, in the implementation of this Government measure.  I am sure that when it does finally come into regulation early in the new year, people will already have become used to the situation and in fact may have realised the benefits of the non-burning of bituminous coal in the city.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="531" /> I compliment the Minister for the work he has done to date and I recommend the motion to the House.</P>
    <Speaker pid="FrankFahey" hpid="Mr. Fahey Mr. Fahey">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Fahey</NameTxt>
      <P>I second the motion.  I join with Senator Finneran in welcoming the Minister, Deputy Browne to the House. I congratulate the Minister on the work he has been doing in the general area of environmental protection since he was appointed, especially on the achievements he has had in regard to this specific motion, the banning of the distribution, sale and marketing of bituminous coal both in Cork city and its surrounding areas.</P>
      <P>The Minister has done a good job in the Department of the Environment in highlighting many areas of environmental protection and, indeed, many new preventative measures to protect the environment in many respects.  The amount of progress that has been made in this area over the last number of years is a great credit to the Minister and his officials in the Department, who have worked in a diligent way to make progress in awareness and action throughout the country.  Indeed, the level of awareness among our local authorities and industry can be seen. While we all appreciate that a major amount of work remains to be done and there are still serious problems with regard to environmental protection which will cost a significant amount of money to correct and cure, significant progress is being made by the Department. I hope the additional resources it requires to continue to make those improvements will be made available to it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The specific example of Cork city and the swift action that has been taken by the Minister is a case in point.  While we have had great success in the initiatives taken in Dublin, I have no doubt that these initiatives will meet with equal success.  I have discussed with the Minister the desirability of expanding this initiative to other cities.  I know it is currently a priority of the Minister to see this initiative expanded to our other cities. <Col N="532" /> I very much welcome the Minister's determination to see the ban on bituminous coal being extended to other cities. I recommend to the Minister to put Galway as high up as possible on the list.  We have seen the positive effects of this development in Dublin.  No doubt we will also see the effects within the new Cork coal ban area as soon as it commences.  The Minister for Social Welfare and the Government should also be praised for the way in which they introduced the new smokeless fuel allowances.  This will ease the burden on families dependent on social welfare and on low incomes.</P>
    <P>I again commend the Minister for Social Welfare for the range of supports he has introduced to social welfare recipients right across the board to ensure there is no financial burden on those people in regard to this new initiative.</P>
    <P>I want to dwell for a moment on the more general area of environmental protection.  This initiative focuses on the great improvement that can be made in the quality of life as a result of such initiatives.  There is no doubt that we have taken our environment for granted over the years.  Sadly, we were unaware of the negative impact that our failure to protect our environment has had.  I suppose it is only now that we have all come to appreciate the great advantage for this country to become the most environmentally friendly and most pollution free environment in Europe. When one considers this in the context of making Ireland the most attractive and prestigious destination in Europe for quality tourism, it brings into focus the importance of environmental protection in all its various aspects.  There is much more work to be done.  More awareness must be brought into place in every aspect of environmental control across the spectrum, from the local authorities and industry to farmers and ordinary people.</P>
    <P>I would like to refer to the subject of litter.  It is a terrible indictment on our young people to see the way in which the streets of our towns are littered with <Col N="533" /> the remnants of the sales of take away restaurants.  Young people come out of a disco or a dance at night, go into a take away restaurant, come out and simply throw their litter on the street.  In the morning one will often see the remnants of a fast food meal lying in the middle of the roads leading out of some of our county towns.  It is a most disgraceful sight to see and I take this opportunity to remind people of the most basic type of environmental control. If we have litter, we should not simply throw it on the street where it becomes a most terrible eyesore.</P>
    <P>I conclude by joining with Senator Finneran in complimenting the Minister; we are proud of his performance.  I hope the Minister and his officials keep up the good work and I hope the Minister for Finance will make available to him the resources I know he needs. Investment in the environment the Minister is trying to protect will certainly give this country a good return.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JarlathMcDonagh" hpid="Mr. McDonagh Mr. McDonagh">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McDonagh</NameTxt>
      <P>I wish to share my time with Senator Doyle.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RoryKiely" hpid="Acting Chairman (Mr. R. Kiely) Acting Chairman (Mr. R. Kiely)">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman (Mr. R. Kiely)</NameTxt>
      <P>You can have eight minutes each.  Is that agreed?  Agreed.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JarlathMcDonagh" hpid="Mr. McDonagh Mr. McDonagh">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McDonagh</NameTxt>
      <P>A Chathaoirligh, ar dtús báire, cuirim fáilte roimh an Aire go dtí an Teach.  Cuireann sé áthas orm bheith in ann cúpla caibidlí a rá faoin ábhar tábhachtach seo.  Is minic a chloistear an abairt &ldquo;Téigh amach san aer agus tiocfaidh biseach ort&rdquo;.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>How often have we heard it said &ldquo;Go out into the fresh air&rdquo;.  There is nothing better for the lungs and indeed, the body then plenty of God's fresh air.  Of course we cannot see the air we breathe and if it contains impurities, it can be very harmful.  Some of the worst air pollutants are gases and particles produced by burning certain fuels.  Some fuels give off a lot of sulphur dioxide, a gas which, when mixed with air, creates a dirty yellow smog.  Smog is unpleasant to breathe and can even kill people.  History tells us that in one winter alone in the <Col N="534" /> great city of London, 4,000 people died from breathing smog.  Thankfully, since the 1950s, the air in London has become much cleaner because the burning of solid fuels that gave off too much sulphur was stopped in the city centre.</P>
    <P>There was a different problem in the American city of Los Angeles where on bright days a yellow/brown haze often darkened the sky and stung people's eyes.  Scientists found that this smog formed when sunlight shone on exhaust gases from cars and trucks.  Inventors designed special filters for vehicle exhausts which helped prevent nitrogen oxide gas from escaping and after that the air became much cleaner.</P>
    <P>Vehicle engines can emit other poisons, the most dangerous of which is lead in petrol.  To prevent pollution from this type of emission governments around the world have started making oil companies reduce the amount of lead in petrol.  The statement by the Minister in today's newspapers, that he will see to it that EU standards are conformed to in this country, is welcome.</P>
    <P>Some power stations and factories have very high chimneys which channel harmful fumes high up where the wind can carry them away, thus keeping the air in nearby cities clean.  We are all familiar with the problems caused by acid rain which rots stone buildings and steel railway lines; it has killed trees in German forests and fish in parts of Sweden, Canada and the United States.</P>
    <P>Air pollution is a serious problem, particularly where there is a high concentration of houses, and it gets worse at this time of the year when people are more inclined to light fires because of the longer evenings.  In winter, when the air is frosty and there is no wind to blow the emissions away, the problem is accentuated.  At Christmas time we all like to see the home fires burning brightly but that means there is an immeasurable increase in air pollution from house fires.</P>
    <P>Air pollution can be a major problem in Cork city due to the outline of the surrounding terrain where a saucepan-type landscape leads onto Cork harbour. <Col N="535" /> It is appropriate that the Government is introducing a ban on bituminous coal in Cork city to improve the quality of the air there.  It takes courage to make such a decision and I commend the Government for that.  However, perhaps the time is inopportune because merchants have new stocks of bituminous coal piled up at this time of year.  It would have been much better to introduce such a measure in springtime. However, I suppose it is appropriate that we should be talking about Cork, and perhaps this is the reason the House is so empty this evening.  There are other activities in that city at this time.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JohnBrowne2" hpid="Minister of State at the Department of the Environment (Mr. Browne, Wexford) Minister of State at the Department of the Environment (Mr. Browne, Wexford)">
      <NameTxt>Minister of State at the Department of the Environment (Mr. Browne,</NameTxt>
      <P>
        <i>Wexford</i>): Do not be cynical.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JarlathMcDonagh" hpid="Mr. McDonagh Mr. McDonagh">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McDonagh</NameTxt>
      <P>It goes without saying that when a transition like this is called for, a cost factor is involved.  We are asking people to buy smokeless fuel costing £205 per tonne whereas up to now they had been buying bituminous coal for £145 per tonne.  I accept that a fuel allowance is available to people on social welfare, and that £3 extra is being given which is helpful.  It is important for the Government and the Department of the Environment to monitor the situation closely and no hardship should be caused because of the changeover.</P>
      <P>Most local authority tenants burn coal, and in council houses fitted with Stanley ranges burning coal is a must.  It has been statistically proven that most local authority housing tenants are in receipt of some type of social welfare benefit.  An increase in the cost of coal, despite an allowance, could lead to hardship, particularly during the winter months when a lot of extra fuel is burned.  People should not have to suffer hardship because of the changeover to smokeless coal.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The better-off members of our society can fill their central heating tanks with £300 worth of oil and have double glazing in their homes.  They can provide as much heat as they like for their families. <Col N="536" /> A person on social welfare or an old age pensioner, however, is dependent on buying, say, one bag of coal per week. In their case the increase in the cost of smokeless coal as against a bag of ordinary coal is significant and could cause hardship.  It is vitally important that this should not be allowed to happen.</P>
    <P>While the technical solution to problems caused by smog in Dublin, Cork and other major cities is straightforward in theory, changing fuels or significantly raising the efficiency of combustion engines would be difficult to achieve in practice.  Two major considerations must be borne in mind on economic grounds &mdash; the increased cost of smokeless fuels and the changeover cost from the simple open grate to a specially designed, highly efficient burner system. This can be very expensive, particularly for people on social welfare and the elderly.</P>
    <P>An educational promotion programme should be put in place outlining to householders the benefits to be gained from using smokeless coal.  The costs involved in the transitional process must also be brought home to the ordinary householder.</P>
    <P>I would like to digress for a moment to mention a problem which has arisen in my own city of Galway.  In recent times, unacceptable levels of radon gas have been found in houses, especially in Salthill.</P>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Acting Chairman Acting Chairman">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman</NameTxt>
      <P>Sorry Senator, but your time is up.  I do not know how you could share it, but it is up now.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JarlathMcDonagh" hpid="Mr. McDonagh Mr. McDonagh">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McDonagh</NameTxt>
      <P>This is an important point so I will try to make it within a minute.  Radon gas is a matter of major concern to people in Galway city.  A special report has been issued highlighting this concern and the mayor of the city, Fintan Coogan, has gone on record expressing his concern.  Householders have found that there are unacceptable levels of radon gas in many houses.  I would appeal to the Minister to look at the situation prevailing in Galway and the problems there.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="537" /> Finally, the General Council of County Councils is hosting an important conference on Friday, 27 January 1995, in Galway on all aspects of pollution and associated problems.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JosephDoyle" hpid="Mr. Doyle Mr. Doyle">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Doyle</NameTxt>
      <P>He is inviting us all.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JarlathMcDonagh" hpid="Mr. McDonagh Mr. McDonagh">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McDonagh</NameTxt>
      <P>I am inviting you all to come along and I hope the Minister will come because that will be an opportunity to highlight various aspects of pollution.  This is one of the most important conferences to come on stream in recent times.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelFinneranFF" hpid="Mr. Finneran Mr. Finneran">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Finneran</NameTxt>
      <P>That is the commercial.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelCalnan" hpid="Mr. Calnan Mr. Calnan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Calnan</NameTxt>
      <P>I welcome the Minister to the House.  I support the motion.</P>
      <P>I know the layout of Cork city fairly well and will know more of it in the next couple of weeks.  I do not think much smog will rest there at the moment because there is an amount of hot air around which will cause it to drift away.</P>
      <P>I welcome the motion and the move by the Government to improve air quality. I know Cork city of old.  It was built on an island on the River Lee and was originally low lying.  As time passed, the main housing areas were built on the high land on each side of the river. Consequently, we must be careful with smog and smoke which would disimprove the quality of life of those people living in the higher areas.  I therefore welcome the ban on the use of bituminous coal.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>In the cool winter weather, when there is little movement of air in the Cork city area, the development of smog is particularly noticeable.  Sometimes there is a good breeze in from the sea and up the harbour or down the river but there are certain times in winter when smoke will rest there.  Any smoke coming from the lower parts of the city will affect the higher areas. People living in the main housing areas in the city, particularly older people and those suffering from asthma and other chest complaints, will suffer greatly as a <Col N="538" /> result of smoke or smog emanating from chimneys.</P>
    <P>It is also very important to ban the use of bituminous coal in a city that is working towards inner city renewal. Many of the older buildings which were left derelict are the subject of work by the corporation and will be replaced by shops and, eventually, more housing. The use of bituminous coal would be fatal because it would destroy the effort to keep the place clean and would also affect the health of those living in the higher areas.</P>
    <P>Bord Gáis have done tremendous work providing services for the people living in the city.  They are and have been extremely busy extending the gas network and finding new customers.  I have to compliment Bord Gáis on the work they have done in Cork.</P>
    <P>We must be vigilant however because any new legislation or ban is going to affect suppliers.  These people are making a living for themselves and providing work.  Consequently, we have to recognise that some effort will have to be put into alleviating the problem for these people.  I believe that is being done.</P>
    <P>The special allowance of £3 per week facilitates full compliance.  The payment of this amount to social welfare recipients is to be welcomed.  I welcome the motion and totally support it.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MaryHenry" hpid="Dr. Henry Dr. Henry">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Henry</NameTxt>
      <P>Like others I welcome the ban on bituminous coal in Cork.  I have to declare an interest.  I come from the Mahon peninsula and I know that it would take quite a breeze from the Lee to shift the smog there at times.  Anything that will alleviate that must be considered useful.  As everyone as said, it is particularly important for the elderly, young children and those with chronic respiratory diseases.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>When the Minister is considering the cost of subsidising smoke free coal, it is worth remembering that there could be a great decrease in the amount of pharmaceuticals consumed by those with respiratory diseases.  A few years ago a colleague of mine, Dr. Luke Clancy in St. James Hospital, conducted a survey <Col N="539" /> on the correlation between death from respiratory diseases, particularly among the elderly, and the occasions when smog was particularly severe in the Dublin area.  The same inversion problem exists in Cork and I believe that if the hospitals there conducted a similar survey, they would find that the death rates were also increasing.</P>
    <P>It is important that we do not think that this will totally solve the smog problem in Cork.  We have to look seriously at the value of by-elections.  If we are not going to get some value out of them, there would be no point in holding them.  We already got some value in Cork because incinerators have been closed down in both the Cork Regional Hospital and the South Infirmary.  I congratulate the Department for doing that.  It now appears that we will not even have to build our own incinerator but will send waste to south Wales.  It seems that a satisfactory solution has been found in the Cork area.</P>
    <P>If we are serious about smog in Cork we must address the traffic problem as well as the coal problem.  It surely must be the time to announce that work will commence on our own &ldquo;channel tunnel&rdquo; under the Lee.  This will divert traffic from the Dublin road on to the ring road to west Cork while bypassing the Mahon peninsula, where I might get involved in opening a petrol station. This is extremely serious and we have been waiting for it for about ten years. I hope it will form part of the Minister's proposals.</P>
    <P>The lack of traffic policy is serious.  In light of the Minister's interest in air pollution he may have noted that the Ministry of Transport's plans for traffic in London have been seriously criticised by an independent report set up to study them.  It has been decided that plans for enlarged roads in city areas will only increase the traffic volume. The Minister might examine cities such as Manchester which have reintroduced trams.  This has had a great effect on air quality in that city and other cities throughout Europe which have introduced <Col N="540" /> similar schemes.  Oslo, in particular, has been very successful.</P>
    <P>The air quality has to be examined as an overall problem and not just taken a piece at a time.  I urge the Minister to consider the traffic situation in Cork. For example, provision could be made for cycle lanes.  Much of the city is flat so it would be extremely easy to introduce cycle lanes.  This could make a great difference to the density of traffic coming into a small city.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PaschalMooney" hpid="Mr. Mooney Mr. Mooney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Mooney</NameTxt>
      <P>Like Members on both sides of the House, I welcome this initiative and I welcome the Minister to the House.  I feel like the person in the fairy story who screamed that all their clothes had been stolen because my colleague, Senator Henry, has addressed many of the problems I was going to raise.  Perhaps I can put a different spin on them.  I hope this initiative is just one aspect of an integrated approach to the elimination of urban pollution, especially in cities such as Cork which continue to expand and grow at an inordinate rate.</P>
      <P>I share Senator Henry's views on the elimination of car, truck and bus pollution. I hope that the Minister will follow up on this initiative by continuing to press for further development in the area of sewage disposal.  One has only to look at the map of Ireland to see that the largest proportion of our population is concentrated on an east west axis rather than a north south axis.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Cities such as Cork and the area along the south east coast up into Dublin and towards the Border have a very high population.  Consequently, there is an equally high distribution of sewage, much of it untreated, due to the rapid urbanisation of this part of the country. The Government is conscious of the need to inject sufficient funds to eliminate this problem and I welcome the developments in that area.  The Minister has taken a lead in ensuring that there are fully equipped, state of the art sewage facilities along the east coast to Cork and beyond.  It is something which the population should be more conscious <Col N="541" /> of.  It is not enough for us to point to the Government of the day or to Government agencies and say it is their problem, because pollution is our problem. We contribute to it one in way or another, particularly in the area of waste management or perhaps waste mismanagement.</P>
    <P>How many of us, especially in cities, have sat in a car behind someone who carelessly tossed an empty cigarette box out the window?  Often if there are children in a car, they throw the remnants of sweet and crisp packets out the window. I blame the parents, not the children. We seem to go through life believing that it does not matter and that waste management is someone else's problem to solve.</P>
    <P>I do not want to stereotype anybody, but we have been hidden from the reality of an outside perception that we are a dirty nation, that we do not take environmental matters seriously, concern ourselves with waste disposal and that we tend to believe it has a low political priority and is of no consequence. Yet we are happy to bask in letters of affection published in newspapers from time to time from people telling us what a wonderfully friendly nation this is and what a beautiful holiday they had.  We rarely hear about the perception people have of this country, particularly visitors from the Continent, about the manner in which we attempt to dispose of our problem.</P>
    <P>There are several areas which the Minister could look at.  There should be legislation to outlaw plastic bags, which are one of the greatest dirt collectors.  It is an area where waste management could be addressed.  As in the case of this motion, there may be criticism that it would prove costly.  However, environmental matters are costly but in the long term the benefits which they bring to our social order and economy far outweigh the initial costs.</P>
    <P>As regards this initiative by the Minister in Cork city, it is right that people should question whether those most affected by this change, those on social welfare, will be in a position to pay for <Col N="542" /> the changeover or the legal requirement under this statutory requirement.  It is equally right to highlight the enormous advantages which will accrue from such measures in terms of the reduction and I hope, the elimination of respiratory illnesses, especially among the elderly.  I do not know whether the Minister has costed this on the basis of the experience in Dublin over the past number of years.  However, it would be interesting to discover whether there has been an appreciable reduction in hospital admissions among this targeted group most at risk from urban and air pollution.  Perhaps if we had those figures it might help to strengthen the argument towards more initiatives of an environmental nature such as this rather than weaken it.</P>
    <P>One significant statistic arising from the debate on this initiative in Cork city by the Minister and his colleague, the Minister for Social Welfare, which shocked me probably more than my urban counterparts, because I come from an a rural environment, related to the £3 allowance.  The Minister for Social Welfare stated that the number of households involved was over 20,000. If one takes the national average of Irish families, between 70,000 and 90,000 people will benefit from the national fuel scheme.</P>
    <P>The significance of the statistic is that an enormous number of people live on or below the poverty line within the designated area for this measure.  Surely it is a challenge for us as politicians to address that problem as well?  An enormous number of people who are recipients of social welfare, and who Senator McDonagh is concerned about, may not be in a position to meet the financial obligations of this changeover and will require more assistance than that outlined. That is a side issue, but one which is important.</P>
    <P>I would welcome more stringent measures than those in existence in relation to car or vehicle pollution.  I am aware the Minister introduced regulations which apply to new fleets &mdash; for example, Dublin Bus has an ageing fleet <Col N="543" /> which it is replacing on an ongoing basis.  Some consideration should be given to speeding up this measure.  I am not sure how practical that would be, but we should not tolerate in cities, especially in those the size of Cork, diesel fumes from public and commercial transport.  Senator Henry suggested that the Minister speed up the decision on the underground tunnel in Cork city to eliminate this problem.  However, it would be less costly in the short to medium term to speed up directives which would eliminate this problem rather than making a by-election commitment for what will be an extremely large expenditure, although I hope it will happen because it would benefit Cork city.</P>
    <P>I welcome, encourage and support the Tidy Towns competition.  Although it is not directly related to this motion, in the context of waste management and the elimination of pollution in towns and cities that competition was one of the most innovative of this generation. One has only to look at small towns and villages to see how they have improved. Perhaps the Minister might look at some way to encourage a more civic response from those in cities, which face major pollution problems.  As Members said, pollution covers a wider area than air.  The EU Commissioner, Pádraig Flynn, recently spoke about the introduction of unleaded petrol in this country. He said the only way people would buy unleaded petrol was if they had a financial motivation to do so.  He proved that by having a disparity between leaded and unleaded petrol.  Perhaps a similar measure could apply to eliminating litter from towns and cities.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JosephDoyle" hpid="Mr. Doyle Mr. Doyle">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Doyle</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator Mooney mentioned the benefits which accrue from banning bituminous coal, referred to in this motion, and he asked how this related to Dublin.  I will give some figures to show the benefit that has accrued in Dublin.  In May 1990 the Minister of State at the Department of the Environment made an order under <Col N="544" /> the Air Pollution Act, 1987, banning the sale of bituminous coal in the greater Dublin area.  The effect was to ban certain types of coal, mainly British, Polish and Texan coals.</P>
      <P>Before the order was made Dublin experienced serious pollution problems and broke EU guidelines on numerous occasions.  It seriously affected the health of citizens in Dublin, especially elderly people who suffered from respiratory problems.  The main environmental problem caused by bituminous coal is serious air pollution due to unacceptably high emissions of smoke and sulphur dioxide.</P>
      <P>The House might be interested to know what have been the effects of banning bituminous coal in Dublin.  Smoke and sulphur dioxide for measurement purposes are expressed in micrograms per cubic meter.  I will deal with smoke first.  In 1989-90, before the ban was imposed, the mean figure for smoke was 41 micrograms per cubic meter, the median was 24 and the highest concentration on any particular day was 1,098 micrograms per cubic meter.  The highest concentration on any particular day occurs when there is an inversion, when during the very cold weather, smoke is unable to escape into the atmosphere; it is held just over the chimneys and causes serious respiratory problems.</P>
      <P>In 1993-94 when the ban was in place, the mean was reduced from 41 micrograms per cubic meter to 15, the median from 24 to 11 and the highest concentration on any particular day was reduced from 1,098 to 193 micrograms per cubic meter.  These figures show clearly the benefits of the ban in relation to smoke emissions.  Similarly the levels of sulphur dioxide were substantially reduced.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Sulphur dioxide, known as SO2, is also expressed in micrograms per cubic meter.  In 1989-90, before the ban was imposed, the mean was 25 micrograms per cubic meter and was reduced to 20 in 1993-94.  The median was reduced from 27 to 19 and the highest concentration on any particular day that related to sulphur dioxide was reduced <Col N="545" /> from 197 to 134 micrograms per cubic meter.  I quote these figures to show the improvement brought to air quality by the banning of bituminous coal.</P>
    <P>I wish to make passing reference to another form of pollution.  There have been a number of references during the discussion to other types of pollution. The Transport Select Committee in the House of Commons published a report yesterday stating that super unleaded petrol which contains cancer forming chemicals should be banned.  The committee's report into air pollution in London highlighted concern about carcinogenic aromatics in petrol, the most significant being benzene, added to petrol instead of lead to improve octane rating.</P>
    <P>The committee reported that the evidence before them suggested that the potential health hazard from excessive aromatics used in super unleaded petrol outweighed any possible benefit from reduced lead.  The committee then recommended the phasing out of super unleaded petrol by the year 1996.  The most extraordinary aspect of this report is that it has highlighted how the development of green fuels as we know them can replace one health hazard with another.  I understand that the Minister made some comment on this report today and I hope he will take note of the report because many motorists &mdash; I spoke to some today &mdash; are under the impression that by using super unleaded petrol they are helping to reduce pollution in the atmosphere.</P>
    <P>I have a problem with the timing of this motion, not from a political point of view but because, unfortunately, many of the merchants in Cork have already bought their stocks of coal for the winter. They will have bought and will be selling bituminous coal this year.  In no way can they be restricted in selling it this year, so Cork will not benefit from the proposition before us until next year.</P>
    <P>It is one thing to make an order banning bituminous coal but the enforcement of such a ban is another.  That is <Col N="546" /> where the officials in Cork County Council will be important.  I understand that in Dublin a number of officials take samples from coal merchants to see what coal they are using.  They send the samples to Eolas who examine them.  I understand that ten or 12 merchants break the regulations each year and they are brought before the courts and fined.  The extraordinary part of the banning of bituminous coal is that the sale and distribution is banned but the burning is not.</P>
    <P>There is a problem in Dublin now where people buy coal outside the area and bring it home to burn.  People should be encouraged not to do that.  A very forceful advertising campaign would inform consumers that it is in their own interest not to buy or burn bituminous coal.</P>
    <P>The citizens of Dublin have benefited substantially from the order the Minister made in 1990.  It has changed the whole atmosphere of the city and we witnessed this recently when we had some cold nights.  We did not experience pollution such as that we experienced some years ago.  This is wonderful for old people with respiratory problems.  It is good for the whole city and I hope Cork will enjoy the same benefits as Dublin.</P>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I call Senator Mooney.  Sorry, my apologies, Senator.  I call Senator Cassidy.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PaschalMooney" hpid="Mr. Mooney Mr. Mooney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Mooney</NameTxt>
      <P>This is not the first time this has happened.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DonnieCassidyFF" hpid="Mr. Cassidy Mr. Cassidy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cassidy</NameTxt>
      <P>No doubt this is officially on the record.  I could never understand how a man with glasses could be confused with a man with no glasses, even though we have been good friends for a long time.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I welcome this legislation.  This is another indication of how seriously we view the problem of pollution.  Having visited many countries over the last ten or 15 years, I can honestly say that Ireland is a beautiful country.  We are going in the right direction; many other <Col N="547" /> countries are much worse off than we are.</P>
    <P>Without being repetitive I wish to make the point about smoke and the coal regulations which were introduced in Dublin in 1990.  I have vast experience of the north inner city of Dublin.  Before bituminous coal was banned, many people will tell you that the filters on their air conditioning had to be changed every two or three weeks; now they only have to change them every three, four or five months. That will show the reduction in pollution there.</P>
    <P>As Senator Doyle will know, more than 1,440 buses go around Parnell Square every day.  Members will appreciate the amount of damage they could have done in that area if they had not been properly fitted with the necessary equipment to keep down pollution emission levels.</P>
    <P>I congratulate the Minister and the Government for bringing this initiative into our second capital city, Cork, a very beautiful city on the banks of the Lee. Cork is unlike Dublin because it has a much smaller population and can be controlled much more easily.  I have no doubt that the proposals before us this evening will bear fruit even sooner there than happened in Dublin.</P>
    <P>What is the position in relation to turf?  We have an abundance of this smokeless fuel.  In our area this industry generates an enormous amount of employment, particularly in the midland counties adjacent to Dublin.  One third of our population lives within 25 miles of O'Connell Street.  What is the position of Bord na Móna in relation to developing a hard and long burning black sod turf briquette to cut down on the imported smokeless fuel?  Turf is a smokeless fuel.  In 1978 I visited the UK and did a study of the city of Southampton.  It was one of the first cities to be declared a smokeless area.  I was pleasantly surprised to see how many people on the outskirts of that city were burning a hard solid turf.  If this <Col N="548" /> turf can be produced, manufactured and create employment in Ireland, the Department should consider the idea, because it would be a terrific asset and a tremendous bonus.  I know from experience that it is easier to light a fire with turf than with coal or timber.</P>
    <P>The Minister should bring proposals to the Oireachtas in the near future with regard to plastic bags.  These bags are a major hazard and in the long term are detrimental to the issue of dealing with pollution.  I am familiar with the plastics industry as the major employer in Castlepollard, Mergon Limited, manufactures plastic components.  Last week the price of plastic was £400 per ton; this week it is in excess of £700 per ton.</P>
    <P>I am unable to understand why it is not possible to find a substitute for all of this plastic, because in the long term it is going to make it more difficult to come to terms with the problem when, eventually, plastic will have to be banned in respect of bags for all goods or for whatever other use.</P>
    <P>Regarding the issue of car and truck pollution today, there has been a major improvement and an increased awareness of this over the past number of years.  Even with the small budget which the Minister may have at his disposal, it would be a good idea to organise reminders in this respect from time to time every year through television and radio advertising, which controls 90 per cent of the market media.</P>
    <P>There are campaigns year after year with regard to drink driving and other matters.  It is all about awareness.  It is also an educational problem which ultimately goes back to the schools.  There should be competitions in schools, and indeed many do hold them on the occasion of Tidy Towns events.  For example, if pupils are advised that the habit of unthinkingly throwing a cigarette box out of a car window is wrong, dirty, unpleasant and will affect the livelihoods of people in the long term, they will bear that in mind.  Indeed, while this still happens in Ireland, it does not happen on the scale which applied three, four, five or six years ago.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="549" /> I welcome the motion before the House today and wish it a speedy passage through the House.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JohnBrowne2" hpid="Minister of State at the Department of the Environment (Mr. J. Browne, Wexford) Minister of State at the Department of the Environment (Mr. J. Browne, Wexford)">
      <NameTxt>Minister of State at the Department of the Environment (Mr. J. Browne,</NameTxt>
      <P>
        <i>Wexford</i>): I thank the Senators for their contribution on the motion before the House regarding air quality in Cork.  It was a wide ranging debate, covering issues such as storage schemes, plastic bags, sprayed on gasses and benzene. The Senators are well briefed and up to date on the areas of the environment which affect people.</P>
      <P>Smoke pollution has been a major environmental concern in Cork city and its environs.  Average annual smoke concentrations in the area are running at twice the average level of other urban areas in the country.  Air quality limits for smoke have not been breached in recent years in Cork, but they are constantly being threatened.</P>
      <P>The Cork smoke problem has therefore been high on my agenda since taking up office last year.  I have met with and listened to many political representatives and interested groups, both Cork Corporation and Cork County Council, in addition to the solid fuel industry in Cork.  The outcome of this process is that the Government has decided to ban the marketing, sale and distribution of bituminous coal in Cork city and surrounding area.  In other words, we are extending to Cork the same smoke control regime as has operated with great success in the Dublin area.  This will include a £3 supplement to the normal fuel allowance to assist low income households in the designated Cork area with the higher costs of using smokeless fuel.  The Minister for Social Welfare &mdash; and I wish to thank him for his interest and commitment in this area &mdash; is making the necessary administrative arrangements.  Exchequer costs will be at least £1.2 million in a full year.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>We have already begun preparations for the coal ban.  These will involve the Cork local authorities, the local fuel industry, and publicity and education campaigns aimed at the public.  We are <Col N="550" /> seeking to have the new regime in place from the beginning of 1995.  Many comments were made on this aspect.  The fuel industry may find it difficult to get rid of their stocks, but we have, from the date of announcement, given them a lead-in time of three to four months, which should be sufficient to ensure that much of the stocks they have at present will be disposed of.</P>
    <P>The area involved will in principle be the same as the one which was designated last year for the more limited smoke control measures applied then.  It includes all of Cork city and the district electoral divisions of Ballincollig, Douglas, Inishkenny, Lehenagh, Rathcooney, Bishopstown and St. Mary's, insofar as they are situated in County Cork.  However, further discussions with the Cork local authorities may result in some refinement of this designated area.  Indeed, at the press conference in Cork to announce the go-ahead for the banning of the coal, a number of public representatives made strong cases for other areas to be included.  We will consider these areas and, hopefully in the near future, we will make a final decision.</P>
    <P>In recent years smoke pollution in Cork city and its environs has reached worrying levels.  Air quality standards have been regularly threatened, although not breached.  Last October, following consultation with the local authorities, the fuel industry and the community groups I introduced a ban on slack and a requirement that all solid fuel retailers should carry smokeless fuels.  These regulatory measures, which applied to the built-up area of Cork, were complemented by voluntary ones applied by major solid fuel suppliers.</P>
    <P>I believe that it was necessary to attempt this lower cost solution before seeking to implement the higher cost measures which we have now decided on.  Our review of air quality in Cork showed, however, that last year's measures would at best contain rather than improve the situation.  In 1993-94 the standard for a three day value was exceeded for single days on three separate <Col N="551" /> occasions, the annual 98 percentile value was 80 per cent of the specified standard, the winter median value was 64 per cent of the specified standard and the annual median value was 63 per cent of the specified standard.</P>
    <P>If these trends were to continue there would be every prospect of air quality limits being breached in Cork.  My judgement was that we should deal with this threat on a precautionary rather than a reactive basis.  Accordingly, we recommended to the Government, and it accepted, that a full ban on bituminous coal should be extended to Cork from the earliest practicable date.</P>
    <P>The Dublin coal ban measures introduced four years ago have achieved a remarkable and rapid transformation of air quality in that area.  From a situation where gross breaches of smoke standards regularly occurred, Dublin smoke levels have now virtually reduced to the guide levels which are fixed aspirationally by the EU Directive as an indicator of optimum air quality.</P>
    <P>It is therefore on the basis of proven effectiveness that the Government is extending the coal ban regime in Dublin to Cork.  However, we must not assume that this regulatory initiative is sufficient of itself.  The whole experience of the Dublin coal ban demonstrates that this measure relies for its success on a shared responsibility.  Government, local authorities, the fuel industry and the public all have distinct but important roles to play in ensuring the success of the coal ban.</P>
    <P>It is the job of Government, as we will do now do in Cork, to establish a clear regulation of the coal ban regime and to ensure that support is provided to lower income households to enable them to cope with any increased costs.  The Government will also, in co-operation with the Cork local authorities and fuel industry, ensure that information on the coal ban is widely available to the Cork public.</P>
    <P>In addition, it is the job of the Cork local authorities to enforce the prohibitions of the new smoke control régime <Col N="552" /> actively and fairly.  In this way the solid fuel trade will be guaranteed a level playing field for the transition to smokeless levels.  It will also be for the Cork fuel industry to co-operate conscientiously with the new régime both by strictly observing the ban on bituminous coal and by ensuring the supply of good quality alternatives.</P>
    <P>Finally, and I cannot over-emphasise this, Cork householders themselves hold the most important key to the success of the coal ban.  Residents' groups, and local politicians on their behalf, have strongly advocated the ban which we are now extending to Cork.  The new regime will not work without widespread public co-operation and consent. It will be for the local public to demonstrate to any unscrupulous traders that disrespect for the coal ban will not be tolerated and that householders are committed to the success of the ban from a civic and environmental point of view.</P>
    <P>I would like at this stage to describe briefly the background to smoke control measures within the EU and Ireland.  At EU level a Council Directive was adopted in 1980 which specified air quality standards for both sulphur dioxide and suspended particulates, or, as we know it, smoke.  In Ireland the Air Pollution Act, 1987, established a modern legislative framework for the control of air pollution in order to meet national requirements and to facilitate the implementation of EU Directives and regulations relevant to air pollution control.  The Act includes general provisions relating to air pollution, special control areas, air quality management plans and standards, monitoring of air quality and emissions and licensing of industrial plant to control air pollution.</P>
    <P>The various EU Directives on air quality standards have been transposed into Irish law by regulations under the 1987 Air Pollution Act.  The most significant of these regulations &mdash; the Air Pollution Act, 1987, and Air Quality Standards Regulations, 1987 &mdash; prescribe air quality standards for the whole country and give effect to EU <Col N="553" /> Directives on smoke and sulphur dioxide, lead and nitrogen oxides, which up to 1987 had been implemented here by administrative measures.</P>
    <P>Air quality standards are useful instruments of environmental policy. They set limits for the purpose of protecting human health as well as the natural and built environments.  The limits are legally binding, but at the same time they do not constrain individual sources of emissions.</P>
    <P>I am happy to state that Ireland has never breached the EU quality standards for sulphur dioxides, lead or nitrogen oxides.  This is partly attributable to a comprehensive range of regulations, including controls on the sulphur content of certain liquid fuels, on the lead content of petrol and more recently on the enforcement of vehicle emission standards for all new vehicles.</P>
    <P>Dublin is the one place in the entire country where breaches of the air quality standard for black smoke occurred. Breaches were significant both in terms of the levels of the exceedance and the numbers of occurrences.</P>
    <P>Smoke pollution or smog occurs when black smoke or tiny grains of unburnt carbon are emitted from bituminous coal fires in large numbers and are not quickly dispersed into the wider atmosphere. This condition is particularly likely to occur in periods of calm cold weather which bring temperature inversions in the lower atmosphere.  Such inversions trap the smoke-laden air close to the ground.  Black smoke has adverse effects on health and can particularly effect the elderly or those suffering from respiratory conditions.  It may also be a contributory factor in some lung cancers.  Studies have shown a direct link between increased morbidity and mortality during incidences of elevated smoke levels.</P>
    <P>There are of course other sources of smoke besides domestic fires.  In modern cities smoke from industry is no longer the major source it once was, but transport, particularly diesel engined vehicles, has been a significant contributor to overall smoke levels.  Obviously, <Col N="554" /> in any area the percentage of smoke attributable to various sources is determined by a wide range of characteristics. These include topography and prevailing weather conditions.  Work done in Dublin prior to the implementation of the bituminous coal ban there indicated that domestic sources accounted for about 80 per cent of the city's smoke and transport emissions for some 16 per cent.  Transport emissions are now being addressed through stricter emissions on all new vehicles, including, in particular, heavy goods vehicles.</P>
    <P>I said in Cork on 6 October that work would begin immediately to prepare for the implementation of the ban and I hope to have the controls in place by the beginning of 1995.  That work is now underway.  In finalising arrangements I will be looking at the precise designation of the area within which the marketing ban will operate in the light of local authority and community views.  I would like to take this opportunity to say I very much welcome the support for the measures voiced by the local community groups and by the Cork coal trade in the wake of the announcement.</P>
    <P>The introduction of the coal ban represents a major environmental opportunity for Cork.  Let us all seize this opportunity.  I am confident that Cork air quality and the health and amenity of Cork householders will greatly benefit from the new measures.</P>
    <P>Some issues were raised in the course of the debate to which I would like to respond.  Senator Mooney raised a number of issues such as sewerage schemes, which we will not get into tonight.  He also raised the issue of plastic bags, as did Senator Cassidy.  I share their concern. It is not an easy problem to solve. All supermarkets use plastic bags and are probably the biggest offenders in this regard.  We have had meetings with the supermarket owners but have not been too successful to date.  However, we will continue to try to find reasonable solutions to that problem.  I accept that it is one of the major litter pollutants. In every road and street as one <Col N="555" /> enters Dublin city one sees plastic bags in the ditches and so on, which is unsightly.</P>
    <P>Senator Fahey mentioned litter from take-aways, which is another major problem.  Litter generally is still a major problem in this country and one which we are trying to come to grips with.</P>
    <P>Senator Cassidy spoke about turf, which is acceptable as a smokeless fuel. Briquettes are widely sold in Dublin.  I concur with him that it is a national fuel and one which could probably create extra jobs if it was purchased on a wider scale.  However, it is acceptable as a smokeless fuel.</P>
    <P>Senator McDonagh mentioned the problem of radon gas in Galway.  Radon is a natural phenomenon, but it can give rise to high levels of exposure to radioactivity. The Government has fixed a precautionary level of 200 becquerels for exposure to radon in buildings.  Our guidelines on building regulations take account of this limit and we are currently running an active campaign of information for the public and to public institutions about measures which can be taken to reduce radon levels.  The Radiological Protection Institute of Ireland has also devised a low cost testing service for this area.  We are monitoring the situation and will be advised of any developments in that area.</P>
    <P>Senator Henry spoke about the traffic management measures in Cork and the need to curb emissions from transport. Much work has already taken place in relation to the future transport problems of the Cork area based on the land use and transportation study of some years ago.  Various components of this planning process are already in place. However, I accept that there is still much work to be done.</P>
    <P>Vehicle emission controls and environmental fuel standards also have a vital contribution to make to reducing transport emissions.  I recently introduced a range of new emission standards for different classes of new vehicles including heavy goods vehicles. These standards will greatly reduce <Col N="556" /> emissions from all new vehicles.  Ireland is fully up to date in regard to the implementation of all EU vehicle Directives. However, I would still emphasise that domestic coal burning is the major source of smoke emissions in urban areas.  By tackling this directly, it has been shown, as in the case of Dublin, that we can achieve major and rapid reduction in such smoke emissions. Extending it to Cork will bring quick results in that area.</P>
    <P>Senator Doyle mentioned benzene levels in petrol.  We are aware of the concerns being expressed in the UK. The current EU and Irish standards fix a limit of 5 per cent for benzene content of petrol.  Analyses conducted regularly by the State Laboratory indicate an average benzene content of 3.4 per cent in Irish petrol in 1993 and an average of 3 per cent in 1994 to date.  These levels are obviously well within the required standards.  This disproves the recent allegations made by Earthwatch that the average benzene content of Irish petrol is 4.8 per cent.  Our monitoring system, which is modern and up to date, shows that it is 3 per cent in 1994 to date.</P>
    <P>We have introduced a number of measures.  The fitting of catalytic converters to all new petrol engined vehicles, as required by Irish regulations, will reduce benzene emissions by up to 75 per cent.  This will contribute greatly to the overall improvement in benzene emissions.  Nevertheless, we all share the growing concern about our exposure to benzene in the atmosphere and we will support relevant EU initiatives to improve our position in this regard.  Initiatives under consideration at present at EU level include a significant reduction in the benzene content of petrol, controls on evaporative emissions from the gasoline distribution chain and additional controls on vehicle emissions.  As soon as those are agreed at EU level, I can assure the House that we will take them on board and implement them immediately, as we have done with all other regulations to date.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="557" /> I thank the Senators for their contributions and their words of welcome for the smoke ban in Cork.</P>
    <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>When is it proposed to sit again?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DonnieCassidyFF" hpid="Mr. Cassidy Mr. Cassidy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cassidy</NameTxt>
      <P>At 10.30 a.m. tomorrow.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Is that agreed?  Agreed.</P>
      <P>
        <i>Sitting suspended at 7.20 p.m. and resumed at 8 p.m.</i>
      </P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Adjournment Matters. -" RHead="Shannon Airport Traffic">
    <Title>Adjournment Matters. - Shannon Airport Traffic.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="MadeleineTaylorQuinn" hpid="Mrs. Taylor-Quinn Mrs. Taylor-Quinn">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Taylor-Quinn</NameTxt>
      <P>I thank you, a Chathaoirligh, for allowing me to raise this important matter on the Adjournment this evening as I know that there are many other demands.  I am delighted to see the Minister of State, Deputy Treacy, present.  As the Minister is aware this is an important issue which has been repeatedly raised in this House because of the great concern in the west and mid-west regions.</P>
      <P>Figures recently released by Aer Rianta show an 8 per cent drop in traffic to Shannon Airport in the first nine months of this year.  The figures have confirmed the worst fears of the people in the west and mid-west regions.  The widespread fear and apprehension is further compounded by detailed studies and reports by Aer Rianta about the future of Shannon Airport.  The projected figures show that traffic through Shannon will be down by 7 per cent in 1995 and total traffic will be reduced by a further 2 per cent in the following year.  The Aer Rianta surplus from Shannon of £4 million in 1993 will be cut to £1.8 million in 1994 and to £1.5 million in 1995.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The Shannon task force stated in its report that unless this trend can be promptly arrested and reversed the only outlook for Shannon is one of inexorable <Col N="558" /> decline.  It goes on to say that the knock-on effect of the decline could set in motion a cycle of falling investment and employment in both industry and tourism throughout the airport's hinterland. Such strong statements by the task force must give cause for serious and grave concern and highlight the need for urgent action.</P>
    <P>I welcome the fact that the Minister visited Shannon recently and announced the establishment of the Shannon Airport marketing group which was recommended in the task force report.  However, it was a pity he did not provide the funding recommended by the task force for the new marketing agency &mdash; a conservative annual budget of £3.5 million.  There was great play made of the fact that £2 million was being allocated to this agency.  However, we must realise that the Government is not providing an additional £2 million subvention to this agency or to the mid-west region.  I understand that this funding will consist of £800,000 from SFADCo and £500,000 from Aer Rianta which will be taken from their current budgets.  Between £200,000 and £500,000 will be provided by direct subvention from the Government. This is a long way from the £3.5 million recommended by the task force report.</P>
    <P>We are tired of the Minister, Deputy Cowen, visiting the area and making statements urging the people of the region to support our airport and our region in order to provide the prosperity and jobs to which we all aspire. The people of the west and mid-west have been doing this but the Government has acted directly against our interests.  It is time the Minister provided leadership on the issue of Shannon Airport.  It is time he exuded confidence about its future by investing in local infrastructure in the airport and by directing the national airline, Aer Lingus, to provide additional flights to London at a competitive cost <i>vis-á-vis</i> those being provided from Dublin to London.  In addition, he should direct the national airline to provide direct <Col N="559" /> flights from Shannon to Manchester and Birmingham.</P>
    <P>Why has no flight been put on the Shannon-Stansted route which was operated by Ryanair until quite recently?  Over 60,000 people were carried on that route, yet Aer Lingus has not been urged by the Minister to provide a service on it.  The onus is on the Minister to act on these matters rather than to plan for an opt out on Shannon. He should give leadership and confidence to the region.</P>
    <P>It is time a proper national aviation policy was put in place.  The policy should take into account not just the interests of the airline but also the interests of the airport &mdash; an aspect that is fundamentally lacking in current aviation policy.  On previous occasions we have discussed the concept of making Shannon a hub for Aeroflot flights and flights from other airlines in the CIS states.  I again urge the Minister to expand Shannon as a wayport providing access to Aeroflot to direct flights from Shannon into New York on pick-up traffic.  This was strongly recommended by the task force but, unfortunately, the Minister to date has not acted on it.  It is an important policy that could be developed in the future and through which much traffic could come through Shannon.</P>
    <P>Many recommendations are made in the task force report.  To date the Minister has only attempted to act on one of them, and he has not fully implemented it.  A number of other recommendations in the report fall within the Minister's ambit and the onus is on him specifically to deal with them.  My greatest concern at this stage is the overall attitude of the national airline, Aer Lingus, which is the responsibility of the Minister.  We have observed, repeatedly and consistently, a pro-Dublin policy being promoted by Aer Lingus.  It can be seen in its advertising at both national and international level, and particularly in its advertising directed at passengers travelling from the United States to Ireland.  The Aer Lingus promotional <Col N="560" /> video on the transatlantic flight is very pro-Dublin: a substantial amount of its content deals with Dublin while other parts of the country receive a small amount of coverage.  That must be addressed.</P>
    <P>The situation is not helped by the cost of fares.  The Minister should get his officials to conduct a survey on the flight costs from Shannon to London and from Dublin to London.  There are serious discrepancies between the two.  I have received a number of representations on this matter.  I received the first last May when I was told that a man from the Shannon region tried to book a flight from Shannon to London for November 1994.  At that stage the cheapest fare quoted to him was £256 and he was advised that he would get a much cheaper flight from Dublin.  After further inquiries he was quoted a substantially cheaper price for a flight from Dublin.  There is no way Shannon can compete while the national airline is not giving equal treatment to both airports. This matter must be addressed.  There are counter-arguments but the reality is what people experience.  This matter is within the Minister's ambit and he must address it.</P>
    <P>The task force is clear about what must be done within Shannon Airport. It states clearly that Shannon Airport is the only national airport that does not have a proper lighting system.  There is an urgent need to have the lighting of the runways in Shannon upgraded.  I urge the Minister to do this quickly.  I understand that Aer Rianta has put money aside to do this work.  Unfortunately, however, it has not been done to date.  Other recommendations in the report do not come specifically within the Minister's ambit.  However, other specific action must be taken.  I hope the Minister in his reply will address the various recommendations of the task force report, will outline what action is being taken in relation to them and when we can expect a positive input from him and the Government on these issues.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="561" /> It is clear from the serious statements made in the report what the future of Shannon will be if action is not taken by the Government:</P>
    <P>Unless this trend can be promptly arrested and reversed the only outlook for Shannon is one of inexorable decline.</P>
    <P>We are experiencing that already in the tourism industry in County Clare.  We have been told that increasing numbers of people are travelling through Shannon but the official figures from Aer Rianta show that there was an 8 per cent decline.  The Minister can make the excuse that it is due to a reduction in transit traffic.  The reality, however, is that hoteliers and guesthouse owners have experienced a very difficult tourist season.  On 15 July about 35 hoteliers held a crisis meeting in the mid-west to address the huge reduction in the number of American tourists through Shannon Airport and in their hotels.  This is a real problem.  The figures compiled by the hotels and those compiled by Aer Rianta do not tally.  The position is serious.</P>
    <P>Because of emigration along the west coast, much of the traffic through Shannon consists of emigrants coming home or their relatives travelling to visit them. There is an onus on the Minister to do a more detailed analysis of the types of passengers coming through and their reason for travelling to see whether they are purely tourists or if they have a family connection.  Family tourists will stay with relatives but true tourists will go to hotels and guest houses.  I thank you again, a Chathaoirligh, for affording me the opportunity to raise this matter in the House.</P>
    <Speaker pid="NoelTracey" hpid="Minister of State at the Department of Transport, Energy and Communications (Mr. N. Treacy) Noel Treacy">
      <NameTxt>Minister of State at the Department of Transport, Energy and Communications (Mr. N. Treacy)</NameTxt>
      <P>A Chathaoirligh, a Sheanadóirí agus a dhaoine uaisle, is chúis an áthas dom teacht anseo chun freastal ar an rún tábhachtach seo faoi eachtraí iompar Aerfort na Sionna.  It is important to consider the Shannon traffic results to date in 1994 in their <Col N="562" /> total context.  Terminal traffic at Shannon increased by over 5 per cent in the first nine months of 1994 compared to the same period in 1993.  It is terminal traffic which provides the spin-off for hotels, etc., in the mid-west and which underpins tourism employment in the region.  North American traffic improved by 9 per cent and European traffic increased by 17 per cent over the same period.</P>
      <P>As expected, transit traffic at Shannon &mdash; that is traffic passing through the airport &mdash; decreased in the nine months to the end of September, due primarily to the new direct Aeroflot flights between Moscow and New York. The fall in transit traffic of 27 per cent meant that overall traffic at Shannon was down by 8 per cent during the first nine months of 1994.  Despite this fall in traffic Aer Rianta's turnover and profits at Shannon to date in 1994, including profits from duty free sales, show an increase on 1993.</P>
      <P>Aeroflot decided to operate non-stop on some of its Moscow to US services, in particular the New York flight.  This was a commercial decision based on its acquisition of new aircraft capable of non-stop service on the North Atlantic. It has been public knowledge for a considerable time that once suitable aircraft became available the Moscow &mdash; New York service would operate direct.</P>
      <P>It is the duty of Government to manage change and we have already taken a number of initiatives in recent months in order to offset the fall in transit traffic at Shannon Airport.  We have given Aeroflot certain additional rights at Shannon.  We have set up Shannon Airport Marketing, or SAM, with an annual budget of £2 million, to boost traffic through the airport.  We have obtained Government approval for a Russian Federation customs pre-clearance cargo facility at Shannon.  A new aviation co-operation agreement with the Russian Federation is at an advanced stage and we hope to sign it very soon with the Minister's opposite number, Minister Yefimov.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="563" /> As regards additional rights for Aeroflot at Shannon, the Russian Federation has been given wayport rights &mdash; pick up rights for transfer traffic &mdash; at Shannon to all destinations, including New York, for traffic from the Russian Federation. Under the Ireland-Russia Air Agreement, Aeroflot has full fifth freedom rights at Shannon &mdash; rights to pick up transfer and local traffic &mdash; for all points in Central and South America, for Washington and Miami in the USA and for Gander in Canada.  Outside the air agreement, Aeroflot has been granted temporary fifth freedom rights at Shannon to Tampa, Florida, and its fifth freedom rights at Shannon to Chicago, granted on a temporary basis, were renewed for a further period.</P>
    <P>In relation to SAM, Shannon Airport, due to the low population density of its hinterland, does not have a sufficient volume of originating and destination traffic to make it commercially viable. To make it so, the airport must be vigorously marketed abroad.  A Government-appointed task force found that the marketing of Shannon is fragmented and that duplication and overlapping of traffic promotion functions at the airport are inhibiting its growth.</P>
    <P>To eliminate this obstacle to development the Government has established SAM, with a budget of £2 million for 1995.  The new marketing team will be a single tightly knit entity with a clear mandate and clear lines of accountability and reporting relationships.  It will put into sharper and more coherent focus the present roles of Shannon Development and Aer Rianta in the marketing of this excellent airport.</P>
    <P>As the Minister, Deputy Cowen, indicated to the Senator in his letter of 7 October, he will be carefully monitoring the progress of the new body over the coming months.  He wants to ensure the benefits which public representatives from the mid-west region have convinced him can be achieved from the establishment of the new body are in fact realised,</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="564" /> On his initiative the feasibility of establishing a pre-clearance customs facility at Shannon for cargo destined for the Russian Federation has been under examination by the Department in conjunction with Aer Rianta over the last year.  This feasibility study was completed recently and the Government has approved the preparation of legislation to set up the cargo pre-clearance facility at Shannon.  This legislation is currently well in hand.</P>
    <P>This facility will eliminate delays and expedite customs clearance of air cargo destined for the Russian Federation and will enable Shannon to be marketed as a major centre for general freight and express cargo.  Aer Rianta estimates the facility will increase traffic at Shannon by 500 landings a year within two to three years, generating revenue of over £4 million a year for the airport and the region and increasing permanent employment at the airport by 30.</P>
    <P>Using the new aviation co-operation agreement with the Russian Federation, it is my intention to identify and implement more new business opportunities with the Russian Federation for Shannon.  In March 1993, when the Minister, Deputy Cowen, and his Russian counterpart, Minister Yefimov, signed the Air Transport Agreement between Ireland and Russia, they recognised there were opportunities for further mutually beneficial co-operation between both sides in the field of civil aviation.  It was agreed to set up a joint high level group on aviation co-operation with the specific mandate of continuing and expanding the range of mutually beneficial commercial co-operation opportunities.</P>
    <P>Since then a wide range of commercial activities involving Aer Lingus and Aer Rianta have been identified, many of which have already been undertaken. In addition, a range of further potential areas of co-operation have been identified for further examination.  When the Taoiseach and the Minister met Russian First Vice Prime Minister Soskovets and Foreign Economic Relations Minister Davydov on 3 October 1994 we handed <Col N="565" /> over a list of the potential areas of opportunity.  Substantial progress has been made on finalising the agreement on aviation co-operation targeting new specific opportunities.  It is hoped Minister Yefimov will travel to Ireland to sign the new agreement.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MadeleineTaylorQuinn" hpid="Mrs. Taylor-Quinn Mrs. Taylor-Quinn">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Taylor-Quinn</NameTxt>
      <P>Will he get off the plane?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="NoelTracey" hpid="Mr. N. Treacy Mr. N. Treacy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. N. Treacy</NameTxt>
      <P>I am highly optimistic that the plane will stop, he will get off and he will sign.  I understand all Ministers leaving Russia are instructed to alight from the aircraft.</P>
      <P>The measures I have outlined clearly demonstrate the Government's commitment to Shannon, the west and the mid-west. I attach first rank importance to the pursuit of all the measures I have mentioned in order to generate additional traffic for Shannon.  In particular I am anxious to establish a framework under which we can do business with the new and dynamic private sector airlines recently established in the Russian Federation.</P>
      <P>I was interested in what the Senator had to say.  If she is prepared to give us precise details of the complaint she has about the style of marketing by Aer Lingus I will have it fully investigated. I assure her I am a solid supporter of Shannon Airport.  I acknowledge its contribution over many years to the mid-west region.  However, we all have to live in the real world and take account of changes in technology, communications and the system of aviation traffic across the world.  We have been, we are and we will be totally positive and supportive of decisions on investment in Shannon.  We are in favour of investment in a new centre-line lighting system and the expansion of the aprons there.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I visited Shannon to attend a number of functions last Friday and made clear to the many people there our absolute support for the airport and its future progress.  I ask the Senator and those with a negative attitude in the region not to talk down this excellent airport. <Col N="566" /> For too long, and over the past two years in particular, there has been too much of a negative attitude.  Anyone who listened yesterday to the &ldquo;Gay Byrne Show&rdquo; on RTE radio and heard the number of Americans who found the mid-west a romantic area can be sure we will leave no stone unturned in marketing Shannon for what it is, an airport with excellent facilities.  We will attract as many international visitors as possible through the airport to the region so that there can be further economic spin-off for the people of the area.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MadeleineTaylorQuinn" hpid="Mrs. Taylor-Quinn Mrs. Taylor-Quinn">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Taylor-Quinn</NameTxt>
      <P>I live in the real world and know what the reality is on the ground in Clare.  Could the Minister clarify from where the £2 million will come?  Is it additional to the current budgets of SFADCo and Aer Rianta? With regard to lighting, I know the Minister is supportive but we want action.  How soon can he see the new lighting system being installed and a new apron built because this will involve direct Government subvention?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="NoelTracey" hpid="Mr. N. Treacy Mr. N. Treacy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. N. Treacy</NameTxt>
      <P>I am not technically or professionally qualified to give a commitment on the lighting system except to say that the national development plan will come into play on 1 January next and will have the full support of EU Structural Funds.  Proposals have been made under the operational programmes for tourism and transport for various measure which will be supportive of the region.  We are very disposed to supporting these proposals and ensuring that the necessary funding is made available so that these improvements can be made.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>With regard to the £2 million funding, in the past Aer Rianta and Shannon Development have marketed the airport. We saw the need, as a result of representations made to us, for a very aggressive, tight knit entity the key strategy of which would be to market the airport throughout the world.  The £2 million we have provided is a large amount and we are confident that through the knowledge and expertise of <Col N="567" /> Aer Rianta and Shannon Development, aided by the Department, we will be able to improve throughput through this excellent airport.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Adjournment Matters. -" RHead="Castlerea (Roscommon) Hospital">
    <Title>Adjournment Matters. - Castlerea (Roscommon) Hospital.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelFinneranFF" hpid="Mr. Finneran Mr. Finneran">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Finneran</NameTxt>
      <P>I wish to share my time with Senator Naughten.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFallon" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Is that agreed? Agreed.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelFinneranFF" hpid="Mr. Finneran Mr. Finneran">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Finneran</NameTxt>
      <P>I raised this matter to ask for clarification from the Minister for Health on the provision of alternative accommodation in Castlerea for the patients in St. Patrick's Hospital following the Government decision of 9 March to locate a prison in the grounds of the hospital.  There is general welcome for this decision by organisations in Castlerea and the general public in County Roscommon.  However, this decision brought a number of complications. The patients will have to be located elsewhere.  On 3 May the Western Health Board stated it had decided that the patients and psychiatric services of the hospital should be located in Castlerea.  On 25 May the Minister turned the sod for the prison.  There is a certain urgency in that work has started on the boundary wall of the prison and is in progress at present.</P>
      <P>There are still approximately 73 in-patients in the hospital.  Over 70 outpatients attend the hospital daily; of these 40 come from their homes for day care services, 25 from foster homes, seven from supervised hostels and five from flats.  When we talk about the patient population of Castlerea hospital, we are referring not only to its approximately 73 in-patients but also to a further 77 who attend daily for professional services.  Around 150 people still require medical and nursing services and support from the hospital.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The Western Health Board has submitted a set of proposals to the Department of Health which it says will cost <Col N="568" /> around £3.5 million.  These include the provision in Castlrea of a high support hostel, a psycho-geriatric unit, a workshop sector headquarters, medium stay hostels and other back up services.  It also asks for central stores in Roscommon town, an extension of the day care centre in Boyle and the provision of a day care centre in south Roscommon, possibly adjacent to Athlone.  However, there are a number of problems with regard to the provision of these services. The health board does not have sufficient funds and has applied to the Department of Health for funding.  It has taken an option on some sites, one or two of which it may have bought; it may have a problem with paying a deposit on one of the sites on which it has an option.</P>
    <P>There is a need for clarification on a number of fronts.  We must allay the fears and worries of the patients and their families and the hospital's staff who are worried about the in and outpatients. We have a responsibility in this area and I seek a reassurance from the Minister that these fears will be allayed. There is the matter of time spans and dates.  Work has commenced on the construction of at least part of the prison. The boundary fence is being constructed at present; this construction is visible to people who attend the hospital.  They see that their time in the hospital is limited, whether they attend daily or are in-patients.  They are also aware that no definite arrangements have been made regarding alternative accommodation, other than the decisions which have been taken.  The physical provision of alternative facilities is not apparent to the staff, in-patients, those who attend the hospital daily and the people of Castlerea.  This is a time for reassuring the people involved and for clarification.  Statements have been made to the effect that it is intended that the prison will open in 1996.  If this timetable is to be adhered to, construction would have to start on the prison itself in the near future.  However, there are no definite plans for alternative facilities for these <Col N="569" /> patients.  There have been no applications for planning permissions.  These things take time.</P>
    <P>Clarification and reassurance are now important.  I appreciate that two Ministries are involved here and that the Minister of State at the Department of Health, Deputy O'Dea, cannot talk about the starting or finishing dates for the prison.  The Minister for Health has first responsibility to the patients, their families and staff at St. Patrick's Hospital in Castlerea and its catchment area.  Finance should not prevent the provision of alternative accommodation. We need reassurance and clarification so that we can tell the patients, their families and staff in the Castlerea area about the up to date position and when alternative accommodation for the patients and staff of St. Patrick's Hospital in Castlerea will be finalised. We want to tell these people what their future will be and what opportunities will be provided for them to continue the excellent service for those who, unfortunately, need psychiatric care.</P>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. Naughten Mr. Naughten">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Naughten</NameTxt>
      <P>I thank Senator Finneran for sharing his time with me.  I endorse what he said about the concerns of the patients, relatives and staff of St. Patrick's Hospital in Castlerea about their future.  Everyone in County Roscommon welcomes the Government's decision to convert St. Patrick's Hospital in Castlerea to a prison and the opportunity it presents for Castlerea. The large drop in patient numbers meant the hospital had outlived its usefulness as a psychiatric hospital.  We are glad these developments are taking place.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>As Senator Finneran stated, these developments are under way at present. However, the Western Health Board has received no commitment for funding from the Government to provide replacement services.  There are more than 80 patients at St. Patrick's Hospital in Castlerea and there are day-care facilities for approximately the same number.  It is of vital importance that those services are provided in Castlerea. <Col N="570" /> As Senator Finneran correctly pointed out, the Western Health Board unanimously decided that those services should be provided in Castlerea.  This is important and cannot be emphasised enough.</P>
    <P>The Western Health Board has also requested funding for a high support hostel, workshop facilities, a dementia unit and other facilities which are needed in Castlerea as a result of the transfer of St. Patrick's Hospital from the Department of Health to the Department of Justice.  This valuable property was transferred for the nominal sum of £1 on the understanding that the health board would get the necessary funding from the Department of Health to provide alternative services. The health board must provide day-care facilities in Boyle, Roscommon and Monksland, one of the fastest growing areas outside Galway city, on the outskirts of Athlone and within the jurisdiction of the Western Health Board.</P>
    <P>I appeal to the Minister to ask his Department to give a clear commitment to the Western Health Board to provide funding.  We need funding to put these facilities in place.  As Senator Finneran stated, the health board has taken options on certain properties to provide facilities for these patients.  However, we cannot provide them without funding from the Government.  An application for funding, in excess of £3 million, has been sent to the Department of Health to provide the necessary facilities as a result of the closure of St. Patrick's Hospital in Castlerea.</P>
    <Speaker pid="WillieODea" hpid="Minister of State at the Department of Health (Mr. O'Dea) Willie O'Dea">
      <NameTxt>Minister of State at the Department of Health (Mr. O'Dea)</NameTxt>
      <P>The Government decided on 9 March 1994 that a new prison facility catering for 150 male offenders should be located at St. Patrick's Hospital, Castlerea, and that alternative accommodation should be provided for patients residing in the hospital.  The west wing of the hospital currently accommodates 43 long stay psycho-geriatric patients and 24 rehabilitation patients.  Some 13 patients reside in a high support hostel in the <Col N="571" /> hospital grounds and 50 persons attend a vocational training workshop on the campus on a daily basis.  The primary concern of my colleague, the Minister for Health, Deputy Howlin, is to ensure that the Government's decision is implemented with the minimum disruption to patients and staff.  Primary responsibility for the welfare of patients and staff lies with the Western Health Board.  The Department of Health has been working closely with the board to ensure that alternative accommodation and services are provided without delay for patients currently residing in or attending St. Patrick's Hospital.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>On the basis of preliminary estimates provided by the Western Health Board of the cost of providing alternative accommodation and services for patients of St. Patrick's Hospital, the Department of Health sought and received the sanction in principle of the Department of Finance to a total of £1.5 million for the provision of alternative accommodation in April last.  The Western Health Board then carried out a detailed assessment of the implications of closing St. Patrick's Hospital and submitted revised estimates of the capital cost of relocating services in September. This revealed a need to provide, in addition to earlier requirements, a high support hostel for the more disturbed patients, two day-care centres to provide activation for less dependent patients moved to community residences, a mental health centre to provide accommodation for professional staff delivering services to the Castlerea sector and a central stores for the health services in Roscommon to replace the stores currently provided on the site of St. Patrick's Hospital.  The cost of these developments and the decision of the <Col N="572" /> Western Health Board to provide a psycho-geriatric unit in Castlerea rather than at the Sacred Heart Home, Roscommon, has added to the cost of the health board's original estimate for vacating St. Patrick's Hospital and providing alternative accommodation and services.</P>
    <P>The Department of Health is at present engaged in discussions with the Department of Finance regarding the additional funding required to provide alternative accommodation and services for the hospital, as proposed by the board.  In the meantime, the Western Health Board has been assessing the suitability of available properties in the area in the context of future service needs and has commenced drawing down the £1.5 million which has already been approved.  It is furnishing two hostels already in its possession; it is in the process of purchasing a property for use as a high support hostel and is negotiating the acquisition of two sites for other hostel developments and a site for an industrial training workshop.</P>
    <P>I am aware that part of the new prison wall in now complete and that the Department of Justice is keen to have access in the middle of next year to certain parts of the hospital site to commence construction of the new prison accommodation.  I assure the House that the Department of Health, in co-operation with the Western Health Board, will make every effort to expedite the provision of alternative accommodation and services.  Measures will also be taken to ensure the safety of patients and staff should building begin before all patients and staff are transferred from the site.</P>
    <P>The Seanad adjourned at 8.50 p.m. until 10.30 a.m. on Thursday, 27 October 1994.</P>
  </MainHeading>
</Debate>