<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE Debate SYSTEM "../Debate.dtd"[]>
<Debate DocTitle="Seanad Debate" Day="Tue" Date="20" Month="Dec" Year="1994" Vol="141" No="12" DateIrish="Dé Máirt, 20 Nollaig 1994" DateEnglish="Tuesday, 20 December 1994" House="S" CommitteeEng="" CommitteeIr="" SubNameEng="" cnum="0">
  <MainHeading Type="Prelude" LHead="" RHead="">
    <Title>
    </Title>
    <P>
      <Col N="1185" /> Chuaigh an Cathaoirleach i gceannas ar 2.30 p.m.</P>
    <P Just="Center">
      <i>Paidir.</i>
    </P>
    <P Just="Center">
      <i>Prayer.</i>
    </P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Nomination" RHead="of Members">
    <Title>Nomination of Members.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFallon" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I announce that on 13 December 1994 the Taoiseach nominated: Michael Mulcahy and Edward Haughey with their prior consent, to fill the casual vacancies in the number of nominated Members of Seanad Éireann <Col N="1186" /> caused by the resignations of Brian Hillery and Brian Crowley.</P>
      <P>I welcome them to the House and congratulate them on their appointment.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Appointment of Taoiseach, Members of Government and Transfer" RHead="of Departmental Administration and Ministerial Functions">
    <Title>Appointment of Taoiseach, Members of Government and Transfer of Departmental Administration and Ministerial Functions.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFallon" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I have to inform the House that letters dated 18 November 1994 and 15 December 1994 have been received from the Secretary to the Government regarding:</P>
      <P>&nbsp;(a)  the appointment of Taoiseach, and nomination as Tánaiste and the allocation of Government Departments; and</P>
      <P>&nbsp;(b)  the transfer of departmental administration and ministerial functions.  The letters will be set out in the usual manner in the Journal of the House and, consequent on this announcement, they will also be printed in the Official Report of the Debates.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <table pgwide="1">
      <tgroup cols="2">
        <colspec colname="1" colnum="1" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <colspec colname="2" colnum="2" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <thead>
          <row>
            <entry rowsep="1">Ref. No.</entry>
            <entry rowsep="1">ROINN AN TAOISIGH</entry>
          </row>
        </thead>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry>S.28291</entry>
            <entry>Department of the Taoiseach</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
            </entry>
            <entry>BAILE ÁTHA CLIATH 2,</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
            </entry>
            <entry>Dublin 2.</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
            </entry>
            <entry>15 Nollaig, 1994.</entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
    <P>Cléireach an tSeanaid</P>
    <P>Tá orm a chur in iúl duit go bfhuil an tUachtarán, ar ainmniú Dháil Éireann, tar éis John Bruton a cheapadh inniú, de bhun Airteagal 13.1.1º den Bhunreacht, mar Thaoiseach.</P>
    <P>FRANK MURRAY,</P>
    <P>Rúnaí an Rialtais.</P>
    <table pgwide="1">
      <tgroup cols="2">
        <colspec colname="1" colnum="1" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <colspec colname="2" colnum="2" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <thead>
          <row>
            <entry rowsep="1">
              <Col N="1187" />Ref. No.</entry>
            <entry rowsep="1">
              <Col N="1188" />ROINN AN TAOISIGH</entry>
          </row>
        </thead>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry>S.28291</entry>
            <entry>Department of the Taoiseach</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
            </entry>
            <entry>BAILE ÁTHA CLIATH 2,</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
            </entry>
            <entry>Dublin 2.</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
            </entry>
            <entry>15 Nollaig, 1994.</entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
    <P>Cléireach an tSeanaid</P>
    <P>Tá orm a chur in iúl duit go bhfuil</P>
    <P>(1)  An tUachtarán, ar ainmniú Dháil Éireann, tar eis John Bruton a cheapadh inniú, de bhun Airteagal 13.1.1º den Bhunreacht, mar Thaoiseach;</P>
    <P>(2)  An tUachtarán, ag gníomhú di ar ainmniú an Taoisigh, le comhaontú Dháil Éireann roimhe ré, tar éis na daoine seo a leanas a cheapadh inniu, de bhun Airteagal 13.1.2º den Bhunreacht, mar chomhaltaí den Rialtas agus bheith, i dteanna an Taoisigh, mar Rialtas:&mdash;</P>
    <P>Risteárd Mac an Earraigh,</P>
    <P>Ruairí Ó Cuinn,</P>
    <P>Micheál Ó Núnáin,</P>
    <P>Muirís Táilliúir,</P>
    <P>Micheál D. Ó hUiginn,</P>
    <P>Breandán Ó Húilín,</P>
    <P>Niamh Bhreathnach,</P>
    <P>Nora Bean Mhic Eoghain,</P>
    <P>Proinsias De Rossa,</P>
    <P>Éanna Ó Coinnigh,</P>
    <P>Risteárd De Briotún,</P>
    <P>Ivan Yates,</P>
    <P>Micheál Ó Labhraí,</P>
    <P>agus</P>
    <P>Aodh Ó Caoibheanaigh;</P>
    <P>(3)  An Taoiseach tar éis Risteárd Mac an Earraigh a ainmniú inniu, de bhun Airteagal 28.6.1º den Bhunreacht, chun bheith ina Thánaiste; agus</P>
    <P>(4)  An Taoiseach, i bhfeidhmiú na cumhachta a thugtar dó le halt 4 (1) den Acht Airí agus Rúnaithe (Leasú), 1946, tar éis na Ranna Stáit seo a leanas a shannadh inniu do na comhaltaí faoi seach den Rialtas a luaitear a nainmneacha os coinne ainmneacha na Ranna:&mdash;</P>
    <table pgwide="1">
      <tgroup cols="2">
        <colspec colname="1" colnum="1" colwidth="60*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <colspec colname="2" colnum="2" colwidth="40*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <thead>
          <row>
            <entry rowsep="1">
              <Col N="1189" />
              <Col N="1190" />An Roinn Gnóthaí Eachtracha</entry>
            <entry rowsep="1">Risteárd Mac an Earraigh,</entry>
          </row>
        </thead>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry>An Roinn Airgeadais</entry>
            <entry>Ruairí Ó Cuinn,</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>An Roinn Sláinte</entry>
            <entry>Micheál Ó Núnáin,</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>An Roinn Comhionannais agus Athchóirithe Dlí</entry>
            <entry>Muirís Táilliúir,</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>An Roinn Ealaíonn, Cultúir agus Gaeltachta</entry>
            <entry>Micheál D. Ó hUiginn,</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>An Roinn Comhshaoil</entry>
            <entry>Breandán Ó Húilín,</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>An Roinn Oideachais</entry>
            <entry>Niamh Bhreathnach,</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>An Roinn Dlí agus Cirt</entry>
            <entry>Nora Bean Mhic Eoghain,</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>An Roinn Leasa Shóisialaigh</entry>
            <entry>Proinsias De Rossa,</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>An Roinn Turasóireachta agus Trádála</entry>
            <entry>Éanna Ó Coinnigh,</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>An Roinn Fiontar agus Fostaíochta</entry>
            <entry>Risteárd De Briotún,</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>An Roinn Talmhaíochta, Bia agus Foraoiseachta</entry>
            <entry>Ivan Yates,</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>An Roinn Iompair, Fuinnimh agus Crumarsáide agus</entry>
            <entry>Micheál Ó Labhraí,</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>An Roinn Cosanta agus Roinn na Mara</entry>
            <entry>Aodh Ó Caoibheanaigh.</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>FRANK MURRAY,</entry>
            <entry>
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>Rúnaí an Rialtais.</entry>
            <entry>
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>Ref. No.</entry>
            <entry>ROINN AN TAOISIGH</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>S.27418</entry>
            <entry>Department of the Taoiseach</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>S.27443</entry>
            <entry>
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
            </entry>
            <entry>BAILE ÁTHA CLIATH 2,</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
            </entry>
            <entry>Dublin 2.</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
            </entry>
            <entry>18 Samhain, 1994.</entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
    <P>Cléireach an tSeanaid</P>
    <P>Tá orm a chur in iúl duit go bhfuil</P>
    <P>(1)  An tUachtarán ag gníomhú di ar chomhairle an Taoisigh tar éis glacadh ar an 17 Samhain, 1994, de bhun Airteagal 28.9.3º den Bhunreacht, le</P>
    <P Just="Center">Risteárd Mac an Earraigh</P>
    <P Just="Center">(Dick Spring)</P>
    <P Just="Center">Ruairí Ó Cuinn</P>
    <P Just="Center">(Ruairí Quinn)</P>
    <P Just="Center">Muirís Táilliúir</P>
    <P Just="Center">(Mervyn Taylor)</P>
    <P Just="Center">Micheál D. Ó hUiginn</P>
    <P Just="Center">(Michael D. Higgins)</P>
    <P Just="Center">Breandán Ó Húilín</P>
    <P Just="Center">(Brendan Howlin)</P>
    <P Just="Center">agus</P>
    <P Just="Center">Niamh Bhreathnach</P>
    <P>d'éirí as oifig mar chomhaltaí den Rialtas, le héifeacht ón 17 Samhain, 1994.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="1191" />
      <Col N="1192" /> (2)  An Taoiseach, i bhfeidhmiú na cumhachta a thugtar dó le fo-alt (1) d'alt 4 den Acht Airí agus Rúnaithe (Leasú), 1946, inniu tar éis:</P>
    <P>(a)  An Roinn Gnóthaí Eachtrachta a shannadh dó féin.</P>
    <P>(b)  An Roinn Ealaíon, Cultúir agus Gaeltachta a shannadh do</P>
    <P Just="Center">Páralan Ó Eachthairn</P>
    <P Just="Center">(Bertie Ahern)</P>
    <P Just="Center">comhalta den Rialtas,</P>
    <P>(c)  An Roinn Sláinte a shannadh do</P>
    <P Just="Center">Micheál Ó hUadhaigh</P>
    <P Just="Center">(Michael Woods)</P>
    <P>comhalta den Rialtas,</P>
    <P>(d)  An Roinn Comhionannais agus Athchóirithe Dlí a shannadh do</P>
    <P Just="Center">Máire Geoghegan-Quinn</P>
    <P>comhalta den Rialtas,</P>
    <P>(e)  An Roinn Oideachais a shannadh do</P>
    <P Just="Center">Micheál MacGabhann</P>
    <P Just="Center">(Michael Smith)</P>
    <P>comhalta den Rialtas,</P>
    <P Just="Center">agus</P>
    <P>(f)  An Roinn Fiontar agus Fostaíochta a shannadh do</P>
    <P Just="Center">Cathal MacRiabhaigh</P>
    <P Just="Center">(Charlie McCreevy)</P>
    <P>comhalta den Rialtas,</P>
    <P Just="Center">agus</P>
    <P>(3)  An Taoiseach tar éis glacadh le tairiscintí</P>
    <P Just="Center">Emmet Stagg, T.D.</P>
    <P>eirí as oifig mar Aire Stáit ag an Roinn Comhshaoil,</P>
    <P Just="Center">Brian Ó Se, T.D.,</P>
    <P Just="Center">(Brian O'Shea, T.D.),</P>
    <P>éirí as oifig mar Aire Stáit ag an Roinn Talmhaíochta, Bia agus Foraoiseachta.</P>
    <P Just="Center">Eithne Fitzgerald, T.D.</P>
    <P>éirí as oifig mar Aire Stáit ag an Roinn Airgeadais,</P>
    <P Just="Center">agus</P>
    <P Just="Center">Joan Burton, T.D.</P>
    <P>éirí as oifig mar Aire Stáit ag an Roinn Leasa Shóisialaigh,</P>
    <P>le héifeacht, i ngach cás, ón 17 Samhain, 1994.</P>
    <P>BRIAN McCARTHY,</P>
    <P>Rúnaí Cunta an Rialtais.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Business" RHead="of Seanad">
    <Title>Business of Seanad.</Title>
    <Col N="1193" />
    <Speaker pid="SeanFallon" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I have notice from Senator Henry that on the motion for the Adjournment of the House today she proposes to raise the following matter:</P>
      <P>The need for the Minister for Defence to outline the present status of the Army Equestrian School in light of the Efficiency Audit Group report.</P>
      <P>I regard the matter raised by the Senator as suitable for discussion on the Adjournment and it will be taken on the conclusion of business.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Order of" RHead="Business">
    <Title>Order of Business.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFallon" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>We now have a new Leader, a man of great wisdom who is the obvious man for the job.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MauriceManning" hpid="Mr. Manning Mr. Manning">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Manning</NameTxt>
      <P>Thank you for that recommendation and I hope it will be listened to in the appropriate place.  I wish to join in the welcome to our new colleagues Senator Haughey and Senator Mulcahy.  I am glad the Taoiseach had their prior consent in making the appointments.  Their stay will be for the life of the Parliament and I hope it will go its full term.  I know they will enjoy the working of this House and I hope they will make a full contribution.</P>
      <P>I take this opportunity to wish a happy Christmas to all Senators and to all members of the staff who have served us with such fairness.  I thank the ushers, the reporting staff and the journalists who have been covering the House more fully in recent times than was the case in the past &mdash; all of them contribute to the smooth running of the House.  At this Christmas season I thank you, a Chathaoirligh, for your fairness and your consideration for all Members and the exemplary way in which you have conducted your office.  I wish you a happy Christmas.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>This is an unusual day, a historic day. It is the first occasion in 70 years that <Col N="1194" /> we have had a change of Government mid-term.  This has a number of consequences &mdash; apart from some of us having difficulty finding our seats when we came in here today &mdash; but the major one being that this will be the first minority Government in the Seanad since the foundation of the State.  I except that will focus extra attention on the House. It will certainly provide opportunities to the Opposition parties but I have every confidence that the spirit of co-operation, which was so exemplified by Senator Wright, will be continued. Senator Wright began a process of reform which we will want to continue and intensify during the remainder of this session.</P>
    <P>Being a minority in Government gives the Seanad a precarious existence but it also provides us with an opportunity to push through reforms and provide the sort of amenities which we believe the Seanad should have.  This is a great opportunity for the Seanad which I know my colleagues on the far side of the House, especially in the back row, will grasp.</P>
    <P>The Order of Business is Items 1 and 2 taken without debate, by agreement.  I know that Item 1, Winter Time Order, 1994, is of special interest to Senator Quinn and I hope the Whips will be able to discuss with him the possibility of having a debate on an allied motion in the new session.  All Stages of Items 3 and 4 are to be taken, by agreement, with the contribution of spokespersons on the Second Stage of Item 4 not to exceed 20 minutes and all other Senators not to exceed 15 minutes.  As outlined in Item 2, I will be providing time at an early stage in the next session to allow all Members an opportunity to contribute to the Appropriation Bill debate.  The Appropriation Bill has been dealt with in this manner on many previous occasions.  The Adjournment matter will be taken at the conclusion of business.</P>
    <Speaker pid="GVWright" hpid="Mr. Wright Mr. Wright">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Wright</NameTxt>
      <P>May I get the formalities of the Order of Business out of the way?  I take it that the Appropriation <Col N="1195" /> Bill will be back to us at some stage. Following a heated debate of our Seanad group we have decided not to oppose the Order of Business today.  It was an honour to be the Leader of the House.  I wish to thank my Chief Whip, Senator Mullooly and Senator Tom Fitzgerald for the superb job they have done in ensuring the smooth running of the House over the past number of years.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Senators Senators">
      <NameTxt>Senators</NameTxt>
      <P>Hear, hear.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GVWright" hpid="Mr. Wright Mr. Wright">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Wright</NameTxt>
      <P>May I also thank my own group for their support in ensuring we had an extremely disciplined front bench on the Government side.  Senator Manning mentioned reforms that have taken place in the House and I was obviously very pleased to be part of that process but they could not have taken place without the total commitment of the House.  I thank Senator Manning and Senator Cosgrave for their co-operation and hope they will be back here in the new year in their rightful positions as Leader and Government Chief Whip. I thank Senator O'Sullivan and Senator Manger who ensured we had an effective, efficient and progressive Seanad and I was pleased to be part of that organisation.</P>
      <P>I welcome my two new colleagues, Senator Haughey and Senator Mulcahy, and wish them a long two and a half years' service in this House.</P>
      <P>Before I offer my festive good wishes, I wish to say that, as Leader of the main Opposition party it will certainly be our intention to read the Programme for Government.  We will come back in the New Year as a disciplined, well organised, cohesive, experienced group who will be a constructive and dignified Opposition ensuring that the progress made by the House during the last number of years will continue.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LouisBelton" hpid="Mr. Belton Mr. Belton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Belton</NameTxt>
      <P>Did the Senator read the last programme?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1196" />
    <Speaker pid="SeanFallon" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>The Senator without interruption.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GVWright" hpid="Mr. Wright Mr. Wright">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Wright</NameTxt>
      <P>We look forward to the New Year.  On behalf of Fianna Fáil I wish a very happy Christmas to the Seanad Staff and I thank them.  To the main Opposition parties, the Cathaoirleach and all Members on this side of the House, I wish a very happy Christmas and New Year.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeOToole" hpid="Mr. O'Toole Mr. O'Toole">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Toole</NameTxt>
      <P>I welcome our two new colleagues to the Seanad.  I am sorry Senator Haughey decided to take the shilling and move forward when there was plenty of space back here.  Had the Senator come back here he would have been one of six rather than one of five. We wish Senator Haughey and Senator Mulcahy well and hope they will contribute to and help develop the work of the Seanad.</P>
      <P>There has been a change of Government. The co-operation, availability, support and openness displayed by Senator Wright and Senator Mullooly, with whom I worked closely on a weekly basis, was much appreciated.  I am sure Senator Manning would agree that their co-operation has set the example of how we deal with each other.</P>
      <P>There are two sides in the House but we call ourselves Independents not Opposition.  For technical and procedural reasons we will act as a group to ensure representation on committees, when discussing items on the Order of Business and the allocation of time.  As regards voting arrangements, we are, as always, independent of each other.</P>
      <P>We wish Senator Manning and Senator Cosgrave well in their new roles.  We hope to be seen as co-operative, flexible and responsible in our approach to the work of the House.  We will not go to the Government side with a shopping list but from time to time issues will arise and demands will be made.  Hopefully the spirit of co-operation that will prevail will allow for openness.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="1197" /> I welcome the fact that this is a minority Seanad.  It means Members must address issues, act responsibly and put forward proposals based on their beliefs.  It has been suggested that Members might act in a mischievous way.  There are five Independents and we are committed to making the Seanad work effectively and responsibly.</P>
    <P>In thanking the previous Administration, I want to end on a sour note.</P>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFallon" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>It is Christmas time.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeOToole" hpid="Mr. O'Toole Mr. O'Toole">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Toole</NameTxt>
      <P>We have had positive relations with the Fianna Fáil Party.  We worked, argued and heckled, which is part of the political process.  The drama played out here last week when Senator Henry was speaking was unacceptable and will not be tolerated.  I will take whatever steps are necessary, either through the party leaders or the Committee on Procedure and Privileges, to state that such behaviour is unacceptable.  I am speaking about a very small number of people and I do not want all on the Fianna Fáil benches to be tarred with the same brush.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="A Senator A Senator">
      <NameTxt>A Senator</NameTxt>
      <P>Name them.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeOToole" hpid="Mr. O'Toole Mr. O'Toole">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Toole</NameTxt>
      <P>I will not name them but it was unacceptable behaviour.</P>
      <P>In relation to today's Order of Business, the Leader of the House will appreciate more than most our anxiety to get a comprehensive list of the legislation he intends to bring before the House.  I will continue to raise this question on every occasion we meet.  The honeymoon ends today.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JanOSullivan" hpid="Ms O'Sullivan Ms O'Sullivan">
      <NameTxt>Ms O'Sullivan</NameTxt>
      <P>Like Senator O'Toole, I am one of a minority of Senators who will remain in the same seat under the new Administration.  I look forward to working with Senator Manning, his Fine Gael colleagues and Senator Sherlock.  I thank Senator Wright.  Senator Mullooly and all the Fianna Fáil Senators with whom we worked during the past two years.  Senator Wright ran the Seanad in <Col N="1198" /> an impeccable manner and I wish to record my appreciation of his excellent work as Leader of the House.  I very much enjoyed working with him.</P>
      <P>I welcome Senator Haughey and Senator Mulcahy who, given their illustrious names, can look forward to giving good service in the Seanad.  I look forward to working with my new colleagues on the Government benches and all Members of the Seanad.  The Seanad has been very constructive and I have no doubt it will continue to be so. Senator O'Toole said that the Independent Senators will continue to be constructive. They have always been very enthusiastic and positive in their contributions. I look forward to the challenges facing us in the knowledge that we will get very good results.  I also look forward to dealing with a comprehensive programme of legislation.  Under the previous Administration we dealt with a substantial amount of legislation and I look forward to continuing this work with my new colleagues.</P>
      <P>I wish the Members and staff of the House a very happy Christmas.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFallon" hpid="An Cathoirleach An Cathoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I am allowing some latitude as this is the last sitting day before the Christmas recess.  However, the Minister is waiting to take the Bill and I ask Senators to be as brief as possible.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnDardis" hpid="Mr. Dardis Mr. Dardis">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dardis</NameTxt>
      <P>Given where he is sitting, I am sure the Cathaoirleach has detected a slight shift to the left in the centre isle.  I do not know if this is indicative of the complexion of the Government.</P>
      <P>I thank the Cathaoirleach for the way in which he has conducted the business of the Seanad.  We appreciate his impartiality in the way he has treated us.  We wish him, the staff, the ushers and the members of the press a very happy Christmas.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I welcome Senator Mulcahy and Senator Haughey and look forward to working closely with them.  I was very tempted to call a vote on the Order of <Col N="1199" /> Business merely to see what the outcome would be.</P>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFallon" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>It is too early.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnDardis" hpid="Mr. Dardis Mr. Dardis">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dardis</NameTxt>
      <P>However, in keeping with the seasonal spirit and in deference to the Cathaoirleach I will resist the temptation. Nevertheless, it would be interesting to test the strength of the minority on the other side of the House.</P>
      <P>In congratulating the new Leader of the House I am concerned about paragraph (ii) of Item 2 on today's Order Paper which states that there shall be no debate on committee, Report and Fifth Stages except by special permission of the Chair to allow a question of a specific nature.  I realise the need for doing this during this week but I caution him to be very careful not to adopt a similar tactic in the future.  Having regard to the points he made when he was on this side of the House, I know he will not adopt a similar tactic; he always resisted such attempts.</P>
      <P>I thank the former Leader of the House, Senator Wright, and the Whips, Senator Mullooly and Senator Fitzgerald, for the way they conducted the business of the House.  I would go so far as to say that their colleagues in the Dáil could learn a great deal from them on how to conduct their business.</P>
      <P>On the question of the type of opposition which can be expected after the Christmas recess, I am sure the Leader and Senators on the other side know that the Progressive Democrats will provide constructive and searching opposition. We have a great opportunity to go forward on the basis of consensus.  I am pleased that the Leader has adopted a positive tone.  It is not a question of our attempting to vote down legislation but of improving legislation.  If that is the spirit in which discussions are held between the Whips and the various group leaders, we can look forward to a very successful Seanad.  I wish Members and staff a happy Christmas and hope we will return invigorated and ready for action.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1200" />
    <Speaker pid="MaryHenry" hpid="Dr. Henry Dr. Henry">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Henry</NameTxt>
      <P>I can assure the Seanad that we will be co-operative.  I am sorry Senator O'Toole raised that issue; it was not my wish.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFallon" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>That matter is finished.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMagner" hpid="Mr. Magner Mr. Magner">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Magner</NameTxt>
      <P>The success or otherwise of the House will be determined by a number of factors.  It augurs well that we can be assured, irrespective of which side we sit, of fair play and decent treatment.  As Leader of the Opposition, Senator Manning set the tone in that he opposed when it was considered necessary but co-operated with the running of the House.  I have no doubt Senator Wright, with whom I have a happy association, will do precisely the same.</P>
      <P>As regards the Whips, nobody could have been more co-operative than Senator Cosgrave.  He moved heaven and earth trying to facilitate Members. I have no doubt that Senator Mullooly and Senator Fitzpatrick will be as co-operative within the remit of their party briefs.</P>
      <P>The Labour Party did not have to move sides in this changeover.  Having said that, I pay tribute to the work, dedication and loyalty of my Fianna Fáil colleagues when they were on this side of the House.  As I said last week I have no intention of decrying that effort.  It was very worthwhile and it was good. We provided good Government.  The fact that the Government fell is not the fault of any Member of this House.  I wish them a happy Christmas and thank them for their comradeship and support over the last two years.</P>
      <P>I too welcome Senator Haughey who has been instrumental in the Northern Ireland peace process.  He deserves his place in this House.  Senator Mulcahy, who has been at the coalface of by-elections &mdash; having returned from Cork I know the pain &mdash; is also welcome.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Admittedly Senator O'Toole did not say he had a shopping list but I am sure he had it in his hand.  As far as possible all shades of opinion will be consulted <Col N="1201" /> because that is Senator Manning's style. We would hope that the independence of the Independent Senators will not be subsumed into a party with which we have to deal.  As in the past, let the issues decide the case.  I wish everybody a happy Christmas.</P>
    <Speaker pid="BrendanDaly" hpid="Mr. Daly Mr. Daly">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Daly</NameTxt>
      <P>I had wished to raise on the Adjournment the operational programme for tourism and the importance of having decisions taken on a number of projects with the relevant Minister.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFallon" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>If the Deputy wishes to raise it in that way rather than ask the Leader, that can be done, after the recess.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BrendanDaly" hpid="Mr. Daly Mr. Daly">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Daly</NameTxt>
      <P>This matter is urgent in that a number of projects relative to tourism are awaiting approval.  All the detailed work has been done and it is necessary to obtain sanction from the Department so that these projects can get under way.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidNorris" hpid="Mr. Norris Mr. Norris">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norris</NameTxt>
      <P>A Chathaoirligh, I add my voice to those who say you represent a focus of stability in this House and I am glad you are still in the Chair.  I join in the welcome given by my colleagues to the two new Senators.  However, to be honest, I have to say that I consider the action of the then Acting Taoiseach, Deputy Reynolds, was nothing other than an abuse of power on the part of somebody who had resigned as Taoiseach and chose to exercise power quite ruthlessly in the dying days of his administration.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Just to show that I am completely impartial, although I normally agree very much with my friend, Senator Magner, I think it is interesting that he said that Senator Mulcahy had earned his place by running in by-elections for the Dáil.  I do not think so.  I mean no disrespect to Senator Mulcahy, but I do not think an appointment as Senator should be seen as a reward for people who have not got into the Dáil.  As I am on that track let me say that the behaviour of Deputy Reynolds contrasts strangely and very unfavourably with <Col N="1202" /> the behaviour of the new Leader of Fianna Fáil, Deputy Ahern &mdash; to whom I send my very best wishes because it has been a difficult thing for him to have the prize snatched from him &mdash; and the new Taoiseach, Deputy Bruton, in his inaction with regard to our Commissioner in Europe, Mr. Flynn.</P>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFallon" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I would like the Senator to put a question to the Leader. He has not had one all day.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidNorris" hpid="Mr. Norris Mr. Norris">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norris</NameTxt>
      <P>One does not get everything one would like in this world.  I also wish a happy Christmas to staff of the House, the ushers and, in particular, the Library staff who, in difficult circumstances and with small resources do an extremely good job by providing us with back up and research information.  I look forward to the reform of the Seanad of which I am sure Senator Magner is thinking.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeSherlock" hpid="Mr. Sherlock Mr. Sherlock">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Sherlock</NameTxt>
      <P>A Chathaoirligh, ba mhaith liom Nollaig faoi shéin agus faoi mhaise ag gabháil duit féin agus do gach duine san tSeanad.  Tá mé an-shásta go mbeidh tú anseo mar Cathaoirleach.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I join in welcoming the new Senators. Since I was elected to the Seanad I have enjoyed support and help, especially from Senator Wright and Senator Mullooly. As the individual representative of my party, the Democratic Left, I had to rely on the Chair and the other parties, particularly the Progressive Democrats and the Independent Members, for time and I was always very much obliged in that regard.  That will give people an idea of the spirit of co-operation that exists in this House of the Oireachtas.  Nobody anticipated when I was elected that, within a couple of years, I would be sitting on this side of the House.  That is indicative of the change that has taken place in politics in Ireland.  My wish for the New Year is that in the future the Seanad will, as it has been doing, play an active and meaningful role in the lives of the people and enact legislation, which it is <Col N="1203" /> empowered to do under the Constitution.</P>
    <Speaker pid="FergalQuinn" hpid="Mr. F. Quinn Mr. F. Quinn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. F. Quinn</NameTxt>
      <P>I was surprised and disappointed to learn that we would not have a Minister here to discuss the Winter Time Order.  However, in the tone set by Senator Manning, I am willing to accept the suggestion that, at a later date, we will find an opportunity to do so.  As the Roman Senator said, <i>delend a est Carthago</i>, Carthage must be destroyed.  I look forward to the opportunity of having a debate to ensure that we gain that extra hour promised.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DickRoche" hpid="Mr. Roche Mr. Roche">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Roche</NameTxt>
      <P>I welcome our two new Senators to this side of the House, and I am sure anybody who read the Constitution would disagree with the contribution made on that issue by an Independent Senator.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I congratulate Senator Manning on his appointment to Leader of the House, I believe the time of this House will be used very constructively.  I compliment our ex-colleagues and friends opposite for the warmth of their contributions today.  I wish to put a suggestion to which the Leader might give consideration. Both the new Programme for Government, which I have read, and the old one, part of which I wrote &mdash; I am sure Senator Magner knows what I am talking about &mdash; contain significant proposals on reform of the administrative and parliamentary systems, something in which I and Senator Manning have a great interest.  This Chamber would be an excellent place for debating those issues.  Will the Leader make time available early in the new year to examine in detail the Programme for Government to ascertain the progress we can make on that matter?  There is a great deal of commonalty between all parties in that regard.  I would also suggest that legislation, such as the amendment of the Ministers and Secretaries Act, an administrative procedures Act, the amendment to the Ombudsman Act &mdash; I note Deputy Magner is smiling broadly &mdash; and a freedom of information <Col N="1204" /> Act should be initiated in this House.</P>
    <Speaker pid="EdwardHaughey" hpid="Mr. Haughey Mr. Haughey">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Haughey</NameTxt>
      <P>I am touched by the warmth and hospitality extended to me. I hope I will be able to make some small contribution towards the peace process and towards making Members of this House more aware of the thinking of the people in Northern Ireland.  I will make any contribution I can towards the peace process.  As the House has a busy schedule today and many of my colleagues on both sides wish to speak I will be brief.  I thank Members for their hospitality and for allowing me to be here.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelMulcahyFF" hpid="Mr. Mulcahy Mr. Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Mulcahy</NameTxt>
      <P>I thank you, a Chathaoirligh, and all the Members who welcomed Senator Haughey and me here today.  I was proud to be nominated by the former Taoiseach, Deputy Reynolds.  I hope my experience as a youth leader and my experience in Dublin City Council will enable me contribute to the working of this House.  It is important that we are constructive.  The people want this Government to succeed and we should do all we can to achieve that end by introducing good legislation to help everybody.  I thank everybody for their kinds words today.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFallon" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Before calling Senator Manning I take this opportunity to wish all Members, staff, ushers and everybody who assists in the smooth running of the Seanad, a very happy Christmas.  I thank especially our staff for their hard work during the year and the great courtesy they showed to all Members of the House.  They are courteous and hard working and I thank them sincerely for that.  Despite the change of Government it would be my hope that we shall have the continued co-operation of all sides of the House in ensuring the better, smoother transaction of our business.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MauriceManning" hpid="Mr. Manning Mr. Manning">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Manning</NameTxt>
      <P>A part from the general goodwill, wishes and promises of co-operation given on the Order of Busiised <Col N="1205" /> ness, which are much appreciated, a number of specific points were raised.</P>
      <P>Senator O'Toole sought a programme of legislation.  Since the new Government held its first meeting this morning, I will be unable to produce that programme until early in the next session. Nonetheless, I will attempt to ensure that legislation is signalled well in advance.</P>
      <P>Senator Dardis mentioned the Appropriation Bill.  This procedure is a one-off because of the time of year; there will be a full debate later.  Because this is a minority Administration, the hand of the House will be greatly strengthened, against Ministers who would endeavour to rush through legislation. This means the Leader of the House will be in a stronger position when demanding a full debate on every issue and full consultation with this House.  Despite the extra work imposed on the Whips, there will be a certain benefit to be derived from the new circumstances prevailing.</P>
      <P>Senator Daly raised a point about the operational programme for tourism.  I am aware of the problem to which he referred and shall contact the Minister for Tourism and Trade, Deputy Kenny, whom I will be meeting this evening and to whom I will pass on the Senator's concerns.</P>
      <P>In reply to Senator Quinn, yes, we will endeavour to have this matter debated in the forthcoming session <i>quam celerrime.</i></P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I should like to take up Senator Roche's proposal with great enthusiasm. In an earlier session there was a very long, useful debate in the House on reform of the Seanad in the course of which a number of specific proposals were advanced.  There is a general concern that the House should take a hard look at itself, in particular to investigate the ways in which it was omitted from some recent developments in the other House.  In that respect, early in the new year would be a very good time to begin a debate, including all Members of the House, so that we can consider events and submit proposals because, as <Col N="1206" /> Members have often said, it is the House which decides and the House which must lead; we cannot depend on Government to do it for us.  I will embrace that proposal in the early new year.</P>
    <P>Order of Business agreed to.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Winter Time Order, 1994:" RHead="Motion">
    <Title>Winter Time Order, 1994: Motion.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="MauriceManning" hpid="Mr. Manning Mr. Manning">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Manning</NameTxt>
      <P>I move:</P>
      <P>That Seanad Éireann approves the following Order:</P>
      <P>Winter Time Order, 1994.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Allocation of Time:" RHead="Motion">
    <Title>Allocation of Time: Motion.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="MauriceManning" hpid="Mr. Manning Mr. Manning">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Manning</NameTxt>
      <P>I move:</P>
      <P>That, notwithstanding anything in Standing Orders, and on the understanding that adequate time will be given in the next session to discuss item 3 on today's Order Paper, the following arrangements shall apply in the debate on the Appropriation Bill, 1994:</P>
      <P>(i)  on Second Stage, the debate shall be confined to spokespersons, the speech in each case not to exceed 20 minutes,</P>
      <P>(ii)  on Committee, Report and Fifth Stages there shall be no debate except by special permission of the Chair to allow a question of a specific nature.&rdquo;</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Appropriation Bill, 1994 [ Certified Money" RHead="Bill ]: Second and Subsequent Stages">
    <Title>Appropriation Bill, 1994  [  Certified Money Bill ]:   Second and Subsequent Stages.</Title>
    <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That the Bill be now read a Second Time.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFallon" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>There is a time limit of 20 minutes per spokesperson, <Col N="1207" /> with no other Members to contribute, as agreed under Motion No. 2 on the Order Paper.</P>
      <P>I welcome the new Minister for Finance, Deputy Quinn, to the House.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RuairiQuinn" hpid="Minister for Finance (Mr. R. Quinn) Ruairí Quinn">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Finance (Mr. R. Quinn)</NameTxt>
      <P>If I may intrude on the festive season I, too, would like to be associated with the welcoming remarks to the two new Senators.  I should like to pay a personal tribute to the unique contribution of Senator Haughey to the peace process at a very delicate stage, for which I am personally indebted to him, as he knows.  History will record his contribution but, as of now, confidentiality requires that we remain discreet at present.</P>
      <P>Senator Mulcahy and I shared a constituency for a certain period.  I should like to assure Senator Norris that not every Senator who is elected to this House wishes to make a career of his or her membership.  Nonetheless, everybody who moves on from the Seanad is improved immeasurably by the high standards of parliamentary procedure and intellectual debate they learn as an apprentice in this Chamber; I include myself in that school.  No doubt Senator Mulcahy will follow his desired objectives but I have no doubt that the quality of his contributions in this House will leave an indelible mark on the Houses of the Oireachtas.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I acknowledge also that the Seanad has handled the transition from one Administration to another with considerable diplomacy and skill, as evidenced by the contributions here this afternoon.  I want to give an assurance to every Member of the Seanad, irrespective of their party allegiance, that I will continue to respect Senators and the Seanad as a body, in the manner in which I believe I have always done.  This House provides a unique contribution to the development of ideas and the improvement of legislation.  I heard what Senator Dardis said about working to improve legislation rather than opposition for opposition's sake or obstructionism. <Col N="1208" /> It is my intention, in consultation with those to whom responsibility has been given, to consult the Seanad in a manner that will ensure that whatever legislation comes into this House will leave it in an improved form.  I thank you, Sir, for allowing me to wander from the Bill before the House.</P>
    <P>The Appropriation Bill provides a good opportunity to review economic and budgetary policy in the light of the new Programme for Government.  With your permission, Sir, I would like at the outset to focus on the main elements of budgetary policy which this Government intends to adopt over the next few years.  There has been much speculation in the media in recent days about the budgetary implications of the Government's policies and I think it would be useful to clarify matters.</P>
    <P>The Government's programme makes very clear our commitment to firm management of the public finances.  It is no accident that, in the programme, fiscal policy stands alongside our other main priorities in areas such as tax, employment and administrative reform.  As Minister for Finance I am determined that our commitments on budgetary policy will be met.  This is essential if the Government is to succeed in promoting an innovative and enterprising economy which will produce the resources needed to secure the social developments to which we are committed in the programme.</P>
    <P>The programme is quite definite about the targets that will be followed in settling the budget arithmetic.  The Exchequer borrowing requirement will be kept prudently below 3 per cent of GNP and steady progress will continue to be made in reducing the debt-GDP ratio towards 60 per cent.  The Government's determination that this will be its approach to budget policy is underlined in two ways.  First, there is a specific target in the programme for the evolution of spending over the next three years. The growth of current spending will be kept to a maximum of 6 per cent in nominal terms in 1995 and to an average annual rate of 2 per cent in real terms <Col N="1209" /> over the following two years.  Second, the implementation and phasing of all the measures to which the Government has committed itself depends on achievement of the budget targets.</P>
    <P>It is important to spell out why the Government has set itself these targets. Control of the public finances is vital to Ireland's full participation in the movement towards greater European integration. This is an issue which is coming to the fore again and on which the debate is likely to intensify in the runup to the 1996 intrgovernmental conference. If Ireland is to play its full part in the future development of an integrated Europe and qualify for entry to monetary union, we must adhere to the fiscal policy targets set out in the Maastricht Treaty, which is why they have been endorsed by the Government in its programme.</P>
    <P>Even if the Maastricht fiscal criteria did not exist, our economic and budget policies would have to follow broadly the same approach.  Ireland's national debt is still relatively high.  As a result, debt service costs pre-empt too high a proportion of our scarce national resources which could otherwise be used to support social progress, reduce the tax burden and establish the right environment for job creation.  The only way to free up some of these resources is to reduce the debt ratio by maintaining low annual deficits.  If we fail to take advantage of the present favourable economic climate to make significant progress in reducing the national debt, we run the risk of finding ourselves in a difficult position if the economic cycle should turn downward.  A relatively high level of debt also leaves us exposed to rises in international interest rates and other external shocks over which we would have no control. The increases in UK interest rates are but one indication that the period of falling interest rates which we have recently enjoyed may indeed be over.</P>
    <P>Budgetary policy is not just a question of getting the numbers right.  The aim is to establish the low inflation, low interest rate environment necessary for <Col N="1210" /> investment and sustained growth. Soundly based economic growth is the only way to provide on a lasting basis the resources to support the developments in areas such as social welfare, health, education and employment spelled out in the Programme for Government.</P>
    <P>Adherence to the Maastricht guidelines undoubtedly played a major part in securing the high level of economic growth here in recent years which, in turn, has made it possible for us to improve the public finances.</P>
    <P>The Government's programme gives priority to tax and spending measures which will encourage job creation and promote social progress and equity, but if these aims are to be achieved and the budget deficit is to remain within the Maastricht guidelines, resources must be reallocated.  I recognise that, on spending, the Government has deliberately set itself a demanding task. Growth in public spending will have to be less than that since 1990.  Our programme targets are designed to ensure this.  I can understand the concerns that many economic commentators have on the rate of public spending growth in recent years.  They should be reassured by our programme.</P>
    <P>We should, of course, keep the spending figures in perspective.  Public expenditure is there to deliver services to the community, on which many people depend for survival.  There are many people who call for reductions in spending but, of course, very few go on to spell out which area of service they would like to see reduced or eliminated.</P>
    <P>Public spending is not out of control here, and I wish Members of the House, including Senator Ross, would take note of that.  The spending increase seen in Ireland has parallels in other European countries.  The increase here has been less than that in the rest of Europe.  Irish public spending grew from 40.2 per cent of GDP in 1990 to 42.9 per cent in 1993: in the European Union as a whole it grew on average from 47.9 per cent to 51.7 per cent over the same period. These figures also show that Government <Col N="1211" /> spending in Ireland is still well below the European average.</P>
    <P>While I do not under-estimate the challenge involved in meeting the fiscal targets and providing resources for programme commitments, there are many factors which will assist the Government. The international recession is now over and the numbers on the live register are falling.  With more buoyant economic growth in Ireland and internationally the pressures on spending and on the budget as a whole may be easing.</P>
    <P>Public sector pay, which accounts for just over half of all Government net current spending, has been a major burden on the Exchequer in the past, but public sector pay is now set on a moderate course.  The pay agreement reached under the <i>Programme for Competitiveness and Work</i> has cost parameters which will ensure moderate developments in pay rates during the life of the agreement.  This, coupled with the fact that all outstanding pay arrears have been cleared, means that we can look forward to seeing smaller increases in Exchequer pay costs in future.</P>
    <P>More than anything else, the strong growth experienced in the economy over the last few years will help the new Government in framing its budgets within the fiscal targets.  The economy has performed very well, despite an unfavourable international environment until relatively recently.  In contrast to some of our partners, Ireland has seen continued annual growth since 1987. Our gross national produce grew on average by more than 4 per cent per annum in real terms in the years 1987-93.</P>
    <P>In 1993, the rate of GNP growth amounted to 3.7 per cent &mdash; significantly better than either EU or OECD averages. Last year's growth stemmed mainly from increased exports of goods while domestic growth was slower.  It seems that 1994 was even better with both exports and significantly, domestic demand making strong contributions to GNP growth.  Improved confidence is <Col N="1212" /> contributing to an increase in consumer demand, especially for cars, and an increase in investment, particularly in the construction sector.  Unlike previous years, domestic demand is strong this year, contributing to GNP growth and, consequently, employment.  As a result, GNP is likely to expand by about 5.5 per cent in the coming year.</P>
    <P>Our improved economic performance has been commended by a number of international bodies.  I cite these to indicate we are not clapping ourselves on the back from a narrow domestic perspective. Recently, the Japanese Bond Research Institute, JBRI, upgraded Ireland's rating for outstanding Japanese bond issues and gave a positive assessment of the economy.  They noted that our debt-GNP ratio has fallen, while most of the other EU countries have seen a conspicuous deterioration in their comparable ratios, reflecting the increase in public spending I mentioned earlier.  Another agency &mdash; Moody's &mdash; has also upgraded the rating of the economy from Aa3 to Aa2 on the basis of our improved performance.</P>
    <P>The economic outlook for 1995 is good.  Assuming that international interest and inflation rates remain broadly in line with present levels, next year looks like being another year of strong economic growth.  There is likely to be an acceleration in growth in the European Union and in the wider OECD area as the international economic recovery gets into full swing and becomes more broadly based.  In Ireland, GDP growth could be of the order of 5 per cent &mdash; with most of this growth coming from domestic demand. This should enable a further significant rise in employment and a continuing decline in the numbers out of work.</P>
    <P>The manufacturing sector sustained production at very creditable levels during a difficult year in 1993 &mdash; because of currency fluctuations &mdash; and is enjoying considerable growth in 1994.  Figures for the first eight months of the year show that the volume of output in manufacturing <Col N="1213" /> grew by over 10.5 per cent over the same period in 1993.</P>
    <P>While the strongest growth was recorded by some of the high technology sectors, the general performance of indigenous industry so far in 1994 has also been very encouraging.  Given the international recovery now emerging.  I am confident that manufacturing in Ireland will record another impressive performance in 1995.</P>
    <P>Ireland's inflation rate over recent years has been among the lowest in the EU, with the rise of just 1.5 per cent in the consumer price index in 1993 being the lowest for many years.  The latest inflation figures published last week show that, despite stronger growth this year, inflation continues to be very subdued. Our current inflation rate of 2.4 per cent is comfortably below the EU average.  The latest manufacturing output prices for October show a zero increase on October 1993, and output prices were actually lower in October than earlier in the year.</P>
    <P>At long last, economic growth is being translated into additional jobs and, more than any other single factor, the increase in employment will reduce pressures on the Exchequer and provide the resources the Government needs to implement its programme.</P>
    <P>The latest employment data show that employment is growing strongly. The 1994 Labour Force Survey, which was published in October, indicates that to April 1994 employment expanded by 30,000.  This compares with an increase of 7,000 to April 1993.  Before the better than expected Labour Force Survey results, employment was estimated to increase by about 25,000 for 1994 as a whole.  These forecasts are now being revised upwards to well over 30,000 &mdash; it could be as high as 33,000.  It is expected that our employment performance will continue to outpace that of our European partners over the medium term.</P>
    <P>This rapid expansion in employment which is welcome has led to a fall in unemployment.  The live register at end-November stood at 271,700 compared <Col N="1214" /> with 297,100 at end-December last, a reduction of 25,400.  This year, the live register is expected to fall by some 12,000 on average.  I am confident that the strong downward trend in unemployment will continue in 1995 as the expansion in employment is maintained.</P>
    <P>I pay tribute to Kieran McGowan and his team in the IDA for their extraordinary efforts.  IDA Ireland, which I established as a separate agency in the implementation of the Culliton-Moriarty proposals, had its best year since its foundation; it exceeded its job creation targets by almost 50 per cent.  We are now the single biggest location for US investment in Europe.  This did not happen by accident.  At this festive time I welcome the many IDA overseas personnel who are home for their annual conference.  I hope the Seanad will join with me in extending our congratulations to them and to the management in Dublin for the extraordinarily good job they have done with great commitment and expertise.</P>
    <P>Although job creation is greater now than at any time in our recent history, the drop in unemployment does not fully reflect the extent of this achievement. Senators will be aware that demographic factors have blunted the impact of the growth in jobs on the live register. In the year to April 1994, employment expanded by 30,000 but unemployment fell by just 9,000 as the labour force grew by 21,000 because of natural increases and the welcome increase in participation in the labour market by women.  These figures illustrate the challenge we face.  We have to ensure that the recent strong economic growth increases the economy's job creation potential.  This is why the Programme for Government has continued to give priority to jobs &mdash; creating additional employment is central to our strategy.</P>
    <P>People in our society will find it hard to get work even if additional growth delivers substantially more jobs.  I am thinking particularly of areas where deprivation and long term unemployment are in danger of becoming endemic.  Without assistance from outside <Col N="1215" /> agencies, many of the disadvantaged have little prospect of ever finding a place in the labour market.  We have to avoid the creation of cycles of deprivation, where unemployment in one generation leads to unemployment in the next.</P>
    <P>The programme contains a wide range of measures designed to bring about a significant improvement in opportunities for those without work. The Government will promote both public and private enterprise, especially small and medium-sized businesses in the early and most vulnerable stages of their development.</P>
    <P>For people who, as a result of disadvantage, are unable to benefit from these additional opportunities, the Government will ensure that training and placement programmes are directed to those most in need.  The success of the new initiatives we have planned will require the greatest possible co-operation between agencies such as FÁS, the partnership companies and local authorities.</P>
    <P>The new Government's task is made easier because the previous Government has left the budget arithmetic in good condition.  I pay tribute to my former colleagues in the Fianna Fáil Party and to the then Minister for Finance, now the Leader of the Fianna Fáil Party on his very successful track record as Minister for Finance.  That Government was, of course, very ably assisted by his then partners in Government.</P>
    <P>The budget indicators are comfortably below the targets in the Maastricht Treaty.  Ireland has seen annual Exchequer Borrowing Requirements of well under 3 per cent of GNP in every year since 1988.  A similar trend is evident in the general Government deficit which the Treaty gives as a primary measure of budgetary convergence. Since 1988, this deficit has not exceeded 2.3 per cent of GDP &mdash; comfortably below the 3 per cent guideline level.  It is a sign of the underlying strength of the economy that this budget performance was maintained even during a period <Col N="1216" /> of low growth in the international economy which saw the emergence of significant pressures in other EU member states.</P>
    <P>The general Government debt-GDP ratio has been placed on a firm downward path, falling from 116 per cent in 1987 to 96 per cent last year.  Ireland's performance has been strong enough to secure the recognition of our fellow EU member states.  Senators will be aware that only ourselves and Luxembourg currently meet the criteria for participation in the final stage of economic and monetary union.  I expect the Exchequer outturn to be below the budget target again this year.</P>
    <P>The Government will start work immediately on the 1995 Estimates and the budget.  I have outlined the emerging budget position to my colleagues and they have endorsed the general policy considerations I have outlined to you to-day.  I am determined that the 1995 Estimates will show that the Government is beginning the important work of implementing its programme and is keeping the budget firmly within the Maastricht criteria.</P>
    <P>The Seanad will be aware that the annual Appropriation Bill gives statutory effect to the departmental Estimates for the supply services, both non-capital and capital, including all the Supplementary Estimates which were approved since the last Appropriation Act.  The 1994 Bill appropriates to the various services listed in the Schedule the sum of £9,623,592,000 and it approves the use of certain departmental receipts as appropriations-in-aid.</P>
    <P>Apart from authorising the Estimates and any Excess Votes, the Appropriation Bill has another purpose.  It provides a statutory basis for the calculation of the issues which the Minister for Finance is authorised, under the Central Fund (Permanent Provisions) Act, 1965, to make from the Exchequer towards meeting the cost of the following year's services before the Dáil has an opportunity to approve the Estimates for that year.  Accordingly, the Appropriation Bill must be passed by <Col N="1217" /> both Houses of the Oireachtas before the end of the year to allow the provisions of the 1965 Act to come into effect.</P>
    <P>I commend the Bill to the House.  I wish you, a Chathaoirligh, and all your colleagues, a happy Christmas.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelOKennedy" hpid="Mr. O'Kennedy Mr. O'Kennedy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Kennedy</NameTxt>
      <P>I welcome the Minister to the House and wish him every success in his role in Government over the next two years.  The continuing economic prosperity and wellbeing of the people will depend on the discipline to which he will adhere and persuade his Government colleagues to adhere.</P>
      <P>I welcome also the Minister's fair and objective statement on the state of the economy.  Scarcely ever in my 29 years' experience in the Oireachtas have I heard a Minister of an incoming administration pay such tribute to the outgoing administration, albeit one in which he participated for two years.  What I welcome is that the Minister quite rightly goes back to where it started in 1987 when the growth of public expenditure was tackled.  The growth pattern of our economy at 4 per cent per annum in real terms is in sharp contrast with the experience of most of our partners in Europe.  That is the firm foundation on which Government policy can be constructed.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>As the Minister acknowledged, this incoming Coalition Government has inherited the public finances in their healthiest state for 27 years.  The Minister has given examples which makes my job easier.  The economic forecasts for 1994-95 indicate that at the end of that period the Government's current budget should be in surplus, assuming one adheres to the discipline applied since 1987.  The ESRI forecast that as a consequence of this effective control of public expenditure since 1987, economic growth should give rise to 37,000 jobs this year and GNP will increase by 5.5 per cent.  It is expected that the GNP growth will be followed next year by a rate of growth of 6 per cent.  One can confidently forecast, therefore, as the <Col N="1218" /> ESRI has done, that because of shrewd, effective and disciplined policies since 1987, we now have a situation where sustainable employment is being created as a consequence of the momentum in the economy itself.</P>
    <P>The business of Government, in any generation, is not to spend for the purpose of spending.  The business of really effective Government is to create the climate in which the entrepreneurs, the workers, the doers and goers will achieve, advance and grow to the benefit of all of the people.  I am glad to say that is what we have witnessed here consistently since 1987 from the Fianna Fáil Government of which I was very privileged to be a member.  We tackled in a vigorous, disciplined way, albeit belatedly, the difficult problems that had to be faced.  We are happy to see the benefits of the difficult decisions of those disciplined programmes benefiting the people.  All objective commentators, including the Minister, acknowledge the healthy state in which we now find ourselves.</P>
    <P>As a consequence of this effective and stringent control on Government expenditure we now have a solid foundation for further development which is characterised by improved consumer confidence, low interest rates and steady growth in real personal incomes which will obviously boost consumer spending and, in turn, stimulate employment intensive growth.</P>
    <P>All of that said, it is now absolutely essential that we do not put at risk the healthy development in our economy since 1987 by any change of Government economic policy.  I am very concerned at the first indication from the Government.  I am talking about an increase of Government expenditure, which was by no means a feature of Government policies since 1987 where we were reducing it in real terms.  The very most one should contemplate in Government expenditure for 1995 would be an increase of 4 per cent to maintain the discipline at home and, even more important, to maintain confidence abroad.  The policies pursued by <Col N="1219" /> Fianna Fáil Governments since 1987 have laid a very firm foundation for this unprecedented growth that the Minister has now acknowledged and welcomed. They have generated external confidence in the econmy to the extent that the investment climate is healthier now than it has been for many years.</P>
    <P>It is also exemplified by the fact that external investment in Ireland &mdash; I always acknowledge the primary role of the indigenous entrepreneur, and we are privileged to have many of them in this House &mdash; is now at an all time high with overseas companies employing 82,600 people at the last count, which represents a net increase of 5,300 in the past year alone.</P>
    <P>It has to be noted that when the Fianna Fáil Government came into office in 1987 external confidence in the economy was in a very deep trough. Each year from 1988 there has been a pattern of dramatic growth from total employment of 65,000 in IDA-assisted companies to almost 85,000 at the end of this year.</P>
    <P>I join with the Minister in expressing our appreciation of the IDA.  I acknowledge the role it has played, but I want to assert that all of its efforts, policy, imgination and commitment would be of no consequence unless the investing public abroad was attracted to this economy because of its direction and control of policy.</P>
    <P>I do not want to hark back too much to history but if one looks back on the coalition years, from 1973-77 and from 1983-87, the level of investment and financial provision for the IDA was at a significantly high level.  Despite the commitment of public expenditure to the IDA in those years, the return was of a very low order by comparison to what we have seen recently.  A good Government is not one that intervenes where it is not needed or that puts its toe into every boot.  A good Government is a Government that withdraws itself from the areas in which it is not needed but creates a climate in which the entrepreneurs will flourish.  We do <Col N="1220" /> not need to teach businessmen how to achieve profitability, any more than the Japanese or the Taiwanese need to tell their businessmen.  What they want is a healthy climate and that is why we can report the success that the Minister has referred to today.</P>
    <P>Foreign manufacturing companies currently spend £10 million per day in the Irish economy and their spending on Irish raw materials and services has grown by 16.6 per cent and 14.8 per cent respectively.  In addition, because of the attraction of Ireland as an investment base, the average cost of each job created with IDA backing has fallen &mdash; which is very welcome &mdash; to £12,780, a decline of almost 20 per cent in real terms.  That is significant proof of the attraction of Ireland for these external investments.  They want less to create more jobs where previously they wanted more to create fewer jobs.</P>
    <P>The growth in external investment is also reflected in a major growth in domestic investment and for this reason I wish to make two points.  I find it quite extraordinary that the new Government in its very first act, or even before it convened as a Government, has drawn up a Government expenditure programme which will increase by 6 per cent in 1995 with further real increases in 1996 and 1997.  That is giving the wrong signals to the external market about our direction. I cannot imagine any more negative signal than for the Government, to say, at a time when we have all the proofs of discipline and control, that it intends to increase expenditure by 6 per cent.</P>
    <P>If I could extend the confidence I have in the Minister, in terms of his overall control and imaginative economic policy approach, to his Government colleagues in general, I would be a happier man this evening.  Because of what the record shows and the demands made &mdash; and I hope his Fine Gael colleagues will not be the ones to cause the pressure here, I do not believe they will &mdash; I cannot have that confidence in the Government unless and until its members prove themselves worthy of it. From what they have said beforehand <Col N="1221" /> and from what they are doing now, I believe that a 6 per cent projection is little short of irresponsible at this stage. This irresponsibility is inexplicable and, having regard to the composition of the Government, the Rainbow Coalition, it can only serve to erode external confidence in the economy which has been such a magnificent feature of our development and growth since 1987-88. In addition, tax refrom will be severely limited by the commitment on expenditure and the many proposals for the generation of further employment will be frustrated by the short term, irresponsible approach of a 6 per cent increase in public expenditure.  Any Government can spend money.  Children can spend money.  Give them goodies and they will throw them around.  It takes a really good, disciplined Government to regulate and control public expenditure which, in terms of economic policy, is the first priority.</P>
    <P>Even allowing for the achievement of the control of fiscal aggregates since 1987-88, it must be acknowledged that growth in public expenditure is excessive but with the commitment given by the rainbow Coalition we are faced with the prospect of a programme which believes good Government is one that increases public expenditure.  Contrast that with the philosophy of Fianna Fáil which has demonstrated that good Government is one that regulates and controls public expenditure.</P>
    <P>It is significant that the European Council recently acknowledged Ireland's major achievement in correcting the trends in public expenditure. We have clearly demonstrated that we are operating within the Exchequer borrowing requirements in line with the Maastricht criteria as has Luxembourg. It is in a different position from the Irish economy.  It is at the core of Europe. The European institutions would be sufficient to guarantee the buoyancy, vigour and prosperity of the Luxembourg economy.  It is smaller in size than my native county.  We are in good company. If we are to be part of the European <Col N="1222" /> economic convergence and maintain our discipline, our inflation and interest rates, which have been a healthy feature of our economy, control of public expenditure is essential.</P>
    <P>Tax reform is essential to the generation of sustainable employment. &ldquo;Reform&rdquo; is a very nice word.  In the United Kingdom in 1988-89 there were grandiose tax breaks and a major increase in disposable income.  If that happened here the economy would be over-stimulated and we would be back in the all too familiar spiral of ever-increasing interest rates and inflation.  In 1983-87 the trend in external interest rates was downwards but our interest rates spiralled.  In 1987, 1988 and 1989 interest rates went up in the UK but they came down here.  The Minister referred to the negative impact UK interest rates might have now but we must adhere to our own disciplines.  I know it is not the only factor that affects our interest rates.  We have demonstrated that we can reduce interest rates even given an outside hostile environment.</P>
    <P>There are inequities in the taxation and PRSI systems but we should have a disciplined and consistent approach.  We should increase from £9,000 to £15,000 approximately the salary levels to which a lower rate of PRSI applies.  The present level has proved to be a disincentive to employment.  I am sure the Minister is conscious of that.  We must target tax packages and incentives in specific areas to get more for less money.  We must target the need to expand small business and bring in more low cost task forces and tax relief for that purpose.  The continuation of a partial and well-regulated privatisation programme of some State companies, by negotiation, must be maintained.</P>
    <P>I wish to pay special tribute to the Irish Congress of Trade Unions and the union movement for the spirit of partnership they have shared with us since 1987.  The healthy state of the economy is attributable in part to their partnership in helping us implement the difficult decisions we had to take.  Day in, <Col N="1223" /> day out the Labour Party attacked me and my colleagues in Government for being ruthless and cruel regarding public expenditure.  The Labour Party attacked me for reducing by 800 the number of jobs in ACOT and in the Agricultural Institute.  However, I thank the trade union movement who helped achieve that reduction while the Labour Party in Opposition followed the easy path of criticism and attack.  They accused me and others of having no concern for employment in the public sector.  Now they know, as the Minister underlined in his speech&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMagner" hpid="Mr. Magner Mr. Magner">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Magner</NameTxt>
      <P>Look at 1977.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelOKennedy" hpid="Mr. O'Kennedy Mr. O'Kennedy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Kennedy</NameTxt>
      <P>Look at the record.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMagner" hpid="Mr. Magner Mr. Magner">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Magner</NameTxt>
      <P>I will put it on the record.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelOKennedy" hpid="Mr. O'Kennedy Mr. O'Kennedy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Kennedy</NameTxt>
      <P>As the Minister stated, we now have the fruits of that decision.  I have more confidence in this Labour Party Minister than I would have in any other member of his party had they been given the job he has.  I hope he will adhere to the programmes and disciplines, from which he will now benefit and that the first signals from the rainbow Coalition will not be followed. If they are, we will return to a spiralling public expenditure as was the case when the Coalition which ended in 1987 were in office.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PaddyBurke" hpid="Mr. Burke Mr. Burke">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Burke</NameTxt>
      <P>I congratulate Senators Haughey and Mulcahy on their appointment and welcome them to the House. I welcome the Minister for Finance and wish him well in his new portfolio.  I have no doubt that he will do an excellent job.  Senator O'Kennedy has left the House.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMagner" hpid="Mr. Magner Mr. Magner">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Magner</NameTxt>
      <P>What a pity.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PaddyBurke" hpid="Mr. Burke Mr. Burke">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Burke</NameTxt>
      <P>He spoke about 1987.  At the time Fianna Fáil had a minority Government.  We set the financial&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1224" />
    <Speaker pid="JohnDardis" hpid="Mr. Dardis Mr. Dardis">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dardis</NameTxt>
      <P>I want my turn so that I may take credit too.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PaddyBurke" hpid="Mr. Burke Mr. Burke">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Burke</NameTxt>
      <P>&mdash;&mdash;parameters and as long as it stayed within them Fine Gael supported us.  Fine Gael did not bring down that Government.  It seemed to be a good Government but it brought itself down.  Senator O'Kennedy took credit for it being a good Government and for starting a revivial in the economy.  Fine Gael can take most credit for that and for not bringing down that Government.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnDardis" hpid="Mr. Dardis Mr. Dardis">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dardis</NameTxt>
      <P>Is it not surprising therefore that Deputy Dukes is not in the Cabinet?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PaddyBurke" hpid="Mr. Burke Mr. Burke">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Burke</NameTxt>
      <P>He is going on to greater things.  The annual Appropriation Bill gives statutory effect to the departmental Estimates to supply services, both capital and non-capital, including all supplementary estimates which are approved by the Dáil since the last Appropriation Act.  Apart from authorising the Estimates and any excess Votes, the Appropriation Bill provides a statutory basis for the calculation of issues the Minister for Finance is authorised under the Central Fund (Permanent Provisions) Act, 1965 to make from the Exchequer towards meeting the costs of the following year services before the Dáil has an opportunity to approve the Estimate for that year.</P>
      <P>No matter how committed and energetic the Government is in devising and implementing policies to reduce unemployment, it will not be effective if wage increases are so high that we become less competitive than our main trading partners.  There are too many people on the live register and the issue of unemployment, particularly long term unemployment, must be tackled because it leads to poverty and deprivation.  The creation of jobs must be a top priority for the Government.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>It is essential that the public finances continue to improve.  This will free resources through the development of <Col N="1225" /> the economy and facilitate the tax reform measures necessary to improve efficiency and create employment opportunities.  The best way to convert economic growth into employment is through reform of the taxation system. The levels of PRSI and levies have made PAYE and pay-roll costs too high. The difference between gross and net pay is too great and each year there is pressure on employers to cut their pay-roll costs and shed jobs.</P>
    <P>The Minister is aware of the difficulties experienced by the small business sector and, in particular, by small businesses in rural areas.  We have seen the difficulties caused by the new licensing laws under the 1994 Traffic Act.  If steps are not taken soon to deal with these difficulties then the rural business sector will decline and deteriorate even further.  I ask the Minister to look seriously at this matter in 1995.  Special concessions should be given to the small business sector, particularly in the areas of taxation and VAT, where the present levels are forcing many people out of business.</P>
    <P>Some people have told me that the loss of their medical card, increased rent etc., mean that it would not pay them to work.  I am referring in particular to people in low paid jobs whose take-home pay does not match the combined benefits from social welfare.  This is totally insane.  Previous Governments have created poverty traps and the people caught in them have been condemned to a life of idleness and unemployment. This is one of the reasons the Minister must change the taxation system, particularly as it relates to low paid jobs.</P>
    <P>I am delighted the Minister set out the position in which we now find ourselves and outlined where he intends to take us in future years.  He said that our improved economic performance has been commended by a number of international bodies, that recently the Japanese Bond Research Institute upgraded Ireland's rating for outstanding Japanese bond issues and gave a positive assessment of the Irish economy. It noted that our debt-GNP ratio <Col N="1226" /> has fallen while most other EU countries have seen a conspicuous deterioration in their comparable ratios, reflecting an increase in public spending. This augurs very well for us and I hope the Minister will achieve the targets. I have no doubt that the measures in next year's budget will strengthen the economy in the future.</P>
    <P>The Minister said it is expected that our employment performance will continue to outpace that of all our EU partners in the medium term.  He said that this rapid expansion in employment has led to a fall in unemployment and that the live register at the end of November stood at 271,000 compared with 297,000 at the end of last December, a reduction of approximately 25,000.  This year the live register is expected to fall by 12,000 on average.  Has there been a comparable increase in the number of people taking up FÁS courses or working on FÁS schemes?  In my area there has been an increase in the number of people working on such schemes.  I hope that any reduction in unemployment is not due to an increase in the number of people working on FÁS schemes but to an increase in the number of people at work.</P>
    <P>I hope the Minister will address the issue of the level of VAT on the clothing industry which, from an industrial point of view, we have a great opportunity to develop.  If the excellent people working in the clothing industry are given the proper opportunities we could become world leaders in this industry.</P>
    <P>I welcome the Minister to the House and wish him the best of luck in his portfolio in the future.</P>
    <Speaker pid="FergalQuinn" hpid="Mr. F. Quinn Mr. F. Quinn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. F. Quinn</NameTxt>
      <P>I wish to share ten minutes of my time with Senator Dardis.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TomFitzgerald" hpid="Acting Chairman (Mr. Fitzgerald) Acting Chairman (Mr. Fitzgerald)">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman (Mr. Fitzgerald)</NameTxt>
      <P>Is that agreed?  Agreed.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FergalQuinn" hpid="Mr. F. Quinn Mr. F. Quinn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. F. Quinn</NameTxt>
      <P>I welcome the Minister and I am sure he has noticed the positive spirit in the House.  It is said that <Col N="1227" /> blood is thicker than water but this will not deter me or others from advising&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMagner" hpid="Mr. Magner Mr. Magner">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Magner</NameTxt>
      <P>Does the Senator intend to shed it?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FergalQuinn" hpid="Mr. F. Quinn Mr. F. Quinn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. F. Quinn</NameTxt>
      <P>Having read the Constitution, it is clear that the job of the Independent Senators and this House is to enrich legislation, not to oppose it.  I look forward to a healthy and useful Seanad in the coming years.</P>
      <P>I am delighted to see the Minister in the House.  I listened very intently to his speech and liked many of the phrases he used, for example, &ldquo;promote development, spending restraint, lower increases in pay bill, growth which will improve Exchequer position, low inflation, an increase in employment and jobs a priority&rdquo;.  That is the sort of talk we want to hear from a Minister for Finance.  I am delighted the Minister is showing confidence in the future and that he is an optimist and realist.  I am also optimistic and realistic and I believe that running an economy is very much like running a business.  Given his background, I am sure the Minister will look on the economy in the same way.</P>
      <P>The time has come to take a fresh look at the way in which we control public spending &mdash; perhaps I should say the way in which we do not control it. In the past we allowed spending to increase in areas where we believed we had no control, for example, social welfare and public sector pay, and squeezed all other spending.  However, we squeezed spending in areas in which it would have been worthwhile to invest.  I am delighted that the Minister referred to the IDA, a typical example of an area where we should increase expenditure.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>One of the two points I want to make relates to the need to exercise stricter control over spending on public sector pay.  We cannot continue to accept the position where public sector pay increases by several times the rate of inflation.  When one is running a business there is a limit to the amount which <Col N="1228" /> can be spent.  Some years ago a leading American businessman asked if the then Minister for Finance ever had to worry about where the pay bill would come from on Friday night.  People in business know that there is only a limited amount of money and they constantly wonder where they will get the money to pay the bills.</P>
    <P>There is a system of management which the Americans call ZBB, zero based budgeting.  I am not sure whether this is an American or Japanese system of management, but it says that when one budgets one starts with nothing and we must work from there for every penny, instead of saying &ldquo;that is what we spent last year and can we maintain spending at that level?&rdquo;  Under this system one starts with nothing and works from there.  It is a marvellous way of restricting pay, you have to argue for every single thing.  We should work like the business person who wonders where the money will come from on Friday night to pay the wages.  We should set cash limits on public sector pay otherwise we will have fewer jobs.  We cannot allow &mdash; as happened in the past few years &mdash; public sector pay to rise above the rate of inflation.  That means tight control on every penny of public sector pay.</P>
    <P>The very opposite should occur when we come to other spending.  I recall the Merrion Street message to the effect that we have paid the public sector pay rises, let us now squeeze everything else at an equal rate and take 5 per cent off everything else.  That is the wrong way to proceed.  Looking at the great success of the IDA perhaps that is the area into which we should put our money if that is where we will get a return.</P>
    <P>I loved the posters seeking help for Africa, a year or so ago which stated: &ldquo;Give a man a fish and you feed him for a day; teach a man to fish and you feed him for life&rdquo;.  We have to consider investing in something that will give us growth and success.  That is not easily done and it is not an easy political decision.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="1229" /> At the Forum for Peace and Reconciliation last week, I spoke about returning from Enniskillen the previous Saturday and stopping at Ballyconnell, only a couple of kilometres from the Border, where I saw a magnificent hotel.  This hotel which has created 100 jobs, if not more, had a couple of hundred cars outside it.  People were being encouraged to visit a part of Ireland which they had not visited previously.  It is difficult to decide to encourage development in swanky hotels and smart golf courses instead of helping the needy in that area but if it creates wealth and 100 jobs for the next century then we should not be shy about investing in the future rather than filling a gap.  We need to set priorities.</P>
    <P>An American writer, Petr Drucker. one of the best management economists of this century talked about the dangers of businesses feeding problems and starving opportunities when they should operate the other way round.  Our objective should be to create the growth that will finance the things we want to do and to concentrate on doing those in the future.  It is important to make a clear distinction between public sector pay, on which we must put cash limits, and areas which will directly help the economy to grow, and to invest in those in order to achieve our objectives.  Some areas, no matter how desirable is investment there, will have to wait for that investment if they do not give a return in the immediate future.  We must protect ourselves against spending too much in some areas and in the other area we will have to continue to invest. It is not an easy political decision but it will have to be taken.  Therefore, I am impressed with the Minister's words today.  Likewise I am confident that he and the team coming into office this week will examine the opportunities and identify the problems.</P>
    <P>I will finish with a story worth telling. A British battleship commander out on manoeuvres in dreary, dark, foggy, uncomfortable conditions for three or four days saw another light in the distance and sent out a message to the signalman <Col N="1230" /> to change direction by 32 degrees.  Word came back: &ldquo;You change direction 32 degrees&rdquo;.  The battleship commander was annoyed and frustrated and replied: &ldquo;I am a five star commander &mdash; change direction&rdquo;.  Word came back: &ldquo;I am a second rate seaman, you change direction&rdquo;.  By this stage the battleship commander was very annoyed and sent out word that his was a battleship in which the reply was: &ldquo;This is a lighthouse&rdquo;.  The battleship changed direction.  That is a lovely story and I do not tell it because I enjoy telling it but because it shows up some of the challenges that will face us.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMagner" hpid="Mr. Magner Mr. Magner">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Magner</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not like the Senator's policies but his stories are great.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FergalQuinn" hpid="Mr. F. Quinn Mr. F. Quinn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. F. Quinn</NameTxt>
      <P>Let us look carefully at the long term objectives and use all the information at our disposal.  Let us not take chances without that information being available.  If we have to change direction let us do so and let us not expect somebody else to do it for us.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnDardis" hpid="Mr. Dardis Mr. Dardis">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dardis</NameTxt>
      <P>I thank Senator Quinn for sharing his time with me.  I missed the point of the Senator's story because I thought he was referring to the arrangements which brought the Government into being and not to the economy.  I congratulate Deputy Quinn on his appointment as Minister for Finance and wish him well in that portfolio. I am sure he will bring the same efficiency to bear on that Department as he did in his previous capacity as Minister for Enterprise and Employment. I am tempted, once again, to force this matter to a vote to see what would happen and the arrival of the Government Whip tempts me even more, but on the assumption that Senators are writing their Christmas cards and are in their offices I will not press the matter. I thank the Minister for his assurance about the manner in which legislation will be dealt with.  The House can work well in improving legislation and it is <Col N="1231" /> not our intention, just because we are in Opposition, to vote down legislation.</P>
      <P>I would not like any party to be omitted from the self congratulation business. The Progressive Democrats were in Government from 1989 onwards and had a significant input into improving the economy and producing the figures, which the Minister has brought to our attention today.  I was disappointed that Senator O'Kennedy did not acknowledge our input.</P>
      <P>When the House comes to the end of its term the Independent Senators will also be able to say they had a significant input into the prudent management of the economy.</P>
      <P>I thank God for Maastricht because without it I do not know where we would be and I would fear where we are going.  It is to the Government's credit that it has accepted the Maastricht criteria. However, it is part of a Treaty which was voted on in a Referendum by the people and it is therefore a Treaty to which we are committed.  When we debated the Maastricht Treaty, I made the point that it would be to the country's advantage if, whatever Administration was in power, it was obliged to adhere to those criteria which I regarded as important to the prudent management of our economy.  That is why we must be grateful for the Maastricht Treaty.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The Minister made a significant point when he said that growth in public spending will have to be less than it has been since 1990.  I say amen to that.  We need to be careful when we talk about a 2 per cent increase in real current spending because the public takes that to mean a 2 per cent increase.  However, that is not so.  What we are talking about is an increase after inflation has been taken into account.  The other point made was that there would be a 6 per cent maximum increase in nominal current spending for 1995.  Again inflation is built in.  However, we must be careful that we do not mislead the public by using words like &ldquo;nominal&rdquo; and &ldquo;real&rdquo; in talking about public spending.  I could <Col N="1232" /> go on at some length on the points made by Senator Quinn but I will not, other than to say that I agree wholeheartedly with what he said about spending in the public sector.  It will not be good enough if spending in the public sector is used as a device to doctor unemployment figures or if the public sector is used as a vehicle for appearing to solve the problem of unemployment.  If we were to do that we would be going down a dangerous road.</P>
    <P>One of the very disappointing features of the excellent growth in the economy is that it has not been translated into jobs to the degree one would expect.  It is orthodox economic theory that every 1 per cent increase in growth over a certain level will automatically result in a 1 per cent decrease in unemployment. That does not seem to have happened.  I share Senator Burke's suspicion that FÁS schemes and increases in employment in the public sector are in some way hiding the real performance of the economy and suggesting that there is a better performance in terms of a reduction in unemployment than is actually being generated from the growth in the economy.</P>
    <P>Because of the extent of our national debt we must ensure that inflation is kept under control.  It would be very serious if we were to face a significant increase in international interest rates thereby increasing annually the burden of servicing our debt and eliminating the buoyancy in terms of the amount of tax revenue and money that the Minister has to disburse within the economy. There is a serious danger of that and that is why it is essential that inflation be kept under control.  From what the Minister said this afternoon I understand that is his intention.  The benefits of growth must be protected to ensure that the people who are working and attempting to create jobs within the economy are helped best by the Government.</P>
    <P>It is evident that we must foster an enterprise culture.  I have said repeatedly that there is a suggestion abroad that there is not an enterprise culture in <Col N="1233" /> our society.  I dispute that.  We have a highly enterprising and intelligent people, a highly creative people.  It is a question of releasing that creativity, that spirit of enterprise and encouraging it so that people who take risks can reap the benefits of those risks.</P>
    <P>We must remember also that Structural Funds will not last forever.  We must begin to frame economic policies to take that into account.  What happens when we get to the end of the rainbow? I am not an economist but I would like to know what is the effect of the Structural Funds on the growth figures that are presented.  Are they factored in?  Is it growth in the economy when we build and open a motorway in north Kildare?</P>
    <P>I hope the Culliton report will not be left to moulder on some shelf.  I know measures have been taken in respect of many of the recommendations of the Culliton report but there is still much to be done.  It can still be a blueprint which can be used to effect.  It is my hope that when the Minister drafts his budget he will take into account some of the things I have said to him in regard to rewarding effort and enterprise.</P>
    <P>I have one final point which it is probably not appropriate to make now, but I will mention it because this is the only chance I am likely to get.  In this country there is VAT on dog food.  I am not referring to the dog food manufactured by a particular company in the midlands which I will not name and which has or may not have a director whom I will not name either.  I am talking about dog food manufactured by Provender Millers. If they produce animal food it is exempt from VAT but if they produce dog food it is subject to 21 per cent VAT.  Across the water there is a zero VAT rate on dog food.  This puts Provender Millers at a competitive disadvantage. I will, therefore, use this opportunity to ask the Minister to look at that aspect of the enterprise economy when framing his budget.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMagner" hpid="Mr. Magner Mr. Magner">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Magner</NameTxt>
      <P>Last week when I paid tribute to my Fianna Fáil compatriots on the way they dealt with us during the <Col N="1234" /> two years they were in Government, I had occasion to attack Senator O'Kennedy. I do it again tonight with as much pleasure as I did on the last occasion. The idea of the Minister, Deputy Quinn, accepting a lecture from Senator O'Kennedy on financial rectitude is akin to accepting advice on protecting the Treasury from emperor Bokassa or Papa Doc because he conveniently forgot that he was one of the people who sat around the Cabinet table and destroyed the income base of this country by removing, at the stroke of a pen, tax on motor vehicles and rates on houses.  We are still suffering the consequences. Of all the people in this House he is the least qualified to offer advice on protecting the Treasury of the Republic of Ireland.  It is a matter of great regret to me that I am unable to say what I have to say in his presence.  I have many more notes relevant to that but there is no point in wasting my sweetness on the desert air.</P>
      <P>
        <i>(Interruptions.)</i>
      </P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMagner" hpid="Mr. Magner Mr. Magner">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Magner</NameTxt>
      <P>I have taken a vow to treat Senator Dardis with gentleness during this Christmas time and also because, now and again, we will probably have to depend on his vote.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnDardis" hpid="Mr. Dardis Mr. Dardis">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dardis</NameTxt>
      <P>What about Senator Ross?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMagner" hpid="Mr. Magner Mr. Magner">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Magner</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator Ross is going to join Fine Gael some time this year.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The Appropriations Bill gives us an opportunity to range widely over the Finance portfolio.  I welcome to the House my colleague and friend, the Minister for Finance, Deputy Ruairí Quinn.  I have no doubt that at the end of his tenure in that office he will have more than justified the confidence we all have in him.  The idea of the markets having nerves is laughable because Deputy Quinn in the Department of Enterprise and Employment was the image of a Minister who did not have any sacred cows &mdash; if he saw one he would shoot it.  He was engaged in modernising <Col N="1235" /> the economy and was recognised by all as a modern, far seeing, &ldquo;can do&rdquo; type of Minister.  His restructuring of the IDA helped to create 30,000 jobs and gives the lie to the idea that he would be anything other than what he is &mdash; prudent and dynamic.</P>
    <P>I would probably part company with the Minister's cousin on the issue of public expenditure which, as an expression, hides a great deal of pain in the public arena.  As Senator Quinn stated, a company sets various norms depending on its income but &mdash; and Senator Quinn has a reputation in this regard &mdash; one must look after those most in need.  There is a great deal of talk about transparency and accountability, but there should also be an audit of where people's money goes.  That is not always apparent to the public. Senator Quinn referred to experts in the business world.  Business people use a language which the public do not understand. There is also a political and a Civil Service language which the public do not understand.  While we sometimes believe we are giving people plenty of information, we are telling them nothing.  We might as well be talking in Hindi because they do not understand the language.  We may tell the public that the Garda and other public bodies cost a certain number of pounds to run each year, but the ordinary people do not understand where their tax money goes.</P>
    <P>The public should be told how much of its money is expended on the services provided by nurses, doctors, teachers, firemen, gardaí, social workers, dentists and so on.  They provide a service and make life better for people.  The Minister should also publish information on the large amount of money expended on grants to industry and business in terms of training, equipment and so on.  I am not saying those grants are not necessary, but such information should be published.  We should also publish the income one can get from shrewd investment in bonds and Government stocks or by playing the stock market.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="1236" /> I come from Cork and some people there are very begrudging because it is often termed the second city, but I detest that.  I am not saying this in a spirit of begrudgery but in terms of highlighting what our society is like.  It gives a wonderful life to a few people &mdash; something I do not begrudge &mdash; a good life to a substantial minority, a modest life to some and a reasonably hard life to others, but it gives a miserable life to far too many, one wrapped up in poverty, want, degradation and a lack of opportunity.  While those people may share the next world with us, they share nothing of this world.  If a Minister for Finance has any obligation surely it is to make life better for the majority of our people.  That is in keeping with prudent financial expenditure as well as not only a Christian but a good conscience.  It is in our interests that this country provides a decent life for all its people, but that is not the case.</P>
    <P>The public audit to which I referred earlier would go a long way to towards providing transparency if it was worded in language that could be readily understood by all people.  It should be sent to schools, universites and regional technical colleges for the information of students.  People of all ages and at all levels should know where their money goes.  Senator Quinn referred to the economy as a company &mdash; not a bad analogy &mdash; but the shareholders do not get much information.  They are not told why they must pay billions of pounds in taxes.  We are about to pass a Bill appropriating the spending of billions of pounds.</P>
    <Speaker pid="RuairiQuinn" hpid="Mr. R. Quinn Mr. R. Quinn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. R. Quinn</NameTxt>
      <P>Ten billion.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMagner" hpid="Mr. Magner Mr. Magner">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Magner</NameTxt>
      <P>I cannot even read the figures they are so enormous.  Out of whose money are we legislating for spending £10 billion?  It belongs to all of us, but it is difficult to find out where it goes.  One should be able to buy a book which deciphers insider language, but such a book is not available.  For example, people in pubs should be able <Col N="1237" /> to have a debate in ordinary language on spending public money.</P>
      <P>I understand the Americans can indicate in a referendum where the money they pay in tax should be spent.  In other words, if they wish, say, to give $5 of their money to the Third World or to a specific area of Government expenditure, they can indicate that in a referendum. I am not saying that is a good or a bad system, but at least they know where some of the tax money goes, whereas the general body of Irish people do not.  When we talk in a global sense about public expenditure, GDP and so on, politicans, clued in business men and their consultants may know to what we are referring, but the ordinary person in the street does not.  The measures proposed in the Bill we are about to pass will be financed mainly by the ordinary people.</P>
      <P>I began by attacking Senator O'Kennedy and to be consistent I will conclude on that note.  He proferred advice on financial rectitude to the Minister, Deputy Quinn, but I would remind the House of the Senator's record as a member of a Cabinet which took tax off cars and rates off houses without providing any other means of obtaining Exchequer funds.  Not to be outdone, the former Minister of State, Deputy Gene Fitzgerald, looked on the public service as a substitute IDA; if decent self-sustaining jobs could not be provided, jobs which the taxpayer sustained were created.  That was his way of dealing with the crises.</P>
      <P>I have no doubt the Minister will do an excellent job on behalf of this Government, and at the end of its term the idea that a Labour Minister should not have charge of the premier position &mdash; the Finance portfolio &mdash; will be buried forever.  I wish him and his wife well and hope he enjoys his job because it is important to enjoy what you do.  I look forward to seeing the fruits of his labour over the next two years.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RuairiQuinn" hpid="Minister for Finance (Mr. R. Quinn) Ruairí Quinn">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Finance (Mr. R. Quinn)</NameTxt>
      <P>I appreciate the warm welcome given to me.  I have positive memories of the <Col N="1238" /> apprenticeship I served here on two occasions.</P>
      <P>Senator O'Kennedy has already borne the brunt of in-house criticism, something on which it would be inappropriate for me to comment other than to say that whether we take a starting date in 1987, 1973 or 1977, we as a people have started to come of age in a manner which is a credit to us all.  We have demonstrated that the political process can learn from its experience.  I share the view expressed by Senator Dardis about the Maastricht criteria. They are an external discipline which will make my job and that of subsequent Ministers for Finance much easier.  It is not only the Minister of the day who benefits from the Maastricht criteria, the people voted for that Treaty and all the political parties in both Houses have recognised the benefits of their discipline.</P>
      <P>At the time of the collapse of the Berlin Wall an American historian of Japanese origin, called Fukuyama, had the temerity to write a book entitled &ldquo;The End of History&rdquo; simply because of the collapse of one distorted form of socialism.  Anybody who looked at the turmoil since 1989 will recognise that the fundamental issues of history did not end simply because one particular political ideology, in its discredited form, fell on its contradictions.  Constraints on the allocation of resources &mdash; which will always be scarcer than the needs prevailing at any given time &mdash; demanding attention, is one fundamental issue which has informed the history of political dialogue and debate within all sorts of Chambers and societies.</P>
      <P>In response to Senator Michael O'Kennedy, we are now moving in a direction that will enable us to consolidate the gains made under different Governments.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Senator Burke referred to problems of unemployment, small businesses and the need to tackle poverty.  He asked, in particular, whether the welcome increase in numbers employed was exclusively or substantially related to an increased participation in FÁS schemes. <Col N="1239" /> The answer is &ldquo;no&rdquo;.  The Labour Force Survey shows there are an additional 30,000-plus people at work.  Increased participation in special employment schemes &mdash; and this is subject to correction &mdash; has risen from the late 20,000s to 37,000 approximately at present. There has been a reduction in the number of people directly employed in agriculture which will continue over the next couple of years because of the historic reduction in that sector.  Therefore, we are recording not only a drop in the live register but an increase in the total number of people at work in our economy at present.  I think I am correct in saying that there are now more people at work here than for a long time.  The actual tax base has increased.</P>
    <P>Senator Burke referred to VAT on clothing in respect of which representations have been made to me but obviously that must await a Cabinet decision on the budgetary package to be presented to these Houses.  The original date for the presentation of the budget, Wednesday, 25 January 1995, has been changed to Wednesday, 8 February 1995, allowing an extra two weeks for the transition from one Coalition-combination administration to another, not an unreasonable postponement given the circumstances.</P>
    <P>Senator Quinn referred to the optimism underlying my contribution and my positive remarks.</P>
    <P>With regard to public spending generally and public sector pay which constitutes approximately 50 per cent of current supply services spending, the social partners in general, in particular the trade unions, within the terms of the <i>Programme for Competitiveness and Work,</i> have agreed to a much more modest array of pay increases over the next two years than was previously the case.  The distortions in the public expenditure profiles that manifested themselves in budgetary form were aggravated in that commitments given at the beginning of the <i>Programme for Economic and Social Progress</i> were deferred because, in the late 1980s and <Col N="1240" /> early 1990s, our economy did not perform as well as expected, when those commitments were rolled-over, suspended and-or postponed.  Therefore, to achieve a new Programme for Competiveness and Work, we had understandably to clear accumulated arrears, hence the distortion of the figures.  In fairness to the Progressive Democrats, who have been accused and criticised in another sense, I should point out that these were accumulated commitments properly paid out at the end of 1993. Therefore, we are in a much better position now to limit the increase in public expenditure.</P>
    <P>In reply to the points made by Senator Quinn and Senator Dardis about increased public expenditure, we have been very fortunate to have in place a social partnership which is increasingly becoming the envy of other northern European countries within the European Union as a consequence of which we have achieved moderation in our pay, albeit somewhat belatedly, and security in the operation of our economy, enabling people to take investment decisions, because they know the likely variables in a manner not possible within open market economies in which domestic costs, such as labour costs, are not planned and agreed on a rolling three-year cycle.  It is not unreasonable that people who have committed themselves to pay moderation &mdash; which clearly the social partners and trade unions have done &mdash; are entitled to a share in the fruits of the growth which will flow from it.  Senator Dardis referred to a figure of 2 per cent real increase.  He is correct in that, if taking into account an average inflation rate of 2 per cent to 2.5 per cent, it will be seen that one is talking about public expenditure increasing between 4 per cent and 6 per cent.  We are saying it will be a 2 per cent real increase on top of inflation.  Hopefully, inflation will remain at its projected level over the forthcoming two years and approximately 2.4 per cent for this year.</P>
    <P>It is not unreasonable to say to a labour force, who have moderated their <Col N="1241" /> pay increase and demands over a three-year period, that they are entitled to a share of the net additional economic growth that will accrue as a consequence of prudent management of our economy.  In this respect the Economic and Social Research Institute has given us a cautious but nonetheless very optimistic forecast of growth between now and the end of the century.  If we are looking at average figures of GNP growth of the order of 4 per cent to 6 per cent, then 2 per cent of that additional growth being deployed on improvement in public services strikes a reasonable balance.  The programme, <i>A Government of Renewal,</i> to which the three parties in Government have committed themselves, has set out a principle that, all other things being equal, we intend to share the fruits of growth equally between reductions in taxation on employment and improvement in the necessary provision of essential public services.  That is why I take issue with those commentators and others who say that public expenditure should be frozen at the rate of inflation because there are still considerable gaps in certain areas of the provision of social services which need to be addressed.  One need only listen to an Adjournment Debate in this or the other House and hear the demands for extra expenditure in specific cases because a specific problem or anomaly has arisen, to realise the justification for the principle I have just outlined.  Indeed the Senator proved his case by requesting a reduction in VAT on dog food at the end of his otherwise fiscally correct contribution.</P>
    <P>Those are the understandable and normal tensions in our kind of society and the objective is to strike a balance between the two.  I agree fully with the comments of my friend and colleague, Senator Magner, in clarifying the background to those figures, eliminating the jargon surrounding much of the public language with which we have become all too familiar in the course of debate.  I shall certainly explore the idea of communicating to our taxpayers what their money is spent on and how the community <Col N="1242" /> at large contributes.  We are all members of clubs, societies, or bodies of one kind or another; we know our membership fee, which is uniform or related to ability to pay, and we know our rights and entitlements as members.  If I understood Senator Magner correctly, he was suggesting something on similar lines so that taxpayers understand that their money pays for a range of services, that the quality, efficiency, or lack thereof, is related to the manner in which that money is spent.  That will be one of the hallmarks of this new administration.</P>
    <P>I respectfully suggest to Senators on both sides of this House that they read carefully the Programme for Government in which we commit ourselves to improving the quality of delivery of services to the citizen, as customer, as client.  Particularly within the public service we have neglected the overall question of quality &mdash; as distinct from quantity &mdash; of service.  The new Minister of State at the Departments of the Taoiseach, Finance and Transport, Energy and Communications, Deputy Avril Doyle, will be responsible for co-ordinating and improving standards of service delivery.</P>
    <P>During my term in the Department of Enterprise and Employment I came to the conclusion there was something incongruous in my being asked, as Minister, to present certificates of ISO 9002 to various companies in recognition of the improvement of the quality and delivery of their service when such a system did not obtain in the public service sector.  I asked a group of horrified public servants why the Department of Enterprise and Employment could not apply, qualify and maintain an ISO 9002 standard in the delivery of its services. Why can the Companies Office not aspire to standards of quality and performance? They are not just buzz words; they are the constituent components for improving the internal competitiveness of our economy.  We have to take full responsibility for the areas over which we have exclusive control to maintain external investor confidence in <Col N="1243" /> this economy.  There are things that only we can do and it would be my intention, as Minister with responsibility for the public service, among other areas, with the help of the Minister of State, Deputy Doyle, to focus on those areas. It is not a question of spending extra money, but of getting better value for the money already spent.</P>
    <P>I thank the House for its courtesy and support in relation to this substantial legislation.  I am acutely aware that this is taxpayers' money, not the Government's money.  As I said in an interview over the weekend, I am acutely aware that every penny of public money is taken painfully and I am committed to ensuring it is spent effectively with equity and with justice.</P>
    <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
    <P>Agreed to take remaining Stages today.</P>
    <P>Bill put through Committee, reported without recommendation, received for final consideration and ordered to be returned to the Dáil.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Maternity Protection Bill, 1994:" RHead="Second Stage">
    <Title>Maternity Protection Bill, 1994: Second Stage.</Title>
    <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That the Bill be now read a Second Time.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFallon" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I welcome the Minister to the House.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MervynTaylor" hpid="Minister for Equality and Law Reform (Mr. Taylor) Mervyn Taylor">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Equality and Law Reform (Mr. Taylor)</NameTxt>
      <P>This Bill represents a concerted response to a commitment in the <i>Programme for Competitiveness and Work.</i>  As such it will facilitate the combining of work and family responsibilities and provide a most important statutory support for women in the labour market.  Basically, it is this principle of support for women in employment on which the existing law was based, namely, the Maternity Protection of Employees Act, 1981. <Col N="1244" /> Such support has also been afforded to women workers in the Employment Equality Act, 1977, where special treatment with regard to pregnancy and childbirth has been accommodated. Indeed, employment protection for pregnant workers has also been applied in the Unfair Dismissals Act and other labour legislation.</P>
      <P>In essence the Bill seeks to acknowledge in statute the true value to society of a woman's role in giving birth, while at the same time seeking to ensure that women should not be disadvantaged in the labour market because of that role. The Government's commitment in the <i>Programme for Competiveness and Work</i> derives from its obligation to implement the directive on the protection of pregnant workers, workers who have recently given birth and workers who are breastfeeding.  As an item of the programme broad support for the measure among the social partners is assured and both employer representative and trade union representative organisations have been duly consulted in the preparation of the Bill.</P>
      <P>Ireland fully supported the adoption of this directive when it was agreed by the European Council of Ministers in 1992.  I am particularly pleased to present this Bill to the Seanad today so that the obligations arising from the Council's decision can be passed into Irish law.  The directive also involves significant occupational safety and health and social welfare measures which my colleagues, the Minister for Enterprise and Employment and the Minister for Social Welfare, are implementing separately in parallel legislation.</P>
      <P>I should mention at the outset that in this Bill a number of improvements in the protection of pregnant workers, which are separate from and additional to the directive, are being proposed. These have been facilitated by the review of the operation of the 1981 Act and I believe they will be of real benefit.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The Bill confers on employees a number of rights to meet their needs arising from their pregnant, recent birth or breastfeeding condition.  While employers <Col N="1245" /> will face important obligations under this new legislation they should also benefit from a clear legislation framework to deal with the special requirements of such workers and the obligations which those workers will have with regard to their employment, particularly as regards notifying the employer of their condition.</P>
    <P>It was decided that it would be more helpful to employers and employees to prepare the Bill as a composite piece of legisltion on the employment rights requirements of the directive.  The alternative would have been to draw up a Bill which amended the 1981 Act.  The value of repealing the 1981 Act and re-enacting it here is that it provides, in a single source, the employment rights of this group of workers.  The re-enactment of the 1981 Act provisions will maintain existing entitlements to 14 weeks maternity leave and the optional four weeks additional maternity leave as well as the rights of workers to job security while on leave and to return to work after leave.</P>
    <P>Employers will continue to be entitled to adequate notification from the employee about her condition and her intentions to avail of entitlements. At the same time the diverse range of potential eventualities associated with childbirth are accommodated and the employee's rights are also respected in those unusual circumstances where notification difficulties may arise.  In all, a careful balancing of rights and obligations is retained in this Bill.</P>
    <P>In line with the requirements of the directive, the Bill introduces a number of important new provisions.  The scope of maternity legislation is broadened to cover all employees who notify their employer of their condition.  It also extends the categories of employee to include not just pregnant employees or employees on maternity leave but also employees who have recently given birth and employees who are breastfeeding. These points are addressed in particular in the definitions outlined in section 2 of the Bill.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="1246" /> The 1981 Act applied initially to those working a minimum 18 hours per week and excluded women on fixed term contracts with less than 26 weeks left to run. In 1991, an amendment was made by the Worker Protection (Regular Part-Time Employees) Act to include regular part-time workers.  This Bill provides maternity entitlements for which all employees who have notified their employer of their condition are eligible, regardless of hours worked or length of service.  This is an important advancement especially as women in the labour market are increasingly to be found in atypical employments where irregular hours or short service periods are so common.</P>
    <P>The Bill will also apply to fixed term contract workers until their contract of employment expires, and it explicitly addresses the position of agency workers with a view to establishing greater clarity as to their rights in this area.  In the past, there may have been some confusion as to whether an employment agency or the agency's client availing of the employee's services was the employer for the purposes of meeting maternity protection obligations. In future, according to section 2, the party who is liable to pay the employee is to be deemed the employer.</P>
    <P>Standard commencement, interpretation, expenses and preliminary and general provisions comprise Part 1 of the Bill.  Part II re-enacts the maternity leave entitlements of the 1981 Act and introduces a number of new provisions. The first of these arises from the directive and involves paid time off for ante-natal medical care.  Although time off for ante-and post-natal care is provided for in the existing legislation, in future such time off will be with full pay.  The Bill, therefore, goes further than the directive and extends the right to paid time off for post-natal care for women who have recently given birth.  I am sure Senators will agree that it is important to facilitate health care needs in the weeks immediately after childbirth and it is a practice which should benefit not <Col N="1247" /> only the employee but very probably the employer by ensuring that post-natal medical problems are tackled before they might seriously impact on the employee's health and her availability to come to work.</P>
    <P>The second new provision is section 16 where it is proposed to entitle the father to leave if the mother has died within 14 weeks of the birth of the child. In such circumstances the Bill will entitle the employed father to leave for the balance of the period of the 14 weeks after the mother's death.  Leave provisions along the lines of additional materntiy leave will apply during the final four weeks of this 14 weeks period, with full maternity leave arrangements operating up to that.  This significant new provision is not put forward as a cheap version of paternity or parental leave.</P>
    <P>Those issues are being actively considered in the context of <i>Programme for Competitiveness and Work</i> deliberations and the European Union social affairs agenda.  In opening up a provision of special leave for fathers in the very limited but traumatic circumstances outlined here, I make no apologies for recognising the need not only of the father but also of the newly born child. This type of provision has already met with the approval of this House in its debate on the Adoptive Leave Bill where widowed fathers of newly adopted children were similarly accommodated.</P>
    <P>Part III of the Bill reflects the special emphasis in the directive on protection of employees who are pregnant, who have recently given birth or who are breastfeeding.  It must be considered in conjunction with occupational safety and health regulations which are being made by the Minister for Enterprise and Employment.  I would like, therefore, to outline the general approach being taken on the safety and health side.</P>
    <P>As Senators will know, we have already in place a comprehensive occupational safety and health code contained in the Safety, Health and Welfare <Col N="1248" /> at Work Act, 1989, and regulations made under it.  Those provisions require employers to identify any hazards at the workplace, assess the risks which may be present for their employees and take any necessary preventative measures. The new regulations being made by the Minister for Enterprise and Employment will make explicit the obligations of employers, as these relate to employees who are pregnant, who have recently given birth or are breast-feeding.</P>
    <P>Once the employee has informed the employer of her condition, the obligation on the employer to take action will apply. If a risk is identified and it is not feasible to remove it, the employer must consider the possibility of moving the employee to suitable other work.  Only when solutions to the problems cannot be found within the workplace do the provisions in Part III of this Bill for the granting of safety and health leave come into play.  Very similar provisions apply as a protection against nightwork.  Here, the employees' doctor must certify that night work for that employee in her condition would be detrimental to her health.  The employer's response to this situation must first be to seek to move the employee to day work.  When, having failed to find other solutions to the workplace risk or night work, the employer is required to grant safety and health leave, there will be an obligation on the employer to pay the employee for the first three weeks, and to give, on request, a certificate stating the commencement date and expected duration of such leave and describing the circumstances in which it was granted.</P>
    <P>It is considered only reasonable that, as the risks exist at the particular workplace, the employer should be obliged to bear some part of the payments during the leave period.  For the remainder of the leave period, there will be a social welfare benefit payable on conditions contained in regulations made by the Minister for Social Welfare.</P>
    <P>The detailed provisions in regard to the granting of safety and health leave, are contained in section 18.  Additional <Col N="1249" /> provisions regarding the varying circumstances in which the leave will end are included in sections 19 and 20.</P>
    <P>In Part IV the Bill addresses the issue of protection of employment rights.  As well as re-enacting the protection of rights during maternity leave, and the general right to return to work at the end of such leave, it extends these rights to cover the newly-provided health and safety leave.</P>
    <P>The requirement to provide suitable alternative employment to the employee on return, where it is not practical for the employer to reassign the worker to her original job, is also dealt with in this Part.  Here the new contract under which the employee is offered the other work must be not less favourable than the previous one.  Notification procedures and postponement circumstances are covered in these sections also.</P>
    <P>The whole area of resolution of disputes is dealt with in Part V of the Bill. The disputes provisions under the 1981 Act have, in general, worked satisfactorily. However, in the light of experience some adjustment has been made and it has been decided that all cases of dispute should be referred to a rights commissioner first.  The right of appeal to the Employment Appeals Tribunal from the rights commissioner will, of course, continue to exist but the current option to bypass the rights commissioner service has been removed.</P>
    <P>In section 38, dismissal on grounds of pregnancy, giving birth or breastfeeding is prohibited by way of an amendment of the unfair dismissals legislation.  By adapting the unfair dismissals provisions the traditional resolution and redress mechanisms for dismissals disputes are maintained.  Protection is also afforded under the Bill for the statutory rights of pregnant employees in respect of redundancy payments, terms of employment and employer's insolvency.</P>
    <P>The preparation of this legislation has involved very detailed co-ordination with a number of Departments.  It has given rise to full consideration of the <Col N="1250" /> recommendations of the Second Commission on the Status of Women in this area.  In addition relevant agencies such as the Health and Safety Authority and the Employment Equality Agency have contributed to the preparation of these proposals and the normal consultation process with employer and employee interests has also applied.  In all the circumstances I would like to hope that we can process the enactment of this Bill without undue delay.</P>
    <P>I look forward to hearing the contributions of the Members of this House to this debate.  I know there is a genuine interest among many Senators on this subject.</P>
    <P>I would emphasise that this Bill is part of wider package of initiatives in this area.  It complements the Adoptive Leave Bill, 1993, which is currently before the other House and which provides for leave in relation to adoption of children.  As I have already said, the area of parental leave is under consideration in the light of the draft EU directive on that subject.  However, as far as pregnant workers are concerned this Bill represents real progress and a real improvement of their rights.  I commend it to the House.</P>
    <Speaker pid="DickRoche" hpid="Mr. Roche Mr. Roche">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Roche</NameTxt>
      <P>I welcome the Minister to the House.  It is rather unusual to be standing on this side of the House. When this Bill was introduced my party was an enthusiastic supporter of the legislation and we still enthusiastically support it.  We will not oppose it or be destructive.  The Bill is very welcome bringing into one statute the full range of protection afforded in Irish and European law to the pregnant worker, workers who have recently given birth and nursing mothers and it provides for leave to male workers in specific circumstances. In all cases it affords protection against unfair dismissal and it provides for a dispute resolution mechanism. The Bill is in every sense complete and a very good approach is adopted, effectively replacing other statutes and consolidating their beneficial provisions in one statute.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="1251" /> In the Dáil the Bill was generally supported by all parties.  However, as the Minister will recall, on Second Stage there was one notable exception.  One Deputy labelled the Bill as disappointing, minimalist in its objectives and pedestrian in its approach &mdash; column 1048 of the Official Report, of 26 October 1994.  The same Deputy labelled the Bill as falling far short of the proposals contained in the report of leave arrangements in a review published by the European Commission Network on Child Care.  That review suggested paid and flexible leave arrangements, including at least 16 weeks post-natal maternity leave, two weeks paternity leave, 12 months parental leave and ten days leave for family reasons per child per year.  With the extended traditional Irish family of seven, eight or nine children, one shudders to think, when you take into account annual leave, how much time a worker would spend in the workplace.</P>
    <P>It is interesting that this rather optimistic set of proposals was the baseline on which the only real opposition to the Bill was voiced in the other House.  As the political order has shifted and the party of the Deputy in question is now in Government, I wonder whether we are engaged in a time wasting exercise. Will the Bill be radically amended?  Will it be rejected for the Utopian ideal? Will the Deputy in question and her party pound on the Minister's door and demand a radical rewrite of what is a very fine Bill or will she, as I suspect will be the case, simply forget all that was said in the Dáil?</P>
    <P>The Minister will recall that in the same debate the Deputy suggested, at column 1050 of the Official Report that &ldquo;the Minister, in this Bill, is solidifying existing gender divisions when the should have lived up to his office&rdquo;.  Does the Minister accept that judgment?  I do not.  Is the Bill minimalistic in its objectives and pedestrian in its approach? Has the Minister failed to live up to his office?  I do not think so.  I hope that the answer to all three questions is in the <Col N="1252" /> negative and will be seen to be so by all Members of the House because I am interested in assisting the passage of progressive legislation.  As was said on this side of the House earlier today, this will be the hallmark of our operations in Seanad Éireann.</P>
    <P>This is a good Bill and worthy of support. It is a positive measure and while it could hardly be described, in terms of the language used, as user friendly, it comes very close to the kind of legislation that can be read and understood by the ordinary man and, in this case, woman in the workplace.  It replaces the 1981 and 1991 legislation and consolidates and builds on their positive aspects.</P>
    <P>In Ireland we have reached an interesting stage in terms of demographic trends.  Our birth rate, which was once one of the highest in Europe, is now the second lowest.  This fact allows us to approach the issue of participation in the workplace, particularly by women, in a more progressive way. The current birth rate is below the population replacement level.  This, too, will pose interesting questions of us as legislators and for planners of public services.  Not alone will this lead to a thinning out of the population, it will also radically after living and working patterns.  Thus far the impact has been more pronounced on the lives of women but within a short space of time it will have an impact on us all.  In less than one generation women's economic and social role has been positively and dramatically redefined.  The Bill recognises some of the changes and will put into effect statutory provisions necessitated by them.  It is therefore following rather than leading change.</P>
    <P>The Bill provides for a degree of flexibility; this won favourable mention in the Dáil.  As one Deputy commented on Second Stage, these affairs do not necessarily follow a clock.  In sections 11 and 12 the Minister has prudently provided for a degree of flexibility.  This is right and proper.</P>
    <P>I am most interested in the provisions which clarify the question of risk for <Col N="1253" /> pregnant workers or for the employee who has recently given birth.  It is particularly important that the right of new and expectant mothers to take time off for ante-and post-natal medical visits is clarified as this is an area where women have encountered difficulty.  The provisions of section 16 to which the Minister referred are not just prudent but compassionate and will be welcomed by all.</P>
    <P>There are, however, a number of questions on which I would like to hear the Minister's views.  How does he intend to monitor the implementation of this Bill?  It has been suggested that in the long term it could, unwittingly, militate against women who wish to enter employment outside the home, particularly during their child bearing years.  There is some anecdotal evidence of hidden discrimination &mdash; and there is also evidence of not too well hidden discrimination against women.  We need to make some adjustments in our monitoring systems.  Like the Minister and other Members &mdash; in a sense this is the reverse side of the coin &mdash; I am familiar with the criticisms of smaller employers in particular about the burden such measures place on them.  Do we have any objective system for monitoring and evaluating such claims?  If not, should we?</P>
    <P>The Minister is familiar with my contributions on other Bills he has brought before the House in which I highlighted the need to provide clear and unambiguous information to those who are intended to benefit from the legislation we pass.  Legislation put on the Statute Book has to be put into effect.  I am confident the Minister will ensure that the people who should know will be made aware of the provisions of this Bill.  I would like to see an information system put in place.  For example, it would be simple to include a resumé of the legislation in wage packets.</P>
    <P>I support the Bill because it is progressive legislation.  We will not create any difficulties for the Minister.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MadeleineTaylorQuinn" hpid="Mrs. Taylor-Quinn Mrs. Taylor-Quinn">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Taylor-Quinn</NameTxt>
      <P>I congratulate the Minister on his reappointment to his <Col N="1254" /> portfolio.  He had undertaken to do much good work and I am delighted he will now be in a position to continue it.</P>
      <P>This is important legislation.  Twenty years ago women were forced to resign from their jobs on marriage, particularly in the public service, semi-State bodies and in the private sector.  We have come a long way since then and women can now remain on in full-time employment. This is right and proper.  The legislation at that time militated and discriminated against women.</P>
      <P>Progressive legislation was introduced in 1977 and in the 1980s.  This Bill is a further step along that road.  It is important that pregnant workers are not discriminated against.  I am delighted the Minister has introduced this Bill and is affording us the opportunity to pass it into law as quickly as possible so that its provisions can be applied in the workplace at an early date.</P>
      <P>The Bill implements an EU directive relating to pregnant works.  One could argue that we should be ahead of directives but given the number of directives being issued from Europe at present this is not always possible.  The Bill is welcome as it extends entitlements to all pregnant employees, including those who work part-time, regardless of the number of hours worked, and contract and agency workers.  This is a major development and extremely important. Up until now pregnant workers not in full-time employment found themselves in an invidious position.  That will change under this legislation.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The Bill also extends the right to leave on additional grounds.  It should be realised that not every pregnancy is the same nor is every delivery; there can be complications before, during and following childbirth.  The Bill contains provisions to cater for these unusual circumstances. Definite ground rules are laid down; an employee should notify the employer, the minimum period of maternity leave is specified, etc.  It is heartening that the entitlement to leave is being extended to fathers.  If the wife dies during the 14 weeks maternity leave the father will be entitled to take <Col N="1255" /> the leave remaining.  This is a welcome innovation.  It is very important that every child has the opportunity to bond with a parent.  In the event of the death of the mother there will be an opportunity for the father to bond with his child.  We all strive to achieve a balance and greater equality in every situation.</P>
    <P>This Bill deals specifically with people who are in employment but does not cover women who are employers or those who operate their own business in the private sector.  The difficulties that arise for women employees arise also for women employers as well as for women public representatives.  If a woman politician who delivers a child takes 14 weeks leave the reality is that the males in her constituency will have taken every opportunity to do a hatchet job on her.  I am sure the Minister will have to use all his brain power and that of his officials to try to get around that difficulty because I do not see how women politicians can be treated equally given the nature of the political game.  I am speaking from experience as I gave birth to two children while a Member of Dáil Éireann and I know exactly what I am talking about.  The maximum I could afford to spend out of circulation was two weeks.  I do not know how the Minister will address that issue.  We aspire to treat all the citizens of the nation equally but let us remember female politicians.  Can anything be done to educate our male counterparts on this issue?</P>
    <Speaker pid="MervynTaylor" hpid="Mr. Taylor Mr. Taylor">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Taylor</NameTxt>
      <P>I will get the opinion of the Attorney General.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DickRoche" hpid="Mr. Roche Mr. Roche">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Roche</NameTxt>
      <P>He better get it right.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MadeleineTaylorQuinn" hpid="Mr. Taylor-Quinn Mr. Taylor-Quinn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Taylor-Quinn</NameTxt>
      <P>We may have to wait for a female Attorney General.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>This Bill is highly laudable and I commend the Minister for bringing it before the House.  The Bill deals also with the difficulties that may arise for female employees who may need leave for <Col N="1256" /> ante-natal care or to breastfeed.  The working environment can be more detrimental to the health of a woman when pregnant than otherwise and this is being addressed in the Bill.  The hours a pregnant woman works have a significant effect on her and night work may not be suitable in most cases.  This is dealt with effectively in the Bill.</P>
    <P>I hope the Bill gets a speedy passage and is enacted quickly.  I am sure all women welcome it as it takes into account not only their position but that of children.  While we would like to see greater developments in the area of parental leave, given where we have come from, we have made major progress in the past 20 years.  The Minister is to be commended for bringing forward this Bill.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MaryHenry" hpid="Dr. Henry Dr. Henry">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Henry</NameTxt>
      <P>I welcome the Minister to this House.  I, too, support this Bill very much.  Having been in employment before maternity leave legislation was put in place I had an even shorter time off work when my children were born.  I worked until the day before my second child was born and was back to work eight days later.  That was not out of choice but because one was afraid of losing one's job.  Tremendous progress has been made in this field in the past few years.  That development is not only wonderful for women but is a benefit to society generally because the health of a woman and her child depends on how well she is during pregnancy and at the time of birth.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>It is particularly good that the Bill also provides for the period of breast-feeding. We have the distinction of having the lowest level of breastfeeding in the world and anything that improves on that must be of benefit.  The 1981 Maternity Act made provision for 14 weeks paid maternity leave for women who work outside the home with the option of taking a further four weeks. The Council of the Status of Women has pointed out that this Act had a number <Col N="1257" /> of shortcomings and I am glad to see that some of these have been rectified, in particular those relating to paid time off for ante and postnatal appointments. Senator Roche referred to the cost to industry of women attending for such appointments.  I think this is being made far more of than it should because, as Senator Roche pointed out, there has been a massive demographic change in just one generation with the completed family size dropping from four to two which is much the same as our European neighbours.  If childbirth is to be a twice in a life time experience for women it is difficult to see how such leave will have an appalling effect on industry.  I think the economic problems it causes may be greatly exaggerated.</P>
    <P>The directive that gave rise to this Bill was greatly welcomed.  Exposure to hazadous, physical, chemical or biological agents must be avoided at all costs.  It is essential that a woman should take proper precautions to avoid such hazards during pregnancy.  It is very important that we will have made provision for paid leave for ante-natal visits as one is always fearful that a woman may hide her pregnancy rather than take care of herself.  This Bill protects against that happening.  In these days of high unemployment where the woman may be the sole earner in the partnership there is more temptation for a woman to cut back on maternity care.</P>
    <P>One could say that our legislation regarding reproductive health is very sexist.  It takes two parents to have a child but one hears very little about the effects of hazardóus agents on a man's reproductive process.  With a reduction of 50 per cent in the male sperm count in the western world and with infertility due to poor quality sperm this very important area needs to be addressed. However, in health and safety legislation I have seen there has been no reference to this issue.  Perhaps this is an area where equality for men needs to be addressed.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="1258" /> In the drafting of the Maternity Protection Bill, 1994, the Maternity Protection of Employees Act, 1981, has been carefully followed but aspects of the 1981 Act which were criticised are also present in the 1994 Bill; for example, the employee is required to give a number &mdash; I think there were 14 in all &mdash; but I was unable to find one section where the employer was required to provide a written notification.  Certainly, one of the most difficult for the employee was that contained in section 9 when they must give four weeks' written notification before the woman intends to return to work.  Has the employer any obligation to remind her of this?  She must also give written notification for a further four weeks if she wants to avail of them.</P>
    <P>The paternity leave referred to in section 16, which Senator Taylor-Quinn mentioned, is very onerous where death certificates may have to be produced by the man if he seeks to use his deceased wife's maternity leave.  Indeed, if one examines our maternal mortality figures, only two or three women, thank God, die within the six weeks period where maternal mortality figures have to be returned.  Within the 14 weeks which are allowed, there would at most, be only another one or two.  How many of those women would be in paid employment in industry and thereby availing of this maternity leave?  Many women with small children leave the workforce for a period or take a career break.  We are talking about perhaps one man a year who might avail of this leave and there are many heavy duties placed on that man which would require him to use up his late wife's maternity leave.  The woman would have died in very stressful circumstances and it would represent a tragic loss to the family. Would it not be possible to allow the man to take the whole period of maternity leave and call it paternity leave, for which there has been much demand recently because the father's <Col N="1259" /> rights and responsibilities, even with a new-born child, are considered increasingly important?  This is an area where we could begin to introduce paternity leave.  It is important to remember that in these tragic circumstances the man is left not only with a new-born baby but also with other small children for whom he must care.  The notifications which that man is required to make are quite onerous.</P>
    <P>To deal with these notifications, will the Minister allow for some form to be produced because it is difficult for some people to come up with the correct phraseology in letters and to send them in at the right time.  When a woman begins her maternity leave she will be given this form and all the various areas where a notification is required would be pointed out to her.  Indeed, a small explanatory booklet would also be useful.</P>
    <P>Many of the complications of the 1981 Bill are contained in this Bill.  In Part III, section 28, notification is required if the woman is fit to return to work.  If she stops breast-feeding or recovers from a medical condition she must inform her employer that she is no longer breast-feeding or suffering from this medical condition so that she can return to work. The woman must be ready to return to work within seven days.  I realise there has to be a time limit but seven days is quite short.  It would be useful if the employer was obliged to point out these requirements to the woman and, in particular, there should be forms available containing this information.</P>
    <P>One area with which I am concerned is section 38.  I am not a lawyer but having obtained advice on the matter, I wonder whether subsection (1) inadvertently breaches the European Union directive because it removes from the employee part of the protection of the Unfair Dismissals Act, 1977.  I am referring to the removal of the words &ldquo;and whose&rdquo;.  That seems to create a one year <Col N="1260" /> service requirement which I am sure is not what was intended.  It has been suggested that section 5 of that Act rectifies the position but it seems to be rather obscure.  I am sure the Minister will be able to explain this but I wonder whether the omission of those words from the 1977 Bill will cause a problem. I welcomed earlier in the year the Minister's Adoptive Leave Bill and I believe if this section had more closely followed section 23 of that Bill, it might have been easier to follow.</P>
    <P>Like Senator Roche, I am concerned about monitoring the Bill.  There are certain parts of it with which I am not happy.  I am not clear for example, about who will assess the risks to the women.  Will it be included in the firm's safety statement?  The guidelines on safety statements say that the services of a competent person must be obtained to assess the risks if the employer is unable to do so.  The risks will be different for a pregnant woman than for other employees and those risks must be pointed out to her.  There is not any section in the Bill dealing with pregnant or breast-feeding women and I wonder if the Minister will have to include a section covering this area.  Very often it is difficult to know what problems might arise with pregnant women until one examines various processes carefully.</P>
    <P>Another important point is that new technology can cause some concern to pregnant women.  Some years ago there was much discussion in the press about visual display units increasing the rate of miscarrage in women.  This was actually found not to be the case.  It exacerbated back strain because often people using visual display units did not have proper chairs.  Who will monitor the new technology?  Will it be the Department of Health, the Department of Enterprise and Employment or the Department of Equality and Law Reform?  Who will examine those areas because they are constantly changing and with new processes it is important <Col N="1261" /> that a person, when going into manufacturing areas, will study literature to determine whether there has been a particular problem elsewhere with them?</P>
    <P>The section dealing with alternative work and conditions of employment is a little vague.  The word &ldquo;substantially&rdquo; is always difficult to deal with; it is generally described as meaning of not great importance but it is difficult to know what it means in the context of this section.  I had dealings recently with a young woman who took maternity leave from her very good job as a buyer and when she came back, although she was restored to that position, it was certainly not the buyer's position she had left. She has very little responsibility in her new job and she sees her prospects for promotion evaporating, although she had a good record up to that time.</P>
    <P>I understand from the Minister's statement that disputes between employers and employees regarding risks, etc., will be dealt with, in the first instance, by a rights commissioner and then by the Employment Appeals Tribunal. I am not sure whether that is stated in the Bill.</P>
    <P>I presume that section 23 (e), which deals with improvements in work conditions while the women is absent from her job, will apply to the new mother also.  For example, if there has been an increase in salary, this will apply to the new mother when she returns from maternity leave.</P>
    <P>I welcome the Bill wholeheartedly and I acknowledge the commitment the Minister and his Department have to this area.  I hope he will take the criticisms I have made in the spirit in which they are intended.  They are merely queries about what I consider to be a very good Bill.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JanOSullivan" hpid="Ms O'Sullivan Ms O'Sullivan">
      <NameTxt>Ms O'Sullivan</NameTxt>
      <P>I welcome the Minister to the House and congratulate him on his reappointment.  I also welcome the Bill.  There is a move in society <Col N="1262" /> towards embracing the family within the world of work.  It is significant that many married women remain in the work-force and are facilitated in doing so without it having a detrimental effect on their families.  The Bill is also about the rights of young babies to have their mothers with them for their first few weeks of life and, through the extension of paternity leave, where the mother has died, to have the father present.  As Senator Henry said, fortunately the death of mothers during or shortly after childbirth is quite rare but it is important that the legislation provides for the father in such cases.</P>
      <P>This Bill implements the 1992 EC Directive, consolidates previous legislation and the commitment in the <i>Programme for Competitiveness and Work</i> is incorporated in it.  There was widespread consultation with employers and unions.  It is important that they support the provisions of the Bill which implements the will of the Council for the Status of Women in this area.</P>
      <P>Present legislation provides for 14 weeks maternity leave with an optional four weeks leave.  It is important that a woman has job security when on maternity leave.  The legislation must extend to all workers whether part-time, on contract or agency workers.  A greater percentage of women than men do contract and part-time work.</P>
      <P>It is important that we encourage as many women as possible to breast-feed if they so wish.  Everything that can be done to facilitate breast-feeding mothers should be done.  The statistics for mothers who breast-feed are lower here than in other countries.  The Bill provides for paid time off for post-natal medical care and that goes beyond the directive.  As Senator Taylor-Quinn said all pregnancies are different and the condition of women after births differ. In some cases there is need for more medical care than in others.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Section 18 deals with alternative work.  If the work a pregnant woman is <Col N="1263" /> doing is unsuitable, alternative work should be found or she should be entitled to leave.  I accept Senator Henry's point that this area is vague but it is hard to say exactly what might or might not be suitable.  Low paid work is often heavy physical work.  The Minister should state in this section where the emphasis should be.</P>
    <P>It is important to monitor the legislation to ensure it operates as intended and women should be made aware of their obligation to give notice to the employer.  The Adoptive Leave Bill discussed in the House recently goes in tandem with this Bill.  This represents progress towards a more human approach to the family and work. People have a family life and obligations outside of work.  This should not be seen as a negative factor but rather a holistic approach should be adopted in this area.  This should not be a problem for employers.</P>
    <P>Part of the fear among Swedish people on entering the EC is that paternity and maternity provisions would have to be reduced.  Sweden is a socially advanced society with a good economy.  The Swedish example shows that it need not be detrimental to the world of work and profit for pregnant employees or those who are breast-feeding to be properly protected.</P>
    <P>Senator Taylor Quinn said that since men do not become pregnant they might steal a march on women in political life.  When we campaigned for access to contraception there was a campaign poster featuring three well known men in a pregnant state with the statement that if men became pregnant we would have a more positive approach to contraception. The man bringing this legislation before us has a great deal of understanding and I welcome that.</P>
    <P>I would like to see progress on paternity leave but I appreciate that we must take one step at a time.  I understand the Minister supports the concept <Col N="1264" /> and it is under consideration at EC level.  It may be something we will come to in the near future.  It is important that fathers be facilitated in playing their full role in rearing children.  Sometimes the world of work does not allow them to do so.  We should be realistic about the fact that many employees are parents and when children become ill they should have a right to stay at home and look after them without going on sick leave and pretending that they, too, are ill.</P>
    <P>I welcome the legislation and the Minister's commitment to it.  We are all aware of what is intended and it should be monitored in order to ensure it is implemented fully in the workplace.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MervynTaylor" hpid="Minister for Equality and Law Reform (Mr. Taylor) Mervyn Taylor">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Equality and Law Reform (Mr. Taylor)</NameTxt>
      <P>I thank all the Senators who contributed so effectively and knowledgeably to the debate.  I welcome their kind comments and assure them that all the points they made have been carefully noted and will be considered by me and my Department.  I thank Senator Roche in particular for his very strong support for the Bill.  He, Senator O'Sullivan and others referred to the monitoring of the Bill.  I assure them that my Department will keep the legislation under close review. Interestingly, under the directive a review must be undertaken by member states on the implementation of the Bill within the next two year period.  This will give a focus to that.  It is worth noting that employer and trade union interests are very much involved with this measure from their perspectives and they will have a major role in the review.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I am conscious of the need to provide information to the public.  Senator Henry and others referred to this point. I will ask the Employment Equality Agency, which has a very important role in this area, to develop comprehensive information provisions in this regard.  It does an excellent job and it will have a <Col N="1265" /> major contribution to make to the monitoring of the legislation and the new positions which it will set up.</P>
    <P>The Health and Safety Authority will also have a role and regulations will be issued by the appropriate Minister. Senator Henry highlighted the crucial issue of health and safety for pregnant workers and, in particular, health and safety in the paternity context.  She referred to the notification requirements and suggested that perhaps formal proceducers involving forms might be implemented and set up.  I will consider her suggestion but my first reaction is negative.  From my experience, people get turned off by forms which tend willy-nilly to become more complex than is necessary.  The basis of the notification requirements is that they should be informal and that no particular form is required.  All that is required is the conveying of the essential and relevant information from one party to the other in any form and without any particular pattern of words being required or necessary.  Forms put people off and people regard a letter or memo as adequate once the message is conveyed. If forms are introduced the trend is that one has to use them.  Of course people do not have to use the form but they get the idea that they have to use them and then start panicking about where they can get them and fret if they cannot get one.  I take the Deputy's point and will consider it.</P>
    <P>Notifications are necessary.  One has to strike a balance between the position of the employee and that of the employer.  The employee is being given important rights under the legislation but employers also have rights.  We have to remember at all times that employers have to run a business and have to know who will be available when and how. They have to plan their business arrangements so as to keep their businesses going and make the profit on which that and all the other jobs depend at the end of the day.  One has to strike <Col N="1266" /> a fair balance between those two positions. We have tried to be fair in balancing the arrangements as between the employer and the employee.</P>
    <P>Senator Henry referred to the amendments she has tabled and these can be discussed in more detail on Committee Stage.</P>
    <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
    <P>Agreed to take remaining Stages today.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Maternity Protection Bill, 1994:" RHead="Committee and Remaining Stages">
    <Title>Maternity Protection Bill, 1994: Committee and Remaining Stages.</Title>
    <P>Sections 1 to 26, inclusive, agreed to.</P>
    <P Just="Center">SECTION 27.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MaryHenry" hpid="Dr. Henry Dr. Henry">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Henry</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 1:</P>
      <P>In page 17, subsection 2 (b), line 29, to delete &ldquo;substantially&rdquo;.</P>
      <P>Is it essential to include the word &ldquo;substantially&rdquo; in this section?  Would it make any great difference if it was deleted?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MervynTaylor" hpid="Minister for Equality and Law Reform (Mr. Taylor) Mervyn Taylor">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Equality and Law Reform (Mr. Taylor)</NameTxt>
      <P>Having carefully examined the matter, the word &ldquo;substantially&rdquo; is necessary.  The word &ldquo;substantially&rdquo; has already been in use in the Maternity Protection of Employees Act, 1981.  It has not given rise to any problems to date and neither of the social partners identified it as a difficulty during the consultations which took place on the preparation of the Bill.  The same text has already been accepted by this House in its recent consideration of the Adoptive Leave Bill.  The text as set out in the Bill achieves a useful balance in protecting the interests of the pregnant worker and in accommodating the exceptional circumstances in which the employer may find herself or himself.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Under section 27 (1) before an employer may consider providing suitable <Col N="1267" /> alternative work it must not be reasonably practicable to permit the employee to return to work on the basis of reinstatement.  If this issue is disputed the employer would have to satisfy a rights commissioner or the Employment Appeals Tribunal that it was not reasonably practicable to do so.  Reinstatement is the first option.</P>
    <P>The purpose of section 27 (2) is to preclude the employer from making an unacceptable dilution of an employee's right to return to work should the employer attempt to use the alternative given to him or her by the provision for re-engagement.  Towards that end section 27 (2) lays down certain conditions as regards the suitable alternative employment to be offered to the employee by her employer, the successor where there has been a change in ownership during her absence or an associated employer under her new contract of employment.  It stipulates that the work to be done must be of a kind which is both suitable for the employee concerned and appropriate for her to do in the circumstances.</P>
    <P>Furthermore, the terms and conditions concerning the place where the work is to be done and the capacity in which the employee is to be employed must not be substantially less favourable to her than those in the contract of employment she held before taking the leave concerned.  The retention of the word &ldquo;substantially&rdquo; allows existing practice to continue, allows some flexibility for the employer in accommodating the return to work of the employee and enables the employee to dispute the terms of the new contract where she considers that they are substantially less favourable to her.</P>
    <P>Acceptance of the Senator's proposed amendment would not only delay passage of the Bill, it would cause problems for small employers in particular.  If there are difficulties for such an employer in reinstating an employee <Col N="1268" /> after leave under this Bill, there may also be difficulties for the employer in not bringing in a new contract for suitable alternative work which is precisely the same or as favourable to her as the previous one.  It would be unfair and unreasonable to expect it to be precisely the same.  Protection against substantially less favourable terms is, on balance, a reasonable provision and one with which employers and workers have been able to live comfortably since 1981.</P>
    <Speaker pid="DickRoche" hpid="Mr. Roche Mr. Roche">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Roche</NameTxt>
      <P>I can see the problem the Minister has.  The word &ldquo;substantially&rdquo; appears in other legislation.  What is intended here is not markedly different. As the Minister pointed out a review process is inherent in all of this.  I accept there is anecdotal evidence of occasional abuse.  The use of the word &ldquo;substantially&rdquo; means the burden of proof lies with the aggrieved woman returning to the workplace.  Clearly that is not something the Minister or the House would intend.  This could be examined if we had a monitoring process. I am sure women in the trade union movement are conscious of this issue.</P>
      <P>The case to which Senator Henry referred triggered a memory of a woman who was given a parallel position but it was one which was going nowhere.  She was moved from a position where she had career prospects to one where she had none; in fact, her only option was to seek alternative employment, and that posed other problems for her.</P>
      <P>The Minister's intention here is not to create a loophole and certainly not to assist the unscrupulous employer but there is the opportunity to abuse the word.  Perhaps before the review we could look at it and take everybody's concerns on board.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MervynTaylor" hpid="Mr. Taylor Mr. Taylor">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Taylor</NameTxt>
      <P>We will certainly do that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryHenry" hpid="Dr. Henry Dr. Henry">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Henry</NameTxt>
      <P>I thank the Minister for his explanation.  As Senator Roche said <Col N="1269" /> people may be in a position where they cannot complain because the word &ldquo;substantially&rdquo; is already in the legislation. My constituent &mdash; and probably Senator Roche's constituent &mdash; tried to make her complaint through the various employment agencies but because there is no substantial difference in the position offered &mdash; she is in a totally different position but her prospects are nil &mdash; she got no satisfaction.</P>
      <P>When monitoring the legislation I ask the Minister to find out if this word is causing trouble for some people because they do not have grounds to complain as the word &ldquo;substantially&rdquo; is in the legislation.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MervynTaylor" hpid="Mr. Taylor Mr. Taylor">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Taylor</NameTxt>
      <P>I will be happy to keep it under review.  To date the unions have not raised that point.  It is a question of balance.  It is a little unreasonable to expect a small employer to provide the precise employment the employee had before she left.  I will keep the matter under review.</P>
      <P>Amendment, by leave, withdrawn.</P>
      <P>Section 27 agreed to.</P>
      <P>Sections 28 to 37, inclusive, agreed.</P>
      <P Just="Center">SECTION 38.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryHenry" hpid="Dr. Henry Dr. Henry">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Henry</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 2:</P>
      <P>In page 23, lines 43 to 47, to delete subsection (1) and substitute the following:</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>&ldquo;(1)  Where a pregnant woman within the meaning of section 1 of the Act of 1977 (as amended by section 22), is dismissed from her employment, and such dismissal results wholly or mainly from the exercise or contemplated exercise by her of any of her rights under this Act, she shall, notwithstanding section 2 (1) (a) of the Act of 1977, be deemed to have been unfairly dismissed unless there are substantial grounds justifying the dismissal <Col N="1270" /> within the meaning of the Act of 1977 and shall be entitled to claim redress under that Act, notwithstanding the fact that she may have less than one year's continuous service with the employer who dismissed her&rdquo;.</P>
    <P>Not being a lawyer I have examined the two parts of this section together and wonder whether section 38 (1), which removes the words &ldquo;and whose&rdquo; from section 2 (1) (a) of the 1977 Act, means that the woman has to be in employment for one year.  I will be guided by the Minister who is a lawyer.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MervynTaylor" hpid="Mr. Taylor Mr. Taylor">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Taylor</NameTxt>
      <P>I can understand Senator Henry's comment about the complexity of this section.  I have a detailed legalistic complex reply which I will be happy to read into the record if required. However, I doubt if, without a concentrated study, it would add much to the debate.  Suffice it to say that I am satisfied that the intent of Senator Henry's amendment is well stitched into section 38.  Ironically, the effect of taking her amendment on board would make the position worse in some circumstances. The 12 month period does not apply and the position is covered in section 38 (5) where the appropriate sections of the Unfair Dismissals Act, 1977, are dealt with.  The matter is in order and taken care of; what the Senator wants to achieve is provided for.  If she wants the full legalistic basis of it I will be happy to give it but I think it is not necessary.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryHenry" hpid="Dr. Henry Dr. Henry">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Henry</NameTxt>
      <P>The subsection reminded me a little of Sir Humphry in &ldquo;Yes Minister&rdquo; when I was going from paragraph (f) to (g) and so on.  I will be guided by the Minister and do not need the long legalistic reply which would detain us even longer this evening.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MervynTaylor" hpid="Mr. Taylor Mr. Taylor">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Taylor</NameTxt>
      <P>I will be happy to give the Senator a copy of the reply which she can study at her leisure.</P>
      <P>Amendment, by leave, withdrawn.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="1271" /> Section 38 agreed.</P>
    <P>Sections 39 to 41, inclusive, agreed.</P>
    <P>Title agreed to.</P>
    <P>Bill reported without amendment and received for final consideration.</P>
    <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That the Bill do now pass.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="MervynTaylor" hpid="Minister for Equality and Law Reform (Mr. Taylor) Mervyn Taylor">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Equality and Law Reform (Mr. Taylor)</NameTxt>
      <P>I thank the Senators who made such valuable contributions to this important Bill.  It will be monitored in accordance with the directive within the appropriate period. I assure Senators that whatever amendment may be necessary following on that review, will be undertaken at the appropriate time.</P>
      <P>I thank you, Sir, and the staff of the Department who worked so diligently in the preparation of the detail of this Bill. They still have some work to do in regard to the finalisation of the regulations in connection with the social welfare and the health and safety aspects. It is my intention to have those completed so that the Bill can be brought into operation as quickly as possible.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I join with other speakers in congratulating the Minister on his re-appointment.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>When is it proposed to sit again?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LiamTCosgrave" hpid="Mr. Cosgrave Mr. Cosgrave">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cosgrave</NameTxt>
      <P>I propose that we adjourn <i>sine die.</i></P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Adjournment Matter. -" RHead="Army Equitation School">
    <Title>Adjournment Matter. - Army Equitation School.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Before I call Senator Henry I extend my congratulations to the Minister, Deputy <Col N="1272" /> Barrett, on his first appearance as a Minister in the House.  I welcome him and wish him good luck in his new appointment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryHenry" hpid="Dr. Henry Dr. Henry">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Henry</NameTxt>
      <P>I should like to share my time with Senator Liam Cosgrave who also has an interest in horses.</P>
      <P>I welcome Deputy Barrett to the House and congratulate him on his new appointment.  I am glad to say he too has an interest in horses.</P>
      <P>It is often dangerous to speak about reports which have not been made public. However, I was so alarmed by some of the leaks from the Price Waterhouse efficiency audit on the Defence Forces that I felt there was one question in particular I wanted to take up.  It relates to the Army Equitation School which it appeared would be left as it was, privatised or got rid of altogether.  As some of these topics may be under consideration at the moment and there might not be another opportunity to bring this up before the budget, I decided to ask for this Adjournment Debate.</P>
      <P>The Army Equitation School was set up in 1926 to advertise the Irish horse through international competition and it has done this extraordinarily ably over many years on a very small budget. Even today the budget for the Army Equitation School is only something over £300,000 a year; yet it is incredibly successful.  This year Captain Gerry Mullins won the Grand Prix at Hickstead, one of the premier shows in England, riding Pallasgreen and Captain John Ledingham won the Hickstead Derby on Kilbaha.  Both of these horses were Irish.  In France in La Boule, another very big event, Kilbaha was the leading horse, again ridden by Captain Ledingham and the Irish team won the Nations Cup at the La Boule meeting.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Kilbaha is owned by all of us, but some showjumpers of international quality command such an appallingly high price nowadays that it is impossible for the school to buy them.  Again it has shown great initiative by leasing young Irish horses which look as if they have a <Col N="1273" /> promising future.  One such example is Millstreet Ruby which won the National Championship of Showjumping in Ireland this year partnered by Captain Mullins.  The school has great judgment regarding horses and a very high standard of training.</P>
    <P>The school is considered extremely successful internationally and its visits to events abroad are highly prized. Recently it was asked to go to Mexico and the fares for everyone involved were paid.  However, it may have made a mistake by being too successful.  It won so much money at the event that it had to pay back the fares to the organisers. Even after that it came home with money in the kitty.  It shows that it is running an extraordinarily professional outfit.</P>
    <P>Another initiative it has taken recently is to become involved in three day eventing.  This is extremely important because it is a rapidly expanding area.  The sport horse and leisure activity, especially three day eventing, is big business now.  Lieutenant Gerry Flynn in particular has done very well with several horses in important world class events.  In fact, the school competed very respectably in the World Equestrian Games in The Hague this year and the teams have been so newly set up they deserve encouragement.</P>
    <P>In 1991 the Minister for Agriculture at the time, when announcing details of grants for sport horses and stressing the importance of this to the country, committed the Government to supporting the Army Equitation School as a means of maximising the potential of the sport horse.  The precise value to our economy of non-thoroughbred horses is difficult to quantify but it is probably somewhere between £15 million and £30 million.  Thousands of people are involved in the production of the sport horse and it is not only their economic importance that should be stressed but their social importance, especially in rural Ireland.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="1274" /> Our horses come up against stiff competition. Although we sell them abroad our efforts at breeding have not been quite as good as those of other countries and we have been rapidly overtaken by Germany, France and the Netherlands. We have been slow to monitor the breeding of non-thoroughbred horses.  I was previously critical about the fact that grants are given to mares for breeding purposes without any inspection. That is serious because hereditary diseases could be passed on.  Even the quality of stallions in the showjumping area is not assessed but is judged on conformation.  It might be a good idea if, as in other countries, stallions had to show-jump for a few seasons so that we could see what sort of prowess they make.  My reason for bringing that up in regard to the Army Equitation School is that we have very fine civilian riders.  I have no worry about what sort of team we can produce for international events. Between civilians and Army we have superb riders.  However, because of a court case taken some years ago, it was decided that to ride on an Irish team Irish riders did not have to ride Irish horses.  This is serious because the Army Equitation School is making sure that the horses they ride are Irish horses. The fact that other countries are coming up so fast behind us and overtaking us in the field of breeding makes it essential that we have a showplace for the Irish horses.  The record of the Army Equitation School speaks for itself and we could hardly have a more economic unit.  It is important to remember that all the people working there are serving soldiers so we are getting good value for money.  Sometimes these soldiers are away in the Lebanon when they are not riding the horses.</P>
    <P>Finally, the school makes good use of the horses even when they are retired. We cannot bring back the Blue Huzzars who used to go forth with the Viceroy &mdash; it is a pity but it would be far too expensive to get a troop like that going <Col N="1275" /> again.  It is unfortunate that when the President comes out on ceremonial occasions it is with a group on Japanese motorbikes but we will have to put up with them for the moment.  However, I was glad to see the initiative of the Army Equitation School at the Horse Show which is our major showcase.  This year when the President came she arrived in a horse-drawn carriage.  The last time that happened was when President O'Kelly did so.  Sadly, the ponies ran away and Mr. de Valera, who was Taoiseach at the time, forbade them to use the ponies any more.  Our President is out again in a horse-drawn carriage and the Army Equitation School provided a small escort of retired recycled showjumping horses.  We are getting extraordinarily good value out of this school which has great prominence on the international scene.  I am most hopeful that the Minister will be able to tell me that the rumours I have heard about any diminution of it are wrong.</P>
    <Speaker pid="LiamTCosgrave" hpid="Mr. Cosgrave Mr. Cosgrave">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cosgrave</NameTxt>
      <P>I want to thank Senator Henry for allowing me a few of her precious minutes.  I also welcome my good friend and colleague, Deputy Barrett, the first Fine Gael Minister to appear in the Seanad since the change of Government.</P>
      <P>I support everything that Senator Henry said.  We are all aware of the great service to the country of the Army Equitation School but, unfortunately, in recent years it has been gradually run down.  If this were to continue it would spell the end of the Army showjumping team as we know it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>In a reply given as recently as 16 November in the Dáil we were told that the number of staff in the Army Equitation School has been reduced from 65 in 1990 to 50 at the end of September this year.  Obviously this trend must be halted and I hope the Minister will give a commitment to reverse it.  In 1990 the school bought three horses and in each <Col N="1276" /> of the years 1991, 1992 and 1993 it bought four.  I understand that one horse will be bought this year and another leased, but I am sure Senator Henry and others will agree that we must think of the future.  It is difficult for the Army Equitation School to buy a &ldquo;ready-made&rdquo; horse, it must revamp its stock and train young horses.</P>
    <P>I am disappointed to note that in real terms funding for the school has remained static.  While the horse industry employs a large number of people, the allocation for 1990 was £320,000, for the following three years it was £325,000 and in 1994 it was £334,000.  One of the advantages of the show jumping scene is that people like the Minister of State, Deputy Barrett, and I do not get an opportunity to lose money.  I hope the Minister of State will consider this matter with a view to ensuring that when matters arise in the forthcoming weeks the equitation school will still exist.  We are all aware of the credit brought to this country down the years by the Army Equitation School and by people such as Commandant Gerry Mullins, John Ledingham, Bill Ringrose and Ned Campion.  We like to see at least one Army officer on the Irish team competing for the Agha Khan Cup.</P>
    <P>I appeal to the Minister to try to reverse the decline in staff numbers at the school and to consider allocating money for the purchase of horses.  It is all very fine to lease horses, but if they are purchased it alleviates the danger of a big offer being made from abroad. There is no doubt that Germans and others have more money to spend than we have.</P>
    <P>I thank Senator Henry for allowing me a few minutes of her time and I hope the Minister responds positively.</P>
    <Speaker pid="SeanBarrett" hpid="Minister of State at the Department of Defence (Mr. Barrett) Minister of State at the Department of Defence (Mr. Barrett)">
      <NameTxt>Minister of State at the Department of Defence (Mr. Barrett)</NameTxt>
      <P>I thank the Leas-Chathaoirleach for the warm welcome and I am very pleased to be here. It is a few years since we had the opportunity <Col N="1277" /> of being in this position.  I thank Senators Henry and Cosgrave for raising this issue and for showing a great deal of interest in the area of show jumping.  I am told that my late father-in-law was a member of the Irish show jumping team for many years.  As show jumping is of great interest to my wife's family, I have a particular interest in it.</P>
      <P>Much of the recent discussion about the future of the Defence Forces has been negative in tone.  I would assure the House that this Government is committed to the development of the Defence Forces and to ensuring that they are properly organised and equipped to meet the important roles assigned to them.</P>
      <P>There has been a considerable amount of speculation about the deliberations of the efficiency audit group and its findings.  In fact, the EAG has not yet submitted its report to the Department of the Taoiseach and when it does it will be examined in consultation with the interests involved.</P>
      <P>The current review of the Defence Forces did not arise as a bolt from the blue.  For some years there has been wide agreement about the need for reform and reorganisation generally.  As regards the equitation school, the short answer to the question raised by Senators Henry and Cosgrave is that there has been no change in the status of the school and it would be premature to enter into speculation in that regard.</P>
      <P>As pointed out by Senator Henry, the mission of the equitation school, as assigned to it on its establishment in 1926, is to advertise the Irish non-thoroughbred horse.  The school has consistently provided horses and riders of the highest quality for Irish international show jumping teams and, allowing for the contribution of individual civilian riders, the Army riders have in many respects formed the backbone of international teams over many years. At present there are 46 horses, six of which are of international standard.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="1278" /> The Army Equitation School has had a very successful year.  In 1993, Army riders competed in 16 international shows winning £52,222.  This year, riders from the Army Equitation School competed in 24 international shows, winning more than £147,000.  Army riders were part of the Irish Team on five occasions in 1993 and on eight occasions in 1994. The Army Equitation School also participated in 36 national shows in 1993, winning £5,031 in prize money.  In 1994 to date they have participated in 33 shows winning £12,514.</P>
    <P>The equitation school has always been a source of pride to the Department of Defence, the Defence Forces and to the Irish people.  I take this opportunity to congratulate everyone associated with the school on their recent achievements in international shows, particularly the victory in the Hickstead Derby.  This is a clear indication of the ability of the equitation school to compete successfully at the highest level both at home and abroad. It is a great sense of pride to every Irish person to see the uniform of the Defence Forces worn by an Irish rider at international events in various parts of the world and I speak for every Member of the House when I say I feel very proud that they represent Ireland abroad in an excellent fashion.</P>
    <P>Recent speculation has created a false impression regarding the likely outcome of the EAG review.  There has been ill-informed speculation about the future of various elements of the Defence Forces, including the equitation school.  The review process is still under way and no decisions have been taken regarding changes in the equitation school, or any other unit of the Defence Forces.</P>
    <P>The many positive features in the Army, Air Corps and Naval Service are generally recognised and provide a solid platform on which to build for the future.  Wherever military personnel serve, they apply themselves to the task in hand with commitment and professionalism. <Col N="1279" /> The introduction of a balanced programme of reform will prove a positive experience for the Defence Forces and will be formulated in consultation with the various interests involved.</P>
    <P>I will endeavour to meet the wishes of Senator Henry and Cosgrave in ensuring that the equitation school gets its fair share of the spoils.  We are conscious of the numbers in the school and, in order to compete and represent our country properly, Senators Cosgrave and Henry are correct in saying that the quality of the horse as well as the rider is important.  We spend a great deal of money advertising Ireland but the medium of an Irish horse with a member <Col N="1280" /> of the Defence Forces riding it is an exceptional way of doing so.  I am very conscious of that and will do all I can to ensure it continues.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MaryHenry" hpid="Dr. Henry Dr. Henry">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Henry</NameTxt>
      <P>I thank the Minister of State for his reassuring reply and I am sure Senator Cosgrave and I will have a much more comfortable Christmas as a result.  The next time the Minister of State visits McKee Barracks there will be a big cheer to welcome him.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I wish all Members of the House and the staff a very happy Christmas and prosperous New Year.</P>
      <P>The Seanad adjourned at 6.30 p.m. <i>sine die.</i></P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
</Debate>