<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE Debate SYSTEM "../Debate.dtd"[]>
<Debate DocTitle="Seanad Debate" Day="Fri" Date="24" Month="Jul" Year="1942" Vol="26" No="23" DateIrish="Dé hAoine, 24 Iúil 1942" DateEnglish="Friday, 24 July 1942" House="S" CommitteeEng="" CommitteeIr="" SubNameEng="" cnum="2017">
  <MainHeading Type="Prelude" LHead="" RHead="">
    <Title>
    </Title>
    <P>
      <Col N="2017" /> Do chuaidh an Cathaoirleach i gceannas ar 10.30 a.m.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Order of" RHead="Business">
    <Title>Order of Business.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFGibbons" hpid="Cathaoirleach Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Before calling the Order Paper, I wish to inform the House that the Taoiseach has intimated that, owing to unforeseen developments since last night, he will be unable to be present until 11.30 this morning.  If the Seanad is agreeable to take Senator Crosbie's motion now, the debate can be interrupted at 11.30 to resume the Committee Stage of the Emergency Powers (Continuance and Amendment) Bill.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Mr. M. Hayes Mr. M. Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Mr. M. Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>I see no objection to that course but I think we can say that in this House on all sides we have proved very accommodating with regard to the convenience of Ministers. It is quite clear that the Taoiseach was not able to come here on Wednesday and he was not able to come here on Thursday until 6 o'clock.  When the Taoiseach came here on Thursday he suggested that we might give him all Stages of the Bill by 9 o'clock, a most unreasonable frame of mind for him to adopt.  We adjourned last night at 9 o'clock, the Taoiseach agreeing to come here at 10.30 this morning.  Now we find that he cannot come.  That is an extraordinary commentary on the whole situation and on the capacity of Ministers, none of whom, apparently, is able to take the Committee Stage of the Bill except the Taoiseach.  I think it shows a great disrespect for Parliament and a complete muddling of Parliamentary arrangements.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamQuirke" hpid="Mr. Quirke Mr. Quirke">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Quirke</NameTxt>
      <P>I think it is only right that it should be explained that the Taoiseach came here with an open mind.  After discussion with the various Parties here, it was decided that the <Col N="2018" /> debate should go on and, if possible, that all Stages of the Bill would be given last night.  The Taoiseach was told so and therefore thought that all Stages of the Bill would be given last night and that the debate would be finished.  Unless I made a great mistake, it was the desire of almost all Senators on the Opposition Benches to get the Bill finished last night.  That was quite obvious at the conclusion of the debate.  The Taoiseach is, perhaps, more tied up than any ordinary member of the Seanad and I do not think it fair at all to suggest that his attitude was anything other than the normal attitude of any man in his position.  I think it is quite unreasonable for Senator Hayes to take the line he has taken.  I am quite sure the majority of members of the House would be quite agreeable to accommodate the Taoiseach.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Mr. M. Hayes Mr. M. Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Mr. M. Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>I am quite willing to accommodate the Taoiseach too. Everybody, as Senator Quirke has stated, was anxious to get the Bill finished last night, but we did not get it finished.  Quite obviously, the Taoiseach wanted to get it finished and did not want to come here at all to-day.  He agreed, however, to come here at 10.30 to-day.  He has not been able to come owing to unforeseen circumstances, whatever they may be.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamQuirke" hpid="Mr. Quirke Mr. Quirke">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Quirke</NameTxt>
      <P>It was quite obvious that other people were more anxious to get the Bill finished last night by 9 o'clock, because anybody who knows the Taoiseach is aware that he is quite prepared to work 23 hours out of the 24 if necessary.  If other people adopted that attitude we should get a lot more work done.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFGibbons" hpid="Cathaoirleach Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Having heard these statements, I suggest that we should now proceed with the debate on Senator Crosbie's motion until 11.30 a.m.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Pigs and Bacon" RHead="Commission&mdash;Motion">
    <Title>Pigs and Bacon Commission&mdash;Motion.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="JamesCrosbie" hpid="Mr. Crosbie Mr. Crosbie">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Crosbie</NameTxt>
      <P>I move:&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>That in view of the reduction in the pig population, the Seanad is of opinion that the operations of the <Col N="2019" /> Pigs and Bacon Commission should be suspended during the period of the emergency.</P>
    <P>In proposing this motion, I should like to assure the House and the Minister that in tabling the motion I was fully alive to the difficulties and pitfalls that beset the Minister and the Pigs and Bacon Commission in their endeavours to keep the pig and bacon industry alive at the present moment.  I assure you, Sir, that this motion is not intended to be an attack on the principle of the Pigs and Bacon Commission, nor is it intended to be an attack on any of the personnel of that commission, nor an attack on the Minister, because I feel that the position which has arisen in the pigs and bacon industry cannot, in present circumstances, be laid at the door of either the Minister or the commission.  However, I do feel that, while the temporary suspension of the functions of the Pigs and Bacon Commission may not by any means solve the problem which faces the Minister, it may be a helpful step.  When, in 1935, this commission was set up, and implemented by a series of further Acts right up to 1940, the present circumstances&mdash; certainly as far back as 1935&mdash;could not have been foreseen, and I do feel that the terms of the commission and their regulations are too hide-bound; they are not sufficiently elastic to cope with those very desperate emergency conditions which exist at the present time. It is obviously quite clear that, no matter how we do it, we must find some means of keeping the pigs and bacon industry alive for the duration of the emergency.  To say that we could keep it in a prosperous condition may be hoping for too much, but certainly, by combining our suggestions, we ought to be able to find some means by which this industry would be kept during the emergency on at least the same basis as a lot of our other industries, which, while they are not prospering, are at any rate managing to keep their heads above water, and, all going well, will be still in existence when the emergency ends.</P>
    <P>This question is a national one, and, as far as I am concerned, it is also a <Col N="2020" /> local one, because the county I come from was at one time the biggest pig-producing area in Ireland.  To demonstrate that, Sir, I may say that the Cork figures for killings in the year 1935 amounted to 4,000 per week. In 1939 they had dropped to about 2,000 per week, and recently, just before those prosecutions, they had dropped to 300 per week.  As the Minister and the House are aware, some of those Cork factories are about to close down, and I, for one, can only view such a step with the very gravest concern.  I will deal only with one factory&mdash;there are others involved&mdash; and I propose to read some extracts from a letter from Messrs.  Lunham. Messrs. Lunham point out that their weekly quota of killings, the quota fixed by the commission, is 1,500, but owing to the stoppage of maize not more than 300 weekly have been handled by them for some time past. In February they were 53 per cent. short of their total quota, and they were 52 per cent. short in March. Owing to recent prosecutions, they secured only 48 pigs last week.  During that week, they spent in wages alone £331 8s. 1d., which works out at £7 per pig.  Their other expenditure, such as rent, rates, taxes, etc., will bring the amount to £800 or roughly £16 13s. per pig.  The present quota demands an average weekly killing of 450 pigs, and it will, therefore, be realised that if they are able to obtain only 50 to 100 pigs weekly it will be impossible to keep open.  I have no reason to believe that Messrs. Lunham are any exception to the rest of the Cork factories; I see by this morning's paper that the Cork Farmers' Union abattoir factory is also about to close.</P>
    <P>I have also here some notes from the Secretary to the Cork Pig Buyers' Association, which may be of interest to the Minister and to the House.  He says:</P>
    <P>&ldquo;For the past 14 or 15 months there was in County Cork a big body of pig breeders.  They were what was known in Dublin as &ldquo;speculative breeders&rdquo;, and for those months this trade had been on the increase, because the breeders <Col N="2021" /> found that they could sell their bonhams to people in the midlands and west of Ireland at fairly good prices. If the Pigs and Bacon Commission insists upon trying to get these pigs at fixed prices, they will put the people in the midlands and in the west out of pig production and pig rearing also.  The result will be that pig breeding in the south will go out because there will be no demand for the bonhams.  At present, we have the pigs and sows and the means of breeding, but this insistence by the commission will do away with a lot of them.  The manure value of pigs, according to findings in Denmark when manure was only £2 a ton, was that the manure available from a single pig was worth £4 per annum.  The present price of manure is much higher.  The country is short of 500,000 pigs of its normal supplies, with the consequent very great manurial loss.  This is a matter that should be taken into consideration if the increased tillage campaign is to be a success.  The ideal solution for the present crux would be the complete abolition of the Pigs and Bacon Act and the Pigs and Bacon Commission; failing this, a minimum price for pigs and a maximum price for bacon, and free trade for all concerned in between.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>I cannot find myself in agreement with the suggestion for the abolition of the Pigs and Bacon Act; otherwise, I think the remarks of the Secretary to the Cork Pig Buyers' Association are very enlightening.</P>
    <P>I do say, however, that this problem will not be solved entirely through the adoption by the Minister of the suggestion contained in the resolution in my name, because I agree with what the Minister said in this House yesterday that the problem of pigs and bacon production is of necessity primarily a question of food, but we cannot overlook the fact that price also has a great deal to do with the problem, and would at least help to alleviate the position both of the pig breeder and the curer.  Therefore, I make the suggestion that the Minister should, first of all, very carefully consider adopting the terms of this <Col N="2022" /> resolution, and suspending the operations of the commission for the period of the emergency.  By that, I do not mean that the Minister should cease to exercise any control over the industry. I would suggest that he might try to experiment, at least for a short period, on fixing a minimum price for pigs and a maximum for bacon, and see if that would help the situation.  It is the suggestion of the people in the trade, and their suggestions should not be lightly turned down.</P>
    <P>I would also suggest to the Minister that in addition it is essential, if the pig and bacon industry is to be kept alive, that future plans should be laid for the production of feeding stuffs. Pigs mean barley, and barley means pigs, and I cannot too strongly suggest to the Minister that, when he has secured the wheat position, if necessary by compulsory wheat growing, he should then take every step to make barley growing a paying proposition for the Irish farmer.  I think he would then cease to have the same amount of worry about the pigs and bacon industry.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickDoyle" hpid="Dr. Doyle Dr. Doyle">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Doyle</NameTxt>
      <P>I beg formally to second the motion.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesParkinson" hpid="Mr. Parkinson Mr. Parkinson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Parkinson</NameTxt>
      <P>I should like to support the proposal made by Senator Crosbie, because I think it is very essential that we should not lose our pigs and bacon trade.  Unfortunately, the big obstacle in the way of producing more pigs is the question of more food.  Next year will be our fourth year of intensive cultivation of the land because of the emergency.  Up to a point, our tillage land has had a sufficiency of potash in the soil to carry us through for the past few years, but, like a banking account on which cheques continue to be drawn, the land now lacks a sufficient supply of the essential manure to grow potatoes, which must, I assume, for the next few years be the main crop on which pigs will be fed.  The main essential to be put into the land in order to ensure a reasonably good crop is potash.  In a normal pre-war year our normal imports of potash fertilisers were the equivalent of 7,500 tons of K20, potassium oxide.  This, of course, is <Col N="2023" /> now completely cut off, and we are left in the position that we will have to provide potash from our own resources. That can be done if sufficient money is spent on the collection of the seaweed which is found on all our coasts, particularly on the western coast, where for years the people have been collecting seaweed to be burned into kelp, from which we obtain our supply of iodine.  We now have to take from that seaweed its potash content.  If we devote enough attention to the matter, and pay a decent price to the farmers and labourers who will collect that seaweed and burn it, I think we will be able to get enough potash to carry us on each year during this emergency. On a conservative estimate we would get 4,000 tons of potash in the way I have mentioned.</P>
      <P>Of course, if we could increase our cereal crops, we would then be in a position to allocate some portion of those crops for pig feeding, because potatoes by themselves are not the ideal food if we want to fatten the pigs quickly.  We can only increase our corn crops by the use of phosphatic manure.  County Clare is in the lucky position of having over a million tons of phosphate rock.  That rock lies between Doolin to the west, and southwest of that it reaches as far as Kilfenora, a distance of nine miles.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The seam of phosphate rock is three feet thick, and it is the same thickness at Kilfenora as at Doolin, so we assume that it does not vary in thickness between those two points.  In the last pre-war year we imported 60,000 tons of phosphatic rock, almost entirely from North Africa.  The phosphate in Clare is very hard rock, and very insoluble.  The insolubility is due mainly to the fact that it has 15 per cent. silica, one of the most insoluble of all metals.  Our difficulty up to the present has been that in order to make the Clare superphosphate soluble you have to use with it sulphuric acid.  The people who have tried to manufacture sulphuric acid from Irish barytes complain that it is not as nearly as feasible a proposition as to import sulphuric acid.  In England the whole supply of sulphuric <Col N="2024" /> acid is used for war purposes, and none is available for the making of superphosphates.  Luckily for us the Germans, who are in the same position as the English with regard to sulphuric acid, are now able to make their superphosphate without using any sulphuric acid.  They have discovered a method by which they can separate the phosphoric acid by adding a fifty-fifty proportion of silica, which combines very easily with the calcium and frees the phosphoric acid. Luckily for us we have in Clare a huge supply of colloidal clay, which is 98 per cent. pure silica.  To prepare the superphosphate the Germans now use simply the ordinary lime kilns.  Of course, they have in Germany good supplies of coal, but we have good supplies of turf, and in our western counties one often sees the lime kilns operating with turf.  We know that we can burn lime with anthracite coal and with anthracite-culm or anthracite slack.</P>
    <P>Another point of great interest to anybody who thinks of development along these lines is that our four sugar factories have the newest and latest type of lime-kilns, where they make lime from limestone to clean the sugar. These factories are idle for at least six months of the year.  They are all near to, or connected with, railways, so that the job of getting the rock from Clare and the colloidal clay from Cork is capable of solution.  It is alleged that there is a very inferior content of phosphate in the Irish rock. An analysis of the North African rock, which we had been importing, shows that it has 59 per cent. of phosphate. Parts of the Clare rock that have been analysed show 47 per cent. of phosphate. That is the lowest it shows and, in the higher grades found at Doolin, it shows exactly the same amount of phosphate as the North African rock shows-59 per cent.  The trouble is that there is 15 per cent. of silica in the Clare rock and there is none in the African rock.  Hence, the better solubility while it is in the raw state of the African rock as against the Clare rock.  The central European countries, as well as Germany, now get <Col N="2025" /> only superphosphate that is prepared by adding silica to the rock and burning it.  The phosphates in Germany have a lower percentage of phosphate than either the North African or Clare product, but Germany is not on a starvation diet yet.</P>
    <P>The last of the fertilisers I should like to talk about is the organic fertiliser, calcium cyanamide.  I do not want to speak about ammonium sulphate. We could make that if our gas works were operating, but there is so little coal coming in that these works are practically closed down. The making of calcium cyanamide is quite simple compared with some of the things we may have to do.  Calcium cyanamide is produced by direct addition of atmospheric nitrogen to hot calcium carbide.  Two factories have for years, in a small way, been turning out calcium carbide at Askeaton and Collooney, so that it is possible for us to do in a big way what is being done in a small way if the Government put up the money and set a staff of technicians at work.</P>
    <P>It may cost more than it used to cost to get the necessary materials in, but it is worth while to preserve the fertility of the land and keep our people from famine.  This would put us in a position to supply our cattle, pigs and other animals with food, so that money would be coming into the country in such volume that everybody would be able to get a job and people who had to go to England to look for work could come back and be employed in this business&mdash;the production of fertilisers to carry on the intensive cultivation of the land.  The raw materials required in production of carbide calcium are limestone, anthracite and electric power.  The subsequent transformation of calcium carbide into cyanamide is relatively simple.  Nothing has to be imported.  It has for years been successfully worked in countries such as Germany, Sweden and the U.S.A.  The machinery could easily be made here.  That is how Sweden is able to get her surplus crops and that is how Germany derived her main nitrate supplies in the last war, not only for the land, but for munitions. I hope that the Seanad will take this <Col N="2026" /> matter seriously.  Everything depends upon the production of grain, grass, cattle and pigs.  Otherwise, I do not see how we shall get out of the mess we are in at present.</P>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamCummins" hpid="Mr. Cummins Mr. Cummins">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cummins</NameTxt>
      <P>I should like to support this motion.  The decline of the pig population is alarming.  It is one of the most serious things which have happened throughout the whole emergency.  Cottiers who were accustomed to keeping pigs have now abandoned the raising of pigs, for the reason that they find it impossible to provide the food.  Following the abandonment of pig fattening will come a scarcity of manures.  Much of the manure available to small farmers and cottiers was the result of the keeping of pigs.  That want is felt already. Those who have taken allotments know that it is almost impossible to get farmyard manure for the reasons I have assigned.  When they do buy it, it is of a very inferior type and is sold at a high price.  Eight shillings and 10/- per load has been paid for it in the county from which I come.  It would take three or four loads of this manure to do one-eighth of an acre.</P>
      <P>Where allotments have been cultivated for three or four years, there is now a decline in the productiveness of the soil and the quality of the crops is beginning to show deterioration.  This makes it all the more necessary to maintain the pig population.  There is a scarcity of manure, owing especially to the increased tillage campaign. Manure has to be carted two or three miles at a cost of 8/- per load at the place from which it is taken.  A sum of 1/- or 2/- may have to be added for delivery, which puts it beyond the means of many people.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The suggestion which Senator Parkinson has made was put forward in this House even before the emergency. It was, however, passed over. One of the objections was that the rocks at Doolin, in County Clare, were so hard that they could not meet the demands of a big manure firm in Cork. Machinery could not be found to break up the rock into sufficiently small portions so as to permit of its being made soluble.  At that time the machinery <Col N="2027" /> could have been obtained to help in this process.  Merely partial help was necessary, as in the matter of digesting food.  The machinery could have been got at that time, but nothing was done about it.</P>
    <P>Senator Parkinson's statement is a remarkable one.  If the materials which heretofore came from Africa and Chile&mdash;and, I think, from Central Europe&mdash;are available here, instant use should be made of them.  I appreciate the difficulty in the matter of machinery and other ancillaries necessary to the production of phosphates, superphosphates and nitrogenous manures.  The Minister talked about ploughing the clover crop into the soil, but you must grow your clover first, and that cannot be done without some kind of manure.  If more fertilisers can be made available at present, it will increase the pig population and consequently increase the quantity of farmyard manure which would follow.  The continued use of fertilisers will impoverish the soil, if a reasonable quantity of farmyard manure is not used as well.</P>
    <P>Potatoes are used largely in the production of pigs in the early stages.  If barley and other pig mixtures are available, and if they can be produced at an economic price, I believe they would be equally as good as the Indian meal on which we depended formerly in great measure.  It would be optimistic to hope that phosphates and nitrogenous manures would be made available, but we have our own limestone, anthracite, turf and electric power, and while we have those in abundance, and as the machinery is simple, I suggest that the question of deposits of phosphates in County Clare should be taken up by the Government. I hope this will not be given the deaf ear, as was given to it some two or three years ago, when the matter was mentioned in this House, and nothing was done about it.</P>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMacEllin" hpid="Mr. McEllin Mr. McEllin">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McEllin</NameTxt>
      <P>In regard to the point expressed by Senator Cummins, in connection with the development of our own minerals, quite recently we passed legislation in this House to establish <Col N="2028" /> companies for the purpose of developing minerals.  As far as I know, work has been going on intensively for a considerable time.  We have succeeded to an extraordinary degree both in Clare and Cork in connection with the extraction of phosphates, and in the production of sulphuric acid in Wicklow.  According to what I hear from one of those directly concerned in the running of the business, the beginning is slow, but the prospects ahead are very good, and a considerable amount of phosphates should be available in 1943.  Whatever may be obtained in the future, the products obviously will be at an uneconomic price to the farmer, unless the State subsidises them.  The couple of years of intensive tillage we have had so far will not seriously affect the productive capacity of the soil, for a number of years, at any rate, except where there has been highly concentrated production in the past.  The soil will give sufficient food for the next couple of years, with the manures we have available at the moment, particularly farmyard manure.  If the farmer would apply the average amount of farmyard manure he has to tillage alone, instead of applying it to meadow lands and things like that, as at present, it would go a long way towards maintaining his usual average of crops.  Of course, that does not apply to the big farmer, who may have Ford tractors and a couple of hundred acres of wheat.</P>
      <P>There was nothing that Senator Crosbie said in his argument which would justify the moving of this motion at all.  As a matter of fact, everything in his argument would justify the continuance of the Pigs Commission and a more rigid control of the bacon business. There should be a minimum price for pigs and a maximum price for bacon.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesCrosbie" hpid="Mr. Crosbie Mr. Crosbie">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Crosbie</NameTxt>
      <P>That is what I suggested.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMacEllin" hpid="Mr. McEllin Mr. McEllin">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McEllin</NameTxt>
      <P>That is exactly what the commission tried to do.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesCrosbie" hpid="Mr. Crosbie Mr. Crosbie">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Crosbie</NameTxt>
      <P>No, they are working between two maximum prices now.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="2029" />
    <Speaker pid="SeanMacEllin" hpid="Mr. McEllin Mr. McEllin">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McEllin</NameTxt>
      <P>In any case, they are trying to maintain the balance between the consumer and the producer. Minor matters of detail are another question.  I agree with Senator Crosbie that there should be a minimum price for pigs and a maximum price for bacon.  I would go further and say that it would be right and proper for them to fix the maximum price for bacon on the basis of the most efficiently working bacon factory. When you argue the merits of costs in running an industry, you can work round costs to a most extraordinary degree, and you can prove that the best bacon in one case might cost half what it would in another.  As in the case of every other job, the cheapest will survive.  When the price of an article is fixed, the margin should be cut to the bone, under the present circumstances.</P>
      <P>The main difficulty comes from the shortage of one particular commodity, and that is food for human use.  It is the shortage of the loaf that is reacting back along the whole line and will continue to react while that shortage is there.  I am sure Senators will agree with me when I say that one would much prefer to be short of bacon or a plate of porridge than to be short of a loaf of bread.  It seems to have turned out to be the primary, staple food of the people.</P>
      <P>So long as that is so, you are going to have a shortage of other things, and the Government, in their desire to ensure that the staple food of the people would be supplied, had to make it more profitable to the farmer to supply their wheat to the miller than to do anything else with it, which is only common sense.  The result, however, was that its price has been considerably increased until, to-day, it is three or four times what it was pre-war, and the idea was to discourage the farmer from using the wheat for any other purpose than human food. The principle of the whole thing, at the moment, is based on the necessity to encourage the farmers to give the wheat to the millers, rather than to use it for animal feeding or do anything else with it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>If we had an increase in wheat growing, <Col N="2030" /> sufficient to give us 100 per cent. of our bread and flour supplies, the other things would automatically follow, and if you had more than 100 per cent., you would have the pollard and bran coming back off the flour and, after that, you would have the development of other cereals, such as oats and barley.  I agree with Senator Crosbie that an encouraging price ought to be given to the farmers to induce them to produce more barley, after we have secured our supplies of wheat, but if the cash price that you would give to the farmer for his barley would make him more inclined to give the barley to Messrs. Guinness than to supply it to his pigs, then Senator Crosbie's object would be defeated. All these things are related to one another, and there has to be a coordination of costs and prices from the farmer's point of view.  First of all, you have to look at the matter from the point of view of what is most suitable for the farmer and what will be best calculated to encourage him to do what the State wants him to do, and that is to put the wheat in the millers' hands and the barley into the pigs, and so on, and co-ordinate the prices and costs.</P>
    <P>Then you will get what we all want to see, and I think the Government has made a very good start in that direction. As far as I know, I think that that is the principle they have been working on, in raising the price of wheat and reducing the price of pigs, so as to ensure that the millers will get all the wheat that is available in the country; and a further development along these lines, in correlating the prices of the different articles with one another, should enable us to arrive at a policy of self-sufficiency in relation to our whole agricultural output.</P>
    <P>I suppose Senator Crosbie is not pushing his motion to a division, but it certainly has produced a very useful discussion.  Personally, I do not think it would be right to upset the Pigs and Bacon Commission now.  After all their work, they must by now have had a considerable amount of experience, and their advice, as a result of the work they have done, will be helpful, undoubtedly, in the future. <Col N="2031" /> Generally speaking, I have no very definite views on the matter, but I am perfectly satisfied in any case that the land will continue, and is capable of continuing for the next year or two at any rate, to maintain its fertility.  A number of people, when they argue about the question of fertility and the question of crops and the shortage of manure, always forget that the elements&mdash;the sun and the rain and so on &mdash;often times have considerably more effect than the amount of manure put on the land.  Rain, coming at the right time, or the heat of the sun coming on grain at the right time, at harvest time, and so on, always influences the value of the crop return from the soil&mdash;by 25 per cent. very often&mdash;and it is very questionable if the bit of phosphate that we could get from North Africa would have the same effect.  All these things are inter-related and, personally, I do not think it is necessary for Senator Crosbie to push his motion to a division, but as I have said, I am glad to see that the motion has produced a very useful discussion.</P>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. Johnston Mr. Johnston">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Johnston</NameTxt>
      <P>Coming from a county which has been noted for pig production for as long as I remember, I want to raise a few points in connection with that matter, and I hope to address myself to the actual terms of the motion, because I think that some of the other speakers were dealing with minerals and several other questions&mdash; very informative and useful, I am sure, but I do not think they have much relationship to the present motion, to suspend the operations of the Pigs and Bacon Commission during the emergency. I want to point out to the Minister at the outset that before the Pigs and Bacon Bill was introduced and became an Act, I submitted, in another place, very strong arguments to the Minister on behalf of the pig producers in County Monaghan.  Now, the position, as we found it at that time&mdash;that may not have any relation to the present position, but I think it is leading up to it, and I am putting this forward lest we get back to that position again&mdash;was that there were pork markets in County Monaghan, and the pigs were brought dead to the <Col N="2032" /> market.  They could not be taken home again and kept for a week or two, as somebody suggested in another connection, when there was not a good price.</P>
      <P>The result was that the pig producers were left at the mercy of the pork buyers.  Whenever there was a big pork market, the buyers met and consulted among themselves and came to an arrangement as to what they would give for the pork, and very often the price was 4/- and 5/-, and sometimes even 10/-, under the prices prevailing at the time.  There were four of these markets&mdash;two in Castleblayney and Carrickmacross, and two in Ballybay and Monaghan.  Two of these markets were held on one day, and two on another day, and it has happened in a few cases that where the markets were held on the same day, and even though there was a distance of only 10 or 12 miles between them, there would be a difference of 10/- and 12/- a cwt. in the prices paid by the pork buyers, by reason of the fact that there was a glutted market in one town and a small market in the other.  Now, we had to get over that difficulty, and I impressed it on the Minister on a couple of occasions, in another place, and later on, when the Act was passed, the Pigs and Bacon Commission was set up as a governing body to deal with the price of pigs and bacon.  It has worked fairly successfully in some cases and not in others, but I fear very much that, as a result of the insecurity with regard to prices that exists at the present time, the work of that commission, as it is being carried on at present, is driving some people out of pig production.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Now, as I said at the outset, I come from a county that is noted for pig production, and what I have been met with in County Monaghan, when discussing the question of pig production, the feeding of pigs, and so forth, is the question: &ldquo;Where is the use in feeding pigs and buying bonhams at a very high price, in view of the scarcity and high cost of fuel and feeding stuffs at the present time, when, after we have got the pigs ready for sale, we do not know whether we will be able to get them marketed in reasonable <Col N="2033" /> time or not?&rdquo;  There is one drawback here, which I intended to mention on former occasions, but I suppose it is better late than never.  Let us take the position that a farmer has three or four or half a dozen pigs almost ready for market.  Under the quota system, the curing companies can take only a certain number of pigs monthly.  If there is a good supply of pigs in the county the quota may be filled within the first couple of weeks.  After that, a farmer who has pigs cannot get them taken at the factory, and has to keep them over until the following month.  At that time they are possibly over weight to bring the highest price prevailing.  He loses on them on that head, and, in addition, he has lost the cost of feeding them, so that in some cases he may lose as much as 10/- per cwt. on the pigs.  I have known neighbours of my own go to Monaghan and almost beg the curing companies to take pigs from them.  They have asked me to appeal for them.  That has not happened so much recently.  It is, however, one of the things that has tended to put farmers out of production.</P>
    <P>Under the Pigs and Bacon Commission this kind of thing used to happen. It has not happened in recent times. They would announce in the newspapers that they were taking pigs at, say, Monaghan on a Tuesday.  The farmers living between Monaghan and Castleblayney attended at Monaghan with the pigs, which were accepted there, and then sent to Cavan.  On the following day the Castleblayney pigs were taken in at Castleblayney and railed to Monaghan.  Would it not have been far better to have taken the Monaghan pigs in Monaghan, and have sent the Castleblayney pigs to Cavan? If that is not happening at the present time, there is something which is much worse so far as the farmers are concerned, and that is that prices are not stabilised.  There is no security with regard to prices.  The farmers in the County Monaghan are quite prepared to feed pigs, not possibly to the same extent as some years ago.  The small farmers in the county would be quite prepared to do that if there was any security as regards prices.  That point <Col N="2034" /> was advocated when the Pigs and Bacon Act was going through the Oireachtas.  It was urged that farmers who bought or reared bonhams to feed them and make bacon pigs out of them should know the price they would get for them when they were ready for the market.  That may not be possible.  I agree that if, a fortnight in advance, it was announced that there was to be a reduction in prices, farmers would rush out their pigs, and that if there was to be an increase, farmers would hold on to their pigs in order to get it. I think it is not outside the scope or power of the commission to fix prices for, say, a period of two months.  The price of cereals is fixed, and why not fix, three months in advance, the price to be paid for bacon pigs?  I move the adjournment of the debate.</P>
    <P>Debate adjourned, to be resumed later to-day.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Emergency Powers (Continuance and Amendment) Bill" RHead="1942&mdash;Committee (resumed) and Final Stages">
    <Title>Emergency Powers (Continuance and Amendment) Bill 1942&mdash;Committee (resumed) and Final Stages.</Title>
    <P>Question again proposed: &ldquo;That Section 8 stand part of the Bill.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="ProfWilliamMagennis" hpid="Professor Magennis Professor Magennis">
      <NameTxt>Professor Magennis</NameTxt>
      <P>I think I owe an apology to the Chair, to the Taoiseach and to the House.  Last evening I objected to the discussion on this Bill being continued.  I had abandoned all hope of the Bill being concluded before a very late hour.  I thought, until I heard further this morning, that it would be a service to all concerned to postpone further consideration of it until to-day.  I now learn that that has interfered with other plans of the Taoiseach, and I apologise.  It might have been possible to conclude all stages of the Bill last night were it not for the fact that a great deal of time was spent unnecessarily during the discussion.  We had, for instance, the criticisms that were made by Senator Fitzgerald.  Listening to him I recalled a remark that the Minister for Education made earlier in his plea for defeating the anglicisation of the people by intensifying devotion to the use of the Irish language as the spoken language.  I am afraid that the Minister for <Col N="2035" /> Education is not as much alive as we in this House are to how deeply anglicised some of our members have become. The criticisms that were made here by the Senator in question were dictated by recollection of the constitutional practice in Great Britain under which we grew up.  Senator Mrs. Concannon made a very effective, vigorous and brief reply to him on one point.  When he said that &ldquo;the Government was taking these powers,&rdquo; she very aply retorted that the Government was asking for these powers, and that it was for the House to give them.</P>
      <P>Now, because the Senator referred to and many others for that matter outside the House think of constitutional practice and ways in the light of the English unwritten Constitution, they have a wholly wrong conception of many of the things that are done here.  In Great Britain legislative sovereignty resides in the Parliament but political sovereignty is in the people.  Hence the type of democracy of which Great Britain is the representative is Parliamentary Government. Britain is a Parliamentary democracy.  Ours is not.  It is a pity that our people do not study the Constitution with more attention.  The type of democracy which we have set up is a constitutional democracy; it is not as in Britain Parliamentary Government.  There is an Article of the Constitution&mdash;unfortunately I cannot quote it by number&mdash;in which &ldquo;The Government&rdquo; is defined.  We speak frequently of Government without adverting to the difference between Government and &ldquo;The Government&rdquo;. Under the Constitution, &ldquo;The Government&rdquo; is the Executive Council, and Government has a wholly different reference.  It would not, therefore, be correct to say, for example, that we who are members of the Houses of the Legislature form part of &ldquo;The Government&rdquo; of the country, for there is that express declaration in an Article of the Constitution that &ldquo;The Government&rdquo; of the country is the Executive Council.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The particular type of fundamental law that our people choose to enact <Col N="2036" /> is the Constitution.  It is an act of the people.  You will see that it is impossible for this House or both Houses to give to the Government the powers which it is alleged the Government are taking, that is powers to subordinate the judiciary or usurp the functions of the judiciary.  Even if we purported to give them such power, there are two Articles of the Constitution which declare that this will be null and void. Any Act that is passed or purports to be passed in the Houses of the Parliament of the State is null and void in respect of any section which conflicts with what is set down in the Constitution.  So that, even though in blind haste or panic we were stampeded in the Houses of the Legislature into passing something which subtracts from the independence of the judges, such legislation would be wholly inoperative.  Therefore we are saved by the fact of our Constitution being written from any such result as that.  I am as strong as Senator Hayes on the upholding of the independence of the judiciary.  We have ceased to have democratic liberty if we have not unfettered courts of law and judges to defend the rights and liberties of the individual, and any encroachment of the Executive on the judiciary would call for the resistance of every good citizen.  But, as I am endeavouring to show, that situation cannot arise, as a study of the Constitution will reveal.</P>
    <P>But, with regard to the lesser or minor judges, if I might refer to them without using derogatory language, known as district justices, there was an attempt, which I may be pardoned for recalling, to interfere with their discretion in the first years of their existence.  In the eyes of many people, district justices are only stipendiary magistrates under another name, and people think they can be dictated to and written to, and called to account even in a House of the Legislature as being only a sort of magistrate.  But I recall that the late Hugh Kennedy, as Attorney-General or Law Adviser to the Government of that day, explained that his conception of their office was: that there is one District Court for the whole State, with justices of that District Court located in different places. <Col N="2037" /> Senator Hayes will recall that there was once an attempt made to criticise in the Dáil a district justice, and the attempt was repelled by himself&mdash;at the time he was Ceann Comhairle&mdash;because it was interference with the liberty of a judge.  Now, district justices, although they are judges, do not hold office in the way in which judges of the High Court do.  A formula we are all familiar with in regard to judges of the High Court is <i>quamdiu se bene gesserunt</i>; that is, they hold office so long as they conduct themselves properly.</P>
    <P>There is a way of dealing with a district justice who does not take his position seriously or who finds himself incapacitated for the discharge of his duty.  He can be dealt with by a committee over which the chief justice presides. I suggest that if it can be shown in the time of the present emergency&mdash;which, in accordance with our First Amendment of the Constitution is in reality a time of war although we are not actually a belligerent&mdash;if it can be shown that in such time of emergency a district justice perversely attempts to thwart the operation of a measure designed by the Government for the protection of the people's interest and shows his contempt for these efforts of our Government by imposing light and ineffective fines for an anti-social act of which a man has been convicted, then it would be possible to arraign him.  I suggest that that is the way to deal with conduct of the sort, a way already provided in a time of peace when there was no possibility of passion or hostile feeling being at work in the minds of those who designed the remedy.</P>
    <P>Now, on another point also of yesterday's debate, I am anxious to say how much I enter into the feelings of Senator Campbell with regard to the Order 83.  When we&mdash;rightly as I held and hold still&mdash;approved an Order or regulation attempting to save the people from the spiral of rising prices by imposing a restriction on an increase of wages and likewise an increase of dividends distributed to shareholders&mdash;for both wage-earners and dividend-receivers were affected by <Col N="2038" /> the Order&mdash;when we did that, undoubtedly it became encumbent to see to the regulation of prices.  An effort has been made, we are assured by the Taoiseach, to keep down attempts at profiteering in prices.  But the effort has not been wholly successful so far as I can learn; and in result, I think I may submit with all respect, it is legitimate to make a plea for further and closer attention to this evil of prices being raised here and there by unconscionable people who sell the necessaries of life to the workers in the city.  Now, the prices regulation authority&mdash;it may be my ignorance which dictates this comment&mdash;seem to regard prices as simply prices of commodities. But there are prices of services, and services are just as apt to become the subject of this unfair action on the part of certain people.</P>
    <P>I have been told, for instance, that it is a grievance of some auctioneers that recently, when private motor cars had to go off the roads, there was a rush to estate agents' offices on the part of house owners in Foxrock, Carrickmines and as far out as Killiney because the difficulty of transport kept people from arriving at their place of business or office and their various centres of avocation.  Then the transport of the furniture from the houses that the owners had the good fortune to sell promptly became to the carriers and the furniture removers an opportunity for profit.  One auctioneer assured me that in several cases where the household contents were brought to his place the levy made on the goods by the carrier used up a large part of the auctioneer's results.  It may be that many of those who suffered from it were well able to bear the impost but that does not make it the less inequitable.  I would like to draw attention to that as a matter which comes under the heading of prices.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JohnCounihan" hpid="Mr. Counihan Mr. Counihan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Counihan</NameTxt>
      <P>Section 8 of the Bill is very drastic and I believe it was influenced by wild and unreasonable and exaggerated statements such as was made last night by Senator Johnston. He spoke of some of the County Monaghan farmers who were tilling <Col N="2039" /> their worst land, putting the worst seed into it and leaving it there and not doing anything further.  I do not think the Taoiseach would believe that that sort of man should be brought before a court.  No men of common sense would advocate that that man should be brought before a court at all.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. Johnston Mr. Johnston">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Johnston</NameTxt>
      <P>On a point of explanation. I did not say that that was general of County Monaghan farmers but that I knew a couple of farmers had done it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnCounihan" hpid="Mr. Counihan Mr. Counihan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Counihan</NameTxt>
      <P>My contention is, no matter whether it is a Monaghan man or a Kerry man or a Limerick man, that sort of man should not be brought before a court but should be medically examined and committed to a lunatic asylum.  The case of a man who would plough his land, go to the expense of putting seed in it and who would leave it there to rot, is, I contend, a case where it could be pleaded and where the judge could say that there were extenuating circumstances&mdash;the man was mad&mdash;and should not be fined £500 or put in jail for three months.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>No matter how the Taoiseach or other Ministers may protest that it is not directed against the farmers, the farmers believe it is directed against the few people who did not comply with the Tillage Order.  The farmers bitterly resent the insinuation.  There are only, as I have heard stated, .12 per cent. of the 450,000 farmers in this country who have not more than complied with the tillage regulations and it is commonsense, I think, to assume that there would be extenuating circumstances in the case of that .12 per cent. for their non-compliance with the Tillage Order.  I know a case where a farmer had no money, no working capital, and was letting his land on the 11 months system.  He let the acreage for tillage that came under the Tillage Order within the last two years.  But, after two years, when he was unable to procure artificial manure, he could get nobody to take it.  He had no means of tilling it himself.  Eventually, he managed to let it at something like 15/- an acre.  If that man could not get <Col N="2040" /> anybody to take his land to till it and if he had no means of tilling it himself, I say that would be another case where there were extenuating circumstances and where it was an impossibility for the man to comply with the Order.</P>
    <P>I would appeal to the Taoiseach to consider the suggestion that I put up last night and to allow a judge in such cases, at least, in connection with non-compliance with the Tillage Order, to state in open court that there were extenuating circumstances and to recommend a mitigation of penalty.  I make that appeal to the Taoiseach. Surely it will be possible to insert something in the Bill giving an intimation to the district justice to act in that way because there are cases where a penalty might be inflicted, where the person might not be in a position to get Deputies or Senators to intervene on his behalf with the Department of Justice or to make recommendations for him, where the fine might be insisted on and perhaps he might have to go to jail, because the case had not been properly considered. His case would be considered if the judge made the recommendation that I suggest it should be possible for him to make.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMcGee" hpid="Mr. McGee Mr. McGee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGee</NameTxt>
      <P>It was not my intention to intervene in this debate but Senator Counihan has appealed to the Taoiseach to reconsider this particular section.  A good deal of criticism is provoked by the idea that when there is a whip to be raised the farmer is the object of the whip.  In view of the quantity of food that it is being sought to produce this year we should look beyond the stereotyped law that requires you to till so much of your land.  If special efforts were made now, I think more than a sufficiency of wheat could be produced by those farmers whose lands are capable of producing wheat.  Some differentiation should be made between the farmer who does not comply with the Tillage Order and the various racketeers that the State, unfortunately, has to deal with.  In my opinion, the farmer who has good land and who is not tilling his complement or all that his available resources will <Col N="2041" /> allow, is a fool hardly outclassed by the gentleman that Senator Johnston referred to.  If his land is suitable and if he has the resources necessary, in my opinion, the farmer on the average land in Ireland is a fool if he will not till.  Tillage is practically an insurance policy for him that he will earn a livelihood for himself and his employees.  In my opinion, it is safer than cattle alone.  I think it would be wrong for the Government to insist that a certain percentage of land on every farm must be tilled, because we are asking people to till who know nothing about tillage and whose land has absolutely no hope of giving results. I see that happening in my own county, which is one of the best from the tillage point of view.  It is a tremendous mistake to ask people to till land which cannot give good results.  It is equally a mistake not to encourage the farmers who can till and whose land will give good results.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Now that they have the farmers on the way, I suggest the Government should coax and court the farmers here in the same way as the Governments of other countries around us, even in the North of Ireland, are doing.  In yesterday's <i>Irish Press</i> I saw an article under the heading, &ldquo;Britain's Plough Now Plan&rdquo;.  The British Minister of Agriculture is asking the farmers to plough an extra 500,000 acres of heavy land between this and harvest time, and the <i>Irish Press</i> reporter understands that it is not proposed to adopt a similar course here.  I do not suppose it is necessary.  Some eight weeks ago I was associated with a motion here, put forward by Senator The McGillycuddy, which suggested that the farmers should be guaranteed 50/- per barrel for the next four years. What prompted me to associate myself with that motion was the hope that soon afterwards we might hear from the Government what was their proposal for next year.  The time is rapidly passing, and, if we want to take the utmost out of the land, we should be getting ready to sow wheat for next year.  As representing a county that is growing the highest proportion of wheat in Eire, I say the time to sow <Col N="2042" /> wheat is October, and we are now almost at the beginning of August.</P>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Leas-Chathaoirleach Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Is not the Senator turning this into a debate on wheat-growing?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMcGee" hpid="Mr. McGee Mr. McGee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGee</NameTxt>
      <P>I am appealing to the Taoiseach to remove from this section the proposal to fine people £100 for not complying with the Order.  I appeal to him to differentiate between the people who do not till the land and the racketeers whom the Government are anxious to involve.  I suggest that it is a matter for the Government&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Leas-Chathaoirleach Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>It is not necessary for the Senator to repeat his statement.  I think the Seanad has heard it.  We all know what he has said.  I should like to point out that this is not a motion on wheat-growing, and perhaps it would be better if the Senator would relate his remarks to the section of the Bill under discussion.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMcGee" hpid="Mr. McGee Mr. McGee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGee</NameTxt>
      <P>I have been here all the morning and I have heard what other Senators have said.  I have not spoken for the past three days.  I have done as much for the country in the matter of food production as any other Senator.  I hold, and have held for the past 20 years, a responsible position in my county.  I have my views on national and local matters.  If other Senators are allowed to speak on this matter, I submit that I am entitled to do so.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Leas-Chathaoirleach Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I am not preventing the Senator.  I am sorry to have to interrupt the Senator, but what he has been saying is not relevant to this section.  It is not pertinent to have a long disquisition as to whether now is the time to prepare for the growing of wheat.  I am asking the Senator to relate his remarks to the section.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMcGee" hpid="Mr. McGee Mr. McGee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGee</NameTxt>
      <P>I appeal to the Taoiseach to differentiate between the farmers who fail to till the required amount of land and the racketeers who obviously should be punished.  I suggest that the same punishment should not be meted out to both parties. <Col N="2043" /> Sufficient food can, in my opinion, be obtained and the way to obtain it is to start now and make preparations to sow wheat in October.  A more pleasing atmosphere would be created in the minds of the farmers if some plan similar to that adopted in England were put into operation here.  I am sorry if I have intruded on this occasion.  I shall not speak in the House this afternoon.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LiamOBuachalla" hpid="Liam O Buachalla Liam O Buachalla">
      <NameTxt>Liam O Buachalla</NameTxt>
      <P>The main reason I have for speaking is to protest against the effort that is being made to import into this discussion the idea that this Bill, or the particular section we are discussing, has been framed against the farming community.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnCounihan" hpid="Mr. Counihan Mr. Counihan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Counihan</NameTxt>
      <P>The farmers believe it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LiamOBuachalla" hpid="Liam O Buachalla Liam O Buachalla">
      <NameTxt>Liam O Buachalla</NameTxt>
      <P>It is claimed that the efforts of the farmers have been so satisfactory, and their work on the whole has been so patriotic, that this particular section is uncalled for, at least so far as they are concerned. Tribute has been generously paid to the work of the farmers in connection with the tillage campaign.  Such tribute has been paid by the Taoiseach and by members of both Houses of the Oireachtas.  I should like to take this opportunity of joining with those who have paid tribute to the farmers, to all those who have rallied to the call of the nation in such magnificent fashion. I must say it did not occur to me at any time that this section was designed against the farming community nor do I believe any such thing.  It occurred to me on reading it that this was an effort to get after the racketeers in the rural and urban areas.  It has been claimed that the farmers resent this provision of power to impose severe penalties.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I will give the House some indication as to the attitude of farmers in the county from which I come.  I attended a meeting not very long ago. The meeting was called for a very awkward hour, but it was a very large meeting and Senator Hawkins will bear me out in this, that at that meeting <Col N="2044" /> there was no question of protest against the Government's call to the farmers to till more; there was no question of protest with regard to the prices that were being guaranteed for their produce.  The outstanding matter of protest there was that certain people were able to evade their responsibilities under the tillage Orders and these farmers called very emphatically for the heaviest penalties to ensure that these people would be compelled to realise what they were doing and, realising that, would hearken to the call of the State to do their share in the provision of essential foods.  If they did not realise that duty and if they were caught, it was urged that they should pay dearly for it.</P>
    <P>I do not know whether Senator Hawkins will speak on this section, but I know that he has the opinions of farmers in various parts of County Galway on this matter.  The farmers expect that legislation will provide for the heaviest penalties for people in their industry who will attempt to evade their duties in this matter. Further than that, I can inform the House that various people have drawn my attention to efforts that were being made to evade this duty in respect of extra tillage.  I just mention two cases.  Two parish priests communicated with me early this year regarding cases in which they believed efforts were being made to evade the tillage law.  They lived very far apart&mdash; practically at different ends of the county&mdash;and they asked me to bring the matter to the notice of the Minister for Agriculture.  They suggested that the matter was so urgent that I ought not to wait until the Seanad met, but should go to Dublin and ask the Minister to send somebody down to them and that they would take that official to see the land in respect of which they believed an effort was being made to evade the tillage Orders. The Minister will bear me out when I say that I came to him post-haste.  The matter was so urgent that, as I know, he called officials back from some other areas and sent them down and, as a result of their visits, the matter was adjusted.  I mention that to show that farmers and those who know the rural <Col N="2045" /> areas do not resent the inclusion in any section of this Bill of a provision setting out the heaviest penalties possible for anybody who attempts to avoid doing his duty in this matter.</P>
    <P>From my connection with and my study of this question, the big difficulty as it appears to me is that the Department has not a sufficiently large number of inspectors to go around and see what is being done and to investigate all complaints.  It is a difficulty which it would be very hard to get over. There might be a financial difficulty, which would certainly not stand very long in the way, but there is also the difficulty of getting competent men. There is the difficulty, as I think everybody here will agree, of getting thoroughly competent people to decide whether particular land should be cultivated or not and to what extent the law is being evaded.  That is one of the big difficulties.</P>
    <P>A good deal of play has been made about the inclusion of this proviso in respect of heavy penalties.  Whom does this penalty frighten?  Practically every law passed has penalties set out in it&mdash;maximum and minimum fines and so on.  Who has any reason to be uneasy about this?  Certainly not the majority.  Laws do not usually frighten the majority.  The majority will carry out the law, but there is always a certain very small element in the community against whom the penal parts of a law are directed, and it is against such an element in the farming community that any section in this Bill which sets out heavy penalties is directed.  There is nothing unusual, nor is there anything startling in that, and the ordinary farmers, with their common sense will agree that it is only right that a penalty, and a penalty in the heaviest terms possible, should be provided.</P>
    <P>I do not know whether the intention of the Seanad to adjourn this week is to be carried out or not, but, if it is, I hope we shall be saved many of the flights of imagination to which we had to listen yesterday evening&mdash;for instance, the one about this strange phantom widow&mdash;widow mind you&mdash;with the 100 <Col N="2046" /> acres, who, strangely enough, had to tend her dying husband, timed very nicely to die during the spring.  If it is the intention of the Seanad to adjourn as is suggested, I hope we shall keep strictly to the matters arising on the Bill.</P>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Leas-Chathaoirleach Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Before naming the next speaker, I should like to reinforce what Senator O Buachalla has said.  As time is limited, it would be well if Senators would remember that this is the Committee Stage and not the stage on which to make general speeches on the question of wheat growing or the relation of farmers to this Bill.  These subjects have been discussed at some length and time is getting short.  If the House is to adjourn to-day, as I understand is the intention, it would be well if speakers confine themselves to the section and to matters relevant to it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrederickHawkins" hpid="Mr. Hawkins Mr. Hawkins">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hawkins</NameTxt>
      <P>If the Seanad, and particularly the Opposition, adopted a different attitude towards this section, that different attitude and the publication in the Press that we were prepared to stand behind the Government in whatever action is necessary to put down black marketing, and to see that everybody carries out the duties imposed on him by whatever regulations are passed, would quite possibly obviate the necessity of imposing these penalties; but once it goes out that we are divided, and that certain people, particularly the Opposition, do not approve of this proposal, there will be dissension among the people, and they will have all the greater grievance with regard to the insertion of this minimum penalty in the Bill than would be the case if it went out from the House that all sides were united and were behind the Government in whatever action it thought necessary to take.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I do not intend to go into the question of whether this is intended for the farmer or not&mdash;I spoke on that last night&mdash;but Senator Buckley made a passing reference to this poor widow whose husband was dying.  I notice that Senator Hayes smiled at my reference to &ldquo;a poor widow whose husband was dying&rdquo;, but I quote the words of <Col N="2047" /> Senator Baxter who introduced the matter.  That is my reason for using the phrase.  If that sad event occurred in County Galway, I can safely guarantee that that woman's land would be ploughed and sown by her neighbours, and I hope the same could be said of Cavan and every other county.  If the people of Cavan have lost that Irish charity, there is another method which that widow could have adopted.  I am sure that there would be people anxious to take the land in conacre so that there was no necessity to leave the land untilled.  We had a long harangue yesterday about the black market and those operating it, but one could get up and make the same case as has been made for the widow to whom Senator Baxter referred for the poor widow with a business, whose husband dies.  Such a widow may have had some chests of tea or some bicycle tyres, and in order to keep her business going she might feel quite justified in charging exorbitant prices and entering the black market.  The same case could be made for that widow as Senator Baxter tries to make for the farmer's widow who, to my mind, never existed.</P>
    <P>It is suggested that price control is not properly operated.  We all know that it cannot be operated without the co-operation of the ordinary citizen, and when one reads that during the debates in the other House&mdash;I am glad it did not occur here&mdash;a responsible member stated that in order to keep 100 men employed in cutting timber for sale in Dublin City, machinery, oil, files for saws&mdash;everything necessary to keep his equipment going&mdash;were purchased by him in the black market, what can one expect from the ordinary citizen?</P>
    <P>I also remember reading another utterance of the Leader of the Labour Party in the other House in which he complained of certain overcharges in Kildare, but he admitted, when he was questioned, that he did not report anything about that to the Department. He left that to those unfortunate people who were overcharged.  I say that if every Deputy, every Senator, <Col N="2048" /> the clergy, and other responsible people of the country came out against black marketing as they should, it would be put down.  It is not, to my mind, the ordinary businessman who is engaged in this black marketing.  It is the type of people who buy up and corner certain articles which they know are becoming scarce.  Then they offer these articles to people who require them urgently, and who are prepared to pay any price for them.  One way to prevent that traffic, although it would be a very expensive method, would be to adopt a proper rationing system or to enforce a more rigid control of distribution.</P>
    <P>The Labour Party are very vocal in regard to control of prices and about the increase of black marketing but they, above all people in the country, have an organisation which could give valuable assistance in counteracting these abuses.  I say, and I have said it before, that if I were closely associated with the Labour organisation I would utilise that organisation to help in putting down this black marketing. I think, if they were to do that, they would be doing much more good for the community than by trying to make propaganda out of the existence of the black market.  Last night some members of the Labour Party in this House spoke about Order No. 83.  I shall not go into that question now but I shall just mention one matter that appears to me terribly inconsistent with their statements on that Order.  Some few weeks ago there was a meeting in County Galway at which some representatives of Labour attended.  At that meeting one of the principal resolutions passed requested the county council not to increase the wages of their employees.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDouglas" hpid="Mr. Douglas Mr. Douglas">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Douglas</NameTxt>
      <P>It seems to me that there is only one issue that arises on this section.  That is whether the Government should be given powers under certain circumstances to impose a minimum penalty.  No amendment has been put down to the section and, therefore, I think it has been made perfectly clear that there is no one who would deny that power to the Government at this stage.  Our object in the <Col N="2049" /> debate is to draw the attention of the Government and of the Taoiseach to the reasons why we felt that minimum penalties should not be imposed, if it is at all possible to avoid them.  The last speaker said that the Opposition should make clear how they propose to deal with persons engaged in black marketing.  I think that has been made as clear as daylight.  To my mind there is no member of the House who is not prepared to give full power to the Government to deal with that evil.  If we agree to give these powers to the Government, then I think our only purpose in discussing this section is to draw the attention to the way in which we think these powers should be operated and to give the Government the benefit of our views on this matter.  It is not proposed as I say to deny the Government these powers, and that is indicated by the fact that no amendment has been put down to the section.</P>
      <P>Senator Buckley asked who was afraid of the minimum penalty.  I should like to answer that.  As far as a person who knows the law and who wilfully disobeys it is concerned, I am not the tiniest bit worried about the imposition of a minimum penalty, but I do say that owing to the enormous number of Orders which have been issued, it is quite possible that many people do not know exactly what the regulations are and, sometimes with the very best intentions in the world, they infringe these laws.  It is in that type of case that I think it would be unwise to provide for a minimum penalty.  For my part I hope the House will be prepared, having put its case and having pointed out that the Government should be very careful in its exercise of this power, to pass this section.  I do not think that any useful purpose would be served by discussing it further.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesTunney" hpid="Mr. Tunney Mr. Tunney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Tunney</NameTxt>
      <P>I desire to say only a few words.  I am satisfied that the Government must get these powers but as a worker and as a trade unionist I object to the way in which these regulations are applied to the working-class so that they are very definitely caught in certain cases, while there are <Col N="2050" /> too many loopholes by which other people can escape the provisions of these Orders.  I shall give a few illustrations. Take the case of bicycle tyres.  The price of these is supposed to be controlled.  I personally have been searching Dublin for the last six months and I could not get one tyre within the city unless I was prepared to go to the black market.  What is the use of making an Order of that kind if some steps are not taken to ensure that cycle agents will keep records showing how they dispose of tyres supplied to them?  I am prepared to wager that not one Senator can buy a single tyre or a single new bicycle at the controlled price.  What is the use then of making these Orders?  These traders are supplied with tyres but to whom are they selling them?  I have been looking for a tyre for a member of my family for a considerable time past.  I have failed completely to get a tyre at the controlled price and the result is that my son has to walk four miles to his work.  That applies equally to many other people.</P>
      <P>As regards tillage, I think that the tillage Order has not been properly enforced.  No matter what Senator Counihan may say, I do not think his statement that people do not till bad land, is accurate.  We have certain gentlemen in County Dublin who hold hundreds of acres of the best land in the county and none of it is tilled.  I personally have gone to the Department and have complained that these people are not tilling and the reply I have got is that they have tilled so many acres in another part of the country.  I have no proof that they have but one thing is certain.  I can take these inspectors to certain people who own hundreds of acres of the most fertile land in County Dublin and who have not tilled one acre of that land. That is a great injustice to the nation and it should not be allowed.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Leas-Chathaoirleach Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>We are dealing with the question of minimum penalties now.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesTunney" hpid="Mr. Tunney Mr. Tunney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Tunney</NameTxt>
      <P>The excuse is sometimes made that people cannot get their land tilled.  I find that in County <Col N="2051" /> Dublin as much as £9 per acre is being paid for tillage land.  In my own native county, Mayo, up to £4 per acre is being paid.  I would appeal to the Taoiseach to be very stern with these people who refuse to carry out the tillage regulations.  The regulations, in my opinion, are much too loose.  I feel also that the person who has ten acres of arable land&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Leas-Chathaoirleach Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>This is not a Bill dealing with compulsory tillage. We are dealing now with a section which, as Senator Douglas has pointed out, is concerned only with the question of the imposition of minimum penalties.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesTunney" hpid="Mr. Tunney Mr. Tunney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Tunney</NameTxt>
      <P>The Bill deals with the punishment for non-compliance with certain regulations and I want to know how it is possible for certain people to evade these regulations.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Leas-Chathaoirleach Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>The Senator must not make a Second Reading speech on the section.  He must relate what he has to say to the particular section under discussion.  We have had too many Second Reading speeches on this stage.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesTunney" hpid="Mr. Tunney Mr. Tunney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Tunney</NameTxt>
      <P>I am pointing out that there are too many loopholes in these regulations, the result being that, while heavy penalties are imposed on certain people, certain other gentlemen escape punishment although guilty of similar offences.  I hold that there is no use in the Government making these regulations if they do not take steps to have them fully enforced.  I have pointed out that they are not being enforced in the case of bicycles and bicycle tyres and also in the case of certain people who have found it possible to evade the tillage regulations.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Mr. M. Hayes Mr. M. Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Mr. M. Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>The opposition to the powers taken by the Government in this section, and to the imposition of a minimum fine without the discretion of the justices, is based on general principles, out of regard for innocent citizens and not guilty citizens.  Those who are opposing it <Col N="2052" /> have no sympathy with those who break the law.  For my part, and for everybody who is opposed to the section, I say that I should like to see law-breakers apprehended and punished, but I prefer to see them punished in court by the person who knew all the circumstances, rather than have a case heard and the minimum penalty inflicted.  I want to get the Taoiseach to confirm my view of the meaning of the section.  It provides for a minimum fine which may not be more than £500, but which may be any figure lower than that.  I think the allusion to the £100 fine is misconceived.  Section (6A) (a) provides a jail sentence as penalty, and that is left to the discretion of the district justices.  There is no power to compel the district justice, if he finds a person guilty, to impose a jail sentence. Senator Counihan asked whether power would be provided for a district justice, although he had no option but to impose a minimum penalty, to state that in his judgment there were mitigating circumstances which he could operate to mitigate the penalty.  As far as I understand it the justice has that power.  Assuming that an Order is made, having heard the evidence, and found a person guilty, the justice is compelled to impose a particular fine, but he may say that in his judgment there are mitigating circumstances, and that only that he was coerced by the Order he would not have imposed such a fine.  I think there is power to do that, and that it would not be necessary to have an amendment. If that were made clear the discussion would be shortened.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonDeValera" hpid="The Taoiseach Eamon de Valera">
      <NameTxt>The Taoiseach</NameTxt>
      <P>One of the difficulties here is that this discussion has been somewhat in the air.  The accumulation of cases which decided Ministers in charge of Departments to ask the Government to agree to have a section of this particular kind has not been before the Seanad.  Therefore, Senators have no idea of what it was that compelled us very reluctantly to take the action I indicated, and that was to adopt some system of minimum fines.  I refer to that because in the <Col N="2053" /> Dáil I had a long list of what, in the circumstances, appeared to be serious offences, and these were dealt with by the justices imposing trivial fines.  That is the fact.  I could not say in any particular case that the circumstances were such that they would justify mitigation. I have simply taken the list of offences and the punishments imposed.  Unless it is suggested that there were extenuating circumstances in a large number of these cases, one is simply forced to the conclusion that the justices, taking them generally, did not realise the seriousness of the position, and did not realise the seriousness of the crime against the community that was committed by those who broke the law in that way.  We have devoted attention largely to some particular individuals who were more or less harshly or severely dealt with by the operation of the minimum penalty.  We have been fixing our attention upon these people, but our duty is to look after the welfare of the community as a whole.  If it is found necessary to adopt this particular method, as the only one that offers hope of success, we cannot pay too much regard to the possibility of hardship in individual cases, but to injury to the community as a whole or we fail to do our duty towards it.  The fact that food is required, and that certain articles like tea are in short supply offers strong temptation to make money, when people are willing and able to pay a high price for tea and others are willing to sell.  We want to protect the people.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I have here a shorter list of these cases.  It is, possibly, true that they are worse than the average of those on a list I had previously.  I concede that at the start.  I had to get some examples. The list I had in the Dáil contained hundreds of cases, and showed that most of the sentences appear to be altogether too lenient for the offences that were committed. I asked to have a smaller list prepared, which would give Senators the same impression as I got after reading the longer list.  It would be impossible to read that now.  I will start with cases dealing with the sale of tea in different counties.  These were cases of <Col N="2054" /> people who wilfully and perversely wanted to act against the general spirit of the Order.  It was apparent that the justices did not realise the seriousness of the offences.  There is a maximum price of 3/4 per lb. for tea, and in a certain county, which I will not name, a person was charged with selling it at the rate of 8/- per lb. on two occasions.  It is quite clear to anybody, who thinks, that if that practice were to continue, only wealthy people would have tea.  Therefore, it was an offence against the community, and an offence particularly against the poorer section.  The Probation Act was applied in regard to the first case, and a fine of 10/6 and 4/- costs was imposed in the second case.  It may be argued that that was the only offence, but if people are carrying on practices like that, we cannot be certain that they have not been doing it over a long period.  I am assuming that there were not extenuating circumstances.  If there were a number of cases like that, Senators can realise that justices did not appreciate the seriousness of the position; in other words, they are so isolated from what the Executive has to deal with that they did not see it. Here is another case of a person who was convicted of selling tea at 5/4 per lb. on two occasions, 5/- per lb. once, and 4/- per lb. on another occasion.  In each case a fine of 2/6 was imposed, 4/- costs, and 10/- witnesses' expenses. It was known that 3/4 was the fixed price.  The people who sold the tea knew perfectly well that it was being sold to those who could afford to pay a higher price, and that they were depriving poorer people of it.</P>
    <P>Unless one assumes that there were extenuating circumstances the fines would show a want of appreciation of the nature of the offences.  There was another case in another county where 5/- per lb. was charged and the Probation Act was applied on payment of 14/- expenses.  In another case in which 5/- was charged the Probation Act was also applied.  Cigarettes, the legal price of which was 8½d. for ten, were sold at 1/- and the fine was £1. Flour which should be sold at 3/2 per stone was sold for 14/- for four stones. It may be said that there was only a <Col N="2055" /> few pence in the difference, but a few pence mean that they would be inclined to give more than their share to those who are prepared to pay the highest price.</P>
    <Speaker pid="DesmondFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Fitzgerald Mr. Fitzgerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Fitzgerald</NameTxt>
      <P>It seems to be more than a few pence.  Did the Taoiseach say 3/6 per stone?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonDeValera" hpid="The Taoiseach Eamon de Valera">
      <NameTxt>The Taoiseach</NameTxt>
      <P>3/2 or 12/8 for four stones.  We must not lose sight of the fact that if people sell at 3/4 or at 3/6 it is a serious offence, and ought not to be dealt with by a justice as being a trifling affair.  I asked for a list that would not be too long.  These are the types of cases that made an impression on me when I read them.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DesmondFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Fitzgerald Mr. Fitzgerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Fitzgerald</NameTxt>
      <P>We accept the Taoiseach's word for that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonDeValera" hpid="The Taoiseach Eamon de Valera">
      <NameTxt>The Taoiseach</NameTxt>
      <P>They are some of the cases that impressed me as I read them through.  Here is a case for the improper use of wheaten products.  We know that we were short of bread and that the feeding of wheat to animals was forbidden.  It was very important from the point of view of the community that such products should not be fed to animals.  In the list there are cases where animals were being fed mainly on feeding stuffs containing wheat and the fine imposed was £1 and 2/6 costs. That does not indicate a proper appreciation of the facts, assuming that there were not some very extenuating circumstances.  In the same county there were two or three cases of manufacturing animal feeding containing wheat products and the Probation Act was applied.  For the manufacture of white bread a fine of £1 and costs was imposed.  I hold that if there is a number of cases of that kind we must conclude that the justices who were administering the law did not understand the seriousness of the situation.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Mr. M. Hayes Mr. M. Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Mr. M. Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>Would it be of any assistance if I said that we accept the view that, generally, fines have been imposed which were too small?  It <Col N="2056" /> can be accepted, generally, that fines were too small.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDouglas" hpid="Mr. Douglas Mr. Douglas">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Douglas</NameTxt>
      <P>We all agree.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonDeValera" hpid="The Taoiseach Eamon de Valera">
      <NameTxt>The Taoiseach</NameTxt>
      <P>The reasons I wanted to give examples was that we might view this question with an air of reality.  In these circumstances the Bill was brought forward and primarily aimed at those who were charging excessive prices and contravening the Orders of the Minister for Supplies. I would not like it to be inferred, as I think it was, that these powers will not be applied.  When the power is given Ministers can, if they feel it necessary to do so use them.  They got them with the idea of using them.  My own hope was that it would not be necessary to use them.  I am afraid that is too much to hope for and that they will have to be used.  I would like to disabuse anybody of the idea that it could be inferred from anything I said last night, that this is not likely to be applied to those offending against the regulations.  If it is necessary to do so it will be done to deal with those who are in the black market or with those who refuse to do their duty.</P>
      <P>Some Senators have given the reply to the argument that this Bill is directed against one particular class of the community, and that it shows want of confidence in the farmers. The answer, which is sufficient, is that this will affect only those who break the law and who do something which, in the opinion of the Legislature and the Government, is a crime against the community.  The only question, as Senator Hayes pointed out, is whether this general application of the law may not be extremely harsh in individual cases.  In that regard, I have only to say that we have even to run that risk, if necessary, to deal with offences against the community as a whole.  I am sorry to see that risk run.  The fact is, as I think Senator Hayes conceded, that the fines imposed were much too light to be a deterrent to those who proposed to break the law.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I referred last night to the independence of the judiciary and justices &mdash;I should say, rather, the isolation of the judiciary and justices from other <Col N="2057" /> branches of government, in the broad sense.  I think it was Senator Fitzgerald said that they were only different aspects of the same thing. The Legislature making laws, the Executive carrying out the laws, the judiciary administering them from the point of view of interpretation and imposing penalties&mdash;these are only different parts of the method by which the community is regulated and governed.  We adopted the British system.  In our books on jurisprudence, the value of the independence of the judiciary is stressed.  We have carried that to an extreme degree here because we have interpreted &ldquo;independence&rdquo;&mdash;which means that they are not to be forced to give opinions in a particular way&mdash;as meaning isolation.  The British have unified the system much more than we have.  The head of the judiciary in Britain&mdash;the Lord Chancellor&mdash;is a member of the Cabinet.  He is also chairman of one of the Houses of Parliament.  There are a number of judges in the Privy Council, where they are brought into close contact with the needs of the Executive of the day. The justices there are not in such a position of independence that they can practically snap their fingers at the Executive.  What I hold is that there should be closer contact between the different parts I have mentioned, just as the Executive is dependent for its power on the day-to-day good-will of the two Houses.  You do not want that in the case of justices, but you do want some contact which will enable them to realise what the governmental problems of the day properly are.  It is difficult to conceive of a scheme by which that can be done.</P>
    <P>One thing can be done and I think that it is desirable that it should be done.  It ought to be regarded as right and proper for the Minister for Justice, in times of crisis, to send round to justices in regard to particular classes of cases&mdash;in, for example, a case like this &mdash;a circular which would indicate the gravity of the offence.  That would not be taking away the independence of the justices.  It is a practice which the Minister for Justice ought to be permitted to adopt.  I see nothing against it.  In their nature, these circulars <Col N="2058" /> would have to be, more or less, of a public character and there ought to be no attempt unduly to influence the justices in a particular way&mdash;merely to bring them into contact with the problems with which the Executive have got to deal.  In our case, the judiciary is not merely independent, as we all desire it to be, but it is, very largely, isolated.  I think that that in itself is a pity.  Of course, it will be said that the judges read the newspapers and have contact with public problems because of the world around them but the contact which members of either House have with the Executive is of a different nature and it does not take from their independence as individuals.  It gives them an idea of Executive problems.</P>
    <P>If justices do not administer the law in the spirit which the Legislature intended, it is quite obvious that the work of the Legislature and the Executive can be nullified to a large extent.  It is not a question of interpretation&mdash;that a passage is not interpreted in the precise way the draftsman or Parliament intended.  There is a remedy for that, if it is not done perversely. But there is no remedy if a justice allows out an offender under the First Offenders Act, as has been done in cases in which people have been guilty, in our opinion, of very serious offences.  The only way we can see of dealing with the difficulty suggested, which is the foundation objection to this clause, is to provide that, if there are cases of very special hardship, they can be reviewed on appeal to the Minister for Justice.  I do not suggest that that is an ideal way of dealing with the matter.  It would be much better if we could depend on the people on the spot to do what is necessary, but we are satisfied at the moment that there is not on the part of the justices an appreciation of the seriousness of these offences, and that this power to prescribe a penalty below which the justice cannot go should be given to the Government.  As was pointed out by some speakers, that is not in the Bill, in the sense that no specific penalty is prescribed.  The power is given to fix minimum penalties within certain limits.  That is the only power <Col N="2059" /> asked for here.  I see no other way of dealing with the matter.</P>
    <P>I do not think that the setting up of special courts would meet the position. Reference has been made to the sympathy which offenders may receive from their neighbours.  That would be more likely to arise if offenders were brought up at special courts.  It is much better that the local courts should have the responsibility of finding whether an offence was or was not committed.  I think that Senator Hayes was right when he suggested that sentence of imprisonment is part of the discretion of the court.  It may be imposed by the court by way of addition.  Where a minimum penalty of £100 can be imposed and it is desired to substitute a period of imprisonment, the period must be one of not less than six months.</P>
    <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
    <P>Sections 9 and 10 agreed to.</P>
    <P Just="Center">SECTION 11.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Mr. M. Hayes Mr. M. Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Mr. M. Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>I move the amendment standing in my name:&mdash;</P>
      <P>Before Section 11 to insert a new section as follows:&mdash;</P>
      <P>11.  Section 9 of the Principal Act is hereby amended by the insertion after the word &ldquo;Order&rdquo; where that word first occurs in that section of the following words:&mdash;&ldquo;whether a Government Order or a subsidiary document.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>This is to meet the case made for it on the Second Stage.  I do not think there is any difference between the Taoiseach and myself on the matter. If it had been adverted to in the first instance, this particular provision would appear in the Emergency Powers Act.  The Principal Act of 1939 provides for emergency Orders made by the Government, and further provides that they must be laid before each House of the Oireachtas and may be annulled by resolution of either House.  That Act also provides that the Government may delegate to a Minister power to make an Order&mdash;a Ministerial Order&mdash;which differs from the Government Order in a way which <Col N="2060" /> seems to be wrong both in theory and in practice.  We are in the position, as a House of Parliament, that we can by resolution annul an Order made by the Government, which is the whole, but we cannot by resolution annul an Order made by a Minister, who is part of the whole Government.  I think it necessary only to point out that that arrangement is a bad one.  For example, I think a Minister would not refuse to come before this House and argue the case if a motion were put down here to annul an Order.  If it were merely an expression of opinion that an Order should be revoked, the Minister might not come and, whatever the practice may be, in theory he need not come at all.</P>
    <Speaker pid="EamonDeValera" hpid="The Taoiseach Eamon de Valera">
      <NameTxt>The Taoiseach</NameTxt>
      <P>I am afraid it is not possible for me to accept the amendment. The number of Orders is very great, and the subsidiaries are of various kinds.  All the principal Orders which have general application are Government Orders, and the others of more general application are laid on the Table of the House.  The acceptance of this amendment would put a burden on the Departments which they could not very well carry, and it might become impossible for them to carry on.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Mr. M. Hayes Mr. M. Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Mr. M. Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>Was not the Clothes Rationing Order a Ministerial Order?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonDeValera" hpid="The Taoiseach Eamon de Valera">
      <NameTxt>The Taoiseach</NameTxt>
      <P>I think so.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Mr. M. Hayes Mr. M. Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Mr. M. Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>Also, we had to deal with an Order in connection with compensation for personal injuries, made by the Minister for Finance.  In that case, the Minister for Finance acceded very properly to quite a number of suggestions made here, and he came in to discuss them on two or three occasions, so I have no complaint about that.  The Clothes Rationing Order was a very important one.  In fact, some of the Orders made by the Ministers may be more important than Government Orders.  I do not want to cause any difficulty about this matter on this particular stage, but it is very important.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDouglas" hpid="Mr. Douglas Mr. Douglas">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Douglas</NameTxt>
      <P>There is a principle involved here of very considerable importance, <Col N="2061" /> and I cannot follow the reasons why the Taoiseach cannot accept the amendment.  As far as this House is concerned, it will not save any time, as there is nothing to prevent members of the House putting down a motion to condemn the Minister, or to censure him for having made the Order.  It is an unsatisfactory way of doing it, but it has happened already, as it was the only way we could bring the matter up for discussion.  In the case of the Order regarding compensation for personal injuries, the debate was of a very helpful character.  The Minister expressed his own appreciation of the criticisms and he made a new Order.  He did this House the courtesy of coming back to tell us what he proposed to put in the new Order, in case there were further suggestions. I do not think anybody can go back over that debate and say that it was anything but of a helpful character from the beginning to the end.  The Minister said so, and I think everybody in this House felt it was so.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>When you have a Bill of this kind in a democracy, it seems that the fundamental power we retain is the right of Parliament to rescind.  If you withhold that, the whole basis underlying emergency powers legislation is changed, and it becomes virtually dictatorial.  I thought this was an accident until I heard the Taoiseach's view.  If he, as Head of the Government, signs an Order, we know that we have control; but if a Minister, through the power given by the Government, makes an Order, we cannot rescind it.  I do not think that is democratic.  It is wrong in principle.  I would respectfully suggest to the Taoiseach that he should go through all the Orders that have been made.  I have followed them fairly closely, but I did not think he would take this line, and as I have not got the list here, I do not want to bring this debate on to another day in order to prove the point.  I follow the Emergency Powers Orders fairly closely, and would say quite definitely that Orders have been made by the Government of a relatively unimportant character.  I was rather puzzled regarding some of them, as <Col N="2062" /> to why they were made by the Government, but I suppose they had to be made by the Government instead of by a Minister.  At any rate, some of the most important Orders affecting the life of every single person in the country, as in the case of rationing, were Ministerial Orders.  There should be an acceptance of this principle that the House can rescind an Order, or there should be an arrangement by which all important Orders affecting the people generally would be made by the Government.  That is essential from the democratic point of view.</P>
    <P>I admit that I am talking in theory. The Government has a majority in both Houses, and there is no danger that a Ministerial Order would be defeated.  However, I am old-fashioned enough to believe that it is worth while maintaining the democratic theories, even when, for the time being, they may not work.  The right that is maintained in the Emergency Powers Act to maintain the control of Parliament seems to me to be something that made it possible to give assent to the Act, even though we know that, as things are, it is not likely to be exercised but changes may take place which no one expects.  We know that, as long as that power is there, the people in Parliament have a responsibility which they would not have if they ceased to have that power.  Even though at present the majority will vote for the Executive, they vote with a full sense of responsibility and that means maintaining democracy.  I put my name to this amendment, as I believe there is a definite principle.  I hope that the Taoiseach will consider it further, and if he cannot see his way to accept it I do not think we can do anything about it.  I would ask him to look into the matter and see that only minor Orders are made by Ministers.  To my certain knowledge, matters of the utmost importance, affecting the daily life of practically everybody in the country, have been made by Ministers.</P>
    <Speaker pid="ProfWilliamMagennis" hpid="Professor Magennis Professor Magennis">
      <NameTxt>Professor Magennis</NameTxt>
      <P>Some years ago it was proposed in the Dáil by Deputy Tom Johnson, as Leader of the Labour Party, to deal with the matter to which Senator Douglas has drawn <Col N="2063" /> attention.  He proposed to have a committee appointed, composed of members of both Houses, whose duty it would be to investigate Orders the moment they were made, and to report on them where necessary.  It is quite obvious that a Ministerial Order cannot be dealt with in the same manner &mdash;that Ministerial work must go on. In the case of a Government Order, it is a different thing.  I have tried to explain this morning that, in so far as overriding the right of Parliament of review, revision and condemnation, could create what Senator Douglas calls a dictatorial attitude, it does not create that, as it is against the Constitution. I hold, and I am awaiting correction, that we cannot amend the Constitution in any way but that decided in the Constitution itself&mdash;that is, by a Bill passed through Parliament and submitted to the people by referendum.</P>
      <P>There is only one limit to the operation of emergency Orders: they are limited by the fact that the Constitution preserves us from anything in the nature of dictatorship, even by the body called the Government.  I submit that that is worth examining.  As anyone who studies them knows, we have an accumulation of Orders which it would be impossible for the ordinary Senator to become acquainted with, and it would be well to have some members on a committee, with the duty imposed on them of keeping a vigilant eye on those Orders and of making a report where necessary.  This is a procedure which would be very helpful to the preservation of liberty.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonDeValera" hpid="The Taoiseach Eamon de Valera">
      <NameTxt>The Taoiseach</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not want to pretend for a moment that I do not see considerable force in the remarks made, that Orders made by the Government as a whole are open to review by both Houses, while such provision does not exist in the case of subsidiary Orders.  We must look at this from the practical point of view as well as from the theoretical one.  My information is that the change suggested would cause a great deal of difficulty in regard to some of the Departmental work.  I cannot accept the amendment, <Col N="2064" /> but I promise to look into the whole situation.  I know that there is a general disposition to have Orders made available and laid on the Table of the House.  This whole matter requires a lot of detailed examination, before one can decide on the best way to deal with it.  On the information at my disposal, I cannot accept the amendment, but I will see if there is any way in which the views expressed can be met.</P>
      <P>In connection with the views expressed by Senator Magennis, it is within the power of both Houses to set up committees if they wish, and to give them the duty of looking over Orders, and of reporting to the House if they think it necessary to do so.  It is a matter for the House itself.  I do not think it is part of the general organisation or that, from the Governmental point of view, we could exactly take the initiative there.  I do not see that there is any way in which we could.  That is the position.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDouglas" hpid="Mr. Douglas Mr. Douglas">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Douglas</NameTxt>
      <P>I think the Taoiseach realises that laying such Orders on the Table of the House only means circulating them to members, and I can quite readily understand that a considerable economy may be effected so far as the mere question of the circulation of such papers is concerned. However, I was not interested merely in the matter of accessibility, and I am sure that every member of the House would have no difficulty in getting a typed copy of any of these.  I know that I never had any difficulty, but that was not my point.  My point was that there should be some provision limiting the making of subsidiary Orders, so that all major Orders of that kind would be clearly and directly subject to Parliament, in the same way as Government Orders are.  My own belief is that all Orders under these emergency powers should be subject to Parliament.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>If you look through the Orders dealing with matters of a minor character, which are subject to Parliament and can be rescinded, you will realise that very many of them are trifling compared with the subsidiary Orders that are made under these emergency powers. <Col N="2065" /> I am not going to divide the House on the matter, but may I take it that the Taoiseach will promise to look carefully into the whole matter?  I am anxious that the principle should be retained in connection with this Act as I believed to be provided in the previous Act, and I may say that I was not alone in my contention.  There were some officials who held the same views as I, but eventually it was held that it was doubtful whether the Orders of a Minister could be rescinded.</P>
    <P>Amendment, by leave, withdrawn.</P>
    <P>Sections 11 and 12 and Title of the Bill put and agreed to; Bill reported without amendment.</P>
    <P>Question&mdash;&ldquo;That the Bill be received for final consideration&rdquo;&mdash;put and agreed to.</P>
    <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That the Bill do now pass.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="JosephJohnston" hpid="Professor Johnston Professor Johnston">
      <NameTxt>Professor Johnston</NameTxt>
      <P>On this stage, there are a few remarks I should like to make.  I think that the Taoiseach, in the course of his speech, has made it clear that there is a real problem involved&mdash;the problem of how to secure penalties, both adequate and just, for serious offences against the common welfare, but I am not convinced that he is right in his policy of trying to secure the solution of that problem by a procedure which, to me, at any rate, seems to involve some usurpation of the functions of the judiciary by the Executive, even though the Oireachtas should become <i>particeps criminis</i> in facilitating that usurpation.  I think that if the district justices are not doing their full public duty in the administration of the various Orders, then the matter should be dealt with along the lines indicated by Senator Magennis, or on some such lines, but not by the procedure of establishing, at the discretion of the Executive, minimum penalties which the district justices have no power to go below.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Now, I am aware that even under English law there are, in certain matters, minimum penalties imposed, and, in fact, I remember, in my own experience, a significant example of <Col N="2066" /> that kind of thing.  Many years ago, before I was fully grown up, I had the misfortune to be carrying a gun without a licence, and I happened, unfortunately, to meet a member of the Royal Irish Constabulary who disapproved of such conduct, as he was rightly bound to do.  In due course, I found myself in receipt of a blue paper&mdash;a summons to appear before the court to answer for this crime&mdash;and my predicament happened to be conveyed to a friend of mine, and a friend of his happened to be a friend of a magistrate who was extremely likely to be sitting on the bench on that occasion.  So that, without any active intervention on my part, I found my case being poured into the ears of this sympathetic magistrate.  The amusing thing was that when the case was actually heard, this magistrate and his friend did their utmost to have the penalty reduced to some quite trifling sum, and then discovered, what they should have known all along, that under the existing law the bench had no power to impose any penalty less than £2 10s. 0d.  In fact, what they did was to impose the minimum penalty and recommend me to the tender mercies of an executive department, the Department of Customs and Excise.  The Department of Customs and Excise, in due course, looked into my case, no doubt with sympathy, and reduced the fine to the modest sum of 10/-, and so that was that.</P>
    <P>I am giving that as an example of the working of the principle of the minimum penalty, but I think that that principle is only justified in English law or any other kind of law where you have the kind of magistracy that then existed in Ireland and that still exists in England: in other words, a magistracy without any professional training and who owed their position to the British device of giving people a handle to their names and entrusting them with the carrying out of important functions, but that kind of thing is quite inconsistent with any respect for professional obligation or civic duty.  Now, we, when taking over control of this country, rightly discarded all that aspect of the British judicial system and established, instead a professional <Col N="2067" /> magistracy to do the work formerly done by the justices of the peace.  These people are trained in the law and they look at matters from the professional point of view, and they should be trained to look at them from the public point of view as well as from the mere point of view of the law and also to take into account the personal circumstances of the victims of the law, and I think that if these people are not carrying out their duty in a manner which takes into account all the circumstances, including the public circumstances, then they should be dealt with in some such way as has been already indicated by Senator Magennis, and not by way of diminishing the discretion that they rightly enjoy as a professional magistracy.</P>
    <P>In whatever way the thing is achieved, I think it is quite right that severe penalties should be imposed on people who feed to animals food which is capable of being directly consumed with advantage by human beings, but I wonder whether it would be possible to devise some procedure which would impose a penalty for feeding to human beings food which is fit only for animals.  I am informed, on the highest authority&mdash;an authority on which, doubtless, the Taoiseach is able to draw as well as I&mdash;that the last 15 per cent. of what is extracted from the wheat in so-called flour is not capable of benefiting the human digestion in any way whatever, although admirable for animals.</P>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFGibbons" hpid="Cathaoirleach Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I suggest that the Senator is unduly extending the scope of this debate.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JosephJohnston" hpid="Professor Johnston Professor Johnston">
      <NameTxt>Professor Johnston</NameTxt>
      <P>I hope that the Taoiseach will inform himself of these matters and look into them.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamCummins" hpid="Mr. Cummins Mr. Cummins">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cummins</NameTxt>
      <P>With reference to many of these Orders, we recognised, early on, the difficulties that would follow from them, and one notorious Order, in my opinion, is one of the greatest blots that exist so far as this Bill is concerned.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFGibbons" hpid="Cathaoirleach Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>We cannot go into the question of Orders.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="2068" />
    <Speaker pid="WilliamCummins" hpid="Mr. Cummins Mr. Cummins">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cummins</NameTxt>
      <P>I am referring to Emergency Order No. 83.  I think it is one that should be reconsidered, and I earnestly suggest its repeal.  It certainly requires re-examination.  Are we not on the Report Stage, Sir?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFGibbons" hpid="Cathaoirleach Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>No, this is the Fifth Stage, and the Senator is not entitled to discuss Orders in detail.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamCummins" hpid="Mr. Cummins Mr. Cummins">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cummins</NameTxt>
      <P>So far as that Order, at any rate, is concerned, it is an undue interference with the rights both of workers and of employers.  We have public bodies that want to keep the wages of their employees to a standard that will give them a decent living, but they are not permitted by the Government to do that.  Whether that is due to an emergency Order or to this Bill, I do not know.  We had the case of Emergency Order No. 83.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFGibbons" hpid="Cathaoirleach Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>The House discussed that particular Order at great length on a previous occasion.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamCummins" hpid="Mr. Cummins Mr. Cummins">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cummins</NameTxt>
      <P>I would earnestly appeal to the Government to look into the matter and repeal the Order as soon as possible.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFGibbons" hpid="Cathaoirleach Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>We have had that matter specially discussed in the House by way of motion.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamCummins" hpid="Mr. Cummins Mr. Cummins">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cummins</NameTxt>
      <P>All that I desire to say is that I do not want to allow this opportunity to pass without making a further appeal to the Minister to have the Order repealed.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DesmondFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Fitzgerald Mr. Fitzgerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Fitzgerald</NameTxt>
      <P>I must say that it was a shock to me to hear from the Taoiseach that the reason why the Government were seeking special powers in regard to the minimum penalty under this Bill was due to the gross disregard for the welfare of the community of a few district justices. I think he implied practically a majority of them.  I have often felt that something ought to be done in regard to certain district justices who always make a point of getting their names in headlines in the papers. Taking district justices on the whole, I have always felt that the majority <Col N="2069" /> do their job conscientiously.  We have always stood for security in their tenure of office of those discharging judicial functions.  I do think there is a right to remove a man from office. If a man's conduct is of such a kind that the Government could assume that its action in regard to him would win the assent of the majority of the legislature, then it ought to be prepared to take that action.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonDeValera" hpid="The Taoiseach Eamon de Valera">
      <NameTxt>The Taoiseach</NameTxt>
      <P>You could not do that unless you could prove that there was gross misconduct.  You would have to prove misconduct in office, and it would not be easy to do that.  In cases such as we are dealing with here, you could not do it at all.  In a particular case the justice may say: &ldquo;My view of the case is so and so.&rdquo; He is entitled to his view, and that is why we are dealing with the matter in this way.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DesmondFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Fitzgerald Mr. Fitzgerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Fitzgerald</NameTxt>
      <P>It was a shock to me to hear that this tendency was so general.  There were references in this discussion to farmers not tilling their land properly, and to people charging exorbitant prices for tea.  The Government under Section 8 have in mind possible offences committed by a man who is technically a citizen here.  The offence itself is committed in the jurisdiction of another State.  Could we have some examples of the kind of offence the Government have in mind? I can understand the case of a man buying flour in the Six Counties with a view to bringing it in here.  As far as we are concerned, that offence is only known to our law once that man has crossed the frontier.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonDeValera" hpid="The Taoiseach Eamon de Valera">
      <NameTxt>The Taoiseach</NameTxt>
      <P>There might be offences in connection with shipping. I am not so sure with regard to currency. The general effect is to give extra-territorial effect to our laws.  The point is that you have citizens here who can commit offences in this State or outside the State.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DesmondFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Fitzgerald Mr. Fitzgerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Fitzgerald</NameTxt>
      <P>Could the Taoiseach give an example?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonDeValera" hpid="The Taoiseach Eamon de Valera">
      <NameTxt>The Taoiseach</NameTxt>
      <P>There might be an <Col N="2070" /> offence of a treasonable kind, though that is not the one I have in mind. The point is that a person resident here can commit some of these offences within the State or without the territory of the State.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DesmondFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Fitzgerald Mr. Fitzgerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Fitzgerald</NameTxt>
      <P>A man outside the State cannot be found guilty of not tilling his land or of selling tea for £1 per lb.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonDeValera" hpid="The Taoiseach Eamon de Valera">
      <NameTxt>The Taoiseach</NameTxt>
      <P>Take the chartering of boats.  A person, say, goes to Belfast and charters a boat without getting permission from the Minister. I do not know which is the offence: chartering the boat or refusing to get the licence.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DesmondFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Fitzgerald Mr. Fitzgerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Fitzgerald</NameTxt>
      <P>What is the position of a non-Irish citizen who comes in here?  You have an Irish citizen in New York and he may also be an American citizen.  Under our nationality laws there are thousands of people with more than one nationality.  Take the case of an Irish citizen in America who charters a boat.  He is guilty because he is an Irish citizen.  Is an American citizen in Ireland going to be guilty in the same way?  This business of dual nationality can very easily cause a difficulty here.  We say that if a man is not Irish, and is here, it is the locality of the man which is to operate in deciding who is to be the judge of his act.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasForan" hpid="Mr. Foran Mr. Foran">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Foran</NameTxt>
      <P>On a point of order, is the Senator in order?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFGibbons" hpid="Cathaoirleach Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>This is too large a matter to raise on the Fifth Stage of this Bill.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DesmondFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Fitzgerald Mr. Fitzgerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Fitzgerald</NameTxt>
      <P>I thought it should have been taken in Committee.  I do not propose to pursue it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasForan" hpid="Mr. Foran Mr. Foran">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Foran</NameTxt>
      <P>The Chair, I think, was a bit rough in its ruling on my colleague, seeing that it was so tolerant of the last speaker.  I am intervening simply to say that our people emphatically object to legislation by Order. We have always been hostile to it. Legislation by Order, in its operation, <Col N="2071" /> is much more severe on the working classes than on any other section of the community.  There were a few instances mentioned by the Taoiseach regarding over-charging for tea.  It is a pity he did not develop that and tell us the social status of the people who were so leniently dealt with.  I know of the case of a widow in a small way who was sent to jail in or about the time that these people were being let off under the First Offenders Act or had nominal fines imposed on them.</P>
      <P>As minimum penalties are contained in this Bill, I should like to have an assurance from the head of the Government that there will be no discrimination, whatever may be the social standing or the political standing of the offender, because, unfortunately, in the past both of these things operated very much.  It is a serious matter and tends to lower the respect of the people for the Government of the country.  What was mentioned by Senator Johnston about the person in the old days who was able through his influence to have a fine reduced from 50/- to 10/- operates to-day.  That is not good for the country generally.  It does not tend to create respect for those in authority when one person gets off with a nominal penalty and others are harshly dealt with.  Unfortunately, it is necessary to have an Emergency Powers Act, but the Government ought to realise that those powers should be used with some sort of uniformity.  No matter what the social status of an offender is, it should not be allowed to influence the courts. When the courts have done their duty, certain people and certain bodies can have penalties substantially reduced, whereas people who have not a &ldquo;pull&rdquo; get the full rigour of the law.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>As I said, the working-class people have suffered more under this Emergency Powers Act than any other section of the community.  Even at the risk of being ruled out of order, I must again emphasise that Emergency Powers Order 83, unless there is proper control over prices, is a terrible hardship on the working classes generally. The latest one&mdash;Order 166&mdash;is <Col N="2072" /> the limit altogether.  I should like to say to those who accuse the Labour Party of making propaganda out of the poverty and suffering of the majority of the people that they are not stating the facts.  It is a falsehood to say that. Has any section of the community contributed more by way of money free of interest to the Government than the working classes have?  Early on, some trade union organisations gave a lead to the capitalists or wealthy classes by putting substantial sums of money at the disposal of the Government free of interest.  The lead has not been taken up.</P>
    <Speaker pid="DesmondFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Fitzgerald Mr. Fitzgerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Fitzgerald</NameTxt>
      <P>The Senator showed himself most punctilious to see that there would be no over-stepping the limits of order here.  I wonder if he is not himself as much out of order as I was when he asked that I be shut up.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFGibbons" hpid="Cathaoirleach Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I am sure the Senator himself realises that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DesmondFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Fitzgerald Mr. Fitzgerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Fitzgerald</NameTxt>
      <P>What section of the Bill is it in?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasForan" hpid="Mr. Foran Mr. Foran">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Foran</NameTxt>
      <P>I think I am entitled to reply to some of the criticisms of the Labour Party and not allow them to remain unchallenged.  I have challenged them and I have no more to say except that I should like to hear a statement from the Taoiseach that there will be no mitigation of or interference with these minimum penalties which we welcome.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DenisHealy" hpid="Donnchadh O hEaluighthe Donnchadh O hEaluighthe">
      <NameTxt>Donnchadh O hEaluighthe</NameTxt>
      <P>Ba mhaith liom cupla focal a radh ar an gceist seo.  I did not intend to speak on this question, but, owing to an interjection of mine when Senator Cummins was speaking that he would have plenty of time at the local elections to deal with Emergency Order No. 83, I noticed that when Senator Foran was speaking he looked over to see what effect it had on me.  I represent a working class district in the City of Dublin.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamCummins" hpid="Mr. Cummins Mr. Cummins">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cummins</NameTxt>
      <P>That is propaganda. Is it in order?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="2073" />
    <Speaker pid="DenisHealy" hpid="Mr. Healy Mr. Healy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Healy</NameTxt>
      <P>Perfectly in order.  The Senator's speech was propaganda, too.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DesmondFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Fitzgerald Mr. Fitzgerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Fitzgerald</NameTxt>
      <P>It is for the Chair to say what is in order.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DenisHealy" hpid="Mr. Healy Mr. Healy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Healy</NameTxt>
      <P>If Senator Cummins has any remarks to make on that matter I will welcome him in my area during the coming election.  Order No. 83 is meant, as I understand it...</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFGibbons" hpid="Cathaoirleach Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I cannot allow any further reference to Order No. 83 on the Fifth Stage.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DenisHealy" hpid="Mr. Healy Mr. Healy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Healy</NameTxt>
      <P>If I am not allowed to answer it here I will answer it on the public platform.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesTunney" hpid="Mr. Tunney Mr. Tunney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Tunney</NameTxt>
      <P>I want to reply to Senator Johnston's remark that there was not full justification for these penalties.  I hold that, if the Government are to retain the confidence of the right-minded people in this country, they will have to take some steps in view of the difference in the penalties inflicted for these offences during the last six months.  When you see a person who, either through ignorance or poverty, charges a penny extra for a packet of cigarettes fined £50, when you see two girls who take the loan of bicycles without any intention of stealing them getting two months in jail, when you see some young fellow who happens to be a member of an illegal organisation getting a sentence of seven years, and then see some man in County Meath, who has 200 acres of land, not doing his duty in providing food for the people, while people in Dublin were standing in queues for bread, it is time that the Government took action.  I hope that there will be no discrimination in connection with these penalties and that everybody will be treated alike.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonDeValera" hpid="The Taoiseach Eamon de Valera">
      <NameTxt>The Taoiseach</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not think it is necessary for me to say anything in addition to what I have said already. But, with regard to the question asked about discrimination, of course, the Orders will be universal.  The cases will be tried in the courts and, if it is found that an offence has been committed, the minimum fine will be imposed. <Col N="2074" /> Then comes the question, which is a difficult one: are you to have no appeal or will there be the usual appeal in very difficult cases, an appeal to the Minister for Justice?  I am sure the Minister would like, from his point of view, that there should be no appeal at all.  If we did that, there would be the difficulty that occasionally there might be&mdash;and it would be only occasionally&mdash;a case in which there was some particular set of circumstances in which it was certain that if the Legislature itself was sitting in judgment it would say that a fine should not be imposed.  It will only be done in special cases like that.  The point is that the Minister for Justice in that case will be acting more or less in a judicial capacity. I think we have confidence&mdash;I am certain anyhow and I think members of the House are certain&mdash;that in any case that he may deal with he will not allow himself to be influenced by any consideration except considerations of justice.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>Ordered that the Bill be returned to the Dáil.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Pigs and Bacon" RHead="Commission&mdash;Motion (Resumed)">
    <Title>Pigs and Bacon Commission&mdash;Motion (Resumed).</Title>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. Johnston Mr. Johnston">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Johnston</NameTxt>
      <P>Prior to the adjournment of this debate, I was dealing with the question of the difficulties of farmers and I was pointing out that the commission should fix two or three months in advance the price for pigs, seeing that the price of cereals is fixed. It is not a common practice but it has happened on one or two occasions in County Monaghan that there were surplus pigs and the local curers were not allowed to take those pigs because their quotas had been exhausted.  The Pigs and Bacon Commission advertised that pigs would be taken by a representative of their commission.  Two men came down from Dublin at the expense, as I am informed, of the taxpayers, and there were nine or ten pigs available for them which they handed over to the local factories to have converted into bacon which would be given to the commission for distribution and disposal.  I want to press upon the <Col N="2075" /> Minister that one of the difficulties is caused by the fact that curers are not allowed to produce more bacon.  They are confined to the production of a certain amount of bacon although the number of pigs in the particular area might supply much more than the factory would be allowed to take.  It occurred some time ago, not recently, but it may occur again, that where the quotas of the local curers were filled, pigs were taken from Monaghan or Castleblayney and sent to Claremorris and to bacon factories in the south, with the result that the pigs depreciated and were injured and marked, some of them by whip marks, in that long journey.  There was a consequent cut in the price of the bacon.  I do not know if that is the case now but that did happen.  It would be much better if the local curers were allowed to take the pigs, produce the bacon and hand the bacon over to the commission for distribution, where necessary.  I think it would be better where there is a surplus of pigs in County Monaghan, to distribute bacon from County Monaghan rather than to distribute pigs from County Monaghan.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I have dealt with the point that the difficulty is not so much the fixed price as the insecurity of the position. One of the things that I would recommend for dealing with this question of the production of pigs and bacon and the improvement of the production is that a price should be fixed by the commission, say, three or four months in advance so that the farmer would know what he was going to get for his pigs.  If he reared pigs or if he bought bonhams he would know that three months hence he would get a certain price for them.  I would also recommend that a maximum price for bacon should be fixed that would be related to the fixed price for pigs, dead weight. It might be argued that if prices were fixed for pigs three or four months in advance and if, after that time, there was an increased price for the next three or four months, some people might buy pigs at the cheaper rate and hold them over for the purpose of selling them at the higher rate.  I think <Col N="2076" /> that would be overcome by fixing quotas, and by fixing the price of bacon, in the same way that the price of flour, sugar, and other commodities have been fixed at the present time.</P>
    <P>There is one other matter about which there has been a good deal of discussion in Monaghan.  It was taken up at a county council meeting and, as a result of discussion there, a resolution was passed asking the chairman of the Pigs and Bacon Commission to come to Monaghan to discuss the position there.  He did not give any reasons but he refused to come.  If he had come he would have been in a position to hear directly from the producers what the position was.</P>
    <P>Senator Crosbie pointed out the number of pigs produced in Cork and said it was the greatest pig-producing county in Eire some time ago, producing 2,000 or 3,000 a week, but that the supply of pigs has been reduced to a very small number.  I do not know what Senator Crosbie's point was&mdash; whether it was that surpluses of pigs in other counties should be sent to Cork for conversion into bacon.  I do not know what he had in mind but certainly, under present conditions, I would not recommend that pigs should be transported long journeys, particularly live weights, to any particular factory.  I would remind Deputy Crosbie that in County Cork they have a beet factory and the opportunity of growing beet as a cash crop.  They have land suitable for growing wheat for which there is a guaranteed price. There is very little land in County Monaghan suitable for growing wheat and one of the things they rely on there to make money to meet their demands is the production of pigs.  From time immemorial it has been a pig-producing country.  Small farmers and cottiers there produce two, three, four or six pigs.  These are the people for whom I am speaking.</P>
    <P>I think it is not beyond the powers of the Minister to fix prices for winter and summer.  I think that was contemplated some time ago.  If the prices were a little higher in summer and lower in winter it would be an encouragement to the farmers to produce <Col N="2077" /> more in the summer time and not have surpluses at another time.  At the moment, of course, there are not many surpluses.</P>
    <P>I do not agree with Senator Crosbie's motion that the Pigs and Bacon Commission should be suspended during the period of the emergency because that would mean that we would revert back to the system that obtained before this commission was set up.  Some of the bigger factories who can afford to pay high prices will be giving bonuses and paying high prices, while other factories that are not in such a strong position will be able to give only a price that will enable them to produce the bacon.</P>
    <Speaker pid="FrederickHawkins" hpid="Mr. Hawkins Mr. Hawkins">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hawkins</NameTxt>
      <P>I propose to address myself to the motion, and not wander as far as some other speakers have wandered.  The motion sets out that the Seanad is of opinion that the operations of the Pigs and Bacon Commission should be suspended during the period of the emergency.  First of all, we must ask ourselves what are the operations of the Pigs and Bacon Commission. So far as I understand them, they are the regulation of prices and the regulation of quotas of pigs to the different factories.  If we adopt this motion; and if the Government put it into operation, I foresee a peculiar position arising.  This morning we had a debate on the black market.  I foresee the driving of the bacon industry into the black market if we allow these people with the greatest amount of capital behind them to pay whatever price they wish for pigs&mdash;in Senator McEllin's words, if we allow the fittest to survive.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Knowing human nature as we do, if an individual or a group of individuals forming a company pay a particular price for an article, it is quite natural that they will expect a profit on their investment.  If the commission fix a maximum price for bacon, and the factories are allowed to pay for the pig, the raw material, a price higher than would pay them to sell the bacon at the controlled price, then it is obvious you will drive the bacon into the black market.  From what we have heard sometimes in the other House, the <Col N="2078" /> people controlling the bacon industry are not so patriotic that they are going to lose thousands in order that people may have a rasher and egg for breakfast.</P>
    <P>It is only natural to expect that if you allow them to purchase pigs at any price, the factories in a position to pay the highest price will get all the animals and you will then create the position that the small factories, probably long-established, and with the capital subscribed by the small farmers from the surrounding districts, will not be able to compete in the buying of pigs.  If they attempt to purchase pigs at the prices offered by the larger factories, they will find that they cannot continue to do so over any lengthy period, with the result that when the emergency is over, you will have in this country only the larger factories functioning and the smaller factories completely driven out of business. That would be bad from the point of view of employment and also from the consumer's point of view.  It is the duty of the commission to allocate whatever pigs are available in equal proportion to each factory.  If we adopt the suggestion that the existing arrangement should be scrapped, and we allow the bacon factories, which are prepared to spend thousands, to capture the trade, we will simply drive other people out of the business.  If the larger factories are prepared to spend their capital with the prospect that when the emergency is over smaller factories will not be in the business, then the consumer will pay in the long run for the action we are asked to take to-day.</P>
    <P>The suspension of the Pigs and Bacon Commission is not going to have anything to do with the production of pigs.  The only thing that will have an effect on the production of pigs is the quantity of food available for feeding to the pigs.  It is true that in a number of instances people have grievances of the type referred to by Senator Johnston.  There are people who take their pigs to the factory only to find that the quota is filled and then they have to take the pigs home again. I think if the Minister gave an undertaking that some of the grievances <Col N="2079" /> mentioned by Senator Johnston and other Senators would be considered, it would bring about a general feeling of satisfaction.  Sometimes farmers are obliged to keep their pigs for a longer time than they originally intended, and in that way the animals move out of a particular grade and the price would be affected in consequence.  However, these are small points and I believe they could be rectified by the commission.</P>
    <P>It would be a good thing if it could be arranged that the grading system, if not abolished, might at least be modified during the emergency.  I would not be in favour of the total abolition of the commission during the emergency.  We have seen in the papers where some managers of factories have been brought before the courts for paying prices for pigs higher than those allowed by the commission. You cannot expect these people to keep selling bacon at the price fixed by the commission if they have to pay a high price to get the pigs.  These people are not that patriotic.  Some of them may be patriotic enough, but they are not going to lose thousands in order that we may have rashers and eggs for breakfast.</P>
    <P>If you were to allow that policy to operate you may not close all the very small factories, but you will close a number of factories and when normal times return you will have one or two of the big combines, that were prepared to spend money during the period of the emergency, controlling the whole industry.  That would be a very bad position, not alone for the consumer but, as will be admitted, for the producer of pigs.  Indeed, in my opinion the position would be worse for the producer of pigs.  The big combines would have considerable influence over the price of pigs because they would be the only people in the business and they would have full control of the situation.</P>
    <Speaker pid="McGillycuddyReeks" hpid="The McGillycuddy The McGillycuddy">
      <NameTxt>The McGillycuddy</NameTxt>
      <P>This motion is a rather timely one.  If the present situation in regard to pigs is allowed to continue, the stage may <Col N="2080" /> soon be reached when the commission will have no pigs for which to fix either a minimum or a maximum price.  They will not even be able to fix a minimum penalty for anybody who contravenes their regulations.  I think this is probably one of the most important problems confronting the country to-day.  It is bound up, first of all, with the provision of farmyard manure.  We cannot get artificial manure of any kind.  Manure is absolutely essential if we are to meet our food requirements and if we are to get that further margin of tillage which we so urgently require.  It is also bound up with the post-war plan which we were discussing yesterday and which ought to be taken in hands at once.</P>
      <P>I listened to some of the other Senators and I heard Senator McEllin say that matters were under consideration. I felt that we were rather fiddling while Rome was burning very hard and that we were fiddling while we were bleeding ourselves.  Senator Johnston gave us an excellent speech, but one had the impression that he was talking as if things were normal and as if our pig population was not dropping by 500,000, and bacon factories closing all over the place.  There are some of which I have just heard which have dropped from 4,000 pigs a week to 500, and in view of this it seems to me to be very unreal.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The last thing with which the motion is bound up is the restoration of our export trade, and I propose to come to that again.  The Minister said, quite rightly, yesterday that it was a matter of food to feed these animals, and he hoped that if barley production this year was greater, we would be in a position to feed an additional number of pigs, but over and above that, anybody who has anything to do with feeding pigs knows that if you want to feed a pig quickly and economically, you must have wheat offals with the barley and that then you will get your bacon quickly and in proper shape.  It seems to me, therefore, that the restoration of this trade is the biggest argument for increased tillage at the moment which can possibly be <Col N="2081" /> imagined.  It is not only an argument for increased tillage, but an argument for the supply of wheat offals from that tillage at a reasonable price, and finally for some export subsidy as well.</P>
    <P>At this time, I do feel that we ought to take advantage of the world situation, not only on account of the present profits, but in order to establish something for the future, because if the war were to stop to-morrow, or next year; shipping will not be available for a number of years for the carrying of food and other commodities from the places in which they are produced for the feeding of Great Britain and Europe.  I do not know whether the House realises that hundreds of thousands of Americans are coming to the North of Ireland and filling up the whole of England.  Those troops are not only bringing their own equipment, but are importing every scrap of food, at a time when one has only to look at the papers to realise the great difficulties they have in the matter of convoying, even on their own side in the Caribbean Sea, and how important every yard of shipping space is to them.  It seems to me incredible that, instead of letting our pig trade die, we cannot make some super effort to till more land and to say to these people: &ldquo;We will save your shipping space up to such an amount&mdash;up to 500,000 pigs or 1,000,000 pigs, if you want them&rdquo;, and try to get some money out of it.  If we can make that effort, we establish ourselves to a very great extent for the years immediately after the war, instead of being in the position, as I have said again and again, of having nothing whatever to bargain with after the war, for the reason that we have nothing with which to pay for the things we want. Even if we cannot supply the whole of their requirements, we can make a deal with them to supply a certain proportion, at any rate.</P>
    <P>The Minister said yesterday, and his statement was headlined in all the papers, that it was going to be extremely difficult to get any more tillage because, notwithstanding the increase in tillage in the last few years, we were still carrying the same <Col N="2082" /> number of stock.  I accept that from him&mdash;he has his own figures&mdash;but I want to point out that this particular business does not affect that issue at all, because the pigs are not roaming over the country.  They are confined, and they are putting their manure in the place in which you want it, whereas the store cattle are roaming over the land, over the ranches which I still maintain are not entirely ploughed as they ought to be, and are not putting their manure where you want it.  For that reason, I suggest that you will collect more manure to make up the diminution in the amount of root crops and to increase the amount of cereals which we require for this job, and you are quite justified in going to it to see what you can do to deal with this problem.  The question of price at the moment is, I think, completely subsidiary to getting the number of pigs and giving the commission something to deal with.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PadraicOMaille" hpid="Padraic O Máille Padraic O Máille">
      <NameTxt>Padraic O Máille</NameTxt>
      <P>Ní shilim go gcuirfeadh an tairisgint atá os ár gcomhair aon fheabhas ar an scéal, ach go ndéanfadh sé an cheist níos measa. Is fíor go bhfuil ganntann beatha muc ar fúd na tíre, ach tá fáth eile le laghdú uimhir na muc.  Le cúpla mí anuas, bhí cuid mhaith shean-fhataí sa tír agus bhí fairsingeacht bhainne ag na daoine ina cheann sin, ach ba dheachair bainbh fháil le ceannacht ar aontaí agus ag margaidhthe.  Deirtear liom gurabé an chúis a bhí leis sin ná go raibh go leor de na bainbh a bhí dá ndíol í Chonndae Lughbhaidh, Chonndae Muineacháin agus Chonndae Cabháin ag dul treasna na Teorann, agus má's fíor é sin, ní h-aon iongnadh é go bhfuil laghdú mór ar an méid muc atá sa tír.  Is docha go bhfuil baramhal ag an Aire go bhfuil an obair seo ar bun agus ba ceart go gcuirfidh sé cosc ar imtheacht na muc go dtí na Sé Conndaethe.  In aimsir mar seo, má cuirtear críoc leis an Coimisiún seo, ní bheidh tada le cur in a áit.  Is furust go leor rud a thairingt anuas, ach níl sé cho-réidh rud do chur in a ionadh.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DanielCorkery" hpid="Mr. Corkery Mr. Corkery">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Corkery</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator The McGillycuddy thinks we should keep on supplying <Col N="2083" /> bacon to the English market.  I saw the prices quoted in Dublin recently and they are from 10/- to £1 more than the prices offered to us for bacon by England, which disposes of the question of increasing our pig production for sale to an outside market. We cannot supply the Americans or the English at the prices they are offering. Pig production has gone down and the principal reason is lack of feeding stuffs.  Senator Johnston does not seem to understand the situation in Cork County.  There is a lot of land there which will grow wheat and beet, but there is a lot of land in West Cork on which it is very difficult to grow any crop, and pig feeding has been the principal industry there for years. There are still a good many pigs in Cork, but, instead of these pigs being fed and fattened there, they are being sent up the country and I am sure that some of them are going as far as Senator Johnston's county.</P>
      <P>I meet buyers from Cavan and the West of Ireland at every fair in the South.  They have been coming there for years and they are still paying a good price for bonhams and store pigs. Pigs between ten and 12 weeks old are fetching anything from £2 to £3.  The number of fat pigs offered for sale at Cork Fair for some time back has been very small.  We have not feeding stuffs in Cork.  We cannot finish the pigs and, unfortunately, the Cork buyers have to go to the West of Ireland to pay a good price for pigs.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I do not think that the abolition of the Pigs and Bacon Commission will remedy the situation.  I agree with everything that Senator Crosbie has stated, but I do not think that the abolition of the commission would be of any help.  We want, if possible, to increase the number of pigs in the country, if we can feed them, but we do not want to increase the number and feed them with wheat or any other form of human food which is required for the people.  Unfortunately, there was a considerable amount of that done during the past 12 months, more than people have any idea of, in some districts.  If we could, by any legitimate <Col N="2084" /> means, increase the price of pigs and at the same time keep the price of bacon at a level which would keep it within the reach of the ordinary person, I think we should do so.  If we could fix a maximum price for bacon, so as to ensure that the bacon is not going to go on the black market, and let the curers and others who want pigs buy them as best they can, I think it would have the effect of increasing pig production.  Pigs were sold at all fairs in the south up to about a month ago, when the weather got very fine. They have been sold to ordinary farmers and workers, who bought them for the purpose of killing and curing them to satisfy their own needs.  Very few pigs have been sold to curers for the past six months at any of the fairs in the south.  Sometimes those buying for the curers sold pigs which they had purchased back again to local farmers who were prepared to go the price for them.  I do not think there is anything wrong in that.  If a man prefers to buy a pig for killing, and to do his own curing at home rather than to go into the shop and buy factory-cured bacon, I think he should be permitted to do so.</P>
    <P>I think that prices should be regulated in the way I suggested, that the price of bacon should be fixed at certain rates not higher than those at present prevailing and that the price of pigs should be left open.  Senator Hawkins has stated there is a possibility that some small curers would be put out of business in that way but I doubt it.  I think they would be well able to hold their own and if there is a quota system, they are bound to get some anyway.  I think that is the only way by which the number of pigs can be increased.  It will also be necessary to increase tillage because if we are going to feed more pigs we must have some feeding stuffs and we are not going to get any Indian meal while the emergency lasts or perhaps for a considerable time after it has passed.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JohnCounihan" hpid="Mr. Counihan Mr. Counihan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Counihan</NameTxt>
      <P>In discussing this matter at a recent meeting of this House, I appealed to the Minister to suspend the operations of the Pigs and Bacon Commission for the period of <Col N="2085" /> the emergency.  I should like now to renew that appeal and to ask him seriously to consider the proposal set out in the motion.  I pointed out on that occasion that the price fixed by the Pigs and Bacon Commission was not an economic price and that if they insisted on pigs being delivered at such a price to the factories, the producers would go out of production and we would have no pigs.  The Minister did not seem to take much notice of that statement.  I suggest to the Minister now that if he would control the price of bacon and allow a free market for the sale of pigs, that will not do any injury to the consumer.  The price of bacon will be controlled.  I presume the Minister will control it at a figure which would be an economic price and which would leave a margin for the bacon merchants or bacon curers.  At the present time, we have practically no pigs in the country. Bacon factories are prepared to pay a good price for pigs and if the price they pay is not an economic price from their point of view, that is their look-out.  The Minister should not be so concerned if the farmer gets a good price for his pigs.  The Bacon Commission price at the present time is not an economic price and that is one of the reasons why we have not pigs at the present time.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I got somebody recently to send me the figures in regard to the killings in the bacon factories in Cork for the week ending July 18th.  In Denny's of Cork, where the normal killings were 1,200 pigs a week, the killings for that week numbered only 36.  In Lunham's the normal killings per week were 1,600 and for the week ending July 16th they were only 90.  In the Farmers' Union factory the normal killings per week were 600 and for that week they were only 12.  In Murphy's factory the normal killings were 400 and for that week they were only 12.  People talk about maintaining the Pigs and Bacon Commission to enforce all these regulations and this grading but what grading could be done in the Cork factories during that week ending 18th July when little more than 100 pigs were dealt with, when normally they dealt with 4,000 or 5,000 in the week?  This is a matter which the Minister should <Col N="2086" /> consider very seriously.  We are not asking that the Pigs and Bacon Commission should be abolished; all the resolution asks is that its operations should be suspended for the period of the emergency.</P>
    <P>In the course of the proceedings against the bacon curers in Cork, Mr. Lunham said that every curer in the Twenty-Six Counties had given over the fixed price at certain periods.  He was asked to supply the names of the particular curers, and he refused, quite naturally.  If it is a fact that every bacon curer in the country was giving more than the controlled price, why should they not be allowed to do so?  If they were not charging a higher price to the consumer for the bacon, I cannot see that their action constituted any serious crime.  The Minister does not agree with me.  He possibly might say that they were poaching; that they were going into other districts into which they had no right to go.  I cannot see any grounds for that argument.  It costs a good deal at the present moment to produce pigs, and the attitude of the Pigs and Bacon Commission is taking money out of the farmers' pockets and putting them in such a position that they are going out of pig production altogether; I know hundreds of cases in which they have sold their sows. If that is to continue, there will be very little use for the Pigs and Bacon Commission for a considerable time.</P>
    <P>On the last occasion on which we were discussing this matter, I mentioned the price at which I sold a pig in the Dublin market on a particular day; if I had sent that pig to the factory I would have got £9 less.  A fortnight ago I sold some pigs in Dublin, and got over 140/- per cwt. deadweight for them, which amounted to about £9 15s. per pig.  Last Wednesday, in the Dublin market I had some pigs of practically the same weight, and the price was £6 10s.  That is a terrible difference.  There is no regulated price at the fairs or in the market.  The pigs are sold at the highest price that can be obtained, and it is only at the factory that the price is controlled.  If the bacon curers close down, we will be left to the mercy of <Col N="2087" /> the pork butchers and a few others, and it is clear that factories with big overhead expenses cannot carry on at the present rate of killings.  If they pay higher prices they will be prosecuted, and, perhaps, under the Bill we have just passed, put into jail.</P>
    <P>Previous speakers have said that a good deal of our present problem with regard to the reduction in pig production is due to the scarcity of feeding stuffs.  I agree that that may have a certain amount to do with it, but price is a bigger factor than anything else. Senator McGee, speaking here some time ago, thanked the Government for taking potatoes from the Cooley farmers for the alcohol factory at a price of £3 per ton, in addition to paying some portion of the expenses; I think the whole lot was about £4 per ton for old potatoes.  Would it not be a much wiser and better policy if the Department of Agriculture sent those potatoes to the people who are engaged in pig production?  We were recently informed by the Department that four tons of potatoes are equal in feeding value to a ton of maize; with maize at £7 a ton, potatoes would then be worth about £2 a ton.  Any big factory would give £25 a ton for maize at the moment, and, at that proportion, potatoes should be worth about £6 or £7 a ton.  Nobody need tell the farmers of this country the value of potatoes as a food for pigs.  Of course, there ought to be a balanced ration, but for centuries potatoes have been the principal portion of the ration for fattening pigs here.  We have always been able to claim that we produce the best bacon, and I hope we will continue to do so, but I am afraid the attitude of the Pigs and Bacon Commission will result in our having none to export.</P>
    <P>I would suggest to the Minister that, by propaganda, he should try to induce the people to go in for making potato ensilage.  I make some of it myself, and it is a simple process enough if you have the necessary appliances. In Germany, they have those cooking and cleaning engines going around, <Col N="2088" /> and they can be hired in the same way as the farmers here might hire a threshing engine.  Without the necessary appliances, the making of potato ensilage is a laborious job which the farmers will not undertake.  Instead of sending potatoes to the alcohol factories it would be of importance to arrange that anybody who wanted to make a quantity of potato ensilage could hire a set to do the work, just as farmers can hire a threshing mill. I appeal to the Minister, seeing that the number of pigs is limited, to abolish the operations of the Pigs and Bacon Commission, to let there be free trade for live pigs, and to control the price of bacon.  That would meet the situation.  Business would be much better by not continuing the operations of the Pigs and Bacon Commission. They have got the feelings of most of the people concerned against them and there is going to be no improvement until the emergency is over.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Minister for Agriculture (Dr. Ryan) James Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Agriculture (Dr. Ryan)</NameTxt>
      <P>A number of points were raised in the debate, but I feel that Senators are not too anxious for a very long reply so I will just run through the points that were raised.  Senator Crosbie, when introducing the motion, and other Senators, seemed anxious more or less to have a discussion on some points but I do not think they made very much of a case for the abolition of the commission. As a matter of fact Senators should realise that in order to abolish the commission we would have to repeal all the legislation that was passed.  It is all dependent on that to carry out the various regulations.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnCounihan" hpid="Mr. Counihan Mr. Counihan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Counihan</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator Crosbie advocated the suspension of the commission, not its abolition.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>The same thing would apply.  It cannot be suspended unless the Act is suspended.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnCounihan" hpid="Mr. Counihan Mr. Counihan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Counihan</NameTxt>
      <P>Could the Minister not make an Order under the Emergency Powers?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="2089" />
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes, but no part of the Act could remain.  Everything in it is dependent on the commission.  Such things as quotas to factories would also have to go.  I was going to deal with the point that Senator Crosbie made about the factories in Cork.  In my opinion the only way that these factories can get an equitable distribution of the pigs available is through the commission.  The fact is that their request is not that the Pigs and Bacon Commission should be suspended, but that it should go further into the business and take over all pigs to see that they were equitably distributed. That matter is under consideration. We had figures quoted by Senators regarding the operation of individual factories.  Senator Counihan corroborated some figures given by Senator Crosbie with regard to Cork.  It would appear that some of the big factories that were dealing with 1,200 or 1,600 pigs a week are now dealing with only 100.  The figures should not be as low as that.  If every factory got a fair share, they should be getting one-third of the normal quota.  The normal output of pigs pre-war and in 1940 was about 1,000,000 a year to the factories. The present weekly supply to the factories is about 6,000.  It is not much under one-third.  If the Cork factory got 1,500 weekly previously, they should now be getting 500.  Whatever pigs are there should be equitably distributed amongst these factories in order to keep the employees working.  I have agreed, at the request of some curers, to ask the Pigs and Bacon Commission if they are prepared to undertake the task of the nominal purchase of pigs, and then distribute them equally between the factories.  There are objections to that.  Those who listened to Senator Johnston's speech will know the objections.  They are obvious.  As Senator Johnston stated, if there were more pigs presented than the equitable fraction of the total, say to a factory in Monaghan, he would seriously object to the transfer of these pigs to Cork. There are also transport objections. It may not be necessary, actually, in working the scheme put up, to transfer pigs from Monaghan to Cork.  It may be necessary to transfer pigs from <Col N="2090" /> Monaghan to Dundalk, and perhaps pigs from this side of Dundalk to Dublin, and pigs in the south to Roscrea, or from Roscrea to Cork. There may be some attempt at zoning supplies to factories.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I cannot say further now because the matter is being considered by the Pigs and Bacon Commission.  If they can find a solution on the lines suggested by the factories we can, at least, do something then to meet the wishes of the factories.  The motion suggests that in view of the reduction of the pig population the Seanad should ask that the operations of the Pigs and Bacon Commission be suspended.  What is the diminution in the number of pigs due to?  Many Senators expressed the opinion that it was entirely due to the shortage of feeding stuffs, others that it was due to the prices offered for fat pigs.  I am inclined to think that it is almost entirely due to the scarcity of feeding stuffs.  I admit that if a very much bigger price was offered for pigs, we might get more pigs, but as a result we might have greater evils.  I do not see how these pigs could have been fed.  Every bit of feeding stuff has been used up.  No trader, no miller, and I believe very few farmers have feeding stuffs.  If there had been more pigs to be fed it is fairly obvious that they would have been fed on cereal food that was required for humans. More pigs would mean less food for human beings.  That would be a very much bigger evil than the evil we have to face of having a scarcity of bacon. Senator Crosbie says that we ought to secure more feeding stuffs for pigs. That is certainly a good suggestion. As far as we could we have tried to secure more cereals, and we have, to a certain extent, by compulsion, induced owners to till at least 25 per cent. of their land.  We have gone in that direction, and have made appeals in every way possible, by advertisement, by Ministers and officials of my Department, and in every way urged farmers to do more than the quota required.  We have got very good results.  Of course we have not got sufficient cereals growing to supply the <Col N="2091" /> human population with all the bread necessary and, at the same time, maintain all the animals we had when the war commenced.</P>
    <P>I should like Senators to keep in mind a few points regarding the cause of the decline in the number of pigs. To realise it Senators must go back and study the trend of prices of fat pigs since the war commenced, and also the number of pigs offered for sale during that period.  They will be inclined then to come to the conclusion that the big factor was the supply of feeding stuffs.  From the beginning of 1940, down to February, 1942, or for over two years, there were frequent increases in the price of fat pigs.  There was never any decrease.  There were about seven changes in prices, all upwards during that period.  At the same time, all through that two years, the number of sows sent to service every month was less than the corresponding numbers in previous years.  It is obvious that the farmer who had his sow and was making up his mind whether or not he should go on breeding pigs was not influenced by the price of fat pigs.  Fat pigs were going up all the time in price and the number of sows going to service was getting smaller.  It is only a coincidence, but it is very strange, that the first time the commission lowered the price of fat pigs was in February and that the first time we had an increase in sow services was the following month&mdash; March.  I do not want Senators to take me as arguing that it took a decline in the price of fat pigs to get farmers to send sows to service but it just happened.</P>
    <P>It is argued by many people that that fall in the price of fat pigs in February had a depressing effect.  It had not.  More sows were sent to service then, and, since then, more sows have been sent every month.  There has been a turn of the tide.  In the months of March, April and May&mdash;I have not yet the figures for June&mdash;the number of sows sent to service has been greater than during the corresponding months of the previous year. <Col N="2092" /> That is a turn of the tide after two years, so that there is some hope that the number of pigs will increase.  If Senators ask me why farmers took that action in March, I answer by saying that they, probably, saw on their own farms and around them that there was an increase in tillage and the prospect of more feeding in the winter months. In the second place, they, probably, recognised that there was a fall in the number of pigs and that it was a good time to go back into production.  They have done so.  I think that the man with the sow is influenced by two things&mdash;the price of small pigs and whether he can feed the sow or not. If he can feed the sow, he is inclined to keep her.  The fact that we had a big decline in the number of pigs in the two years of which I speak was entirely due to the want of feeding. Farmers thought that they could not go on rearing the sow and rearing the small pigs.  The price of small pigs was extremely good for the past two years to any man who was selling the small pigs and not fattening them.</P>
    <P>I come now to the man who bought small pigs to fatten them.  He paid a good price.  He would not have done so if he were losing on the fattening. If I were in the place of a farmer with a certain amount of feeding and if I thought that I would make very little by feeding from six to 12 pigs but that I would have the manure, I might feed them knowing that I would not have very much profit.  That was, probably, the position of those who were paying high prices for small pigs and who had a small amount of feeding on hands. However, we discussed that point here before.</P>
    <P>Senators will have to admit, at least, that the present position is not entirely due to price.  The continuous rise in prices had not the effect of increasing pig production.  As soon as prices went down, pig production increased.  I should be prepared to argue that, even at present, fat pigs are paying, whatever certain Senators may think.  I know very well that if I had to go to a shop and buy meal to feed the pigs they would not pay, but I would not get more than 1 cwt. or 2 cwts. of meal. <Col N="2093" /> I tried and I know.  One cwt. or 2 cwts. of meal is all right to help out with whatever waste potatoes are available even if you pay £1 or 22/- a cwt. for the meal.  But there is no use in talking about the cost of feeding pigs on purchased meals, because you cannot get them.  What you must take into account are surplus potatoes.</P>
    <P>The sort of ration that the farmer is giving to his pig to make a cwt. of pork is: 2 cwts. of oats, 8 or 10 cwts. of potatoes, and a 1/2 cwt. of meat-meal, if he has not skim-milk.  It is a ration of that kind we should have in mind when we consider whether the present price of pigs is remunerative or not. Taking a ration of that kind, I think the present price of pigs is good.  If any Senator cares to work the matter out, he will find that he can allow himself 2/- a stone for his oats, 4/- or 5/- a cwt. for his potatoes&mdash;small and big &mdash;which is very good, and 24/- a cwt. for the meat-meal which he buys. Feeding that ration to the pigs, he will have a profit&mdash;though not a big profit &mdash;as well as having the manure which has been so highly rated in this debate. In these circumstances, I do not think that any Senators can hold that pig-rearing is not remunerative at present prices.</P>
    <P>It is another question whether prices should be increased or not.  Sometimes, because of a certain psychology amongst farmers, it is advisable, though the price be a paying one, to raise it as an indication that pigs will be better and that it is a good time to go back into them.  From that point of view, I am quite willing to ask the Pigs and Bacon Commission to reconsider the present prices.  But I am more inclined to ask the commission to reconsider the present gradings, because I think that there is a good deal in what Senators have said with regard to the grading of pigs.  We must remember what we had in mind when passing the first Pigs and Bacon Act. We had in mind that we had a surplus for export, and some of us may have had the hope of increasing that surplus and making a greater profit than we were making at the time on the foreign market.  We saw, however, that <Col N="2094" /> we were up against a very keen competitor on the foreign market.  We were told&mdash;with a great deal of truth &mdash;that that competitor had got her position on the British market by putting there the bacon the British consumer wanted&mdash;uniform size, uniform weight, and uniform in the amount of fat and lean.</P>
    <P>When a retail merchant in England went to a wholesaler and asked for a side of Danish bacon, he knew exactly what he would get.  If he asked for a side of Irish bacon, he would get good bacon, undoubtedly.  We held here&mdash; and I think rightly&mdash;that it was the best bacon to be got, but the retailer was not sure whether he would get a side or 56 lbs. or 66 lbs. or whether it would have a great deal of fat or not so much fat.  We were told that we could not compete very much longer on the English market unless we put a uniform side on the English market, as the Danes have done before us.  We set out in that legislation to try to get some uniformity.  We had been breeding a very good type of pig here for some years, but that was not enough; we had to induce the farmer to market his pig at a proper weight and we had to offer him a price to feed his pig properly, so that there would be the correct proportion of lean and fat on the side.  All these regulations, which were made possible under the Pigs and Bacon Act, 1933, were designed to accomplish that.</P>
    <P>I mention that in case Senators may forget and ask the object of all this legislation.  It may seem very silly at the moment, but I think Senators desire that we should get back on the foreign market as soon as the war is over and it would not be desirable to drop all our regulations now.  If we did that, and dropped the grading of bacon, we would leave the farmer to learn during the next year or two that he will get the very same price for a 20 stone pig per cwt. as he would get for a 12 stone pig per cwt.  Naturally, he would come to the conclusion that he would make very much more on the 20 stone one than on the 12 stone one, and when the war is over it would take <Col N="2095" /> some years to convince him that he was doing the wrong thing by keeping to the 20 stone pig and get him back on to the 12 stone one.  Therefore, I think we must keep the regulations, to some extent.  I do not say that there need be as many, or that they need be as severe, as they were pre-war.  In present circumstances, we should keep the grading, but perhaps the prices could be brought very much closer than if we were competing on the foreign market.  Further, if by any chance a farmer's pig goes from grade I to grade II he should not suffer as a consequence. These are things that should be considered, and I am quite prepared to ask the commission to consider these matters and see if they could not be brought into line with present conditions.</P>
    <P>With regard to manure, Senator Crosbie quoted from a very scientific article that when artificial manures&mdash; phosphates, I suppose&mdash;were £2 per ton, the manure from one pig the whole year round was worth about £4.  If a person is fattening pigs and has three batches of them, one batch every four months, each pig in his four months would be worth 30/- or, at the present price of manure, about £2.  There is no doubt that, when we were importing our foodstuffs, pigs were very valuable for the making of manure, but, under present circumstances, where the farmer is feeding his own grain and potatoes to animals, I do not think it makes very much difference, so far as manure is concerned, whether he feeds this grain and potatoes to pigs or cattle or any other animals.</P>
    <P>There may be something in the point mentioned by Senator The McGillycuddy, to have the manure from a house-fed animal, as you can distribute where and how you wish, rather than from a grass-fed animal. Assuming that we have a certain amount of grain, roots, and so on, for winter feeding, I do not think it makes any difference whether that is fed to pigs or bullocks.  It does make a difference whether it is fed to a mature <Col N="2096" /> animal or a young animal, but that applies to cattle as well as to pigs.</P>
    <P>Senator Parkinson spoke of the development of other sources of manure.  I will not deal with that now, as I dealt with it fully yesterday. Every source of native manure has been very fully examined by my Department and by other Departments, such as the Department of Industry and Commerce and the Department of Supplies, and the question also has been put to the Research Bureau.  We have not got very far yet.  Senator Parkinson mentioned in particular calcium cyanamide.  I read a report on that some time ago.  My recollection is that the machinery necessary to manufacture that fertiliser is just as elaborate&mdash;if not more so&mdash; and just as expensive and, under our circumstances, just as inaccessible, as the plant necessary for the manufacture of sulphate of ammonia from the air.  We have been told definitely that the manufacture of sulphate of ammonia from the air is impossible while this war lasts, as we cannot get the equipment.</P>
    <P>In dealing with pig production, we have three main points to consider.  In the first place, we have the present position, how best to deal with the pigs that we have, to get the best possible price for the farmers and give the consumers the best possible value in bacon, while at the same time maintaining whatever employment is possible in the bacon factories.  I think this point can be dealt with best by the equitable distribution of pigs between all the bacon factories.  The factories feel they have a grievance if they do not get a fair share and they are inclined to say that they cannot keep persons employed otherwise.  As I have said already, I am having that point examined and expect to make an announcement about it some time next week.  If possible we will see that pigs are equitably distributed and we will make an appeal to the factories to do the best they can with regard to continuing employment.</P>
    <P>The second point to be considered <Col N="2097" /> in this whole question is the possibility of increasing the supply of pigs to an extent sufficient to provide for our own needs in bacon.  For some time past, I have been very hesitant to advocate greater pig production, or to induce it by requesting the Pigs and Bacon Commission to reconsider the prices.  I feel that the commission will reconsider the prices whenever I make such a request to them.  I was first of all waiting to learn the acreage under grain.  We have got that now, and it has been published, so Senators will know what it is.  I may say that it is very satisfactory.  We get rather disquieting reports&mdash;not official reports&mdash;which come from various parts of the country, saying the oats crop is not so good, or the potato crop or barley crop is not so good.  I must say that the reports regarding the wheat crop are much better, on the whole, than the reports with regard to the others.  If we get less oats and barley than last year, even with the increased acreage, there is no possibility of feeding more pigs. If we get less potatoes, it also would militate against keeping more pigs.  I am very hesitant about it at present. If I felt that the increased acreage, even though the yield may be a little less, would mean more oats, barley and potatoes in the country, I would then request the Pigs and Bacon Commission to reconsider the price.  I think that at that stage, if I was fairly sure of that, I would request the Pigs and Bacon Commission to reconsider the prices, and even go so far as to say to them that I think the prospect of pig feeding will be a bit better this coming year than it was last year. We may, perhaps, be in a position within a week or two to get more reliable reports as to the yields of these crops, and, if so, we will be able to have this matter reconsidered.</P>
    <Speaker pid="McGillycuddyReeks" hpid="The McGillycuddy The McGillycuddy">
      <NameTxt>The McGillycuddy</NameTxt>
      <P>Did the Minister make the point that the more the price went up the fewer pigs there were?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>No.  I stressed the fact that I was not making that point.  I said that it was merely a coincidence <Col N="2098" /> and certainly did not follow.  Now, the third point is the long-term policy.  I need not deal with that, because we went into it very fully yesterday.  In any case, as I pointed out, we are setting up a committee to deal with the question of post-war planning in general, and, naturally, one of the questions that that committee will deal with is the question of pig production after the war.  Senator Johnston mentioned a point which has often been mentioned before, about pigs being offered to the factory and then having to be brought back, and then when they are offered again, two or three weeks later, they are of a higher grade or weight and are worth less money. These are two points that I think should be dealt with, and, as a matter of fact, the Pigs and Bacon Commission have the matter under consideration at the moment.  I may say that that matter of pigs not being taken by the factories has not been felt by any producer for some time back, and I hope that it will not be felt again, because I think that whatever plan we adopt we should certainly cover that point, and when a farmer brings a pig to a factory, the factory should take it from him, no matter what the factory may do with the pig afterwards.  The point about a pig being brought back and, as a result, going into a higher grade, is also being considered.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>In that connection, Senator Johnston gave an instance of pigs being taken in Monaghan on a particular day and then being sent to Cavan, and on the next day pigs were taken in Castleblayney and sent to Monaghan.  In trying to get an equitable distribution of pigs among the various factories, that may happen, and it is a very difficult thing to deal with because, if you are coming towards the end of the month, for instance, and Cavan still wants some pigs, while Monaghan has got what they are entitled to for the month, it is natural that some pigs should be shipped from Monaghan to Cavan, but it is then assumed that Cavan had got their full complement and there are still pigs there at the end of the month.  Well, if all the factories have got their complement, <Col N="2099" /> then the pigs should be sent to the nearest factory.  If this system of getting an equitable share of the available pigs for the different factories comes into operation, as I think it probably will, there will undoubtedly be some shifting around, because it cannot be avoided, but I quite admit that there should be as little shifting as possible and that the journeys should be as short as possible.</P>
    <P>Another question that is raised is why we do not fix a minimum price for pigs and let the factories pay what they like for them, and also fix an ex-factory price for bacon, over which the bacon manufacturer cannot go.  Now, that was one of the big issues when the Pigs and Bacon Act was first being passed through both Houses of the Oireachtas.  I think that if Senators could find the time to go back through the debates of that time, they would find that there was more discussion on that particular point than on any other point.  In addition, it was discussed very fully by a Select Committee of the Dáil, and I think it was agreed, generally, in both Houses, in the end, that the fixed price was more advisable than the minimum price.  It would take too long to go into all the points that were raised then, and, if I were to do so, it might deprive Senators of their week-end.  However, I shall mention a few of the points. Those who argued for the minimum price, of course, had the obvious arguments that are used here, to the effect that if the factory is prepared to pay more, why not let the farmer have it? That is the big argument so far as that side of it is concerned, and I think it is a sufficient argument, without trying to make any other, because I do not think any other argument could be made.  Against that, however, was argued: you are now going to regulate the whole business, and if you regulate at all, then it is unfair to tie the hands of the factories in some respects and to leave them free in other respects.  Now, the factories would be tied in some respects, but they would not be tied in the one instance of competing, one against another, by paying <Col N="2100" /> more for pigs, and the obvious result of that&mdash;it was quite obvious&mdash;was that certain factories would be driven to the wall, and it would eventually come to a question of the survival of the fittest.  How many of them would be affected in that way, it is hard to say. I imagine that the very small factories would be able to carry on.  These small factories that deal with only 100 pigs or so in the week get these pigs locally from the farmers, and are very much in touch with the local pig producers, and they would probably do all right. I think it is the medium factories, without capital or with very little capital, that would fail, whereas the big factories, with unlimited capital, undoubtedly would succeed.</P>
    <P>The second point was that all this legislation was brought in principally to deal with the very serious grievance that farmers had&mdash;a grievance amounting to dissatisfaction, and which was the very point mentioned by Senator Johnston in this debate to-day&mdash;that a farmer who sold his pig in a certain fair for 60/- live-weight, read in the paper when he went home that on the same day, in another fair only a few miles away, another farmer got 70/-, and naturally he could not understand&mdash;and he certainly would not agree&mdash;why he did not also get 70/- for his pig.  The result was that that farmer had a very big sense of grievance and was very dissatisfied.  In fact, it was held by members of both Houses at the time&mdash;and with a certain amount of conviction&mdash;that that was one of the big causes of the decline in pig production&mdash;that feeling of dissatisfaction: that you had to take what you got and that, if you were lucky enough to be in another fair on the same day, you would have done much better.  Now, you would have that if you allowed bacon curers to pay a minimum price.  The factories would pay that price in one place, where they had to pay it, and might not pay it in another, and the result would lead to great dissatisfaction, and whatever we might say about having this minimum price and allowing the curers to compete more, and trying to maintain an ex-factory price, I agree with Senator Hawkins that that ex-factory price for <Col N="2101" /> bacon could not be maintained, however much we might wish to do it.</P>
    <P>I was asked also, would it not be possible for the Pigs and Bacon Commission to fix prices for longer periods in advance.  Of course, that is a very big question.  Since they came into operation, seven or eight years ago, there have been very few reductions in price.  Nearly all the time, there have been increases, and there have been very few reductions in price, but I feel that they will have to retain that power, even though they do not exercise it very often, and especially the power to deal with grading, because various things might crop up, as we have experienced in the past, and also, of course, it would be against the spirit of the legislation on which the Pigs and Bacon Act was built: the idea of how to regulate the trade in future.  All these things are bound up very much, one with the other.</P>
    <P>I must say that I cannot agree with Senator The McGillycuddy that wheat offals are necessary for the proper fattening of pigs.  I think it should be possible to get a ration for the feeding of pigs without wheat offals, especially wheat for the smaller pigs.</P>
    <Speaker pid="McGillycuddyReeks" hpid="The McGillycuddy The McGillycuddy">
      <NameTxt>The McGillycuddy</NameTxt>
      <P>It is what the Irish farmer has been used to, and he is terribly conservative.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>Even though we have a very good wheat acreage this year&mdash; most reports go to show that the wheat yield will be very good&mdash;I do not think there is any hope that we will have wheat offals in the coming year. If I understood Senator The McGillycuddy properly, I think he made the point that we should be in a position to produce bacon on a large scale when the war is over, because the people of Europe will need bacon and other foodstuffs. I do not see how we can do that except on our own feeding stuffs, because if we had to import maize or other feeding stuffs at that stage to feed pigs it would be easier for us, or for any other country in Europe, to bring in a boat-load of bacon than four or five boat-loads of maize.  It comes <Col N="2102" /> back to the point that, unless we can produce our own feeding stuffs, we cannot do anything in regard to increasing bacon supplies.  To get some picture of increasing our own feeding stuffs, I may mention that we have, after a great deal of persuasion, appeals and so on got our barley acreage up from 100,000 acres to 160,000 acres.  That represents an increase of 60,000 acres in the last three or four years.  Even if we were to jump by another 100,000 acres, which would be phenomenal and more than we could expect, that would represent only 250,000 pigs.  The production of our own feeding stuffs is a very big matter.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Senator Counihan raised a point about sending potatoes to the alcohol factories, and thought we would have been better advised to send them for the feeding of pigs.  Personally, I would rather see them fed to pigs, but I felt, and I think probably a good many others felt, that any farmer who had pigs and wanted potatoes to feed to them could have got them himself. If any farmer had written to say that he wanted some of the potatoes that were being sent to the alcohol factories, I am quite sure we would have put him in touch with farmers who had offered us potatoes for the alcohol factories. We could have got the farmers who had the potatoes for sale to send them on to the farmers who had the pigs.  It could have been quite easily arranged.  Evidently that was not necessary, and farmers were able to get their own supplies.  On the point about the ensilage of potatoes, Senator Counihan thinks that we should have a machine to go around.  I am quite with Senator Counihan on that.  I have already mentioned in the Dáil that if these machines can be got by any group of farmers&mdash;co-operative societies, groups or even individuals-anxious to bring the machines around to the farmers' houses for cooking the potatoes for ensilage, I will be very willing to evolve some sort of a credit system for the purchase of such machines.  I think that would be my function in the matter and not to organise societies.  The farmers themselves can do that, but at least they could feel that the financial part of it would <Col N="2103" /> not be a deterrent if they could form societies and get the machinery necessary. I think that is all I have to say.</P>
    <Speaker pid="HelenaConcannon" hpid="Mrs. Concannnn Mrs. Concannnn">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Concannnn</NameTxt>
      <P>I intervene on behalf of the housekeepers in the country, first of all, to thank Senator Crosbie for initiating a very valuable discussion.  He did it in a most effective speech and elicited some of the most interesting and valuable speeches that I have heard in this House.  It seems to me that the House is at its best when discussing these subjects.  I was tremendously impressed by the speech of Senator Parkinson.  I also desire to take this opportunity, on behalf of the housekeepers, of thanking the Minister for the promise he has made to interest the Pigs and Bacon Commission in the question of providing for our own home needs in bacon. There is nothing that is of more interest to women with a small house to budget for than a good supply of bacon.  It is easily cooked in places where they have not good cooking facilities, and that is of great importance at this time when there is a shortage of fuel.  I want to stress one point which perhaps the Minister and the Pigs and Bacon Commission might be inclined to overlook, and that is to encourage the production of fat bacon. The people in the country want fat bacon.  It provides a good splutter on the pan, and combines very well with cabbage.  There used to be a demand for lean bacon for the fastidious English market, but that need not be such a potent factor in our planning now.  We need not be afraid to allow our pigs to grow fat.  The thing is to have them as fat as you please, and plenty of them, so that we may all get enough to eat.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesCrosbie" hpid="Mr. Crosbie Mr. Crosbie">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Crosbie</NameTxt>
      <P>I think that the discussion that has taken place on this motion has been a useful one.  As Senator McEllin and Senator The McGillycuddy have stated, the motion is a token one to this extent that I do not intend to push it to a division.  I have been challenged that I have not been sincere in desiring to suspend the activities of the Pigs and Bacon Commission. <Col N="2104" /> I will deal with that at the end.  The Minister stated that he would not be empowered, without legislation, to suspend the activities of that commission.  For what it is worth I offer to him a repeal Act that I drafted last night&mdash;a measure to repeal all the Pigs and Bacon Acts passed from 1935 to 1940.  I am quite willing to place it at his disposal at any time he should require it.  I agree with Senator McEllin that the maximum price for bacon should always be fixed on the basis of what the most efficient bacon factory in the country can produce bacon at.  The Senator and myself are at one on that question as well as on the question of the survival of the fittest.  It seems strange to me, however, that the Senator should agree with me on that point, because that principle has not been applied by this Government to other matters.  The milling trade is an example where the price of flour has always been fixed on what the most inefficient mill could produce the flour at.  I rather welcome it as a sign of a modern tendency perhaps in Government policy that Senator McEllin and I are in agreement on the question of fixing the maximum price on the price of the most efficient factories.</P>
      <P>Senator Johnson was in some doubt as to what the situation was in Cork and was puzzled about the pig situation there.  Senator Corkery, I think, explained the Cork position to Senator Johnston very clearly and definitely, and I have no doubt that Senator Corkery is right when he states that some of our pigs found their way as far afield as Monaghan.  Senator Hawkins seems to be under a delusion as regards the curers passing on the increase.  So far, the facts as disclosed in the recent prosecutions in Cork tend to show that the curers made no effort to pass on the increase, or, if you like to call it, the black market price that they paid for the pigs, to the consumer in any way.  That, I think, was admitted.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrederickHawkins" hpid="Mr. Hawkins Mr. Hawkins">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hawkins</NameTxt>
      <P>The Senator will admit that that may not continue.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="2105" />
    <Speaker pid="JamesCrosbie" hpid="Mr. Crosbie Mr. Crosbie">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Crosbie</NameTxt>
      <P>I would not admit it or deny it.  I only can state that so far there has been no evidence produced that there would be a tendency that way.  It is, however, possible.  I am glad to hear that the Minister intends to ask the commission to go into the question of revising gradings of pigs and, if this motion was productive of nothing else except that undertaking by the Minister, it would, I think, have served a very useful purpose.  As regards the operation of a minimum price for pigs and a maximum price for bacon, to which Senator Hawkins and the Minister both objected, surely the quota system would protect the smaller or the more medium factory from being completely swamped by the bigger and wealthier factories.</P>
      <P>Senator Parkinson dealt very fully with the question of artificial manures and I was disappointed that the Minister, when replying, did not deal with the question of superphosphate and potash.  Perhaps on some other occasion the Minister will take an opportunity of dealing with that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>I dealt very fully with that on the Estimate.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesCrosbie" hpid="Mr. Crosbie Mr. Crosbie">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Crosbie</NameTxt>
      <P>I agree with the Minister, as I said before, that it is principally a question of feeding-stuffs.  But we cannot altogether ignore the machinations of the commission and the question of price.  I have been challenged about the commission from all sides.  Let us see exactly what the situation is and what has happened. A situation was allowed to arise by the commission which has resulted, in tremendous waste of time, energy and money.  The position was that if the curers did not fill their quotas they were liable to penalties and to be fined.  When they paid more than the price fixed by the commission for pigs, they were prosecuted, although it is admitted on all sides that on that occasion they made no endeavour to increase the price of bacon, or in any way to pass on the increased price which they paid for the pigs either to the retailers or the consumers.  In my <Col N="2106" /> opinion the commission has failed in not foreseeing the possibility of that situation arising and the position as it exists at present, and as long as the <i>status quo</i> is allowed to remain, may best be described as a lunatic position and one which, if it were not for the serious repercussions on our national economy, would be laughable.  To my mind the commission has proved, not that it is not efficient&mdash;I do not for one moment make that case&mdash;but that it is not sufficiently elastic to deal with the rapidly changing conditions.  It is the duty of the commission to serve the industry and to serve the people, not to regiment them.  I still maintain that the commission's activities should be suspended for the duration of the emergency, or at any rate as long as the Cork factories are shut.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="McGillycuddyReeks" hpid="The McGillycuddy The McGillycuddy">
      <NameTxt>The McGillycuddy</NameTxt>
      <P>I should like to ask a question about a matter which has not been dealt with, and that is a drive for the collection of bones for the production of bone meal similar to that in England.  Is that possible in this country, or how does that stand?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>We are turning out bone and blood manure.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="McGillycuddyReeks" hpid="The McGillycuddy The McGillycuddy">
      <NameTxt>The McGillycuddy</NameTxt>
      <P>I find it most effective.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>I will take that point into consideration to see if it will be possible. Of course we have not such populous centres here and it may not be possible.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="McGillycuddyReeks" hpid="The McGillycuddy The McGillycuddy">
      <NameTxt>The McGillycuddy</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not think people, really know about it.  It is the same with waste paper.  There are no agents in the towns.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>I will take a note of it. When speaking, I meant to give Senators the figures of the number of pigs in the country in June of this year, so that they may have an idea of how we stand.  We had 50,000 sows. <Col N="2107" /> I do not know whether that is the lowest number on record, but it is the lowest for many years.  In the last normal year, namely, 1940, we had 103,000 sows.  In fact, 103,000 would be above the normal; probably 100,000 would be about the normal.  We had 464,000 other pigs, as against 946,000 in 1940.  Therefore, we had about half. I mentioned already that the number of sows is increasing slightly, so that the outlook is not entirely so bad as it would appear at the moment.  I think the position will improve.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="2108" />
    <Speaker pid="SeanFGibbons" hpid="Cathaoirleach Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Is the motion being withdrawn?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesCrosbie" hpid="Mr. Crosbie Mr. Crosbie">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Crosbie</NameTxt>
      <P>No, I am not withdrawing the motion, but I will not put it to a division.</P>
      <P>Motion put and negatived, Senator Crosbie dissenting.</P>
      <P>The Seanad adjourned at 3.30 p.m. until 3 p.m., September 23rd.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
</Debate>