<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE Debate SYSTEM "../Debate.dtd"[]>
<Debate DocTitle="Seanad Debate" Day="Wed" Date="14" Month="Jun" Year="1961" Vol="54" No="8" DateIrish="Dé Céadaoin, 14 Meitheamh 1961" DateEnglish="Wednesday, 14 June 1961" House="S" CommitteeEng="" CommitteeIr="" SubNameEng="" cnum="707">
  <MainHeading Type="Prelude" LHead="" RHead="">
    <Title>
    </Title>
    <P>
      <Col N="707" /> Do chuaigh an Cathaoirleach i gceannas ar 3 p.m.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Business" RHead="of Seanad">
    <Title>Business of Seanad.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="OwenSkeffington" hpid="Dr. Sheehy Skeffington Dr. Sheehy Skeffington">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Sheehy Skeffington</NameTxt>
      <P>Before we start, I should like to know whether it is yet possible for you, Sir, to make a statement with regard to the position of the Reporting Staff.  I have heard it said&mdash;I think it was said officially&mdash; that the Reporting Staff are prepared to go to arbitration, provided the <i>status quo ante</i> 1961 is reverted to during arbitration.  I should like to know whether that is a fact, and what precisely is being done by the authorities in relation to this difficulty which is putting obstacles in the way of the smooth running of the business of Parliament.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Professor Hayes Professor Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Professor Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>Have you notice of that question, Sir?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LiamOBuachalla" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>No notice.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DenisBurke" hpid="Mr. Burke Mr. Burke">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Burke</NameTxt>
      <P>I should like to ask have you been able to ascertain when we will take this motion standing in my name and in the name of three other Senators which has been on the Order Paper for about six months now.  This is a motion of public importance and I think the Seanad would have time to deal with it, if the appropriate Minister could come here.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LiamOBuachalla" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>That is a question for the Leader of the House.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>It will be taken as early as possible.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DenisBurke" hpid="Mr. Burke Mr. Burke">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Burke</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not want the Leader of the House to bring relativity into the matter.  It might be early in relation to what?  It might not be early in relation to Senators who are elected for a certain period.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OwenSkeffington" hpid="Dr. Sheehy Skeffington Dr. Sheehy Skeffington">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Sheehy Skeffington</NameTxt>
      <P>In view of <Col N="708" /> the fact that at the last two meetings of the Seanad, I raised the question of the Reporting Staff, asked for a statement and was told the matter was under active consideration, I feel that we should at least be told what the present position is, even if it irritates Senator Hayes.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LiamOBuachalla" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>The matter is under active consideration.  Arrangements have been made for the adequate reporting of the proceedings today starting at 3 o'clock.  I am not in a position to make any further statement on the matter to the House now.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OwenSkeffington" hpid="Dr. Sheehy Skeffington Dr. Sheehy Skeffington">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Sheehy Skeffington</NameTxt>
      <P>Thank you.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Order of" RHead="Business">
    <Title>Order of Business.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>It is proposed to take business as on the Order Paper, down to item No. 4.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OwenSkeffington" hpid="Dr. Sheehy Skeffington Dr. Sheehy Skeffington">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Sheehy Skeffington</NameTxt>
      <P>Arising out of that statement, I should like to ask when it is proposed to take my motion on parent-teacher groups which has been pending for some time and the discussion on which was started.  I should like to link that query with a query as to all the other motions which have been pending for so long.  I feel that time should be made available for the House to take these motions before we reach the very end of the session.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>We will see what we can do about that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOQuigley" hpid="Mr. O'Quigley Mr. O'Quigley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Quigley</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not think it will do for the Leader of the House to say that the matter will be taken as soon as possible or that it is under consideration. Item No. 6, the Electricity Supply (Amendment) Bill, 1960, has been on the Order Paper for over a year.  One wonders when that will be reached.  When is it to be taken?  If these things are not to be taken, we are making a laughing stock of this House and of Parliament.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickSDonegan" hpid="Mr. Donegan Mr. Donegan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Donegan</NameTxt>
      <P>Hear, hear!</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>The Senator will recall that on a couple of occasions I was prepared to take it but either the <Col N="709" /> Senator was not available or he was not ready to take it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LiamOBuachalla" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>That is a matter for discussion with the Leader of the House.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOQuigley" hpid="Mr. O'Quigley Mr. O'Quigley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Quigley</NameTxt>
      <P>It is an improper statement for the Leader of the House to make.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Charities Bill," RHead="1957&mdash;Fifth Stage">
    <Title>Charities Bill, 1957&mdash;Fifth Stage.</Title>
    <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That the Bill do now pass.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOQuigley" hpid="Mr. O'Quigley Mr. O'Quigley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Quigley</NameTxt>
      <P>It is with considerable trepidation that I rise to speak on the Final Stage of this Bill because those who spoke on the Final Stages of Bills in recent times found themselves running into difficulties, particularly at an early stage.  I do not like to find myself either having to have to resume my seat or being put out of the House.  I hope that with a gentle hint or two from the Chair, I may be able to keep within the rules of order on the Final Stage.  I shall be very brief.  Brevity, I think, is the best way of keeping in order on the Final Stages of Bills.</P>
      <P>This Bill is mainly a consolidation of the existing law.  I think it is a happy thought for the Seanad to know that it leaves this House a little better than it was when it came into the House. For that, we must express our appreciation for what I might call the benevolent attitude which the Parliamentary Secretary adopted towards the amendments which were put down.  As far as the amendments which were accepted are concerned, one would have hoped that the Parliamentary Secretary would have adopted a different attitude on some of them.  At any rate, the Bill is, perhaps, not very greatly deficient because some of the amendments were not accepted.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I think that the administration of charities in this country will proceed in much the same way after the passing of this Bill as it has up to the present time.  Indeed, in any such matter as the administration of charities, a great deal, in the last resort, depends upon the manner in which the principal executive officer and his staff carry out <Col N="710" /> the duties imposed upon them by statute.  A great deal depends upon these for the effective implementation of the legislation which is passed by Oireachtas Eireann.</P>
    <P>For that reason, I am somewhat concerned about the provisions of Section 10 of the Bill.  I do not readily understand why it becomes necessary in this Bill to have one Minister appoint staff and another Minister approve of the terms and conditions under which the staff shall be appointed and hold office and then have the staff operate and work subject to the control of a body which has no relationship with either the Minister appointing or approving of the terms and conditions of service. That seems to be an unnecessarily cumbersome method of doing things.</P>
    <P>The particular matter which concerns me is the inadequacy of Section 10 in relation to the well-being of the staff of the Commissioners of Charitable Donations and Bequests.  I had occasion to refer to this before.  The Parliamentary Secretary seemed to be satisfied that the section was adequate to meet the needs of the staff of the Commissioners of Charitable Donations and Bequests.  In that connection, I pointed out that the wording of this secion was similar to the wording of a number of Acts, including the Industrial Development Authority Act and the Adoption Act.  I think the Parliamentary Secretary was misinformed as to the effect of the Industrial Development Authority Act because, as I indicated on Committee Stage, the Industrial Development Authority is an authority which, by subsection (2) of Section 2, shall be responsible to the Minister in the exercise of its powers and functions.  Therefore, I think that the members of the Authority and their staff become State servants but the Commissioners of Charitable Donations and Bequests which are being established under this Bill are not in any sense comparable with the Development Authority and the officers of that body are not in any way comparable with the officers of the Commissioners of Charitable Donations and Bequests.</P>
    <P>I think the section is somewhat in adequate in that we are not providing clearly&mdash;in fact, I do not think we are <Col N="711" /> providing at all&mdash;that the Superannuation Acts will be applied to the staff of the Commissioners of Charitable Donations and Bequests.  It is very significant at a time when the status of the staff of the Houses of the Oireachtas is under consideration to refer to that Act of 1959.  It is perfectly clear that the staff of the Houses of the Oireachtas are State servants and not servants of the Government, as everybody will recognise, but servants of the Legislature.  Nonetheless, in the 1959 Act by virtue of Section 27, it has been found necessary to provide that:</P>
    <P>The provisions of the Superannuations Acts, 1834 to 1956, shall apply to or in respect of members of the staff of the Houses of the Oireachtas.</P>
    <P>That is a specific enactment which we have not here and which gives the staff of the Houses of the Oireachtas beyond any shadow of doubt the benefit of the Superannuation Acts.  The only point I want to make&mdash;I do not want to labour it&mdash;is that I do not believe that in this Bill we are providing that the staff of the Commissioners of Charitable Donations and Bequests can lawfully and validly be paid out of public funds for superannuation under the Superannuation Acts, 1834 to 1956. Up to the present time, money has been paid on the foot of an Estimate but I do not think there is statutory authority for doing that.  It is a matter, indeed, which the Comptroller and Auditor General should seriously consider. I do not think, if we have any respect for law or any intention of regulating the disbursement of public money in accordance with law, we ought to leave matters in the haphazard way in which they have been left in this Bill in so far as it relates to the superannuation of the officers and servants of the Commissioners of Charitable Donations and Bequests.</P>
    <P>I do not think any amount of talking at this stage can amend the Bill or persuade the Parliamentary Secretary and his advisers to amend it at a later stage.  It has been quite evident that the Parliamentary Secretary has been eager to find a precedent <Col N="712" /> which is equally wrong and the constant repetition in an Act of Parliament of something which is wrong in its application administratively over a period of years never makes it right. In this Bill, we are doing less than justice to the officers and servants of the Commissioners.</P>
    <Speaker pid="CharlesJHaughey" hpid="Parliamentary Secretary to the Minister for Justice (Mr. Haughey) Charles J. Haughey">
      <NameTxt>Parliamentary Secretary to the Minister for Justice (Mr. Haughey)</NameTxt>
      <P>First of all, let me say that I am very grateful to the House for the manner in which they have discussed and examined this Bill.  I am prepared to agree with Senator O'Quigley when he says that the Bill leaves the House better than when it came into it, because of the improvements we have been able to effect here.  As Senator O'Quigley rightly suspects, I am not persuaded that the staff of the Board are not fully protected in every way.</P>
      <P>Finally, I want to say to the Seanad that I think we have here a Bill which is a very good measure, which effects valuable and useful reforms and which will certainly contribute in a substantial way towards the better and more efficient administration of charities in Ireland.  I would not attempt to say it is the last Bill on charities that will ever be enacted.  As time goes on, if there appears to be a need to amend or alter the law that can be done, but I think that as of now we have done everything in the Bill that we should do in present circumstances.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Courts of Justice and Court Officers (Superannuation) Bill," RHead="1961&mdash;(Certified Money Bill). Second and Committee Stages">
    <Title>Courts of Justice and Court Officers (Superannuation) Bill, 1961&mdash;(Certified Money Bill).  Second and Committee Stages.</Title>
    <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That the Bill be now read a Second Time.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="OscarTraynor" hpid="Minister for Justice (Mr. Traynor) Oscar Traynor">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Justice (Mr. Traynor)</NameTxt>
      <P>This measure contains two provisions, both of which have been formulated in response to representations from members of the judiciary and others regarding the absence at present of any arrangements to provide financial assistance for the dependants of a person who dies while either in office or on pension.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="713" /> The members of the judiciary and the court officers covered by this Bill have at present a maximum pension of two-thirds of salary and there is no provision for a death gratuity or a lump sum on retirement.  The Bill proposes to provide for cases of premature death by exchanging the present pension provisions for new provisions which actuarially do not involve additional expenditure. The pensions for the various categories, as calculated at present, will be reduced by one-fourth, and in return for that reduction a death gratuity of one year's salary will be available after not less than five years' service, and a lump sum of one-and-a-half times the amount of the annual pension will be payable on retirement. The new terms which I have mentioned will be applied to all persons appointed after the passing of the present measure, and persons at present holding office will, subject to certain conditions, have an option of accepting the new terms or retaining their existing terms in accordance with their individual wishes.</P>
    <P>The second provision of this Bill will enable a person retiring on pension to surrender, subject to certain conditions, a portion of his pension in order to secure a pension for his wife or for one nominated dependant.  This provision which will apply only at the time of retirement is being made available to present office holders and to future appointees.</P>
    <P>As I mentioned in the other House this Bill has been prepared on the basis that it does not involve any additional expenditure.  Actuarial advice has been obtained to the effect that the new terms in this Bill will, over a period of years, cost the same as the existing provisions, and are the most generous which can be provided without incurring additional expenditure.  In the case of the provisions relating to the allocation of pensions, the principle of not increasing the burden on the Exchequer has also been applied.</P>
    <P>This Bill will, I am confident, be welcomed for the reason that it is designed to reduce hardship which often arises from premature death even in cases where the office holder is, by general standards, in receipt of substantial <Col N="714" /> remuneration.  It is desirable that the measure should be enacted with as little delay as possible so that the benefits of the Bill may become available in the very near future.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Professor Hayes Professor Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Professor Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>We find this an acceptable measure.  As the Minister has explained, it involves no charge on public funds, a fact which has been ascertained on the basis of an actuarial investigation.  It is agreeable to the people concerned, the judges and certain court officers.  What is being done here has already been done for civil servants of certain classes.  It really amounts to this, that people are allowed to use benefits or moneys they already enjoy in a particular manner, which seems to be in order and which the Minister agrees would be better for themselves and for their wives or dependants. For that reason, the Bill appears to be acceptable and I see no reason why it should not pass rapidly.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOQuigley" hpid="Mr. O'Quigley Mr. O'Quigley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Quigley</NameTxt>
      <P>The one outstanding feature in the present age is the consciousness on the part of all classes of society of the necessity to provide for the time when either people themselves are not working or when they are dead.  Consequently, it is not surprising to find that even people who are in the exalted position of being members of the judiciary are concerned about what will happen their dependants when they are no longer in a position to support them.  For that reason everybody will welcome this Bill as another step forward in the development of social consciousness in relation to making provision for dependants. I gather from the Minister's opening statement that this Bill in all its terms is acceptable to the judiciary. If that is the case, there does not seem to be much in it that calls for amendment, so far as its application to them is concerned.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>As Senator Hayes has indicated, this Bill will not impose any new charge upon the Exchequer.  In the Dáil, the Minister for Justice indicated that was the cardinal principle upon which the Bill was framed.  I suggest it is never too late for the Minister to change his mind.  The Bill deals not only with judges but with other court officers, <Col N="715" /> namely, certain Masters and Registrars of the High Court and county registrars.</P>
    <P>As I understand the position with regard to county registrars, I have heard it said that there is at present only one county registrar in the country who, if he lives to the age of 65 years, will qualify for full pension.  All those who have been appointed since the Act was passed in 1945, with one exception, will not qualify for full pension. There used to be a provision applicable to State servants in the Superannuation Acts, and that provision enabled the Minister for Finance to grant added years of service in the case of people who, by reason of a particular qualification of which they had to be possessed before they were appointed, were appointed at a late age.  In such circumstances, the Minister for Finance was empowered to add years to their service to enable them to qualify for full pension.  For some reason which I have never been able to understand, that section of the Act was repealed, mainly in connection with the change over from sixtieths to fortieths and the lump sum.</P>
    <P>The plain fact of the matter is that no Minister for Justice, whoever he may be, would appoint a county registrar who has not considerable experience as a practising solicitor.  Since that is absolutely necessary for appointment as county registrar, and because it is in the public interest that they should have a fairly long period in practice before being appointed, it is not right that their services should be availed of without giving them appropriate superannuation conditions equivalent at least to non-technical State servants.</P>
    <P>If the Minister looks into the matter, I think he will find there are very few persons in State employment who are placed in that position; and, if there are other persons in the same position, then the superannuation code should be reviewed with a view to meeting the position of county registrars and others.  I do not know whether or not they have made any representations to the Minister on this point, or whether they have any <Col N="716" /> association or union which speaks on their behalf, but I have discussed the matter with many people and I think the Minister should take advantage of the position now to put down recommendations in the Seanad to meet the position of these people.</P>
    <P>There is another section of people who do not appear to be covered by the Bill and I wonder if the Minister has been able to do anything about their position.  There was quite a time-lag between the rise in the cost of living and the increase in the salaries of the judiciary.  There are widows living today in conditions of real hardship. That hardship is not due to previous high living or anything like that.  There are cases of which I am aware in which the widows have large families to provide for.  I had the mortification of seeing the widow of one district justice engaged in work which one would not expect a person of that social standing to have to engage in.  I know she has no income except what she can earn herself.  I wonder whether anything can be done for the few who are in that penurious position?  I am quite sure it is unnecessary to make any appeal to the Minister&mdash;his humanity is well known&mdash;but if there is any way in which these people can be helped, they should be helped.  As the years go by then, and they get older, they can look forward to even a meagre widow's pension.  The Minister will encounter no opposition to the granting of such pensions from Parliament, or, indeed, from the public.  The Bill will to some extent relieve the hardship involved when the breadwinner dies.</P>
    <P>With regard to the allocation of pension, I understand it can be allocated in favour of only one dependant. I wonder if there were two children and the position was that they could not earn their living, is there provision in the Bill whereby the allocation of the pension could be made in favour of each of the children?  It may be that at the present time such allocation in favour of two dependent children does not arise but there can always be an accident.  It may be that in the future such a provision would be desirable.  It may be that it is not possible to make an actuarial calculation to enable <Col N="717" /> allocation of the pension to be made in those circumstances, but if I understand the Bill rightly, I think the allocation can be made in favour of only one child.  If I am correct in that opinion, I would ask the Minister to consider the desirability of enabling allocation to be made in favour of more than one child.  Subject to that, the Bill can be given a speedy passage through the House.</P>
    <Speaker pid="OwenSkeffington" hpid="Dr. Sheehy Skeffington Dr. Sheehy Skeffington">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Sheehy Skeffington</NameTxt>
      <P>I should like to associate myself with what has been said in support of the Bill.  The Bill is a just Bill and it includes a principle which is being extended under our legislation.  I think we were given the first indication of that when a similar Bill in relation to civil servants was brought in by the previous Government.  I am not quite clear&mdash; and I am afraid I did not have time to make the comparison&mdash;whether this Bill contains some provisions that were not in the Bill relating to civil servants.  I have the feeling that some provisions here are new.  They are all provisions I welcome but I should like to feel that civil servants also might get the benefit of such provisions.  I should like to hear what the Minister feels about that.</P>
      <P>For instance, I notice that subsection (3) of Section 2 reads as follows:&mdash;</P>
      <P>Upon the death, while holding office as a judge of the Supreme Court, the High Court, or the Circuit Court or as a justice after five years' service or upwards as a judge or justice, as the case may be, of any person to whom this section applies, there shall be granted to the legal personal representative of that person a gratuity of an amount equal to the yearly amount of his salary as a judge or justice, as the case may be, at the time of this death.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>There is a similar provision which is covered in subsection (2) of Section 4. I do not remember any such concession being made to civil servants.  As I remember it, the only matter dealt with in the Bill relating to civil servants is that they will be entitled to forego part of their pension in order <Col N="718" /> that their widows may get that portion of it after their death.  I do not remember any introduction of the right of an annuity upon death while in office.  I wonder whether I am right in thinking that this is new and appears for the first time in this Bill.  I may be wrong in that.</P>
    <P>I should like to ask two more questions arising out of subsection (3) of Section 2 because the Minister, as I understood him in his opening remarks, said more or less that this Bill will not cost the State anything.  I may have misunderstood him.  I understood him to say it was based on actuarial calculations and that it really was a question of allowing these judges and court officers to reallocate their pension rights so that the cost to the State could be met because it is a self-supporting scheme.</P>
    <P>Can that be true of this subsection where a gratuity of an amount equal to the yearly amount of his salary is to be given to the dependants of a judge who dies while holding office? Where does that money come from, if not from the Exchequer?  I have the feeling that that subsection cannot be covered actuarially but must, in fact, put a fresh charge on the State.  I think I could make that point clear by asking whether it would be in order in the Seanad to put down an amendment to change this from a yearly amount to an amount of his salary, say, for 15 months?  I would suggest that to put down such an amendment would be out of order in the Seanad because it would place an additional charge on the Exchequer.</P>
    <P>If it is on an actuarial basis within a scheme which is self-supporting, then such an amendment would be possible and would be in order in the Seanad.  Either it is a self-supporting scheme, in which case no such amendment by the Seanad would put an additional charge on the Exchequer and consequently it would be in order or it would be out of order because it would put an additional charge on the Exchequer and consequently the basis for this is not quite entirely the actuarial basis.</P>
    <P>I should like to turn to Section 6, <Col N="719" /> subsection (2), paragraph (b) which reads:</P>
    <P>a person shall not be entitled to adopt provisions of section 2 or 4, as the case may be, of this Act unless the Minister decides that he is of sound health.</P>
    <P>Paragraph (c) says:</P>
    <P>Where a person is required to undergo medical examination under the regulations he may be required to pay such fee as the Minister may determine in respect of the examination.</P>
    <P>I should like to make two separate comments on the underlying principle there.  One of them I made before in relation to the Civil Service for whom similar provision is made because we are saying: &ldquo;We are granting you the right to sacrifice portion of your pension but we are only granting you that, if you are in sound health.&rdquo;  I remember the previous Minister for Finance resisting very strongly any suggestion that that was an unjust provision.  I should like to make again the point I made then.  The very person who is most likely to be anxious to sacrifice some of his pension is the person not in sound health.  I feel that the demand that the pensioner shall be in sound health before he is entitled to make this sacrifice cuts down very considerably the utility of this Bill.  I would suggest that it cuts down also the probability of the Bill coming into effect because on a general actuarial basis, if there is a married couple and you insist that at the age of 60, 65 or 70, one of them shall be of sound health, on an average the chances are that in the majority of cases, the other one will be less likely to survive.  A great deal of the value of the Bill is removed by this insistence that the person shall be of sound health.  I think it is a bad thing.  I think that actuarially it should be possible to make calculations upon an average state of health at the age of 65 or 70 without insisting that the person, before he makes this sacrifice, shall be of sound health.</P>
    <P>The other point is a separate one. Paragraph (b) says that the Minister will decide that he is of sound health. I cannot imagine the Minister going <Col N="720" /> round with a stethoscope.  I can only assume that the only legitimate way in which the Minister can so decide is by means of a medical examination.  I am bewildered then to find that paragraph (c) says:</P>
    <P>where a person is required to undergo medical examination under the regulations he may be required to pay such fee as the Minister may determine in respect of the examination</P>
    <P>as if there were some circumstances in which he would not be required to undergo a medical examination&mdash;as if it would be, in fact, the Minister who would decide without any medical examination. I find that a little puzzling. Are we granting the Minister the right to decide that a judge is not of sound health?  We are not saying that all of them must undergo a medical examination but only those about whom there is some doubt.  I find that puzzling. I do not think it is very sound. It is giving the Minister power which he might find embarrassing and which, in fact, he should not be given.</P>
    <P>If there is a decision as to the soundness of the health of such a person, it should be solely upon medical considerations and not upon a ministerial decision.  The ministerial decision should be based only on medical examination and not upon how the person looks.  I suggest that, as at present framed, paragraph (c) implies that there would be some cases in which a medical examination would not be necessary and in which the Minister himself could decide that the candidate was not of sound health.  That is not a very good principle.</P>
    <P>I notice that in Section 7, subsection (2), the suggestion is that this is not the same principle as applies to civil servants and that the pensioner can at the time of retiring, if he retires for reasons other than reasons of ill health, surrender part of his pension &ldquo;in return for the grant by the Minister under this Act of a pension to the wife or one dependant of the person specified by him&rdquo;.  The question I want to ask is: is this not a new provision also?  I do not remember that civil servants were entitled to nominate a <Col N="721" /> dependant.  My recollection may be faulty but I thought it was only for the benefit of the widow.  I should like to put the question whether that is a new provision or not, or whether that is the general provision in relation to civil servants also.</P>
    <P>The final point I want to make is in relation to Section 7, subsection (4), which has a number of paragraphs. Paragraphs (a) says:</P>
    <P>A pension under this section granted to the wife of a person shall be payable either, as the person may elect when he makes the surrender under this section&mdash;</P>
    <P>(i)  during the period (if any) for which the wife survives the person, or</P>
    <P>(ii)  during both the period of the joint lives of the person and the wife subsequent to the retirement of the person and the period (if any) for which the wife survives the person.</P>
    <P>Paragraph (ii) seems to be a new provision and a very good one.  It is excellent that a person should have the right to decide that the pension shall be payable to the wife during the period of his life, as well as to the widow, if she survives him.  It is an admirable provision and I should like to know if that also is a new provision, as I do not remember civil servants being granted that privilege. The reason I ask whether these are new provisions is simply to express the hope that where they are new, they will be extended perhaps in some future Bill to all servants of the State. This type of Bill is a good one.  The concessions are good ones and I should like to be assured that they are widely applied, or are going to be widely applied, to all civil servants and not merely to the judiciary or officers of the courts.</P>
    <Speaker pid="SeanODonovan" hpid="Seán Ó Donnabháin Seán Ó Donnabháin">
      <NameTxt>Seán Ó Donnabháin</NameTxt>
      <P>I welcome this legislation which certainly must relieve some of the difficulties experienced by members of the judiciary and officers of the courts.  I notice in the Dáil Debates that a Money Resolution was brought in to the effect:</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>That it is expedient to authorise such payments out of the Central <Col N="722" /> Fund or the growing produce thereof and out of moneys provided by the Oireachtas as are necessary to give effect to any Act of the present session to make further provision in relation to the superannuation of Judges of the Supreme Court, the High Court and the Circuit Court, of Justices of the District Court and of certain Court officers.</P>
    <P>I am puzzled why it is necessary to bring in a Money Resolution in the Dáil to provide for moneys to be paid when we are assured that this will not put any extra charge on the Exchequer. If no extra charge is involved, one would think that it would not be necessary to bring in a resolution to provide for payment of charges on the Exchequer.</P>
    <P>Another point which has been brought to my notice is that judges and justices retire at 70 but court officers are still required to retire at 65.  The same thing seems to apply to people who are appointed as judges or justices because they get these positions later in life.  We are reducing the 30 years' service to 20 years' service under this legislation to facilitate the people retiring or getting a pension without having to spend 30 years in the service, when naturally they would be beginning those 30 years late in life.  It seems wrong that different conditions should apply to justices and judges from those applying to people similarily appointed in the offices of Registrar or High Court officers.  They are appointed pretty late in life and I suppose they would have to be physically fit to continue until they were 70 years of age, the same as judges and justices.  I just want to bring that point to the Minister's attention, that similar conditions could surely be applied to judges and justices and Registrars and officers of the court generally.</P>
    <Speaker pid="OscarTraynor" hpid="Mr. Traynor Mr. Traynor">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Traynor</NameTxt>
      <P>This is a very simple Bill which has been brought in at the express desire of the judiciary.  As I said in my opening remarks, it does not impose any cost on the national Exchequer.  It is based entirely on the Civil Service Act which provides <Col N="723" /> similar conditions for civil servants. There are no new sections that I know of.  They are based, in the main, on the Civil Service scheme and generally speaking, they apply in the same manner to the judges and district justices as they do to civil servants.  I said in my opening remarks that it was desirable that we should expedite the passing of this measure, for the simple reason that should it occur&mdash;and I hope it will not&mdash;that any member of the judiciary died between now and the passing of this Bill, it would not affect the relatives left behind.</P>
      <P>It has no retrospective effect, either, and I should like to refer to Senator O'Quigley's remarks in regard to wives and widows.  It could not in any sense apply to widows who become widows before the passing of this Act.  As I say, it can have no retrospective effect. Senator Sheehy Skeffington was worried because the Minister would appear to be the judge of whether a person was in sound health or not.  The Senator knows very well that the Minister making that judgment would make it only on the basis of a certificate provided to him by the doctor examining the individual. If the Senator were a member of an insurance company, he would not be prepared to accept what I think is called a bad prospect.  Some regulations must be made governing the type of individual who might, if he found himself in a very bad state of health decide: &ldquo;Now is the time to get out.&rdquo;  We are the guardians of public money and, as such, we must do what the directors of a business would do, that is, look after the interests of those concerned, in our case, the people.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>That does not mean for a moment that the person in whom the Senator is interested would not be given the fullest possible consideration.  I am pretty certain that any Minister &mdash; and the Minister referred to, as the Senator knows, is not the Minister for Justice but the Minister for Finance&mdash;would naturally be as humane as either the Senator or I would be in a case of that kind.  If by any chance a man did feel it was time for him to get out, I presume he would do so before he would become so very bad that no doctor <Col N="724" /> would pass him.  This provision is there merely to ensure that State funds will receive that type of protection.</P>
    <P>I do not think there is anything very much more that I can say on the Bill. It is a simple type of Bill based on the Civil Service scheme which, so far as I am informed, is operating very successfully. The judiciary were aware of that fact, and when they found that after negotiations the Government were not prepared to do this out of public moneys, they immediately turned to the Civil Service scheme and asked to be given the right to opt for that scheme.  That is what is happening now.  We are giving them the same rights as civil servants have and have had for quite a long number of years.</P>
    <P>I am sure I am not leaving out anything I should mention because, as I said a moment ago, this Bill is based entirely on the Civil Service scheme. There is nothing that can be regarded as new, or that is not as effective as the other scheme.  I would strongly urge the House to pass the Second Stage and I suggest that in the circumstances I might be given the remaining Stages today.</P>
    <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
    <P>Agreed to take remaining Stages today.</P>
    <P>Bill considered in Committee.</P>
    <P>Section 1 agreed to.</P>
    <P Just="Center">SECTION 2.</P>
    <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That Section 2 stand part of the Bill.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOQuigley" hpid="Mr. O'Quigley Mr. O'Quigley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Quigley</NameTxt>
      <P>I merely want to refer to the point raised by Senator Sheehy Skeffington.  The position is, if I am correct, that subsection (5) deals with the manner in which the new provision of the lump sum will be financed.  Senator Sheehy Skeffington wondered whether or not the Bill imposed any charge on the Exchequer. My interpretation, at any rate, is that the reduction by a quarter of the pension payable is the way in which the lump sum payable on death or on retirement will be financed.  I wonder if I am correct in that?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="725" /> Incidentally, the Senator is not correct in stating that there was no provision in the 1954 Act or in the Act that allocated pensions to the Civil Service, for payment of a lump sum. That point arises because, as the Minister knows, the lump sum has been payable to male public servants since the 1909 Superannuation Act, and to female public servants since 1954, so that in fact what is being done in this Bill is effecting two changes as I see it: one is the provision of a lump sum which has been payable since 1909 to male civil servants, and since 1954 to female civil servants, and the other is the allocation of pension payable, in respect of which an Act was passed dealing with civil servants some time in the 50's.  I should like the Minister to confirm that subsection (5) is the method by which the lump sum is being financed.</P>
    <Speaker pid="OscarTraynor" hpid="Mr. Traynor Mr. Traynor">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Traynor</NameTxt>
      <P>The Senator is perfectly correct, but I should like to point out to the House that the judges do not have to accept it, if they do not so desire.  If they regard the position which they occupy in respect of pensions at the present time as being superior to what is contained in the Bill, they need not opt to accept it. Generally speaking, what the Senator has said is correct.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P Just="Center">SECTION 3.</P>
      <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That Section 3 stand part of the Bill.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOQuigley" hpid="Mr. O'Quigley Mr. O'Quigley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Quigley</NameTxt>
      <P>This is the section which gives judges and district justices the option to avail themselves of the benefits of the Bill.  I wonder can the Minister hold out any hope that widows of judges and district justices can expect at any time in future that some form of widows' pension scheme will be introduce in relation to them?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Secondly, in relation to the type of person whose health is such that he cannot avail himself of the provisions of the Bill, and who wishes to allocate part of the pension in favour of his wife or child, can the Minister say will provision be made in future to cover <Col N="726" /> the widow or dependants of that type of person?  They stand just as much in need of protection as do the other people who will be covered by the Bill.</P>
    <Speaker pid="OscarTraynor" hpid="Mr. Traynor Mr. Traynor">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Traynor</NameTxt>
      <P>I would not say there would be any provision in regard to the circumstances which the Senator has described.  A judge in the position to which the Senator has referred would be entitled to his normal pension, and we must presume, too, that members of the judiciary, like members of the middle classes, will take out insurance and try to provide in that way, or in some other way, for the circumstances which the Senator has in mind.  We must remember that if a judge is in bad health, that does not deprive him of his normal pension, but only of the right to come under this scheme which might be described as an insurance scheme.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOQuigley" hpid="Mr. O'Quigley Mr. O'Quigley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Quigley</NameTxt>
      <P>I appreciate that there is no intention of depriving a judge of anything he is entitled to but I think the Minister will agree that the prospective widow of a judge who cannot avail himself of this scheme is in as much need of some kind of pension or annual allowance as the person who can avail of this scheme.  The person in bad health is likely to be the person who runs into a good deal of financial trouble because of his illness.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>It is quite true that all classes of persons try to insure themselves, to cover themselves, to cover their dependants in regard to the eventuality of death.  There is no doubt about that.  There is no walk of society in which people are living on salaries at the present time where the salaries are such as would enable them to take out insurance to cover the contingency of widowhood and also to provide for their children.  While judges and justices do take out insurance policies, there is no doubt that eventually people will find themselves without any means of subsistence.  It is to meet that kind of situation that I would impress upon the Minister the desirability of providing some kind of scheme whereby the position of these people can be met.  That also takes <Col N="727" /> into account the widows of deceased former members of the judiciary.</P>
    <Speaker pid="OscarTraynor" hpid="Mr. Traynor Mr. Traynor">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Traynor</NameTxt>
      <P>I cannot commit myself to any promise in respect of this Bill but there is always the future, of course.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>Sections 4 and 5 agreed to.</P>
      <P Just="Center">SECTION 6.</P>
      <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That Section 6 stand part of the Bill.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOQuigley" hpid="Mr. O'Quigley Mr. O'Quigley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Quigley</NameTxt>
      <P>The regulations to be made under this section will be made by the Minister for Finance, after consultations with the Minister for Justice.  I wonder would it be in order to inquire whether it is the intention to consult some representatives of the judiciary?  I know that in relation to regulations made under the corresponding Superannuation Acts, the appropriate representative bodies of civil servants were consulted on the regulations.  When regulations of that kind are being made, every contingency ought to be covered and the way in which that can be provided for is to have consultation in advance.  Perhaps, the Minister does not want to say whether or not he proposes to consult with the judiciary in this matter and I do not want to press him to say whether he will or not, but I would express the view that it is very advisable and desirable that there should be advance consultation when these regulations are in draft.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OscarTraynor" hpid="Mr. Traynor Mr. Traynor">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Traynor</NameTxt>
      <P>The Senator knows that there is a period of six months allowed from the passing of the Act during which a person will have the right to examine the whole position as to whether he would prefer to opt or not to come under this Act.  However, we can look into that particular question.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOQuigley" hpid="Mr. O'Quigley Mr. O'Quigley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Quigley</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not see any provision in the Bill for laying these regulations before each House of the Oireachtas.  Am I right in that? <Col N="728" /> This seems to me to be a case peculiarly appropriate for laying the regulations before each House of the Oireachtas because under Section 3 the regulations are such as may affect the position of existing judges and justices.  It might be desirable that if that were not quite in order, the regulations could be annulled by one or other House of the Oireachtas.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OscarTraynor" hpid="Mr. Traynor Mr. Traynor">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Traynor</NameTxt>
      <P>I am informed that the regulations in respect of the Civil Service were not laid on the Table of the House either and that the same will apply in this respect.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOQuigley" hpid="Mr. O'Quigley Mr. O'Quigley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Quigley</NameTxt>
      <P>One always assumes that these are regulations which will be laid before each House of the Oireachtas, While I am very anxious that the Bill should go through immediately, I am inclined to wonder whether further consideration should not be given to the kind of regulations which will be made in cases of this kind.  We should not vest too much power in the Minister for Finance in relation to matters affecting the position of the judiciary, without having that power controlled in any way.  I am inclined to think that unless there is a very good reason to the contrary, the regulations in the case of this Bill are peculiarly a type of regulation which ought to be laid before each House of the Oireachtas as a safeguard for the position of the judiciary.  When it comes to the end of the Committee Stage, I may have something further to say on that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OscarTraynor" hpid="Mr. Traynor Mr. Traynor">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Traynor</NameTxt>
      <P>I think the regulations in respect of civil servants came in away back in 1954 or some such time. There have been no complaints suggesting that there is anything sinister occurring in that regard.  These regulations are purely mechanical.  They operate between the Minister for Finance and the person who will be benefiting from this Bill.  As I said in reply to Senator Sheehy Skeffington, the Bill is in the main based on the Civil Service scheme and what applies, in fact, to the various sections of the Bill applies also to the regulations.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOQuigley" hpid="Mr. O'Quigley Mr. O'Quigley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Quigley</NameTxt>
      <P>If that is so, it is the same scheme but, of course, the <Col N="729" /> terms and the conditions of service of the judiciary who hold office for the whole duration of their natural life until 72 years of age are quite different from those of civil servants who hold office at the will and pleasure of the Government.  It is an entirely different set of circumstances where you are dealing with people whose constitutional position is that their salary may not be reduced during their term of office as judges.</P>
      <P>I certainly agree that under this Bill the Minister for Finance should have the first and final word in relation to the kind of regulations to be made under the Bill.  We are all aware of the tremendous power of the Minister for Finance in relation to matters of one kind and another.  We often see the powers which the Minister necessarily has in relation to the control of public money used in a manner which ordinary people would not commend. When it comes to dealing with matters affecting the judiciary, I for one would not agree that the Minister should be the last authority in the making of regulations under this Bill. One possible way out of this dilemma as I see it, if this Bill is to go through all Stages to-day, is an assurance in relation to the regulations made under this Bill that the members of the judiciary will be consulted.  Otherwise, I think it is a clear case where the regulations should be laid before the House.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OscarTraynor" hpid="Mr. Traynor Mr. Traynor">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Traynor</NameTxt>
      <P>I shall bring the Senator's remarks to the notice of the Minister.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>Sections 7 to 10, inclusive, agreed to.</P>
      <P>Title agreed to.</P>
      <P>Bill reported without recommendation.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LiamOBuachalla" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Next Stage?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOQuigley" hpid="Mr. O'Quigley Mr. O'Quigley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Quigley</NameTxt>
      <P>In view of what I said on Section 6, I should be most anxious to have an opportunity of putting down an amendment on Report Stage to cover the question of regulations. That can be done later this evening.  I should be glad of the <Col N="730" /> opportunity, but otherwise I would ask to have it deferred until this day week.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LiamOBuachalla" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>It is suggested that the Report Stage be postponed until later in the evening.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OscarTraynor" hpid="Mr. Traynor Mr. Traynor">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Traynor</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not mind, if that suits the House.  At what time would it be taken?  I have an appointment at 7 o'clock.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LiamOBuachalla" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>The Seanad is adjourning from 6 to 8 o'clock.  Would that suit the Minister?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OscarTraynor" hpid="Mr. Traynor Mr. Traynor">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Traynor</NameTxt>
      <P>It would not suit me, but if the House met tomorrow&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonKissane" hpid="Éamon Ó Ciosáin Éamon Ó Ciosáin">
      <NameTxt>Éamon Ó Ciosáin</NameTxt>
      <P>It could be fixed for an earlier hour, say, 5.30.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LiamOBuachalla" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Will we order the Report Stage for 5.30?  That will enable Senator O'Quigley to put down an amendment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OscarTraynor" hpid="Mr. Traynor Mr. Traynor">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Traynor</NameTxt>
      <P>This amendment will not involve any expenditure?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LiamOBuachalla" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>That will be a matter for the Chair, when the amendment is prepared.  It will have to be examined.</P>
      <P>Report Stage ordered for 5.30 p.m.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Industrial Research and Standards" RHead="Bill, 1961&mdash;Second Stage">
    <Title>Industrial Research and Standards Bill, 1961&mdash;Second Stage.</Title>
    <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That the Bill be now read a Second Time.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="ErskineHamiltonChild" hpid="Minister for Transport and Power (Mr. Childers) Erskine Hamilton Childers">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Transport and Power (Mr. Childers)</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister for Industry and Commerce is unexpectedly engaged in the Dáil on his Estimate and has asked me to take the Second Stage of this Bill for him.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The Bill is the result of a review which I have had carried out with a view to ascertaining what changes were required in the legislation dealing with the Institute for Industrial Research and Standards.  The original legislation under which the Institute was established was enacted in 1946, and an amending Act was passed in 1954.  As it is now fifteen years since the original Act was passed, it is not, perhaps, surprising that it has been <Col N="731" /> found necessary to amend the existing legislation.  This Bill is designed to overhaul the functions, powers and organisation of the Institute so as to enable it to function more effectively.</P>
    <P>Perhaps, the most important change proposed in the Bill is that relating to the organisation of what might be described as the governing body of the Institute.  Senators will be aware that the Institute's functions under the 1946 and 1954 Acts were discharged by several constituent organs, namely, the Industrial Research Committee, the Standards Committee, the Director and the Council.  The Bill provides for the concentration of functions in the hands of a single entity in the form of a Board which is to be established. This simplification in the organisation of the Institute is designed to improve its efficiency.  The Board will be responsible for the general government of the Institute and the administration of its affairs, and it will operate in much the same way as the Board of Directors of a company.  It will be appointed by the Minister for Industry and Commerce and will consist of a maximum of nine members.</P>
    <P>Senators will recall that it had been hoped to keep industry in close touch with the work of the Institute through the Council, which comprises in addition to the members of the Industrial Research Committee and of the Standards Committee, not more than fifty ordinary members, who are appointed for their special attainments in this sphere.  In passing I should like to pay a tribute here to the members of the present and past Councils for the selfless service they have rendered.  The rôle of the Council was a useful one in the formative years of the Institute, though the results achieved were, perhaps, more modest than we had hoped for.  Under the new developments which are proposed there will no longer be a need for a Council, and, arrangements are being made to discontinue its functions.  Instead, the new Board is being given authority to appoint such <i>ad hoc</i> Committees as it sees fit to assist and advise it in <Col N="732" /> carrying out its functions.  The revised arrangements now proposed should have the effect of introducing greater flexibility into the conduct of the Institute's affairs, of broadening the base of the Institute, and of giving it more latitude in determining the appropriate industrial and scientific contact which should be enlisted to help towards the solution of specific problems.</P>
    <P>The functions of the reconstituted Institute will be, broadly, similar to those of the present Institute.  It is proposed, however, to vest the Institute with authority, where the public interest so requires, to undertake or assist in the development or exploitation of inventions.  It is felt that this would be a desirable extension of the existing powers of the Institute in relation to scientific research.</P>
    <P>Under present legislation, the maximum annual grant from funds provided by the Oireachtas which may be made to the Institute for expenses of administration is £35,000.  It is proposed to remove this limit, and to arrange that, each year, the Minister for Industry and Commerce, with the concurrence of the Minister for Finance, will propose in the Estimates, for approval by the Oireachtas of whatever amounts are required to meet the capital or current expenditure.  With the expansion of industrial enterprise in this country, with the greater awareness which we may expect from industrialists of the necessity for a scientific approach to problems relating to production, we may anticipate an increase in the demands likely to be made on the services of the Institute in the future.  Three new laboratories have recently been completed and handed over to the Institute.  The removal of the statutory limit on the level of the annual State grant should ensure that the Institute will not be prevented by lack of funds from using the new laboratories to the best possible advantage.</P>
    <P>This greater flexibility in regard to financial matters should I feel be accompanied by similar flexibility in regard to staffing arrangements.  At present, the numbers, grades, remuneration and conditions of service <Col N="733" /> of the staff are subject to the approval of the Minister for Industry and Commerce, given with the consent of the Minister for Finance.  The new Bill is designed to remove this control, except for such posts in the Institute's service as are designated by the Minister for Industry and Commerce as posts of special responsibility.  The change proposed will, it is hoped, make it easier for the Institute to recruit suitable personnel for the various posts in the organisation.  The number of posts likely to be designated as special posts will be very few&mdash; perhaps one or two.  The posts equivalent to Chief Scientific officer or chief administration officer may be ones which I will designate.</P>
    <P>The connection between the Institute and industry which it was created to serve should be as intimate as possible. Towards this end, provision is made in the Bill whereby industrial firms and other bodies may become associated with the Institute on payment of an annual fee, in return for which they can become entitled to certain facilities from the Institute. The exact terms of the relationship which will thus be created between the Institute and the associated firms will be a matter to be worked out by the Institute.</P>
    <P>In regard to standard marks, the Bill provides that certain functions, which are at present exercised by the Minister for Industry and Commerce, are transferred to the Institute, and some other minor amendments which appear desirable in the light of experience, are also proposed.  The most important change in this respect is that which empowers the Institute to grant a licence to use a standard mark.  This is at present a function of the Minister for Industry and Commerce. I think, however, that it is advisable that the Institute should continue to prepare specifications on the basis of a programme and priority schedules established by the Minister for Industry and Commerce.</P>
    <P>The Bill also provides for the prescription by the Minister for Industry and Commerce of compulsory standards for certain commodities intended for sale.  In recent years, public attention <Col N="734" /> has been focussed on the fact that there is no power to prevent the sale to the public of articles which may constitute a hazard to life or health.  The provision to which I have referred seeks to remedy this deficiency, and it is the intention normally to utilise the powers involved only for the protection of life and health.  There is no intention to make compulsory the ordinary standard specifications which will be drawn up by the Institute.</P>
    <P>The Bill makes other provisions in regard to finances, accounts, and audits, annual reports, Board procedure, offices and premises, and other matters, which are generally on the lines of those approved by the Oireachtas for other State sponsored bodies.</P>
    <P>In regard to the general merits of the Bill, I feel that there will be general agreement with a measure which is designed to improve the working of such a key establishment as the Instistute for Industrial Research and Standards. This Bill will, I believe, have this effect.  The day has long gone when Industry could afford to carry on from year to year with the same old processes and practices, and in every country it is increasingly recognised that scientific research is essential to any worthwhile development of resources in the industrial field.  This is more than ever important for this country which has limited natural resources, and the additional handicap, so far as human resources are concerned, of a lack of tradition in industrial and managerial skills.  For this reason, there is a very urgent need for industrial research to improve technical processes and techniques, to develop new processes and new products, to promote the use of substitutes and byproducts, and to eliminate waste.</P>
    <P>This research is expensive, and the smaller type of industrial firm which we have in this country is often not in a position to provide the skilled staff and the laboratory equipment needed to conduct research with a view to establishing newer, more efficient and cheaper ways of making a better article.  The Institute exists as a central organisation to provide these facilities for industry.  It has, or will have, the <Col N="735" /> skilled staff and the equipment to do the job.  I should like to see a greater awareness among industrialists firstly of the need for scientific research and secondly, of the great advantages which they can achieve from utilising the services which the Institute provides for them.  This Bill represents an effort at improving the organisation of the Institute and giving it more independence with a view to improving its working and making it a better servant of industry.</P>
    <Speaker pid="EdwardMcGuire" hpid="Mr. McGuire Mr. McGuire">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGuire</NameTxt>
      <P>This measure is a very acceptable one and one which I am sure we must all welcome.  Quite clearly, it makes improvements in this Institute that could be of the greatest value to our industrial economy.  The improvements, as the Minister has said, are the result of some 15 years' experience which the Institute has had, and now, as a result of that experience, this Bill makes the Institute more flexible both administratively and financially. The machinery has been cut down to a very much more manageable and workable size and should, therefore, be much more flexible and much more satisfactory on the financial side, instead of being rigidly bound by the grant of a fixed sum.  There is provision also to provide whatever sum becomes necessary in the light of experience of the needs of the Institute.</P>
      <P>We have now had some 40 years' experience in building up the industrial economy of the country.  We are all interested in this industrial drive which is really the very lifeblood of our whole existence.  Everyone, in fact, in the community is concerned to see that we have an efficient industrial economy, and it behoves our industrialists to realise the vital necessity of having our articles well made, well designed and above all, competitive in price.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>On the other hand, it is most important that the trade unions and their worker members should co-operate not only in aiming at better things, but in achieving the highest standard products. The absence of standards was a fault inherent in the building up of the hurried industrial economy which we had to undertake for the past 40 years, because of the high protection <Col N="736" /> barriers which had to be raised in order to shelter our infant industries which, at the beginning, were lacking in capital and the know-how we have now learned.  I think we can say we are at the take-off period and are in a position to do bigger and better things, especially from the purely economic points of view of saturation on our home market and the necessity for exports to meet our balance of payments problem.  We now have to look to outside markets in which our products must compete.  There we can find no protection and we must meet the cold wind of competition from more experienced and, in some cases up to now, more highly skilled operators than we had here.</P>
    <P>We are facing, probably in company with other countries, the advent of the Common Market in which our products must compete.  We will be drawn into the Common Market inevitably, we think.  It is probably a very good thing that we should be drawn in, and in that market we will have to produce such goods as will compete with the products of the whole of Europe.  Recently I saw a statement made by Dr. Andrews of C.I.E. with which I heartily agree.  I cannot remember the exact words but to paraphrase, he said: &ldquo;It is not only good enough for us to produce our best; we must produce the best.&rdquo;  Very often, our best is not at all good enough, and only the best will enable us to live in the modern world.</P>
    <P>Up to now, the only competition our home industrialists met with was competition from the small amount of goods that infiltrated into our home market and with which they had to compete.  They were very few and far between, and as a result of that lack of competition, a sort of complacency grew up, design was not improved sufficiently, and moreover quality was very often neglected, in the knowledge that the consumer had to take and like what he was presented with, because he had no alternative choice.</P>
    <P>As I say, that position is changing and, therefore, this measure is very timely in that it is designed to continue this Institute.  In Section 6, the ten or 12 functions of the Bill are <Col N="737" /> enumerated.  To sum them up, they are to undertake, encourage and foster scientific research and investigation with the object of achieving economical and efficient use of our resources, and the highest standard and quality. In a few words, that covers the functions of the Institute.</P>
    <P>The Minister has said that the Bill repeals the 1946 and 1954 Acts.  The organisation has been streamlined and its finances have been put on a broader basis.  The unwieldy committee and council, numbering some 50 people, is now being replaced by a board of nine, including the chairman.  The feature I welcome is the idea of <i>ad hoc</i> committees which can be set up to contact industry and industrialists at all required levels and all required times. That is a much better way of getting into contact with the industrialists and with those people who should look to this Institute for guidance and help.</P>
    <P>One of the complaints in the past of such institutions, artistic as well as scientific, has been the difficulty of getting industrialists to take the advice and help which is often there for them to receive, even for nothing.  I had experience of that myself in the Arts Council where we tried to take certain steps to help industrial design and so on.  We found there was very little approach from people who should have approached us and accepted the free help and advice which was there for them.  I trust this Institute will not wait to be asked.  I hope it will take positive steps to see that their services are utilised even by unwilling patients.</P>
    <P>I do not want to say very much on this Bill because I think the Bill speaks for itself.  I welcome the scientific approach to the question of the improvement in standards of industrial production.  No matter what scientific research we bring to bear upon our industrial production, it must be borne in mind that the human factor is the most important one in achieving success. Unless men's minds are made ready and willing to use and apply scientific knowledge to their everyday work, the good work of the Institute will be negatived.</P>
    <P>Production has undoubtedly made some industrialists and some workers <Col N="738" /> far too complacent and satisfied with their existing circumstances and far too unwilling to adopt new and more efficient methods of industrial activity, but, in fairness, it must be said, however, that there are many industrialists nowadays, in view of what has been impressed upon them by our Government and by the knowledge that the Common Market is something that is looming up in the near future, who are making every possible effort to increase their productivity, to make their goods competitive in both price and quality and who are prepared to meet whatever situation may arise in the future when they may no longer rely upon the protective tariffs and measures which have been sheltering them from competition by other countries.</P>
    <P>I have already made a slight reference to the importance of workers on their side giving every help in the application of scientific means and methods to their factories and workshops.  We can take heart from the things happening at the moment as between employers and the trade unions who are now making an effort to see what can be done about increasing productivity.  The question of the introduction of scientific methods in our operations here is of primary importance.  It is one in relation to which we can never get anywhere, unless the employers and the workers as well are willing to sit down together and work out some harmonious method which will enable them not only to agree to making use of these modern scientific methods of production but also to feel that they are getting a square deal and a fair share of the extra wealth and extra productivity created, never forgetting, of course, that they must not just merely divide the fruits of this improvement among themselves but that the rights of the community and the interests of the community must be borne in mind as well.  If the happy result is secured whereby employers, workers and the community are all made to share in the benefits of productivity, I think we can look forward to a successful future for our industrial economy in this country.  In that hope, I should <Col N="739" /> like to welcome this Bill which makes a very big contribution to this scientific step forward which we would all like to see.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickQuinlan" hpid="Professor Quinlan Professor Quinlan">
      <NameTxt>Professor Quinlan</NameTxt>
      <P>I welcome the spirit of this Bill in that it shows that the Government and the country as a whole are becoming aware of the importance of scientific endeavour and scientific research which will enable us to hold our place in the modern world. The Bill is to be welcomed on that account but I am very sorry that such a major step as this was not preceded by a period of at least external investigation leading to the preparation of a White Paper on this whole question of industrial research and its co-ordination with other research in this country.  We missed a valuable opportunity. The only conclusion that we must arrive at is that the scheme has been the result of an internal effort in the Department of Industry and Commerce.</P>
      <P>That is not a good enough approach to modern scientific work because, good and all as the administrators in any State Department are, they cannot of themselves comprehend the problems that arise above all in coordinating and developing industrial research.  I am not aware that there is within the Department any regular research section that could claim to have the competence to do this.  I am sorry this opportunity was missed but even at this late stage, if we do some clear thinking on the co-ordination of research, we may be able to chart the way for this re-organisation of the Institute, because we must, first of all, be quite clear on the divisions of research.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>There is at one end of the spectrum what I think most people here would call research, that is, solving some problem for industry, making tests or prescribing some standards of excellence and so on but that is only what one would call routine research.  It is a type of research, of course, which those engaged in it should have done over and over again.  There is nothing new in it; it is everyday routine work. It is just like calling in a medical man. <Col N="740" /> In most cases, he is on routine work and he applies routine techniques, but the medical adviser has to know more than that.  He has to be able to cope with the unusual.</P>
    <P>Similarly in research work, you must be able to rise above the routine and come to the next level of research which is what one might call applied research.  At all stages this presents a challenge because one is striving to do something that has not been done before&mdash;at least it has not been done in that particular way.  To do that, you require a different type of scientist, a man who is abreast of what is happening in the modern scientific world. Over and above that, you have what is called pure science, where those interested in it are interested for the sake of science itself and for the sake of collecting knowledge, as, for instance, those scientists who first split the atom.  They were interested only in exploring the mysteries of the atom; yet we see that in the course of the last three decades that has gone from the realm of pure research.  Nobody thought it would lead anywhere, industrially or otherwise.</P>
    <P>Today we find it the scientific work behind nuclear power, the atomic bomb and all the other tremendous applications of that one item.  It is interesting to note that, when the scientists in the 1930 period were working on the splitting of the atom, the public took no interest in their work, but the public despised the chemists because they were the people who were responsible for developing poison gas.  The people engaged in splitting the atom were regarded as harmless and doing something which could never have any real application.  It shows how the levels all link up together.  What has been pure research in this category provides the ideas behind the research in the following category.</P>
    <P>The quicker we translate that applied research into products in our factories, the sooner we will beat our competitors to it.  Competition in modern industrial development is really competition in taking applied research and making it into goods and services.  Therefore, if we we are serious in research development, we must recognise the interdependence of these <Col N="741" /> three branches.  If you try to set up an institution which is solely devoted to routine research, you will find you have a fossil on your hands, one which after 10 years will be completely useless, as far as gaining firsts with applied research are concerned.</P>
    <P>If we were to have all those three together, or even if we were to rule out pure research for the moment, we would, in effect, have to create what is called an institute of technology, or a large scientific department within the universities.  That is the only way it could be organised.</P>
    <P>Those branches must be in continuous inter-communication, passing ideas one from the other.  Above all, there must be a continuous succession of new minds coming in to look at the problem.  Those new minds are provided by the post-graduate students who work in research for four or five years to get their doctorates, working under established scientists.  They are the motive power that draws forth the full potential of those established scientists.  Consequently, you are forced into the system that involves having students as well.  After three or four years, the students get their degrees.  Perhaps the best may be retained on the staff and the others pass on, but you have the lifeblood in them. If we were to set up such an institution, we would have to face an expenditure which would be away beyond our resources.  It would involve an expenditure of anything in the order of £1,000,000 a year.  That would be a small expenditure for such an institution, which would have to be a university centre in itself.</P>
    <P>Recently, I spent a month visiting the Californian Institute of Technology, which is the premier institution for that type of scientific work in the United States.  Their annual budget is in the region of £3,000,000 a year.  They have just completed an extension to their buildings at a cost of £7,000,000 a year.  That is the type of money involved in providing a centre for both applied research and routine facilities.  We cannot do that and therefore we must recognise at this very late stage the essential part that our existing scientific institutions <Col N="742" /> must play in co-ordination with this new body, if it is to give the service which we hope it will give in our industrial development.  That means we must harness the energies in the various departments in our universities. We must recognise that the institution will largely be an institution concerned with what is called routine research.  Therefore, I appeal that all our energies should be harnessed.</P>
    <P>There is a very effective way of harnessing them.  It has been done in many countries.  In England, it has been done through the Department of Scientific and Industrial Research grants and in America, by means of various sponsored research.  What sponsored research means is that you give the institution certain sums of money for certain general scientific investigation. For instance, it might be in the field of making better use of some of our natural products here.  The grants are given to university departments where there are people who are acknowledged as having the capacity and drive and the willingness to undertake that work.  They, in turn, employ many postgraduate students and even post-doctorate students to carry out the main research under the direction of the senior professor concerned.  By that means, you can co-ordinate the efforts here of all our institutions.  That would be to the benefit of the institution and the universities because those in applied research like to see the ultimate use that is made of their discoveries. On the other hand, those engaged in routine research cannot exist in a vacuum, without being closely linked to the other branch.  I appeal that right from the start it should be clearly enunciated that the Government wish to see the maximum of co-ordination between the various scientific centres.</P>
    <P>I think that at least 50 per cent. of the budget of this new body should be spent on sponsoring research.  That would be something very new for this country but it is the modern and efficient way to do it.  I think it is well that the Seanad and the Government should realise that in our universities here we have men of the highest international standards who are capable of holding a position in a university institution <Col N="743" /> anywhere in the world.  Unfortunately, our public relations, or should I say our public press from the universities, ignore the task of letting the people of the country know the achievements of our people and what they are doing.</P>
    <P>For instance, I might mention that in one department very intimately connected with any applied research for industrial development, the Department of Chemistry, we succeeded less than 12 months ago in attracting back a young scientist from the United States after he had six years' experience there.  We attracted him back at a quarter of the salary he could have secured in the United States.  He came back for £2,000 a year&mdash;having been offered 25,000 dollars in the United States&mdash;and with no prospects of going higher here.  He is back, and he was willing to come back.  He is one of the many who are available in our university institutions.</P>
    <P>Again, we have many young students abroad carrying out post-graduate studies in various university institutions. Only last week, I had the privilege of seeing one of our students head the engineering class in the California Institute of Technology.  These are facts which are scarcely ever made known. We should have full confidence in our young scientists.  Our scientific departments can play their part in the development of our resources, provided they are given adequate help and encouragement and provided above all, that there is co-ordination with the new body.  I agree with what Deputy de Valera said on this topic during the Dáil debate.  I wish to stress it far more and to stress again the importance of co-ordination in the sponsoring of research.</P>
    <P>We come now to some other facets of the Bill.  I am unhappy about the amount of ministerial control embodied in the Bill.  We are in a unique position in this country in that we came so late to the control of our own affairs. Since 1922, we have been forced to do so much by means of State bodies and State boards that it can be said we probably have more State-controlled or State-sponsored industries than almost any other country in western <Col N="744" /> Europe.  There are historical and practical reasons for that.  Yet, we should face up to the fact that wherever there is an opportunity of lessening State control, we should avail of it.  Above all, that occurs in appointing the boards of these bodies.  We cannot always expect that angels like the Minister, his predecessor or his successor, will be in charge.  We must take precautions for the future and try to leave our State structure as invulnerable to absolute State control as we can.  We can do that only by lessening State control everywhere it can reasonably be lessened.</P>
    <P>Here we find that the whole board will be appointed by the Minister.  I think that is very wrong.  We are setting up a scientific institute and there are so many scientific bodies in the country that it should be quite feasible to have the majority of the board appointed directly by those bodies.  I have in mind that the four university centres should contribute at least two, maybe three or four members.  I should prefer three because I would like to get a system of rotation.  I do not like to see institutions sending back the same member time and again.  It would be possible to have rotation, if there were three members.  There are four university centres involved and the rotation itself would ensure there would be a change every nine years, and probably more often.</P>
    <P>We also have the Institute of Civil Engineers of Ireland.  Engineers are very much concerned with industrial development and make a large contribution to it.  It is only right and proper that <i>pro tem</i> the President of the Institute of Civil Engineers should be <i>ex officio</i> a member of the board.  We have also the Institute of Chemists.  We recognise the important part chemists play in our industrial development. The President of that Institute or, if necessary, a nominee of that body, could fill a similar role.  There is also the Federation of Irish Manufacturers. That body might legitimately feel they should have an <i>ex officio</i> representative. There are probably one or two others.  That would probably bring the representation from those sources to six and after that, the Minister could nominate, say, a minority of three or <Col N="745" /> four.  That would be a far healthier board and it would command much more confidence.</P>
    <P>Again, I am rather worried about the power the Minister is taking to designate special posts as posts that cannot be filled without his consent.  I understand that the intention is merely to keep salary control on those posts so that by controlling the salaries at the top, they will not be allowed to get out of step with corresponding grades in other services.  If we are concerned about industrial research, we must get the top men, and we must pay them salaries that are out of line with the salaries paid to administrators.  We must recognise the fact that today science commands a far higher salary than administration or at least it is tending that way and will tend still further in that direction in the future.</P>
    <P>I believe that to designate posts solely for the purpose of controlling salaries is a very retrograde step. We must have confidence in the board itself that it will husband its resources and will not pay more than it has to. In any case, the board must present its budget to the Minister to get an allotment for the following year. Surely the salaries will be shown in that budget, and the Minister will have an opportunity there to object, if he thinks the board has been extravagant.</P>
    <P>The section says that a member shall be appointed &ldquo;by reason of his attainments in scientific research&rdquo;. That is a wonderful phrase but what does it mean?  It means absolutely nothing until you sit down and define what &ldquo;attainments in scientific research&rdquo; are.  What does it mean? Does it mean a man who has had post-graduate training or does it mean that he has to have a published work in the research field?  I think that any scientific interpretation of those words would hold that is so.</P>
    <P>If that is the case, the Minister's choice is narrowed down to the choosing of university members alone. I do not think it would be right to <Col N="746" /> narrow it down so far.  The phrase in relation to &ldquo;attainments in scientific research&rdquo; is ridiculous.  It is ridiculous from the point of view of judging those attainments.  Again, while I pay the highest tribute to the officers of the Minister's Department, I must challenge any suggestion that there is anybody in the Department engaged in scientific research.  I doubt if there is anybody in the Department who has done scientific research. Consequently, how can you judge something that you have not done or been trained in?</P>
    <P>That is the dilemma of the administrator trying to step outside his field and make decisions on something away beyond his competence.  In normal circumstances, such an administrator will have the assistance of scientific people to advise him.  I am not aware that such a situation exists in the Department and if it did exist, we should quickly transfer it to this Institute.</P>
    <P>Again, there is this fact.  Fees are paid to members of the board for services rendered to the board.  That is a rather dangerous provision.  It is dangerous in the sense that it makes it rather tempting for members to hang on to the board.  Consequently, it encourages the approach of exercising a little political pressure to ensure that you are renominated after your three year period.  I would prefer to see in respect of members of the board who played an active part in it and who were recognised as leaders in research that quite considerable grants be made available to such a person's department and graduate students to carry on.  That would be a far better and more beneficial use of the money involved.  That also would be a privilege which would not end when the member ceased to be a member of the board, because if his research work was good enough, the research sponsorship department would carry on as before.  Such a temptation of monetary rewards like this is rather doubtful.</P>
    <P>Let me now refer to Section 11 of the Bill which is totally repugnant to the autonomy of any research institute. I ought not to use the word &ldquo;autonomy&rdquo;<Col N="747" /> in relation to this board because there is so much Ministerial control in it that it is only the shadow of autonomy but even that shadow is considerably worsened by Section 11 whereby the Minister may remove a member from office simply by notification in writing giving the reasons which the Minister considers sufficient. When you appoint for a three-year period, the necessity for this obnoxious clause is hard to see.  Again, who is to advise the Minister that a member of the board is not doing his duty?  It would be quite possible to say that the only way he would probably fail would be by not attending.  It would be possible to stipulate that a member would cease to be a member of the board, if he were absent from 50 per cent. of the meetings in any one year.  That would be a reasonable and automatic provision but I do not like this.</P>
    <P>When we come to the composition of the board, I might mention the parallel with the Agricultural Institute where the majority of the members are appointed by the organisation concerned. I do not see why there should be such a radical difference between a board set up to do research in agriculture and a board set up to do industrial research and why there should be far more State control in respect of one than the other.</P>
    <P>Again, we have this obnoxious Section 13 which goes on to brand members of this House and the other House as undesirable persons.  It has been modified in its passage through the Dáil to the extent that at least by becoming a candidate for the House, you do not cease to be a member of the board but that is not enough.  If a man is entitled to membership of the board, then membership of any House should be no barrier to him.</P>
    <P>Let us have a look at the parallel provided in regard to another institute we have in this country&mdash;the Institute for Advanced Studies in Merrion Square.  There is no such provision in respect of that board.  I have been a member for at least five years and no cognisance has been taken of the fact.  In any case, I think we should use every effort to get rid of those <Col N="748" /> outmoded restrictions.  I welcome that part of Section 13 of the Bill which refers to either an officer or a servant of the board becoming a member of either House of the Oireachtas.  He can get leave of absence.</P>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I think the Senator is going into a shade too much detail on Second Reading.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickQuinlan" hpid="Professor Quinlan Professor Quinlan">
      <NameTxt>Professor Quinlan</NameTxt>
      <P>I am just discussing the general principle involved.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>We have got the general principle.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickQuinlan" hpid="Professor Quinlan Professor Quinlan">
      <NameTxt>Professor Quinlan</NameTxt>
      <P>With your leave, I will pass on.  I should like to remark, however, that it does not go as far as they go in the Netherlands.  In the Netherlands, any official or any member of any body, public or private, can get leave of absence from his post and the difference in salary, if it exists, between his allowance as a Deputy or Senator and his pay in his post must be made up.  Consequently, it is established that by answering the call of public service, any public servant or company servant will not lose.  I think that so long as Section 13 stands as it is, we need have no fear that it will ever be used because I cannot see any higher official of this board voluntarily accepting even £1,000 a year or any other allowance in the Dáil, of which £500 is regarded as expenses&mdash;in other words, dropping his income to £10 a week in order to serve.  Certainly his family would suffer very severely.</P>
      <P>Many of the other points I want to raise can be better raised on Committee Stage when I hope to put down a number of amendments.  I have endeavoured to speak as one who has some connection with research work and as one who has done such and, therefore, appreciates some of the difficulties.  I appeal to the Minister to stress the co-ordination between the universities and this new body, if it is to do the work we hope it will do.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryDavidson" hpid="Miss Davidson Miss Davidson">
      <NameTxt>Miss Davidson</NameTxt>
      <P>I should like to give a very warm welcome to the Bill because it seeks to widen and strengthen the working of what I consider a most valuable body, the Institute of Industrial Research and Standards.  If this Institute is enabled <Col N="749" /> to function even more effectively than it has been doing it can be of the greatest possible value to manufacturers and consumers alike.  If its functions are properly availed of, it can do a very great deal to enhance the reputation of Irish manufactured goods and by so doing, increase the demand for them on both the home and export markets.</P>
      <P>The proposals to concentrate the functions of the Institute in a board would appear to make for greater efficiency and achieve better results from the activities of the Institute.  I am glad to see that the Bill gives power to the Institute to make compulsory standards for articles or substances which constitute hazards to life and health and I hope this will be enforced in the firmest possible way.  I do not know whether the Institute will deal only with articles and substances manufactured here but in regard to health hazards, I would like the Minister to direct their attention to the position in relation to cosmetics, most of which are imported and some of which have proved harmful to eyes and skin, but which are often marked as being highly beneficial in their effects.  This may be considered a small matter but when we remember that such things can be, and are, purchased by mere school children, there should be some safeguard where there is the slightest risk of skin or eye irritation.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>On this point, it might be possible, although I am not sure if it would come under this Bill, to prevent cosmetic firms from extracting very considerable amounts of money by absurd claims for their products.  In the United States of America, there are Federal Committees whose function it is to compel advertisers to refrain from making false claims for their products, including cosmetics, cigarettes, medical goods, etc.  These committees publish in the Press the names of the manufacturers and the names of the offending articles. From time to time, there appear in the American Press notices which state that such-and-such a firm have been notified to refrain from claiming that their materials are non-shrink, colour-fast, and in one case I recall that furs which were being advertised were rabbit <Col N="750" /> fur and not musquash, as was stated.</P>
    <P>Many of us are &ldquo;Buy Irish&rdquo; minded and many of us have been humiliated to hear visitors being recommended to take non-Irish goods, with the recommendation that they are much better. Unfortunately, this is sometimes true and it is here that the Institute can be of very great value by indicating to the public, by means of a distinctive mark, that the goods offered have been passed by the Institute and comply with certain stated standards of design and material.  I know there is an Irish standard mark but as far as I know, it is not in very wide use.  It is used only in a very limited way and the mark is not very attractive.  I should like to see a much more attractive design.</P>
    <P>I have seen garments, particularly those for children and women which are sometimes made of good material but are so badly designed, so badly sewn with inferior thread that they parted into the original cut-out pieces after one wearing and one wash.  On the other hand, I have seen material sold as &ldquo;all wool Irish tweed&rdquo;, and I have even seen it used in school uniforms. While it can truthfully be described as all-wool, such a description can only injure the Irish tweed trade because it is not Irish tweed as we know it.  This so called Irish tweed is made of the poorest shoddy, attractively dyed.  There is a great need to fix a standard which will guide the uninitiated citizen, or our tourists, to understand that Irish tweed is manufactured from live, springy wool and not from rewoven wool waste which is known as shoddy.  This standard should apply to all material and articles being sold as wool.</P>
    <P>A costly item in the budget of the average household is the school uniform.  If standards were fixed for both the material and the making, much expense would be eliminated.  I have seen expensive school uniforms that simply faded away after a term's wear.  I have seen uniforms so badly made that they had to be entirely remade by the manufacturer before they could be worn&mdash;all adding, of course, to the cost of production and to the cost to the parents.  If such garments bore the mark of the Standards Institute, parents could buy with confidence, <Col N="751" /> knowing that the price did not include the charge for a possible remaking afterwards.  If the garment eventually proved unsatisfactory, the purchaser would know where to go to seek redress because of its having carried the standard label.</P>
    <P>I can see the difficulty of trying to compel manufacturers to produce all their goods up to a specified standard but if the public came to understand the significance of the mark, they would soon learn to discriminate.  Therefore, I should like the Minister to recommend to the Institute the production of a distinctive, attractive emblem or mark to indicate that the article has been passed by the Institute, and also that wide publicity be given to this purchaser's safety mark.  Press publicity is most essential to ensure success in this matter.  Slogans should be drawn up such as &ldquo;Buy wisely&mdash; look for this mark...&rdquo; and a clear picture given of the mark of the Standards Institute, a design which would be as easily recognised and described as the British mark.  The public would soon learn to look for the mark, with the result that, by public demand, all firms would be forced to apply to have their goods tested and approved so that they might bear the mark.</P>
    <P>It will be recalled how, during the Emergency period, when most goods were rationed and clothing, etc., had to last for long periods, the public came to seek out these garments which bore the &ldquo;utility&rdquo; label because it indicated that the garment was of good quality, having passed certain tests, and was within a certain stated price range.  This mark was very simple and easily recognisable.  If the public are made aware that a particular mark indicates a certain guarantee, they will look for it and the shoddy, get-rich-quick manufacturer will be well and truly on the way out.  I would stress, however, that the success of the standard mark depends on its being an outstanding one, made familiar to everyone through press and other publicity.</P>
    <P>There are many other forms of manufactures that would benefit from <Col N="752" /> the use of the standard label but it would take too much time to mention them all.  I should like, however, to refer to the manufacture of furniture. Much poor quality furniture is being manufactured here today and the application of the standards mark would be a useful guide, particularly to inexperienced buyers, such as young people setting up homes.  They could be saved much expense if they were helped to sort out the good from the bad that will have to be scrapped after a short time in use.</P>
    <P>In regard to articles made of wood, the standard mark should indicate that the materials used have been treated against the ravages of woodworm and furniture beetle, very destructive pests that have increased greatly in recent years.  These pests could ruin the structure of the house in which such furniture is placed.</P>
    <P>In the matter of upholstery, mattresses and such like, the standard mark should indicate that the materials used have been sterilised and that they conform to certain standards of hygiene as well as to certain standards of workmanship.  In this country, where we are constantly seeking to improve our exports, I cannot think of anything more valuable to manufacturers, old and new, than an Institute of this kind.  We should be generous in our financial support of its work and should do everything in our power to give publicity to its work and its possibilities.</P>
    <P>It is true to say that many people do not know of the existence of the Institute of Research and Standards. That is something that must be put right.  Without publicity for its work, the value of the organisation is greatly lessened.  A publicity campaign should be initiated as soon as the Bill is passed.  I am glad to give the Bill the fullest support.</P>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I understand it was arranged that the House would take the Report Stage of the Courts of Justice and Court Officers (Superannuation) Bill, 1961, at 5.30 p.m.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamStanford" hpid="Professor Stanford Professor Stanford">
      <NameTxt>Professor Stanford</NameTxt>
      <P>Might I inquire is it intended to adjourn for tea and <Col N="753" /> then resume the debate on the Second Stage of the Industrial Research and Standards Bill, 1961?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>There will be a tea interval until 8 o'clock and then we will resume on this Bill.</P>
      <P>Debate adjourned.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Courts of Justice and Court Officers (Superannuation)" RHead="Bill, 1961&mdash;Report and Final Stages">
    <Title>Courts of Justice and Court Officers (Superannuation) Bill, 1961&mdash;Report and Final Stages.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOQuigley" hpid="Mr. O'Quigley Mr. O'Quigley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Quigley</NameTxt>
      <P>I move the following recommendation:&mdash;</P>
      <P>In page 8, between lines 6 and 7, to insert the following:&mdash;</P>
      <P>&ldquo;Every regulation made by the Minister under this Act shall be laid before each House of the Oireachtas as soon as may be after it is made and if a resolution annulling the regulation is passed by either House within the next 21 days in which that House has sat after the regulation is laid before it, the regulation shall be annulled accordingly but without prejudice to the validity of anything previously done under the regulation.&rdquo;</P>
      <P>I do not exaggerate when I say I was pretty alarmed at the notion that regulations would be made by the Minister for Finance under this Bill, without their being laid before each House of the Oireachtas.  I want, first of all, to disabuse the Minister's mind of any idea that this Bill is in any way comparable in its application with the Civil Service (Superannuation) Act.  There is all the difference in the world between people who hold office at the will and pleasure of the Government, such as civil servants, and people who are established under the Constitution to hold office completely independently of the Government and who can be displaced and removed only under the most strict conditions laid down in the Constitution.</P>
      <P>Article 35 of the Constitution provides:</P>
      <P>All judges shall be independent in the exercise of their judicial functions and subject only to this Constitution and the law.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The intention of this recommendation <Col N="754" /> is to provide that the judges will not in any way be subject to the Minister for Finance and that if regulations have to be made they shall be made by the Minister for Finance and thereafter appear before Parliament, so that Parliament can decide whether or not they should be made.  The fundamental principle is that the judges in relation to their superannuation or in relation to any other matter shall not be subject to the Minister for Finance. That is the main purpose of the recommendation.</P>
    <P>In Section 6 of the Bill, we find that the Minister for Finance may make regulations relating to whether or not judges of the Supreme Court, the High Court and the Circuit Court can avail themselves of the provisions of the Bill.  He can make regulations with regard to notification by a person as to whether or not he wishes to avail of the provisions.  He may also make regulations as to whether or not a judge is of sound health.  Those powers should not be vested in any Minister of State over any judge who is supposed to be independent of the Executive.  If such power is necessary, it should be by regulation to be made by the Minister and reviewable by the Houses of the Oireachtas.</P>
    <P>Section 7 runs for nearly three pages of the Bill and deals with the allocation of pensions for the future. That matter is all to be dealt with by regulation, so that the whole of the superannuation code relating to the allocation of pensions by judges will be dealt with by regulation to be made only by the Minister for Finance. That is undesirable and it is something with which this House most certainly cannot agree.</P>
    <P>In that connection, I would point out that without exception every superannuation scheme made under the authority of Parliament is laid before each House of the Oireachtas.  Every amendment to every such superannuation scheme is laid before each House.  This is going altogether too far and I am sure the Minister will agree that it would be claiming too much for a Minister of State&mdash;I do not say this in relation to any particular Minister &mdash;to say he should be given very far-reaching <Col N="755" /> powers which he is supposed to exercise by regulation.</P>
    <P>I believe the necessity for the recommendation is so obvious as not to require me to say anything further on it I very genuinely hope the Minister will accept it.  I trust I was not unduly lengthy in what I have said, but I believe the recommendation is so clearly necessary that the Minister will in fact accept it.</P>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamStanford" hpid="Professor Stanford Professor Stanford">
      <NameTxt>Professor Stanford</NameTxt>
      <P>I want to say a word in support of what has been said by Senator O'Quigley.  The principle he has laid down that the judiciary should be as independent as possible is of supreme importance, and if then they are to be subject to various controls, it is most desirable that that control should be vested in Parliament in the sense that the whole country should be able to make up their minds, through their representatives, on all matters of this kind.  There is, of course, the grave danger&mdash;not under the present Minister but it is an ultimate danger&mdash;that some Minister might put pressure upon the judges, and in unfavourable circumstances a clause of this kind might be used in a most deleterious way.  Senator O'Quigley has put forward a very important point and I hope the Minister will give it the fullest consideration.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OscarTraynor" hpid="Minister for Justice (Mr. Traynor) Oscar Traynor">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Justice (Mr. Traynor)</NameTxt>
      <P>The fears of the Senators are entirely groundless.  Senator O'Quigley knows just as well as I do that these regulations have been operating in respect of the Civil Service scheme, of which this Bill is practically a duplicate, and that regulations do not in any sense affect the tenure of office of the judges, or in any way affect their independence.  I have examined the terms of the recommendation very carefully and I cannot accept it.  I have gone into this question pretty carefully and I am satisfied that the regulations, which will be purely mechanical, will not in any way affect, as I say, the judge's tenure of office or his independence.  They will operate merely in that mechanical fashion such as, for instance, the appointment of a medical officer to decide whether he should or should not grant a certificate to an individual <Col N="756" /> who appears before him to seek that sort of certificate.</P>
      <P>The furthest I can go is to undertake to submit these regulations to the representatives of the various groups affected.  For instance, in the case of the judges, I would undertake to submit the suggested regulations to, say, the Chief Justice in the case of the judges or the Principal District Justice in the case of the district justices and have their views.  I would not be prepared to accept this recommendation and to do something in this Bill that has not been done in other Bills corresponding to it.  I am satisfied in my own mind, and, as I say, I have gone into this question pretty carefully since we had our discussion. There is no ground for the fears which have been expressed by Senator O'Quigley in particular.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Professor Hayes Professor Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Professor Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister's line is a very familiar one&mdash;that this is mechanical and that nothing would be done under these regulations to which anybody could take exception.  The Minister goes further to meet the case which Senator O'Quigley makes and which Senator Stanford supported by saying that he would submit the regulations to the judges or to other interested parties but that is merely saying that he will consult them.  What is being asked here is quite simple.  It does not mean that this matter becomes public.  It simply means that, when these regulations are made, a copy will be placed in the Library and any member of the Oireachtas who wants to read them can do so.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>That is not a very great demand. There is a curious objection to doing this kind of thing.  I do not know what it is.  There is the firm belief that the Minister and officials generally are of great integrity.  I agree. Senator O'Quigley's recommendation does not cast any reflection on anybody. If it were agreed to, it would not hurt anybody.  It would make people feel more comfortable about a matter which is important.  There is no analogy between judges and civil servants.  Even if people are a little too pernickety or too careful about the position of the judges, that <Col N="757" /> is the way they ought to be.  Everybody ought to be in that position.</P>
    <P>The recommendation ought to be agreed to.  If it were inserted it would not hurt anybody.  It would not delay the passage of the Bill if the Minister agreed to it.  He could bring it into the Dáil and the Bill would be law tomorrow morning.  I do not see why he should not do it. It does not give the Oireachtas any more powers.  I presume one could discover by Parliamentary Question what the regulations were but I doubt if that power would ever be invoked. The recommendation gives power to see what the regulations are like.  If this were inserted in the Bill, it would be a safeguard and it would be a good idea as it would mark the distinction between the civil servant who holds office at the will and pleasure of the Government and the judge who has quite a different tenure of office.</P>
    <P>I do not think that the Minister would be at any loss by accepting the recommendation.  I think it would be very desirable.  I should like to appeal to him to waive his objection and accept the recommendation.  If he accepts it, it cannot do any harm to anybody.  It cannot be a precedent for a superannuation Bill.  It is a desirable recommendation and it should be inserted.</P>
    <Speaker pid="DominickMurphy" hpid="Mr. Murphy Mr. Murphy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Murphy</NameTxt>
      <P>I agree in the main with what has been said by Senator Hayes.  The Minister did not make the distinction that Senator O'Quigley was making in regard to the difference between civil servants and judges.  It is no answer to the argument to say that all that is being provided for in this Bill in regard to superannuation or the making of regulations is similar to that which exists in regard to civil servants.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Civil servants are servants of the Government.  We are dealing with judges who are not servants of the Government, as such.  I think it is very desirable that the regulations should be laid upon the Table of the Oireachtas and, furthermore, as is provided for in the recommendation, that they can be annulled by resolution of either House.  The Minister has come some way towards meeting the views put forward by agreeing to undertake to submit <Col N="758" /> the regulations, before they are made, to the representatives of the people concerned.</P>
    <P>What happens if the regulations are not suitable in the view of the people concerned and what happens if the people concerned think that the regulations bring some undue pressure on them?  Apparently, there is no way they can make known their views and there is no appeal they can make, Surely the proper course is that provided in the recommendation that the regulations shall be laid before the Houses of the Oireachtas and be the subject of debate and can be annulled if that is the view of Parliament?</P>
    <P>I hope the Minister will reconsider this matter.  None of us doubts the Minister's integrity or the integrity of any possible successor of the Minister. As Senator Hayes said, we should be pernickety in regard to judges.  Because of that, it is a good recommendation.</P>
    <Speaker pid="DenisBurke" hpid="Mr. Burke Mr. Burke">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Burke</NameTxt>
      <P>I have very little to say except to make this comment.  I do not think the recommendation will in any way restrict the Executive.  If the Minister had said that it would interfere with the administration and make difficult the executive functions of Government, I think there would be some case.  There is the underlying assumption that civil servants for whom we all have the highest respect will not do anything wrong but that, perhaps, Deputies and Senators might, if the regulations were put before them.  It would be much safer for democracy if the assumption were that Deputies and Senators were, just as civil servants, above suspicion, like Caesar's wife.</P>
      <P>There is the assumption that in this country we have a Christian tradition and that our laws will be administered properly.  That is all right but we ought to have good laws.  Somebody recently remarked that the Romans had good laws and savage customs. We ought to have good laws and Christian customs.  There is no reason why we, having Christian customs, should not have good laws.  The Minister ought to concede the point which has been so well put by Senator O'Quigley and other Senators.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="759" />
    <Speaker pid="OscarTraynor" hpid="Mr. Traynor Mr. Traynor">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Traynor</NameTxt>
      <P>The recommendation goes further&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I take it there is no objection to the Minister speaking twice?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Professor Hayes Professor Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Professor Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>There is no objection.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OscarTraynor" hpid="Mr. Traynor Mr. Traynor">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Traynor</NameTxt>
      <P>In the recommendation there is a suggestion that the regulations can be annulled, if necessary. I want to make this point clear, that the terms of this Bill were in the hands of the judiciary for a considerable period and they had the right to examine the draft Bill and to make whatever suggestions they wished to make, and they did make suggestions. Despite the period of time during which the Bill was in their hands, no reference was made good, bad or indifferent, to the suggestion now being made.  We discussed it at length in the Dáil and Deputy Sweetman, who might perhaps be described as the architect of the Civil Service scheme, discussed the Bill at length and this particular point was not raised.  I believe the reason was that there was no necessity to raise it.  There seems to be a suspicion running through the discussion that something sinister or something like that&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOQuigley" hpid="Mr. O'Quigley Mr. O'Quigley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Quigley</NameTxt>
      <P>No.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OscarTraynor" hpid="Mr. Traynor Mr. Traynor">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Traynor</NameTxt>
      <P>&mdash;&mdash;will arise from these regulations.  I think I can allay the fears of the House in that respect. As I said, the regulations, which will not be very numerous, will be purely technical; they will merely arrange that two doctors shall be made available to an applicant rather than one, and other matters of that kind of which I cannot just think at the moment.  As far as I am concerned, this Bill is one of a number of Bills of the same kind and I am not prepared to accept the recommendation, for, if I accept it, I am pretty certain I would also have to amend the other schemes which operate similarly to this.  I am not prepared to do that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I have given an undertaking which goes very far, and for which I am not sure there is a precedent, of submitting the regulations to the appropriate heads of the sections, such as, say, the Chief Justice in the case of the higher <Col N="760" /> judiciary, and the Principal Justice in the case of justices.  If they see anything wrong, or anything which is likely to operate against their best interests, they will have an opportunity to make representations to the Minister for Justice and, in turn, the Minister for Justice can make representations to the Minister for Finance.  I am quite certain that these people are as understanding as any member of this House, or the other House, and they would very quickly realise the necessity to meet the requirements, if they should be met.  From that point of view, I think it is unreasonable to ask me to accept this recommendation without also going into the question of amending other Acts which, as I said, I am not prepared to do.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickQuinlan" hpid="Professor Quinlan Professor Quinlan">
      <NameTxt>Professor Quinlan</NameTxt>
      <P>I should like to appeal to the Minister to accept this recommendation.  The fact that the judiciary have not raised the point, and that it has not been raised in the other House, is no excuse and is no reason why a valid point raised here should not be considered on its merits. Probably the reason it has not been raised is the fact that due to the rigid Party system which we have had at all times, the laying of Orders on the Table of the House is almost valueless. We hope we may have a little more fluidity between the Parties and that members will be prepared to cross the Party line where only details of administration are concerned.  I appeal to the Minister to accept this very reasonable recommendation.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Professor Hayes Professor Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Professor Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>In regard to the point made by the Minister that this matter was not raised in the other House, I have always set my face here against putting down amendments put down by the Opposition in the other House.  In the same way, we should be at liberty to suggest points which were not suggested in the other House.  I do not accept the argument that just because certain people in the other House did not think of something, we have no right, and it is not advisable for us, to do some thinking on our own.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>Nobody said you had no right.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOQuigley" hpid="Mr. O'Quigley Mr. O'Quigley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Quigley</NameTxt>
      <P>The very reason for <Col N="761" /> our existence in this House is to do the kind of thing they do not do in the other House.  The fact that this was not raised by the judges is perhaps due to two causes, one, that the judges did not notice it any more than did those in the Dáil, and two, that the judges did notice it but, as a matter of delicacy, did not raise it with the Minister for Justice.  I do not exclude the second point as being a reason why it was not raised with the Minister.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I do not want to say any more on the recommendation than this.  Before we interrupted business we were dealing with the Industrial Research and Standards Bill, in which, in Section 35, subsection (8), there is a provision that every superannuation scheme shall be laid before each House of the Oireachtas.  The Minister says that this was not done in the Civil Service scheme.  The whole purpose of the <Col N="762" /> recommendation is to emphasise the difference between the judiciary and the Civil Service.  That is the very pith of the recommendation.  Civil servants hold office at the will and pleasure of the Minister for Finance; their conditions of service are controlled by the Minister for Finance; but in relation to the judiciary, it is the Constitution which is the determining authority.  It is absolutely imperative that superannuation regulations should not rest with the Minister but should require the full approval of both Houses of the Oireachtas.</P>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I take it the Senator is pressing the recommendation?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOQuigley" hpid="Mr. O'Quigley Mr. O'Quigley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Quigley</NameTxt>
      <P>The Chair has interpreted my tone correctly.</P>
      <P>Recommendation put.</P>
      <P Just="Center">The Seanad divided: Tá: 18; Níl: 22.</P>
      <P Just="Center">Tá</P>
    </Speaker>
    <table pgwide="1">
      <tgroup cols="2">
        <colspec colname="1" colnum="1" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <colspec colname="2" colnum="2" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry rowsep="1">Barry, Anthony.<br />Burke, Denis.<br />Carton, Victor.<br />Connor, Patrick.<br />Crowe, Patrick.<br />Crowley, Patrick.<br />Davidson, Mary F.<br />Donegan, Patrick.<br />Hayes, Michael.</entry>
            <entry rowsep="1">L'Estrange, Gerald.<br />Murphy, Dominick F.<br />O'Donovan, John.<br />O'Keeffe, James J.<br />O'Quigley, John B.<br />Quinlan, Patrick M.<br />Sheehy Skeffington, Owen L.<br />Stanford, William B.<br />Tunney, James.</entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
    <P Just="Center">Níl</P>
    <table pgwide="1">
      <tgroup cols="2">
        <colspec colname="1" colnum="1" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <colspec colname="2" colnum="2" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry rowsep="1">Ahern, Liam.<br />Brennan, John J.<br />Carter, Frank.<br />Cole, John C.<br />Colley, Harry.<br />Connolly O'Brien, Nora.<br />Crowley, Tadhg.<br />Dillon, Gerard B.<br />Dowdall, Jane.<br />Fitzsimons, Patrick.<br />Hayes, Seán.</entry>
            <entry rowsep="1">Lahiffe, Robert.<br />O Ciosáin, Eamon.<br />O Donnabháin, Seán.<br />O'Dwyer, Martin.<br />O Maoláin, Tomás.<br />O'Reilly, Patrick.<br />O Siochfhradha, Pádraig.<br />O'Sullivan, Ted.<br />Ruane, Thomas.<br />Ryan, Eoin.<br />Walsh, Louis.</entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
    <P Just="Center">Tellers:&mdash;Tá: Senators Donegan and O'Quigley; Níl: Senators Carter and Ó Donnabháin.</P>
    <P>Recommendation declared lost.</P>
    <P>Bill received for final consideration.</P>
    <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That the Bill be returned to the Dáil.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="JohnODonovan" hpid="Dr. O'Donovan Dr. O'Donovan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. O'Donovan</NameTxt>
      <P>I am one of those people in this House who have a conviction about these matters.  I do not know what alternative arrangements will have to be made about matters like the superannuation of judges but they cannot be subordinate to the Executive under the Constitution. I am not saying that any member of the present Executive or any other executive has ever done anything wrong.  I am just saying what the correct interpretation of the Constitution is, in my opinion.  I have no doubt that for the proper interpretation of the Constitution, my opinion is correct in this matter.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="763" /> It is not that we are afraid of anything at the moment or any period we can see, but under our Constitution there are three units, the executive, the judiciary and the legislature.  Each of them must be independent of the other.  They must be so independent that you cannot have people like the judges arguing or discussing with the civil servants of the Executive.</P>
    <P>This business in Section 6 that a person may undergo medical examination under the regulation is not correct at all.  Let the House not misunderstand me.  There could be a deal done on this kind of thing.  I am not suggesting that anybody present can do it but it would be quite possible to do a deal on it.  It could be said that if you agree to be examined, it would all be fixed up.  All that kind of thing is possible.  I think the day is approaching in this country when there will have to be complete segregation of the arrangements for the payment to people attached to the Executive of allowances and pensions and the members of the legislature, people attached to the legislature and the members of the judiciary and the people attached to the judiciary.  That is my idea of what this Bill does not comply with.</P>
    <Speaker pid="EoinRyan2" hpid="Mr. Ryan Mr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>I would suggest that Senator O'Donovan take proceedings in connection with this Bill when he will be as popular with the judiciary as he now is with the members of the Oireachtas.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrankCarter" hpid="Mr. Carter Mr. Carter">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Carter</NameTxt>
      <P>Have his cake and eat it, so to speak.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOQuigley" hpid="Mr. O'Quigley Mr. O'Quigley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Quigley</NameTxt>
      <P>We now have a position where we have enacted a piece of legislation which I would have amended further on Report Stage but Standing Orders did not permit me.  I am going to read part of Section 6 and part of Section 7 and I defy the Minister for Justice or any member of the judiciary to say that it means anything.  Indeed, it just does not mean anything.  In relation to judges' superannuation, we cannot amend the Bill in any way.  I now discover that we have groups of English words which do not mean anything.  I do not know <Col N="764" /> what the Minister for Justice is going to do about it.  It might well be that Senator Ryan, who is so interested in taking proceedings, might get instructions on this from a judge of the High Court and ask him how to construe what I am about to read.</P>
      <P>According to subsection (1) of Section 6, &ldquo;the Minister may, after consultation with the Minister for Justice, make regulations for the purposes of Sections 3 and 5 of this Act.&rdquo;  That is an impeccable piece of drafting.  Subsection (2) of Section 6 is as follows:</P>
      <P>The regulations made under this section may, in particular, make provision with respect to all or any of the following matters:</P>
      <P>(a)  notification by a person of his wish to adopt the provisions of section 2 or section 4, as the case may be, of this Act may be lodged not later than a specified date.</P>
      <P>What does that mean?  If you were to call to your aid the professors of a university who know something about language, they would tell the House that that does not mean anything.  It has not been translated into Irish yet. I do not know how the Translation Staff will manage that one.  Paragraph (b) of subsection (2) of Section 6 says:</P>
      <P>a person shall not be entitled to adopt the provisions of section 2 or 4, as the case may be, of this Act unless the Minister decides that he is of sound health.</P>
      <P>Would the Minister tell us what that means?  It means nothing.  Paragraph (c) of subsection (2) of the same section is as follows:</P>
      <P>where a person is required to undergo medical examination under the regulations he may be required to pay such fee as the Minister may determine in respect of the examination.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I do not know what that means.  I think this is a most disgraceful piece of legislation.  This House could not be allowed even to make an amendment. This is what comes of having too close an affinity with the Civil Service Regulation Act.  I find there is a great correspondence&mdash;indeed, too <Col N="765" /> close a correspondence.  In Section 7 (2) (b), we find the following:</P>
    <P>The regulations under this subsection may, in particular, make provision with respect to all or any of the following matters:</P>
    <P>(i)  notification by a person of the person's wish to make a surrender under this section may be lodged not later than a specified time before the date of retirement,</P>
    <P>That does not mean anything&mdash;it is gibberish.</P>
    <P>Section 7 (2) (b) (ii) states:</P>
    <P>a person shall not be entitled to make a surrender under this section unless the Minister decides that the person is of sound health,</P>
    <P>How is the Minister going to make regulations under these provisions?  The Minister will want to make some kind of inquiry as to how this kind of thing passed through the Draftsman's office and his own office.  The Taoiseach described the report of the Vocational Education Committee as a slovenly document.  I return that compliment on this particular Bill.</P>
    <Speaker pid="EoinRyan2" hpid="Mr. Ryan Mr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>It is a terrible reflection on the Opposition in the Dáil.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOQuigley" hpid="Mr. O'Quigley Mr. O'Quigley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Quigley</NameTxt>
      <P>That may be, but it emphasises most clearly that when it comes to giving a hasty passage to legislation of this kind, one should say &ldquo;No&rdquo;.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>Could we ever induce Senator O'Quigley to become chief draftsman?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOQuigley" hpid="Mr. O'Quigley Mr. O'Quigley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Quigley</NameTxt>
      <P>No.  I would never yield my place in Oireachtas Éireann for that kind of thing&mdash;not for any money.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LiamOBuachalla" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator O'Quigley on the Bill.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOQuigley" hpid="Mr. O'Quigley Mr. O'Quigley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Quigley</NameTxt>
      <P>If these interruptions are made, I must, in courtesy, reply to them.  How does the Minister propose to implement the provision of the Bill in Section 7 (2) (b) (iii):</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>requirement by the Minister of production <Col N="766" /> by a person wishing to make a surrender under this section of any proofs which the Minister may consider necessary (including, in particular, production of a statutory declaration that the proposed grantee (not being the wife of the person) is, in relation to the person, a dependant).</P>
    <P>I could go on with that kind of thing to the mortification of the Minister who must accept responsibility for this slovenliness although he is not responsible for it at all.  I do not want to say any more, lest it be an embarrassment for one for whom I have much respect.  I hope the Minister will say to whoever is responsible for this that this is a Bill which cannot be implemented and I suggest he had better repeal it and re-enact it.</P>
    <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Business" RHead="of Seanad">
    <Title>Business of Seanad.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="LiamOBuachalla" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>In case a remark I made at the commencement of business might be misunderstood, I should like to say for the information of Senators that the Reporting Staff available for the House is obviously depleted and that there may be some delay in getting out the Official Reports.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OwenSkeffington" hpid="Dr. Sheehy Skeffington Dr. Sheehy Skeffington">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Sheehy Skeffington</NameTxt>
      <P>I should like it to be understood that if the House is being asked to adjourn until 8 o'clock, I for one do not think we should do so.  The matter of the sittings of the House was referred to the Committee on Procedure and Privileges and it decided that we should sit at our normal hour of 3 o'clock in order to conduct business normally. Now we find that because of the failure of negotiating machinery&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LiamOBuachalla" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I should point out to the Senator that the adjournment is to accommodate the Inter-Parliamentary Union&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>It is meeting at 7 o'clock.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OwenSkeffington" hpid="Dr. Sheehy Skeffington Dr. Sheehy Skeffington">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Sheehy Skeffington</NameTxt>
      <P>I am aware of that but it quite frequently happens that committees such as that meet <Col N="767" /> while the House is sitting and I should not like to feel we are&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LiamOBuachalla" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>This arrangement was reached at the special request of many Senators.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OwenSkeffington" hpid="Dr. Sheehy Skeffington Dr. Sheehy Skeffington">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Sheehy Skeffington</NameTxt>
      <P>I should like to say on behalf of the Independents that we might be consulted before this kind of thing is put before the House.  I do not think that is an unreasonable request.</P>
      <P>
        <i>Business suspended at</i> 6.25 <i>p.m. and resumed at</i> 8 <i>p.m.</i></P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Industrial Research and Standards Bill," RHead="1961&mdash;Second Stage (Resumed)">
    <Title>Industrial Research and Standards Bill, 1961&mdash;Second Stage (Resumed).</Title>
    <P>Question again proposed: &ldquo;That the Bill be now read a Second Time.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamStanford" hpid="Professor Stanford Professor Stanford">
      <NameTxt>Professor Stanford</NameTxt>
      <P>Everyone seriously interested in the future prosperity of our country will certainly welcome this Bill. We are living in an age, as everyone knows, of ruthless technological competition and unless we gather all our forces, we simply will not survive in this competitive world.  Very often, when these drastic developments are put into operation, the work of some smaller private or voluntary bodies is affected.  This evening, very briefly, I should like to refer to one voluntary body which will be affected to some extent by this Bill.  I should like the Minister to give the position his sympathetic consideration, as I am sure he will.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The body I have in mind is the Institute of Irish Inventors, founded about four years ago by some citizens of Dublin and of the country in general. It collected a very fine body of advisers and has a hard-working committee, and for nearly four years now, it has been pursuing its objectives very effectively in its quiet and small way. I should like to mention two of the objects which this Institute of Irish Inventors has before it: (1) To assist the members by giving advice on the protection of their ideas, suitability of inventions, marketing, and patents; to <Col N="768" /> encourage potential inventors to pursue their idea so as to ensure a useful flow of ideas to the market and to form a link between the inventor and the various sources of information, supply and demand; (2) to provide a panel of experts to assess the commercial potentialities of a novelty or device and to give advice on the best method of manufacture and marketing.</P>
    <P>Clearly, a good deal of this effort will be taken over by the reconstituted Institute.  What I should like to know is what is the future of the Institute of Irish Inventors?  It has no paid staff; it has no property; it has no offices except those given by voluntary support About a year ago I understand some representatives of the Institute approached the Minister's Department. They had very friendly discussions with some of the officials and they came away hopeful that perhaps they might get some Government support.  With that in mind, the Institute has not been as active within the past year as in previous years.  The Institute knew something was brewing and developing and held its hand.</P>
    <P>During the past year or so, the Institute has mostly confined its activities to affording help and advice on a purely personal and voluntary basis to inventors, because the introduction of legislation was apparently impending.</P>
    <P>The problem for us in the House and I think for the Minister is whether an Institute of that kind can continue to serve its useful function under this legislation.  The newly reconstituted Institute will take over a good many of its functions and, what is more, the newly constituted Institute will take over most of the lucrative inventions. I imagine that if any one of these Irish inventors has something that is likely to be really valuable for Irish industry, he will, of course, go to the Industrial Research Institute from this private body.</P>
    <P>On the other hand, as Senator Quinlan was saying, it is unwise to draw too firm a line between commissioned industrial research and what we might call free invention.  Very often, it is the crack-pot inventor, or the person who is believed to be a crack-pot inventor, who really turns up <Col N="769" /> with something of immense value not only to his country but the whole world.  That has happened in the past.  It is the eccentric who sometimes produces the unusual and valuable invention.</P>
    <P>I suggest that this small but effective body can still serve a useful purpose but its sources of revenue which are very small will be probably considerably diminished by the new body set up under the Bill.  I wonder what the Minister's policy in a matter of this kind would be?  Would he be prepared either under this Bill or by some separate provision to give some funds to this Institute of Irish Inventors to help them to work parallel with his own Industrial Research Institute? Personally, I think that for the sake of the country, it would be worth doing. This Institute is able, on a kind of personal direction basis, to do what a big Government institute sometimes cannot do.  I think something will be lost if this Institute completely goes out of operation, as there is some risk, although I hope it will not come to that.</P>
    <P>I would ask the Minister if there is any possibility that he could either under this Bill or in some other way find funds to help this voluntary organisation.  It has, amongst others, on its list of patrons a Nobel prizewinner and several other distinguished Irish scientists and industrialists.  It is not a completely negligible body by any means.  The Minister would be well advised to consider its welfare and how this Bill will affect it.</P>
    <P>Another measure the Minister might consider is to give one of its leading members representation on the board which is being set up under this Bill so that at least there will be some kind of liaison between the Institute of Irish Inventors and the Industrial Research Institute.  I know there is a certain risk that when these very desirable and necessary developments are put into operation, small and valuable bodies will be swept aside.  I know that the Minister is broad-minded enough to realise that it is not always the big, highly-organised body that gets all the good results, that occasionally the small <Col N="770" /> rather personally run bodies can produce very surprisingly valuable results. While welcoming this Bill otherwise, I would appeal to the Minister to take this matter into account and do what he can do to keep this useful element in our society going as strongly as it has been going in the past.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickSDonegan" hpid="Mr. Donegan Mr. Donegan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Donegan</NameTxt>
      <P>In every country, there is a necessity for legislation and for an institute such as this in relation to standards as was so ably pointed out by Senator Quinlan.  The present scope of the Institute and any future scope it can have is, in fact, extremely limited in relation to the extraordinary efforts that are being made in this field both commercially and otherwise.  Senator Quinlan envisaged almost a teaching institute&mdash;an institute involving study as well as investigation by the ordinary people employed there.  Having regard to the size of this country and the relatively small amount of large industries in it, we must be satisfied with the type of Institute that is now being set up.  It is wise that we should realise that we cannot expect wonders from this organisation.</P>
      <P>Where this Institute can do a valuable job is in the setting up of standard specifications and standard marks. When a product is sold, the fact that there is legislation in respect of it and a scientific description of the project laid down by law is of great value and will be availed of in the law courts. Where goods arrive in a country and where it would be most expensive to send them back, such a system of arbitration has long been in use.  If, for instance, animal foods do not come up to the standard specification, then the samples are taken in a certain way and sent to London for arbitration when the prices are altered, the goods rejected or some other recommendation made.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The most commonly known instance of specification started during the war and was carried on here afterwards. It related to the meat content of sausages.  I am sure the Institute for Industrial Research and Standards could lay down specifications which would be of value to the consumer, the legitimate producer or the legitimate manufacturer over a wide field. <Col N="771" /> At the same time, there are difficulties in the way.  It is not unwise to remark on the fact that not so long ago an institute such as this ruled on a certain non-alcoholic beverage and pronounced it not to be of the type described on the label.  Arguments have been put forward since that the physical properties might have tended to give that impression but at the same time, other properties in that particular mixture would give the desired results as set out on the label.</P>
    <P>These are things that we all know and read about in international magazines.  They do point out that the Institute for Industrial Research and Standards is not the be-all and the end-all of the specifications of a product.  A sedative might be described in an advertisement as a remedy for something like arthritis. A sedative would not be a remedy for arthritis because it is a condition of the bone, but it would be a pain killer.  The Institute might rule against the description of such as a cure-all but it might at the same time be of great value.</P>
    <P>The example I should like to refer to on this point is red flannel.  If the purveyors of red flannel suggested it was good for lumbago, the Institute could rule them out of court but we all know it is good for lumbago, so that we cannot take the decisions of that body with regard to standard specifications as absolutely and always correct because of their physical approach only.  I have instanced the fact that large firms are spending fantastic sums on the sort of thing that should be done in the Institute in its improved state.</P>
    <P>It is true that firms have banded together to employ consultants to do such work and such consultants are usually specialists, so that in a particular trade we might have a manufacturer employing 50 to 70 people on research and testing and procuring standards.  The industry would have a very limited field to work in and from that would stem the fact that the bigger, very highly skilled specialists in that end of industrial research and standards, having a very large field to <Col N="772" /> work, could not be expected to compete in this way.</P>
    <P>For instance, in the flour milling trade, there is a firm in England, whose principal died in Dublin not long ago, which employs 60 to 70 operatives constantly testing wheats of all kinds and milling processes to see how the best flour can be produced.  If the Institute were to reach that degree of application, we would need 60 people for that industry.  Some of them, of course, because of their abilities, could go into another field, but at the same time, we would need a huge staff and a huge amount of money, so that I do not think the research end of this Institute is going to bring us a lot.</P>
    <P>In Section 6, the Institute is instructed or empowered to publish the results of any tests or analyses carried out by it or by any person on its behalf.  I should like to warn that this sort of thing should be done very warily because, like a statistic, it is part of a set and any conclusion drawn from a few investigations can, in this extremely complex era in which we live, be very misleading.</P>
    <P>I know of an instance where the Institute, in my view, gave the Minister for Agriculture a result which was misleading.  I think it is in order to discuss what has been happening over the past few years.  It is known that the Institute produced an all-Irish loaf. Quite frankly, I think that had a bad effect.  Even from the point of view of my own business, and everything about it, I would desire an all-Irish loaf, but it had the effect that the millers and the bakers who knew that an all-Irish loaf was not factual got their backs up and were inclined to disprove it.  The result, in my view, has been a conflict of ideas and I am convinced that the suggestion by the Institute that this could be done, even in a good season, was a bad thing because it affected the whole flavour of things in the trade.  It would have been better if they had refrained from that.</P>
    <P>Even this year, at this late stage, the argument is being produced as to how much Irish wheat should be included in the grist.  The Institute presented a report that 60 per cent. <Col N="773" /> should be included.  At the same time, the laboratory in Britain which I mentioned has produced a report that 30 per cent. should be included and in Sweden a report has been presented that 25 per cent. should be included. You could produce, I am quite certain, a one hundred per cent.  Irish loaf if you did it literally in a test tube.</P>
    <P>I am quite certain from viewing the Irish crop this year, that while the laboratories in Britain and Sweden are being over-conservative, as far as the Irish farmers are concerned, it would only be regarded as an argument. I suggest that the Institute should proceed warily and make quite certain, in association and cooperation with the industries they are investigating, that the tests they are carrying out, as well as being clinical tests, also relate to large scale commercial production.  It would be a pity if this body did not become, without having the powers, almost a judicial body and a place of reference to which people in doubt could go.</P>
    <P>In summing up, I would say that the standards specifications end is really the end in which the Institute can do good.  Senator Miss Davidson was on the same line when she talked about shoddy being put into school uniforms. I do not think there is a lot of that, but at the same time the good industrialists and the good producers who could keep up to certain standard specifications laid down by the Institute are entitled to their price because their products will give the wear and the return which they should. It is also true that we should not have to pay for an article under the name of a quality product when the article is not a quality product.  The list of standard specifications is the one that could really benefit this country.  Therefore, I hope the Institute will proceed cautiously on any findings they produce in industrial production.  If they do that and avail of any opportunity that comes their way to cooperate with industry, agriculture and with those who must live by what they do commercially, then we will have a good Institute.</P>
    <Speaker pid="OwenSkeffington" hpid="Dr. Sheehy Skeffington Dr. Sheehy Skeffington">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Sheehy Skeffington</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not <Col N="774" /> want to speak at length on this measure but I should like to support the Bill and welcome it.  I think the spirit in which it has been introduced is excellent and we all recognise the necessity underlying it, for the promotion of industrial research and the standardisation of the commodities and processes.</P>
      <P>I notice in the definition section, Section 2, both &ldquo;standard specification&rdquo; and &ldquo;standard mark&rdquo; are referred to. I read at line seven of page four:</P>
      <P>&ldquo;standard mark&rdquo; means a mark prescribed or deemed to have been prescribed by an order under section 24 of this Act for use in connection with a commodity, process or practice to indicate that it conforms to a particular standard specification.</P>
      <P>All of that is excellent, but I read at the end of the page in Section 6, subsection (2), paragraph (d), that the functions of the Institute are:</P>
      <P>to make recommendations to the Minister as to the provision and use of standard marks for commodities, processes and practices which conform to standard specifications,</P>
      <P>I read further down under paragraph (g) (iii)</P>
      <P>encouraging the standardisation of commodities, processes and practices,</P>
      <P>The whole of Part V of the Bill deals with standard specifications and standard marks.  As I say, all that is excellent, but I should like to put a question to the Minister arising out of that.  Is there any feeling that the Irish public may be put off by the fact that the commodity is marked with a standard mark which is taken to indicate a standard specification because, as he probably knows, one of his Cabinet colleagues is of opinion that a standard mark on an Irish egg prevents people from buying that egg?  We shall be dealing in a moment or two with a Bill specially designed to remove the necessity for putting any standard mark on an egg to mark its standard specification and so on.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnODonovan" hpid="Dr. O'Donovan Dr. O'Donovan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. O'Donovan</NameTxt>
      <P>It does not really, unfortunately.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="775" />
    <Speaker pid="OwenSkeffington" hpid="Dr. Sheehy Skeffington Dr. Sheehy Skeffington">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Sheehy Skeffington</NameTxt>
      <P>I agree with the attitude of the Minister that this type standard mark and standard specification is excellent, and I do not share the view of his colleague that the public are put off by such a mark.  I cannot help adverting to the fact that we are passing a Bill to enable this kind of code marking to be engaged in, and in another quarter of an hour or so, we will be asked to pass a Bill for the purpose of abolishing such a practice in relation to eggs.  I should like to know if the Minister shares my belief that this code mark does not, in fact, have a deleterious effect upon the buying public.  With those words I should like to welcome the Bill now before us.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnODonovan" hpid="Dr. O'Donovan Dr. O'Donovan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. O'Donovan</NameTxt>
      <P>Not for the first time and, indeed I am sure not for the last time, I do not agree with the grandiose welcome which has been given to this Bill in the House this evening.  I have not a warm welcome for it.  What I am about to say in one way reflects on the Minister.  His Department has produced a vast mass of legislation and it has no objection to producing an amending Bill in the following month.</P>
      <P>Looking at the 1946 and the 1954 Acts, and at this Bill I find that whole chunks are the same.  I am not going to make any detailed complaint about that because, in fact, this approach bears out something I should like to see in other Bills.  I believe we should begin from scratch and produce a completely new document.  That is a very good idea.  I suggest that when we find that the only worthwhile change in the Bill is the change which removes the restriction on the amount which may be voted each year for the Institute, it is a pity the Department would not produce a Companies Bill. The last effective Companies Bill was passed in 1908.  The 1908 Companies Act is the only worthwhile piece of legislation to come from the Department for quite a long time.  There have been two Companies Bills in Britain since then, one in 1928 and one in 1948.  The 1954 Bill altered the 1946 Act only in relation to specification and standard, which are, of course, most important.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="776" /> We have now really a completely new organisation for the Institute. There is no doubt that this new organisation is more coherent, and likely to work more effectively, than the existing organisation, but there is not a whole lot in it.  I notice the usual undercurrent of the managers taking things closely under their own control. That idea is very definitely there.  It is being brought closer to the Department from the control point of view, in spite of the fact that the Minister said in his brief that there is more freedom. I refer to the appointment of staff generally at any rate.  Previously the Institute did certain things and the Minister had to confirm them or to put his seal on them.  In future, the Minister is to do these things.</P>
    <P>There is not a great deal in this Bill. I think that some of the encomiums bestowed on it this evening were bestowed because of the removal of the financial restrictions.  Most of the other matters dealt with were, in fact, covered already.  As I say, I would prefer to see the Department producing a Companies Bill.  If it ever does, I hope I will be still alive to see it.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOQuigley" hpid="Mr. O'Quigley Mr. O'Quigley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Quigley</NameTxt>
      <P>I am glad to see that members on the Government side have dropped the practice of welcoming Bills.  It was markedly absent on a recent Bill.  This Bill is not unwelcome but neither is it greatly to be applauded because the objects of the new Institute will not differ in any material respect from the objects and functions of the council and the various committees established under previous legislation.  The Bill really streamlines the co-ordination of the functions of the existing bodies, and the only other significant change so far as I can see is the removal of the restriction of £35,000 on the annual grant.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>An extraordinary thing about the Institute for Research and Standards is that no one ever hears anything about it.  In Britain, they have some kind of housekeepers' institute which certifies that certain articles reach certain qualities and standards and one sees the seal of that Institute on quite a number of items of household use. The people in this country are very <Col N="777" /> interested in an Institute with that kind of function.  It is a function I should like to see given to the Industrial Research and Standards Institute to fulfil effectively under this piece of legislation.</P>
    <P>There is no doubt that the price of the industrial drive has been very heavy when we consider the inefficient and defective quality of some of the goods which have been produced behind the shelter of tariffs and quotas.</P>
    <Speaker pid="FrankCarter" hpid="Mr. Carter Mr. Carter">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Carter</NameTxt>
      <P>Utter nonsense.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnODonovan" hpid="Dr. O'Donovan Dr. O'Donovan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. O'Donovan</NameTxt>
      <P>They have got better.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOQuigley" hpid="Mr. O'Quigley Mr. O'Quigley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Quigley</NameTxt>
      <P>I will come to it in a moment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrankCarter" hpid="Mr. Carter Mr. Carter">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Carter</NameTxt>
      <P>I hope the Senator does.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOQuigley" hpid="Mr. O'Quigley Mr. O'Quigley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Quigley</NameTxt>
      <P>I will.  That is the price that is being paid, and it applies not only to goods that are produced here from scratch.  It applies equally to goods which are assembled here from imported parts.  There is hardly an item in the kitchen of any house in this country that does not go &ldquo;wallop&rdquo; within a few months of being bought, because of inefficiency in putting it together.  That applies to electric cookers, washing machines, electric fires and other commodities.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BrianLenihanSnr" hpid="Mr. Lenihan Mr. Lenihan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lenihan</NameTxt>
      <P>And sabotage.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrankCarter" hpid="Mr. Carter Mr. Carter">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Carter</NameTxt>
      <P>That would be libel outside the House.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BrianLenihanSnr" hpid="Mr. Lenihan Mr. Lenihan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lenihan</NameTxt>
      <P>National sabotage&mdash; the Senator is very good.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOQuigley" hpid="Mr. O'Quigley Mr. O'Quigley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Quigley</NameTxt>
      <P>There is no use denying that is so.  Anybody who takes an interest in his domestic affairs and keeps his eyes and ears open will hear and see the complaints in relation to these ordinary articles that should not show the defects they are showing.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BrianLenihanSnr" hpid="Mr. Lenihan Mr. Lenihan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lenihan</NameTxt>
      <P>The Senator is an excellent domestic.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOQuigley" hpid="Mr. O'Quigley Mr. O'Quigley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Quigley</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not consider that uncomplimentary and I can do my public duties equally well.  I do not <Col N="778" /> like being delayed in having to ring up the E.S.B. or the G.E.C. and people like that.  When you pay money for articles, they ought to work efficiently in the years to come.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrankCarter" hpid="Mr. Carter Mr. Carter">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Carter</NameTxt>
      <P>And so they do.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOQuigley" hpid="Mr. O'Quigley Mr. O'Quigley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Quigley</NameTxt>
      <P>I hope that this Bill and this resuscitated and revivified Institute for Industrial Research and Standards will produce this kind of effect&mdash;that if you buy a pair of shoes, they will not leak within a matter of a few days.  I had the experience of buying Irish-made shoes and within a week they let in water.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrankCarter" hpid="Mr. Carter Mr. Carter">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Carter</NameTxt>
      <P>Has the Senator Irish-made shoes on him at the moment?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOQuigley" hpid="Mr. O'Quigley Mr. O'Quigley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Quigley</NameTxt>
      <P>Certainly he has and he always wears them.  He always insists on getting Irish goods in Irish shops but he likewise insists upon getting quality.  I do not think that is unreasonable.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrankCarter" hpid="Mr. Carter Mr. Carter">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Carter</NameTxt>
      <P>Absolutely.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOQuigley" hpid="Mr. O'Quigley Mr. O'Quigley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Quigley</NameTxt>
      <P>If you buy a pair of Irish-made shoes, I think you ought to expect that they will remain waterproof. I bought a pair of Irish-made shoes and they let in water after a week.  I wrote to the manufacturers and I received a very impudent reply. I am sorry I have not got the letter here in order to put it in the Library so that members could see the way a particular Irish manufacturer treats a member of the Irish public who makes a complaint because a pair of shoes for which he paid upwards of 60/- or 70/- were so bad as to let the water in in a week.  The reply I received was that they were not guaranteed to be waterproof.  For what purpose does one put on a pair of shoes solemnly every morning except to keep one's feet dry?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OwenSkeffington" hpid="Dr. Sheehy Skeffington Dr. Sheehy Skeffington">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Sheehy Skeffington</NameTxt>
      <P>For kicking yourself.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOQuigley" hpid="Mr. O'Quigley Mr. O'Quigley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Quigley</NameTxt>
      <P>That was the answer I got.  The reason the shoes were not waterproof was that the manufacturers, who are an English firm manufacturing apparently under licence here, were obliged by the laws of the Oireachtas&mdash;they knew I was a member of the Oireachtas&mdash;to use Irish leather.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="779" />
    <Speaker pid="FrankCarter" hpid="Mr. Carter Mr. Carter">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Carter</NameTxt>
      <P>That is an old one.  It is too old.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOQuigley" hpid="Mr. O'Quigley Mr. O'Quigley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Quigley</NameTxt>
      <P>If the members disbelieve me, I can do a little research. I can unearth the letter, if they disbelieve me.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BrianLenihanSnr" hpid="Mr. Lenihan Mr. Lenihan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lenihan</NameTxt>
      <P>They knew their man.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrankCarter" hpid="Mr. Carter Mr. Carter">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Carter</NameTxt>
      <P>We disbelieve the manufacturer who wrote that.  We are not doubting the Senator's word.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOQuigley" hpid="Mr. O'Quigley Mr. O'Quigley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Quigley</NameTxt>
      <P>That is why we ought all to be interested in the new function to be assigned to the Institute of promoting the utilisation of the natural resources of this State.  I think it is most reprehensible that Irish leather should be said by Irish manufacturers to be unsuitable for the manufacture of Irish shoes.  I hope that something will be done by this Institute and that the Minister for Industry and Commerce will bring about a situation in which if people pay 50/-, 60/- or 70/- for a pair of shoes, they will be able to wear them after a week.  That is not the first complaint I know of about shoes letting in after a week.  In a previous case, I knew the answer to be that they were not guaranteed to be waterproof.  If people state they regard that as sabotage, I cannot help it.  These are the facts.</P>
      <P>There is another matter which concerns the female section of the country. I see letters in the paper and I hear quite an amount of conversation about it from time to time.  It is that the manufacturers of nylon hose have fallen down on their job.  Nylon stockings are an item of ordinary and everyday use and it is very necessary that they should last for months.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JackLynch" hpid="Mr. J. Lynch Mr. J. Lynch">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J. Lynch</NameTxt>
      <P>The Senator is stretching his yarn or the nylon a bit.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOQuigley" hpid="Mr. O'Quigley Mr. O'Quigley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Quigley</NameTxt>
      <P>I may be weaving an unpleasant story for the Minister but time was when they would last.  I should like the Minister to have the matter investigated by the Institute for Industrial Research and Standards. Nowadays nylon stockings last no time whatever.  It seems to me to be appropriate for some authority to prevent the <Col N="780" /> women of this country from being fleeced by the stocking manufacturers. If the Institute for Industrial Research and Standards pay some attention to things of that kind, I think that whatever money is being paid to finance it will be well worth while.</P>
      <P>There is no use talking about being at the dawn of an era of prosperity when according to some we are on the verge of an economic breakdown. There is no use talking about a major industrial break-through or things of that kind, if tangible results are not brought home to the Irish consumer.  I have here one of the reports of the Institute for Industrial Research and Standards, the annual report for 1959. It refers to standards having been settled in the previous year in relation to white spirit, linseed oil, turpentine and so on.  That may be all very useful but there is a great deal more urgent and useful work that an institute can engage itself in and thus confer greater benefit on Irish housewives and, indeed, aid in the reduction of the cost of living in this country and counter the decline in the value of money.  If it is intended that this Institute is to make any headway, then clearly money must be found to finance it.</P>
      <P>What I say in relation to the Institute is not to be taken in any way as reflecting on the personnel up to the present because they are a body who have the courage of their convictions.  In a report for 1958, we read observations by the Committee which, to my mind, suggest they are people who have the courage to stand up to an unwilling Department of Industry and Commerce and a miserably-minded Department of Finance who perhaps would not allow the Department of Industry and Commerce to do what should be done. In the report, on page 8, we find it stated that the Institute has found difficulty in filling some of the vacancies. This is at a time when we are supposed to be in earnest about industrial expansion and here we have an institution that takes an extraordinary step for a semi-State body and puts down in writing what is a shocking indictment of the Departments of Industry and Commerce and Finance.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>In 1960, two years later, they come <Col N="781" /> back again, when confidence has been restored and development principles have been laid down, and at page 20 they say that the difficulty referred to in previous reports&mdash;so that it must have arisen prior to 1958, because it does not appear in the 1959 report&mdash; in recruiting suitable technical staff continues, as does the unattractiveness of the salary offered by the Institute. This is in August, 1960, and a number of positions remained unfilled.  The report said that the matter was under discussion with the Department of Industry and Commerce.</P>
    <P>If one looks at the Appendix to see the details of the staff, one sees that literally there were more &ldquo;officers than men&rdquo;.  There were 50 on the Industrial Council which is the Government body but the effective technical staff of the Institute in 1960 consisted of 11 people.  Among these is included the administrative officer, so that in effect there were ten.  If the Government and the Minister for Industry and Commerce are in earnest about providing an Institute that is going to do research and all the things associated with research, they are not going to do it with a staff of ten or 11 people.</P>
    <P>Another matter which occurs to me is in regard to the provision in Section 43 where the Institute is to be permitted to undertake or assist in the development and exploitation of an invention.  The Institute is supposed to be an autonomous body and independent, but under this section it cannot incur expenditure on any one project in excess of £5,000, save with the consent of the Minister.  In these modern times, I do not see how the Institute is to get very far with £5,000. If they have to put a case to the Minister for Industry and Commerce to justify the expenditure of more than £5,000 on a certain invention, they will be required, on paper, to prove that the invention will be a success before they can undertake the research upon the particular invention.  That is the queer kind of inverted approach we adopt, that they will have to establish the success of the invention before the money is provided.</P>
    <P>I am rather inclined to share the <Col N="782" /> view expressed by Senator O'Donovan that this is not a great Bill.  It can only be a great Bill and a real benefit to the public if adequate finance is placed at the disposal of the Institute and if the Minister for Industry and Commerce, or the Minister for Finance, interfere as little as possible in its day to day workings.</P>
    <P>One again observes the dead hand of the Department coming in in Section 34 where offices of special responsibility may be designated by the Minister and they can be filled only with the consent of the Minister and the remuneration, tenure of office and conditions of service of such office is to be determined by the Minister, subject to the approval of the Minister for Finance.  In my opinion, that is not the way to progress.  If that is the way in which the Institute is to be permitted to conduct its business in future, I cannot hold out any great hope for the results everybody would wish for.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PadraigOSiochfhradha" hpid="Pádraig Ó Siochfhradha Pádraig Ó Siochfhradha">
      <NameTxt>Pádraig Ó Siochfhradha</NameTxt>
      <P>Ba mhaith liom tacaíocht a thúirt dona Seanadóirí a aontaigh cheana féin leis an mBille seo.  Molaim an Bille.  Ní maith liom an síor-cháineadh a chleachtaíonn daoine áirithe i dtaobh déantús na hÉireann mar a dhein an Seanadóir Ó Coigligh.  Táim i bhfad níos sine ná an Seanadóir&mdash;go deimhin, táim níos sine ná é fé dhó agus ní bhfuair mé aon locht ar bhróga de dhéantús na hÉireann.  Rud eile, ní raibh orm riam rudaí den tsaghas sin a mhalartú. Ní chloisimid aon rud ach gearáin den tsórt seo.  Is trua nach gcloisimid dhá thaobh an scéil chun a mheas cé acu olcas nó maitheas a bhaineann leis na h-earraí seo.</P>
      <P>Caithfidh sár-rud agus rud cuíosach a bheith ann.  Sin iad na neithe a ritheann tríd m'aigne.  Cad a dhéanfar i leith na gcaighdeán nuair a cheapfar iad?  Sin ceist nárbh aon dhíobháil beagán a chloisint mar gheall uirthi.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Maidir le rudaí a déantar in Éirinn, níl siad ar fad go holc.  Is dócha nach bhfuil le fáil aon bheoir atá níos fearr ná Guinness ná aon uisce bgatha níos fearr ná an t-uisce beatha a dhéanaimid. Níl a fhios agam má tá aon <Col N="783" /> chaighdeán eile níos fearr le cur i bhfeidhm orthu san.</P>
    <P>Tá a lán rudaí fónta dhá ndéanamh in Éirinn.  Sé an locht atá le fáil agamsa ar an gcaint a rinne ár gcara, an Seanadóir Ó Coigligh, ná go mbeadh sé le tuiscint uaithi nach bhfuil aon rud fónta in Éirinn.  Ní mar sin atá.  Tá neithe fónta in Éirinn.  Is aithnid dúinn iad agus is fearr a bheadh siad ach caighdeán a chur i bhfeidhm ar neithe eile nach bhfuil chomh maith sin agus an t-eolas a chur ar fáil in aisce ón Institiúd atáimid ag ceapadh anois.</P>
    <P>Is cóir an tInstitiúd a bheith ann agus mara bhfuil an cumhacht acu ba cheart go mbeadh an cumhacht acu chun caighdeán ceart a chur i bhfeidhm agus a chur in iúl do dhaoine a bhíonn ag déanamh rudaí áirithe go gcaithfidh siad caighdeán a dó nó a trí dena h-earraí sin a chur ar fáil. Is iad so na neithe a ritheann tré aigne duine ar an mBille seo.  Níl an tarna tuairim ann ná gur Bille fónta é agus molaim é.</P>
    <Speaker pid="FrankCarter" hpid="Mr. Carter Mr. Carter">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Carter</NameTxt>
      <P>Despite the criticism of Senator O'Quigley who made use of the privilege of this House to indulge in some biting criticism of this Bill, we still believe in it.  The fact was mentioned in the <i>Programme for Economic Expansion</i> issued by the Government in 1948 that the Institute for Industrial Research and Standards would be made a progressive body.  That promise has been honoured in the full.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I should like to mention a point that was overlooked in this debate.  Due to the American Counterpart Grant fund, the Institute was enabled to set up three very important laboratories to deal with raw materials. We should always bear that fact in mind and be grateful to the American Government. Senator O'Quigley speaks like a millionaire.  He would like us to think we could have royal standards on a republican income.  It is all right to indulge in that sort of barrel-rolling in the House and say that the goods produced by our Irish industrialists are shoddy, and that if you buy a pair of shoes today, they will leak tomorrow. <Col N="784" /> I think I know more about shoes than Senator O'Quigley.</P>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamStanford" hpid="Professor Stanford Professor Stanford">
      <NameTxt>Professor Stanford</NameTxt>
      <P>On a point of fact, Senator O'Quigley did not say that.  He referred to one pair of shoes, not shoes.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickSDonegan" hpid="Mr. Donegan Mr. Donegan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Donegan</NameTxt>
      <P>That is so but let the Senator go on until he hangs himself.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrankCarter" hpid="Mr. Carter Mr. Carter">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Carter</NameTxt>
      <P>I recognise that, but in referring to one pair of shoes, he did not specify the fact that every pair of shoes is not immune to leakage.  The best pair of shoes in any country today may not be waterproof and it is only shoes bearing the brand &ldquo;waterproof&rdquo; or &ldquo;weldschoen&rdquo; that are, in reality, waterproof.  That may be something new to Senator O'Quigley.  The Senator can go to England or America and purchase a pair of shoes and they will leak if they are not treated as they should be treated.  In speaking of our industrial efforts under the privilege of the House or indeed elsewhere unwarranted attacks are sometimes made on some of our Irish industries.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickSDonegan" hpid="Mr. Donegan Mr. Donegan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Donegan</NameTxt>
      <P>No attack was made.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrankCarter" hpid="Mr. Carter Mr. Carter">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Carter</NameTxt>
      <P>I think so.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickSDonegan" hpid="Mr. Donegan Mr. Donegan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Donegan</NameTxt>
      <P>An individual instance was quoted.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrankCarter" hpid="Mr. Carter Mr. Carter">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Carter</NameTxt>
      <P>I think so.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JackLynch" hpid="Mr. J. Lynch Mr. J. Lynch">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J. Lynch</NameTxt>
      <P>Surely the whole range of household goods was not an individual instance?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickSDonegan" hpid="Mr. Donegan Mr. Donegan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Donegan</NameTxt>
      <P>He mentioned individual instances.  There was no question of Irish industries always being at fault.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrankCarter" hpid="Mr. Carter Mr. Carter">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Carter</NameTxt>
      <P>He said the whole range of household appliances could be found to be defective.  That is not so, of course.  You will get defects in any range of goods and it is hardly fair to say, under the privilege of the House, that the whole range of household appliances manufactured here is defective.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>In formulating this legislation and on the advice of his Department, the Minister is taking certain powers.  I <Col N="785" /> believe he is adopting a wise course. We have no means nor indeed have we the subscriptions forthcoming from those engaged in industry to enable the Institute to carry on by voluntary effort.  When America, England and such countries are quoted here, it would be well, indeed, to recognise the fact that we have no industrialists large enough to be able voluntarily to subscribe money to this type of Institute in order to enable it to carry on industrial research.</P>
    <P>Looking at the 14th annual report issued in 1960 by the Institute, I find that the Institute has engaged in various activities.  I welcome the fact that they mentioned they have set up a laboratory for testing building materials, paper and leather.  That is to be welcomed.  I believe that not merely could we supply our own home market with first-class leather but we could have a substantial export in leather as well, if we handled it properly.  I should think that we are losing anything up to £5,000,000 or £6,000,000 a year as a result of the rough treatment hides get in the course of flaying and tanning and all the rest of it.  It is a pity that should be so.  As a matter of fact, it should be one of our basic raw materials and it should be the best on the market because we have the scope and the necessary raw material to produce the leather.  For that reason, I welcome the fact that the Institute is proceeding to examine that aspect of leather production.</P>
    <P>I also note that the standards committee are taking steps to increase the output of standards, in particular the standard mark regarding consumer goods.  It is regrettable, I think, that as time goes on, more of our industrialists do not examine this aspect of the matter and apply to the Institute to have certain goods tested and stamped with the standard mark.  That would in itself, despite what Senator Sheehy Skeffington said, be a guarantee to the consumer that the goods would give the service required.  The absence of that mark is notable at this stage of our industrial development on goods produced for the home market.  It is <Col N="786" /> more of a necessity, of course, to have that mark on goods for export.  I understand and I know that most goods produced for export carry the mark.  We appreciate that, but I think this House will recognise, and those of us in public life should be concerned to see that the goods displayed in the shops here should carry the standard mark&mdash;a guarantee of quality of the Institute for Industrial Research and Standards.</P>
    <Speaker pid="OwenSkeffington" hpid="Dr. Sheehy Skeffington Dr. Sheehy Skeffington">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Sheehy Skeffington</NameTxt>
      <P>What about the code marking of eggs?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrankCarter" hpid="Mr. Carter Mr. Carter">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Carter</NameTxt>
      <P>I think that matter was explained.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickSDonegan" hpid="Mr. Donegan Mr. Donegan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Donegan</NameTxt>
      <P>You do not manufacture an egg.  Is that not the answer?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrankCarter" hpid="Mr. Carter Mr. Carter">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Carter</NameTxt>
      <P>It is one of the answers. I think that matter was explained to the Senator.  There is really no comparison. It is not a comparable proposition, if you like.  The reason for the removal of the code mark on eggs was explained to the Senator by the Minister for Agriculture.  I think it was accepted by the House.  It was more or less an agreed measure. Perhaps the Senator may be the only one dissenting from it.  I do not know, but I think that may be so.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OwenSkeffington" hpid="Dr. Sheehy Skeffington Dr. Sheehy Skeffington">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Sheehy Skeffington</NameTxt>
      <P>I am in favour of marking.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrankCarter" hpid="Mr. Carter Mr. Carter">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Carter</NameTxt>
      <P>I think I explained my position to the Senator.  I said that due to the fact that people like to buy a fresh egg&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>You could not very well mark vegetables.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrankCarter" hpid="Mr. Carter Mr. Carter">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Carter</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not want to be dragged into an argument of this description with the Senator.  The Senator might come around to the view prevailing here and elsewhere that eggs for the home market will do very well without the code mark.  I was glad to note that the Institute had examined the problem of effluents in water.  That has given rise to certain difficulties down the country where objectionable effluents from tanneries and other industries pollute the rivers. <Col N="787" /> It clashes with our aim to promote our inland fisheries.  Therefore, I welcome the fact that the Institute intend to deal with that point.  I also note that the relevant merits of phosphatic fertilisers are being examined.  That is a step forward which will be welcomed by the farming community.</P>
      <P>There is nothing much more to be said on the Bill.  It more or less tidies up the previous Acts; it divests certain functions and makes certain changes and altogether it is a step forward.  Despite the biting, cynical attitude of some people towards our industries, I think we are making very good progress and that our figures show that.  The figures in the last Budget showed it and the figures for the first half of this year will show it and if we can continue in that direction, it cannot be said that we are not taking steps to deal with all aspects of industrial production.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnCole" hpid="Mr. Cole Mr. Cole">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cole</NameTxt>
      <P>I should just like to say a word on Section 44 which, to the ordinary man in the street, is one of the most important sections in the Bill. That is the section under which, if the Minister is satisfied that it is in the public interest to do so, he may, by order, declare in relation to any commodity intended for sale to the public that it shall be unlawful to manufacture or sell that commodity, unless it complies with the standard specification declared by the Institute.  One can go one step further.  Undoubtedly, in spite of what Senator Carter and others have said, badly turned out goods have appeared on our home market and while their numbers may be getting less and less, they do appear. The purchaser of those goods gets very little assistance, if he wants to find out where they came from.  Would the Minister go further and take power to compel manufacturers to put their trade mark or some mark on all goods they produce, if they have put goods of an inferior standard on the home market?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>A manufacturer may produce a particular lot of goods, say, the day's manufacture, and he cannot afford to <Col N="788" /> discard them altogether.  They are put on the market and as a result they give a bad name not only to that manufacturer but also to other Irish manufacturers. Therefore, I suggest that the Minister should take power to compel manufacturers to put their mark on their product.  That would be of great assistance to the purchaser.  Most of the firms who manufacture good products are proud of their commodities but I have purchased commodities about which I would have liked to complain to the manufacturers but I could not find out who manufactured them.  The shopkeeper told me he got them from a wholesaler and from there on their history seemed to get lost.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JackLynch" hpid="Mr. J. Lynch Mr. J. Lynch">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J. Lynch</NameTxt>
      <P>First of all, I should like to apologise to the Seanad for not being here this afternoon when the Second Reading was given to the Bill, but as the House probably knows, I was engaged in the other House moving the Estimate for my Department.  However, the Minister for Transport and Power who read my speech gave me a fairly complete note of what had been said before the House adjourned for tea.  I am glad to see that Senator McGuire, who led off on behalf of Fine Gael, gave the Bill unqualified approval.  As he is the Senator on that side of the House who is perhaps most representative of industry, it is a commendation that I am very glad to receive.  Of course, some of his colleagues went to the other extreme and, as Senator Carter said, approached the Bill in a rather derisive and cynical fashion.  However, Fine Gael are entitled to have that kind of approach and have the best of both worlds, and indeed the best of every world, in relation to any measure coming before the Oireachtas.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I deplore the attitude of Senator O'Quigley who comes in here in a sniping fashion, not so much at the Bill itself but at Irish industry in general.  However, he is entitled to put forward that point of view and perpetuate the old reactionary approach towards Irish industry and its advancement. On the other hand, I do not like him to get away with the suggestion that Irishmen cannot produce goods <Col N="789" /> as well as people in other parts of the world and that only inferior goods come on the market in Ireland.</P>
    <P>I should like to say to him in relation to the specific instance he quoted in regard to leather and boots, that recently I had the pleasure of going through one of the largest boot and shoe factories in the country.  It has a strong association with an English firm and I was very pleased to hear that the upper leather which that firm was procuring from Irish sources was, in their opinion, the best that could be procured in any part of the world.  I should like to remind him also that we have quite a substantial export market in leather to Britain and other countries. I think we are amongst the three major exporters of leather to the British market.</P>
    <P>I am sorry he had such an unfortunate experience with the shoes he bought, but leather is not expected to be waterproof in all conditions.  I do not know if the Senator ever played golf but if he has not, he should consult some of his friends who do.  They will tell him that one of their greatest difficulties is to find leather shoes, no matter where they are manufactured, which will withstand water.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOQuigley" hpid="Mr. O'Quigley Mr. O'Quigley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Quigley</NameTxt>
      <P>I am talking about walking around the streets of Dublin.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JackLynch" hpid="Mr. J. Lynch Mr. J. Lynch">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J. Lynch</NameTxt>
      <P>The Senator is quite entitled to his point of view and to express it here, whether it is a point of view that one condones or not, or a rather unfortunate attack on Irish industry&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOQuigley" hpid="Mr. O'Quigley Mr. O'Quigley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Quigley</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister can try to interpret me if he wishes.  I</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JackLynch" hpid="Mr. J. Lynch Mr. J. Lynch">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J. Lynch</NameTxt>
      <P>I hope I am not misinterpreting the Senator.  He went through the whole range of household goods and said there is no day in which some household appliance does not go &ldquo;wallop&rdquo;.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOQuigley" hpid="Mr. O'Quigley Mr. O'Quigley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Quigley</NameTxt>
      <P>I did not say that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickSDonegan" hpid="Mr. Donegan Mr. Donegan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Donegan</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister is often in better humour.  He should ease up.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JackLynch" hpid="Mr. J. Lynch Mr. J. Lynch">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J. Lynch</NameTxt>
      <P>I am in quite good humour&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="790" />
    <Speaker pid="JohnOQuigley" hpid="Mr. O'Quigley Mr. O'Quigley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Quigley</NameTxt>
      <P>When the Minister reads what I said, he will understand it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JackLynch" hpid="Mr. J. Lynch Mr. J. Lynch">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J. Lynch</NameTxt>
      <P>&mdash;&mdash;but I should like to strike Senator O'Quigley's sniping hand to the desk.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister must not be constantly interrupted.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JackLynch" hpid="Mr. J. Lynch Mr. J. Lynch">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J. Lynch</NameTxt>
      <P>I did not interrupt the Senator.  He had his way in attacking Irish industry.  I am Minister for Industry and Commerce and I shall not defend Irish industry on all occasions, but I will not have implied attacks on the quality of Irish workmanship.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOQuigley" hpid="Mr. O'Quigley Mr. O'Quigley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Quigley</NameTxt>
      <P>I related my remarks to the Bill.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JackLynch" hpid="Mr. J. Lynch Mr. J. Lynch">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J. Lynch</NameTxt>
      <P>I hope my remarks are related to the Bill also, because I am following exactly what the Senator said.  To come, perhaps, to the more serious observations, offered on the Bill, the first speaker, apart from Senator McGuire, was Senator Quinlan, who mentioned several aspects of the Bill with which he did not agree.  I do not think I need go into every one, but he suggested that this Bill would be useless unless there were a degree of co-ordination between the new Institute and the universities.  I do not expect that there will be any lack of co-ordination.  In fact, I believe there will be full co-ordination.  Whether in the matter of pure, applied or routine research, I do not think the Institute will lack in any way co-operation either from industry in general, or from the universities, if it is required.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>So far as criticism of ministerial control over the Institute is concerned, I can say again very safely that the intention in this Bill is to relax control and that has been done in several instances.  As to the suggestion by Senator O'Quigley that we should let the Institute rip, so to speak, and exploit developing inventions, I do not believe that any member of this House would agree that the Minister who has ultimate responsibility to the Oireachtas should not have some control <Col N="791" /> over the expenditure of an Institute such as this in the matter of inventions and their development.  It is quite reasonable that a certain amount of money should be expended by the Institute without recourse to the Minister and for every single invention £5,000 is not an unreasonable sum.</P>
    <P>The criticism of Ministerial supervision of the higher posts as to salary and conditions is not any serious criticism, I think.  Certainly, the effects of any supervision the Minister would be enabled to exercise would not be any deterrent to the activities of the Institute.  That matter was raised in the Dáil and I explained it would not be my intention, or the intention of any other Minister, to select any particular person for the higher post and to confine it to a senior technical and administrative man.  The purpose of the designation of the posts requiring the Minister's sanction is to ensure that the salary so fixed will not be out of line with similar salaries and remunerations in other public companies and in the Civil Service.</P>
    <P>I gave as an example of the type of instance I had in mind the case of the Institute requiring the services of a particular man who was working in industry, say, in some part of Great Britain, a man who was willing to work for the Institute but who, by reason of the salary he gets in industry in Great Britain or elsewhere, would not come to the Institute unless he got a certain sum.  It is in such circumstances that I would expect the Institute to come to me, if it is a designated post, and ask whether A.B. working in Coventry or somewhere else could be given a certain salary by the Institute.  If A.B. were the person the Institute wanted, if he were properly appointed and if the salary were reasonable, I think the Minister could have no objection to the making of that appointment.  These are the only circumstances in which the Minister would interfere in any way with the appointments.  The Minister himself would not be responsible for the selection of any such person.</P>
    <P>The Senator also suggested that the board should be representative of certain <Col N="792" /> groups including universities and the Federation of Industries.  In dealing with this point, I think I could deal also with Senator Stanford's suggestion that the Institute of Irish Inventors might also be represented. I do not mind telling the Seanad that I have a strong objection to nominating boards as if they were conventions. The qualifications for membership of this Institute are set out in Section 8, subsection (3).  The Minister is required to make the appointment &ldquo;by reason of his attainments in scientific research applied to industry or because he is representative of industry or of persons employed in industry or is capable of giving substantial practical assistance in the work of the Institute&rdquo;.</P>
    <P>I should prefer a person to be selected because of his qualifications under one of those heads, and not because he represented an organisation or a university.  It is quite likely that one or more university professors will be appointed.  In saying that, I do not want to be bound in any way. Speaking generally, I think that in order to procure the best qualified board, the most effective board, the Minister should be free to cast his net as wide as possible, without being limited in any way, in a small board such as this with eight members and a chairman, by being obliged to put representatives of certain institutions on it.  I gave an undertaking to the Dáil, which I now repeat here, that the only consideration I will have in mind when making any of these appointments will be that the person so appointed will be able to fulfil his functions in accordance with the provisions of that subsection and that no other considerations will apply.</P>
    <P>You, Sir, made certain criticisms&mdash; perhaps not criticisms&mdash;I do not know if it is in order for me to address the Chair in this fashion&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>It is quite all right.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JackLynch" hpid="Mr. J. Lynch Mr. J. Lynch">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J. Lynch</NameTxt>
      <P>You made the comment that you did not give a warm unqualified welcome to the Bill.  I should like to point out that in introducing this Bill in the Dáil I did not <Col N="793" /> claim anything very special for it.  I did not claim it was a revolutionary measure or that it would blaze a trail in any way in the matter of industrial research and standards, or in the matter of improving techniques or the quality of Irish goods.</P>
      <P>I said the Bill was designed to overhaul the functions, powers and the organisation of the Institute so as to enable it to function more effectively. As reported at column 988, Volume 189, No. 7, of the Official Report, I said:</P>
      <P>While it is proposed in the Bill to repeal the 1946 and 1954 Acts I should like to make it clear that the changes now proposed are not very radical inasmuch as the Institute as set up in 1946 is being continued in being, although its organisation, financing and functions are being adapted in the light of experience of their working.</P>
      <P>That is exactly what the Bill proposes to do.</P>
      <P>There are important changes in the Bill inasmuch as the financial restrictions within which the Institute had to operate hitherto will be removed to a considerable extent. Hitherto, it was given an annual subvention with a ceiling of £35,000 and it often happened that by reason of trying to work within that £35,000, it was never spent.  Henceforth, money will be made available for this work in the same manner as it is for any Department or section of a Department. The Institute will submit its programme and its estimate of the cost of that programme in advance, and it will be examined in the ordinary way in the Department, and approval will ultimately be sought for that amount from the Oireachtas. I think it is a more flexible arrangement. It is one that will give the Institute the opportunity of putting forward a realistic programme of expenditure and will give it, I hope, the opportunity of fulfilling its functions much more effectively than it has been able to fulfil them in the past.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="794" /> With regard to appointments&mdash;I should say that the existing Institute is not yet abolished&mdash;they had to come to the Minister for Industry and Commerce in respect of every appointment made.  The director had the making of the appointments but in the case of every appointment, he had to get specific sanction from the Minister for Industry and Commerce.  Now, except for those two or, perhaps, three designated posts, the Institute will have full authority to employ all its staff without any recourse to the Minister.</P>
    <P>There are, of course, some other changes in the Bill.  Again, I do not claim they are in any way revolutionary but they provide for the matter referred to by Senator Stanford&mdash;the development of inventions.  They ensure that certain commodities will conform to certain safety standards and some other minor matters.  Since I mention inventions, I might now deal with the comment made by Senator Stanford.  I do not think there is any threat in this legislation to the continuance in being of the Institute of Irish Inventors.  The Institute did seek and were given an interview by my Department. Even as late as last week, the Federation of Irish Industries came and one of the deputation mentioned this specific matter.  I take it that that particular member of the deputation had something to do with the Institute of Irish Inventors.  He was probably a member of it.  In giving the new Institute certain powers in relation to inventions, it is envisaged that the Institute will have the necessary equipment in respect of inventions which the voluntary body, the Institute of Irish Inventors, has not got.</P>
    <P>As far as subvention is concerned, there will not be any direct subvention as such by the Institute to the Institute of Irish Inventors but the Research Institute could employ the Institute of Irish Inventors if it happens to do any specific work and pay them for it.  In saying that, I am not in any way suggesting that this is to be a direction to the Institute for Industrial Research and Standards so to employ the voluntary Institute of Irish Inventors but it will have that power under the section. <Col N="795" /> Certainly, as far as co-operation is concerned, I would expect the Institute to give full co-operation to the existing voluntary body.</P>
    <P>I pass from what Senator O'Donovan said about the Bill.  I may say in passing that while there has been quite a volume of legislation from the Department of Industry and Commerce, I do not think it can be suggested that this Bill is unnecessary.  It is introduced because of the experience of the working of the existing Institute.  It has been said to me by more than one member of the existing council that the council is too unwieldy and that the two committees which operate are also too unwieldy and that the smaller board will be a much better servant of industry than the old council and committee.</P>
    <P>As far as the Senator's reference to the Companies Bill is concerned, if this Oireachtas is in existence in the autumn, I hope to have the pleasure of introducing this Bill.  In saying that, I feel that if it is not in existence in the autumn, the next Minister for Industry and Commerce will have the pleasure, as one of his first legislative acts, of introducing such a measure.</P>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>It will be a great day.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JackLynch" hpid="Mr. J. Lynch Mr. J. Lynch">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J. Lynch</NameTxt>
      <P>It will be appreciated that it is a voluminous document.  It involves a lot of research and a lot of drafting and redrafting.  The office of the Parliamentary draftsman has been kept very busy in recent months.  While I am not suggesting that that is the only reason the Bill has not yet been produced, it is one of them.</P>
      <P>Maidir leis an méid adúirt an Seanadóir Ó Siochfhradha d'fhiafrigh sé conas atá sé beartaithe an caighdeán a chur in éifeacht.  Sé an rud atá beartaithe ná caighdeán a ghlacadh agus aon earraí a chaithfear a dhíol agus an marc sin orthu caithfidh siad bheith suas chun an caighdeán sin.  Ni chuirfear cosc ar aon earraí a dhéanamh ach amháin má tá baol ann do bheatha nó do shláinte.  Sin é an t-aon chás amháin ina gcuirfear cosc ar dhaoine aon rud a dhéanamh mar sin.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I think that largely takes care of the <Col N="796" /> question asked by Senator Cole in reference to Section 44.  The Bill as it stands is, perhaps, not specific enough. The intention is that restriction will be put on manufacturers in the making or producing of articles, only if they constitute a danger to life or health.  I propose to bring in on Committee Stage an amendment to clarify that section and to ensure that there can be no doubt about it.  I agree that there can be certain doubt as to what the section may mean in its existing form.</P>
    <P>I should refer to Senator Donegan's suggestion that the publication of the results of tests or analyses should be undertaken only on very rare occasions, if at all.  I think he chose a bad example.  He will be more aware than I, because of his association with the cereal trade, that the tests carried out in relation to the production of a palatable loaf from all Irish wheat were carried out following quite a lot of public interest and even agitation.  It is only reasonable that the results of these tests should have been published.  Whether it was a good thing or a bad thing, I do not know. As far as the millability of wheat is concerned, he will know that countries all over the world are trying to find tests as to millability without success.</P>
    <P>In any event, the testing of wheat is something that will now be given over by the Institute for Industrial Research and Standards to An Foras Talúntais, being more an agricultural than an industrial problem.  I take it that An Foras Talúntais will be more properly equipped and have the necessary technical power to carry out these functions as well at least, if not better, than the Institute has done heretofore.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickSDonegan" hpid="Mr. Donegan Mr. Donegan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Donegan</NameTxt>
      <P>We have a lot of leeway to make up.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JackLynch" hpid="Mr. J. Lynch Mr. J. Lynch">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J. Lynch</NameTxt>
      <P>That about meets all the points which have been raised and if there are any clarifications or any other points they could be dealt with&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OwenSkeffington" hpid="Dr. Sheehy Skeffington Dr. Sheehy Skeffington">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Sheehy Skeffington</NameTxt>
      <P>Might I ask the Minister to reply to the question I put as to whether he anticipates encountering any prejudice in <Col N="797" /> the public mind against goods because of the standard mark?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JackLynch" hpid="Mr. J. Lynch Mr. J. Lynch">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J. Lynch</NameTxt>
      <P>I think the example put by the Senator in suggesting there is a certain amount of inconsistency in what we are doing here this evening has been dealt with by Senator Carter and Senator Donegan, inasmuch as an egg is not manufactured.  In regard to the stamp on the egg, many people felt, rightly or wrongly, that the dye might have some obnoxious substance in it which would penetrate the shell and affect the contents, but the intention of the standard mark is that when a manufacturer accepts the standard mark and applies it to his goods, it will be <i>prima facie</i> evidence to the public that the goods conform to the standard set out by the Institute.  If the goods do not carry a standard mark, there certainly is no power in this Bill to require all goods to carry a standard mark, but it will be an indication to the public that they are not intended to conform to the standard specification as formulated by the Institute.  Therefore it is to be presumed, in my opinion anyhow, that the members of the public will assume that the goods are perhaps not up to the required standard.  Therefore, the goods carrying the mark will enjoy a selling value above the goods not so marked.  I do not think there is any question of prejudice.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>Committee Stage ordered for next sitting day.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Agricultural Produce (Eggs) Bill, 1961" RHead="&mdash;Committee and Final Stages">
    <Title>Agricultural Produce (Eggs) Bill, 1961 &mdash;Committee and Final Stages.</Title>
    <P>Section 1 agreed to.</P>
    <P Just="Center">SECTION 2.</P>
    <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That Section 2 stand part of the Bill.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="OwenSkeffington" hpid="Dr. Sheehy Skeffington Dr. Sheehy Skeffington">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Sheehy Skeffington</NameTxt>
      <P>This is the section that particularly concerned me in asking the House and the Minister to delay the Committee Stage until to-day. It is the section I wanted to think over in relation to the possibility of proposing amendments.  I am grateful to the House for the delay and to the <Col N="798" /> Minister for taking it in good part and being prepared to come along, particularly at this late hour, to consider the Committee Stage.  I hope we are agreed that the general principle of such delay is a good one because it enables us to reconsider the questions raised on the Second Stage and also gives time for possible reactions to them to make themselves manifest, if there are such reactions.  I considered putting down an amendment to delete this section but I thought, in the light of what the Minister said, and in view of the fact that there did not seem to be any manifest public reaction against this change, and also in view of the fact that it was apparently unlikely that the section could be deleted since the Minister considers it to be one of the most important parts of the Bill, that instead I would content myself with making a final comment.</P>
      <P>The comment I want to make is to stress the fact that I still cannot help feeling that to remove the necessity for code marked eggs&mdash;the code mark being a guarantee of relative freshness&mdash;is a retrograde step.  When we buy a film which is marked &ldquo;To be developed before 1962,&rdquo; or whatever it may be, we take that as an indication of the film's freshness.  We also like to see on the milk bottle cap the day on which the milk was bottled.  On the last occasion, I feel the Minister exaggerated, shall we say, a prejudice which may exist but which I think does not exist to the extent he suggests, against code marked eggs.  If such exists, I should like to ask is the best way of removing the prejudice to remove the code mark?  I do not think so.  We should rather ask why is it that the public have this prejudice against these eggs?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>We have had another Minister saying how valuable it is to know that a commodity is marked with a standard specification mark and measures up to certain specifications which are guaranteed by the mark.  I fail to see why that should not apply equally to marking our eggs.  Perhaps the Department itself has not done all it might.  I feel that the public should <Col N="799" /> recognise that a code marked egg is guaranteed to come within a certain standard of freshness.  I notice that is done in Britain and I notice also in Britain that they still find it useful to have the Lion brand on the eggs which is widely recognised as a useful code mark.</P>
    <P>I do not want to delay the House but I want again to appeal to the Minister to recognise that in this matter he is moving backwards.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickSDonegan" hpid="Mr. Donegan Mr. Donegan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Donegan</NameTxt>
      <P>I think Senator Sheehy Skeffington finds himself alone in his view on eggs.  In Ireland, we are better judges of fresh eggs than the 49,000,000 who have to live in highly-industrialised England.  We enjoy a fresh egg and due to the multitudinous processes through which an egg has to go to be stamped before it reaches the consumers in England, it is no longer a fresh egg. The stamp guarantees that it is not a rotten egg.  We have the opportunity of getting a fresh egg. Because it does not have to go through all these processes and into the big wholesalers and out again, we feel it is a fresher egg.  I do not think the comparison with the film or even with the milk bottle holds water&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OwenSkeffington" hpid="Dr. Sheehy Skeffington Dr. Sheehy Skeffington">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Sheehy Skeffington</NameTxt>
      <P>It sometimes does.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickSDonegan" hpid="Mr. Donegan Mr. Donegan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Donegan</NameTxt>
      <P>Perhaps it sometimes does.  The position in regard to a film is that it is manufactured, and the position in regard to milk in the bottle is that it is processed and, as such, is expected to be of standard quality and of a standard age and everything else.  I believe there is nothing like a fresh egg.  The fresh egg I refer to has not got a code mark on it, because it is so fresh that there would not have been time to take it into a store, mark it and take it out again.  Whether we live in O'Connell Street or anywhere else, there are ways and means of getting fresh eggs. Before creamery butter came on the market, there were ways and means of getting fresh butter.  We are comparing <Col N="800" /> industrial England with agricultural Ireland and I think that is the answer.</P>
      <P>When I make my next comment with regard to a subsidy, the Minister will know that it is not meant in any political way because if he refers to my contribution on Second Stage, he will find that I said there was not an opportunity here for a subsidy.  I wanted to raise this point in relation to Section 42 of the principal Act dealing with fresh eggs and second quality eggs. The general view of the Advisory Committee was that there should be a minimum guaranteed price for eggs.  I said on Second Stage that I held the view, and still hold it, that the subventions would be too great even with the possibility in the future of a cessation of the subsidy.  There may be an opportunity in the future if we are doing a thriving trade in the export of eggs, but in present circumstances conditions are not such as to justify a subsidy.  I should like to hear from the Minister on that point if he would be good enough to elaborate on it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanODonovan" hpid="Seán Ó Donnabháin Seán Ó Donnabháin">
      <NameTxt>Seán Ó Donnabháin</NameTxt>
      <P>Senators who have spoken are forgetting the other sections of the Bill.  I predict that inside of two years we will be buying eggs in the packet or in the jar.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickSDonegan" hpid="Mr. Donegan Mr. Donegan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Donegan</NameTxt>
      <P>God forbid.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanODonovan" hpid="Seán Ó Donnabháin Seán Ó Donnabháin">
      <NameTxt>Seán Ó Donnabháin</NameTxt>
      <P>We can buy soups in the packet now and people are quite pleased with them.  In a subsequent section of the Bill provision is made for the appointment of qualified bacteriological examiners to examine all products.  Senators are forgetting about those conditions and dealing only with the fact that it is proposed to dispense with the stamping of eggs.  I have considerable experience of the practice of stamping eggs and I think when we find it is not serving the purpose it was intended to serve it is reasonable to dispense with it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I have no hesitation in predicting that we will in future be buying eggs in the jar, in the tin or in the packet, as we can now buy so many articles of food, including soups.  We are undoubtedly making industrial progress and that is the tendency.  The transport <Col N="801" /> of eggs on the home market and on the export market would undoubtedly be facilitated, if they could be transported in a concentrated form.  They would be much less liable to damage or putrefaction in transit.  It is better to dispense with a system which is not achieving the purpose for which it was intended, and I believe it is a good thing that we should dispense with it now.</P>
    <Speaker pid="OwenSkeffington" hpid="Dr. Sheehy Skeffington Dr. Sheehy Skeffington">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Sheehy Skeffington</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator Donegan referred to the Report on Shell Eggs and Liquid Egg.  In paragraph 29 which relates to this section, the Advisory Committee said:</P>
      <P>The present regulations in regard to the code marking of eggs for the home market are not being observed and in our opinion they cannot be effectively enforced.</P>
      <P>That means that the machinery of the Department has broken down and not that the Irish buyer in some magical way can spot a fresh egg as Senator Donegan suggested.  In fact in the same paragraph we read:</P>
      <P>One might even say that at present she will still buy unstamped eggs even if the chances are against their being better than stamped eggs. In any event, it is quite certain that at present the quality of stamped eggs is suspect and that such eggs will not be purchased if unstamped eggs are available.</P>
      <P>I suggest that is the result not of the system but of the failure on the part of those whose duty it is to enforce it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I think the Senator is stretching the meaning of that paragraph.  However, it is late at night to discuss it.  That is not my interpretation of its meaning.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OwenSkeffington" hpid="Dr. Sheehy Skeffington Dr. Sheehy Skeffington">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Sheehy Skeffington</NameTxt>
      <P>The regulations &ldquo;are not being observed&rdquo;.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>The plain meaning of the paragraph is that they are inoperable.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OwenSkeffington" hpid="Dr. Sheehy Skeffington Dr. Sheehy Skeffington">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Sheehy Skeffington</NameTxt>
      <P>With respect, if they are inoperable, I fail to see how they are operated in other countries.  We all know that poteen is manufactured occasionally but it is <Col N="802" /> not found impossible to enforce the regulations in that regard.  We do not simply say: &ldquo;Let everyone make it&rdquo;.  I feel that the apparatus or the machinery of the Department is breaking down and I regard that as a retrograde step.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickSDonegan" hpid="Mr. Donegan Mr. Donegan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Donegan</NameTxt>
      <P>I should like to refer Senator Sheehy Skeffington to paragraph 30 of the Report.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>May I interrupt the Senator?  It is now 10.10 p.m. and the Senator knows we have been operating with a very limited Reporting Staff to-day.  Perhaps the Senator would summarise his remarks.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickSDonegan" hpid="Mr. Donegan Mr. Donegan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Donegan</NameTxt>
      <P>Certainly.  Section 30 of the Report reads:</P>
      <P>In our opinion, the code mark on eggs sold on the home market serves little purpose at present and we recommend that it should be abolished. This will eliminate a great deal of the abuses in connection with the sale of unstamped eggs at premium price and we do not consider that it will be to the detriment of consumers.</P>
      <P>I did not suggest there was some magical way in which the consumer can spot a fresh egg.  There are always ways and means of getting eggs which one knows to be fresh from farmers, and that is really the point.  Would the Minister be good enough to give his views on the point I raised about the subsidy?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I doubt if it is relevant.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickSmith" hpid="Mr. Smith Mr. Smith">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Smith</NameTxt>
      <P>I thought I had dealt with this point on a previous occasion after the debate on Second Reading. If I did not, this is what I would say on the subject.  If you fix a price for any product, you fix that price to achieve some purpose.  The purpose we would want to achieve by fixing a price for eggs would be, I assume, that the production of eggs would be increased over and above what would be necessary to supply the demand on the home market.  In order to do that, the price would have to be sufficiently attractive.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>If the price were not sufficiently <Col N="803" /> attractive, you would not get that increased production, and if you did not succeed in getting increased production and attempted to fix the price just as in the case of the stamping of eggs, you would not be able to make the fixation of the price effective.  If you did succeed in determining the price that would encourage increased production then we would have to look for markets outside.  Even the Advisory Committee in their presentation of the report and in the words they use talked about trying to find markets on the Continent.  They were very shaky, indeed, when they came to deal with this whole matter of the prospects of finding these markets and the problems associated with the disposing of any increased production resulting from such an effort.</P>
    <P>I did say on the last occasion that this was one business that suited this country.  It suits our small farmers; suits the way of life of a great number of our people.  It was one business that I was never engaged in other than as a farmer's son.  I knew a little bit about it and it is important.  It was one of the businesses to which I personally as an individual and surely as Minister for Agriculture would be delighted to lend a hand in promoting and expanding.  In the present state of affairs and knowing conditions, I could not see any prospect at all of doing that, nor do I see, to tell the truth, very much sense in the recommendation. I suspect that those who made it were not very enthusiastic about it even if they did commit themselves on paper in that regard.  That is all I want to say about that matter now.</P>
    <P>Senator Sheehy Skeffington referred to the fact that in 1939 the code marking of eggs was introduced for export and later for home sale.  He thinks that, in 1961, we are abandoning the code marking of eggs for home sales and that we are giving power to abandon it in certain cases, should there be any exports to certain countries which do not like code marking.  He says that is a retrograde step.  I do not know for the life of me how one can regard as a retrograde step something you did 20 <Col N="804" /> years ago in the belief that you were suiting public opinion and public feeling at the time.  I remember the people were pleased with and traders welcomed the code marking of eggs in 1939.  It was done in response to public demand.  It was believed by most people that it was a good thing.  It was tried out since.  In 1961, we find the body which investigated this whole matter making this recommendation. As I said on the last occasion, we know ourselves from contacts that after this experiment we were prepared to say that we tried this and it did not turn out to be what we thought it would be.</P>
    <Speaker pid="OwenSkeffington" hpid="Dr. Sheehy Skeffington Dr. Sheehy Skeffington">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Sheehy Skeffington</NameTxt>
      <P>We have not been able to do it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickSmith" hpid="Mr. Smith Mr. Smith">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Smith</NameTxt>
      <P>It is not that, because on page 8, paragraph 28 of the Advisory Body's report we find these lines:</P>
      <P>We understand that in Britain also sales of unstamped eggs are considerable even though no subsidy payment is made on the eggs.</P>
      <P>Even in Britain where there is this code marking, where everything is done properly, where the law is observed by everybody and where everything is always perfect&mdash;we are not saints in this land of ours, I know; but we are not as bad as we think we are by comparison with some others&mdash;they are prepared to pay the higher price and to neglect and ignore the subsidy paid by the taxpayer in order to get eggs that are unstamped.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OwenSkeffington" hpid="Dr. Sheehy Skeffington Dr. Sheehy Skeffington">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Sheehy Skeffington</NameTxt>
      <P>It is very exceptional.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickSmith" hpid="Mr. Smith Mr. Smith">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Smith</NameTxt>
      <P>They know.  Evidence was tendered to them but there is no country in the world in which that is not the case.  Rather than being a retrograde step, it is indicative of our approach and our understanding of public thought on matters like this and of Parliament falling into line with public thought.  If that is a retrograde step, I do not know what the meaning of true democracy is.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOQuigley" hpid="Mr. O'Quigley Mr. O'Quigley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Quigley</NameTxt>
      <P>Despite what the Minister may say about Senator <Col N="805" /> Sheehy Skeffington's approach to the abolition of the code marking of eggs, there is the great argument in favour of Senator Sheehy Skeffington that code marking persisted for a period of 22 years.  That is the great argument in favour of its continuance.  The reason I believe the code mark did not work is this: If on a Sunday night Radio Éireann announced that the Minister had fixed the code mark 73 for eggs tested next week, on Monday afternoon the housewife would not know whether the mark was 73 or 49.  It broke down.  In the operation of that system there was the failure to require those selling the eggs to have the particular code mark on display in the shops.</P>
      <P>It remains to be seen, when all these restrictions are removed, whether or not the people will get fresh eggs or eggs as fresh as they got up to the present time.  I agree with the notion that if you try out one thing and you have a belief it is not correct, Parliament should not hesitate to experiment.  The only observation I wish to make to the Minister is that I heard him saying that we were not half as bad as we think.  On this side of the House, we are not half as bad as he thinks sometimes.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickSmith" hpid="Mr. Smith Mr. Smith">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Smith</NameTxt>
      <P>I rarely think of you at all; that is the truth of the matter.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOQuigley" hpid="Mr. O'Quigley Mr. O'Quigley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Quigley</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister becomes quite abusive at times.  At any rate, the stout defender of his position was Senator Donegan. Senator Donegan talked about the phrase used in the country that &ldquo;eggs is eggs.&rdquo;  That is as good as the English used in the Courts of Justice <Col N="806" /> and Court Officers (Superannuation) Bill 1961, which we had before us today.  Here in this Bill is another example of the slovenly draftsmanship we are getting in Bills lately.  I take a stand against handing to Parliament slovenly Acts and draftsmanship when people can be recruited to do the job in a proper way.</P>
      <P>In subsection (3) of Section 2 of the Bill, the following occurs:</P>
      <P>In this section &ldquo;fresh eggs&rdquo; has the meaning assigned to it by section 42 of the Principal Act.</P>
      <P>Here we see that the phrase &ldquo;fresh eggs,&rdquo; is followed by the singular form of the verb.  If we are going to write English, we might write it correctly. The proper way to do that is to say: &ldquo;In this section the expression &lsquo;fresh eggs&rsquo; has the meaning assigned to it by section 42 of the Principal Act.&rdquo;  We ought to do something of that nature instead of indulging in slovenly expressions. It does no credit to Parliament, the Minister or the Department to pass legislation that way.  I have no doubt that that observation will find no favour whatever with the Minister.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>Sections 3 to 5, inclusive, agreed to.</P>
      <P>Title agreed to.</P>
      <P>Bill reported without amendment.</P>
      <P>Agreed to take remaining Stages to-day.</P>
      <P>Bill received for final consideration and passed.</P>
      <P>The Seanad adjourned at 10.25 p.m. <i>sine die.</i></P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
</Debate>