<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE Debate SYSTEM "../Debate.dtd"[]>
<Debate DocTitle="Seanad Debate" Day="Wed" Date="5" Month="Jul" Year="1961" Vol="54" No="10" DateIrish="Dé Céadaoin, 5 Iúil 1961" DateEnglish="Wednesday, 5 July 1961" House="S" CommitteeEng="" CommitteeIr="" SubNameEng="" cnum="955">
  <MainHeading Type="Prelude" LHead="" RHead="">
    <Title>
    </Title>
    <P>
      <Col N="955" /> Do chuaigh an Cathaoirleach i gceannas ar 3 p.m.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Order of" RHead="Business">
    <Title>Order of Business.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomas Ó Maoláin Tomas Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomas Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>It is proposed to take business as on the Order Paper, from No. 1 to 4.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Professor Hayes Professor Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Professor Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>Apart from the Order of Business today, might I ask whether we could have any indication what business we shall be asked to conclude before the Adjournment?  I know that we shall have to finish financial business, the Finance Bill and the Appropriation Bill, and the Bills on the Order Paper, but I find on the Dáil Order Paper eleven other Bills.  Could the Leader of the House, at the next sitting perhaps, let us know how far we are expected to go?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>It is intended to complete all the Bills, to which Senator Hayes has referred, except the Local Government Planning and Development) Bill.  In addition, there are three or four minor Bills which do not involve any major changes and which will be coming along in due course.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Professor Hayes Professor Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Professor Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>That is not only absurd but it will also prove to be impossible.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamStanford" hpid="Professor Stanford Professor Stanford">
      <NameTxt>Professor Stanford</NameTxt>
      <P>On the orders of the day, none of us has received the printed reports of the debates for our last sitting.  This is a serious impediment to the effectiveness of our debates in this House.  Could we have some explanation for it and could we have some assurance that this will not recur?  It is definitely a handicap that we are not able to study the previous day's debate in print before our sitting.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OwenSkeffington" hpid="Dr. Sheehy Skeffington Dr. Sheehy Skeffington">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Sheehy Skeffington</NameTxt>
      <P>On the related problem, I should like to ask <Col N="956" /> the question again: has there been any result from the active consideration which we have been told is being devoted to the question of the Reporting Staff and which I would describe rather as passive consideration, judging by results?  I felt on the last occasion when at 10 o'clock we were told we were concluding the legislative business and not taking the motions and not meeting on Thursday that we should have been told at seven o'clock. I feel that the Seanad is being rather pushed around and that this arises from the fact that those in control are unable to handle staff problems in a way which would satisfy the Seanad. I should like to ask whether the question has been considered of setting up an <i>ad hoc</i> committee of the two Houses to settle this problem which apparently the Ceann Comhairle has been unable to settle?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LiamOBuachalla" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>In reply to Senator Stanford's question, the delay in printing is caused by the shortage of staff.  We had hoped that the report would be available for today but that hope has not been justified.</P>
      <P>With regard to the question raised by Senator Sheehy Skeffington, as far as I am aware, the position regarding the Reporting Staff dispute remains unaltered from that of last week.  The position is that the staff have not yet availed themselves of the arbitration and conciliation machinery.  Members of the Committee on Procedure and Privileges are kept appraised of any developments in the situation and I do not think any useful purpose can be served by question and answer in this House.  I may say that anything the Chair can do to have this matter adjusted satisfactorily will not be left undone.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OwenSkeffington" hpid="Dr. Sheehy Skeffington Dr. Sheehy Skeffington">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Sheehy Skeffington</NameTxt>
      <P>Arising out of your reply, Sir, I have seen in writing that the Staff are prepared to resort to arbitration and submit their case, provided the <i>status quo ante</i> January, 1961, is restored.  Am I to take it from your reply that the authorities have refused it?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LiamOBuachalla" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>The proper course is for the staff to avail of the <Col N="957" /> machinery that is there for the adjustment of this dispute.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamStanford" hpid="Professor Stanford Professor Stanford">
      <NameTxt>Professor Stanford</NameTxt>
      <P>May I just say that the proper course for the administration of Leinster House is to see that our debates are as efficient as possible, and they cannot be as efficient as possible unless we have the previous week's debates in our hands before the next sitting.  I should like to emphasise that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OwenSkeffington" hpid="Dr. Sheehy Skeffington Dr. Sheehy Skeffington">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Sheehy Skeffington</NameTxt>
      <P>I should like to ask further is it the intention of the House to sit tomorrow?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>It all depends on how the business goes this evening.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OwenSkeffington" hpid="Dr. Sheehy Skeffington Dr. Sheehy Skeffington">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Sheehy Skeffington</NameTxt>
      <P>How late is it intended to sit this evening?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>Again that depends on the progress of the business.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OwenSkeffington" hpid="Dr. Sheehy Skeffington Dr. Sheehy Skeffington">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Sheehy Skeffington</NameTxt>
      <P>I should like to ask the Leader of the House will we be told before 10 o'clock if it is intended to sit late, because we were not told on the last occasion?  I do not think business should be conducted in that manner.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LiamOBuachalla" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Perhaps we can get an announcement after the tea interval.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>We will probably be able to make an announcement after tea.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Hospitals Federation and Amalgamation Bill," RHead="1961&mdash;Committee and Final Stages">
    <Title>Hospitals Federation and Amalgamation Bill, 1961&mdash;Committee and Final Stages.</Title>
    <P>Section 1 agreed to.</P>
    <P Just="Center">SECTION 2.</P>
    <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That Section 2 stand part of the Bill.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Minister for Health (Mr. MacEntee) Minister for Health (Mr. MacEntee)">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Health (Mr. MacEntee)</NameTxt>
      <P>Perhaps I might explain that under this section the Minister by order may appoint a day to be called the establishment day, that is, the day upon which the hospitals group will be established as a federation under the Bill.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P Just="Center">
      <Col N="958" /> SECTION 3.</P>
    <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That Section 3 stand part of the Bill.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>This section enables the Minister to appoint a certain critical day under the Bill, that is, the transfer day upon which all the property and functions of the existing federation will be transferred to the amalgamated hospitals.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>Sections 4 to 6, inclusive, agreed to.</P>
      <P Just="Center">SECTION 7.</P>
      <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That Section 7 stand part of the Bill.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>Just in case some Senator may wish to know, this section defines the constitution of the Central Council.  Basically, there will be 40 members, five from each hospital authority and five appointed by the Dublin Health Authority.  In addition, two members may be appointed in each case by any university, college or any institution which has entered into an agreement with the Council for the clinical education of medical students.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P Just="Center">SECTION 8.</P>
      <P>Government amendment No. 1:</P>
      <P>In subsection (1), line 50, before &ldquo;of&rdquo; to insert &ldquo;or subsection (3).&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>I suggest we take amendments Nos. 1, 2 and 3 together.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LiamOBuachalla" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Amendments Nos. 1, 2 and 3 may be taken together.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>Under subsection (1) of Section 6 and subsection (1) of Section 8 of the Bill, every person who on the establishment of the Federated Dublin Voluntary Hospitals was a member of the governing body of a participating hospital will become a member of the hospital board of that hospital and, under Section 8, as now drafted, would continue in a membership until he died, resigned or ceased to be a member because of, shall we say, slackness in attending meetings.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="959" /> That provision does not apply to the Meath Hospital, elections for which will continue to be made under the Meath Hospital Act, 1951.  While there is no statutory provision for local authority representation on the governing body of any of the seven participating hospitals, with the exception of the Meath Hospital, in practice, an arrangement has been operated by each of the other six hospitals under which the Dublin Corporation appoint a member or members to the governing body.  Those members hold office during the term of the Corporation and the places in the governing body which they fill are thrown open and have to be refilled after each local election.</P>
    <P>It has been represented on behalf of the participating hospitals that it would be undesirable that those who happen at the moment to be Corporation assignees on the governing bodies of the participating hospitals should be entitled to continue in perpetual membership in the same way as the ordinary members of the governing body.  It was accordingly proposed that Section 8 should be so amended that the Corporation members would go out of office from the hospital board at the time when they would have ceased to be members of the governing bodies of the hospitals, if this Bill bad never been introduced.</P>
    <P>The effect of amendment No. 2 is to provide for this, and amendment No. 3 will provide that a vacancy in the membership of a hospital board caused by a person ceasing to be a member in accordance with amendment No. 2 or by a person who would have so ceased to be a member dying, resigning or relinquishing membership, will be filled by co-option by the hospital board but having regard to any recommendation made by the Dublin Health Authority as to the person to be co-opted.</P>
    <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
    <P>Government amendment No. 2:</P>
    <P>In page 9, before subsection (3), to insert the following subsection:&mdash;</P>
    <P>&ldquo;( )  Any member of the hospital board who</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="960" /> (a)  became a member of the board by virtue of his having been, immediately before the establishment day, a member, appointed on the recommendation of a local authority, of the governing body of the hospital, or</P>
    <P>(b)  was co-opted as a member of the board on the recommendation of the Dublin Health Authority,</P>
    <P>shall cease to be a member of the board on the day of such first meeting of the Dublin Health Authority after the quinquennial appointment of the members of that Authority as next follows the commencement of his term of office.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
    <P>Government amendment No. 3:</P>
    <P>In page 9, before subsection (4), to insert the following subsection:&mdash;</P>
    <P>&ldquo;( )  Where a vacancy in the membership of a hospital board falling to be filled under subsection (3) of this section is caused by&mdash;</P>
    <P>(a)  a person ceasing under subsection (*) of this section to be a member of the board, or</P>
    <P>(b)  the death, resignation or cesser of membership under subsection (2) of this section of a person who, if he had not died, resigned or so ceased.to be a member of the board, would have ceased under subsection (*) of this section to be a member of the board,</P>
    <P>the hospital board, in filling the vacancy, shall have regard to any recommendation made by the Dublin Health Authority as to the person to be co-opted.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
    <P>Section 8, as amended, agreed to.</P>
    <P>Sections 9 to 13, inclusive, agreed to.</P>
    <P Just="Center">SECTION 14.</P>
    <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That Section 14 stand part of the Bill.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>The Seanad may be aware of the proposal to assign in detail functions in relation to the participating hospitals which are to be performed by the Council.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="961" /> Question put and agreed to.</P>
    <P>Sections 15 to 18, inclusive, agreed to.</P>
    <P Just="Center">SECTION 19.</P>
    <P>Government amendment No. 4:</P>
    <P>In page 14, subsection (4), line 15, before &ldquo;of&rdquo; to insert &ldquo;or the hospital board&rdquo;.</P>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>I am indebted to Senator O'Quigley for this amendment and am glad to pay him that tribute. The section provides for the adaptation of references in conveyances, deeds, wills and other instruments, so that they can have effect after the hospitals are amalgamated on the transfer day. Under subsection (4) of Section 19, as it stands, it is provided that references to the hospitals and to their governing bodies will be given appropriate new constructions.  The effect of amendment No. 4 will be to give similar construction to a reference in any conveyance, deed, will or other instrument to the hospital board of a participating hospital which will be established under Section 6 of the Bill.</P>
      <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
      <P>Section 19, as amended, agreed to.</P>
      <P>Section 20 agreed to.</P>
      <P Just="Center">SECTION 21.</P>
      <P>Government amendment No. 5:</P>
      <P>In page 15, paragraph (b), lines 2 and 3, to delete &ldquo;by whom&rdquo; and substitute &ldquo;by whose death, resignation or cesser of membership under subsection (8) of section 7 of this Act&rdquo;.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>This is a drafting amendment.  It is a simple amendment.</P>
      <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
      <P>Government amendment No. 6:</P>
      <P>In page 15, to delete subparagraph (ii) of paragraph (b) and substitute the following subparagraph:&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>&ldquo;(ii)  if such member was a member of the visiting medical staff of a participating hospital or of the visiting medical staff of the participating hospitals or of the visiting medical staff of any hospital <Col N="962" /> administered by the Council, the person co-opted shall also be a member of one of those visiting medical staffs,&rdquo;.</P>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>Section 21, paragraph (b), subparagraph (ii) provides that where, by co-option, a vacancy in the Central Council is filled after the establishment day and the person occasioning the vacancy was a member of the visiting medical staff of the participating hospitals, his successor will also be a member of that staff. This subparagraph is defective as, in fact, those persons holding office on the visiting medical staff of a particular participating hospital on the establishment of the federation will retain their status of attachment to the one hospital.  Those appointed after the establishment day will be &ldquo;visiting medical staff of the participating hospitals&rdquo;, that is, the hospital group as a whole.</P>
      <P>In addition, there is power in subsection (3) of Section 5 of the Bill under which the Council could at some future time provide a completely new hospital, which would not, of course, be one of the &ldquo;participating hospitals&rdquo;. Therefore, provision should have been made in subparagraph (ii) for three categories of visiting medical staff, those for individual hospitals, those for the participating hospitals as a group and those for any new hospital which may be established by the Council. The purpose of the amendment is to make such provision.</P>
      <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
      <P>Section 21, as amended, agreed to.</P>
      <P>Sections 22 to 27, inclusive, agreed to.</P>
      <P>First Schedule agreed to.</P>
      <P Just="Center">SECOND SCHEDULE.</P>
      <P>Government Amendment No. 7:</P>
      <P>In page 16, paragraph 1 (1), line 31, to delete &ldquo;date&rdquo; and substitute &ldquo;day&rdquo;.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>This is merely a drafting amendment in the Schedule. The word &ldquo;date&rdquo; is used when it ought to have been &ldquo;day&rdquo;.</P>
      <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="963" /> Second Schedule, as amended, agreed to.</P>
    <P>Third and Fourth Schedules agreed to.</P>
    <P>Title agreed to.</P>
    <P>Bill reported with amendments.</P>
    <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That the Bill be received for final consideration.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Professor Hayes Professor Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Professor Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>On the Report Stage, which comes to us after amendments have been inserted on Committee Stage, it might be appropriate to say that the amendments we have inserted in this Bill are proof of the usefulness of a second House in enabling members of that House and Ministers themselves to take a second look at a Bill which has been passed through the Dáil.  It shows us also that we should be very loath to allow all Stages of any Bill to be passed on the same day and Ministers should be very loath to ask for that.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That the Bill do now pass.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>I should like again to say that I, as Minister for Health, and the whole community, owe a debt to the governing bodies of the seven hospitals concerned in this Bill for the manner in which they have been able to compose differences and to sacrifice certain traditional autonomies to enable us to solve a problem which has been crying out for solution for a very great many years.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Nurses Bill, 1961&mdash;Committee" RHead="and Final Stages">
    <Title>Nurses Bill, 1961&mdash;Committee and Final Stages.</Title>
    <P>Sections 1 to 6, inclusive, agreed to.</P>
    <P Just="Center">SECTION 7.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickQuinlan" hpid="Professor Quinlan Professor Quinlan">
      <NameTxt>Professor Quinlan</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 1:</P>
      <P>To delete subsection (1).</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I move this amendment so that the Seanad may be aware of the very serious tendencies towards centralisation and more State control that are contained in this apparently very <Col N="964" /> innocuous amending Bill.  The main purpose of this Bill is really enshrined in Section 7.  It shows that the purpose is simply that the Minister shall appoint the president.  The president had previously been appointed by a majority decision of the board.  As Senator Jessop pointed out the last day, had this been in the original Bill, perhaps, we would not have taken so much notice of it.  It is our duty to call attention to the tendency by the State to control everything.  I made it quite clear in my previous speech on this that we, of necessity, being a poor country that came late to our independence and having so much to do, were forced into doing quite a great deal of this through the State.</P>
    <P>I refer to such concerns as the E.S.B., Bord na Móna, the Sugar Company, and so on.  These have all done very good work.  In the past 12 months, we have had another, spate of Bills setting up more semi-State bodies &mdash;the various marketing organisations. It might be contended that they could have been dealt with on somewhat different lines.  Anyway, the decision has been taken.  They are there as semi-State bodies.  That being so, we owe it to our future citizens to try to safeguard the future against the dictatorship of complete centralisation.</P>
    <Speaker pid="LiamOBuachalla" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>The discussion must concern the amendment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickQuinlan" hpid="Professor Quinlan Professor Quinlan">
      <NameTxt>Professor Quinlan</NameTxt>
      <P>I am moving to the amendment.  Where possible, we must return power to the lesser organisations. As the State power grows, we must try to prune a certain amount from it.  This section and especially subsection (1) is directly contrary to that spirit.  The only reason the Minister advanced the last day for seeking this power was that previous presidents admittedly did not toe the line. So, a Minister of State is henceforth to be the sole arbiter on whether an outside body is performing its function or not.  The measure of the efficiency of the holder of the office is to be judged apparently by the readiness with which he complies with the dictates of the State.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The Minister tried to soften this for us by stating he himself had no intention in regard to this post.  I readily <Col N="965" /> grant that to him.  He said that, as proof of that, it was proposed that the present holder should continue for his full term of office and go on for whatever three or four years he has left. That makes it all the worse.  We are here to legislate not for today but for the future, not for the next three or four years.  We are here to pass legislation that will be as valid in the future as it is today.  Consequently, the Minister's assurance about the present occupant of the post is not satisfactory.</P>
    <P>Apparently the last day, the Minister took grave exception to what I said, especially when I quoted the principle of subsidiary function which is the principle on which I based my opposition to this section.  This is the keystone principle of all Catholic social teaching as contained in <i>Quadragesimo Anno</i>.  It is a principle of universal validity.  The principle from <i>Quadragesimo Anno</i> states:</P>
    <P>It is an injustice, a grave evil and a disturbance of right order for a larger and higher association to arrogate to itself functions which can be performed efficiently by smaller and lesser societies.</P>
    <P>That is a general principle.  It is sufficiently elastic perhaps to be interpreted in the framework of the country concerned.</P>
    <P>Essentially, it says that the State should not do what other bodies can do efficiently.  That is the position here.  This other body, An Bord Altranais, has been appointing its president for the past ten years.  It has been doing so efficiently by all the standards we can observe.  Consequently, it is a move in the wrong direction for the Minister to arrogate that power to himself.  He does not dispose of this principle merely by the <i>reductio ad absurdum</i> he suggested the last day that when you carry that on to its extreme limit, you have to go down and down and that the upper bodies can do almost nothing.</P>
    <P>Nobody who knows anything of Christian social teaching would endeavour to decry a principle in that fashion.  In giving those principles, we have to be careful, on the one hand, <Col N="966" /> to be scrupulous of their terms, showing the wide latitude involved, and so on.  They are principles based on the natural order which is the result of a very long and protracted study by very keen minds over many years.</P>
    <P>As principles and as expressions of social teaching, they deserve to be considered carefully and their contexts examined in connection with our situation.  On the other hand, in exposing those, we must treat with the contempt it deserves any defiance that simply seeks to make a mockery of the principle.  Consequently, it is with a full consciousness of the position that I move this amendment.  I move it solely so that the Seanad may be aware of the tendency towards which we are heading and that the Seanad may examine each piece of legislation to ensure we are building up a healthy society for the future and not merely one that will be utterly and completely paralysed by the colossus of State control.</P>
    <P>As far as principles are concerned and as far as the details of Bills are concerned, I do not see why each Senator should not regard himself as having a duty to examine each matter, completely independent of Party principles or Party politics.  If we can import Party politics into mere subsections of Bills, then, I think we are going very far.  I know nobody wishes to do that.  Consequently, I appeal to the House to consider this, to study the principle and to see that each group in our society is allowed to function in the way it should function in a proper democracy.</P>
    <Speaker pid="GeraldLEstrange" hpid="Mr. L'Estrange Mr. L'Estrange">
      <NameTxt>Mr. L'Estrange</NameTxt>
      <P>I think the step taken by the Minister in this Section is a retrograde step, a step in the wrong direction.  I think the Board was established under the Nurses Act, 1950.  It has worn very well since then and the Minister cannot deny that.  The reason it has worked so well is, I think, the large measure of freedom it has from Departmental and Ministerial control.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>We are entitled to look with a certain amount of suspicion on this section.  A man was president of the Board for a long number of years&mdash;I <Col N="967" /> think ten years&mdash;a man of independence and of character.  He differed from the present Minister and I think he differed also from other Ministers for Health.  I think the Minister wants to make certain that that man will not be appointed president of this Board in the future, although for ten years he had the full support and the full cooperation of the members of An Bord Altranais.</P>
    <P>Senator Quinlan has spoken about private enterprise and voluntary bodies. I myself believe private enterprise and voluntary bodies do much better if left to themselves, without too much Ministerial or State control.  I feel this whole question should be divorced from petty Party politics, but unfortunately it is not.  I happen to have some little experience of this.</P>
    <P>At column 783, Volume 189, of the Dáil Reports, the Minister stated that 13 members of the Board were appointed by the Minister and Deputy O'Higgins said:</P>
    <P>Appointed, on nomination, by the Minister.</P>
    <P>Mr. MacEntee: No, after consultation-that is not nomination.</P>
    <P>Mr. T.F. O'Higgins: I know the Minister's view in relation to that.  I certainly appointed them on nomination.</P>
    <P>Mr. MacEntee: I happen to feel that I am the custodian of the rights of Dáil Eireann.</P>
    <P>I should love to think there is nothing else at the back of the Minister's mind than that he was the custodian of the rights of Dáil Eireann but unfortunately there was a little bit of Party politics behind all that.</P>
    <P>On one occasion, the General Council of County Councils gave the Minister the names of three people who were members of the General Council. At the time, the Minister recommended that they appoint a man who was not a member and they refused to do so. They gave him the name of one man who was a Fianna Fáil man but he stuck to his views and appointed a man <Col N="968" /> who was not a member of the General Council of County Councils.</P>
    <Speaker pid="LiamOBuachalla" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>The Senator is now going outside the scope of the amendment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeraldLEstrange" hpid="Mr. L'Estrange Mr. L'Estrange">
      <NameTxt>Mr. L'Estrange</NameTxt>
      <P>I may be, but I am entitled&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LiamOBuachalla" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>The Senator is not entitled to go outside the scope of the amendment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeraldLEstrange" hpid="Mr. L'Estrange Mr. L'Estrange">
      <NameTxt>Mr. L'Estrange</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister's attitude is a dictatorial one.  The Minister wants to make sure that it is not the Board's wishes which are adhered to, but his own wishes.  I think I am entitled to state that if the different bodies want a particular man to be president, the Minister over the years has made sure, and is at present making sure, that it is not their representative but whoever the Minister himself wants to be president of that Board, will be president.  If the Minister has a good reason for introducing this section, he should take us into his confidence and give us the reason.  The fact that the Minister appoints the chairman of the Voluntary Health Insurance Board is no valid reason or justification why he should appoint the president of this Board.</P>
      <P>There are 23 members on the Board and the Minister nominates or appoints 13 of those.  He appoints the majority. Surely he should have confidence in his own nominees to do what they believe to be best.  I think this is a retrograde step and, as Senator Quinlan says, we should remember that we are legislating for the future.  I support the amendment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>I am very sorry that the debate has taken this turn because it will be necessary for me to clear up some misapprehensions which appear to lurk in the minds of Senator Quinlan and Senator L'Estrange. Senator L'Estrange said that I approached these appointments in a partisan spirit.  In the same breath, he tells me the General Council of County Councils sent up three Fianna Fáil nominees and I did not appoint one of them.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="969" />
    <Speaker pid="GeraldLEstrange" hpid="Mr. L'Estrange Mr. L'Estrange">
      <NameTxt>Mr. L'Estrange</NameTxt>
      <P>I said three members, one of whom was Fianna Fáil.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>And I did not appoint him ?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeraldLEstrange" hpid="Mr. L'Estrange Mr. L'Estrange">
      <NameTxt>Mr. L'Estrange</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister wanted to appoint another Fianna Fáil man.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not recollect the particular episode to which Senator L'Estrange refers, but if I appointed somebody else, it was because I thought the other person was a better representative.  There was no question of Party politics.  I am not like Senator L'Estrange, I do not approach public affairs in Ireland with the same squint as he does.  I look them straight in the face and try to do the best I can.</P>
      <P>It was stated by Senator Quinlan, and repeated by Senator L'Estrange, that the immediate predecessor of the present president had been president of this Board for ten years.  Of course that is not true.  There was as president, from 1951 to 1953, a very distinguished man, and a one-time comrade of my own.  He died and was succeeded by another eminent physician in the city of Dublin, of considerable eminence, the present chairman of the Midwives Committee of the Board, and he held office in 1954 and 1955 and was beaten in an election in 1956.  There was not raised then any high argument based on subsidiary function.  The arguments which were used were the arguments used on the other side of the Border against a person of a particular religious persuasion.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeraldLEstrange" hpid="Mr. L'Estrange Mr. L'Estrange">
      <NameTxt>Mr. L'Estrange</NameTxt>
      <P>Like Deputy Booth used against Deputy Dockrell.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>We are talking about nurses and the appointment of the president.  An important feature of this organisation is that a very important part of its functions relate to nurses who have to be trained as midwives, The president of that committee is the person who is nominated by the Minister to be a member of the Board and, <i>ipso facto</i>, by virtue of the nomination, becomes chairman of <Col N="970" /> the Midwives Committee.  That has worked very satisfactorily and I am asking the Seanad to support me and to say that the same principle should apply to the appointment of president of this Board.</P>
      <P>I am fully convinced after what I heard about the arguments used during the 1956 election that if we want to be quite certain that a worthy person will be appointed president, he should be nominated by the Minister who will then have to come to Dáil Éireann to justify his nomination, if it should be criticised on the grounds that the person nominated is unworthy.  For that reason, I hope Senator Quinlan's amendment will be rejected.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Professor Hayes Professor Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Professor Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>I take this amendment as I find it.  The provision in the Bill is that the Minister shall have power to appoint the president of a board, a majority of which he nominates himself.  The amendment is to delete that power from the Bill and leave the Board itself to appoint its own President.  I do not know who the present president is and I have not followed any proceedings of this Board.  I am taking this amendment on its face value and for what I conceive it means.  I have listened to the Minister and the Minister has convinced me by his attitude that the amendment is sound and one that should be supported.</P>
      <P>The Minister began in his usual pharisaical fashion by saying he is not like other men&mdash;he is not a politician and does not use politics like Senator Quinlan and Senator L'Estrange.  The Minister must have an immensely brazen impudence to think that anybody in this country would believe he is not an ardent politician.  He is the most ardent politician in the country.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>Except yourself.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Professor Hayes Professor Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Professor Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>I am a milder form and I am not completely pharisaical. I do not appeal to Caithlin Ní hUalachain and say: &ldquo;Look at me; I am different from all these other&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>You certainly are; we are good looking.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="971" />
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Professor Hayes Professor Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Professor Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>I did not interrupt the Minister.  The Minister is, in fact, intoxicated with vanity.  He constantly preaches the doctrine of the immense majesty of Ministers, the immense responsibility of Ministers, that Ministers can do no wrong but that other people can do wrong.  He very often resorts to the tactics to which he resorted to-day when he said something dark, murky and dreadful happened some time in 1956 and that if he revealed it, we would all fall down and say: &ldquo;How wise a man is MacEntee, the Minister for Health.&rdquo;</P>
      <P>I cannot for the life of me see why the Minister wants power to appoint the president of this Board except on the basis he has given us that a previous board was so incompetent that it did not appoint the right president. The right president, of course, is the president the Minister thinks is right. In other words, the right president of the Board must be the kind of person who will kow-tow to the Minister.  Like all vain people, the Minister is, of course, capable of being humbugged by people who play up to him.</P>
      <P>The amendment seems quite simple. I do not want to go into the question of the subsidiary bodies with which Senator Quinlan dealt.  I do not think the Minister has anything to do with Papal Encyclicals.  This is a practical matter of appointing a board to do a particular job.  The Board is as likely to know the best president as the Minister. He may be on the Board already and the Board can appoint him without the advice of any Minister.  Quite obviously, on his own showing, the Minister is gathering power to himself because he does not like the way independent people exercise their powers. Ministers rarely like them, and no one dislikes them more than the Minister for Health, in order to satisfy his vanity and his absurd state of mind about the majesty of Ministers.  The amendment should be agreed to and the subsection deleted.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>I just want to&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Professor Hayes Professor Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Professor Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister has no right to make a second speech on this amendment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="972" />
    <Speaker pid="LiamOBuachalla" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>We are in Committee.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Professor Hayes Professor Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Professor Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>We are not in Committee.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LiamOBuachalla" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>We are on Committee Stage.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Professor Hayes Professor Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Professor Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>I apologise.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>I just want to make the House aware of one thing.  Senator Hayes has said that I wish to get this power to appoint the president of the Nurses Board, An Bord Altranais, into my own hands.  That power will not be exercised by me at all I believe, because I hope that the gentleman who is now president of the Board will continue to be president until his term of office expires, which will be three years from now, when some other person will probably have the right to exercise the authority which I now ask the Seanad to give him.  There is no question of vanity or otherwise.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickQuinlan" hpid="Professor Quinlan Professor Quinlan">
      <NameTxt>Professor Quinlan</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister's revelation about 1956 has actually shocked me.  I am shocked that the Minister knows precisely what happened in a committee that is supposed to be secret.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>It is not supposed to be secret.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickQuinlan" hpid="Professor Quinlan Professor Quinlan">
      <NameTxt>Professor Quinlan</NameTxt>
      <P>Why not?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>Because it is not a committee to start off with.  It is a board responsible to the Minister.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickQuinlan" hpid="Professor Quinlan Professor Quinlan">
      <NameTxt>Professor Quinlan</NameTxt>
      <P>How does the Minister know the arguments used at its meetings?  Apparently the Board gave a wrong decision in 1956 but it has now given a right decision.  To me that smacks of the worst type of dictatorship. The Minister used the argument that he is the custodian of the rights of Dáil Éireann, or that he is the only impartial person who could decide it.  I put it to the House that any dictator in any country could claim exactly the same rights for himself. If that dictator were a benevolent dictator, perhaps his decision would be the best possible, but we cannot build democracy on such grounds.  I respect <Col N="973" /> the Minister's intentions.  I am not concerned whether he is or is not the Minister who will appoint the next president.  So far as I am concerned, that is totally immaterial because we are legislating for the future.  I warn the House that there is a great uneasiness throughout the country about the rather brutal centralising tendency his Department is showing, a tendency which he is showing as Minister but which can ultimately be traced back to his Department.  His Department has a far more centralised outlook than any Department of State.  That is an unhealthy position and one which we should combat in this House and outside.</P>
      <P>The Minister has paid tribute to the present eminent holder of this office.  I do not even know his name.  If the committee were capable of giving the right decision a year ago, what is the reason for this Bill being rushed through to prevent any wrong decision being taken in the future?  Whether or not it is wrong is interpreted by the Minister, and really refers to how far the holder of the office complies with the Minister's wishes in all respects. We cannot build a nation on that foundation and consequently I must press this amendment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnODonovan" hpid="Dr. O'Donovan Dr. O'Donovan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. O'Donovan</NameTxt>
      <P>Listening to the debate on Second Reading, it was quite obvious that the rest of this Bill is just a frame into which to put Section 7.  I did not know what was really involved until the Minister spoke at the end of the Second Reading debate and then I understood.  The fact of the matter is that this is a squabble between the Minister and an individual. We all know that, or at least I knew it <Col N="974" /> when the Minister spoke at the end of the Second Reading debate.  I was not aware of it until then.</P>
      <P>It is not nice to see a section put in a Bill in this way because the Minister is afraid&mdash;when I use the word &ldquo;afraid&rdquo;, I am using it colloquially&mdash; or should I say, does not want an individual who might quite easily become president, to be president again.</P>
      <P>Leaving out the other surrounding circumstances, what astonishes me is that the Minister, as everyone knows, is an exceedingly pleasant person socially and personally but when he gets dn his feet in a debate, he seems to blow up in some way.  I cannot describe it. Some people suggest that he becomes bloated but that is not the idea I want to convey.  He blows up&mdash;there is something like a fission movement, an atomic bomb goes off inside him and he feels that his standing or his pride, or whatever it may be, is involved, and he commits himself to this kind of action.</P>
      <P>Really, I agree most heartily with Senator Quinlan.  Like Senator Quinlan, I did not know about these matters at all and Senator Quinlan still does not know about them.  I did not know about them until the last night here. As I heard the Minister reply on Second Reading, then I understood what was involved.  When I cast my mind back, I could bring the whole thing together and the pieces fell into place.  Ministers never do this kind of thing.  The Minister would really add to his stature among us all, if he withdrew this section.</P>
      <P>Question put: &ldquo;That the subsection proposed to be deleted stand.&rdquo;</P>
      <P Just="Center">The Committee divided: Tá, 22; Níl, 11.</P>
      <P Just="Center">Tá</P>
    </Speaker>
    <table pgwide="1">
      <tgroup cols="2">
        <colspec colname="1" colnum="1" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <colspec colname="2" colnum="2" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry rowsep="1">Ahern, Liam.<br />Brady, Seán.<br />Brennan, John J.<br />Carter, Frank.<br />Cole, John C.<br />Colley, Harry.<br />Crowley, Tadhg.<br />Dillon, Gerard B.<br />Dowdall, Jane.<br />Farnan, Robert P.<br />Fitzsimons, Patrick.</entry>
            <entry rowsep="1">Hayes, Seán.<br />Ó Donnabháin, Seán.<br />O'Dwyer, Martin.<br />Ó Grádaigh, Seán.<br />Ó Maoláin, Tomás.<br />O'Reilly, Patrick.<br />ÓSiochfhradha, Pádraig.<br />O'Sullivan, Ted.<br />Ruane, Thomas.<br />Ryan, Eoin.<br />Walsh, Louis.</entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
    <P Just="Center">Níl</P>
    <table pgwide="1">
      <tgroup cols="2">
        <colspec colname="1" colnum="1" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <colspec colname="2" colnum="2" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry rowsep="1">
              <Col N="975" />Carton, Victor.<br />Crowe, Patrick.<br />Hayes, Michael.<br />L'Estrange, Gerald.<br />McGuire, Edward A.<br />Murphy, Dominick F.</entry>
            <entry rowsep="1">
              <Col N="976" />O'Donovan, John.<br />O'Keeffe, James J.<br />O'Sullivan, John L.<br />Quinlan, Patrick M.<br />Stanford, William B.<br /></entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
    <P Just="Center">Tellers: Tá, Senators Carter and Ó Donnabháin; Níl, Senators L'Estrange and Quinlan.</P>
    <P>Question declared carried.</P>
    <P>Section 7 agreed to, Senators L'Estrange and Quinlan dissenting.</P>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>They were recorded as voting against it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickQuinlan" hpid="Professor Quinlan Professor Quinlan">
      <NameTxt>Professor Quinlan</NameTxt>
      <P>Against the amendment.</P>
      <P>Sections 8 and 9 agreed to.</P>
      <P>Schedule and Title agreed to.</P>
      <P>Bill reported without amendment.</P>
      <P>Agreed to take the remaining Stages today.</P>
      <P>Bill received for final consideration and passed.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Industrial Research and Standards Bill," RHead="1961&mdash;Report and Final Stages">
    <Title>Industrial Research and Standards Bill, 1961&mdash;Report and Final Stages.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="LiamOBuachalla" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Before we take up consideration of the Report Stage of this Bill, it would be well if I indicated that there is one amendment&mdash; amendment No. 7&mdash;standing in the name of Senator Quinlan which is out of order, on the ground that the section proposed to be deleted by the amendment was affirmed positively in Committee.  Amendments Nos. 1 and 2 may be taken together.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickQuinlan" hpid="Professor Quinlan Professor Quinlan">
      <NameTxt>Professor Quinlan</NameTxt>
      <P>Before moving these amendments, I should like to express my appreciation to the Minister for the way in which he has met five of the amendments I moved previously.  In so doing, he has given hope to us that perhaps we are not, after all, hitting our heads off a stone wall in trying to do our duty on Committee Stage.  I think the Minister's action in this is the most positive response we in this House have got on a major Bill from a Minister, certainly during my period here.  I thank the Minister very much for his approach to the problem.</P>
      <P>I felt I had something to contribute in these amendments dealing with a research organisation.  The amendments arose very largely out of comparisons between this organisation and other research organisations we know are working smoothly.  That is why I return here and hope the Minister will still be open to conviction on some of the remaining amendments.</P>
      <P>I move amendment No. 1:</P>
      <P>In page 5, to delete section 8 (2), lines 36 to 38, and substitute the following new subsection:&mdash;</P>
      <P>&ldquo;( )  The Board shall consist of&mdash;</P>
      <P>(i)  One member appointed alternately by the Science and Engineering Faculties of each of the following institutions:</P>
      <P>University College, Dublin.</P>
      <P>University College, Cork.</P>
      <P>University College, Galway.</P>
      <P>Trinity College, Dublin.</P>
      <P>(ii)  The President of the Institution of Civil Engineers of Ireland, or his nominee.</P>
      <P>(iii)  The President of the Institute of Chemists or his nominee.</P>
      <P>(iv)  Three members appointed by the Minister.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The amendment proposes that portion of the Board should be nominated by outside bodies actively engaged in research or actively engaged with those taking part in research, like the University Colleges, the Institution of Civil Engineers and the Institute of Chemists.  I think it would be very worth while that power should be given to those bodies to nominate to this Board.  This is necessary.  First of all, the general principle is sound, the principle being that the State should not try to do what other bodies can <Col N="977" /> do as efficiently or better.  I can hold here, without fear of contradiction, that the universities are far more capable of appointing suitable research people to man the Board of this new Research Institute than the Minister's Department can be, because the Minister's Department has not got any section dealing with this type of research work.  It has no active scientists on its staff.  Consequently, I fail to see how any officials in that Department can advise as to how those scientists should be selected from a roster of at least 50 or 60 active scientists in the country.</P>
    <P>I appeal to the Minister to give portion of the nomination over to the University Colleges and to Trinity College, Dublin.  In doing that, I am not asking any favour for the universities. In fact, it involves more work for the faculties concerned.  However, it is a type of public service and a free, gratis, work that we feel we are in a particularly suitable position to achieve.  It is the type of work that would be asked from universities in any other country, namely, taking responsibility for nomination to research organisations that are rather closely linked with the State.</P>
    <P>We have the parallel here, if we need a parallel, in the Agricultural Institute which was set up in January, 1958. That Institute was subjected to greater scrutiny and greater investigation than any other body we set up in the past 15 or 20 years and the results are obvious.  It is a properly constituted and highly autonomous institute which is already doing tremendous work and fully justifying the confidence we all reposed in it.  That body has its Council of 12, plus a chairman.  Of those, you have one nominated by each of the University Colleges, Dublin, Cork and Galway and Trinity College, Dublin.  You also have a nomination from the producer interests concerned, divided into five panels.  The Minister nominates three members as well as nominating the chairman.  That is a reasonable balance on such a board and I cannot see why there should be such a radical departure from that system when we come to deal with the <Col N="978" /> corresponding institute to carry out research problems, both routine and applied, for all industry.</P>
    <P>I would regard it as being far more necessary that we should break with the past.  In the ante-room today, I was speaking to a scientist who had spent some time with this Institute and his verdict was that the reason it had not achieved more was that it was subjected to far too much State control and day-to-day interference.  I am appealing that these four members should be appointed.</P>
    <P>Next, we come to those actively concerned in research work.  They fall into several broad categories.  We have the engineers and the chemists.  The engineers are banded together in the Institute of Civil Engineers of Ireland, although mechanical engineers and others are admitted to membership, and many of them are members of this Institute.  Therefore, this is an ideal body to contribute a number of its members.  It is stated in subsection (3) of Section 8 that the members to be appointed by the Minister should, amongst other things, be representative of persons employed in industry.  If the Minister is looking for persons representative of those employed in industry, then I submit that the body which should make that nomination is the Institute which caters for them. Therefore, we have this Institute and we have the Chemists Institute and I think no other institute would regard itself as being on the same level as those two institutes.</P>
    <P>It would be worthwhile that the position should be tied to the president of the institute or his nominee. That is probably debatable but still the president is the person who is the representative of that broad group of scientists.  Consequently, I appeal to the Minister to give representation to it; otherwise, what is the Minister to do?  Is he to write to the University Colleges asking them to submit the qualifications of members engaged in research?  Likewise, is he to write to other institutions and ask them how their chief officers are working?</P>
    <P>If he is not to take that obvious course, what other course can he take? <Col N="979" /> How can he get to know who is who in these various fields, unless he asks who is working in them?  Otherwise, we will have the unsatisfactory position which we have faced in the appointment of many boards where there does not seem to be any line of reasoning in relation to choosing the members. For that reason, I hope the Minister will come some distance to meet this amendment which I assure him I put down only after very serious consideration and after much experience in research organisations both in this country and elsewhere.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JackLynch" hpid="Minister for Industry and Commerce (Mr. J. Lynch) Jack Lynch">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Industry and Commerce (Mr. J. Lynch)</NameTxt>
      <P>As I said in the course of the Second Reading debate I have a strong objection to nominating boards as if they were conventions. I want to appoint a working board, a board of management, of people who are not only interested in and versed in research but interested in and versed in management of the affairs of industries and of companies.  If my hands were tied in the manner suggested by the Senator, by nominating representatives of Universities, of certain institutions, the civil engineers, the chemists and others, then my choice of a board would be very limited, limited to what he suggests, three members to be appointed by me.  I suggest that the basis on which the board will be appointed, as set out in the section, is sufficiently broad to enable me to select people for membership of this board who will be effective.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Speaking of effectiveness, the Senator mentioned having met a scientist or a chemist in the Lobby a few moments ago, who complained that one of the reasons the former board&mdash; or should I say, the existing board&mdash;was not effective was that there was too much State interference.  The exact contrary was the case.  Apart from the rights of the Minister in the matter of appointing staff, the amount of State interference in the activities of the existing Institute for Industrial Research and Standards was minimal, certainly since I came into office.  I met the committees of the Council at their own request on one occasion, <Col N="980" /> and I visited the Institute on another occasion, again at the request of the Council.  There was no other interference by me or, as far as I know, by any member of my Department.</P>
    <P>The Senator mentioned that the State should not interfere generally. What is the State?  He is the State. Everybody in the country is the State and we, the elected representatives, are the representatives of the people who form the State.  When somebody suggests there is too much State interference in this or that activity, it means the people's direct representatives are interfering.  That is their function and that is what they are elected for.  I have made inquiries myself, and I know from experience gained in my Department, that one of the reasons the outgoing Institute was not effective was that it had not enough of the direct application to industries which it was set up to achieve.</P>
    <P>If, as the Senator suggests, representatives of the University Colleges in Dublin, Cork and Galway, and Trinity College, Dublin, should be appointed, then I am completely in the hands of whoever is going to nominate these representatives.  I would not know how effective they would be or what their particular lines of activity might be and I would not know their idiosyncrasies.  Similarly, in regard to the requirement that I should select the president of the Institute or his nominee I would be tying his hands and the hands of the Oireachtas in the matter of selection.</P>
    <P>If some members of the Dáil or Seanad complain about the activities of a member of the Institute, I can only say: &ldquo;I am afraid I have no function.  That member was nominated by a university college or a certain institute outside my control.&rdquo;  On the contrary of the Board which I propose to appoint, I shall be personally responsible to the Oireachtas for the appointment of each and every one of the members.  As I say, I want a board that will be fully representative of the interests set out in the section as it stands.  It will be sufficiently broadly based, I think.</P>
    <P>My point with regard to appointing <Col N="981" /> a nominee of a certain institution is that that person might not be fully effective as a member of the Institute because his allegiance might be elsewhere. He will owe allegiance to the organisation which he represents and he will probably owe primary allegiance to that organisation.</P>
    <P>I want to repeat what I said originally. Membership of this Board will be decided only after very careful consideration. Again, in reply to a remark made by the Senator, that consideration will not be confined to information available within my Department. I have at my disposal the advice in that respect of the outgoing Council of the Institute.  I have at my disposal the advice of industrialists, of people engaged in research in industry, and even of members of the universities.</P>
    <P>I have no doubt that if I applied to the President of University College, Cork, for comment on the qualifications and suitability of a person on his staff whom I had in mind to appoint to the Board of the Institute, he would give me a helpful and objective appraisal of that man's capabilities and suitability for the Board.</P>
    <P>I do not propose to appoint a convention. I want to appoint a board of management comprised of men and women, or men or women, who will owe allegiance in this matter to the Institute only, who will be selected to serve on the Institute.  For those reasons, I do not propose to accept the amendment.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Professor Hayes Professor Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Professor Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>I accept entirely the Minister's good faith in this matter. He has a very difficult task indeed in selecting an appropriate board to do the work which this Institute is being set up to do.  I am not enamoured of the amendment as drafted.  It has the defects the Minister alleges against it and, as it stands, I think it would not be quite workable.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The Minister perhaps is not sufficiently apprised of the real difficulties in this kind of situation.  He said at the beginning that he would like people who were very good at research applied to industry and good at the same time at management.  There are not very <Col N="982" /> many of those people available in this country or indeed in any country.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JackLynch" hpid="Mr. J. Lynch Mr. J. Lynch">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J. Lynch</NameTxt>
      <P>We could have a balance of them.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Professor Hayes Professor Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Professor Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>Perhaps, but you might get a good manager who was not good at research, or a good research man who was not good at management. To get a person who comprehends the difficulties of research and, at the same time, is good at management, is a matter of very great difficulty.</P>
      <P>The Minister also said&mdash;and I know he said it in perfectly good faith; we are all at one on this point&mdash;that we want industry to progress and science to be applied and get the best possible results.  The real difficulty is: what kind of board would be best to achieve that?  I think the Minister suggested &mdash;I hope I am not misrepresenting him&mdash;that one of the causes of the comparative failure of another board was that it had not sufficient direct application to industry.  One of the most difficult things in the world is to get people to do research which will be applicable to industry, that is, to get people to go into laboratories and find out something which can be applied to a factory making boots, or petrol for the matter of that.</P>
      <P>I suggested on the last occasion when we were discussing this amendment in Committee that the Board would be very much improved if a person were appointed even if he did have idiosyncrasies.  The Minister mentioned the word &ldquo;idiosyncrasies&rdquo; and seems to think that was a bad thing.  Unfortunately, in university circles, a great many people have idiosyncrasies and some of the best research people in the world have perhaps more idiosyncrasies than others.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I can see this matter entirely from the outside and I think the Board would be improved, and the Minister's object nearly achieved, if he were to appoint to the Board one person highly skilled in pure unapplied research.  He would want only one such person on the Board.  The Board might find him to some degree difficult but I think his difficulty, his knowledge, and his experience, would be a very good leaven, so to speak, in the general make-up of <Col N="983" /> the Board.  There is a great problem in harnessing pure science to industry to be availed of in a practical way in the development of industry.</P>
    <P>Having heard the Minister, trying to understand his mind, and giving him, as I say, complete credit for being entirely <i>bona fide</i> in this matter, I doubt that his attitude of mind will get the best board.  If I were Minister&mdash;and I am afraid this is where I differ from Senator Quinlan&mdash;I would not accept this amendment.  I have the same objection as the Minister to a board made up of people who did not necessarily come together in a particular way, but I think the Minister's power is too restricted.  If he were to go to a university college or a research institute, find someone there and put him on the Board&mdash;or her&mdash;the Board would probably be very much improved, and what the Minister has in mind, and what we all have in mind, would be nearer to achievement than the application of what I conceive to be the Minister's present state of mind to getting this Board to work properly.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JackLynch" hpid="Mr. J. Lynch Mr. J. Lynch">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J. Lynch</NameTxt>
      <P>The Board will not be a paid research staff.  It will have a staff.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Professor Hayes Professor Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Professor Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>The Board will have to cope with a research staff and in order to cope with a research staff, the Board should have someone on it who understands research, not only from the point of view of its application to industry but to pure research.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PadraigOSiochfhradha" hpid="Pádraig Ó Siochfhradha Pádraig Ó Siochfhradha">
      <NameTxt>Pádraig Ó Siochfhradha</NameTxt>
      <P>Ní doigh liom gur féidir liom taobhú leis an leasú a mhol an Seanadóir Ó Cuinnleáin. Tá sé ag iarraidh an iomarca nuair a éilíann sé go nainmeódh na hOllscoileanna agus na hInstitiúid baill an Bhoird agus go bhfágfaí ainmniuchán triúr faoin Aire.  Is locht é sin ar an leasú atá dhá iarraidh aige. Aontaím leis an Aire nár cheart dó glacadh leis.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeraldLEstrange" hpid="Mr. L'Estrange Mr. L'Estrange">
      <NameTxt>Mr. L'Estrange</NameTxt>
      <P>According to what the Minister said, one would think that the Agricultural Institute would be a complete failure.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="984" />
    <Speaker pid="JackLynch" hpid="Mr. J. Lynch Mr. J. Lynch">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J. Lynch</NameTxt>
      <P>I made no reference whatsoever to the Agricultural Institute.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeraldLEstrange" hpid="Mr. L'Estrange Mr. L'Estrange">
      <NameTxt>Mr. L'Estrange</NameTxt>
      <P>There the different bodies nominated the different people to the board.  Their hands do not seem to be tied.  The Minister for Agriculture is in control of it and I doubt if his hands are tied.  The Board seems to be functioning properly and it is agreed by all that it is a success.  Its personnel are dedicated to their task; they owe allegiance to nobody but the Institute.  The Minister claims that if they were nominated by particular bodies they would owe allegiance to the bodies nominating them. Deputy de Valera, as he was then, piloted that Bill through the Dáil and Seanad.  Whether in his wisdom or otherwise, he made the arrangement that the different bodies would nominate the different people.  To whom do they owe their allegiance? They are men dedicated to their work.  I do not think the hands of the Minister for Agriculture are tied in any way.  It has proved a success. The same applies to the Milk Board set up recently.  The different bodies nominate their own particular members to it.  We set up a marketing research board recently and we had the same procedure.  The Minister is adopting a different procedure in this Bill.  I doubt if his argument holds water.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanODonovan" hpid="Seán Ó Donnabháin Seán Ó Donnabháin">
      <NameTxt>Seán Ó Donnabháin</NameTxt>
      <P>There is actually no comparison between the body which it is suggested to set up and An Foras Talúntais.  I should like to remind Senator Quinlan that when the Bill in connection with An Foras Talúntais was going through this House, he proposed 30 amendments. At the time the Taoiseach, now An tUachtarán, conducted the Bill through this House and we ultimately finished it by changing one word in that Bill.  The Senator succeeded by agreement in changing one word, if my recollection is correct.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>One would expect Senator Quinlan to rave completely about the fact that the Minister now sitting here proposes to nominate nine members to <Col N="985" /> this Board himself.  We had a division in this House on a recent Bill because the Minister then here suggested that he should nominate the chairman of a body consisting of twenty members.  Let us be factual. If we could quote Papal Encyclicals in regard to what the Minister for Health was doing, what should we quote in regard to what the Minister for Industry and Commerce proposes to do in nominating nine members of this Board?  The Board is to consist of not more than nine members, of whom one shall be the chairman and the others ordinary members.</P>
    <P>The amendment proposed by Senator Quinlan is ridiculous.  Candidly, I must be rather stupid if I cannot interpret the matter correctly.  If my interpretation is correct, the thing would actually be inoperable.  It would, I think, negative the whole effect of the Bill. Subsequent clauses in the same section would have to be altered.  If this amendment were accepted, one might as well withdraw the Bill.  He suggests in the amendment that the Board shall alternately consist of one member appointed by the Science and Engineering faculties of each of the following Institutions: University College, Dublin; University College, Cork; University College, Galway, and Trinity College, Dublin.  The Science faculty at University College, Cork, appoints a man for three years and subsequently for the next three years the Engineering faculty would do likewise.  That is my interpretation of the word &ldquo;alternately&rdquo;.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickQuinlan" hpid="Professor Quinlan Professor Quinlan">
      <NameTxt>Professor Quinlan</NameTxt>
      <P>That is correct.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanODonovan" hpid="Seán Ó Donnabháin Seán Ó Donnabháin">
      <NameTxt>Seán Ó Donnabháin</NameTxt>
      <P>If that is correct, the thing is idiotic because the subsequent subsections of Section 8 would be negatived altogether.  You might have four institutions.  I call them three university colleges and one university.  One would appoint a member from a faculty for three years. Others might appoint from different faculties.  I think the Minister would be in difficulties altogether if he tried to keep track of this.  It would not work. If a Senator were seriously to put down an amendment such as this, he should follow it up with the consequential <Col N="986" /> amendments in the other subsections of the section.  The system he suggests would negative the whole thing.  We might just as well withdraw the Bill.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanBrady2" hpid="Mr. Brady Mr. Brady">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Brady</NameTxt>
      <P>He was told that by Senator Hayes.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickQuinlan" hpid="Professor Quinlan Professor Quinlan">
      <NameTxt>Professor Quinlan</NameTxt>
      <P>In reply to my very good friend, Senator Ó Donnabháin, I must go on record as saying that I am proud of the part I played in the debate on the Agricultural Institute Bill. Again, it was a type of research work and organisation that I knew something about and have studied considerably.  Also I am proud of the replies made by the then Taoiseach, now our distinguished President, on that occasion.  Many of the amendments were put down to elicit information and I got that information to the satisfaction of the House and everybody else as Senator Ó Donnabháin should know.  Consequently, I am not going to be intimidated by Senator Ó Donnabháin or anybody else in doing my duty as I see it in moving an amendment where I think it is necessary.</P>
      <P>Everything the Minister said could have been directed completely against the Agricultural Institute or against any other board whether it is An Bórd Bainne, An Bórd Altranais or any of the others.  I think the Minister's reasoning is all wrong.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JackLynch" hpid="Mr. J. Lynch Mr. J. Lynch">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J. Lynch</NameTxt>
      <P>Would the Senator have a representative of every type of industry in order to bring his argument to a logical conclusion?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickQuinlan" hpid="Professor Quinlan Professor Quinlan">
      <NameTxt>Professor Quinlan</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister could include those, if he wished.  I very much appreciate the good faith of the Minister in this; I appreciate his approach to it.  I know he will appoint the best Board possible but we are dealing with legislation as of to-day.  We are dealing with the present Minister, with future Ministers and future situations.  That is what legislation is for.  As I say, hell is paved with good intentions and so are many Acts.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>We have got to be on our guard against this modern fallacy that we get <Col N="987" /> from every Minister who comes here acting in good faith.  One might sum it all up in the 18th Century quotation that the King can do no wrong, because in our situation&mdash;this is a Republic and not a monarchy&mdash;the Minister can do no wrong.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JackLynch" hpid="Mr. J. Lynch Mr. J. Lynch">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J. Lynch</NameTxt>
      <P>If he does, he will be told off very quickly.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickQuinlan" hpid="Professor Quinlan Professor Quinlan">
      <NameTxt>Professor Quinlan</NameTxt>
      <P>That is a totally unrealistic concept of democracy. Democracy means more than merely having a choice of team every five years.  It means that some outside groups should play a part in the development and work of the five years while the team was there.  I have made my points clearly.  I cannot accept the answer because it is so much at variance with what we know is happening in relation to other boards and what is the correct thing to have.</P>
      <P>Also, of course, the President of the Institution of Civil Engineers could be a crank and therefore could be ineligible to be a president of the board of any institution.  That is ascribing, again, a power to a Minister that he can say a person is a crank while the whole profession which honours that person and elects him as President for the year does not know he is a crank. To my mind, that seems a very wrong thing.</P>
      <P>In appreciation of the Minister's attitude in meeting some of the amendments I put down the last day, thereby showing I am not wasting my time in moving amendments, despite what Senator Ó Donnabháin may appear to think, I have pleasure in withdrawing this amendment.  I suggest to Senator Ó Donnabháin that he might put down an amendment or two and then perhaps we might function more properly.</P>
      <P>Amendment, by leave, withdrawn.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Amendments Nos. 3, 4, 5 and 6, might go together.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Professor Hayes Professor Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Professor Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>We agree with the Ministerial amendments.</P>
      <P>Amendment No. 2 not moved.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="988" /> Government amendment No. 3:</P>
    <P>In page 6, line 2 to delete &ldquo;third&rdquo; and substitute &ldquo;fifth&rdquo;; and in line 4, to delete &ldquo;triennially&rdquo; and substitute &ldquo;quinquennially&rdquo;.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JackLynch" hpid="Mr. J. Lynch Mr. J. Lynch">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J. Lynch</NameTxt>
      <P>In effect, this amendment is on all fours with the amendment submitted by Senator Quinlan but it was submitted in this form before his amendments on the Report Stage were submitted.  That is why they both appear in the same form.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickQuinlan" hpid="Professor Quinlan Professor Quinlan">
      <NameTxt>Professor Quinlan</NameTxt>
      <P>I wish to thank the Minister.  I think it is a very wide extension that these boards will be appointed every five years rather than every three years.  The longer the period in a research organisation, the more continuity we may expect in work.</P>
      <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
      <P>Amendment No. 4 not moved.</P>
      <P>Government amendment No. 5:</P>
      <P>In page 6, line 6, to delete &ldquo;triennial&rdquo; and substitute &ldquo;quinquennial.&rdquo;</P>
      <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
      <P>Amendments Nos. 6 and 7 not moved.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickQuinlan" hpid="Professor Quinlan Professor Quinlan">
      <NameTxt>Professor Quinlan</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 8:</P>
      <P>In pages 6, to delete section 13 (1), lines 30 to 33, inclusive.</P>
      <P>This amendment is an attempt to ameliorate the ban placed on members of the Oireachtas in relation to serving on public boards.  The amelioration suggested here is that subsection (1) be deleted, so that, if a member of the Board of the Institute for Industrial Research and Standards becomes a member of the Dáil or Seanad, he may continue his membership of the Board until the Board comes up for re-election.  Then, under subsection (2), he would be ineligible for reappointment.  That is just a half-way measure to what I hope will later be the full measure that will rule out such restrictive clauses altogether.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>It is right and proper for members of the Oireachtas to sit on boards of the universities, to be members of the Senate of the University, to sit on the <Col N="989" /> Agricultural Institute Board, to be members of the Institute for Advanced Studies.  If it is right and proper for them to be on those boards, then I do not see why they should be anathema on boards like this.  I believe we are growing up and if we are growing up, then it behoves us all to remove some of the stigma that attaches to the word &ldquo;politican&rdquo; which is used to denigrate those who make their contribution to public service.</P>
    <P>I believe the time has come for the Government to review this and at least let us have consistency.  Either one is qualified and acceptable to sit on all boards or on none.  Surely the first hallmark of very good legislation must be consistency and continuity? Consequently, I am appealing that the Minister take at least one step in this direction by deleting subsection (1).</P>
    <Speaker pid="JackLynch" hpid="Mr. J. Lynch Mr. J. Lynch">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J. Lynch</NameTxt>
      <P>At the outset, I want to say I am sure I share with everybody in this House the high regard that must be held for people in public life.  It is a calling, a dedication.  I would always defend public persons, representative persons, from attack, no matter from what quarter.  I would even hold a brief for Senator L'Estrange if he were attacked, because he is a man in public life.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Professor Hayes Professor Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Professor Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>I hope the Minister will open the brief and make the appropriate speech on the brief.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JackLynch" hpid="Mr. J. Lynch Mr. J. Lynch">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J. Lynch</NameTxt>
      <P>In relation to this Board, I want to say that I think it is wrong that a person who is a member of the House should also be a member of a board like this.  I think each House of the Oireachtas should be entitled, on any occasion, to call to account the membership of a board like this, to call to account their activities and to be able to deal with these activities objectively.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>A member of a board who is also a member of the House would find himself to a certain extent in perhaps an embarrassing position by having to defend the activities of a board, if it were called to account.  On Committee Stage, I accepted an amendment which required a member of the <Col N="990" /> Board to resign if nominated for election to either House of the Oireachtas. I think that is as far as I ought to go.</P>
    <P>The Senator mentioned a number of other organisations established under statute of which, he said, membership was permitted while a person was still a member of the Oireachtas.  He mentioned An Foras Talúntais.  As far as I am concerned, and the boards for which I am responsible, it has been consistent practice that membership of the Oireachtas is not compatible with membership of these boards.  It is not because it has been the consistent practice that I stand on the section as it now is but because I agree with that practice.  I agree with it for reasons that are obvious to the House and for reasons that are shared by the vast majority of members of both Houses.  I do not think I need elaborate on it.  I do not propose to accept the amendment.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickQuinlan" hpid="Professor Quinlan Professor Quinlan">
      <NameTxt>Professor Quinlan</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister's reasons, as given, appear quite valid in this context.  Then when you take the sister organisation, the Agricultural Institute, they just do not hold water.  There is no such section in the Agricultural Institute measure.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JackLynch" hpid="Mr. J. Lynch Mr. J. Lynch">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J. Lynch</NameTxt>
      <P>There is no member of the Oireachtas in it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickQuinlan" hpid="Professor Quinlan Professor Quinlan">
      <NameTxt>Professor Quinlan</NameTxt>
      <P>The Institute for Advanced Studies might be quoted. I have been a member of that Institute for 10 years and it is in no way incompatible with my duties here.  The Minister's concern is for members who might be embarrassed. If we take that far enough we might say that the same embarrassment might be felt here by members of a political Party when it is being attacked or, actually, in the case of universities, of which I have the honour to be one of the representatives, that we should hang our heads when a university is being attacked here. I think we have shown we do no such thing; in fact, we have been instrumental in showing how wrong some of those attacks have been.  I have just put this down for consideration. I do not expect to gain the point <Col N="991" /> today or tomorrow but we will keep at it and any time such a clause appears in a Bill, we will keep plugging away and some time we will succeed.</P>
      <P>Amendment, by leave, withdrawn.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathoirleach An Leas-Chathoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Amendments Nos. 9, 10, 11 and 12 go together.  If amendment No. 9 is negatived, the others may not be moved.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickQuinlan" hpid="Professor Quinlan Professor Quinlan">
      <NameTxt>Professor Quinlan</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 9:&mdash;</P>
      <P>In page 7, lines 4 and 5, to delete &ldquo;stand seconded from such employment&rdquo; and substitute &ldquo;obtain the necessary leave of absence.&rdquo;</P>
      <P>This is a variation on some other Bills which require that such a person should resign.  Of course the whole thing is nebulous.  What officer of one of those boards, of the high standing required for service on such a board, could possibly resign from the board and accept the allowance given in the Dáil or the Seanad and condemn his family to live on that?  I hope that the day is not too far distant when the professional classes, who, you might say, are excluded from either House of the Oireachtas, will at least get a chance to serve their country in this respect.  The only professions that can be represented here at the moment are the lawyers, and to a minor extent the teachers who can appoint substitutes and get the difference between their salary and the substitute's salary. Another group are the medical officers of health, but the vast majority of our professions cannot serve.  Take, for example, the engineers of whom 95 per cent. are in public employment with local authorities or with various boards.  These are precluded from ever becoming members of the Dáil or Seanad.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I put down this amendment to draw attention to this type of political apartheid which is being practised here. The question is asked why do graduates of the universities not play a greater part in the national life and the answer is they cannot afford to do <Col N="992" /> so, unless they are prepared to reduce their families to penury.  That was never the intention and it should not be expected of anybody.  We should begin to progress like they have begun to progress in Holland where professional classes are attracted to play a part, at least in proportion to their numbers, in the affairs of their country. In Holland, any professional person, even a civil servant, can obtain leave of absence to become a member of Parliament.  That shows how they value their freedom, when it extends as far as the Civil Service itself.  Not only that, but if there is a differential in salary, between what the officer is getting at the time he gets leave of absence and the allowance in the Dutch Parliament, the body concerned, the State or local authority, will make up the difference so that his family does not suffer from the fact that he goes into public service.</P>
    <P>Again, I must quote the Agricultural Institute because it is the companion body to this Institute; agriculture and industry are the twin partners in our development.  The Agricultural Institute, on the one hand, and the Industrial Institute, on the other, should be twin partners and what is proper for one should surely be proper for the other.  In the vast majority of cases, I think, in the Agricultural Institute, many of those employed are not debarred by statute from membership of either House.  Can the Minister justify the application of one rule to the agricultural officers serving in the Agricultural Institute and another to the officers in the Institute of Industrial Research and Standards?</P>
    <Speaker pid="JackLynch" hpid="Mr. J. Lynch Mr. J. Lynch">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J. Lynch</NameTxt>
      <P>I am not certain that officers of the Agricultural Institute can become members of either House of the Oireachtas&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickQuinlan" hpid="Professor Quinlan Professor Quinlan">
      <NameTxt>Professor Quinlan</NameTxt>
      <P>Oh, yes.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JackLynch" hpid="Mr. J. Lynch Mr. J. Lynch">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J. Lynch</NameTxt>
      <P>&mdash;and still hold their jobs.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickQuinlan" hpid="Professor Quinlan Professor Quinlan">
      <NameTxt>Professor Quinlan</NameTxt>
      <P>With the permission of the Board.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JackLynch" hpid="Mr. J. Lynch Mr. J. Lynch">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J. Lynch</NameTxt>
      <P>They will hardly draw their salaries at the same time.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="993" />
    <Speaker pid="PatrickQuinlan" hpid="Professor Quinlan Professor Quinlan">
      <NameTxt>Professor Quinlan</NameTxt>
      <P>The whole thing depends on the Board.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JackLynch" hpid="Mr. J. Lynch Mr. J. Lynch">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J. Lynch</NameTxt>
      <P>I think it is undesirable where a person is appointed, whether as a technical, administrative or clerical assistant, that he should be entitled to absent himself from the duties for which he is primarily paid out of State funds, and come along and be paid again out of State funds.  Some of his activities will have to suffer.  If he cannot attend his job in the Institute, somebody will have to be appointed in his place.  That person appointed in his place does the work&mdash;it might be essential work of a research nature of practical help to industries&mdash;and after a short time he will become expert.  He will then find himself faced with the return of the person he has replaced and with the prospect of being out of a job.  That would be a difficult and undesirable situation which should be avoided.</P>
      <P>Any officer or servant of the Board, having been elected to either House of the Oireachtas, is seconded from his employment but that does not mean his employment is terminated. Not only is it not terminated, and not only can he return to work if and when he resigns or loses his seat in either House, but he can also preserve his superannuation entitlement over the period by paying the necessary contribution.  I think that is not ungenerous in the circumstances. He will always have his job to return to and will have preserved his superannuation entitlement.  The country will know that no matter in what sphere he serves, whether as a member of the Institute or a member of either House of the Oireachtas, he will be able to devote sufficient time to the one or the other.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I might also instance a person who might be in the Dail at the moment and also be holding down a job in the Institute.  He might be a chemist doing some special work and at present he would be required to attend to the Dail from 2 p.m. until 11 p.m. for two days of the week, and from 10.30 a.m. until 5 p.m. on the third day, which is a normal working day.  It is unreasonable to <Col N="994" /> assume he can attend to the two jobs at the same time, attend to his duties in the Institute and also his duties in the Oireachtas.  Duties in the Oireachtas are not limited to attendance at Meetings of the Houses. There are committee meetings and other activities which have to be attended to.  Therefore, it is not unreasonable to require that a man who finds that his bent is for politics should have leave to stand seconded from his original job, with the right to go back to it, if and when he ceases to be a member of the Oireachtas, and, at the same time, preserve his superannuation rights.  I do not think this country is well enough off to pay a salary to a person for not doing a job.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickQuinlan" hpid="Professor Quinlan Professor Quinlan">
      <NameTxt>Professor Quinlan</NameTxt>
      <P>That is not suggested.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JackLynch" hpid="Mr. J. Lynch Mr. J. Lynch">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J. Lynch</NameTxt>
      <P>The amendment does not take it into account.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickQuinlan" hpid="Professor Quinlan Professor Quinlan">
      <NameTxt>Professor Quinlan</NameTxt>
      <P>The next amendment does.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JackLynch" hpid="Mr. J. Lynch Mr. J. Lynch">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J. Lynch</NameTxt>
      <P>However, the question would arise in any case that the person would have to be replaced in his original job.  If he lost his seat, I take it he would have the right to go back and, therefore, he would displace whoever had replaced him in the interim.  That is undesirable and should be avoided.  I do not propose to accept the amendment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickQuinlan" hpid="Professor Quinlan Professor Quinlan">
      <NameTxt>Professor Quinlan</NameTxt>
      <P>The point made by the Minister was that the main objection would be that if the person went back to his original job, he would displace someone else.  Surely that applies anywhere people are seconded. Surely there are provisions under which a person can be given leave of absence, and surely leave of absence could be given, taking this amendment in conjunction with amendment No. 10 which provides: &ldquo;he shall be paid by the Board such salary or wages as the Board with the consent of the Minister for Finance, may decide.&rdquo;  I did not at any time envisage that people would be paid for work they did not do.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The Seanad meets a few times a <Col N="995" /> year.  Perhaps we have not more than 30 sessions, and if we take the average attendance, it is not good.  In fact, it cannot be classed as being more than a part-time job.  Consequently, the amendment would relate more to membership of the Seanad than to membership of the Dáil.</P>
    <P>The Minister has indicated his mind on the matter and has gone further in this Bill than most other Bills in that he has made provision for secondment. At least we can hope that line will be followed in future Bills, and we can hope that we will advance to the ideal situation proposed in my amendment. Even here, it can be said that we get leave of absence from our employment. I do not see why the professional group should be treated differently.  I withdraw the amendment.</P>
    <P>Amendment, by leave, withdrawn.</P>
    <P>Amendments Nos. 10 to 13, inclusive, not moved.</P>
    <P>Government amendment No. 14:</P>
    <P>In page 14, to delete lines 22 and 23.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JackLynch" hpid="Mr. J. Lynch Mr. J. Lynch">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J. Lynch</NameTxt>
      <P>This amendment is designed to meet the point raised on Committee Stage that the Institute should not be required to hold public examinations for posts calling for specialised qualifications.  The point was made that almost any post in the Institute, apart from clerical posts, would call for specialised qualifications not commonly held.  I propose to accept the point which was made and not to include in the posts in respect of which the Institute is required to hold public competitions posts which in fact require specialised qualifications not normally held.  I think that fully meets the point which was made.</P>
      <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
      <P>Amendments Nos. 15 and 16 not moved.</P>
      <P>Government amendment No. 17:</P>
      <P>In page 14, line 34, to delete &ldquo;any office&rdquo; and substitute &ldquo;not more than two offices&rdquo;; and in line 35, to delete &ldquo;an office&rdquo; and substitute &ldquo;offices&rdquo;.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="996" />
    <Speaker pid="JackLynch" hpid="Mr. J. Lynch Mr. J. Lynch">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J. Lynch</NameTxt>
      <P>This amendment goes almost as far as Senator Quinlan wants me to go.  Originally in the Bill, the Minister was empowered to designate certain posts in respect of which the Institute would have to consult him before the appointments were made. The purpose of that consultation was to ensure that the terms of these appointments would not get out of line with similar posts in other spheres of activity.</P>
      <P>I still hold it is essential that the Minister should have that power and I hope that the amendment limiting the scope of that power of two designated appointments will meet the case.  I can only repeat that it is likely that these two designated posts will be the senior posts on one side or the other, or on one side or both sides.  When I refer to one side or the other, I refer to the administrative, technical or scientific side.  I think it is necessary that the Minister should have power to regulate the conditions of employment and the salaries to be given.  It is a power that will be used liberally and with full regard to the necessity for attracting the best type of person to each of the designated posts.  I think the House will agree that power is necessary, and that I have gone quite a distance in limiting the power I propose to take.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickQuinlan" hpid="Professor Quinlan Professor Quinlan">
      <NameTxt>Professor Quinlan</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister has met most of the objections raised and the power he now asks is similar to the power conferred on the Agricultural Institute.  I should like an interpretation of paragraph (b) of subsection (4) which says:</P>
      <P>a person shall not be appointed to an office so designated save with the consent of the Minister,</P>
      <P>I take it that implies that the, appointment is with the Minister's consent. I take it that the appointment of a person rests completely with the Board of the Institute and that this subsection merely means that the Minister shall consent to the appointment being made?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JackLynch" hpid="Mr. J. Lynch Mr. J. Lynch">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J. Lynch</NameTxt>
      <P>The purpose of the paragraph is to keep an eye on the remuneration and not on the person to be appointed.  I said on Second Stage that a man will be selected and I <Col N="997" /> will have no knowledge of his capabilities or how he would fit the requirements of the Institute.  It is only natural and perfectly reasonable that we should leave the personality to the Institute, my function being limited to ensuring that the remuneration and conditions of employment will not get out of line.</P>
      <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickQuinlan" hpid="Professor Quinlan Professor Quinlan">
      <NameTxt>Professor Quinlan</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 18.</P>
      <P>In page 15, line 45, to delete &ldquo;industrial&rdquo; and substitute &ldquo;applied&rdquo;.</P>
      <P>We discussed this matter on Committee Stage and the Minister for Transport and Power undertook to look into the terminology.  I think that has been done.  I would prefer the word &ldquo;applied&rdquo;, but I think the general feeling was that we should leave the term as wide as possible.  I thought it was wider than the word &ldquo;industrial&rdquo;, but the Minister seems to hold that the word &ldquo;industrial&rdquo; is the widest term. Perhaps the Minister would enlighten the House?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JackLynch" hpid="Mr. J. Lynch Mr. J. Lynch">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J. Lynch</NameTxt>
      <P>I still think that the word &ldquo;industrial&rdquo; is the widest.  It is the term that conforms to the Long Title in the Bill.  There could be research in many forms of activity&mdash; agricultural, medical, social, political and so on.  The word &ldquo;research&rdquo; could apply to any one of these.  There could be applied, pure or basic research.  I must insist on the retention of the term &ldquo;industrial research&rdquo; in this section.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickQuinlan" hpid="Professor Quinlan Professor Quinlan">
      <NameTxt>Professor Quinlan</NameTxt>
      <P>The difficulty that arises there is to decide what is industrial research.  In other words, there is the question of the giving of a research grant to a post-graduate student to carry on his training in some branch of chemistry, with the ultimate expectation that he will be a properly trained person to tackle the more specific problems of industrial research later on.  I want to ensure that such grants can be given under this.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JackLynch" hpid="Mr. J. Lynch Mr. J. Lynch">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J. Lynch</NameTxt>
      <P>That will be a matter for the Board.  The Board will make up their own minds.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="998" />
    <Speaker pid="PatrickQuinlan" hpid="Professor Quinlan Professor Quinlan">
      <NameTxt>Professor Quinlan</NameTxt>
      <P>I am anxious to ensure that the term &ldquo;industrial&rdquo; is interpreted as liberally as the Minister interprets it for us.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JackLynch" hpid="Mr. J. Lynch Mr. J. Lynch">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J. Lynch</NameTxt>
      <P>I am sure it will.</P>
      <P>Amendment, by leave, withdrawn.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickQuinlan" hpid="Professor Quinlan Professor Quinlan">
      <NameTxt>Professor Quinlan</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 19:&mdash;</P>
      <P>In page 15, to delete all words from and including &ldquo;undertaking&rdquo; in line 47 to the end of the subsection and substitute &ldquo;engaged in research.&rdquo;</P>
      <P>This amendment was designed more or less to cover the same field.  I think we can take the Minister's assurance.</P>
      <P>Amendment, by leave, withdrawn.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickQuinlan" hpid="Professor Quinlan Professor Quinlan">
      <NameTxt>Professor Quinlan</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 20:&mdash;</P>
      <P>In page 16, between lines 42 and 43, to add a new subsection to section 42 as follows :&mdash;</P>
      <P>&ldquo;( )  A comprehensive summary report of the work of the Institute shall be prepared every five years.&rdquo;</P>
      <P>I think it very wise to include this provision in any Bill dealing with the setting up of a new body where at least we have the customary yearly reports laid on the Table of the Oireachtas.  I am asking that a comprehensive summary report of the work of the Institute shall be prepared every five years, rather than that the members of the Oireachtas should be faced with five separate reports.  We should have a brief summary report covering the main research carried out over that five-year period.  There is such a provision in regard to the Institute for Advanced Studies and, I think, there is a corresponding provision in regard to the Agricultural Institute.</P>
      <P>It would not take very much effort to prepare such a report by a Board having a staff available to it.  They could take the results of the five years and condense them into single report size.  That would give to the members here a satisfactory progress report as to how the Institute was faring.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JackLynch" hpid="Mr. J. Lynch Mr. J. Lynch">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J. Lynch</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not think it would be necessary and certainly it <Col N="999" /> would make for duplication.  As in the case of every State board, the Board is required to submit its report annually.  I do not think it would impose any undue strain on anybody, if they wanted to get a two or three years view of the activities of a board, to consult the yearly reports, which, as in the case of other boards, follow a certain format.  I do not think it is unreasonable to assume that activities started in one year which were not quite completed will be adverted to in the report of subsequent years.  There will be that continuity of account in regard to the activities of the board.</P>
      <P>Another point I should like to make is that these reports are fairly costly and I think that in the interests of economy, we should not require boards like this to publish accounts of their activities already available not only in another form, but in another very convenient form.  I have received complaints from time to time in respect of the annual reports of boards that they are not published within a sufficiently short time after the end of the year with which they deal.  There are many reasons for that.  First of all, there is the fact that the Board itself has other activities to look after.  Also, the printing facilities in this country are not unlimited and neither are the financial facilities.  Therefore, under all headings, I think it unnecessary that we should impose this extra burden on the Board itself, on the resources of the State printing office or on the Exchequer.  I do not think the amendment is necessary.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickQuinlan" hpid="Professor Quinlan Professor Quinlan">
      <NameTxt>Professor Quinlan</NameTxt>
      <P>This burden is imposed on the Institute for Advanced Studies and to very good effect.  A report from a research institute is not like a report from C.I.E. with tabulated figures and so on.  Research, of necessity, flows from one to the other.  Most of the report would be taken up with describing many beginnings and trying to forecast endings.  It would be impossible for members of the House to take five reports together and make a reasonable assessment of the progress made in those five years.  It is a professional <Col N="1000" /> job, calling for somebody who understands research.  If the Minister is concerned, as he is, with undue costs, printing and so on, it would be far better if he settled for a consolidated report every three years than to give what some research men call promissory notes to meet a shorter period.</P>
      <P>Amendment, by leave, withdrawn.</P>
      <P>Government amendment No. 21.</P>
      <P>In page 17, to delete section 45, lines 43 to 45, and substitute the following new section:&mdash;</P>
      <P>&ldquo;45.  The Institute may from time to time publish scientific and technical information in its own name, including, with the consent of the Minister, codes of recommended practice.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Amendments Nos. 21 and 22 go together.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JackLynch" hpid="Mr. J. Lynch Mr. J. Lynch">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J. Lynch</NameTxt>
      <P>This amendment is designed to meet a point made by Senator Quinlan on Committee Stage. Section 45 says:&mdash;</P>
      <P>The Institute may from time to time with the approval of the Minister publish scientific and technical information including codes of recommended practice in the name of the Institute.</P>
      <P>Senator Quinlan suggested that the words &ldquo;with the aproval of the Minister&rdquo; should be deleted.  My amendment proposes to meet his point but only insofar as it affects the publication of scientific and technical information. In other words, any scientific and technical information the Institute wishes to publish, it can publish, without any recourse to the Minister, in its own name and under its own authority.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>A different consideration arises when we come to the publication of data on codes of recommended practice.  In that matter, the Minister must have some rights to ensure that the data it does publish are in no way harmful. I use the word &ldquo;harmful&rdquo; in a very liberal way.  If I take an example, it may, perhaps, illustrate what I mean.  If, in the course of one of these publications, the Institute suggests a certain component part, which <Col N="1001" /> is available inside and outside the country, should be used in the manufacture of a certain commodity and if it recommended that the component should be the one procurable in Britain and not in Ireland, I do not think it would be desirable that an Institute in respect of which I have over-all authority should be permitted to publish such a code of practice without my specific knowledge and consent.</P>
    <P>Similiarly, in publishing codes of practice, it might invade the field of labour relations.  For example, in regard to demarcation between one employment and another or one skill and another, it might make proposals in its published codes of practice which would be matters peculiarly within the province of the Minister himself, and perhaps, more peculiarly still, matters for settlement between labour interests.  I do not think it should be given <i>carte blanche</i> to publish matters such as these under the heading of Codes of Practice.  That might well be dangerous from the national point of view and from the labour relations point of view.</P>
    <P>I do not know that it could ever arise but nevertheless I do not want to take a chance that it could issue such publications that would be dangerous or a source of embarrassment. They might create difficulties that they are not competent to assess.  The Minister, whoever he might be, would be in a much better position, having regard to the experience of his Department in the use of certain commodities, in the matter of the line of demarcation between certain trades and crafts as applied to particular industries.  Therefore, any publications in that line ought to be subject to the Minister's approval.  I have no objection to the publication of technical scientific data without the approval of the Minister and without recourse to the Minister because it must be assumed that the Institute and not the Minister is the best judge of the data it proposes to publish. Therefore, I submit the amendment goes some distance to meet the Senator's point but, on the other hand, it only goes so far as to ensure that <Col N="1002" /> the safeguards I have mentioned will be still there.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickQuinlan" hpid="Professor Quinlan Professor Quinlan">
      <NameTxt>Professor Quinlan</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister's amendment fully meets the case I made on Committee Stage.  I was concerned with safeguarding that the publication of scientific and technical information should solely be the function of the Institute.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanODonovan" hpid="Seán Ó Donnabháin Seán Ó Donnabháin">
      <NameTxt>Seán Ó Donnabháin</NameTxt>
      <P>I wonder if the word &ldquo;may&rdquo; here means &ldquo;shall&rdquo;?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I think it means &ldquo;may&rdquo; on this occasion.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanODonovan" hpid="Seán Ó Donnabháin Seán Ó Donnabháin">
      <NameTxt>Seán Ó Donnabháin</NameTxt>
      <P>I was going to support Senator Quinlan on his amendment No. 22, strange to relate, on this section about including a summary of the work every three years or every five years.  Under Section 45 the Institute &ldquo;may&rdquo; do this.  I would rather have &ldquo;shall&rdquo; do this.  In Senator Quinlan's previous amendment, he suggested a comprehensive summary report of the work every five years.  I should like to see something to that effect published every few years.  It will not necessitate scrutinising three annual reports.  We could add &ldquo;including a summary of the work every three years&rdquo;.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JackLynch" hpid="Mr. J. Lynch Mr. J. Lynch">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J. Lynch</NameTxt>
      <P>I think Section 45 as it stands gives the Institute power to publish matters of that nature, comprehensive or otherwise, covering a period of three, five or seven years.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I think it does, too.</P>
      <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
      <P>Amendment No. 22 not moved.</P>
      <P>Bill, as amended, received for final consideration and passed.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Road Traffic Bill," RHead="1960&mdash;Second Stage">
    <Title>Road Traffic Bill, 1960&mdash;Second Stage.</Title>
    <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That the Bill be now read a second time.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="NeilTCBlaney" hpid="Minister for Local Government (Mr. Blaney) Neil T. Blaney">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Local Government (Mr. Blaney)</NameTxt>
      <P>As Senators will be aware, the main provisions of this Bill were made known to the public in a White Paper published last year.  Public reaction was strongly in support of the major proposals which have been embodied <Col N="1003" /> in the Bill.  The problems with which the Bill sets out to grapple are first, that of road accidents, and second, the need to secure a more efficient use of our road system.  Last year there were, in round figures, 300 fatal accidents and 4,000 accidents involving personal injury on our roads.</P>
      <P>These are the cold statistics and we can readily conjure up the picture of domestic tragedies that in many cases lie behind them.  In that perspective I am confident that I will have the full support of the House for the general principles underlying this Bill.  At this point I might mention that in order to achieve the greatest possible degree of unanimity, the Bill as now presented to this House differs in a number of important respects from its original conception.  I will refer in more detail to these changes later.</P>
      <P>As a corollary to the passing of the Bill, it is hoped to make its provisions familiar to all road users by a well-planned programme of Road Safety propaganda.  We will be looking to voluntary bodies for their continued co-operation in this field, and here I would like to pay a tribute to the work they have done in the past.</P>
      <P>It would be a waste of time to pass this legislation if it were not to be properly enforced and I have got an assurance from the Minister for Justice that the Garda Siochána will act on that basis.  Lest this statement might be misinterpreted let me add that the enactment of the Bill is not intended to herald an era of persecution for the motorist.  The ordinary law-abiding motorist will have nothing to fear from this Bill.  On the contrary quite a number of its provisions are aimed at reducing the difficulties under which at present he has to operate.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Above all, the provisions of the Bill will depend ultimately for their success on the degree of co-operation which the general public will be prepared to accord them and I would like to appeal particularly to parents and teachers to make sure that young children under their care will be fully instructed in the Rules of the Road.  I feel sure that <Col N="1004" /> Senators will unanimously endorse and support this appeal.</P>
    <P>Turning to the detailed provisions of the Bill, which is a comprehensive measure intended to replace the Road Traffic Act, 1933, and other enactments dealing with road traffic, it will be observed that Part 1 deals with the usual preliminary and general matters, such as citation, commencement, interpretation, regulations and repeals.  Section 3 is important in that it is the section which gives the interpretation of certain phrases used throughout the Bill.  Section 4 provides that Part VI of the Bill which deals with compulsory insurance, will not apply to vehicles owned by the State and similar categories of vehicles for which however the State accepts responsibility under Section 116.  All other Parts of the Bill will of course apply to persons in the service of the State and to vehicles owned by the State.</P>
    <P>Section 5 confers power on the Minister to make regulations and provides for the laying of every regulation made under the Bill before each House of the Oireachtas and for the annulment by either House of any such regulation by resolution passed within 21 sitting days.  The Bill gives power to prescribe various details, largely technical or operational in character, by regulations.  It is the intention that except in a very exceptional case where extreme urgency may demand a different course, there will be full consultation in advance with all bodies or organisations whose interests may be affected by a particular regulation.  Section 6 prescribes the procedure to be followed by the Commissioner of the Garda Síochána in making bye-laws.  These bye-laws are of two kinds namely, general bye-laws and local bye-laws.  The general bye-laws would be those made under Section 86 or Section 88 of the Bill for the general regulation and control of traffic throughout the State or, for example, the control of queues at bus stops.  The procedure is the same as under the 1933 Act, with one modification.  Subsection (7) of Section 6 now provides that general bye-laws shall be laid before each <Col N="1005" /> House of the Oireachtas in the same way as Ministerial regulations.  The local bye-laws are of local interest; in framing them the Commissioner is bound to consider any representations made to him by the elected representatives of the local authority concerned; before approving, modifying or refusing to approve of such bye-laws the Minister is also bound to consider the views of the local representatives.  Section 7, 8, and 9 largely replace corresponding provisions in the 1933 Act, while Section 10 provides for repeals.</P>
    <P>Before leaving Part 1, I should mention the question of owner liability. Under the 1933 Act the owner of a vehicle was liable for its insurance and also liable in respect of certain offences. Under the Bill, the owner continues to be liable for insurance and is also responsible for ensuring that a vehicle required to be tested under Section 18 has been so tested.  In the case of certain requirements where it is only reasonable that the owner should be responsible, he is liable for consequential offences; examples are in Sections 11 and 54, which relate to the construction of vehicles and their condition. Finally, under Section 86 and 90 the registered owner of a vehicle is made liable for parking offences.  Improper parking can cause serious economic loss to the community in various ways and it is practically impossible to prevent it unless the registered owner is made liable.  It is only fair to require the registered owner to ensure that his vehicle does not cause traffic congestion and delays.  In all cases suitable defences are available to the owner.  I may say that the provisions I have mentioned were the subject of considerable debate in the Dáil and as a result were amended in several respects.  These amendments provide further safeguards for the owner but do not defeat the overall purpose of the provisions.</P>
    <P>Part II of the Bill enables the Minister to regulate the construction, equipment, use, lighting and weights of vehicles and contains provisions for a new scheme of vehicle testing.  Section 11 enables regulations to be made in relation to the use of all classes of <Col N="1006" /> vehicles in public places.  These regulations will deal with the dimensions of vehicles (including trailers), their brakes, steering, lights and reflectors. It will also enable the use of safety harness or crash helmets to be made compulsory if deemed necessary or particular areas to be declared silence zones at night-time.  It will be clear that it is essential to have completely flexible powers to deal with all these details in view of changes that are constantly taking place in the design and equipment of all classes of vehicles as a result of research and study.  A review of the existing regulations is being undertaken by my Department.</P>
    <P>Sections 18 and 19 are the next sections which call for special comment. These sections envisage the introduction of a scheme of vehicle testing for which there is a considerable volume of support from the public.  It is intended to apply the scheme, initially at least, to old vehicles and possibly to heavy goods vehicles. Experience may reveal that it would be desirable at a later stage, to extend the scheme to other classes.  Flexible provision is available to enable the Minister for Local Government to decide on the authority to operate the scheme.  The Bill will enable commercial garages to be used for testing if that is thought desirable.  A choice will be made of the authority to use in the beginning and, if experience shows that a change is necessary, such change can be effected.</P>
    <P>Section 20 is, to an extent, complementary to the provisions contained in Sections 18 and 19.  It will enable the Garda Síochána to deal with vehicles having obvious defects which make their use on roads a danger to the public.</P>
    <P>Part III of the Bill, which replaces Parts III and VI of the 1933 Act, deals with driving licences, driving and fitness tests, disqualifications and other allied matters.  The most noteworthy features of this Part are the introduction of driving tests, fitness tests and provisional licences.  Due to the introduction of testing arrangements it is necessary to provide in Section 22 that applications for driving licences may be confined to particular classes of <Col N="1007" /> vehicles.  A person disqualified for a particular class, for example, because of age, fitness or an ancillary or special disqualification order, may not apply for a licence to drive that class of vehicle.  If an applicant is of a class required to pass a driving test he must produce the appropriate evidence, a certificate of competency, with his application to show that he has passed the test. Section 23 obliges a licensing authority to issue a driving licence unless it appears that the applicant is disqualified or that he has not a satisfactory knowledge of the Rules of the Road. It will be possible to arrange for the issue of driving licences for, say, three-yearly periods if such an extension is deemed desirable.  In this connection I should mention that it will also be possible to arrange for the adoption of a different form of driving licence from that used at present.  This form could provide for the use of a photograph on the licence such as is used in other countries.</P>
    <P>The introduction of driving tests, has received a general welcome.  The necessary provisions are contained chiefly in Section 33.  It is intended that in the beginning only new drivers will be required to pass the test which will consist of a test in competency to drive and in knowledge of the Rules of the Road.  Persons convicted of certain offences, for example, dangerous or careless driving, may also be required to pass the test.  I am now in a position to announce that after full consideration of all relevant factors, including in particular the need for uniformity and economy, it has been decided that the authority to deal with driving tests should be the Department of Local Government. The testing staff will be recruited through normal Civil Service channels. A close study has been made of the systems operating in some other countries and the advantage of being in a position to profit from their experience should facilitate the smooth working of the scheme.</P>
    <P>Fitness tests are provided for in Section 34 and will apply in the beginning only to persons who suffer <Col N="1008" /> from particular disabilities, to persons driving particular classes of vehicles, such as buses, and to persons over a certain age.  In addition the courts will have power to require persons to undergo fitness tests.</P>
    <P>Section 26 provides for consequential disqualification for driving on conviction of certain offences which are clearly set out in the Second Schedule to the Bill.  The disqualification relates to all mechanically propelled vehicles and must be imposed by the court where a person is convicted of any of the offences set out in the Schedule.  It will be agreed that disqualification is a very effective way to help to eliminate road traffic offences.  The offences which now appear in the Schedule are all of a very serious nature and I feel sure that there will be no quarrel with the proposal to impose disqualification in all these cases.  The two most serious offences included in the list are those of driving while under the influence of drink and of dangerous driving causing death or serious bodily harm; these two offences are accordingly singled out for more severe treatment than all the other offences specified in that they both merit disqualification on commission of a first offence and the disqualification period is longer; the other offences listed only carry disqualification for a second or subsequent offence within any period of three years.</P>
    <P>Section 27 deals with ancillary disqualification, that is, disqualification which may be imposed at the discretion of the court and Section 28 enables an officer of the Garda Síochana to apply to the court for a special disqualification order in respect of a person who is obviously unfit or incompetent to drive.</P>
    <P>Section 29 enables a person to whom a consequential or ancillary disqualification order applies to apply to the court for its removal.  As a corollary to this provision Section 124 of the Bill provides that disqualifications may no longer be remitted by the Minister for Justice under the Criminal Justice Act, 1951.</P>
    <P>Part IV of the Bill contains provisions <Col N="1009" /> for speed limits in respect of mechanically propelled vehicles.  The main item of interest here is the provision in Section 45 for a general speed limit of 30 m.p.h. for all vehicles on public roads in &ldquo;built up areas&rdquo;, as defined in the section.  There has been an incessant demand for a number of years for the introduction of a general speed limit such as is now proposed.  If experience shows that the figure of 30 m.p.h. is too low&mdash;and doubts have been expressed in some quarters to that effect&mdash;the section contains power to increase it.  It will be agreed, however, that it is more advisable to fix the limit on the low side and then if deemed desirable later to increase the limit, rather than to proceed on the reverse basis of setting the limit possibly too high and then bringing it down.</P>
    <P>As a supplement to the provisions of Section 45, Section 46 enables special speed limits to be fixed for specified roads or specified areas on the application of the Garda Commissioner or the local authority concerned.  It is anticipated that these powers will be availed of only in exceptional cases.</P>
    <P>I should also mention that Section 44 in this Part will enable speed limits to be fixed for the whole country for particular types of vehicle.  These limits are known as &ldquo;ordinary speed limits&rdquo;.</P>
    <P>Part V groups together a number of serious offences.  Section 49 deals with the offence of driving while under the influence of drink or a drug.  It provides that the penalty shall be imprisonment for a maximum period of six months, or, at the discretion of the court, a fine of £100 or both such imprisonment and such fine.  In order to underline to the courts the serious view which is taken of this offence by the Legislature it will be noted that, contrary to normal practice, the penalty of imprisonment is first cited and that of a fine is cited as an alternative to be imposed as a penalty at the discretion of the court.  My original intention was that imprisonment should be practically mandatory for this offence and that the court which convicted a person should be empowered to impose a fine only where it considered that there were special <Col N="1010" /> reasons for not imposing imprisonment. My personal view still is that this offence should in the normal course be punished with a term in prison.  I have reluctantly accepted the less severe approach which appears in the Bill now before the House in the hope that such an approach will have the widest possible measure of support. In taking this decision I was also influenced by the fact that a Commission is to be set up to investigate and report on this entire question of drunk driving, including the use of objective tests of drunkenness.  When the Commission has reported it will be possible to have another look at these provisions. I am sure that at least there will be no quarrel with the proposal that the Probation of Offenders Act shall not apply to offences under the section.</P>
    <P>The provisions of Section 53 (2) (a) might be appropriately mentioned next.  These provisions relate to the very serious offence of dangerous driving which causes death or serious bodily harm.  In regard to this offence also I have modified my original proposal of mandatory imprisonment and have deferred to the view that the decision should be left to the discretion of the court.  Here again, however, imprisonment is the punishment first mentioned in the section.</P>
    <P>A new offence of dangerous parking appears in Section 55.  The offence will apply to all vehicles since it will be clear, for example, that a detached trailer can on occasion cause a very serious traffic hazard.  The more serious offence of dangerous parking of a vehicle unlit at night-time is emphasised by the heavier penalty laid down in the section.</P>
    <P>In Part VI, dealing with compulsory insurance, there are a few changes to which I wish to refer.  The basis of compulsory insurance is being changed to cover &ldquo;use&rdquo; of vehicles instead of &ldquo;driving&rdquo;; this will make it clear that stationary vehicles must be covered. Regulations under Section 65 will enable the Minister for Local Government to specify the classes of vehicles to which compulsory passenger cover will apply.  My present intentions are to apply these regulations to all <Col N="1011" /> vehicles of the private-car and station-wagon type, in addition of course to public service vehicles to which this requirement already applies under the 1933 Act.  Section 78 provides that new vehicle insurers, guarantors and exempted persons must become members of the Motor Insurers' Bureau or give the undertaking laid down in the section.  Here I wish to record my appreciation of the valuable service given by the Bureau since it was established in 1955.</P>
    <P>Part VII deals with the control and operation of public service vehicles. The setting up of Coras Iompair Éireann as a statutory transport body has made a significant change in conditions relating to public service vehicles compared with those prevailing when the 1933 Act was enacted.  It is intended that public service vehicle licensing will not apply to C.I.E., nor will drivers and conductors employed by C.I.E. require to be licensed under this part of the Bill.  It was originally proposed also to remove &ldquo;hackneys&rdquo; from the scope of public service vehicle licensing but at the request of the hackney owners and drivers themselves it has since been decided to continue the licensing of this type of vehicle.</P>
    <P>Section 84 will enable the Commissioner of the Garda Síochána, as at present, to retain control over taxi stands by means of bye-laws made after consultation with the local authority concerned and with the consent of the Minister for Local Government. A new provision will enable the Commissioner to make temporary rules regulating taxi stands so that, for example, in the cities of Dublin and Cork, traffic control experiments can be facilitated.  These powers should be considered in conjunction with similar powers being conferred under Sections 89 and 90 to deal with local traffic and parking bye-laws.</P>
    <P>Sections 85 and 86 cover such matters as bus-stops and stands, the regulation of bus queues and the provision of bus shelters.</P>
    <P>Part VIII deals with the regulation and control of traffic and parking. Points worthy of mention arise on a <Col N="1012" /> number of sections.  Sections 88 and 89 deal respectively with the making of general bye-laws for the control of traffic and of local bye-laws for the control of traffic in particular areas. The powers conferred by these sections largely correspond to similar powers under the 1933 Act, but the opportunity is being taken to remedy some deficiencies in the earlier Act to enable modern traffic conditions to be dealt with adequately.</P>
    <P>Section 90 will enable us to avail of modern methods of dealing with the parking problem, such as parking meters.  Section 91 makes it clear that the Gardaí may take appropriate steps to control traffic on special occasions, such as processions.  Section 97 enables the Garda Síochána to remove vehicles which are abandoned or cause obstruction and to recover the reasonable costs of removal and storage of same from the owner.  Section 101 confers comprehensive powers on local authorities in the provision of, or in assisting private enterprise to provide, off-street car parks.  I hope that this section will enable a worth-while contribution to be made to the relief of traffic congestion in the larger centres of population.</P>
    <P>Part IX contains miscellaneous provisions, a number of which appeared in the 1933 Act and which have been improved where necessary.</P>
    <P>A new provision appears in Section 103.  It introduces a system which has been inaccurately described as &ldquo;fines on the spot.&rdquo;  It is emphasised that there will be no question of a fine being handed over &ldquo;on the spot&rdquo; to a member of the Garda Síochána.  A notice will be given to the person concerned and a prescribed sum which will be set out in the notice may then be paid within a period of 21 days at a Garda Station or the person concerned may, entirely at his own discretion, decide to have the charge alleged against him determined by the court.</P>
    <P>Another new provision is made in Section 120 which authorises local authorities to incur expenditure on road safety.  It also enables Road Fund grants to be given for road safety purposes both to local authorities and to bodies, such as the Safety First <Col N="1013" /> Association, who are primarily concerned with that very laudable objective.</P>
    <P>I have outlined what in my view are the features of this Bill worth specific mention.  Without prolonging my speech unduly it would be impossible to give an exhaustive account of all the various provisions incorporated in a measure of this magnitude and scope.  I will, however, be glad to supply any further information that Senators may wish to have or to clarify any points that Senators may feel require clarification.</P>
    <P>I am confident that Senators will welcome this Bill and will be fully in agreement with the objectives which it is hoped will be achieved by its implementation.  On this latter point let me conclude by saying that it is my wish and the wish of the Government that all its various provisions be brought into force as quickly as possible.</P>
    <P>
      <i>Business suspended at</i> 6 <i>p.m. and resumed at</i> 7.15 <i>p.m.</i></P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Business" RHead="of Seanad">
    <Title>Business of Seanad.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="OwenSkeffington" hpid="Dr. Sheehy Skeffington Dr. Sheehy Skeffington">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Sheehy Skeffington</NameTxt>
      <P>The Leader of the House promised us a statement at 7.15 p.m. in regard to the probable procedure, as to whether we could finish tonight, whether we were meeting to-morrow and whether we would take motions.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>The Senator did not mention motions, so far as I can remember.  It is proposed to finish the Second Stage of the Road Traffic Bill to-night.  If necessary, we might even consider sitting after the normal time to do so.  It is not intended to meet tomorrow in that event.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OwenSkeffington" hpid="Dr. Sheehy Skeffington Dr. Sheehy Skeffington">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Sheehy Skeffington</NameTxt>
      <P>Rather than hear the Leader of the House saying he thought perhaps the Seanad might decide, the House should decide whether or not it is the intention to meet after 10 o'clock.  We have done that too often and got rid of legislation in a hasty way and put motions permanently on the long finger by that means.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1014" />
    <Speaker pid="PatrickQuinlan" hpid="Professor Quinlan Professor Quinlan">
      <NameTxt>Professor Quinlan</NameTxt>
      <P>Could we have some statement as to when the motions will be taken?  Many have been on the Order Paper for nine months? It is gross dereliction of duty by the Seanad to allow them to remain on the Order Paper for so long.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>If Senators curbed the length of their speeches, we might have got to these motions long ago.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickQuinlan" hpid="Professor Quinlan Professor Quinlan">
      <NameTxt>Professor Quinlan</NameTxt>
      <P>The House has sat not more than 20 times in the past six months.  If that is not dereliction of duty, I do not know what is.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>The Senator was not here half that time.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickQuinlan" hpid="Professor Quinlan Professor Quinlan">
      <NameTxt>Professor Quinlan</NameTxt>
      <P>I have attended far more times than Senator Ó Maoláin.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Professor Hayes Professor Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Professor Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>This is not going to get us anywhere.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LiamOBuachalla" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Perhaps the Leader of the House could give us an indication at 9 o'clock?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Professor Hayes Professor Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Professor Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>It is no contribution to the getting of business done here to say that if speeches were curbed, we would do more work.  The truth is that there are not enough people here to speak.  That is the truth about the Seanad.  We should be grateful to anyone who speaks here.  We could decide now&mdash;I do not see why we could not&mdash;to continue until 11 o'clock to finish the Second Stage.  We have to take cognisance of the circumstances. I understand that the Minister will probably have his own Estimate in the Dáil tomorrow.  As far as I am concerned, I am prepared to agree to sit until 11 o'clock to finish the Second Stage.  I do not agree that finishing the Second Stage of the Bill will have any effect upon the taking of motions.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OwenSkeffington" hpid="Dr. Sheehy Skeffington Dr. Sheehy Skeffington">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Sheehy Skeffington</NameTxt>
      <P>I personally would agree to going on a little later with the Second Stage of this Bill but I should like to see that, by so agreeing, we are not simply agreeing that we want these motions today, that we want them tomorrow or that we want them next week.  I think it is unfair for the Leader of the House to put us in that position.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1015" />
    <Speaker pid="LiamOBuachalla" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Perhaps the Leader of the House would indicate about 9 o'clock&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OwenSkeffington" hpid="Dr. Sheehy Skeffington Dr. Sheehy Skeffington">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Sheehy Skeffington</NameTxt>
      <P>Perhaps he would examine his conscience quietly in relation to motions?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>I have examined it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OwenSkeffington" hpid="Dr. Sheehy Skeffington Dr. Sheehy Skeffington">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Sheehy Skeffington</NameTxt>
      <P>Quietly, I said.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>Very quietly.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Road Traffic Bill," RHead="1960&mdash;Second Stage (Resumed)">
    <Title>Road Traffic Bill, 1960&mdash;Second Stage (Resumed).</Title>
    <P>Question again proposed: &ldquo;That the Bill be now read a second Time.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Professor Hayes Professor Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Professor Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>I regret that, owing to a miscalculation, I did not hear the Minister's speech but I had the advantage of seeing it since.  We had this matter discussed twice in the last Seanad&mdash;in 1955 and 1956.  It is not a political matter.  We are all at one in desiring that the roads should be made safer and that the law should be improved, if that will be of any advantage.  We differ merely on matters of detail and occasionally on matters of principle, such as the imposition of fines on the spot.</P>
      <P>My first reaction to this measure, like my first reaction to every other measure like it, is that there is no use in enacting an enormous amount of legislation about traffic when the rules we already have are not enforced.  I know that the Minister in his speech this afternoon said he has an assurance that this legislation will be enforced. It is a very large Bill with 127 sections. They make a considerable addition to the law as we have it but if it cannot be enforced, then it is no use because law that is not enforced is bad for the morale of the public.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Your last case is worse than the first if you multiply the provisions of the law and at the same time, make no provision for adequate enforcement. One of the difficulties of the whole question of traffic is that you never know under which thimble the pea is. <Col N="1016" /> We have the Minister for Local Government, the Minister for Justice and the Minister for Industry and Commerce. One is never quite sure who is responsible for what.</P>
    <P>In Dublin, the position is that when police are in charge of traffic, they are wholly admirable.  However, the police not concerned with traffic appear to be, of set purpose, neutral about traffic, as the old D.M.P. were about Irish Volunteers.  As far as I see in Dublin, if Gárdaí are not on traffic duty as pointsmen, when they are wholly admirable, they do not bother about traffic at all.  There may be reasons for that but I do not know what they are.</P>
    <P>There are two things which can be done about this matter.  One is education and the dissemination of information and the other is punishment. Education is by no means as simple as people think.  There is certainly a hard core of road users, motorists, cyclists and pedestrians, whom nobody can educate and therefore they must be punished.  The punishment is punishment of a minority but I think there is no doubt that it should be drastic and if possible, swift.</P>
    <P>The whole process of reporting somebody for a breach of a traffic law and having to wait until the case comes up in court&mdash;and they have to go there and give evidence; a Guard has to attend, they must spend a day in the district court&mdash;seems too slow a method.  Here is a matter of principle. Our legal friends tell us: &ldquo;You must have trial; you cannot have summary punishment&rdquo; and so on.  It is a desperate situation.  Every couple of days, three people are killed on the roads.  Unless we have some swift, drastic measures for an intractable minority, we shall not get any further in our desire to improve the position.</P>
    <P>Another point in regard to punishment and reporting is that we hardly ever see a case of a prosecution in court unless an accident has taken place.  Anybody who uses the roads here as a pedestrian or a motorist knows that people constantly disobey the rules.  It seems to me, and always has seemed to me, that the punishment <Col N="1017" /> should be either a jail sentence or loss of licence.  When you say that motorists should lose their licences, you are confronted with the problem of what you are to do with cyclists without lights.  The cyclists without lights are not the exception but the rule, certainly in the city of Dublin.  Driving home from here to Rathmines or Rathfarnham, or driving north, the great majority of cyclists one meets have no lights.  I do not know what we can do about them.  What you would like to do is to take away the bicycles. Of course, they are not licensed and you cannot do anything about them at all.</P>
    <P>As far as the regulations are concerned, they should be clear, they should be uniform and they should be enforced.  I do not know what steps the Minister proposes to take. There is a booklet in which it is set out that you should give way to traffic on your right but nobody does.  I do not know whether the Minister, in consultation with the Minister for Justice, can take any steps to see that is done.  A short distance from my house, I meet Kimmage Road on my left with traffic coming from it.  The buses are much bigger than my car and I yield to them.  Once in a while, you will meet a bus driver who gives way but in the majority of cases, particularly private motorists, they come from your left at a fast speed.  People coming up and desiring to go on to a minor road want to pass out in front of you, going on your right. I do not know if the Minister has any method by which he can see that these rules are enforced.  I do not mind whether the rule is to give way to traffic on your left or on your right but whichever it is, it should be enforced.</P>
    <P>Similarly, is there any way of discovering what is a major road and what is a minor road?  Is it really possible at law to say what is a major or a minor road and have people on major roads any particular rights?  Apparently that is a matter of grave doubtat present.  With regard to pedestrians, they have no rights at all unless they are lively, <Col N="1018" /> nimble and young, and I am not lively, nimble or young.  I am very familiar with two places where there are traffic lights, at Terenure where I live, and the junction of Leeson Street and Earlsfort Terrace.  I used to find it easy to cross at Earlsfort Terrace but in recent years it is difficult to cross there.  If pedestrians coming up by St. Vincent's Hospital want to cross to Earlsfort Terrace, they proceed to cross when the lights are green but the motorists, in the main, are coming up past the hospital, proceeding towards Leeson Street and they charge the pedestrians right away. I do not know what happens then.  If you are nimble you run but I am not nimble and I find it more and more difficult to cross the road.  I presume people of a certain age still have their rights.  If the motorists did not go around that way, I do not think they could get around.</P>
    <P>There are certain things in the Bill with regard to enforcement and there is the driving test.  Speaking for myself, I would never have passed a driving test which required me to know what an engine was.  I have been driving for quite a long time and I never had an accident but if I had been examined in regard to the details of an engine, I would not have passed the test.  The type of test that is required is one in regard to road courtesy rather than knowledge of engines.  The most reckless drivers on the road are those who are experts on engines and they take all kinds of risks because they have all kinds of knowledge.  The test I should like to see is in regard to how a person behaves on the road.</P>
    <P>The arrangements about speed limits are admirable and allow the Minister to impose speed limits and to vary them in the light of experience.  The speed limit in the Bill is 30 miles an hour.  I live on the Templeogue Road which is a main road to Wicklow and Wexford and also to the south because you can get to Naas from that road. When you have a new car and have to travel at 30 miles an hour, you are in everybody's way.  It seems to me that 30 miles an hour, while it is desirable, is a speed limit which it will nearly <Col N="1019" /> impossible to enforce.  I think I am right in saying that the Minister has power to vary it and make it more realistic.</P>
    <P>I wonder if there is any way of defining pedestrian's rights.  I take it the Minister is not responsible but it is no harm to remark that from Rathfarnham, through Terenure and down to the quays by Harold's Cross, there is only one pedestrian crossing, which is at the school at the Hospice.  It is a very wide road and there is no way of getting across.  In a great many cases when people are crossing, the traffic lights change.  I do not know what the position is in law or whether the pedestrian has rights.  He may have but if he insists on them, he will probably get killed and that is no use to him.</P>
    <P>One other matter I should like to see dealt with is in the use of horns. I think there is a provision in the 1933 Act that motorists can be prosecuted for creating a nuisance through the use of horns.  I should like to see an endeavour being made to have a silence period say from 11 p.m. to 8 a.m.  I know that on all main roads there are a great many motorists who drive on the horn and do that even in winter evenings when it is dark, at 10 o'clock, 11 o'clock and 12 midnight. On the road on which I live, people sound their horns to get other people out of the way, but everybody knows that at night time the proper use of one's headlights is sufficient for this purpose.  In many cities, in Rome and Paris, for instance, the introduction of silence zones has been very successful and they should be tried in Dublin. Some people suffer inconvenience because they have to live on corners which perhaps were once quiet places but which are now subject to all kinds of noises.</P>
    <P>There are aspects of this matter which are not certain.  I saw, for example, that there was a discussion about people travelling in different lanes through traffic lights.  What does that mean?  If I am turning left at traffic lights, I approach them as near as possible to my left and if I am not going left, I leave room for cars <Col N="1020" /> beside me but people come up on your left and shoot out in front of you.  I do not assert my rights any longer. Professional drivers can assert their rights but I never try.  In Dublin, it is quite common for people to approach on your left and then go ahead in front of you.</P>
    <P>I wonder is that the law?  I am sure the Minister would know.  I do not know what the law is.  I do feel that this whole question of driving and death on the roads cannot be dealt with merely by passing laws.  When we pass this law, we will be only at the beginning.  I think improving the roads is not such a wonderful thing. Quite lately, I saw a very bad accident on a very wide road.</P>
    <P>I think it was the late P.S. O'Hegarty, an inveterate cyclist, who said that the proper thing was not to make better roads but to put traps or gullies on them.  If these gullies were approached at speed, the drivers would break their wheels, if not their necks. There is something in that.  If Senators lived, as I do, on a road on which there is heavy traffic, on which people travel at enormous speeds, they would feel that a big notice in Templeogue: &ldquo;Beware of the Gullies&rdquo; or &ldquo;Mind Your Wheels&rdquo; might be of some use. It would not be of much use, but it might be of some use.  It could not be done, of course, because it would cause trouble to other people, but there is no doubt whatever that the problem of speeding on the roads will have to be dealt with.</P>
    <P>It is not a problem of a social nature. It is not rich people who speed; it is not the people with enormous cars who speed.  My experience is that small cars, in particular, seem to be driven at very high speeds.  It is not the motorists who are the most neglectful.  Women with prams and children approaching to cross a road at a pedestrian crossing find crowds of cyclists there and a great many motorists and bus drivers shove their vehicles right across pedestrian crossings in the presence of policemen who do not seem to take any notice. It is no wonder that pedestrians do not bother about pedestrian crossings because when they go to cross, they <Col N="1021" /> find them already occupied by cyclists, motor cyclists or motor vehicles.  If we could have the enforcement of some clear and uniform law even in a simpler Bill, it would do a lot of good.</P>
    <P>I welcome the idea of driving tests. I am not quite convinced&mdash;I think the Minister gave way on this matter in the other House&mdash;on the question of summary punishment, but I am prepared to hear it argued.  If there was clarity and enforcement even in a simpler code than this, we would have made considerable progress.  The Bill should certainly get a Second Reading.</P>
    <Speaker pid="BrianLenihanSnr" hpid="Mr. Lenihan Mr. Lenihan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lenihan</NameTxt>
      <P>As a legal practitioner, the sections of the Bill which interest me most are Sections 48 to 55 in Part V dealing with driving offences. A certain amount of public hysteria has been generated, both by public utterances and press editorials, with regard to the problem of dangerous driving and, in particular, the problem of drunken driving.  The latter problem in particular has been exaggerated. Actually Garda statistics bear me out in the statement that something in the region of 90 per cent. of all driving offences are not related to drink.  In many cases, this public hysteria tends to prevent some unfortunates from getting justice when charged with offences under the road traffic code.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>That sort of public hysteria in regard to driving offences was responsible to a certain degree for what I might describe as the Draconian provision of mandatory imprisonment penalties for drunken driving and dangerous driving which result in serious bodily harm or fatality.  The Minister met the wishes expressed in the other House on Report Stage, and in regard to both those offences, there is now a fine alternative. I feel that justice is best served by that provision, because one can quite easily imagine a case of minimum dangerous driving resulting, through misfortune or otherwise, in serious bodily harm or a fatal accident. Under the original provision, that would result in mandatory imprisonment. I feel that provision was wrong. It would mean that the courts would operate as a cypher and impose the penalty which, by legislation, they must <Col N="1022" /> impose.  That has been adjusted now and judicial discretion is provided to take into account the type of case I have mentioned.</P>
    <P>For the same reason, I am glad there is a similar fine alternative in the case of drunken driving.  Any person who practises in the courts sees the enormous variations in cases of drunken driving from the borderline case to the man who is completely and absolutely incapable because of drink.  A judicial tribunal such as the courts, can exercise discretion as between the case of minimum drunkenness and maximum drunkenness. The original provision was brought about by the excessive public hysteria about driving offences, and in particular, drunken driving offences.</P>
    <P>Another basis for the section which referred to dangerous driving which caused bodily harm or a fatality was that it was said that far too few convictions were being obtained where manslaughter was charged arising from a road accident, and that the courts took a rather liberal view in charges to juries.  The Attorney General v. Dunleavy is the classic case of manslaughter arising out of a road accident.  In recent months, the courts have been taking a more strict view of those cases in charging juries. There have been quite a few convictions of manslaughter arising out of driving offences.  In the Dublin Circuit Criminal Court about three weeks ago there were two manslaughter prosecutions arising out of driving offences in which convictions were secured on the manslaughter charge and the present penalty imposed. I believe that, provided judges take a proper view of the matter in the really serious cases of driving offences involving a fatality, convictions can be got under the existing manslaughter provisions.  I agree that the situation was not quite as satisfactory 12 months ago as it is today.  The position now is that convictions are being got in manslaughter charges in driving offences where a fatality occurs.</P>
    <P>In regard to the drunken driving problem, I very much welcome the Minister's announcement here, and on <Col N="1023" /> Report Stage in the Dáil, that he is setting up a commission to consider the question of blood tests or some similar scientific tests by which the degree of drunkenness can be ascertained. I would not go as far as some of our humourless and puritanical neighbours in the Scandinavian countries have gone.  They can get a conviction of drunken driving if the blood test shows the driver has consumed a few half whiskeys, a few bottles of beer, or the equivalent.  We should not go as far as that.  There should be a little more latitude here about the type of test in respect of this problem of ascertaining when a man is incapable of driving a vehicle by reason of the consumption of drink.</P>
    <P>Because of a court decision a year or two ago, it is now permissible for members of the Garda to give expert evidence in the courts on drunkenness. Formerly, medical evidence was required but it is no longer required. If a man is charged with drunkenness and Garda A, B or C stands up in court and says that he staggered or smelled of alcohol, supporting medical evidence is no longer required.  I believe that could give rise to a dangerous situation.  I do not mean this as any reflection on the Gardaí, but by reason of their training and their day-to-day routine, they tend to give stock examples of drunkenness: He staggered; he smelled of alcohol; and his speech was slurred.  You get the same stock examples to sustain the view that he was drunk coming up in the courts day in and day out.  That situation could lead to abuse by reason of the Guards dealing with the matter inevitably in a routine way.  That could lead to abuse, particularly when it does not require to be supported by medical evidence.</P>
    <P>The real answer to it&mdash;and this is also the Minister's view&mdash;is that there should be some scientific test.  The whole question of convincing proof in the district court at the moment as to whether a man is drunk or not is highly unsatisfactory.  I welcome the Minister's announcement that he is setting up a commission to deal with this problem.  My only plea is that we <Col N="1024" /> do not put the scale too low but that we put it within reason and modification, bearing in mind the fact that a person who is charged with an offence is also a person who has rights and privileges.  We should not overweigh this argument against a driving offence by way of hysteria.  It is because the individual has his rights that I welcome particularly the provisions which eliminate the mandatory jail sentence. I welcome for that very same reason a scientific test.  If there is a scientific test, the individual can rest assured that his case will not be prejudiced.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JaneDowdall" hpid="Mrs. Dowdall Mrs. Dowdall">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Dowdall</NameTxt>
      <P>I welcome this measure, too.  I hope that, when enacted, it will have been improved in its passage through this House and that the conditions on the roads and road traffic conditions generally will be greatly improved.  Most of what is called reckless and careless driving would be eliminated by ordinary simple education and by people using good manners.  If I had to define reckless driving, I would say it is inevitably somebody who in the ordinary social sense is quite well-behaved and whose manners are extremely good but to whom something seems to happen when he or she gets behind the wheel of a car.  The savage or primeval in all of us seems to take control and people behave quite irrationally.</P>
      <P>The many points mentioned by Senator Hayes are experiences that we all have in our ordinary driving from day to day.  I would agree that what we need at the moment is education in road safety.  On that account I was very pleased with one point in the speech made by the Minister.  He proposes to grant money to local authorities for this purpose and to the Safety First Association which is an Association that over the years has taken upon itself this enormous task of educating us to try to avoid accidents.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>We are all aware in recent times of very many fatal accidents caused by dangerous parking of large vehicles on the road at night and, indeed, small vehicles as well.  There are parts of our city which are used at night exclusively for the parking of these great <Col N="1025" /> lorries and trucks.  They have no indicators or lights on them.  They happen to be in a part of the city which is well-lighted.  They are a positive danger.  Large trucks parked or being driven at night are inadequately lit at the back or at the sides.  In other countries they have to have a light every couple of feet on the side of a large truck.  Here they seem to have one or two small lights at the back which are quite inadequate to indicate to passing motorists the extent of these great trucks.  These are parked at night with one light in front and another behind.  There should be many more lights.</P>
    <P>I cannot agree with Senator Lenihan in regard to the hysteria about drunken drivers.  I think it is a lamentable situation that because a man is drunk in charge of this lethal weapon, he cannot at once be taken off the road by whatever means we have.  Perhaps we could take them off the road and lock them up for the time being.  That would be a kind thing to do.  I think they should be removed from the road at once and any quibbles as to whether they are or are not drunk and whether they prove in law that they are drunk or sober is a very unimportant matter when it is suspected by a Garda.  In this case, I would be with the Garda 100 per cent.  If the Gardaí have the slightest suspicion that a person is not competent to drive a vehicle, I say that he should be removed from the road at that moment.  What happens to the person after that is another day's work.  The technicalities of knowing what quantity of alcohol a person has in his bloodstream is a very unimportant point, when you consider the dangers to other people on the road.</P>
    <P>The rights of the individual are very much discussed in this country, but the individual in this case is a menace to other individuals.  I doubt very much that we will get in a short time to the point of having all this technical examination of the blood and all the rest of it.  I hope we do; I hope we will perfect the system whereby there will be no legal or technical difficulty in regard to a person driving under the influence of drink.</P>
    <P>In the meantime, I certainly would <Col N="1026" /> agree that if the Gardaí have any doubt whatever about a person being incapable of driving, that person should be stopped from driving at once.  We will have other opportunities to discuss this.  Just now, that is all I have to say except to congratulate the Minister and express the hope he will be able to improve the conditions on our roads by this new measure.</P>
    <Speaker pid="SeanOGrady" hpid="Mr. O'Grady Mr. O'Grady">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Grady</NameTxt>
      <P>Like the previous speaker, I, too, would disagree very strongly with the views expressed by my colleague, Senator Lenihan, on the question of drunken driving.  In my opinion, a man who drives a car while drunk or under the influence of drink is a potential murderer and, as Senator Mrs. Dowdall pointed out, should not be permitted to continue with the murderous engine in his hands.  Last year, I understand that 300 were killed on the roads in this country.  I do not know how many may have been killed by drunken drivers or if any at all were killed by these people.  Four thousand others were seriously injured.  It is a very serious situation.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>With regard to punishment, a man who can afford the luxury of getting drunk before he starts motoring does not mind a fine of £5 or even £10. To some of these gentlemen who have money to burn, that is no deterrent.  They will go out from the court and start off again.  Something will have to be done.  If this new system of testing the blood will ease that situation we shall be very pleased.  I should also like to point out that even a small quantity of alcohol has an injurious effect on the brain.  I daresay it differs with the capacity of different individuals.  Some people may be able to take a lot of it.  We all remember the case of the lady driver who was found drunk under a car in Lucan.  When a Garda found her, she said: &ldquo;Hello, Catswhiskers&rdquo; to him.  That was her response to the Garda.  She admitted having taken 18 glasses of brandy.  I do not know the price of a glass of brandy but I think it is 5/-.  Eighteen glasses would <Col N="1027" /> cost £4 10s.  She was imposing a little fine on herself to make her funny but she was capable of doing a lot of damage.</P>
    <P>I do not want to single out the ladies; I am sure that that would be an exceptional case.  One will meet perhaps 100 and more men under the influence for every one of the opposite sex.  A fine, in my opinion, in such a case is just a way of letting off the wealthy man.  The poor man, for a lesser offence, might have to go to jail if he could not afford to pay the fine.</P>
    <P>I am afraid I would be a very poor justice if I had to decide cases.  I am afraid I would be violently prejudiced against the man brought before me on a charge of drunken driving or half-drunken driving.  One needs all one's wits nowadays on congested roads in cities and towns.  Some towns have old, narrow streets.  Take my native Ennis, for instance.  It is much easier to drive in the worst traffic jam in Dublin than in some of the streets of my native place.  A person would want to know his geography in order to avoid an accident there, even when he is stone cold sober.</P>
    <P>The trouble about this Bill is that with the tremendous number of sections, we would all want to start going to school again before we could have the vaguest idea of all the implications involved.  There are many people who commit offences with regard to traffic lights and movement against traffic lights.  Senator Hayes mentioned a driver coming across from the left-hand side, after passing the traffic lights, and turning right.  I do not think a driver is correct to come along at speed and then turn right after the traffic lights.  It could lead to a very serious accident if another driver happened to be coming in the opposite direction and was unaware of the approach from the left.</P>
    <P>I agree that everyone driving a car will, as it were, have to commence school all over again and make themselves familiar with the various sections of this Bill and other legislation which has been in force in the past so as to avoid accidents on the road <Col N="1028" /> I which are taking such an awful toll of life in modern times.  Perhaps it might be worse in more densely populated countries than here but, with our small population, the loss of 300 people is a terrible tragedy.</P>
    <P>We all welcome this new measure. We hope that, as a result of the measure, with the co-operation of the Gardaí and in particular, of the legal fraternity, very beneficial results will follow.  I admit I might be prejudiced, but to my mind, the legal fraternity are always inclined to be on the side of the Good Samaritan.  Take a man charged with driving under the influence.  If the Gardaí prove substantially that he has taken more than he should have to be on the road, the district justice might have another point of view on it and let that man off with a slight fine.  I do not think that should be permissible.</P>
    <P>Another thing is that in different courts different fines are imposed for the same kind of offence.  I dread going home at night at a late hour from this House.  Immediately around certain public houses, both sides of the road are lined with cars, even at 11 p.m., 11.30 p.m., and later, to the danger of every motorist passing on a legitimate journey.</P>
    <Speaker pid="EoinRyan2" hpid="Mr. Ryan Mr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>I should like to welcome this Bill and to congratulate the Minister on the manner in which he has introduced it.  I refer to the White Paper he issued some time ago to give everybody interested in this problem an opportunity of studying what was proposed in the Bill and of making proposals of their own.  I refer also to the manner in which he met amendments suggested in the Dáil and the many amendments he made in an effort to meet various points of view.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>This Bill is badly required.  Having regard to the constant increase in the number of vehicles on the roads and to the increasing speed of these vehicles, it is very important that every effort should be made to keep the roads as safe as possible for those using vehicles of all kinds and for pedestrians.  Although a great deal has been done to make the road safer <Col N="1029" /> by giving us better roads, wider roads, dual carriageways, the removal of corners, and so on&mdash;although all that is very important and has done a great deal of good&mdash;it is far more important that there should be very strict measures as to the manner in which vehicles are controlled.</P>
    <P>Provision for a driving test is essential.  I understand it will be restricted for the time being to new drivers and possibly those who have been convicted of certain offences.  I suggest&mdash;it would be possible under the Bill as it stands&mdash;in relation to anybody who shows by his driving, without necessarily committing a specific offence, that he is a potential danger on the roads, that a member of the Garda should be empowered to require him to submit to a test within 30 days or something like that and, if he has not passed the test within that time, that his licence should be revoked.  It might be necessary to provide for an appeal to the district court by the person concerned if he felt the demand by the Garda authorities was unreasonable. It would induce people to be very careful in their driving if they felt that, apart from being convicted of an offence, they were liable at any time to be asked to undergo a driving test.</P>
    <P>When I say I welcome driving tests, I think that by far the most important part of the driving test is the test as to whether the person is familiar with the rules of the road and whether he realises there are certain conventions and certain courtesies to be observed.  By and large, we have not many bad drivers in the sense of people who cannot drive a car.  Any intelligent person can become competent to drive, but unfortunately we have a great number of drivers who are unfamiliar with the rules of the road and completely unaware of the fact that they have obligations, for example, to give way to other traffic in certain circumstances and that even in certain circumstances, if there is a particular rule, they should still give way in order to avoid the possibility of an accident or a dangerous situation developing. It is often the good driver, the man <Col N="1030" /> who has been driving for ten, 15 or 20 years, who might make an excellent racing driver in the sense of being competent to drive, who seems to be completely unaware of the rules of the road and that there are certain courtesies and conventions to be observed: He is unaware that he has an obligation to other users of the road, apart merely from getting from point A to point B.</P>
    <P>For that reason, something on the line I suggest, asking a person to submit to a test if he shows he is not aware of these rules, is something which would make him much more careful when driving.  One thing which a person who has been driving for a long time dreads more than anything else is the possibility of having to undergo a test.</P>
    <P>The Minister in his opening speech said that it was intended to have a publicity campaign to familiarise the public with the contents of the Bill and generally with the rules of the road.  I was glad to hear that.  It will go a long way towards meeting the problem I have mentioned, of people who are not aware of, or not willing to comply with, road courtesies and so on.</P>
    <P>I should like to ask the Minister to comment on two points.  One is that compulsory insurance applies only to third parties and does not apply to passengers in a car.  My experience in the courts has been that passengers are very often the victims of accidents and are injured in accidents.  Arising from the fact that there is no compulsory passenger insurance, if a passenger finds that the motorist was not insured and attempts to make a claim with the Motor Insurers Bureau, he finds that the agreement with the Minister for Local Government and the Motor Insurers Bureau applies only in cases in which passenger insurance is in operation. This means that a passenger would have no claim against the bureau for personal injuries.  I am sure there are many reasons for and against this, but I should like the Minister to comment on the reasons which induced him not to make a change in this respect.</P>
    <P>The second point may be covered by <Col N="1031" /> one of the sections dealing with the inspection of vehicles.  It is in regard to such vehicles as mechanically propelled agricultural implements of one kind or another which appear on our roads.  There is one implement which is used for lifting haycocks and which has five or six huge spikes sticking out at the rear.  Every time I see one of them on the road and let my imagination run riot, I visualise the most horrible accidents occurring and the terrible injuries involved if anybody ran into one of them, not so much in a motor car, where they would have some protection, but on a bicycle or a motor cycle.  It seems to me that some regulation should prohibit the use of a vehicle of that kind on the highway without some sort of guard or protection to prevent it from causing damage in the event of anybody colliding with it.  That is all I wish to say, except to congratulate the Minister on the Bill.</P>
    <Speaker pid="GeraldLEstrange" hpid="Mr. L'Estrange Mr. L'Estrange">
      <NameTxt>Mr. L'Estrange</NameTxt>
      <P>I welcome the Bill and wish to congratulate the Minister on its introduction.  I think it is long over-due.  We all admit that an up-to-date code is necessary in present-day conditions and the need for this legislation is beyond question.  We heard the Minister state that even last year, in round figures, there were 300 fatal accidents and 4,000 involving personal injuries on our roads.  I do not agree with Senator Lenihan when he refers to mass hysteria.  As a matter of fact, I am inclined to think that our attitude to road accidents is a most shocking indictment of our present age.  Road accidents are too often the results of drunken driving and the result of idiotic and bad behaviour by both drivers and pedestrians.  Unfortunately today there are many people who seem to have little regard for the Fifth Commandment, &ldquo;Thou shalt not kill.&rdquo; Many human lives are snuffed out and limbs broken through the careless use of modern vehicles.  I looked up some statistics recently and I found that from 1921 to 1959, the number of deaths in world air disasters totalled 5,090 and the number of deaths from earthquakes totalled 307,756.  The <Col N="1032" /> number of fatal road accidents in Britain was 201,000 for the same period.  The estimate for Europe was 1,000,000 and for the United States of America 1,190,000 and here in our own country it is reckoned that between 5,000 and 5,500 people have been killed since 1921.  That is a serious problem and a problem which should be faced up to immediately.  If things are to continue as they are at present, at least 300 more people who are alive today, in full health and vigour, will be in their graves before this day 12 months; 300 families will be bereaved and many will have lost their breadwinner. Over 4,000 more people will be injured.  We have this dreadful waste of life and loss of money.</P>
      <P>In the Twenty Six counties we have over 300,000 vehicles.  The Minister may have the correct figure, but I think it is roughly 300,000.  Over 335,000 people, I think, have driving licences.  Due to the closing down of the branch lines, more traffic is thrown on the roads: more lorries, buses, cars, motor cycles&mdash;and I think the number of auto-cycles in the past couple of years must have increased by 200 or 300 per cent.  As I say, I suppose the Minister will have the correct figure.</P>
      <P>We all know that when the amount of traffic on the roads increases, the risk to life and limb increases accordingly. Unfortunately, many of our roads were not made for the big buses, the lorries and the huge trailers we see on them at the present time.  In fact, I suppose we could say that this increase in traffic has made the introduction of this Bill mandatory, if we are to deal effectively with lawbreakers and prevent deaths on our roads in future.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I agree with Senator Mrs. Dowdall that we must educate our people and have a proper code of rules and good road manners.  I have advocated in this House before that there should be some form of small booklet setting out the road code, the rules and regulations and the &ldquo;dos&rdquo; and &ldquo;don'ts&rdquo; of the road traffic code, with a place into which the driving licence can be slipped.  The Gardaí have authority <Col N="1033" /> under this Bill to stop a person and question him on the road code.</P>
    <P>We must try to change the mental attitude of our people towards this whole problem.  We must try to impress on our people that if everyone took more care on our roads, we could perhaps prevent 30, 40 or 50 per cent. of the deaths that are taking place on our roads today.  We must try to impress on our motorists that if they drink, they should definitely not drive, and that if they have a defective car, they should not take it on the road but bring it to the nearest garage and have it put into a proper state of repair.  We should try to impress on drivers that they should not drive at excessive speeds, no matter what hurry, they are in, and that it is better to be five minutes late than to be the late John Citizen. We should impress on them also that they should not pass on bends.</P>
    <P>Travelling the roads today, as Senator Hayes said, you will find small cars travelling at very excessive speeds. I drive a reasonably big car that can do a very fast speed.  I suppose my car is capable of doing 80 m.p.h.  I usually drive at between 50 and 55 m.p.h. and I am passed by six-horse-power cars which leave me standing on the road, so to speak. They are doing anything from 70 to 75 m.p.h. but if there is an accident and they appear in the courts, they say they were driving at 30 to 35 m.p.h.</P>
    <P>We should also educate our cyclists. They should have lights on their bicycles and, in their own interests more than anyone else's, they should definitely have reflectors on their machines&mdash;and a very good reflector at that.  When driving at night, and especially when meeting another car, it is very hard to see a cyclist if he has not got a proper reflector fitted to his bicycle.  In addition, when meeting cars, they should keep as near as possible to their own side of the road.</P>
    <P>We should also try to educate pedestrians.  We all know they have their rights on the roads, but as well as having rights, they have duties and <Col N="1034" /> responsibilities to other users of the roads.  Jay-walking is a danger to themselves and to others.  Everyone, motorists, cyclists and pedestrians, should know the highway code.</P>
    <P>School children should be taught the highway code at least in so far as it affects pedestrians.  I have to admit that I do not think I know which is the proper side of the road to walk on. I know that I meet children coming from one school walking on the left hand side of the road, and coming from another school walking on the right hand side.  These are things that should be taught in our national schools.</P>
    <P>I am sorry I cannot agree with Senator Lenihan.  I agree with the Senator who said that drunken drivers are potential murderers.  I agree that drunken drivers should and must be put off the roads.  A far greater percentage of accidents is due to drunken driving than people care to admit.  I knew young men who were killed in car accidents because they were under the influence of drink.  That fact did not come out because no one wanted the parents to think their son had been killed while under the influence of drink.  It is a well-known fact in this country that if a man is killed due to the consumption of alcohol, or due to the fact that he is under the influence of drink, that fact does not come out.  Perhaps that is right in the interests of the relatives, but it is done in any case.  A great percentage of the accidents which come in to the courts are due to people taking too much to drink.</P>
    <P>The law should be enforced without fear or favour, no matter who the culprit is, whether it is a rich man or a poor man who is involved and irrespective of whether or not he is in a good position.  Unfortunately, the law is not being enforced throughout the length and breadth of the country.  Even our police authorities are afraid to apprehend certain people who are in well-paid positions and have pull, as it is known.  There are too many people who say: &ldquo;I will see so-and-so, the T.D.; or I will see so-and-so, the Senator.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>I have been approached by a few <Col N="1035" /> people but I can say that never in my life have I gone to the Minister for Justice, a Garda superintendent or any one like that, on behalf of anyone with drink taken who was concerned in an accident, but I know people who have drink taken and have been in accidents and they have been able to get out of it because of political pull.  That is completely wrong and I hope we will hear no more of it in future.</P>
    <P>Senator Lenihan talked about mass hysteria and said it was easier now to get a conviction for drunken driving than it was some years ago.  In 1959, 479 people were charged with being drunk in charge, or attempting to drive while drunk, and the percentage of convictions was less than 10 per cent. or 12 per cent.  Last year, 535 people were brought to court for driving or attempting to drive while drunk. Again, the number of convictions was very small.  The police are almost afraid to do their duty to bring people to court because there is such an attack made upon them by solicitors and counsel for the defence in respect of those who are under the influence of drink that one often thinks it is the policeman who is in the dock and not the man who is charged with crime. That is completely wrong.  Everyone who uses the road, whether the driver of a car, a pedestrian or cyclist, is under a heavy duty to take reasonable care.  If that reasonable care were taken by all and if the law were enforced as it should be enforced and as I hope it will be enforced in the future, I think we could prevent 50 per cent of the accidents that take place today.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PadraigOSiochfhradha" hpid="Pádraig Ó Siochfhradha Pádraig Ó Siochfhradha">
      <NameTxt>Pádraig Ó Siochfhradha</NameTxt>
      <P>Maraon leis na daoine eile, ba mhaith liom comhgáirdeachas a dhéanamh leis an Aire mar gheall ar an mBille seo a thúirt ós ár gcóir.  Tá súil agam go n-éireoidh leis.  Is fada atá gá leis an mBille see.  Tá riachtanas ann le rialú agus riarú ar lucht gluaisteáin ar neithe eile agus ar dhaoine ar na bóithre.  D'fhás an riachtanas sin go h-an-mhear ar fad ó méadaíodh uimhir na gcaranna, na ngluaisteán agus na gléasanna eile iompair ar na bóithre.  Níor ghluais an dlí chomh <Col N="1036" /> tapaidh leis an méadú a tháinig ar an mbaol a d'fhás as sin.  Ach tá san mBille see, measaim, soláthar maith dhá dhéanamh chun rial agus smacht éigin a chur ar neithe a bhaineann leis an obair atá i gceist againn.</P>
      <P>Ar dtúis, is dóigh liomsa gur gá an-mhéid oiliúna do lucht tiomána, oiliúnt ar an inneall atá dhá thiomáint acu, oiliúint ar an tslí is sábháilte chun an bóthar a chur díobh gan dochar do dhaoine eile agus oiliúint ar gach duine chun iad féin a iompair agus a chosaint ar dhochar nó díobháil a dhéanamh dá chéile nó dóibh féin. Tá riachtanas ann an teagasc sin go léir a chur ar fáil.  Ní hiad amháin lucht tiomána a chaithfidh an teagasc sin d'fháil ach an pobal ar fad, pobal siúl an bhóthair, pobal gluaisteáin, pobal gléasraí eile agus fiú amháin pobal le h-ainmhithe agus chúrsaí eile a bhaineann le bealaigh agus le bóithre na tíre.</P>
      <P>Tuigim san mBille seo gur ar na daoine a bheidh ag lorg ceadúnais a éileófar triail nó teastanna.  Is trua liomsa a rá gur dóigh liom go bhfuil sé fíor-riachtanach an triail sin a chur ar a lán daoine atá ag tiomáint ghluaisteán leis na blianta.  Tá siad chomh neamh-chúramach sin, chomh lán de thoirtéis go bhfuil gluaisteán acu, go gceapann siad gur féidir leo imeacht leo ar fíbín ar fuaid bailte na tíre.  Do chuirfinnse triail orthu an chéad lá eile a raghaidis amach ar na bóithre agus na daoine a shábháil ar an mbaol a dheineailn siad don phobal.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Maidir le lucht siúil ar na bóithre is rí-mhinic gurb iad sin fé ndeara cuid den olc.  Deineann siad neamh-chúram den ghluaisteán a thagann ina ndiaidh nó rompa le barr faillí.  Faoin dteideal deireanach sin do chuirfinn leanaí gan eolas, leanaí óga a bhíonn ar fuaid na mbóithre agus sna bailte móra.  Beidh sé deacair oiliúint a thúirt dóibh conas iad féin a chosaint, conas aithint go bhfuil daoine ag gabháil an tslí nach bhfuil chomh mór fé smacht agus atá siad féin.  Sin é an rud is deacaire i gceist na h-oiliúna, na daoine óga gan chiall atá fé mar a bheadh caoirigh gan chiall, nó ainmhithe beaga gan chiall agus a dheineann an rud díchéille nuair a thagann rud go hobann <Col N="1037" /> orthu.  Cuireann siad lad féin i mbaol agus ní hamháin sin ach cuireann siad lucht tiomána i mbaol.  Sin iad na neithe a chaithfear a scrúdú agus oiliúint agus gnó poiblí a dhéanamh den oiliúint sin i leith na gluaiseachta see ar na bóithre.</P>
    <P>Caithfear ní eile a mheas agus a scrúdú.  Baineann sé seo go mór le bailte móra agus áiteanna a bhfuil pobal mór sa tír.  Is minic ná tugtar am do dhuine dul treasna bóthair. Tagann gluaisteán ar luas 30 nó 40 míle san uair agus na daoine aosta nó na daoine nach bhfuil lú na ngéag go ró-oilte acu, mo dhalta féin, ní tugtar am dóibh an treasna a chríochnú. Is minic san gcathair nach bhfanann roint gluaisteán go dtí go mbíonn an treasna glanta ag daoine in aon chor ach a luaithe a bhíonn slí siúd leo ar fíbín gan tuiscint ró-mhaith acu do néaróga na ndaoine.</P>
    <P>Tá rud amháin maidir le bealaigh treasna sna bailte.  Is minic a sílim gur mór an trua gan teagasc ar leith a thúirt mar gheall air.  Bíonn líon caranna lastiar dá chéile gach ceann acu ag feitheamh le hathrú na soillsí. Is minic ná bíonn an ceann deireanach imithe thar an treasna nuair a thagann athrú soilse arís a stopann cuid desna caranna a bhíonn sa líne.</P>
    <P>Anois, deartear liom i gcathaireacha eile go bhfuil nós múinte ag lucht gluaisteáin nuair atá siad ag feitheamh laistiar de solas.  Nuair athríonn an solas, gluaiseann an sreath caranna ar fad ag an am céanna.  Níl sé sin mar nós annseo.  Gluaiseann an chéad car agus ní thosníonn an tárna char go dtí go bhfuil an chéad ceann 10 nó 20 troigh roimhe agus, mar sin, i ndiadh a chéile.  Ansin, nuair ná bhíonn ach b'féidir sé caranna imithe tríd na soilse, athrítear an dath arís agus bíonn ar an faoileach eile fanúint.</P>
    <P>Dá ngluaiseach an slua iomlán le chéile do bheadh sé ar a gcumas uile go léir dul tríd na soilse.  Do bhéadh fhios acu, freisin, go mbeadh sé contúirteach feitheamh nó stad ag am mar sin agus, sa tslí sin, rachadh siad treasna.  Bíodh sin mar atá, níl an nós sin foluimithe againn i mBaile Átha Cliath ar cuma ar bith.  Ní ghluaiseann an tárna nó an triú car go <Col N="1038" /> dtí go bhfuil an chéad car ag gluaiseacht treasna na soilse.</P>
    <P>Rud eile go mba mhaith liom go ndéanfaí rud éigin faoi isea an glór agus an fothrom ós na caranna agus na rothair gluaiste agus na rudaí eile a dheineann an oiread sin torann agus cliotair agus iad ag gluaiseacht leo.  Tá saghasanna car ann a ghluaiseann ciúin go leor, nach osclann freathracha na spéire leis an torann a dheineann siad; ach tá gluaisteáin eile agus níl na huairlísí ionnta chun an ghlór do bhogadh, go haraithe chuid des na caranna eatroma cosúil leis na cinn a úsáidtear go minic ag rásanna.  Do chuireadh an fothrom a dheineann siad sin mearbheall ar aon duine agus is fíor an rud céanna a rá faoi chuid des na rothair ghluaisteáin agus na &ldquo;scooters&rdquo;, chuid acu níos measa ná car ó thaobh fothrom agus ghlór.</P>
    <P>Do bhíomar ag cainnt faoi séideadh na hadharcha.  Níl sé sin ro olc i mBaile Atha Cliath.  Tá roinnt daoine nach ligeann a lámh ó'n adhare ar chur ar bith.  Deineann siad an oiread fothrom agus is féidir leo chun daoine a scuabadh amach as a slí í dtró is go ndéanfar slí dóibh.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Professor Hayes Professor Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Professor Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>Lá agus oiche.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PadraigOSiochfhradha" hpid="Pádraig Ó Siochfhradha Pádraig Ó Siochfhradha">
      <NameTxt>Pádraig Ó Siochfhradha</NameTxt>
      <P>Lá agus oiche.  Níl aon mhaitheas ann go bhfeiceann siad na daoine ós a gcomhair. Tosaíonn siad ag séideadh na hadharcha chomh cruaidh agus is féidir leo i gcathair nach dóigh liom go mba cheart go mbeadh adharcha á seideadh ar chur ar bith.  Freisean, sílim nach bhfuil sé cheart go mbeadh an ghlór as na hinneall chomh hárd agus atá sé ó roinnt des na carr beaga agus na gluais rothair.  Sin rud a dhéanann muintir na cathrach bodhair.  Bíonn ort do bhéal d'éisteacht má tá tú ag cainnt le haoinne ar thaobh na sráide agus tagann cuid dóibh id threo.  Sin cuid de no rudaí gur dóigh liom go mba chóir féachaint chucha.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Rinneadh trácht d'ól agus an tubaist a dheineann an t-ól i gcursaí tiomáint. Is fíor nach bhfuil aon rud ar bith níos measa ná duine ar meisce ag tiomáint gluaistán agus é ag dul ar fuid an bothair nó na sráideanna.  Is ionan é agus fear meisce a ligint amach ar an <Col N="1039" /> bóthair le inneall-ghunna agus a thosnódh ag caitheamh píléir ar fud na sráide.  Tá an fear eile chomh contúrach leis.  Rachadh cuid des na píléar suas ins an spéir ach ní raghadh an car ins an spéir.</P>
    <P>Is fíor, má deintear scrúdú ar na timpistí a thárlaíonn, nach lad muintir an óil ar fad atá cionntach leis na timpistí ar fad.  Thárlaíonn timpistí do dhaoine nach nólann braon agus tárlófaí sin arís agus tarlófaí sé in ainneoin pé rialacha a dheintear.  Maidir le fear an óil, ní bheadh aon trua agam dó ach pionós a chur air chomh fada agus atá ól tógtha aige agus é i mbun car.  Is trua nár coimeadach an pionós a bhí ins an mBille ar dtus agus nach bhfuil ann anois.  Is marathóil aoinne a rachadh i gear nó a ghluaiseadh tríd na sráideanna ina bhfuil na daoine agus gan é a bheith in dhon an car a smachtú nó a dhiriú nó a choimead amach ó dhaoine.</P>
    <P>Arís, deirim go bhfuil sé fíorriachtannach ar fad an phobal do theagasc ar nósanna tiomáiniochta, dea bhéasa ar na bóithre do mhúineadh dóibh chomh maith le chionas aire a thabhairt dóibh féin&mdash;agus sin é an príomh rud, sílim.  Dá bhrí sin, tá sé riachtanach tosnú leis an teagasc le leanaí scoile agus a dhinne ionntu an baoghal atá ann agus chomh tabhachtach agus atá sé a bheith ag siar fhearrach orthu féin.  Tá na daoine a thiománann gluaisteáin á dhéanamh fá'n dlí agus aoinne atá cionntach i dtionóisc ba chóir é a smachtú agus pionós a chur air.  Caithfear aithne do thabhairt do's na rudaí sin.  Caithfear trácht a dhéanamh dos na nithe sin ins an teagasc.  Tá na contúirt ag méadú in aghaidh na bliana agus tá sé fíor-riachtanach síor-chaint do dhéanamh futha agus don contúirt bás atá ann d'óg agus d'aosta.</P>
    <P>Ní hé sin é an taon rud atá contúirteach. Cimíd gach lá na heitealáin. Gléasanna an-mhaith iad chun daoine a mharú go mear agus go hiomlán. Ach támaíd ag phlé anois rudaí a ritheann ar na bóithre i measc an phobail, áit atámuid ag siúl.  Tá an ceart ag na tiománaighthe usáid a bhaint as na bóithre ach bá chóir go mbeadh aithne acu ar ár gceart freisin. <Col N="1040" /> Freisin, ba chóir go mbeadh deaghbhéasa ag gach aoinne ag dul tríd na sráideanna idir siúileóirí agus tiomáinithe.</P>
    <P>Molaim an Bhille agus an tAire a thug isteach í.  Tá súil agam, nuair a bheidh sé ina Acht, nach mbeidh aon leathscéil ann chun daoine a shaoradh ó smacht an dlí, má tá siad cionntach faoi rialacha an bóthair.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JohnLOSullivan" hpid="Mr. J.L. O'Sullivan Mr. J.L. O'Sullivan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J.L. O'Sullivan</NameTxt>
      <P>I welcome this Bill.  There is no doubt that it was needed and that everybody in this country was alarmed at the number of accidents on the roads day after day. There is no doubt that drink has contributed to a number of accidents on the road.  Everything possible should be done to deter the man who is under the influence of drink from driving. Of course there are other factors which, in my opinion, are also responsible for accidents.  In my opinion, speed is becoming a major cause of accidents.  I entirely agree with Senator L'Estrange that every driving licence issued should be accompanied by a copy of the highway code.  That is very important, especially for youthful drivers who are getting their licences for the first time, and indeed it would be no harm if older drivers referred to it now and again.</P>
      <P>Senator Ryan referred to farm implements which are driven on our roads.  I suppose they will appear in greater numbers as the harvesting season approaches.  I would not like to put any impediment in the way of these implements being driven on the road.  They are very necessary and very costly implements and their owners are contributing heavy taxes to the State.  While I agree that they should be well lighted, I do not think they should be prevented from coming on our roads.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>There is one other matter which I think should be dealt with, that is, the question of trailers attached to big lorries.  We see them every day on our roads.  They are dangerous enough on our main roads but they are more so on minor roads.  In West Cork, where our railway has been taken from us, we have a good example of this and the chief offenders are Córas Iompair Éireann who send lorries and trailers <Col N="1041" /> from Skibbereen to Cork and from Bandon to Cork.  You may see six big lorries with trailers attached to them and motorists are compelled to wait behind them because there are many bends on these roads and they cannot pass out.  The railway line crossed the road at different points and in addition to bends there are bridges and it is nearly impossible to travel this road.</P>
    <P>If C.I.E. are going to retain these big transports&mdash;they look more like trains than the trains themselves&mdash;I would ask the Minister to have the roads straightened out so that people will have an opportunity of travelling along them.  The trailers are responsible for delays on the road. Something should be done immediately before the tourist season starts properly &mdash;and there are prospects in our area that it will be a very good one&mdash;to see that these lorries and trailers are not put on the road indiscriminately.</P>
    <P>I have seen them driving up and down with nothing in them.  I do not know whether that is to illustrate their power or to show that they are available but they will be the cause of very serious accidents.  They may be all right on main roads but they are a public nuisance on the small country road in the district I come from.  I hope that before the tourist season advances much further, at least the trailers will be taken off and the people will have an opportunity to look at the country through which they are passing instead of having to keep an eye on the road all the time.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JohnCole" hpid="Mr. Cole Mr. Cole">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cole</NameTxt>
      <P>I also should like to congratulate the Minister on bringing in this comprehensive Bill and to compliment him on the great patience he showed in the Dáil and which I hope he will show here also.  It is a very necessary Bill but a great many of these regulations already existed in some form or another, and while I do not like to say they were not enforced, I feel they could have been enforced a little more vigorously at times.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>A great many people are unfamiliar with the rules of the road.  My impression is that in the country, 99 times <Col N="1042" /> out of 100, there is nobody there to enforce the regulations and another road user will not report the offending motorist.  I have seen cases of appalling driving especially in areas where a sporting event or a holiday fixture is being held.  There is not very much evidence of Garda cars to enforce the rules and while I do not want to see a series of prosecutions against people, we should have more &ldquo;courtesy cops&rdquo; for a while to warn these people in regard to small points in driving etiquette.  On three occasions recently, I had to stop almost dead to give way to cars which were passing out coming towards me.  That involved cases of older cars which had not got the required speed to pass out more modern cars.  If for six months or 12 months after this Bill has been passed, it were seen that the Minister and the Guards intended to enforce the rules stringently, it would be a good thing.</P>
    <P>I am sorry that in regard to bye-laws, the Minister to a certain extent has disregarded the local authority.  I think the section says that certain bye-laws will be made by the Commissioner after consultation with the local authority. I should have thought that the local authority and the Commissioner together would be quite capable of and more suitable for making local bye-laws than the Department.  Another responsibility has been taken away from the local authorities. A great many local authorities have been actively interested in making bye-laws for their own urban districts and yet, now apparently, they are to be consulted only on what, to my mind, does not matter very much at all.</P>
    <P>In that regard, I should like some explanation from the Minister of Section 86 (9) (d) which relates to stopping places or stands in respect of a route upon which omnibuses are operated and provides:</P>
    <P>a sign or markings provided under or in pursuance of this subsection may be provided on a public road without the consent of the road authority charged with the maintenance of the road;</P>
    <P>It strikes me that could lead to an extraordinary <Col N="1043" /> position in which, say, a private bus company might decide to erect rather showy road signs or markings at stopping places for their buses. I cannot think who would be responsible for limiting the size or the position of those road signs.</P>
    <P>Section 85 fixes the stopping places and stands for buses.  Would the Commissioner have power under that section to prohibit a person from leaving a bus at an unauthorised stopping place?  I am thinking of the cities particularly.  A person might decide that the nearest place, or the easiest place, to home was somewhere between two stopping places and jump from the bus, with the result that a car following would be in great danger of running him down.</P>
    <P>One other matter struck me when Senator O'Sullivan was speaking, and I did not come across it in the Bill. Has the Commissioner power to compel slow moving vehicles to drive at a certain distance from other slow moving vehicles in order that faster moving vehicles may pass them one at a time?  That is very important.  Quite often, you meet two or three slow moving lorries, perhaps with trailers. The drivers stay close together, with the result that if you want to pass, you have to be able to go 100 yards ahead to pass the two or three vehicles together. In other countries there are bye-laws which compel them to drive a certain distance apart in order that an overtaking car can pass them one at a time.</P>
    <P>I agree with what has been said about drunken drivers and the menace they are on the roads.  Perhaps there is a mental attitude in this country against compulsion to a certain extent, but I would urge on the Minister when this Bill becomes an Act to initiate a campaign to get the assistance of the public in dealing with people who are liable to drive while drunk.  In that respect also, there is no reason why we should not approach the publicans, perhaps in a semi-private circular, in an effort to get their assistance also. They could perhaps do a great deal of good by persuading customers that they should not drive their cars or <Col N="1044" /> lorry or whatever it might be.  I would urge on the Minister to initiate a campaign seeking the assistance of as many people as he can in that respect. The other matters with which I wish to deal can be dealt with on Committee Stage.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickQuinlan" hpid="Professor Quinlan Professor Quinlan">
      <NameTxt>Professor Quinlan</NameTxt>
      <P>I welcome this Bill and I congratulate the Minister and his Department on it, under two headings especially.  The first is that the Bill consolidates into one Bill the road traffic regulations.  It does not seek to amend the 1933 Act but presents the whole thing in one Bill.  That is very commendable and it is the type of Bill we like to get, where we can see all the various provisions at one reading, rather than having to chase back to an old Bill which refers to other provisions in a previous Bill.  The Minister is to be heartily congratulated on that.</P>
      <P>Secondly, the Minister is to be congratulated on his approach to the Bill. A special committee was set up and followed by a White Paper, and a very reasonable interval was allowed for representation and discussion.  In that sense, it is a very well explored Bill and one which we feel tackles a very vital problem in a most praiseworthy manner.</P>
      <P>Most of the provisions of the Bill are essentially Committee Stage for discussion purposes.  We all agree with the principle of the Bill.  We all agree with the necessity for tightening up these regulations and taking every measure possible to cut down the death rate on our roads.  Consequently, most of the work will really be done on Committee Stage, but there are just one or two points I should like to raise at this stage.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I welcome the provision with regard to driving tests, but in their administration, I think due regard should be had to older people, retired people and so on, who have been driving for a number of years.  Their faculties may be failing slightly but to be deprived of their right to drive would be a very heavy penalty on them.  I wonder whether it would be possible to have some restricted licence issued to such people, for instance, preventing them <Col N="1045" /> from driving, except in daylight hours, or within a certain number of miles of their homes?</P>
    <P>Secondly, the Bill seems to embody one major concern of traffic that is, the question of traffic signs.  I should like to see very heavy penalties imposed on those who deface such signs.  It is deplorable to see signs turned the wrong way around or, worse still, pulled down and broken. I have it on good authority that it is scarcely possible to get steel plates strong enough to avoid being broken.  In this comprehensive measure, it might be possible to introduce a section dealing specifically with traffic signs or at least with penalties for defacing them.  That would be a very worthwhile addition to our road traffic code.</P>
    <P>On the question of parking meters, we have all seen them operating in other countries, and they seem to be the ideal answer, but a practical engineer with whom I discussed them in our traffic department said: &ldquo;It is all very well, but who is going to stand guard over these meters?  I guarantee if two dozen meters are provided, at the end of one week, a dozen will be out of action.&rdquo;  Again, that calls for very heavy penalties.</P>
    <P>Above all, if we are seeking to educate the public in the rules of the road, part of that education should surely be directed to the young people, and especially to those in the 14 to 18 age group, who very often think it is a high achievement to be able to turn and twist road signs, to work out some means of putting traffic lights out of action, or to prevent parking meters from operating properly.  There is one other point which concerns the question of imprisonment or fine.  I think the amendment brought in by the Minister is very wise in that case.  It was originally intended that imprisonment would be mandatory, in which case there would scarcely be any necessity for the local courts to try the cases.  We must leave the matter to the discretion of the local courts.  There must be varying degrees of offence.  They will sort themselves out into a practice as applied by the district justices in those cases.  It is very wise to leave the option there.</P>
    <P>With regard to the question of overall <Col N="1046" /> speed, it seems to me that a speed of 30 miles per hour in built-up areas is rather low.  Of course, it depends a great deal upon what is meant by a built-up area.  Will a village on a main road count as a built-up area?  Underground crossings for pedestrians along the main roads and in some of the larger towns might be an answer to the problem.</P>
    <P>The other points I have in mind can best be raised on the Committee Stage. I do not wish to take up the time of the House, seeing that Senator Ó Maoláin has an announcement to make on what he wishes to do in regard to the motions.</P>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>I think we should continue.  There are not so many who wish to speak.  Perhaps, we might get an indication of the number?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I think it will be quite all right if the Minister will not be too long.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Professor Hayes Professor Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Professor Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>Does that mean that we adjourn at 10 o'clock?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>We will not be long after 10 o'clock, judging by the indications.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Professor Hayes Professor Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Professor Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>Could we fix a time ?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>I suggest that the Minister could begin his reply at 10 o'clock.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="VictorCarton" hpid="Mr. Carton Mr. Carton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Carton</NameTxt>
      <P>At a quarter to 10.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I think the Minister will be in at a quarter to 10.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanODonovan" hpid="Seán Ó Donnabháin Seán Ó Donnabháin">
      <NameTxt>Seán Ó Donnabháin</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not intend to delay the House, like other speakers. I should like to make a few personal remarks in connection with this Bill. It is a very voluminous document consisting of 91 pages and 127 sections.  It was certainly debated at length in the other House.  I presume there was a greater number of amendments in the other House.  They are more in contact with the people than we are here and we have to bow to their opinions.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1047" />
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Professor Hayes Professor Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Professor Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>That thesis should be combated, Sir.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanODonovan" hpid="Seán Ó Donnabháin Seán Ó Donnabháin">
      <NameTxt>Seán Ó Donnabháin</NameTxt>
      <P>I am commenting on the fact that it has been debated by a greater number of public representatives in the other House.  We will have to take cognisance of that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Professor Hayes Professor Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Professor Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanODonovan" hpid="Seán Ó Donnabháin Seán Ó Donnabháin">
      <NameTxt>Seán Ó Donnabháin</NameTxt>
      <P>I have not read all the Bill, I admit.  I read the accounts in the newspapers but what strikes me is the fact that many members of this House previously forcefully objected to legislation by regulation, order and bye-law.  When this voluminous document becomes law, there will be a vast collection of bye-laws, regulations and orders.  I am afraid we will find it difficult in future to interpret the law as far as road traffic is concerned.</P>
      <P>Fatal accidents hit the headlines always.  There are many accidents which might have been fatal and in respect of which no proceedings were taken.  The accidents that do not happen are far more numerous than the ones that happen.  One such accident happened to myself.  I want to refer to one difficulty.  Part IV concerns speed limits.  Section 44 does not refer to any speed limit generally.  The Minister may make regulations.  I understand that there is no speed limit at present.  You can go 100 miles an hour or more, if your car is capable of that speed.  The Bill only provides for the making of regulations governing speed limits generally.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Section 45 says that there shall be a speed limit of 30 miles per hour in respect of all public roads in built-up areas.  Candidly, that worries me a bit.  Are we doing the right thing?  A speed of 30 miles per hour is too slow. Were we to drive at 35 miles an hour, it would not contribute to any more accidents than travelling at 25 miles per hour or 30 miles per hour.  I have experience of driving through Belfast and the northern counties where there is this 30 miles per hour regulation. They have it in Britain also.  We find it hard to keep to that regulation here. I found it very difficult to keep a check <Col N="1048" /> on the places where you were to drive within the 30 miles.  I want to have here the liberty to drive at a greater speed.  The Clontarf road is a bit of a speed track.  It is a built-up area. Driving along there, I think we would all be held up for driving at a greater speed than 30 miles per hour.</P>
    <P>I think it would be difficult to designate a speed in built-up areas.  A speed of 30 miles an hour is slow.  It will not provide any greater safety than a speed of 35 miles per hour.  In the centre of the city, one has to drive at five, ten and fifteen miles an hour, but in the other case I think it will be difficult to impose that limit on all of us.</P>
    <P>My other point is in relation to travelling at night.  I abhor driving at night against on-coming traffic with headlights glaring or with headlights dimmed.  I suggest that nobody should be allowed to drive at more than 50 miles an hour at night.  You have a certain control over your car when you are travelling at 30 or 40 miles an hour. Anybody driving above that speed cannot stop within the time requisite to prevent an accident, after passing on-coming vehicles with glaring lights.  I know people say that one's lights are the best signal at night and that, unless there are cattle on the road, there is then no danger of people or vehicles crossing the road.  With the mounting speed of vehicles and the increased numbers of them on the roads, I recommend the Minister to consider a limit of 50 miles.  In that way, anybody going from Dublin to Cork can say: &ldquo;I have such and such a distance to travel.  I may not travel at a faster speed than 50 miles per hour.  I can regulate the time and start accordingly.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>People drive shockingly fast on the road at night, depending on their lights. I got a shock myself on one occasion when passing a very high lorry with, I think, the lights full on.  As I passed, I had my headlights dipped.  Immediately after passing the vehicle, I switched on my headlights as quickly as possible and saw two children walking on the road within 30 yards of my car.  If I had been going fast, I could not have avoided an accident.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="1049" /> These are the serious suggestions that I make&mdash;that the 35 niiles or 30 miles per hour speed limit in the built-up areas is low and that anybody driving at night on an open road should be limited to 50 miles per hour.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MaryDavidson" hpid="Miss Davidson Miss Davidson">
      <NameTxt>Miss Davidson</NameTxt>
      <P>Every thinking citizen must welcome this Bill.  It is the first Traffic Act since 1933, I think, and the traffic on the roads to-day bears no relation to the traffic in 1933.</P>
      <P>The Bill should go a long way to make the roads safer but, as Senator L'Estrange has said, until the drunken driver is forced off the roads, we cannot feel completely safe, either as pedestrians or as drivers.  I would, therefore, support his plea for the severest possible penalties which the law permits in cases of drunken driving.</P>
      <P>There are many incompetent drivers on the roads and the enforcement of the driving tests should take care of them.  I do not know what form the tests will take but I would ask that some knowledge of what takes place under the bonnet of the car should be expected.</P>
      <P>Anyone in the habit of travelling by car in this city will agree that there is much driving without consideration of other road users or, in other words, that the bad manners of many motorists contribute greatly to accidents and near accidents.</P>
      <P>By education and propaganda, motorists must be trained into having more consideration for both pedestrians and their fellow motorists. Where there is dangerous driving due to a disregard of ordinary good manners in the use of a car, whether there is an accident or not, heavy fines should be imposed.  I suggest that part of such fines should be used to give special lessons in road drill to children and to issue propaganda leaflets to schools.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>There are many small items in regard to car fittings that the Minister could keep an eye on.  There is the big showy car, carrying lights like a travelling circus.  When the brakes of such cars are applied, or when the searchlight indicators are switched on, the motorist following in a more <Col N="1050" /> modest model is blinded and remains in that condition for a few seconds and, on the roads to-day, seconds are vital.</P>
    <P>Some attempt should be made to standardise lighting systems as these can be a cause of accidents.  The same thing applies to indicators&mdash;some cars have them placed high and others low and it is often difficult to see quickly when a car is making a turn, particularly when the driver fails to give the signal in good time.</P>
    <P>Senator O'Sullivan mentioned speeding as a dangerous practice.  I am sure the Minister travels the Stillorgan-Dún Laoghaire road on occasion; if he does, he will know what a speed track looks like even if he never saw Brooklands.</P>
    <P>I do not know if the Minister controls crossings but I would ask that there should be more pedestrian crossings on the road I have mentioned.  I have waited very long periods, having alighted from a bus, but there was no possibility of crossing because of the endless stream of cars, none of which would pull up to allow anyone to cross. This is ordinary evening traffic, but when there are races in the vicinity, the situation is even worse.  There have been several fatal accidents at the particular part of the road I have in mind, that is, near Brewery Road, quite close to a school which caters for deaf children.</P>
    <P>The Bill, if it is enforced, should do much to reduce the slaughter on the roads and I heartily support it.</P>
    <Speaker pid="LouisWalsh" hpid="Mr. Louis Walsh Mr. Louis Walsh">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Louis Walsh</NameTxt>
      <P>Like other speakers, I should like to compliment the Minister on this excellent piece of traffic legislation which is badly required. We must protect our society by sterner methods due to the increased number of mechanical vehicles on our roads which probably is indicative of the higher standard of living of our people in the past few years.  At any rate, there are one or two sections of the Bill which I am particularly glad the Minister has brought in.  I refer to the question of speed in built-up areas.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The Minister and I have considerable knowledge of driving through a part of our territory which is not yet under <Col N="1051" /> the control of the Department of Local Government.  We realise how fast we drive when we have to reduce the speed to 30 miles per hour when passing through these towns and villages. Senator Ó Donnabháin seems to feel that 30 miles per hour is too low.  I think it is a good guide to us that we are driving too fast.  I am quite satisfied that, in consequence of the reduction of speed which takes place in these towns and villages, fewer accidents are taking place.</P>
    <P>One of the troubles in the country today is the fact that there are not sufficient places for parking cars in our towns and in our villages.  We can see, for instance, the number of towns in which it is an infringement of the law to park a car within 30 feet of a road junction.  The reason for that is that there is nowhere else for the car to go.</P>
    <P>I feel there is considerable delay on the part of the Commissioner of the Gárda and sometimes on the part of the members of an urban district council in bringing in the necessary by-laws to provide that parking shall not take place in streets which are too narrow.  In one provincial town which I pass through very frequently, the street is exceedingly narrow but cars are parked on both sides of it.  Sometimes that leads to traffic jams and considerable delay in passing through.</P>
    <P>I feel that if responsibility rests with the members of an urban district council, who are business people to a fair extent, because they do not want to divert trade from their premises or because they wish to encourage the farming community to come and park as conveniently as possible to their premises, there will be undue delay in bringing in these necessary regulations to provide car parks.  The Minister in this Bill has made provision whereby money from the Road Fund can be diverted for the provision of car parks. I should like the Minister to encourage local authorities to make alternative sites available as soon as possible for car parks.</P>
    <P>I am very glad the Minister has relented about getting courts to inflict <Col N="1052" /> prison sentences for infringements of certain sections of the Bill.  I feel, like other Senators, that the court should have this discretion and that they are as capable of deciding as any member of this House.  They have all the facts before them and they are trained lawyers and will do the right thing. The disqualification of a licence is very often just as great a hardship as being sentenced to jail for one month.</P>
    <P>There are many people who require to drive vehicles in order to earn their livelihood and I am particularly pleased that there is provision now for appeals to the court after a certain period of time and that there is provision for the court to remove the disqualification, if it thinks fit.  It was undesirable that this power should be in the hands of the Minister for Justice because at times people suggested that political influence was being used.  The court is the proper authority for dealing with this matter.</P>
    <P>I hope there will be some provision whereby dimming will be mandatory, apart from the present provision requiring dimming appliances to be affixed to a vehicle.  There is no doubt that on many occasions at night, drivers, and particularly lorry drivers, do not dim as often as they should and sometimes serious accidents take place as a result.  I am glad that the registered owner of a vehicle will now be responsible for infringements of parking regulations.  Up to this it was often difficult to prove who was the person who had done the actual parking and consequently the Guards were not in a position to bring the offender to court.</P>
    <P>Under these regulations, the registered owner will be responsible and for that reason, there should be a considerable improvement in regard to parking offences.  I would be very anxious to see that when these parking regulations are brought in accommodation for parking will be provided.  There is no point in bringing in regulations that cannot be put into force.</P>
    <P>Senator Ó Donnabháin stated that people who drive at over 50 miles an hour at night should be prosecuted.  It would be very difficult to detect such an offence and I do not believe in <Col N="1053" /> bringing in legislation which cannot be I enforced.</P>
    <P>In regard to disqualification or jail sentences for offences under this Bill, if it appears that the Guard who brings the offender to court will be responsible for that person losing his licence or being put in jail, then he may turn a blind eye.  We all know that medical people have a certain bias in favour of the defendant because they realise that on their evidence may depend whether a person's licence will be endorsed. Therefore, if the discretion is not left to the court, if it depends on the person who has to give evidence, on which evidence the individual may lose his livelihood or be put in prison, too many people may be allowed to infringe the law without being brought to justice.  For that reason, I am pleased that the mandatory sections which the Minister originally proposed to bring in are not now to be implemented.</P>
    <P>I do not think that imprisonment is a good thing if it can be avoided.  It has a demoralising effect because people sent to jail have to mix with evil associates.  Jail is only a deterrent for those who have never been there, but once people have been sent to jail, they have a habit of going back again. If you look at statistics you will see that a number of people in jail at the moment have been there on many occasions.  The only other effect that jail has is to reform and from what I have stated, I do not think that people are reformed by being sent to jail. Therefore, disqualification is sufficiently severe in most cases.  I hope that regulations will be brought in at the earliest possible moment and that in consequences many lives will be saved, that fewer people will be injured and consequently that motor insurance premiums will eventually be reduced.</P>
    <Speaker pid="NeilTCBlaney" hpid="Mr. Blaney Mr. Blaney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Blaney</NameTxt>
      <P>I must say I am very gratified indeed to find that the general attitude towards this measure has been a welcoming one, in principle, at any rate, if not in regard to exact detail. Quite a few points have been raised but one which was common to many of the speakers was in regard to enforcement and the feeling that this measure, if not properly enforced, would be a <Col N="1054" /> waste of time.  I can assure the House that those are my sentiments and that I would feel that my time had been much more wasted than the time of the good people here if in fact, through lack of enforcement, the measure were to fall into disuse and disrespect.  So strongly did I believe this that it was almost a condition of my bringing in this measure that I got from the Minister for Justice, on behalf of the Garda, a very definite assurance that there would be full co-operation by the Garda and full enforcement by the Garda of this measure when enacted by the Oireachtas.  With that assurance, I am fully satisfied that the fears expressed here this evening are groundless.</P>
      <P>Another matter which has been mentioned by quite a few Senators is the need for the education of road users, and the existence of so much ignorance in the use of the roads.  Let me say straight away that while we all seem to think of the vehicle drivers when we talk of road traac and the traffic laws, there are many others who use the roads and misuse them as frequently and, indeed, more frequently than do the vehicle drivers.  I suppose that is only natural because a mechanically propelled vehicle, be it a bus, car, scooter or motor cycle, is a very dangerous weapon and indeed a lethal weapon in the hands of one who is not careful or considerate of other road users.  We are all inclined to talk of road traffic, enforcement and infringements as if these infringements and abuses were solely the responsibility of the drivers of vehicles.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Without any doubt, there is a great deal of ignorance of the rules of the road, no matter what anyone says. There is no question whatsoever about that.  I do not hold myself out as knowing the rules of the road as well as I should.  As one who has driven quite a lot on the roads, I would go so far as to say that not one person out of five in the country knows the rules of the roads as prescribed by our-present regulations.  If we are to eradicate that general ignorance of our road code, we must look to the younger generation now coming up.  In their own interests, they should be <Col N="1055" /> instructed in the road code at a very tender age.  They should be taught in the schools, no matter how young they may be.  It is never too early for them to start learning to look after themselves and to have regard to other road users as they grow up.</P>
    <P>If we are to make headway in that direction, and headway we must make if we are to improve the present situation of abysmal ignorance of the road code, the proper place and the lasting place to make the first big effort is in the minds of the young, to make them aware of their responsibilities not only in regard to their own safety but in consideration of the safety of others as they go through life.  Various efforts will be made to try to educate the rest of us but, at this stage, our minds are not as impressionable as the minds of young people still at school.  Every possible effort will be made, and indeed we are looking forward to the introduction of our own television service which will be an excellent medium for education for the young and the not so young.  They will see on their own television screens how they should behave and are expected to behave, as distinct from the manner in which they think they are behaving on our roads today.</P>
    <P>Mention has also been made of the fact that increased traffic seems to have brought increased accidents.  I wonder is the increased number of road users who do not have regard or consideration for other road users the cause of the increase in the number of accidents, rather than the increase in traffic itself?  I believe the misuse of the roads is the cause of the increase in accidents, rather than the actual increase in the number of vehicles.  I do not hold with the argument that the increase in the number of vehicles&mdash; if properly used&mdash;would cause an increase in the number of accidents.</P>
    <P>Senator Ryan raised the question of the Insurance Bureau and wondered whether or not passengers were covered under the agreement with the Bureau. The position at the moment is that passengers other than passengers on public service vehicles are not so covered by the agreement which is in <Col N="1056" /> existence between this Bureau and the insurance companies.  It is possible, of course, that a new agreement may be arrived at, but I think to comment further on what we may expect a new agreement to cover, or hope or feel it should cover, at this juncture would not, possibly, be in the best interests of getting that agreement in a new and advantageous way.  In answer to the question, passengers other than passengers on P.S.V. are not covered by the agreement between the Bureau and the insurance companies.</P>
    <P>I think it was Senator Hayes who mentioned the question of silent zones. The Senator will be glad to know that under Section 11 there is power whereby this matter can be controlled. Senator Hayes, and other Senators also, queried the wisdom of the 30 m.p.h. speed limit.  That speed limit has been regarded as being rather low.  I made a particular point of saying that while there would be a difference of opinion as to whether it was too low or too high, the general consensus of opinion might be that it is too low but that we will have the power to change the limit upwards or downwards, as the case may be.  Of the two courses, I should prefer to start low and move up rather than start high and move down.  From my experience in the towns, villages and cities of the Six Counties&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Professor Hayes Professor Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Professor Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>May I say that, for Dublin, inside the canal bridges in the old city, 30 m.p.h. is certainly right, but outside the canal bridges, there is a doubt.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="NeilTCBlaney" hpid="Mr. Blaney Mr. Blaney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Blaney</NameTxt>
      <P>I am very glad Senator Hayes mentioned that difference because the general opinion was that it was too low.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Professor Hayes Professor Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Professor Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>There is doubt there.  I was thinking of outside the canal bridges.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="NeilTCBlaney" hpid="Mr. Blaney Mr. Blaney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Blaney</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not think it is too low with a limit of 30, 35 or 40 m.p.h. prosecutions will scarcely arise unless the speed limit is actually exceeded by about five miles.  There is that margin of error, or whatever you like to call it, to be added on to the speed limit and it is at that point that you <Col N="1057" /> can expect enforcement to take place. There is no question of bringing anyone to heel for an infringement of .2, .3, .4, or .5 of a mile but when you get to 34 or 35 m.p.h. you will undoubtedly and justifiably get the knock.  That is why I say that 30 m.p.h. is not an unreasonable figure.  From my experience of driving in the Six Counties, that would not be an undue burden on anybody.  There is another point which can be tied in with Senator Hayes's interjection.</P>
      <P>While that would be that general speed limit and while it would be the intention to apply the general speed limit of 30 m.p.h. in the various county boroughs, urban areas and so on, there is power within the framework of the Bill to vary it.  On request and by Ministerial order, the speed limit on an open road within a city can be brought up to 40 miles an hour.  In fact, we will say that a small village on a through traffic route can be brought under the 30, all depending upon the circumstances and the location of the road.  These matters will arise and can be dealt with only after we have applied a general over-all speed in the first instance.  We can then start to deal with the exceptions which might be that in Dublin, outside the canals, there could be a case made for increasing a speed limit of 30 miles an hour.  There may be a road or roads leading into and out of the city where the speed limit with benefit to all, could be increased.  These exceptional cases will be dealt with after we have got going on the over-all application of the 30 miles per hour as the starting point.</P>
      <P>Senator Mrs. Dowdall thought that large trucks were not properly lighted, particularly at the rear and sides.  This is a matter which can and, indeed, will be covered by regulations made under Section 11.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Senator Ryan suggested a procedure that might possibly give rise to abuse. He said that a Garda should be able to require a person thought to be driving badly to undergo a test. Section 28 does enable an officer of the Garda to apply to the courts to disqualify a person in respect of whom that officer considers there are reasonable <Col N="1058" /> grounds for believing that he is incompetent to drive.  The court can, if satisfied, disqualify that person until he has passed his driving test.  That is not quite as direct a method as Senator Ryan sought.  Nevertheless, in a more indirect and possibly in a better safeguarded way for the general public interest, we can get the same end ultimately with recourse to the courts.</P>
    <P>It is the belief and the intention of those of us who are sponsoring this measure to require drivers to be tested in regard to their competency for driving and their knowledge of the rules of the road but it goes without saying that we cannot do it all right away. We have got to start somewhere.  We indicated that we propose starting with the new applicants for driving licences. Possibly, that has something to be said for it and something to be said against it.  My own belief is that we should start with the new applicants rather than pick out a particular group within those who already hold licences and have had experience in the past.</P>
    <P>There will be arguments as to why this category or that category should be taken rather than the new applicants.  The argument will be used that it is not the inexperienced driver who has accidents, the implication being that it is the experienced drivers who do have accidents.  I wonder how many of those who argue thus think of the number of accidents caused indirectly, if not directly, by the incompetent handling of vehicles on the roads by new drivers and persons learning to drive?  How many accidents are caused by those who, if you suggested to them they were doing anything wrong would practically have a fit, who hold, in their belief of self-righteousness, to the righthand edge of the white line in the centre of the road and move at 25 miles per hour whom neither God nor man can shift?  They believe, I have no doubt, that what they are doing is right and proper and if everybody else did likewise, there would be no accidents.  If everybody else did likewise in other spheres, there would not be anything else, either.</P>
    <P>There were a few other points raised which possibly might be of some interest.  Senator O'Sullivan of Cork <Col N="1059" /> mentioned the trailers and the heavy trucks using those much maligned narrow roads of West Cork which are carrying traffic far beyond their capacity as a result of the closing of the railways in that part of the country. The idea that there are C.I.E. lorries with huge trailers more reminiscent of trains than trucks using these roads unnecessarily is something that is beyond me.  I cannot understand that C.I.E., as would appear to the Senator&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    <Speaker pid="JohnLOSullivan" hpid="Mr. J.L. O'Sullivan Mr. J.L. O'Sullivan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J.L. O'Sullivan</NameTxt>
      <P>The feeling is that they want to impress on the people that, although they were losing £50,000 per annum on the railway line, they are not entirely broke.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="NeilTCBlaney" hpid="Mr. Blaney Mr. Blaney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Blaney</NameTxt>
      <P>I would suggest that instead of looking for the £500,000 to bring the roads up to accommodate these unnecessary trucks which C.I.E. are parading round West Cork, C.I.E. might be asked to consider stabling those trucks elsewhere and bring some smaller trucks to that area.  From the roads point of view, from the economic point of view and from the point of view of the visiting tourist, not to speak of the natives, I think that would be an ideal solution for all concerned.</P>
      <P>Senator Cole suggested that in regard to the making of road traffic regulations, the power should lie directly with the local authority rather than what is proposed.  He suggested that we have taken something away from the local authorities.  I do not agree that we have taken anything away from them.  The reason we think the Garda should initiate in this matter is to get uniformity throughout the local authority areas in the country.  It is better that the initiative should lie with a group or a central body such as the Garda and that by obliging them to consult each local authority, local views will be fully considered before model bye-laws are presented to the Minister.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>If the Garda Commissioner has not given sufficient weight to what the local people think, even at that stage the Minister is obliged to give full consideration to and consult with the <Col N="1060" /> views of these local authorities. Accordingly, if anything is overlooked by the Garda Commissioner, the Minister can correct it at that stage and modify the bye-laws to fit in with the views of the local authorities.  In that way, I believe we can take care of the interests of the local authorities and each individual case, while at the same time, as nearly as possible, make a uniform approach to our local traffic bye-laws.  Overall, we will have a better system of local bye-laws than if we left the matter to each individual local authority.</P>
    <P>Somebody wondered if Section 85 would enable the driver of a bus improperly parked to be prosecuted.  Bye-laws under Section 86 will have this effect.</P>
    <P>Section 86 provides for road markings at those spots and whether these markings must be of a form that will not be objectionable or too large or in some way or another not just up to standard.  The fact is that these markings must be of a type approved by the Minister under Section 86 (9) (c) of the Bill before us.</P>
    <P>Senator Quinlan mentioned in particular the question of limiting driving licences for aged people.  The wisdom of this is something I should not like to come down on straight off without very much further consideration.  The power to do so is in the Bill and we can consider it and could have a look at it.  At the moment, I would not agree or disagree that it would be good or bad but I think there is no doubt that we shall take the power to do it.  The same Senator also spoke strongly as to his feelings in regard to defaced traffic and other signs of that nature. He asked whether or not we had any power to do anything about it.  We have, in section 95 (12) of the Bill.</P>
    <P>A question was also raised about parking meters.  In this regard of course we take it that local bye-laws would probably cover this and it would arise under subsections (1) and (2) of Section 90.  There is just one note that I have here.  The fact that I have already mentioned it briefly should not preclude me from giving the House a little further elaboration of what is intended <Col N="1061" /> in regard to the application of the thirty mile per hour speed limit. I shall give the House a short excerpt from the White Paper as issued before the Bill came before you.  In relation to this matter it reads as follows:</P>
    <P>The Minister for Local Government may by regulations exclude any particular road in those areas from the scope of the speed limit or bring within its scope particular roads outside those areas.  Thus, through roads in a village or suburban roads in a county might be included or wide, clear roads in a city might be excluded; the police and local authorities concerned would be consulted before such decisions were taken.</P>
    <P>that in fact is what we think and did circulate in the White Paper.  It gives fairly full scope and a fairly flexible arrangement which I think can be made to accommodate all possible circumstances and considerations in regard to this matter.</P>
    <P>Senator Ó Donnabháin suggested that we should have a fifty mile per hour speed limit for all vehicles at night time.  We could of course do this and we have the power to do so under Section 44 but, again, the wisdom of the step and indeed the limit mentioned or what limit there would be if we did get down to deciding on some such lines are matters I should not like to comment on at this stage.</P>
    <P>Senator Cole mentioned something with which I thoroughly agree, namely, the question of courtesy cops and the point that we should not appear to start to go out after the offenders but rather that we should try to bring them to behave in the proper way. I entirely agree with that approach.  It is not our intention or our wish and it is not our belief that the best way is to go out after our road users and persecute them, to follow them up and to try to get convictions.  That is not the intention of this measure at all. Only in the last resort will these prosecutions take place.  When all else has failed, we must punish.  I think that really is the whole approach of this matter of road traffic.  It is far from my mind that there should be any <Col N="1062" /> bye-law, as it were, or officers of the law to bring everybody into court and to try to instil into them the good sense they should have on the roads.</P>
    <P>The idea of &ldquo;traffic cops&rdquo; in our cities and built-up areas is one which, I believe, will pay off handsomely. I think we can rest fairly easy in our minds that the Garda, who, I believe, are speedily becoming equipped for this type of work, will be in a position to do just that type of job in the not too distant future.  I am a great believer in this type of collective enforcement rather than in prosecutions. The prosecutions undoubtedly will come also in their own good time but they are not the be-all and the end-all of this Bill.</P>
    <P>There has been mention here that it would be difficult to know all the law, that this is a pretty hefty volume even as it is.  It has rightly been said that, when all the various regulations and bye-laws have been added to it. it will be very formidable and a subject which it will be very difficult or impossible for people to know all about.  I do not believe it will be necessary to know everything that is in this Bill or in every bye-law and regulation that is made.  We will come to know many things and we know a great deal already.</P>
    <P>If we abide by all the ordinary, everyday rules and routine I do not think we need worry too much, if we mind ourselves, about what exactly is contained within the two sides of this document or the covers of any regulation that may be made arising from it.  The question of knowing everything in this Bill is one which I think can be brought too far.  There are the specialists in the law in this country and indeed in this House.  We are not bereft of quite a considerable number.  They are there.  They are fully trained for this job.  It is to them we have got to go when we get into trouble.  Therefore, why worry our heads about knowing every last thing in this law when, in fact, we have people trained in the law itself whose job it will be, at our expense, to instruct us as to what we have done wrong and how to get out of it.  When we have people properly trained in this line and whom we will pay in the future to educate us, if in <Col N="1063" /> fact we ever need them, why should we worry ourselves unduly about knowing every provision contained in this Bill?</P>
    <P>The question of more pedestrian crossings was mentioned by Senator Miss Davidson and particularly did she relate this matter to the Bray Road. It is a matter which undoubtedly may need extension.  As the House will recall, it is not so very long since we introduced these pedestrian crossings for the first time.  Naturally, the Garda Commissioner and those concerned with laying them down, in the first instance, went rather warily into this matter, were possibly somewhat conservative or over-economic in their use.  I think it was better to approach the matter in that way than to splash them all over the place and then find they were a nuisance and unnecessary and had to be removed.  I have no doubt there may be on the Bray Road, and at other places points where further pedestrian crossings are required. The views of the Senator will be brought to the notice of those concerned with policy in this matter and possibly further crossings will be provided to allow the Senator to get across the road more easily in future.</P>
    <P>The question of dimming devices has been mentioned.  That is a matter which will be dealt with by regulation. The point was aptly brought out by Senator Walsh who said that while you have to have proper dimming devices on vehicles, their proper use is really what we are after.  That is very true. There is not much point in having dimming devices, if they are not used.  It is only too true that on the roads today, in keeping with the lack of consideration generally that we find in all walks of life at the moment, there is this complete disregard by some of our road users for other road users.  This is particularly true if the person in question has brighter lights than those coming towards him.</P>
    <P>It is amazing what will happen if you have a dazzling spotlight on your car which is not on but which you put on when you have dipped your ordinary headlights and those meeting you pay no attention.  If you flip on <Col N="1064" /> your spotlight, you very soon get the reaction you had expected in the first instance.  That law of the jungle has really gone too far and it is a law of the jungle today.  Fortunately, we still have some bends on our roads which save us from the glare of approaching headlights.  Where we have straight and fast stretches carrying heavy traffic, we have the roadhog who not only wants the whole road but also has dazzling lights.  He blazes through with his lights full on while you have to pull up.  Somebody said that the thing was that in such a situation, you had to pull up dead.  My relief always is that I was not dead when I pulled up.</P>
    <P>It is a fact that there is this unwholesome law of the jungle developing, particularly in relation to night driving.  From my experience of night driving, I would say that the practice of dipping headlights when you are within 100 yards of the other vehicle is no use.  I have always dipped my headlights as I would like others to dip them.  I have done that over the years, believe it or not.  I have always done it before the actual lamps came into my line of vision or my lamps came into the vision of those approaching me.  If dipping is not done, then it is very often useless because the damage has been done once the light strikes the windscreen and glances off it, as it can so mysteriously do.  You get the shot in your eyes and there is nothing much you can do but pull up and you are fortunate if you pull up on your own side and get clear.</P>
    <P>All this comes back to the question of dimming devices and their proper use.  We will try to ensure that not only are the regulations proper regulations but that they are used in the future.  If that is done, the toll on our roads at nighttime will be lessened and a great number of fatal accidents will be avoided.  There was one thing which was said here and I do not think it was intended the way I took it up. It was said that jail only deters those who have never been there.  It does not really matter if that is what was said but when I took it up and looked at it, I thought it was really good.  It is a very good argument why jail should <Col N="1065" /> be mandatory because fortunately there are so many more who have not been in jail than have been in jail.  If it does deter those who have never been there, we would have chastened drivers on our roads, all feeling they might go there if we made a jail sentence mandatory.</P>
    <P>On the question of mandatory jail sentences, I want to say that apparently a misconception of what was intended has grown up.  I have heard it said that it would be better if discretion in this matter were left to the courts and that if we had mandatory jail sentences, there would be little sense in having courts at all.  That is not the conclusion to draw from what we proposed to do.  In the case where drunken driving was proved or where driving under the influence was proved, there was a proposal that a jail sentence be imposed, no matter for how short a period.  There was no reason why, once guilt had been proved, an hour's sentence or up to five years could not be given.  Surely there was absolute discretion there, discretion to give a sentence of an hour, or a half an hour, which might have been spent in court, or five years at the limit.  They can still give them that and I have no doubt they will and in many cases, it will be deserved.</P>
    <P>What really decided me to do away with mandatory jail sentences for driving under the influence was because in the situation which obtains, there is a complete lack of means of determination of whether a man is under the influence.  There is a complete lack of any real technical know-how to decide when such a point has been reached. It is because of that lack that I felt injustice could be done and in fact may be done, although I doubt it because the benefit of the doubt usually goes the other way in these cases.  It was with a view to determining the matter once and for all that a commission is being set up.  I have bowed to the wishes of quite a number of members in the other House who thought that this mandatory jail sentence should be removed.</P>
    <P>It may well be that when the commission comes to consider the whole question of drunken driving or driving <Col N="1066" /> under the influence, they will report back and give us a method whereby it will be possible to ensure that when a man is convicted of driving under the influence, he will have been under the influence.  There would be a lot less doubt in my mind then as to where the man should go than there is now. This whole matter may be reviewed and you may come to discuss it at a later stage as an amendment to this Bill.  However, what we are discussing is the question of mandatory jail sentence which have been removed in these two cases.</P>
    <P>Farm machinery was mentioned and it was said that while we should see to it that such machinery is properly lighted, we should not impede its usage on the roads in any way.</P>
    <P>I should like to say in regard to that matter that there is no doubt whatever that farm machinery is most important. We cannot do without it.  It is equally true that farm machinery is brought onto our roads&mdash;due to pressure of work possibly, the season or the weather-very often in a manner that is a real danger to other road users. I am thinking of large machinery. Very often their width is 10 or 12 feet and very often, possibly from usage in the fields, through grass or cereal crops or otherwise, it is not easy to see them coming out on the roads. That type of thing is done unwittingly but nevertheless it is done, and it creates a real hazard on our roads. There will be regulations of various kinds to discourage it but I am afraid that when farmers are going from one field to another, regulations will not have very much effect on them.  We should try to get it into their minds that what seems innocent to them is dangerous to others, and get their co-operation and consideration for other road users.</P>
    <P>As other speakers have said, this is a Committee Bill.  I thoroughly agree and with that in mind I do not intend to say anything further except that it has been my wish in the other House and in this House that it should be as near an agreed measure as possible. I want to pay tribute in this House&mdash; I had not the barefaced cheek to do so in the House where it belongs&mdash;to <Col N="1067" /> the members of the Dáil, the Opposition as well as those belonging to my own Party&mdash;to members of all Parties in that House&mdash;for the manner in which the matter was kept completely on an objective plane and for the constructive discussions we had there on all Stages, from the Second Stage to the Final Stage.  I want to express my appreciation in this House, and I am sure it will get back to the other House.  As I say, I could not say it to their faces.</P>
    <P>We still need general unanimity on this matter in order to get acceptance by the public of what is contained in the Bill.  That is why I have been most anxious that we should have near unanimity in the two Houses.  If we have not got unanimity here, there is not much hope of getting it outside.  If we are to make any impression on the staggering toll on our roads today, we require unanimity and with the help of all members of the two Houses and other interested parties, I believe we could go a long way to awaken a sense of responsibility and awareness in our road users, drivers, cyclists, and pedestrians.</P>
    <P>If we could get that awareness and <Col N="1068" /> get people to understand that all users of the roads are due some consideration, we would have gone half way towards solving this problem which is, without doubt, the scourge of modern mankind.  If we can get that goodwill, that thoughtfulness and that sense of thinking, we will have done a great deal and this Bill will bring to heel those few whom we all hope will become even fewer who still will not consider anyone's welfare but their own.</P>
    <P>As I say, this is a Committee Stage Bill and on Committee Stage, we will be able to discuss the various matters which I am sure every member of the House has considered.  If there is any information which any member of the House may wish to have between now and Committee Stage which he cannot find in the debates or in the Bill, and which would be of assistance to him in considering this matter, I shall be only too glad to provide it.</P>
    <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
    <P>Committee Stage ordered for Wednesday, 12th July, 1961.</P>
    <P>The Seanad adjourned at 10.30 p.m. until 3 p.m. on Wednesday, 12th July, 1961.</P>
  </MainHeading>
</Debate>