<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE Debate SYSTEM "../Debate.dtd"[]>
<Debate DocTitle="Seanad Debate" Day="Thu" Date="28" Month="Nov" Year="1929" Vol="13" No="4" DateIrish="Déardaoin, 28 Samhain 1929" DateEnglish="Thursday, 28 November 1929" House="S" CommitteeEng="" CommitteeIr="" SubNameEng="" cnum="141">
  <MainHeading Type="Prelude" LHead="" RHead="">
    <Title>
    </Title>
    <P>
      <Col N="141" /> Do chuaidh an Cathaoirleach i gceannas ar 3 p.m.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Ministerial Orders and Regulations." RHead="- Proposed Examining Committee">
    <Title>Ministerial Orders and Regulations. - Proposed Examining Committee.</Title>
    <P>The Seanad resumed discussion on the following motion in the name of Senator Johnson:&mdash;</P>
    <P>That it be an instruction to the Committee on Procedure in revising the Standing Orders of the Seanad to make provision for the appointment of a Standing Committee whose function it shall be to examine all orders and regulations made by Ministers of State which are required by statute to be laid before the Oireachtas, and when they deem it necessary to report to the Seanad respecting the purpose and effect of such orders or regulations.</P>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMilroy" hpid="Mr. Milroy Mr. Milroy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Milroy</NameTxt>
      <P>I think that the Seanad acted prudently the last day that this matter was before it in not coming to a decision, because though on that day when the matter first came before us I could not say that I had any very strong reasons to urge against the proposal, and some of the arguments that were put forward by the proposer and the seconder seemed weighty, still upon further consideration I, for one at any rate, did not find that that consideration tended to support the idea that the setting up of this Committee would fulfil a very useful purpose.  Before I come to the actual proposal I should like to refer to one or two of the statements made by Senator Johnson and by Senator Comyn in seconding the motion, statements which probably constitute the arguments most likely to weigh in favour of the proposal but which, to my mind, were entirely inaccurate. <Col N="142" /> I refer to those statements which were, in fact, contentions that orders and regulations could override, vary or alter the statute law.  I think that if that contention could be substantiated a very serious issue has been provoked.  Senator Johnson said: &ldquo;I am drawing attention to the fact that statute law may be altered by the exercise of the Minister's powers.  The Minister makes that alteration by order to be laid upon the Table.  It is true to say that the original Act of the National Health Insurance has been entirely altered and would not now be recognised as being the law prevailing today. The alterations therein have been effected by orders laid upon the Table,&rdquo; and he asks that this Committee should be set up so that closer examination would be made of those orders, so that possible departure from the intentions of the legislature should not be made without such matters being reported to the Seanad.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Senator Comyn went a stage further when he said: &ldquo;Acts of Parliament passed here have even gone so far as to authorise a Minister to ignore the law of the land.&rdquo;  I would like to call attention to the fact that Senator Comyn qualified this statement later on by saying: &ldquo;I do not think I have examined one set of rules.&rdquo;  That seems a strange preparation for such a drastic denunciation of these rules and orders. Speaking not as a lawyer but as a layman I doubt if it is accurate, in fact I think it is entirely wrong to say that the statutes can be altered or varied by orders.  I think I am on safe ground in suggesting that if an order does conflict with the existing statute law it is <i>ultra vires</i> and is a matter for the courts.  If I am right in that contention I think that one of Senator Johnson's weightiest arguments in favour of the setting up of this Committee goes by the board; in other words, if one of his objectives&mdash;it seemed to be the objective at least of the Senator who seconded him, that such a committee should be set up in order to detect whether a Minister or a Department overrides the law by an order&mdash;is <Col N="143" /> unsustainable, then I say one strong argument goes by the board.  In all these general allegations of this kind not one single instance was quoted to prove that the contention was correct.</P>
    <P>Apart from that consideration, apart from regarding the Committee as a watch-dog of the sanctity of the statute law against the unauthorised interference of Departments, the only other consideration that can be urged on behalf of it is the elucidation of these orders so that members of the Seanad may be quite clear as to what their powers and meaning are.  But I wonder if a Committee of this House, representative of different parties, as it would necessarily be, would be an effective body for that purpose.  The one essential thing, if the decisions of such a committee were to be of useful guidance in such matters, would be the agreement of the members upon the interpretation of an order, and is that likely in the present state of parties? My experience of committees representative of different parties in the House is that when party issues arise there is always a rigid distinction between the interpretations which the different parties take.</P>
    <P>For instance, supposing some order were issued dealing with the collection of land annuities, I wonder if it would be possible, say, for Senator Moore and Senator MacLoughlin to come to an agreement upon the matter. That is perhaps an extravagant illustration but it is an illustration showing how lacking in real value the report of such a committee would be in guiding Senators as to the meaning of an order.  But Senator Johnson indicated that in the matter of these reports which such a committee would issue the members of the committee would not be dependent upon their own resources but would call in Department experts to help them to ascertain the intentions and the purpose of these orders.  It seems to me that that would resolve itself into a report, really drafted by an official of the Department responsible for the order, which would simply be sponsored by the committee <Col N="144" /> itself.  If that is all that is required for elucidating and making clear certain orders, it seems to me that that would be much more efficiently done by the Department officials responsible for issuing the orders than by a body of Senators, largely unskilled in the construing of these things.</P>
    <P>In connection with the Expiring Laws Continuance Bill, Senators will remember that a Memorandum was issued with short explanatory notes as to the meaning of each statute which was expiring and which was to be continued by the Bill.  If that is all that is required, if that is the real purpose of Senator Johnson's motion, it seems to me that the setting up of this committee would not be the most expeditious method of attaining that end.  For these reasons, and not out of a sheer desire to oppose what Senator Johnson has put forward, I am taking up this attitude of opposition to his motion, I believe that such a committee would not fulfil any useful purpose, might possibly be a source of mischievous and diverse interpretations of orders, and might involve us in discussions as to the different reports which such a committee would issue upon different orders.  Further, because any elucidation that is required, in my opinion, can much more efficiently and much more quickly be done by the Department responsible for issuing the order, I have taken up my present attitude.</P>
    <P>Remember that the task which this committee would have to undertake would not be a very light one; it would be a very formidable one.  On the day that this motion first appeared on the Orders of the Day there were over two pages referring to orders laid on the Table.  They may be important or they may be formal; they may be very far-reaching or they may be purely technical, but the task which this committee would undertake, if the motion was passed, would be to examine all orders and regulations made by a Minister.  It could not simply select one here or there and say: &ldquo;This is important and this is unimportant.&rdquo; Such a committee <Col N="145" /> would have to investigate and carefully peruse each and every one of these orders, and so far as I can see that is a task which would involve very protracted sittings and very exacting attention from a very seriously-minded body of Senators, and possibly it would result, as I have indicated, in very little useful work. For these reasons I am opposing the motion, and I regret that some more useful work could not be suggested for a Committee of the Seanad.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOFarrell" hpid="Mr. O'Farrell Mr. O'Farrell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Farrell</NameTxt>
      <P>I am afraid that Senator Milroy's speech is suggestive of a strong disinclination for any sort of work that could possibly be avoided.  Presumably he has given very serious and thoughtful consideration to this motion since it first appeared on the Order Paper, and after all that care and thought he has come back and solemnly announced that for one reason in particular&mdash;as the work would be excessive&mdash;he cannot see his way to vote for the motion.  The motion is merely a suggestion for giving practical effect to the procedure by which statutory orders and regulations are laid upon the Table of the legislature. Presumably there would be no provision for the laying of these orders and regulations if it was not important that they should be at the disposal of members of the legislature for examination, and, if necessary, for annulment.  They are undoubtedly legislation by regulation, otherwise there would be no real object in laying them on the Table of the House.  In theory they are supposed to be a protection for the rights of the legislature in regard to legislation which devolves on Ministers, but in actual practice we know what happens&mdash;that what is everybody's business is nobody's business. Nobody perhaps feels that it is his particular duty to examine these rules, orders and regulations, and, if necessary, to move a motion for their annulment.  They are laid in dozens on the Table of the House.  Some of them may have far-reaching consequences. It is the bounden duty of members of the legislature to see that these are examined and, if necessary, <Col N="146" /> that a motion for annulment is moved.  But you cannot hold any individual responsible.</P>
      <P>The motion suggests that this House should appoint a committee whose task it would be to examine these orders and regulations, and if for any particular reason they thought it necessary that they might report to the House in regard to some of them regarding their effect. There is no necessity at all for agreement amongst the members of the committee in the event of party issues entering into it.  They can agree that it is not necessary to report on a particular order, an order on which there has been disagreement, to the House, but any one or more members of the committee can, if it is thought desirable, put down a motion for the annulment of the order at least for the purpose of discussing its effects.  The real effect of passing this motion would be that the Seanad, or a section of it at least, would make itself acquainted with what is being done by way of legislation through orders and regulations. We are not doing that at the present time; it is too much for any one member of the Seanad to take upon himself, I suppose.  It certainly is a task that members of the Dáil in the main feel that they have no time for.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Arguments are advanced from time to time as to the necessity for a Second Chamber at all.  In my opinion, this is certainly the kind of work that a Second Chamber should do, to be able to inform their colleagues in the House if necessary as to the effect of these orders.  All sections would be represented on that committee, I presume, and in that way all sections would, through one or more of their members, be acquainted with what was being done as legislation through regulations and orders.  Senator Milroy talked about the large number of these and the vast amount of work that would be involved in their examination.  It does not require any extraordinary intelligence for a committee to see at a glance that very many of these orders would be <Col N="147" /> of a very formal and routine nature and that they did not require any more than a mere cursory examination. Quite obviously they need not go into them.  There are orders, though, of a very important character, and to these they would, as sensible people, devote special attention and, if necessary, report to the House.  But in my opinion the principal effect of the motion would be to enable us to do in a businesslike way what we are supposed to do as individuals and what we do not do, rightly or wrongly.  I make no apology for not doing it myself.</P>
    <P>I admit that I do not do it and I admit I should do it, but I think we ought to have a way of spreading the work in matters of that kind, and I do hope that no pernickety considerations will prevent the Seanad from passing this motion.  I have heard no really effective argument made against it.  Certainly it is worth the experiment, and I do hope that the general sense of the House and their desire to discharge their duties as members of the Chamber will enable them to carry this motion.</P>
    <Speaker pid="SamuelBrownKC" hpid="Mr. Brown Mr. Brown">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Brown</NameTxt>
      <P>I am entirely in sympathy with the idea that underlies this motion.  My difficulty is to see how it could really be effectively carried out.  Senator O'Farrell did not define with accuracy what the motion is.  It is not that this House should appoint a committee; it is that it should be an instruction to the committee which is to revise our Standing Orders that they should make a Standing Order which would have the effect of establishing a committee of this kind, and really my difficulty is to see what Standing Order you could draw which would effectively carry out the idea that Senator Johnson has in his mind, that is, to find the test which is to be applied to any particular regulation in order that it might be reported to the House.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>There are two kinds of regulations under our Acts of Parliament. There is the one that requires our approval.  That comes here as a matter of course and we deal with <Col N="148" /> it.  The Rules of the Supreme Court, the Circuit Court and the other Courts come before us without being laid on the Table at all, because they require our approval to make them valid.  Then there is the other class to which the Senator's motion is intended to apply&mdash;regulations made under a statute which are to have the effect of a statute if they lie for twenty-one days on the Table of each of the Houses without a motion being carried to annul them.  Those are the kind of regulations to which the Senator's motion applies.</P>
    <P>There are two kinds of objections to regulations of that kind which might be made and would be made before this committee if it were set up and got to work.  The first is that the regulations are <i>ultra vires</i>, or some of them, or any one of them; that is, outside the intention of the Act, and outside the power of the Minister to make; that is, <i>ultra vires</i> the statute.  The other is that the regulation, although <i>intra vires</i>, although properly within the Minister's power to make, is not an appropriate one.  As to the first of those objections, that the regulations are <i>ultra vires</i>, or that some one of the regulations is <i>ultra vires.</i> I very much doubt if this House is the proper tribunal to decide that.  I rather think that it is really a question of the construction of the statute itself, that it involves the construction of the statute itself, and that it is a proper question to be dealt with by a court of law.  <i>A fortiori</i>, it is not a question which the committee, if it were set up, would have power to or could appropriately decide.  Therefore, I think that if the objection to the regulation was of that nature it is not one that could be appropriately dealt with either by the committee or by the Seanad itself.  As far as the other is concerned, of course, it would be absolutely within our power to deal with it.  But here again, what test are you to apply, what kind of Standing Order could the Committee on Standing Orders make which would create a test?  Is it to be just the test that the majority of the <Col N="149" /> people think that the regulation is not a proper one, or is there to be some principle laid down in the Standing Order?  I submit that there ought to be, and that it ought not to be left haphazard to the particular committee for the time being.  I feel that this would really not work effectively.</P>
    <P>I wonder if there could not be some other way of arriving at the very wise object that the Senator has in view, some way of getting us more information than we get.  These papers are laid on the Table of the House.  Would there be any way of getting in a memorandum with each of these regulations, some sort of short but sufficient description of what it is, so that anyone of us who get notice of a set of regulations being laid on the Table would know what they were about and it would put him on notice, so that if he were interested, as many of us are, in subjects which we know ourselves we could at once look the thing up, and if we found that there was anything objectionable in the orders themselves as appropriate orders we could then bring the matter before the House?  But I do feel a very great difficulty in voting for the motion, although I am entirely in favour of what underlies it, because of the difficulty of carrying it out.</P>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasEsmondeBart" hpid="Sir T. Grattan Esmonde Sir T. Grattan Esmonde">
      <NameTxt>Sir T. Grattan Esmonde</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator Johnson has raised a very important matter.  The question is exercising many minds in various countries, as to the tendency which is growing up more and more latterly of Ministerial interpretation of legislation. Notwithstanding what Senator Brown has said, I am in favour of the motion and for this reason: I am not tied to any method of achieving some protection for the rights and liberties of the common citizen. I am not tied to any details of method.  But Senator Johnson's proposal seems to me to carry us a step further.  The important thing is for this Seanad to approve of the principle of the Oireachtas' or the Parliament's pre-eminence in matters of law.  I have felt, because I have studied this question somewhat <Col N="150" /> deeply, that we are at the opening of a very long vista.  There is the Parliament or the Oireachtas of the Twenty-Six Counties at this end, and on the horizon is bureaucracy, and the rights and the liberties of the people follow that vista in a decreasing succession.  It seems to me that this motion carries us some distance along the road.  The supremacy and the rights and liberties of Parliament are very important.  In many countries people have laid down their lives to support them.  But the liberties and the rights of the common citizen are very much more important than the liberties and the rights of Parliament.  I am not tied to methods.  I think we should check as far as we can Ministerial interpretation of legislation.  We should do what lies in our power to make the ordinary citizen protectable by the courts, which really interpret the law.  It is enough for the Seanad to certify its opinion in favour of this principle of the liberties and the rights of the ordinary citizen.  As to whether Senator Johnson's method is suitable, I have no opinion, but at all events, it carries us some distance along the road we should travel, and if the Senator carries his motion to a division I shall certainly support it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardWilson" hpid="Mr. Wilson Mr. Wilson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Wilson</NameTxt>
      <P>I have been listening to Senator Esmonde with a view to getting instruction on this matter. The Senator has not replied to Senator Brown's point.  This committee would take cognisance of objections, but will the objections be <i>ultra vires</i> or <i>intra vires</i>?  Senator Esmonde has not enlightened me on the question whether a committee of that sort is capable of dealing with an Order which it considers <i>ultra vires</i>, or which it considers <i>intra vires.</i>  For that reason, while I am in sympathy with the idea that these Orders should be investigated, I am doubtful whether this committee would be the proper method of doing so.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MauriceMoore" hpid="Colonel Moore Colonel Moore">
      <NameTxt>Colonel Moore</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator Wilson has asked a question which seems to be simple enough.  He wants to know <Col N="151" /> whether this committee will be <i>ultra vires</i> or not.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardWilson" hpid="Mr. Wilson Mr. Wilson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Wilson</NameTxt>
      <P>No, whether its decision will be on the point whether an Order is <i>ultra vires</i> or <i>intra vires.</i></P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MauriceMoore" hpid="Colonel Moore Colonel Moore">
      <NameTxt>Colonel Moore</NameTxt>
      <P>That is not proposed.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Cathaoirleach Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>That question will arise.  It has been submitted by Senator Brown that such a question will arise.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SamuelBrownKC" hpid="Mr. Brown Mr. Brown">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Brown</NameTxt>
      <P>It is one of the questions that must arise.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MauriceMoore" hpid="Colonel Moore Colonel Moore">
      <NameTxt>Colonel Moore</NameTxt>
      <P>Any Senator can go at any time and look at these Orders and can go through them one by one, and make notes about them. When he has done that he may come to the conclusion that certain Orders or one Order change the meaning of Acts that have been passed by the Oireachtas.  Having come to that conclusion, which he is perfectly entitled to come to, he can put down a motion on the Order Paper to discuss the matter in the Seanad. No one objects to that.  Admitting that is so, and admitting that it is not <i>ultra vires</i> or would lead to anything of the sort, how then would there be any greater difficulty in half a dozen people going and examining these orders one by one? Having come to an agreement amongst themselves, or disagreement, as the case might, be, any one of the members of the committee can come here and bring a motion before the House.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardWilson" hpid="Mr. Wilson Mr. Wilson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Wilson</NameTxt>
      <P>Any member of the committee?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MauriceMoore" hpid="Colonel Moore Colonel Moore">
      <NameTxt>Colonel Moore</NameTxt>
      <P>Any member or the whole or a part of the committee. Any member, the whole or part of the committee may say that they want to discuss the matter and may bring a motion before the Seanad in the ordinary way.  If one person, or if several persons can do that, I can see no reason why a committee appointed by this House should not be in a better position to do it.  The motion is not <Col N="152" /> asking the committee to decide whether these Orders are <i>ultra vires</i> or not, or whether they ought to be altered, but it asks them to consider them.  The Seanad can consider whether a particular Order should be reversed or not.  The only difficulty I see is that we may not be able to find individuals to take this trouble but that would be a great reflection on the Seanad.  The Seanad does not sit very often, goodness knows.  It is as important a body as the Dáil in its way.  The Dáil sits ten times oftener, and very much longer than this House.  Why should the Seanad or Senators flinch from doing a little job that would be useful and which the Dáil is doing every day?  I do not like to see the benches here empty, and I do not like to see people flinching from doing what they ought to do.  I think it would be possible to find a few people to do this work. At any rate, I think the Seanad ought to try to find them.  To say that you cannot find them when you do not try does not seem to me to be reasonable.  I do not profess to have studied this question very deeply, but anybody who has been interested in it knows that it has been raised in Great Britain, and that it has arrived at a very important stage in London. One of the highest judges in Britain has written a book on the subject, in which he discusses and strongly condemns the present method of administration by these orders.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMilroy" hpid="Mr. Milroy Mr. Milroy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Milroy</NameTxt>
      <P>In England, not in the Free State.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MauriceMoore" hpid="Colonel Moore Colonel Moore">
      <NameTxt>Colonel Moore</NameTxt>
      <P>Lord Chief Justice Hewart has protested and has written very strongly on the tendency to hand over power from the Parliament, and from the people whom Parliament represents, into the hands of a bureaucracy which draws up these papers that nobody looks at.  We all know that they are not examined.  I doubt if any single member of this House examines these papers.  I have not done so.  I wish I had time to do so.  I was never asked, and if I did probably everyone would say I was a great fool to take so much trouble about them. <Col N="153" /> The question has now arisen and Parliament, on account of the increasing amount of business that is going on, has allowed itself to be drawn into a method of legislation which is contrary to democracy and to an appeal to the people.  I cannot see the objection to the passing of the motion.  Senator Brown has raised some objection, but not very strongly, because he only thinks there might be difficulty about carrying it out.  There might be a difficulty, but there are always difficulties about these things.  The only way to do these things, unless you have got some very definite and strong opinion against them, is to try them.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Cathaoirleach Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>The difficulty is to make a Standing Order comprehensive enough to deal with all the details for the committee.  At present, the House has power to appoint a committee if anyone wishes to do so, and to deal with a matter for a specific time for a specific purpose.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SamuelBrownKC" hpid="Mr. Brown Mr. Brown">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Brown</NameTxt>
      <P>What is to be the test?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Cathaoirleach Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>And no test is to be applied.  You must have a test laid down for the guidance of the committee.  That is only a detail and it is for the House to consider it. There is nothing at present to prevent the House, if it so desires, from appointing a committee and asking it within the next month to examine all these papers and to report.  There is nothing outside the competency of the House at the moment to do that, but the framing of a Standing Order comprehensive enough to deal with the whole question would be rather difficult.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MauriceMoore" hpid="Colonel Moore Colonel Moore">
      <NameTxt>Colonel Moore</NameTxt>
      <P>No doubt the Seanad can do what it likes.  These things are not carried out unless some method is provided.  If we merely say that the Seanad can do this and that anyone who likes can go on the committee, that is not the way to do it.  At present, there is no means of carrying out this proposal unless by asking the Seanad to pass a resolution appointing a committee. That is what is being asked here&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Cathaoirleach Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>The motion is asking <Col N="154" /> for a specific Standing Order&mdash; that a Standing Committee be formed&mdash;and it must always exist.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MauriceMoore" hpid="Colonel Moore Colonel Moore">
      <NameTxt>Colonel Moore</NameTxt>
      <P>&mdash;just in the same way as appointing a committee for any other purpose.  There was no proposal of that kind before.  A proposal is now being made that the Seanad shall have a Standing Order to that effect.  As to the difficulty of drawing up that order that seems very simple.  All that has to be done is to ask the Selection Committee to appoint a committee to examine orders.  They need not give any particular direction as to how it is to be done and as to technicalities, but are simply asked to examine orders, and if there is anything important in them to report to the Seanad.  That seems pretty clear.  I do not see any great difficulty about it.  As to the objections to that course I do not see any objections.  I am quite sure that nobody here, even those opposed to the motion, wishes that these things should be kept secret.  If that is so what is the objection to the committee?  Let us try it.  If it fails, that is all about it.  No great calamity will have happened and the Constitution will not be seriously infringed; the Seanad will not lose anything by it.  Senator Brown, I think, admits that the proposal would be a good one.  Let us try it. I do not think the Seanad is asked to do a very serious thing, and some who hitherto had doubts about it now seem to desire it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickKenny" hpid="Mr. Kenny Mr. Kenny">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Kenny</NameTxt>
      <P>The whole trend and object of the motion seem to be that when this committee, if and when set up, should report to the Seanad respecting the purpose and effect of such orders or regulations. What goes before that is merely the ways and means of setting up this committee.  The crux of the whole thing is that this committee, when set up, if they deem it necessary, should report to the Seanad respecting the purpose and effect of such orders or regulations.  I do not know who should know better than the Minister and his legal advisers, and I presume he consults these <Col N="155" /> legal advisers before making the order.  Who should know better the purpose and effect of an order that he is going to make?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasFarren" hpid="Mr. Farren Mr. Farren">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Farren</NameTxt>
      <P>Why have a Parliament at all?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickKenny" hpid="Mr. Kenny Mr. Kenny">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Kenny</NameTxt>
      <P>I mean to say with relation to existing statute law how far that order is outside or within the particular statute that is affected by the order.  You must have a Department in order to administer statute law, but the Minister in making an order to carry out the intention of the statute will certainly have to consult his legal advisers, because it is a matter that may ultimately come for decision before a law court.  That being so I think the suggestion made by Senator Milroy&mdash;that accompanying each of these orders there should be a note framed by the Minister or his Department&mdash;and I presume also with the assistance of his legal advisers, setting out their purpose and effect, is a good one.  That would save a great deal of research work on the part of anyone undertaking the task of interpreting such an order, according to his own light and experience.  Anyone taking up the Order Paper and seeing the number of Orders that are laid on the Table from week to week will know that some of them are so worded that it would be necessary to go to a great amount of trouble reading up the various sections and tracing the various Acts of Parliament that come within the ambit of these orders.  If that work is elucidated and lightened for him by a concise minute or note a member might then, if he so desired, go further than what is contained in the Ministerial note.  It would break the back of the research work as the note would set out what would be the effect of the order.  It would enable a member to see at a glance what the intention was, and if he thought that the intention was not warranted by the wording of the Act he may go further and investigate the matter.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="156" /> I think that information would be sufficient for the ordinary Senator or Deputy, and would enable him to perform his duty, which, I admit, is the duty of every individual Senator and Deputy to enable them to perform the duty in such time as is reasonably at their disposal.  There is not much time available.  The fact is, I suppose, that no member of this House has given very much time to the investigation of these orders.  No matter what one's disposition may be, there is not time at the disposal of members to do their duty fully in this matter, and I think the suggestion made by Senator Milroy would meet the case better than the proposal in the motion.</P>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasFarren" hpid="Mr. Farren Mr. Farren">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Farren</NameTxt>
      <P>It appears to me that most of those who have spoken against this motion really do not understand what the motion aims at. In my humble opinion, the motion aims at doing exactly what Senator Brown says it may not do.  I do not think that these legal questions arise at all.  The question of whether an order is <i>ultra vires</i> or <i>intra vires</i> does not arise at all.  In my opinion the motion simply means that the Seanad should give an instruction to the Committee of Procedure to prepare a Standing Order to the effect that a Standing Committee be appointed for the purpose of examining these orders, and if they think necessary of reporting to the House.  The question as to whether an order is <i>ultra vires</i> or <i>intra vires</i> does not arise at all.  As a matter of fact, the question that does arise is this: that we all know that owing to the modern trend of legislation extraordinary powers have been given to Ministers to draft orders and make regulations in conformity with our Act of Parliament for the carrying out of it.  We all know that has been the tendency in modern times, and in order that the members of the Seanad will have an opportunity of knowing exactly what is being done by way of order or regulation, this motion has been put down so that it will be somebody's business to examine these orders and, when they think necessary, <Col N="157" /> to report to the House.  The motion simply means that we are going to departmentalise the work of the Seanad, because this particular work of examining orders is everybody's business, and therefore nobody's business.</P>
      <P>The motion asks that a few members of the Seanad undertake this particular type of work.  There are members of the House who do a considerable amount of work on the various committees appointed by the House.  There are, however, some members who never serve on any committee.  I think that the work of the House should be subdivided, and that some members should undertake the responsibility of doing this work.  I submit that we are not facing up to our responsibilities unless we are prepared to do this work.  Senator Kenny said that the Minister, with his legal adviser, was the proper person to say what the regulations should be.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickKenny" hpid="Mr. Kenny Mr. Kenny">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Kenny</NameTxt>
      <P>I did not say that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasFarren" hpid="Mr. Farren Mr. Farren">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Farren</NameTxt>
      <P>My interpretation of the words used by Senator Kenny was to the effect that the Minister, with his legal adviser, was the person who knew what regulations were to be made according to the Act of Parliament.  I would like to know from the Senator if that is right.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickKenny" hpid="Mr. Kenny Mr. Kenny">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Kenny</NameTxt>
      <P>If regulations were required to be made.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasFarren" hpid="Mr. Farren Mr. Farren">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Farren</NameTxt>
      <P>I hold that an order can be strictly legal and still be unjust. Some of the orders made, for instance the orders relating to Civil Service examinations, are very important, particularly for parents who have young boys and girls eligible to sit for such examinations. Is there any harm in examining the regulations that are made to see that they are all right?  If, in the opinion of the committee that is appointed to examine these regulations, they come to the conclusion that the regulations are not all right, is there any harm in that committee reporting to this House?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="158" />
    <Speaker pid="SeanMilroy" hpid="Mr. Milroy Mr. Milroy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Milroy</NameTxt>
      <P>What is to prevent any Senator from examining them?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasFarren" hpid="Mr. Farren Mr. Farren">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Farren</NameTxt>
      <P>Nothing, if one had the time to do it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMilroy" hpid="Mr. Milroy Mr. Milroy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Milroy</NameTxt>
      <P>How will the committee find time?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasFarren" hpid="Mr. Farren Mr. Farren">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Farren</NameTxt>
      <P>All that I will say on that is this, that some members take it very easy in this House.  When I hear all the talk that there is about this being a colossal job, it reminds me of what I hear so often about the unfortunate artisan with his restriction on output.  But there is no talk at all about the restriction of output in the Seanad.  All that this will mean is the giving of a few hours' work to the examination of these orders, and are we to take it that members of the House are not prepared to undertake that task?  I am perfectly satisfied that if the motion is passed it will be found that there are members of the House who are prepared to take on that responsibility, and to do this particular job.  All that it would mean is getting the work done here in a businesslike way, having the order, when made, examined by a Committee of the House, the members of which will report to the House in regard to these orders when they think it necessary to do so.  I am sure that no member anticipates for a moment that anyone is going to examine these orders with a microscope for the purpose of trying to pick holes in them.  The object of setting up the Committee is that as occasion demands it the House will be put in possession of the information that it ought to have so that it may exercise the authority it possesses.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The House has passed numerous Acts of Parliament which give power to the Minister to make orders and regulations, but while we do that we safeguard ourselves to this extent, that we retain the power in our own hands to annul those orders and regulations made by the Minister under the Act of Parliament if we think that the orders or regulations made are not satisfactory or in <Col N="159" /> order.  If we are to retain that power of annulling these orders, then surely we ought to make provision to have them examined, or else the whole thing is a farce.  What is the use of insisting on the right of being able to annul orders or regulations within twenty-one days after they have been made and laid on the Table of the House if we do not also insist on the right of taking steps to examine them and see that they are in order?  What this motion aims at is that orders made under Act of Parliament should be examined by the Committee set up.  If the Committee found that some of the orders made, while they might be strictly legal, were not desirable, or were not in conformity with the Act of Parliament, then it would report to the House.  There is no question at all of bringing the lawyer's mind to the examination of any of these orders.  It is simply a question, in the first place, of the protection of the rights of the House, and in the second place of the rights of the citizen, and for that reason I hope the House will pass the motion.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDouglas" hpid="Mr. Douglas Mr. Douglas">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Douglas</NameTxt>
      <P>With much of what Senator Farren has said I am in agreement, but I am not in agreement with his conclusions.  It is impossible not to admire Senator Kenny's implicit confidence in the accuracy of every Order that comes before this House, but I am afraid it is not shared by very many.  I think that Senator Johnson in bringing forward this motion has raised a point of very real importance.  I do not know&mdash;I am simply speaking for myself&mdash;how many of these orders are read by members of the House. Personally, I look through the list. If any of the Orders deal with matters that I know anything about, I get a copy of them and read them. Those relating to subjects which I do not feel competent to deal with I do not read at all.  I think it is the duty of every member to look through the list, and in particular to read those Orders which we have the power to annul or to prevent coming into force.  Senators, I think, <Col N="160" /> should read them and attend to them.  If it is not possible for every member of the House to do that, I think it is possible for some members to do it.  This House is divided into parties more or less, and amongst them it should be possible to get some of their members to go through the list and examine these Orders.  To that extent, I am in agreement with the arguments put forward in support of the motion, but with regard to the conclusions I cannot see that the delegating of this duty to a committee, thereby giving an excuse to every member not to read any Order, is the way to deal with it.</P>
      <P>What is your committee to be? There are members of the Cumann na nGaedheal Party in this House, and I have a kind of feeling that they have a mild tendency to approve of Orders made by Ministers. Senator Colonel Moore, if I may say so, has the mild tendency always to disapprove.  I am putting the point as mildly as I can.  It seems to me that if you had a majority of the members of the particular Government of the day on the committee you would always get a majority that would not be willing to draw attention to the matters concerned. I cannot see for the life of me what you are going to gain by delegating what is the duty of every member of the House to a committee. At the same time, I do think that the matter ought to be considered to see whether there is not any better way of bringing the problem before members of the House. At the moment we only get this list on the printed Orders of the Day when we come to the House.  We get it at a time when we are busy, and when there are urgent matters before the House.  The tendency, therefore, is not to read the list through.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I think that perhaps some provision could be made for dealing with the matter.  Probably if the Cathaoirleach considered it himself he would find that he has power to do a good deal more than is done at present in the matter of calling attention <Col N="161" /> to orders that are laid on the Table of the House.  I think myself that special attention ought to be drawn to every order that is laid upon the Table of the House, particularly those orders in respect to which the House has special powers. If special attention were drawn to these orders and notice to that effect was sent out with the preliminary orders which Senators receive, then members would be in a position to take special note of them.  For instance, attention could be drawn to an order which the House has power to annul or to prevent coming into force within the period of twenty-one days.  I know that if I got such a notice I would certainly pay more attention to it than if I were simply to see a list here containing a great number of orders.  Personally I am opposed to the idea of getting rid of the awkward responsibility at present placed on members simply by saying that there is a standing committee to look into these matters. Suppose that that standing committee is appointed now, it would I think be excellent on some subjects and useless on others.  I feel that if I were a member of that committee I would be quite incompetent to deal with many of these orders, while with regard to others, about which I know something, I might be a useful member to the committee.  The idea of appointing such a committee and delegating to it what is the duty of every member of the House is, I think, wrong in principle.</P>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. Johnson Mr. Johnson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Johnson</NameTxt>
      <P>I am astonished at the criticism that has been made with respect to this proposal as well as at the line that criticism has taken.  I admit at once that it is a valid argument to say that the duty of examining every order devolves equally on every member of the Seanad and the Dáil just as it is the duty of every member of the Dáil and Seanad to examine every Bill that is brought before them.  But, at least, in regard to Bills they are brought to the notice of Senators by argument in the Seanad in respect to their content and purport.  It may be that we do not read the Bills through and <Col N="162" /> through on every occasion, but at least we are able to hear an explanation by the Minister as to what the Bill is intended to do.  We are able to discuss it and to have our interest and perhaps our doubts aroused by the discussion that has taken place on the Second Reading of the Bill. In regard to orders and regulations they are, if I may say so, minor enactments, and they do not come before us in the definite way that Bills do.  It is equally of course the responsibility of every member to read them, but they are not brought before the House for positive approval in the same way that a Bill is. Consequently they become, in effect, statutory orders which may be enforced in the courts.  They become obligations upon every citizen without any consideration whatever by even an individual member of the House.  That is the point.</P>
      <P>It is well enough to say that there is a diffused responsibility, but it is because it is so diffused, because it does not come specifically and definitely before the individual Senator, that there is no special responsibility in regard to it.  I think, as a matter of fact, it is a business-like arrangement, and certainly in accord with the modern tendency towards specialisation and is not unreasonable to place upon a given number of members of the Seanad the duty of examining these orders and regulations without, as I say, removing the individual responsibility at all.  The individual responsibility still remains, and perhaps will be no more effective in the future than it has been in the past. But, at least, the likelihood of the purport of such orders may be brought specifically before the Seanad.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>A proposition which I myself considered has been referred to by two or three speakers, that in presenting the order to the House a <i>précis</i> or memo. of the intention of the order should be presented at the same time, so that the special attention of the House would be drawn to the effect of the order.  I think that would be quite valuable.  We <Col N="163" /> are in this unfortunate position that we have no power to instruct the Minister, when making an order, to prepare a <i>précis</i> of it and present that to the Seanad.  The Acts simply say that the order shall be laid on the Table.  The alternative, suggested, I think, by Senator Douglas, was that the Cathaoirleach should make arrangements&mdash;presumably with the Clerk&mdash;to present a <i>précis</i> to the Seanad of the content and purport of these orders.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDouglas" hpid="Mr. Douglas Mr. Douglas">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Douglas</NameTxt>
      <P>I did not make that suggestion.  What I did suggest was that Cathaoirleach should send out a list drawing attention to such orders as we have the power to annul.  I did not say that a <i>précis</i> should be prepared.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. Johnson Mr. Johnson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Johnson</NameTxt>
      <P>You may take it that 95 per cent. of these statutory orders are capable of annulment by the House.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDouglas" hpid="Mr. Douglas Mr. Douglas">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Douglas</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not think so at all.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. Johnson Mr. Johnson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Johnson</NameTxt>
      <P>As far as my little observation has gone I think that is so.  I will not be too positive about the proportion, but I think with regard to statutory orders laid on the Table that in the great majority of cases they are capable of annulment by the House.  You may take it that in regard to these statutory orders they are in almost all cases capable of annulment by a vote of the House if laid on the Table.  So that we come to the alternative as to whether the Seanad itself should set up a committee to examine these orders and bring their content and purport before the Seanad in a specific manner or invite the Minister to do it.  If we had any assurance that the Ministers were desirous of facilitating both Houses by presenting a <i>précis</i> of the content and purport of these orders, that undoubtedly would go a considerable way to meet what my desire is in this matter.  But I think that even then we are shirking a responsibility which we need not place upon the Minister, because the work <Col N="164" /> can be done quite effectively in the manner that I have suggested.</P>
      <P>Senator Milroy thought that I exaggerated when I said that Ministers have power to amend an enactment. Of course, formally they do not amend an enactment because under the Act itself power is given to make the alteration.  You may say that is not amending an enactment, but so far as the public are concerned it is amending the working of the Act.  I again draw attention to the very outstanding example of the Local Government Act under which we are at present working. We all know that the poor law system which had existed was condemned by most people interested in that subject who had examined it.  As a result of the general denunciation and dissatisfaction with the working of the poor law, during the régime of Dáil Eireann in pre-Treaty days, the various local authorities proposed and enacted for their own purpose schemes which, in effect, altered the poor law very radically.  Those schemes were embodied in the Temporary Provisions Act of 1923.  Twenty-two of those schemes, all differing, were made and attached to the Act as schedules.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Under a provision in that Act certain counties which had not put these schemes into operation are allowed to do so.  The Minister may approve of the schemes.  The Act provides that these schemes be laid on the Table of both Houses, and in that way they become law.  That has been done.  Is there any member of the Seanad who knows what the poor law is regarding County Waterford?  If he does not know, how is he to find out?  Is he to go to the Acts?  Not at all.  He must go and look up the statutory orders. The whole of these twenty-two schemes have been modified by order of the Minister, and in effect the poor law that is governing this country to-day has been made by order of the Minister.  I think that probably on the whole that is advantageous, but they have not been approved of, nor have they been examined by either House of the <Col N="165" /> Oireachtas.  Judged by the confessions that we have heard here to-day they have not even been looked at by Senators.  That is my point.</P>
    <Speaker pid="RichardWilson" hpid="Mr. Wilson Mr. Wilson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Wilson</NameTxt>
      <P>Is it not a fact that those particular schemes were attached when the Bill was going through the House?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. Johnson Mr. Johnson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Johnson</NameTxt>
      <P>That is so.  The schemes were before the House. That is my point.  The Minister gets power to alter any of these schemes and amend them.  They have been altered and brought into conformity with another scheme, but there is no positive approval sought from the House, and that is an illustration of my point that Senator Milroy seems to doubt.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMilroy" hpid="Mr. Milroy Mr. Milroy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Milroy</NameTxt>
      <P>Would the Senator quote the statute or provision where the Minister gets power to alter the Act?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. Johnson Mr. Johnson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Johnson</NameTxt>
      <P>The Local Government (Temporary Provisions) Act contained schedules, and the schedules became part of the Act.  The Act states:&mdash;</P>
      <P>&ldquo;(1)  From and after the passing of this Act the relief of the poor in a County to which an existing County Scheme relates shall be administered under and in accordance with such existing County Scheme, and the law relating to the relief of the poor in that County shall be deemed to be and is hereby altered or modified in such manner and to such extent as is necessary to give full force and effect to such existing County Scheme.&rdquo;</P>
      <P>There is a later provision which states:&mdash;</P>
      <P>&ldquo;The Minister may by order do any of the matters following, that is to say:&mdash;</P>
      <P>(1)  apply to any public body established under or in pursuance of this Act or any county scheme any existing enactment relating to county or district councils or boards of guardians with such modifications as he shall deem necessary;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="166" /> (2)  make such adaptations of any existing enactment relating to any matter dealt with or affected by this Act as appear to him necessary or expedient for carrying into effect this Act,&rdquo;</P>
    <P>and so on.</P>
    <P>Nobody will doubt that the schemes enacted under the 1923 Act have been modified by order.  As a matter of fact they have been brought into conformity with the model scheme.  I am not taking the line that Senator Sir Thomas Esmonde has taken.  I do not think that the charges regarding bureaucracy are sustainable, or that the tendency towards legislation by administrative orders can be avoided. I think that with modern complications it is necessary, and even most valuable, in maintaining the authority of Parliament that the Act itself instead of giving all the details of the possible variations that may be required in the carrying out of the Act, shall give power to the Minister to make regulations.  If, for instance, all possible variations of the application of the Act in the various counties owing to new conditions that might be imagined were put into the statute itself every Bill of importance would be so voluminous that the Seanad would be overwhelmed and would not be able to deal with them, and they would be passed <i>en bloc.</i>  It is more to the advantage of control by the Legislature that the Minister would have power to issue by order regulations to give effect to the Act, provided that the Legislature keeps a watchful eye over the orders and regulations. It is only because of the necessary tendency of modern times towards legislation by administrative orders, which is, I think, inevitable in the complex circumstances of modern times, that I feel it absolutely imperative to maintain the authority of the Legislature that there should be constant vigilance in regard to orders we are empowering a Minister to put into effect.  If they did not matter we should not ask them to be laid on the Table.</P>
    <P>As to the question of <i>ultra vires</i><Col N="167" /> or <i>intra vires,</i> I do not see how it concerns or is affected by this proposal. As some Senator has pointed out, whether it is <i>ultra vires</i> or <i>intra vires</i> is a matter at the moment for the individual Senator.  If it is a question of it being <i>ultra vires,</i> surely it is right it should be brought to the notice of the Seanad.  I admit candidly that it is not desirable the Seanad should take upon itself the duties of a court and expound the law and declare whether a certain regulation was or was not <i>ultra vires,</i> but if the question arises as to its being <i>ultra vires,</i> and the question is publicly explained in the House, at least there is an opening up of the question, and the responsibility will lie upon whoever feels himself aggrieved by the order.  But as to those orders which are <i>intra vires,</i> within the power of the Minister, my desire is that the intention of these orders should be made known to Senators, but it should be something more than a mere statement&mdash;&ldquo;under the Factory Act, so and so; regulation so and so; affects so and so&rdquo;&mdash;that is not enough.  The intention of the orders should be brought before the Seanad, and if then any individual Senator thinks it is desirable to test the opinion of the House as to whether it conforms with the wishes of the House the necessary action can be taken and a motion made calling for its annulment.  Since the 1st January this year there have been laid on the Table 83 statutory orders or regulations which would come within the scope of this proposed committee.  There are 23 that are Defence regulations, and deal with Army administration, and are purely formal and internal.  Fourteen relate to Civil Service examinations, and are formal matters not raising any questions.  Six are National Health regulations, and four are Agency Orders, transferring authority from one Minister to another.  I am not sure whether they can be annulled by action of the Seanad, but there may be two or three, or perhaps a dozen, that might have been brought before the Seanad.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="168" /> For instance, there is one order making it possible for young persons between sixteen and eighteen years of age to work at night in the Carlow sugar factory.  That is within the power of the Minister, but under an Act passed many years ago.  It might conceivably be the wish of the Legislature in this year to prohibit the employment of young persons throughout the night in a factory.  If that, which is conceivable, were in fact the will of the House it would be the duty of the House to annul that order and prevent the doing of such a thing.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDouglas" hpid="Mr. Douglas Mr. Douglas">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Douglas</NameTxt>
      <P>Has the Seanad power to annul that Order?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. Johnson Mr. Johnson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Johnson</NameTxt>
      <P>I am not positive, but I am practically certain that it has.  I do not think there is difficulty in framing a Standing Order. I have not been able to understand where the difficulty arises.  I have considered the objection made privately and publicly, and frankly I cannot understand why there should be an objection.  The point has been made that the Seanad has responsibility. To put the matter frankly, if there is any legitimate function for a Second Chamber, if there is any place for a Second Chamber in the Legislature, surely this kind of work ought to be done by that Second Chamber.  It is reasonable, it is formal, it is a kind of research work, which does not involve Party passion or the rising or falling of a new Government.  It does not involve any of these things. It could be done in a simple manner without raising any of these high political feelings, passions or objections. It is letting the Seanad do a class of work which it can reasonably do with advantage to the community, for when a report is made on the effect of an order it is not coming to the Seanad alone, but it is also coming to the Dáil, it would be made public so that the public will know what is being done by the Minister in a matter by which they would be bound in their future lives.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I think the sentiment of the <Col N="169" /> Seanad is in favour of the contents of these orders being brought to their notice.  The only point then to consider is whether this method of doing it is effective.  I contend that it is.  Again, let me say that my motion is simply an instruction to the Committee on Procedure to do a certain thing.  If after consideration it is found impossible to frame <Col N="170" /> a Standing Order of the kind proposed, if a committee such as the Committee on Procedure finds it is not practicable, it can report to the House, and this work will not be accomplished until the question is further examined.  I hope the Seanad will accept the motion.</P>
    <P>Question put.</P>
    <P Just="Center">The Seanad divided: Tá, 15; Níl, 19.</P>
    <P Just="Center">Tá</P>
    <table pgwide="1">
      <tgroup cols="2">
        <colspec colname="1" colnum="1" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <colspec colname="2" colnum="2" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry rowsep="1">William Barrington.<br />R.A. Butler.<br />Michael Duffy.<br />Sir Thomas Grattan Esmonde.<br />Thomas Farren.<br />Thomas Foran.<br />Thomas Johnson.<br />Thomas Linehan.</entry>
            <entry rowsep="1">Colonel Moore.<br />Joseph O'Connor.<br />Joseph O'Doherty.<br />M.F. O'Hanlon.<br />James J. Parkinson.<br />Siobhán Bean an Phaoraigh.<br />Séumas Robinson.<br /></entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
    <P Just="Center">Níl</P>
    <table pgwide="1">
      <tgroup cols="2">
        <colspec colname="1" colnum="1" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <colspec colname="2" colnum="2" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry rowsep="1">Sir Edward Coey Bigger.<br />Samuel L. Brown, K.C.<br />Miss Kathleen Browne.<br />Alfred Byrne.<br />Mrs. Costello.<br />John C. Counihan.<br />The Countess of Desart.<br />James G. Douglas.<br />Michael Fanning.<br />Henry S. Guinness.</entry>
            <entry rowsep="1">Right Hon. Andrew Jameson.<br />Cornelius Kennedy.<br />Patrick W. Kenny.<br />Francis MacGuinness.<br />Seán Milroy.<br />Sir Walter Nugent.<br />Bernard O'Rourke.<br />Dr. William O'Sullivan.<br />Richard Wilson.<br /></entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
    <P>Motion declared lost.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Motion to Establish a Tribunal. - Mixture of Maize" RHead="Meal and Maize Products with Home-Grown Cereals">
    <Title>Motion to Establish a Tribunal. - Mixture of Maize Meal and Maize Products with Home-Grown Cereals.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelOHanlon" hpid="Mr. O'Hanlon Mr. O'Hanlon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Hanlon</NameTxt>
      <P>I move:&mdash;</P>
      <P>&ldquo;That it is expedient that a Tribunal be established for inquiring into a definite matter of urgent public importance, that is to say&mdash;</P>
      <P>(1)  To ascertain and report whether, having due regard to the interests of</P>
      <P>(a)  producers of cereals in Saorstát Eireann; and</P>
      <P>(b)  consumers of maize meal and maize products in Saorstát Eireann,</P>
      <P>it would be in the national interest to enact that all maize meal and maize products before being offered for sale in Saor-stát Eireann shall be mixed with some one or more of the following home-grown cereals,</P>
      <P>namely, wheat, barley, oats, or rye, so that the resultant mixture shall contain a definite percentage of such cereals; and, if so, what that percentage should be.</P>
      <P>(2)  To consider and report upon the effect, if any, which such enactment would be likely to have upon tillage and the production of cereals in Saor-stát Eireann.</P>
      <P>(3)  To consider and report upon the administrative machinery necessary to make such enactment operative.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I make this motion under the Tribunals of Inquiry (Evidence) Act, 1921.  Under that Act a tribunal may be set up to inquire into any matter of urgent public importance, and that tribunal will have the powers of a High Court both in respect of the attendance of witnesses and the taking of evidence on oath.  A tribunal has been set up to inquire into this matter. <Col N="171" /> It consists of Mr. McElligott, Professor Whelehan and Dr. Hinchcliffe. I might say that a preliminary meeting of this tribunal has been held, and it is considered that a very useful purpose would be served if powers were conferred on them to hear evidence on oath. Further, all Parties in the Dáil are agreed on the terms of reference specified in the motion.  Representatives of those associated with the propaganda for the mixing of maize meal and maize products with home-grown cereals have no objection to the course taken.  Some of them have expressed themselves anxious in that respect.  I might say that we have almost absolute unanimity upon the matter, so that there would be no delay in connection with it.  A similar motion has been submitted to the Dáil.  If the motion is passed by both Houses the tribunal can take the powers specified.  A preliminary meeting of the tribunal has been held; the work is under way, plans have been prepared for investigation, and future meetings have been arranged.  I hope the House will pass the motion so that the unanimous desire of the parties concerned may be carried into effect.</P>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasEsmondeBart" hpid="Sir Thomas Esmonde Sir Thomas Esmonde">
      <NameTxt>Sir Thomas Esmonde</NameTxt>
      <P>I second the motion.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Cathaoirleach Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>There is an amendment standing in the name of Senator Linehan.  I did not see it until yesterday morning.  I have given it a good deal of consideration, and I have come to the conclusion that under Standing Order 27 it is not relevant to the motion, for the reason that the motion deals with a mixture for cattle foods, and the amendment deals with the manufacture of flour for human consumption. I do not think that the amendment is relevant, and I rule it out of order.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeamusRobinson" hpid="Mr. Robinson Mr. Robinson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Robinson</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not say we approve of the motion.  What I do say is that the motion approves of us.  Our people have been protagonists of the policy of dealing with maize and home-grown cereals in the <Col N="172" /> manner mentioned in the motion, and we would be well pleased if the motion was carried.  I fear the Greeks when they come with gifts. Imitation may be a subtle way of giving a gift.  We know it is a sincere form of flattery, but when the imitation is a close copy, and does not acknowledge the original, it may be regarded as plagiarism.  However, we are not opposed to the motion the Senator has brought forward, and we hope it will be accepted.  I think there is one possible fly in the amber.  There is a danger that this tribunal would simply keep the thing hanging fire, and there would be no report for a long time.  In the meantime a discussion of this and similar matters would be tabooed.  I would like that if possible a time limit should be put as regards making a report, or at least that there should be an interim report.  If the tribunal reported every three months we could see how things are going and have a discussion.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WalterNugentBart" hpid="Sir Walter Nugent Sir Walter Nugent">
      <NameTxt>Sir Walter Nugent</NameTxt>
      <P>I think we all welcome the motion.  I think we ought to realise that a great deal more might be made out of the food product in Ireland.  Most of the grain raised here is disposed of very cheaply, and an enormous amount of maize is brought in.  Much as I sympathise with the motion, and much as I hope that something will come of it, nevertheless, I feel doubtful as to the possibility of doing what the Senator wants.  I am sorry that Senator Linehan's amendment was ruled out of order, as I agree with it altogether.  I think it opens up what is a very big question.  My own idea is that if milling could be revived in Ireland the question raised in the motion would solve itself, for I think if milling were revived, and the minor and subsidiary products of milling were available, such as bran, they would be used as a substitute for maize.  I realise that if the amendment were carried&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Cathaoirleach Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>The amendment is not before the House.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="173" />
    <Speaker pid="WalterNugentBart" hpid="Sir Walter Nugent Sir Walter Nugent">
      <NameTxt>Sir Walter Nugent</NameTxt>
      <P>I am entirely in favour of the motion.  The amendment might be enlarged.  I would like to widen the scope of inquiry. I think if the inquiry were enlarged it would be exceedingly useful.  It touches a subject which concerns us all.  Nothing, in my opinion, is so vital to the prosperity of the country as the points raised in the motion, but, as I have said, I think it ought to be enlarged as regards its scope.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnCounihan" hpid="Mr. Counihan Mr. Counihan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Counihan</NameTxt>
      <P>This motion is the result of the agitation of the Barley Growers' Association.  They have been agitating for a considerable time to get the Government to take action to compel other farmers to use portion of their produce at a big price.  Personally, I think it is a sheer waste of time to set up the proposed tribunal.  If the tribunal recommended what is mentioned in the motion such an agitation would be raised by farmers in the Free State that no Government could stand against it.  Barley is not a crop that is grown extensively in many parts of Ireland.  It is confined to five counties, and the farmers in those counties who grow it expect the rest of the farmers of Ireland to subsidise them for growing barley.  I believe that 75 per cent. or 80 per cent. of the farmers of this country would be sternly opposed to the proposal into which a tribunal is being set up to inquire.  The proposal to mix home-grown corn with maize is not new, but the proposal to have legislation to compel farmers who are buying Indian meal to mix the commodities is quite new, and it is one the country would not stand for at present.  The proposal would mean that farmers who grow corn for sale are the people who should be most looked after.  Every farmer who buys maize is a tillage farmer. He grows corn, and it is not ten per cent. or twelve per cent. of the home-grown corn he mixes with maize but sometimes as much as 75 per cent. The farmer who grows corn for sale is not as desirable as the tillage farmer who feeds his corn to stock and walks it off the land.  For that <Col N="174" /> reason, I say that the farmer who grows corn and feeds it and buys maize is a man who should have more consideration from the Government than the man who simply grows corn for sale.  I grow a good deal of corn and I buy corn.  I also buy maize, and in most cases I mix it with from 50 to 80 per cent. of home-grown corn.  What is suggested in the motion has been promised by the Government owing to the agitation by the Barley Growers' Association, and I am prepared to support the motion.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardWilson" hpid="Mr. Wilson Mr. Wilson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Wilson</NameTxt>
      <P>As I understand it, the Government have already set up a tribunal and this motion merely gives the Committee powers which the High Court has, to examine witnesses on oath.  So far as that goes I am quite in agreement with Senator O'Hanlon that the Committee should have these powers.  If the question before the House was whether it was right to set up such a tribunal or not, I would say that it was quite wrong to do so.  The question is merely to give the tribunal which has been set up power to examine witnesses on oath. I do not know that I would be in order in discussing the question that is to go before the tribunal.  If I were in order, I could give certain facts and figures which, in my opinion, would give the Government information that would make the tribunal unnecessary and which would show them that farmers know their duty better than anyone else about the use of corn and grain and that they do not want any more advice on the subject.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelComynKC" hpid="Mr. Comyn Mr. Comyn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Comyn</NameTxt>
      <P>I am in favour of the motion for reasons other than those already stated.  My main reason is that it refers to the matter now before the House as &ldquo;one of urgent public importance.&rdquo;  I would be glad with Senator Sir Walter Nugent if the scope of the motion could be extended, but as it has been passed in the other House it cannot be altered here.  The matter is so urgent that I imagine it is better to let the inquiry go on.  We all know <Col N="175" /> the object of the inquiry&mdash;to encourage tillage and employment in this country.  I am not in favour of using compulsion.  I do not think the farmers of Ireland can be compelled to do anything if they do not desire to do it themselves, but they can be enabled to do something.  I think the result of the inquiry will be that they will be enabled, by steady prices and perhaps by increased prices for their products, to bring more land into cultivation. We have only one main industry, and I make this protest, that the main industry of agriculture is not properly attended to or considered in either House.</P>
      <P>Senator Counihan has stated that this motion is the result of the agitation by the Barley Growers' Association. Well, if it is the result of the agitation by the Barley Growers' Association what I say is, more power to their elbow.  It is not merely a question of barley growing. It is a question of wheat growing, of the growing of oats and the growing of rye.  It is really a question of agriculture in this country.  It is the first time we are really devoting attention to the main purpose, as I submit, for which Governments are intended, the development of industry, in our case the development of agriculture and the prevention of land going into grass.  I am in favour of this motion.  I hope it will be expedited, and that the result of the inquiry will be satisfactory from my point of view, and above all I hope that Senators and T.D.'s will do as the French are doing: where statesmen on both sides do not make this a party question at all, and concentrate on agriculture and its development.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. Johnson Mr. Johnson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Johnson</NameTxt>
      <P>I would like to draw attention to the terms of the motion and to utter a cautionary not.  The form of the motion is I think based on an Act passed to deal with immediately urgent matters.  The phrase was used on two or three occasions when similar motions were passed with the object of enabling <Col N="176" /> tribunals to have power to call witnesses, but it seems to me to be a stretching of the meaning of words when we say that this is a definite matter of urgent public importance, in the light of the statement made by the Minister for Agriculture, that there could be no expectation of a report before January or February at least, and one of the supporters of the motion saying that there may be a report every three months.  In the light of that one cannot think in terms of urgency, and this term &ldquo;urgent public importance&rdquo; has become established in Parliamentary proceedings, and has been held hitherto to mean something that cannot wait.  While I think that this question ought to be discussed quickly and some decision taken early, it hardly comes within the category of a matter of urgent public importance in the sense that was intended when the Act was passed.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I would like to have an opportunity of saying on the main purpose of this agitation which is undoubtedly to encourage the growing of cereals in this country that I was examining the Northern Ireland Census returns recently and I found that a very interesting lesson could be drawn from them.  We are apt to compare the situation of agriculture in this country with that of Denmark and Holland, but if we compare it with Northern Ireland, I find that if the crops and pastoral land of the Free State were made to give as good a return as the land in Northern Ireland, the net output of agriculture in the Free State would be added to by £22,000,000.  That is a very considerable item, and when one considers the fact, that methods of farming, cultivation, tenure and calculation in Northern Ireland and in the Free State are almost identical, the comparison is very striking, indeed, especially when one bears in mind that four-fifths of the output of agriculture in Northern Ireland, as Senator Counihan declared, consists of live stock and live stock products. The fact is a very important one, and indicates how desirable it is to encourage by one means or another <Col N="177" /> increased output of agricultural commodities from the soil of the Free State.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickKenny" hpid="Mr. Kenny Mr. Kenny">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Kenny</NameTxt>
      <P>This proposal has to do mainly with stock-feeding.  Of course, for human purposes Indian corn or maize is not now in use as much as it was in the old days.  Some people still like to use Indian meal as human food in porridge mixed with some proportion of oatenmeal, but that is a negligible quantity.  At present the principal use of maize meal is for feeding pigs and poultry. Senator Wilson, speaking, I think, on behalf of the farmers, said that there was no necessity for this tribunal, and that the farmers know their own business. Every intelligent farmer does, but we all know that there are certain farmers who are wedded to old systems, and who find it very hard to get out of them.  It is very hard to enlighten them.  The Department of Agriculture was set up here over a quarter of a century ago, and if the farmers had followed closely the work it undertook, and the result of that work, I think they would have been very much better able to carry on economically the work of their farms.  Senators who are familiar with the work of the Department, particularly in regard to the displacing of the imported maize meal by our own products, by cereals which farmers are capable of growing, and who are familiar with leaflets sent out by the Department setting out the formulæ and the relative quantities of these meals, mixed together in certain proportions for the feeding of stock, particularly pigs, will know that it has been the whole trend of the Department's programme during all these years to displace the importation of Indian meal.  On more than one occasion I have seen the practical results that followed the recommendations of the Department with regard to the formulæ they have set out in their leaflets, showing that Indian meal is not a necessity in this country, that far better results can be <Col N="178" /> achieved by an admixture of our own cereals.</P>
      <P>I have seen in Glasnevin a litter of bonhams from which two lots of sixes were taken, one being fed upon a mixture of our own home-grown cereals and the other fed, as they are ordinarily fed by farmers, almost exclusively on Indian meal.  I noticed from month to month the difference in the conditions of these two lots.  They were brought up and attended to in the same way, and it was most surprising&mdash;it would certainly be an eye-opener to any ordinary farmer who was wedded to Indian meal for the fattening of his pigs&mdash;to see the difference at the end of the fattening period between the two lots.  In as far as this tribunal, if and when it does bring its report in, will emphasise, as I hope it will, the percentage which I hope it will advocate, and a very large percentage too, of home grown cereals that should be mixed with Indian meal, it will be doing great good.  I am sure, if they get evidence from the Department and from practical and progressive farmers who have followed out the teachings of the Department in this respect, the tribunal will emphasise those very practical and useful results that the Department has achieved in the feeding of the cereals.  The Department is not a theoretical Department, as many farmers would seem to view it; its work is very practical.  It does not set out in theory from food values what results ought to be achieved, but, having made sure of the results, it applies its theories of food values and admixtures to the actual feeding process in the matter of stock, and it shows the definite, tangible results that have been achieved in its farms at Glasnevin and elsewhere.  If, as I say, the tribunal emphasises what farmers could usefully do for themselves and what economy and profit would result to them from doing it, then I say it will be doing very good work, and I will heartily approve of it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelOHanlon" hpid="Mr. O'Hanlon Mr. O'Hanlon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Hanlon</NameTxt>
      <P>I am not going to follow Senator Kenny in his observations because, I respectfully submit, <Col N="179" /> the matter under consideration is not that of the value of this tribunal or the relative fattening values of the various feeding stuffs &mdash;maize or maize meal with home-grown cereals.  That is not the point.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickKenny" hpid="Mr. Kenny Mr. Kenny">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Kenny</NameTxt>
      <P>That is what the motion says&mdash;the percentage.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelOHanlon" hpid="Mr. O'Hanlon Mr. O'Hanlon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Hanlon</NameTxt>
      <P>That is not my motion.  My motion specifies that there is a situation existing where a Commission has been set up to inquire into a matter of urgent public importance, that is, the admixture of maize-meal and maize products with home-grown cereals.  That Commission has been set up and is functioning.  It already has had one sitting.  That Commission and certain other people think that they should have greater powers than they have at present.  At the moment they can hear evidence, arrive at their decision, and issue their report.  They have power to do that, but they have not power to hear evidence on oath and compel witnesses to attend.  My motion asks that they be given those <Col N="180" /> powers.  That is all it contains.  I ask by my motion that they be given those powers, and particularly as there is demand for them by the tribunal itself which thinks that a useful public service will be rendered. I do not want to discuss the merits of the case.  I wish to assure Senator Robinson in regard to the credit for the initiation of the propaganda which brought this tribunal into existence and with regard to the credit for this protagonism, as he has called it, for mixing grains with home-grown cereals, I am not going to claim credit for that.  As a matter of fact, I am opposed to it myself, so that there is no question of my sharing the credit.  There is no question of diving into the hive for honey at all.  If this motion were extended and if we were to discuss this question of the admixture of imported flour with home-grown wheat&mdash;sufficient for the day is the evil thereof&mdash;by all manner of means let whoever chooses put down a motion and we can discuss it on another day.</P>
      <P>Motion put and declared carried.</P>
      <P>The Seanad adjourned at 5.10 until Wednesday, December 4.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
</Debate>