<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE Debate SYSTEM "../Debate.dtd"[]>
<Debate DocTitle="Seanad Debate" Day="Wed" Date="11" Month="Dec" Year="1929" Vol="13" No="6" DateIrish="Dé Céadaoin, 11 Nollaig 1929" DateEnglish="Wednesday, 11 December 1929" House="S" CommitteeEng="" CommitteeIr="" SubNameEng="" cnum="249">
  <MainHeading Type="Prelude" LHead="" RHead="">
    <Title>
    </Title>
    <P>
      <Col N="249" /> Do chuaidh an Cathaoirlcach i gceannas ar 3 p.m.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Expiring Laws Bill," RHead="1929&mdash;Second Stage">
    <Title>Expiring Laws Bill, 1929&mdash;Second Stage.</Title>
    <P>Question: That this Bill be read a second time, put and agreed to</P>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Cathaoirleach Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Apparently this is not a very contentious Bill.  I do not think it gave rise to any contention in the Dáil, and if the House is agreeable I suggest that the Committee Stage of it be taken tomorrow.</P>
      <P>Agreed.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="National Health Insurance" RHead="Bill, 1929&mdash;Second Stage">
    <Title>National Health Insurance Bill, 1929&mdash;Second Stage.</Title>
    <P>Question proposed: That this Bill be read a second time.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDowdall" hpid="Mr. Dowdall Mr. Dowdall">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dowdall</NameTxt>
      <P>As this is a very comprehensive Bill amending and altering six existing Acts, I think it would help the House in the discussion of it if the Minister were to outline its main provisions.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="Minister for Local Government and Public Health (General Mulcahy) Richard (General) Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Local Government and Public Health (General Mulcahy)</NameTxt>
      <P>The Bill is intended mainly to give effect to some of the recommendations of the Commission that was set up to go into the question of National Health Insurance.  In the first place, there were persons called exempted persons.  Though they were called exempted persons they were not exempted.  They came in under the Act, but were exempted from paying contributions. Their employers and the State paid contributions, and these persons got certain benefits under the Act.  They were exempted for the reason that they had a certain income of, I think, about £26 a year, or for the reason that they were dependent <Col N="250" /> on some other person.  The Commission recommended that they were a privileged class.  They were a very small number.  I think that at the moment the number is only about 700.  We think that exempted persons should be done away with. They got certain privileges that were paid for.  The cost of administering benefit to these people was out of all proportion to the number of persons involved and was without any advantage whatever to the system. Therefore, exempted persons are being done away with as recommended by the Commission.</P>
      <P>With regard to deposit contributors, the number of them is between three thousand and four thousand. Deposit contributors are persons who are liable to be insured, but who do not join any approved society. They come under the head of deposit contributors and pay the usual contributions, but are only entitled to receive benefit to the extent of their own moneys paid in, plus the moneys the State pays in.  They are being done away with under this Bill.  There was a special arrangement in connection with migratory labourers by which they were exempt from the Act.  Certain moneys that were paid in respect of them were not paid over to them in benefit, but actually were paid over to some nursing bodies in the West of Ireland.  At the present moment there are only, I think, two persons who are claiming to be exempt as migratory labourers.  We think that the circumstances out of which exemption in the case of migratory labourers arose have passed since about the year 1918 or earlier.  There are certain small changes in the Bill by which the period for giving notice of sickness under the Bill is being extended from three days to seven days.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The major changes that the Bill covers relate to the abolition of insurance committees.  Certain funds were made available under the National Health Insurance Act for the treatment of tuberculosis, and were paid over annually.  They amounted to 1/3 per head of the insured <Col N="251" /> persons, and were paid over to the insurance committees throughout the country for administration.  The insurance committees as set up represented the county council, the approved societies which represented the insured persons and the Insurance Commission.  The money was handed over to the insurance committees and was administered by them.  With the exception of about five counties, these insurance committees have entered into arrangements with the county councils or the boards of health by which the moneys that used to come over to the insurance committees are transferred to the boards of health bodily.  Insured persons looking for sanatorium treatment are recommended by the insurance committees to the boards of health, and are dealt with under the ordinary county schemes.  These insurance committees will also deal with such matters as had to be dealt with in respect of deposit contributors. The machinery generally for dealing with tuberculosis throughout the country has been very considerably increased during the last few years.  In fact the amount of money that has been spent on insured persons is greater than the amount of money that has actually been paid over to the insurance committees. The committees, in many instances, find themselves in the position that the amount of money at their disposal is not sufficient to cover the number of insured persons who are looking for sanatorium treatment. The general position is that sanatorium benefit, which was in the Insurance Act originally, was dropped in England because it was not adequately provided for in the finances of the Act.  It is proposed to drop that here now.</P>
    <P>At the present moment the amount paid annually to the insurance committees is about £27,000.  It is proposed under this Bill that there should be a State contribution of £27,000 made to the local bodies over and above the 50 per cent. contribution payable to them in respect of their total expenditure on tuberculosis <Col N="252" /> schemes.  That £27,000 will be available, and will be spent on tuberculosis treatment for insured persons. Under the agreements that have been made between the insurance committees and the county councils a certain proportion of that will be for sanatorium treatment, a certain proportion of it for domicilary treatment and, generally, medical treatment, but as far as expenditure by the local bodies is concerned the same proportion will stand.  Until that amount has been totally spent, no person who can give evidence of being a member of an approved society will be charged for tuberculosis treatment, so that we are ensuring that, while doing away with the insurance committees, the amount of money that has been available for free treatment for insured persons up to the present moment will continue to be available.  There has been a very large increase in the amount expended on tuberculosis treatment. It has increased from about £30,000 a year in 1922 up to approximately £110,000 in the current year.  Therefore, the amount of money generally available through public sources for tuberculosis treatment is going to be very much increased.  We are making the change at a time when there will be no loss of benefit to anyone entitled to sanatorium treatment and who had it before.</P>
    <P>Another important change that has been made relates to medical certification. Because of political and general circumstances of the country, it came to be left entirely outside the scope of the finances of our National Health Insurance scheme.  The State annually passes a sum of approximately £34,000 for medical certification. As I have said, we are taking out sanatoria benefit, but medical certification is now being put into the finances of the scheme.  In future, the National Health Insurance scheme will have to bear the cost of medical certification.  That is covered by relieving the National Health finances of the amount of money that is to go for tuberculosis treatment. The amount of money that will go for that will be £27,000.  That money <Col N="253" /> will be voted separately by the State for that purpose.  As I have said, it will be entirely outside the finances of the National Health Insurance scheme.</P>
    <P>The next important change is with regard to the position of married women.  Under the National Health Insurance scheme the present position is: a person who, within twelve months after her marriage, or eight weeks immediately before her marriage, is for eight weeks unemployed, or by reason of sickness is for eight weeks continuously in a state of ill-health, comes into what is called the K Class.  She becomes no longer entitled to ordinary benefit, but she simply becomes entitled to this, that during the next ensuing two years she will be paid benefit to the extent of 7/6 per week for eight weeks in the case of ill-health.  She will have certain rights with regard to sanatorium benefit inside a period of two years, and she will get a gratuity on the occasion of her first confinement inside of two years.  It is proposed to change the position of married women and to bring about this position: that when a woman who is an employed person marries she ceases to be an insured person. She will get on her marriage a gratuity which will be actuarially figured out.  If a woman who is an insured person marries, and then comes into employment again, and as a result of that into insurance again, she must restart as an insured person.  There is just that special provision by which, in the first year of her married life, she will not be allowed to enter into any scheme which may exist at the moment by paying up certain arrears in order to come into benefit.  The actuary has pointed out that a married woman in the first year of her married life is not a normal person, so far as the National Health Insurance scheme is concerned.  The scheme is liable to risks in the case of a person like that, and ought to be safeguarded against.  The position, therefore, is this: that if a married woman, immediately after marriage, becomes employed again, she <Col N="254" /> can work up her ordinary benefit and become entitled to benefit in the ordinary way.  But in the period of twelve months after her marriage she cannot get that special type of consideration by paying up any amount of arrears that may be due, in order to get into benefit in the way that another person would be allowed to do.</P>
    <P>The Bill, as I have pointed out, provides that no longer will there be exempted persons and no longer will there be deposit contributors.  At the present moment approved societies have the power to refuse to take in insured persons into their societies.  As a result of doing away with exempted persons and deposit contributors, we will have to make arrangements so that approved societies will not be able to refuse persons in the future, except in certain circumstances, in which it can be proved that the person ought not to be allowed to enter into insurance. The deposit contributors will be given an opportunity of joining within three months the particular society which they desire to join. If the deposit contributors have not elected to join a particular society within that period, they will be assigned by the Insurance Commissioners to some particular society or societies chosen by the Insurance Commission.  The Bill makes certain arrangements with regard to other classes of insured persons, as regards military service particularly.  Provision will be made for persons who may be called up for training on the reserve.</P>
    <P>I think these are the principal matters touched on in the Bill. Perhaps I should say that the Commission drew attention to the fact that the large number of approved societies was contrary to conserving effectively the funds put into National Health Insurance schemes. In the discussion on the Bill that took place in the Dáil I undertook to introduce next year a measure which will enable a number of approved societies to be reduced.  They have already been reduced pretty considerably within the last two or <Col N="255" /> three years&mdash;that is, since the Commission reported.  A reduction to an appreciably smaller number is desirable.  While that recommendation of the Commission has not been touched on in this Bill, I hope to introduce a proposal dealing with it some time next year.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelComynKC" hpid="Mr. Comyn Mr. Comyn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Comyn</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister, as I understood him, intends to provide that girls when they are about to get married will cease to be insured persons.  I understood him to say that they would get a sum at the time of their marriage that will represent the actuarial value of the contributions which they had paid in.  He went on to say that during the twelve months after their marriage they will not be insurable. He was very frank in stating the reason for that, that from the actuarial point of view the risk would be too great.  What I want to know is whether the loss would be so great as to make it worth while to introduce special legislation of this kind.  Even if the risk is so great that married women should be excluded, I suggest for the consideration of the House that there is something small in a provision of that kind.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General Mulcahy General Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>General Mulcahy</NameTxt>
      <P>I think the Senator misunderstands.  They will be able to start again.  After their marriage, they are given a certain gratuity.  If they continue in their employment or enter into employment shortly after marriage they can become insured persons again. There has been a system by which persons who have in fact made a certain amount of national health insurance payments and fell short of the statutory limits for benefits and thereby fell into arrears were within certain limits given an opportunity of paying up the arrears in order to come into benefit.  The only discrimination against married women in these circumstances is that they are not allowed to become voluntary contributors.  They are not allowed, inside the first twelve months after their marriage, to pay up what are purely arrears.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="256" />
    <Speaker pid="MichaelComynKC" hpid="Mr. Comyn Mr. Comyn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Comyn</NameTxt>
      <P>So as to come into benefit.  I think that at first sight the Seanad would be against that provision, because in the first year of a woman's married life she certainly incurs great risks.  These, however, are risks which people consider are of advantage to the State, and for that reason I would suggest to the Minister and for the consideration of the House that there is no need for special legislation in that regard.  I certainly think that the reason which was very frankly given by the Minister is not sufficient for the introduction of such a provision in the Bill, namely, that the risk is too great, and that married women in general would be likely to get more out of the fund than they pay into it. That is the only objection that I have at the present stage to the statement made by the Minister.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasFarren" hpid="Mr. Farren Mr. Farren">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Farren</NameTxt>
      <P>Speaking with some knowledge of National Health Insurance, I must say that I am in agreement with the general provisions of this Bill.  I think the Bill is an attempt to tighten up the loose joints in the existing Acts.  With regard to the particular point mentioned by Senator Comyn, I think if the Senator understood the actual position he would not be found in opposition to the proposal with regard to newly married women.  If a woman who is an insured person gets married, then she ceases to be an insured person if she does not continue to follow her ordinary occupation. In nine cases out of ten that type of insured contributor who gets married would be safeguarded, for the purpose Senator Comyn has in mind, by the husband.  Speaking generally, a woman who is an insured contributor under the National Health Insurance scheme gets married to an insured person, and the husband's insurance will cover what Senator Comyn has in mind.  The important fact that must be borne in mind is that the money is contributed just the same as a contribution to a trade union for the purpose of unemployment benefit.  The money in that pool belongs to the members, and it must be properly administered for <Col N="257" /> the benefit of the members as a whole.</P>
      <P>No special privileges must be given to anybody, and the funds must be managed in the most efficient way, so that the greatest possible benefit will be given out of them.  With regard to the wiping out of insurance committees, I am entirely in favour of that.  As the Minister has pointed out, there is a certain sum of money available each year for the purpose of free sanatorium treatment for insured people suffering from tuberculosis.  The whole of the money will now be available for the treatment of insured people suffering from tuberculosis, and the cost of running the committees will be wiped out.  While there may be some things in the Bill with which I do not agree, I am, as I said, entirely in favour of its general principles.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelComynKC" hpid="Mr. Comyn Mr. Comyn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Comyn</NameTxt>
      <P>On a point of explanation, I understood from the Minister, and in reading through the Bill the impression I also got was, that whether a married woman continues in the same employment or not, she is not entitled to be insured and to get full benefit in the first year.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General Mulcahy General Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>General Mulcahy</NameTxt>
      <P>She is entitled to be insured, but she starts as an insured person again, and what is not allowed to happen is that she cannot go into pseudo-employment for three weeks and get three stamps on her card, and then pay up the rest of the stamps herself as arrears and come automatically into benefit.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelComynKC" hpid="Mr. Comyn Mr. Comyn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Comyn</NameTxt>
      <P>She cannot continue as an insured person.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General Mulcahy General Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>General Mulcahy</NameTxt>
      <P>No, she cannot continue.  She may enter as an insured person, but she is denied for one year of her married life the type of privileges allowed to certain persons in paying up arrears.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SamuelBrownKC" hpid="Mr. Brown Mr. Brown">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Brown</NameTxt>
      <P>There is no gap, as I understand it, if she goes on working after her marriage.  This is only to deal with the case of arrears due at the date of her marriage.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="258" />
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General Mulcahy General Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>General Mulcahy</NameTxt>
      <P>The arrears must accrue after her marriage.  If the arrears had already accrued that will affect the gratuity she will get.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Cathaoirleach Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Her gratuity will absorb her contributions.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>Committee Stage ordered for Wednesday, 18th December.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General Mulcahy General Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>General Mulcahy</NameTxt>
      <P>May I say that this is one of the Bills it will be essential to get finished before the end of the year?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Cathaoirleach Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>If notice of motion to suspend Standing Orders is given in regard to the Bill it will enable us to finish it in time.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDouglas" hpid="Mr. Douglas Mr. Douglas">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Douglas</NameTxt>
      <P>Is it not absurd to get from the Dáil after it has adjourned a Bill which must be passed by the end of the year?  If an amendment is passed here it will mean holding up the Bill.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General Mulcahy General Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>General Mulcahy</NameTxt>
      <P>If an amendment is inserted in the Bill it will be necessary to recall the Dáil.  If I do not get the Bill this year I will have to deal with certain things that must be covered by this Bill or another Bill, such as medical certification, before the end of the year.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDouglas" hpid="Mr. Douglas Mr. Douglas">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Douglas</NameTxt>
      <P>All I wanted is the assurance of the Minister that if necessary the Dáil will be called together.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Poor Relief (Dublin) Bill," RHead="1929&mdash;Second Stage">
    <Title>Poor Relief (Dublin) Bill, 1929&mdash;Second Stage.</Title>
    <P>Question proposed: That the Poor Relief (Dublin) Bill be read a second time.</P>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. Johnson Mr. Johnson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Johnson</NameTxt>
      <P>This Bill is intended to replace the Bill which was sent from the Seanad to the Dail.  In my opinion it is a much worse Bill than the Bill which was passed by the Seanad, and it will in fact, in my view, be very difficult to consent to its adoption in its present form.  I realise that there is a certain risk in not passing the Bill, but, frankly, I am very doubtful whether it would not be more beneficial to risk the non-passing of the Bill than to pass it without amendment.  So far from <Col N="259" /> merely doing what the Seanad decided upon doing, that is to say, to bring the city and county of Dublin into line with the rest of the country in respect to the legality of relief for able-bodied persons outside workhouses, the Bill re-enacts in specific terms some of the most obnoxious provisions of the old poor law.  Those of us who have been interested in this question will remember that there was a Commission set up in 1906, of which a Senator, Sir Edward Bigger, was a member. That Commission made special reference in its report to the work of an earlier Commission, an Irish Commission set up and consisting mainly of Irishmen in 1836, and which clearly reported in a direction which was a contrary to the prevailing view regarding the poor law in England, and contrasted in its report between the state of things in England which the English poor law was adopted to remedy and the state of things in Ireland.  The Irish Commission reported quite clearly in specific terms that the conditions were very different, and implied in its report that the law which might be considered to be requisite in England at that time was not applicable to Ireland, but the Government of the time decided in favour of applying the English poor law system to Irish conditions, and passed a Bill in 1838 adopting the English poor law system for Ireland quite in the face of every exponent of what was desirable and necessary, and in the teeth of the recommendations of the Irish Commission. Some of the provisions of that obnoxious Poor Law Act, which everyone interested in poor law reform in this country has denounced, have been inserted in this Bill.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I take special exception to the reintroduction of the words &ldquo;destitute poor person.&rdquo;  In Section 2 boards of guardians may relieve outside the workhouses any destitute poor person who could not heretofore have been relieved by them.  I think it is true to say that there has been, even before the adoption of the county <Col N="260" /> schemes, a gradual getting away from the insistence upon destitution as a condition of relief.  Under the Medical Charities Act in practice throughout the country, but not everywhere to the same degree, insistance upon destitution has not been made necessary.  We are now asked in this Bill to re-enact in specific terms the obnoxious words &ldquo;destitute poor person.&rdquo;  What is the effect of that?  It is that the relieving officer, whatever he may have done in the past for the relief of persons who are not destitute, must now see&mdash;for the Dáil and Seanad have re-enacted it&mdash;that destitution must be a condition of relief, which may mean in practice that the man or woman who has a few sticks of furniture in the house or a few pictures will have to sell them, if they are saleable, before he can get relief.  It was the practice for many long years that a person who had any saleable goods could not receive poor law relief.  We are asked in this Act to re-enact these very words, which is an indication to the relieving officer that unless he can satisfy himself the applicant for relief is destitute he may legally refuse to give relief.  I think that is a great blot in the Bill.  I hope the Minister will embody in the Bill such amendments as will bring the law in Dublin into line with the rest of the country, that is to say, that a person eligible for relief would be a person who is unable by his own industry or other lawful means to provide for himself and his dependents the necessaries of life, or medical or surgical treatment.  That is a very great difference, and unless the Minister tells me in so many words that this Bill cannot become law this year unless it is enacted without amendment I shall certainly attempt to amend it in the direction I have indicated.</P>
    <P>I think that Section 4 is dangerous, and may be used in a sense which is not intended by the Bill. It enables boards of guardians to use the poor law for purposes which are no doubt not intended by the Bill, but would be distinctly obnoxious <Col N="261" /> to the general community&mdash;I mean that where a board of guardians is empowered to enter into any work of public utility on behalf of any person or public authority, the board may become public contractors employing persons in receipt of relief to do work of any kind for anybody, provided that it can be brought within the term of &ldquo;public utility.&rdquo;  A public utility is not defined. There is a very wide range of operations which may come under that term, &ldquo;public utility,&rdquo; which, if the guardians were to enter upon, would well be treated as being in competition with private industry, and in fact merely be the substitution of a man who was out for a man who was in, not relieving employment to any extent and not touching the problem.</P>
    <P>In fact, Section 4, to my mind, appears to be an attempt to tackle the problem of unemployment from the standpoint of poor law, which is an entirely wrong way to tackle the problem.  There has been a good deal of agitation on other aspects of this Bill as far as it affects Dublin, and I must say that the agitation sounds very false and empty to me. I have had, as I presume every other Senator has had, this morning a circular letter containing certain provisions of what the circular states is an agreed Bill passing through the British Parliament in regard to settlement&mdash;the transfer of persons from one part of the country to their native place.  It would appear from the circular issued from the Chamber of Commerce that this is some new proposal which has been generally agreed upon in England, and, therefore, should be accepted in Ireland, but the authors of the circular do not appear to appreciate the fact that the Bill that is now being discussed by a Joint Committee of the House of Commons and the House of Lords is a Bill for consolidating the existing Acts.  It is for the exclusive purpose of the consolidation of the existing Acts of Parliament. This consolidation process is merely preparatory to the introduction of new legislation.  What the Chamber <Col N="262" /> of Commerce seeks to suggest as something new is merely, in fact, re-enacting in a consolidated form what has been the practice in England and Wales for probably 60 or 70 years.</P>
    <P>In any case, conditions in England and Wales are very different indeed from conditions in this country and the provisions regarding settlement in England are clearly intended to deal with vagrants.  The problem we are dealing with is not the problem of vagrancy.  It is the problem of men who would normally be working if employment were available, but who owing to continuous disability arising from unemployment, are unable to maintain themselves and their families in decency, and in respect of the other Section&mdash;the sick, the disabled and the unfit&mdash;we desire that they should be relieved outside the workhouse where they can be&mdash;and they usually can&mdash;more cheaply relieved than inside the institution.  This is not a problem of vagrancy at all and, therefore, the circular of the Chamber of Commerce has really no effect with regard to conditions in this country.  I hope that the Minister will be able to give us some assurances that he is prepared to modify the form of this Bill in respect of this question of destitution, and also that he will agree to insert in the Bill, if he can give us some assurance that it is likely to be considered by the Dáil, that no person eligible for relief shall be relieved in any institution provided or maintained by the Board of Guardians, unless he can be relieved effectively in such institution at less cost than in any other lawful way.  Both these provisions that I have spoken of are already the law in every other part of the country except Dublin county and city, and inasmuch as they have been embodied in every scheme for the rest of the country I think they may reasonably be embodied in this Bill, so long as there is an intention to enlarge on the simple proposition contained in the Bill sent from the Seanad to the Dáil.  Having extended to some extent the proposals <Col N="263" /> of the Seanad Bill I am hopeful that the Minister will agree, at least, to embody these two portions of the general scheme of Poor Law in the Bill which is to apply to Dublin.</P>
    <Speaker pid="SamuelBrownKC" hpid="Mr. Brown Mr. Brown">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Brown</NameTxt>
      <P>Unfortunately this is a necessary Bill and I think the question that this House will have to consider is to what extent, if any, are we justified in inserting any amendments.  With reference to the point that Senator Johnson made about the description of the persons who are to be eligible for relief under this Bill, I am afraid both he and I, and other Senators who backed the small Bill in the Seanad before the Recess are guilty of the very same crime of restriction as there is in this Bill, because when we come back to the Bill which was introduced by Senator Johnson and backed by Senator Sir Edward Bigger and others we find that the persons who were described as the persons who were to be entitled to outdoor relief under that Bill are the persons who were eligible for it, that is, eligible for it under the then existing law for relieving poor persons.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. Johnson Mr. Johnson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Johnson</NameTxt>
      <P>I would ask the Senator to realise that there has been a usage to get away from the destitution that has been recommended specifically in these words.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SamuelBrownKC" hpid="Mr. Brown Mr. Brown">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Brown</NameTxt>
      <P>I agree, but as a matter of strict definition the Senator is only partly responsible for it. I admit my own share of responsibility. I join with Senator Johnson very cordially in hoping that the Minister will alter the definition in this Bill, not only for the purpose of getting rid of the rather unpleasant nature of the definition, but also for the purpose of extending it in a proper and legitimate way to persons who are entitled to relief.  I do not know whether the definition as given by Senator Johnson would satisfy the Minister or not, but some definition can be got which will take away from this Bill the unpleasant reference to the destitute <Col N="264" /> poor.  The House will remember the object of the short Bill which was introduced last June which passed through this House and was held up in the Dáil.  The object of that Bill was to render legal in the Dublin Union what had been done illegally by the Poor Law Commissioners who were giving outdoor relief.  They had been doing this for some time and had been expending very large sums of money.  I have forgotten the exact sum, but it ran into something like £90,000.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General Mulcahy General Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>General Mulcahy</NameTxt>
      <P>Oh. no.  The amount disallowed by the auditor up to 31st March of this year was £8,000 odd.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SamuelBrownKC" hpid="Mr. Brown Mr. Brown">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Brown</NameTxt>
      <P>I thought it was very much more than that.  Of course, that is what was surcharged by the auditor.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General Mulcahy General Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>General Mulcahy</NameTxt>
      <P>He surcharged everything.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. Johnson Mr. Johnson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Johnson</NameTxt>
      <P>Up to what date was that audit?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General Mulcahy General Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>General Mulcahy</NameTxt>
      <P>I think the 31st March of this year.  I will be able to supply the date later.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SamuelBrownKC" hpid="Mr. Brown Mr. Brown">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Brown</NameTxt>
      <P>At any rate that was the object of the Bill, to render legal &mdash;a perfectly justifiable thing owing to the necessity of the case&mdash;the expenditure incurred by the Commissioners in granting outdoor relief to persons not strictly entitled to get it because they were not in the Union. That was quite right, and it went as far as we thought it was then necessary to go.  The present Bill goes far and away beyond that.  How far it goes, if no limit is put on the amount which can be expended under the Bill, nobody can say.  I think the real question for this House when considering this Bill in Committee will be: &ldquo;Should we put any limit on the expenditure which can be made by the Commissioners, and if so, what should that limit be,&rdquo; or are we going to give absolute <i>carte blanche</i> to the Commissioners for expenditure on relief?  The Bill is only a temporary one and comes to an <Col N="265" /> end in March, 1931.  It covers one year or a little more.  It is a temporary Bill, with a promise by the Minister that the question will be reconsidered at the end of that time, and that probably permanent legislation will then be considered.  To my mind, that makes it all the more advisable that there should be some limit to the expenditure.  This is an experiment.  We know that there is an absolute necessity for the Bill. These unfortunate people must be relieved.  But are we justified in not putting some limit to that relief? Let us see, by putting some reasonable limit in this Bill, how the Commissioners will work under a Bill with a limit for this short trial between this and March, 1931, and having tried the experiment we would know whether it would be right to give the Commissioners or the poor law guardians in the future a perfectly free hand in the matter of outdoor relief, or whether it will be necessary to put into permanent legislation a limit to be put on them by the Minister which they could not exceed without the consent of the Minister.  He would then be able to look into the peculiar circumstances of the time and grant permission to go beyond the limit.  But whether it is temporary in this legislation, which we are dealing with now, or in the permanent legislation which will be dealt with hereafter, in my opinion there ought to be some limit to the amount of rate which the Commissioners or the poor law guardians will be entitled to spend for the purpose of outdoor relief.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelComynKC" hpid="Mr. Comyn Mr. Comyn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Comyn</NameTxt>
      <P>There is a limit in this Bill, a very strict and a very rigid limit, and the limitation is contained in the word &ldquo;destitution.&rdquo; No person is to be relieved unless he is a destitute poor person.  The speech of Senator Brown seems to be contradictory, because on the one hand he wants an extension of that defination and, on the other hand, he wants to dry up the sources of supply.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SamuelBrownKC" hpid="Mr. Brown Mr. Brown">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Brown</NameTxt>
      <P>Certainly not.  I said a reasonable limit.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="266" />
    <Speaker pid="MichaelComynKC" hpid="Mr. Comyn Mr. Comyn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Comyn</NameTxt>
      <P>A reasonable limit fixed by the amount of the rate or a reasonable limit fixed by the state of destitution?  I am in favour of a reasonable limit being fixed by the state of destitution of the poor, and no other limit, because the destitute poor have, and always have had, first charge on the resources of a particular area.  That is not new law; it is old law.  In regard to the defination of destitution, I think the statement of Senator Johnson rather confined the meaning too much.  I think that destitution is arrived at long before the bed is sold.  However, if there are any doubts on that point, I would urge the Minister, if it is feasible at the moment, to have such a defination as will sanction the practice already adopted, if that is possible.  If it is not possible, I think the word &ldquo;destitution&rdquo; itself is capable of a more liberal construction, and I am sure the officials will give it that liberal construction.</P>
      <P>There was another point in the speech of Senator Johnson that alarmed me at first&mdash;namely, that it seemed to the Senator that there was some possibility that under this Bill work would be given which would put men now in employment out of employment.  Of course, that would be entirely wrong, because it would increase the ranks of the destitute.  On looking more closely into Section 4, I think the doubt that Senator Johnson had in his mind is provided against, because if you read the clause&mdash;</P>
      <P>For the purpose of the provision of work under this section a board of guardians may&mdash;</P>
      <P>(a) contract with any person or body of persons for the performance by the board for or on behalf of such person or body of persons of any work of public utility undertaken for the purpose of providing additional employment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>It seems to me that the new work must be for the purpose of providing additional employment, and upon a fair construction of the last words in the paragraph, I think it is quite <Col N="267" /> impossible, under the provision of this Bill, to put workmen who are employed at present out of employment. Therefore, I would be satisfied with that section as it stands, particularly as I am most anxious that this Bill should not be lost.  If there is any fear that by any amendments of ours we would lose this Bill, I would much prefer that it should go through the Seanad without any alteration.  Like Senator Brown and Senator Johnson, I have a preference for the Bill which we sent to the Dáil.  I suppose that is only natural, but taking a fair view of this Bill, perhaps there are some things in it which are an improvement on the Bill we sent down.  Perhaps it will be possible by agreement to give legislative sanction to the custom that has grown up in reference to the meaning of destitution. If it is not possible to do that, I would be prepared to rely on the good sense of the persons who will have to administer the Bill.</P>
    <Speaker pid="RichardWilson" hpid="Mr. Wilson Mr. Wilson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Wilson</NameTxt>
      <P>I am pleased that this Bill has come before the House because it focussed the attention of the people of the metropolis to the laws that have hitherto been in existence in connection with the relief of the poor all over the State. Those who are now criticising the provisions of this Bill had very little sympathy with the ratepayers in the rest of the country who were bearing this burden.  Now when the people of Dublin are asked to bear it they strenuously object.  Senator Brown wants a limit.  We would not have heard anything about the limit if the Bill did not apply to the city of Dublin.  What I want to get at is this, that we are trying through the poor law to bring about a reform and a service which is really as much a national service as Old Age Pensions.  The poor law is being used and the people who pay rates are bearing the expense of a service that should be borne by the community at large.  If that was the arrangement we would not have this question of a two-years residential qualification raised.  I object <Col N="268" /> strongly to the two years residential qualification being inserted in the Bill because it is not provided that it will be reciprocal, that if a Dublin person is being helped in another county, there is no provision in the Bill by which that charge can be placed on Dublin, or by which a person can be sent to Dublin.  It only applies to the outsider unemployed in Dublin who needs relief. I do not think that is fair.  I will vote for the Bill because it is a necessary one, but I would point out that we have been carrying on this service for five or six years in other parts of the country.  It is only right that the city of Dublin should do its duty as well as other parts. This Bill brings out clearly the necessity for a revision of the law so that this service which hitherto has been borne by the ratepayers should be borne by the national Exchequer. It is a service identical with Old Age Pensions and should be a national charge.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasFarren" hpid="Mr. Farren Mr. Farren">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Farren</NameTxt>
      <P>The necessity for the introduction of this Bill is a strong condemnation of the present system of society.  It should have been introduced in 1923 when similar provisions applied to other parts of the country.  Since 1923 thousands of families in Dublin have been suffering untold misery because they could hardly get sufficient to keep them alive.  After six years during which they have been deprived of the benefits that the people in other parts of the country got there is an outcry against the introduction of this Bill.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Several reasons have been given why this Bill should not be passed in its present form.  Every section pretends to be in sympathy with the principle of the Bill, and with the poor people who are starving in their homes in the city of Dublin and the surrounding areas, and considers that they should be relieved but that it should be at somebody else's expense.  That is exactly the position that is taken up.  Nobody will say &ldquo;we are opposed to the principle of the Bill, that these people should be relieved but the <Col N="269" /> other fellow should pay.&rdquo;  That has been the line of argument.  I confess that from its first introduction I have read all the discussions that took place and I am not very much wiser.  The appalling fact is before us in the statement made by a person who ought to be the best authority in Dublin, Dr. Dwyer, the Chairman of the Dublin Union Commissioners, before the Chamber of Commerce on October 22nd, in which he stated emphatically that there were at least 5,000 families in Dublin and in the surrounding districts who could not be relieved under the existing law. The Poor Law Authorities were prevented from relieving them.  That is a dreadful state of affairs and it has been going on since 1923.  This Bill was introduced for the purpose of endeavouring to come to the assistance of people who have not enough to eat.  I support the Bill; I could not do otherwise, but there are certain provisions in it which are not entirely to my satisfaction. Everything depends on the manner in which the Bill is administered. With regard to Section 2&mdash;the destitute poor person&mdash;I have gone to the trouble of looking up the dictionary to see what is the meaning of the word &ldquo;destitute,&rdquo; I find that a destitute person means a person in need of food, clothing and shelter.  If it is humanely administered Section 2 will be all right, but if it is not humanely administered it will be all wrong.  If there is a decent unemployed man and his family in a tenement in Dublin and if he has a few sticks of furniture that he does not like to part with he will not be destitute until he sells every stick. If a relieving officer is a humane man, as I believe most of these officials are, and if he finds a few sticks of furniture, bed clothes and other things in a house where the man is unemployed and without means of procuring the food necessary to keep body and soul, if Section 2 is administered humanely, as I expect and hope it will be, I will have no complaint.</P>
    <P>Another section that in my opinion is not satisfactory is Section 4, <Col N="270" /> not that I disagree with employment being found for people who are able to work, because in my opinion, the proper solution of the whole problem is to provide useful employment for the whole people so that there would be no necessity for a Relief Bill at all.  There has been too much relief in this country for a long time. It was introduced under the old poor law system to pauperise the people for all time.  If Section 4 is properly administered I have no objection to it.  There are dangers there which we see, and we have seen them before, but everything depends on how it is administered. I am not going to waste any time in talking about residence qualifications and those other matters that have been raised, because any poor person who is driven from home and has to look for employment in another place, should be given bread if he is needy.  When we say our prayers we promise to love our neighbours as ourselves.  If we love our neighbours as ourselves we should give to the poor what is necessary to keep body and soul together.  All these other matters are only side issues.  The big problem is there&mdash;these 5,000 families without the means of subsistence in this Christian city of Dublin.  That problem has been there for years; we have repeatedly called attention to it in this House.  I am glad that at last something is being done to meet the situation.  Nobody could dream of opposing this Bill.  As I have said, certain of the details might be altered, but no matter what happens, this Bill must go through as speedily as possible in order that the suffering of the poor people may not be continued one hour longer than can be avoided.</P>
    <Speaker pid="EdwardBigger" hpid="Sir E. Coey Bigger Sir E. Coey Bigger">
      <NameTxt>Sir E. Coey Bigger</NameTxt>
      <P>I support this Bill.  I would appeal to the Minister, with reference to what Senator Johnson has said, to try to find a better term than &ldquo;destitute poor.&rdquo;  It is all very well to leave the interpretation of the term to those who will be administering this Bill, but I would much rather see a proper definition in the Bill.  In some other Acts, certainly <Col N="271" /> in the Medical Charities Act, the term is &ldquo;poor person&rdquo; and not &ldquo;destitute person.&rdquo;  When the poor law was established by the Act of 1838 a destitute poor person could only be relieved in the workhouse. That was afterwards extended and outdoor relief became available, but it was given mostly on a doctor's certificate that the person was ill and could not be removed, or something of that sort.  The amount of the relief that was given was very small, very often 3/6 or 4/- a week, not at all sufficient for a family, and it rarely ever went beyond 7/6 a week. I would like a much more liberal interpretation here.  We know that in the city of Dublin there are a very large number of destitute people, people who are on the verge of starvation.  I hope that this Bill will remedy that state of things.  At the same time, as Senator Brown suggested, it might be possible to put in a limit, not a limit as to the amount of the relief given, but as to the amount of the rate that might be levied.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JanePower" hpid="Mrs. Wyse Power Mrs. Wyse Power">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Wyse Power</NameTxt>
      <P>I hope that the House will not listen to any soft talk for limiting the amount to be distributed to the destitute poor, for the reason that it cannot be done.  No matter how willing you may be to limit it, undoubtedly no limit could be put into the Bill under any circumstances. Every case must be settled on its own merits.  How would you make a limit in the case of exceptional cases?  The work of the Commissioners for the past four or five years is a very strong earnest that they are not going to give too much away, and I believe that they will not do so.  They will have control of this matter for about fifteen months, and even if they are to go at the end of that period, I do not think that they will run riot with the citizens' money.  As a citizen and a ratepayer of Dublin I think that this Bill is overdue, that we should have had it some time ago, and I can only add that I hope that the passing of piffling or minor amendments will <Col N="272" /> not prevent the Bill from becoming law immediately.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDouglas" hpid="Mr. Douglas Mr. Douglas">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Douglas</NameTxt>
      <P>I agree very largely with Senator Brown, but I differ entirely from Senator Farren when he suggests virtual insincerity in those who say that they support the Bill, but doubt whether the whole of the charge should necessarily be borne by the city of Dublin.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasFarren" hpid="Mr. Farren Mr. Farren">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Farren</NameTxt>
      <P>I did not say that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDouglas" hpid="Mr. Douglas Mr. Douglas">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Douglas</NameTxt>
      <P>I apologise if I am wrong, but I understood from Senator Farren that he believed those who were in favour of a limit as to the amount which might be charged on the Dublin rates were pretending that they were in favour of the principle of the Bill.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasFarren" hpid="Mr. Farren Mr. Farren">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Farren</NameTxt>
      <P>I never referred to the area of charge at all.  I never even mentioned it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDouglas" hpid="Mr. Douglas Mr. Douglas">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Douglas</NameTxt>
      <P>I am sorry if I accused the Senator wrongly.  There certainly is in this House a general acceptance of the principle of the Bill.  That, I am satisfied, is perfectly sincere on all sides.  There is, at the same time, in the city of Dublin a certain amount of panic, probably unjustifiable, but genuinely there.  Senator Wilson's remarks very largely support what I want to suggest to the Minister, that is, that some way should be found, not for limiting the amount of necessary relief which this Bill will involve, but for limiting the amount which will be charged to the city of Dublin, at any rate until the matter has been further considered.  I think it possible that a way might be found by which, as soon as the Commissioners responsible were satisfied that a figure of 2/- or 2/6 in the £ will have to be added to the rates, that a report should be made to the Minister, and that the matter should be again considered.  There is no question about being in favour of the principle of the Bill and hoping that somebody else will pay.  Whether this charge is paid for by Dublin, by Wicklow, or by anywhere else, it has got to be paid by the people, and <Col N="273" /> there is no use in thinking that we can get out of it.  It has got to be paid by the ratepayers or by the taxpayers, and the only question is whether an unlimited amount will be charged on the ratepayers.  I think that the charge on the ratepayers should be limited, and that the balance should be paid by the taxpayers.  It would be outside our functions to move an amendment proposing to put a certain amount of the charge on the Central Fund, but I think there might be some way of inserting an amendment requiring a special report to be made when a certain sum had been reached, so that the matter could be again considered by the Dáil and the Seanad.</P>
      <P>I quite disagree with the feeling that some people seem to have, that because you doubt the wisdom of placing an unlimited charge on the city of Dublin you are necessarily opposed to the principle of the Bill itself.  When the previous Bill was before a Committee of this House&mdash; I was not a member of the Committee &mdash;the impression I got from members of the Committee was that we were largely legalising a principle which had been applied illegally, or with somewhat doubtful legality, by the Commissioners, and that that might lead to some increase on the rates, but a comparatively small increase. That would probably have been the impression still prevailing but for statements made by one of the Commissioners which suggested that the sum would be a very large one. Because I do think that there is a great deal of genuine anxiety in the matter I hope that the Minister will deal with the possible cost.  I know that it is impossible to gauge it accurately, but I would very much like to know his Department's view in regard to it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOFarrell" hpid="Mr. O'Farrell Mr. O'Farrell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Farrell</NameTxt>
      <P>I am glad to see that in this discussion we have not reproduced the rather crude arguments that have been advanced against this Bill elsewhere and in the public Press.  The only argument that might be said partly to restrict the operations of this Bill was the suggestion of Senator Brown, and <Col N="274" /> also of Senator Douglas, that a limitation should be placed upon the amount of money to be spent under the Bill.  I cannot see any justification whatever for imposing a restriction in the case of Dublin when no such restriction is imposed in the rest of the country.  It can only be an attempt to enable Dublin city and county to get out of its responsibilities in this respect.  The arguments advanced in support of that line of action have been to the effect that Dublin, being a capital city, has more than its due proportion of destitute people, that Dublin is the Mecca of the unemployed and the destitute generally, that, consequently, it has an abnormal proportion of destitute people from other districts, and that the city and county should not be called upon to meet the cost of that abnormal influx of destitute people.</P>
      <P>It may be true that Dublin has an undue proportion of destitute people, but it is also true that Dublin has an equally undue proportion of pretty well-to-do people and of members of the professions.  The population of Dublin city and townships represents sixteen per cent. of the total population of the Saorstát. If we examine its proportions of the professions we will find that as compared with the whole country it is very remarkable.  There is in the city and townships 54 per cent. of the whole of the civil servants. Forty-two per cent. of civil servants work away from the places where they were born.  The taxpayers as a whole pay the civil servants, but 54 per cent. of the total live in Dublin city and townships, spend their money there, and in that way add to the prosperity of the district. Of the barristers, a very important section of the community from the viewpoint of earning capacity, 65 per cent. of the total are allotted to Dublin city and townships.  The solicitors, another important section of the community have 36 per cent. of their number in the same district. There are 30 per cent. of the medical profession and 43 per cent. of the dentists in the same district.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="275" />
    <Speaker pid="RichardWilson" hpid="Mr. Wilson Mr. Wilson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Wilson</NameTxt>
      <P>How many clergymen?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOFarrell" hpid="Mr. O'Farrell Mr. O'Farrell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Farrell</NameTxt>
      <P>I have no particulars in regard to the clergy.  There are 57 per cent. of the chartered accountants, and of shopkeepers there are 33 per cent. in Dublin city and townships.  Generally speaking, if one goes down the list of the professions one finds that in most cases the big majority are living here, but in all cases considerably more than 16 per cent. of them, which would represent the proportion that Dublin city and county should have if it were a matter of their due proportion in accordance with population, are living here.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDouglas" hpid="Mr. Douglas Mr. Douglas">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Douglas</NameTxt>
      <P>Does the Senator know how the rates here compare with the rates outside?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOFarrell" hpid="Mr. O'Farrell Mr. O'Farrell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Farrell</NameTxt>
      <P>It is quite possible that the rates here are as high as in most other places, but the capacity to pay per head of ratepayer is infinitely greater here than in other places, so that the actual amount per pound of the rates is no indication of the highness or otherwise of the rates.  A destitute person could not pay a penny in the pound, while a well-to-do person might pay twenty shillings in the pound and still be able to live well.  How can you place any restriction on the amount if you are going to adopt a certain principle for the relief of distress? You must either provide the money that is necessary for the relief of every person that is entitled to it or you must leave a number who are not to be provided for.  Then why should we seek to pass a vote of lack of confidence in the City Commissioners, seeing that every other local authority in the country, whether managed by elected representatives or by commissioners, is trusted not to run amok in the allocation of relief to the destitute?  If the definition mentioned by Senator Johnson were applied to the term &ldquo;destitute poor person&rdquo; it would be nothing short of criminal lunacy to insist that a destitute person would have to sell his few sticks of <Col N="276" /> furniture before he could get any relief.  It would mean that he would have to sell these poor articles at a sacrifice, less even than they were worth, and goodness knows when he would ever be able to purchase them back again.  As Senator Sir Edward Bigger has said, it would be much better for us to put in a proper definition rather than to leave to be interpreted by relieving officers, commissioners and others what &ldquo;destitute poor&rdquo; means.  If the term means what Senator Johnson said it would simply be sticking to a formula which had its origin in the distant past and in circumstances totally different from those operating to-day, and it would be utter foolishness for us to try to adhere to that in the present Bill.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="HonJameson" hpid="Mr. Jameson Mr. Jameson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Jameson</NameTxt>
      <P>Several of the speeches made to-day would seem to imply that we were discussing a permanent Bill, but the view that many of us take is that this Bill is of an entirely temporary nature, dealing with a state of affairs which exists at present, and I have no doubt, dealing with it on the advice of the Commissioners, who know the needs of the situation.  I hope that the Minister will be able to deal with the question of what the probable cost of this will be, whether it may cost five shillings in the pound or may cost more than one shilling. There are figures which, of course, could have been obtained.  It is perfectly certain that the Commissioners know the number of families that they will like to relieve.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasFarren" hpid="Mr. Farren Mr. Farren">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Farren</NameTxt>
      <P>Five thousand is what has been stated to be the number.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="HonJameson" hpid="Mr. Jameson Mr. Jameson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Jameson</NameTxt>
      <P>Take five thousand. It is quite easy to calculate what it will cost if there are five thousand families to be relieved and if you know how much they will be given each week.  It is quite easy to know exactly how many shillings in the pound it will cost, but before the Minister asks us to sign a blank cheque he should be able to give us some idea as to the amount of money that will be required.  Senator <Col N="277" /> Farren seems to think that there are some of us who do not wish to run up rates to relieve the poor.  It is not use talking like that at this time of day.  As Senator Douglas said, we have got to support the destitue poor as we cannot leave them starving.  There is wisdom, however, in considering the cost of such a measure because if we had Commissioners who would recklessly spend money the matter is one that would weigh heavily on the citizens of Dublin.  The whole House has spoken with one voice in saying that the Commissioners are excellent people who will do their job well.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasFarren" hpid="Mr. Farren Mr. Farren">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Farren</NameTxt>
      <P>From the ratepayers point of view.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="HonJameson" hpid="Mr. Jameson Mr. Jameson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Jameson</NameTxt>
      <P>Of course, if I considered that I got hard treatment from them I would not take the same point of view, but they are going to deal out justice.  As this is a temporary measure, I do not think that we need say things which we would say if a permanent measure were under consideration.  I would like Senators to consider that in the city of Dublin employment depends in great measure on the rates, and when a big measure like this comes up to be considered, if Dublin is excessively rated, a great many businesses will be ruined.  We should not, therefore, go on drawing blank cheques, and if we are going to give relief out of the rates, we should have an estimate of the probable cost.  I am sure that that is what Senator Brown means.  If we know that extra relief will be required, it ought to be left to the Minister to sanction that extra relief, and not to allow illegalities to go on, as they did in the past, where relief was absolutely required and had to be given.  There are two phrases that are pretty bad in this Bill.  One is &ldquo;destitute&rdquo; and the other is &ldquo;at their discretion.&rdquo;  I dare say that the Commissioners are well able to take care of themselves and to judge the cases properly, but if it is known by people that there is no limit to the amount of money which the Commissioners can spend, I would not like to be in the Commissioners' <Col N="278" /> shoes if I had to say &ldquo;No,&rdquo; because when you know that you are appealing to a man who can draw an unlimited amount of money, your application takes a different tone.  We do not know what amount of money will be required.  We are trusting the Commissioners to deal justly with it, and only relieve people who really require relief, and not to waste money.  I am not at all sure that we ought in any way to alter the wording of the Bill because it is a temporary measure, and we trust the people who will administer it.  If, however, it was a permanent measure, and if we were entrusting its administration to bodies about which we know nothing, it would be a bad measure to pass.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="AlfredByrne" hpid="Mr. Byrne Mr. Byrne">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Byrne</NameTxt>
      <P>When we hear the Minister's definition of the meaning of the word &ldquo;destitute,&rdquo; can we speak afterwards?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Cathaoirleach Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I would like to get the debate finished before the Minister speaks, but if there is any particular point he wishes to raise afterwards, I will not prevent the Senator from speaking.  Does he wish to speak now?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="AlfredByrne" hpid="Mr. Byrne Mr. Byrne">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Byrne</NameTxt>
      <P>I would like to say a word afterwards.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General Mulcahy General Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>General Mulcahy</NameTxt>
      <P>I would like to brush aside at once any false interpretation that might be put on the words &ldquo;temporary measure.&rdquo;  This measure is only temporary in the same sense that the Local Government (Temporary Provisions) Act, 1923 is temporary.  It extends to the city and county of Dublin a principle which as national policy has been accepted and in force throughout the rest of the country, namely, that you can relieve the able-bodied destitute poor outside the workhouses, the workhouses having been abolished in places other than the city and county of Dublin. I hope that when speaking of this as a temporary measure no one will get it into his head or into the heads of others, that relief of the able-bodied poor will only be given this year, next year, or the year after.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="279" />
    <Speaker pid="ThomasFarren" hpid="Mr. Farren Mr. Farren">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Farren</NameTxt>
      <P>The liability stops in 1931.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General Mulcahy General Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>General Mulcahy</NameTxt>
      <P>It does not.  I would like to say in regard to that point that I put the year 1931 into the Bill because I had a fairly reasonable anticipation that we would be able to deal with the major measure before March, 1931.  I may not be able to do that and so I was anxious to put in 1932 in order to save parliamentary time.  I am, however, leaving 1931 to stand.  I realise that it is a very serious problem to put before the Commissioners, in the first place, to administer a measure of this particular kind and to lay on the shoulders of the citizens of Dublin the financial responsibility of dealing with such a problem as we have here.  We have been asked for an estimate.  I do not know the extent to which relief may have to be given under this Bill.  I say that to take a figure out of the Commissioners' mouths for, say, June or July of this particular year and that to double, treble, or multiply it by ten, as some of our public persons and some sections of the Press have been doing, is not the way to arrive at an estimate.  Before the Commissioners advise the Corporation what rate will be required they will have to consider the matter before the 15th January and will have to say, if they can, the amount of money that will be required. They may delay it longer to examine the matter further.  After a practical examination of the cases of applicants they may require further time to state what their requirements will be, but we can neither assist ourselves, the Commissioners, the poor, nor the ratepayers by pretending that we can make an estimate at the moment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>What I say is that this particular type of relief has been in operation in Cork and Waterford practically since 1925, and that for the last four years the increase in the amount of outdoor relief to-day has not shown itself to be anything like the proportionate increase such as the figures quoted in various quarters would suggest.  But, whatever it is, the <Col N="280" /> situation has to be examined carefully, faced boldly and dealt with.  I think that Senator Brown does himself an injustice when he says that he co-operated in the introduction of the original Seanad Bill to overcome the illegalities of the Commissioners. There was no illegality.  There may have been a doubtful legality inasmuch as from November, 1927, realising a certain position in the city, the Commissioners extended, with the permission of the Minister for Local Government, the interpretation of provisional relief and such relief as has been given outside the distinct terms of the Act to able-bodied persons has been given as provisional relief.</P>
    <P>The Auditor's report which has been mentioned dealt with two years down to 31st March, 1929.  As far as this particular type of provisional relief is concerned, not more than five full quarters with perhaps a month or two added were affected, and the total amount expended in respect of these six quarters was £8,700 6s. 11d.  So that the Senator hardly does himself justice when he suggested that the original measure of relief, in a particular situation, was of doubtful legality.  I think he will recognise that the extension to the city and county of Dublin of the provisions that operated in other parts of the country was necessary. I do not think that anybody in the Seanad would want to argue against that.</P>
    <P>Senator Johnson takes exception to the definition of the word &ldquo;destitute.&rdquo; If the word &ldquo;destitute&rdquo; is going to prevent a person getting relief under the Bill, unless he sells the last stick of furniture or even the second, third or fourth last stick of furniture, I am not going to leave it in the Bill, but I would suggest at this stage, at any rate, that the word &ldquo;destitute&rdquo; in the Bill will have no such effect and that &ldquo;destitute poor person&rdquo; is a description which can be legally applied to a person who is in any way unable to provide himself through his own lawful labour with the necessary sustenance or to provide himself and his dependents with the necessaries of life generally.</P>
    <Col N="281" />
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. Johnson Mr. Johnson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Johnson</NameTxt>
      <P>Do you agree to delete it?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General Mulcahy General Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>General Mulcahy</NameTxt>
      <P>If I am assured that the word &ldquo;destitute&rdquo; has not that effect, I would not be prepared, when we know it will not affect the situation, to recall the Dáil in order to get an amendment like that inserted in the Bill, as it is desired to have the terms of the Bill operative in the city at the earliest possible moment.  I suggest that the Senator would not wish to do that either. If, in fact, the presence of the word &ldquo;destitute&rdquo; will restrict an able-bodied person in the city from getting relief in a way in which he would not be restricted in other parts of the country, I would be prepared to take the word out.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. Johnson Mr. Johnson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Johnson</NameTxt>
      <P>Would the Minister also consider the relieving officer's power in the matter and his legal liabilities?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General Mulcahy General Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>General Mulcahy</NameTxt>
      <P>Certainly, every aspect of it.  With regard to Section 4, I feel disposed to subscribe wholeheartedly to the Senator's statement when he says that you cannot attempt to deal with unemployment as a problem through the relief system. There is no intention in this measure in any way to do so.  An attempt has been made to suggest that this matter has been discussed as a provision of relief for unemployment, but I have never faced it in any way like that.  I realise that there is between normal industry in the country with its present organisation and its employing power, and relief pure and simple, an area over which employment has to be organised. I am inclined to agree with Senator Johnson that the relief authorities cannot organise that, and I would ask the Seanad to accept it, that the powers sought for in this particular measure are powers which, in the first place, can hardly be very much utilised.  I want the machinery put into the hands of the Commissioners to enable them to get work for a particular class of person who will be seeking relief and whom it will be a charity to employ rather than to <Col N="282" /> give him relief.  I do not think that even the critics of the proposals in this particular measure seriously believe that if there is anything sinister or that there can be any effective barrier under the measure, to prejudice the position in ordinary employment of people who might expect to earn their living by ordinary employment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>On the general question that has been raised, with regard to the charge, settlement, and so on, I would like to refer to the matter which has already been referred to by Senator Johnson.  That is the suggestion coming forward from the Chamber of Commerce with regard to this question.  I find it rather difficult to comment on the present communication from the Chamber of Commerce.  As Senator Johnson suggested, there is at present before the British House of Lords a measure arising out of an Act passed in 1927.  The real consolidating Act of the poor laws in Great Britain was the Act of 1927.  The present Act is simply bringing the consolidated poor laws into conformity with the new changes that are taking place in the organisation of the poor law authorities in Great Britain.  We are referred to this great find by the Chamber of Commerce as enshrining the tremendous experience of a country that has such a long tradition in giving poor relief, and we are asked to enshrine in our poor relief system here the idea of settlements. The whole position has been fully described in the majority and the minority reports of the British Poor Law Commission published in 1909. I said before that the introduction of this matter is going back to the flood.  Our poor law system was introduced in 1838.  British intelligence as to the utility of the Law of Settlement in England, at that particular time in 1838, was so enlightened that, although they applied the British Poor Law system to Ireland in that year, they left out the provisions with regard to settlements, and we never had a law of settlement here in this country. Tradition and vested interests of one kind and another have prevented <Col N="283" /> them, year after year, in England from getting rid of the idea of settlements.  At a dozen different times in a dozen different ways, different bodies and different persons have tried to get rid of it.  So much has been said about it that without going into the scathing comments of the minority report on the subject, or even the very vital discussion of the matter by the majority report, I just want to read a short paragraph from the majority report, which says:&mdash;</P>
    <P>Theoretically, there is much to be said in favour of the proposal to abolish the Law of Settlement and Removal.  From a practical point of view, however, there is much to be said against its entire abolition, and, accordingly, until experience has been gained of the work of our new organisation of Public Assistance we think it better to retain the law, but in a modified and simplified form.  The specific recommendations we make are:&mdash;</P>
    <P>(a)  That the county or county borough shall be the area for all purposes of settlement and removal;</P>
    <P>(b)  That the forms of settlement be reduced to four, viz.:&mdash; birth, parentage, marriage, residence;</P>
    <P>(c)  That a settlement be acquired by one year's residence in a county or county borough;</P>
    <P>(d)  That the Local Government Board determine all cases of disputed settlement unless the Board consider that a particular case should be decided in a court of law;</P>
    <P>(e)  That there be reciprocity of removal as between England, Scotland and Ireland.</P>
    <P>Then they say: &ldquo;If these changes be given effect to, the labour of inquiry, the cost of litigation and the hardship of removal under the <Col N="284" /> existing law will be very greatly diminished.  We would thus hope that most of the objections to the law would be met.  But if experience showed that total abolition of the law was preferable, that course might be adopted later.&rdquo;  That is the majority report.  The minority report was very scathing in its whole criticism and showed that in the year in which they made the report, if all the applications of the different bodies for the removal of people from one area to another were carried out, something like 40,000 people would have been removed from one district to another at great cost, perhaps at great cost arising simply out of the transaction in the courts alone and with very great hardship to the people themselves. We never had the law of settlement here.  One of the practical reasons that prevented the particular Bill now going through, wiping out the law of settlement, is that, perhaps, benefiting by our experience here in trying to improve the hospital side of their poor law institutions, the British authorities are afraid that if they did away with the law of settlement and broke down the barrier as between the counties, instead of going ahead with the improvements in their institutions which the governing authorities in Great Britain desire, the local bodies would be prevented from improving these institutions, as improving the institutions in some counties would attract people from other counties. Whenever the question of doing away with the law of settlement has arisen, the kind of fear which has been expressed in certain circles in Dublin has arisen in municipalities in Great Britain&mdash;that the country people are going to come in out of the rural areas and are going to swamp other areas; that in seaports they are going to be swamped by incomers in another way.  Every reasoned intelligence that has been brought to bear on the question of the law of settlement in Great Britain has agreed that it should be wiped out, and it is only political reasons, and these most nebulous reasons that are called practical <Col N="285" /> reasons, that prevent it being done. I find it difficult, when I get a communication like this from the Chamber of Commerce, to think that any group there has set out to consider the matter.  I think it is almost unfair to blame the Chamber of Commerce for the contents of a document containing certain things that are the product of minds going back before 1601, and asking us to adopt them as the recent and up-to-date decisions of a progressive nation.</P>
    <P>In dealing with this subject, we are also treated to another type of discussion that is grouped round the question of de-rating.  We are up against the eternal question of one person who thinks that the thing ought to be run as a tax and another person who thinks that it ought to be run as a rate.  This is simply part and parcel of the Local Government (Temporary Provisions) Act, 1923.  I hope that very soon there will be a chance to discuss the whole matter and that people from one end of the country to another can face the question as to where the burden of this charity should fall, in order that it may be effectively applied for the work that it is supposed to do and in order that dangers that lie in administering money of this kind in this way, without the necessary responsibility for collecting it, may be fully foreseen.  So much have we heard in a nebulous kind of way as to these things that I rather shrink from bringing in a measure to have it discussed as a measure without bringing in beforehand one simple law to clarify the existing situation. I think if we did get a Poor Law Act that would be a formal codification of the existing situation, such as in Great Britain in 1927, a lot of people would know where we stand with regard to poor law when they came to discuss what exactly they wanted to do in a measure that we want here, as distinct from any codification.</P>
    <P>That is a question for other days. My main interest in this particular Bill is to suggest to the Seanad that there is nothing material in this that was not in their own Bill.  Certain changes have been made with regard <Col N="286" /> to what is the area under the Dublin Union Commissioners.  Under the Dublin Union Commissioners there are Dublin City, Rathmines, Pembroke, the old North Dublin Rural District, South Dublin Rural District and Celbridge.  It has been the policy in the past that it was desirable that an urban district should be associated with the country around it, even in the days of boards of guardians, for the financing of the administration of poor relief.  In so far as it has been possible, we have endeavoured to do that, and we have succeeded in getting it in Waterford and in Cork.  Waterford city and county have together a joint scheme. Cork and one-third of the county&mdash; the South Cork Board of Assistance area&mdash;have a joint scheme.  In Limerick we did not succeed in getting a joint scheme.</P>
    <P>I want to suggest that there is a very great difference between joining up in a joint scheme, with the area-at-large as a charge, a city like Waterford, where the population is 26,000 and the valuation £76,000, and a county of 51,000 population with a valuation of £271,000, and an area like the borough of Dublin and Rathmines and Pembroke with a population approaching 400,000 and a valuation of approximately £1,500,000, with a rural area with a population of 42,000 and a valuation of only £208,000.  Very strong representations were made that it was unfair that there should fall upon a small rural area a charge that was more applicable to the city of Dublin.  As we are proposing to put immediately before the Oireachtas proposals for re-arranging the areas of Dublin City and County, so that the County Borough shall be approximately the City, Rathmines and Pembroke, and the rest will be a unit area of itself, we consider it would be only reasonable that, as a joint scheme had been refused, we should make the area of the new Dublin City, so far as it is represented by the City, Rathmines and Pembroke as a unit area of charge for itself.  It would be unfair to take the small narrow belt of low valuation, comparatively, around that <Col N="287" /> city, and in a temporary measure&mdash; a real temporary measure, because most of that area will come away from the city when the Local Government (Dublin) Bill is passed &mdash;put on it what is practically city taxation.  That is one of the main differences between this Bill and the Bill that the Seanad passed.  However, my main interest is to point out that there is very little difference between this Bill and the Bill the Seanad passed, and that the sooner we get this Bill into operation the sooner the intention of the Dáil and the Seanad with regard to this particular class of relief for the poor of Dublin will be put into operation.</P>
    <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
    <Speaker pid="AlfredByrne" hpid="Mr. Byrne Mr. Byrne">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Byrne</NameTxt>
      <P>Every section of the House has admitted the necessity of this Bill, and in view of the Minister's statement and his definition of the word &ldquo;destitution,&rdquo; and his promise to take out that word if it is found to be harmful, I ask the permission of the House to move the suspension of the Standing Orders in order to take all the stages of this Bill to-morrow, so as to secure that the poor, needy and the hungry in the City of Dublin will get the benefit of it before Christmas.  I hope the Bill will not be amended, because if we amend the Bill it means calling back the Dáil to consider our amendments, and that means depriving those who are suffering untold hardships of the benefits they might otherwise secure. Under these circumstances I ask you, sir, if it is possible to allow all the stages of this Bill to be taken to-morrow.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Cathaoirleach Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>No, we require two days' notice for the suspension of the Standing Orders.  As notice should be handed in before 11 o'clock in the forenoon, we could not possibly arrange to take all the stages of this Bill even on Friday morning.  What we can do is this:</P>
      <P>If the House would agree we could meet on Tuesday next and carry this Bill through all its stages.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="288" />
    <Speaker pid="HonJameson" hpid="Mr. Jameson Mr. Jameson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Jameson</NameTxt>
      <P>Could the Minister tell us if a day or two's delay would make any difference?  Does it matter much whether we pass this Bill to-day or within the next four or five days?  Why then should we break the Standing Orders?  I do not think we shall do any harm to anybody by keeping to the Standing Orders.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General Mulcahy General Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>General Mulcahy</NameTxt>
      <P>I am making the necessary arrangements so that as little damage as possible will be done by the delay.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="AlfredByrne" hpid="Mr. Byrne Mr. Byrne">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Byrne</NameTxt>
      <P>At the earliest possible moment we should pass the Bill through all its stages.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Cathaoirleach Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>If the House desires it we can do that on Tuesday, and considering the near advent of Christmas perhaps we ought to meet on Tuesday.  The Senator can then move the suspension of the Standing Orders so that all stages of the Bill can be taken on that day.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="AlfredByrne" hpid="Mr. Byrne Mr. Byrne">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Byrne</NameTxt>
      <P>Very well then, Tuesday next.</P>
      <P>Committee Stage ordered for Tuesday.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Housing (Gaeltacht) Bill," RHead="1929&mdash;Second Stage">
    <Title>Housing (Gaeltacht) Bill, 1929&mdash;Second Stage.</Title>
    <P>Question proposed: That this Bill be now read a Second Time.</P>
    <Speaker pid="FionanLynch" hpid="Minister for Lands and Fisheries (Mr. Lynch) Minister for Lands and Fisheries (Mr. Lynch)">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Lands and Fisheries (Mr. Lynch)</NameTxt>
      <P>This Bill is really the result of the recommendations of the Gaeltacht Commission in connection with housing, and adopted by the Government as set forth in the White Paper.  I may say that the Gaeltacht Commission's recommendations also govern the Schedule to the Bill.  The Gaeltacht Commission's recommondation was that all places where more than 25 per cent. of the population are Irish-speaking, should be embraced in the Gaeltacht. There was an internal definition, if you like, of Fíor-Ghaeltacht and Breac-Ghaeltacht.  For the purposes of this Bill we have adopted the recommendation that the 25 per cent. <Col N="289" /> Irish-speaking district would generally be called the Gaeltacht, and the Schedule of the Bill is based upon that.  We had then to get the areas which are 25 per cent.  Irish-speaking, and the only place where we could get such definite information was in the 1926 census of population. The Schedule is, therefore, based on the 1926 census of electoral areas which are 25 per cent.  Irish-speaking or more.</P>
      <P>This measure is one generally to give certain special facilities for the building of dwelling-houses and poultry houses in those areas to which I have referred.  I do not think there is any necessity for me to go into oratorical flights to describe the conditions of the Gaeltacht. Most members of the Seanad are familiar with them.  They are familiar with the barren tracks of mountainous land divided up into small holdings entirely uneconomic; they are familiar with the squalid dwelling-houses which are there; they are familiar with the small window which gives bad light and bad ventilation, or in many cases, none.  They are also probably cognisant of the facts that this applies chiefly to areas that may be called the &ldquo;Fíor-Ghaeltacht,&rdquo; the most Irish-speaking districts&mdash;Connemara and Erris, in Mayo, the Rosses in Donegal, and a few areas in Cork and Kerry, which are also most Irish-speaking.  These are the &ldquo;Fíor-Ghaeltacht,&rdquo; and probably the areas where conditions from the point of view of dwelling-houses, are worst.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Now, the conditions in these particular places are in fact so bad that nearly all legislation in the past escaped them.  There were various Acts between 1924 and 1928 passed by the Oireachtas dealing with Housing. These applied generally to the Gaeltacht, but in fact they were not availed of to any extent in the Gaeltacht, or, at any rate, one can say that they were not availed of by persons for whom this particular Bill is intended.  There were 114 houses built in the Gaeltacht under the Housing Acts passed by the Oireachtas, but these were built by people who had, at least, some capital or <Col N="290" /> other.  This Bill is for those who have been most submerged, if one might say so.  It aims at getting at the lowest strata from the point of view of housing, because those people had not been able to avail of former Acts.  These people were in this extraordinary position.  The old Labourers Acts passed them by. These old Labourers Acts provided that persons should have less than one acre of land.  All these people have one acre of land, if one could call it land, and because of these miserable patches of land the Labourers Acts could not apply to them.  They missed the Labourers Acts, and they were unable to avail of the existing legislation passed by the Oireachtas for housing.  In the Dáil there were many wreaths laid on the grave of the old Congested Districts Board.  I pointed out there that I should be the last to say a word against the old C.D.B. because, in fact, in my Department we are, to a great extent, carrying on the work of the C.D.B., and a great part of our policy is based on the groundwork that they had prepared.  I think we are doing somewhat better under the new arrangement.  The C.D.B. passed by these people.  They did a great deal of work in the way of striping of land and so on in the congested areas of the Gaeltacht, but when they came down to certain places they were so bad that they felt they could not be remedied, and they passed them by.  We are hoping to get at them here.  We are hoping that this Bill will help even those people who were passed by by the C.D.B.</P>
    <P>It is a fact, though, that the problem is somewhat simplified by certain things that are in the Gaeltacht and that are not elsewhere, as far as I know.  I know the conditions in the Gaeltacht perhaps better than conditions in other rural districts. I know that practically every one of the small holders in the Gaeltacht is a bit of a stone mason. Every one of them can put up his own little outhouse.  When he wants to put up his outhouse he builds the walls and makes the roof.  He puts <Col N="291" /> up a comparatively substantial outhouse. Of course, it is a thatched roof with scraws over a certain amount of rafters.  It is that type of skill that will be useful under this Act.  We are taking cognisance of the fact that that skill is there because the Bill is based on the fact that the skill in the man himself who is looking for this grant will be utilised in putting up a house.</P>
    <P>I will come to the point where there is more technical skill required, that is, in putting on a roof, in putting in window frames and placing the doors.  For that, he will have to get some technical help. There, again, you have something that is rather peculiar to the Gaeltacht. You have what may be called the journeyman handyman, the handyman who travels around from parish to parish, who gets his keep in the particular house where he is working and is paid perhaps £1 or £2 per week while he is doing certain work.  He is a journeyman and handyman.  He is neither a slater, a carpenter nor a stone mason.  He is a jack of all trades and does his work quite efficiently.  We have taken cognisance in the Bill of the fact that that man is available.  He is not at all a rare commodity.  I know in the parish where I was born there are three or four such persons who go around putting in windows or roofing houses, putting on slates or setting up doors and so on.  These are available in the Gaeltacht, and we have taken full cognisance of the fact that they are.  That, of course, simplifies the problem.  You have that skill available.</P>
    <P>Those things have been taken cognisance of in the costs.  The money that will be provided in the Bill is £250,000 between grants and loans and the purposes are specified as you go through the Bill.  The chief purpose, of course, is the building and improving of dwelling houses.  Minor things were put in, poultry houses and, a little bit further down, piggeries, but at any rate building and improving above and beyond anything else.  After that, poultry houses and piggeries, <Col N="292" /> with very little money allotted for these purposes.  We want the greater part of the money to be spent on dwelling houses.</P>
    <P>Again, a case was made in the Dáil for extending the provision to cattle houses, for instance.  That matter was very carefully threshed out before the Bill was introduced at all.  We felt that in many cases where there was a cow there was something in the nature of a cowshed. If there was not, and if there was a house built, the old house could be used for the purpose.  There was £250,000 to be spent, and there is no more money to be available under the Bill.  We felt we did not want that to be spread out over anything beyond what we now specify in the Bill&mdash;that is, dwelling-houses, and the minor questions of poultry and pigs.  If you extend it to cattle, you must cut something down somewhere else.  Probably it would mean the dwelling-houses, because the building of the cattle houses would cost more than is spent on poultry and pigs.  If you extend it to the cattle houses, you will build fewer dwelling-houses.  I take my agricultural outlook from the Department of Agriculture.  I take my advice from them.  They say these are the stock that will best pay the persons for whom we are catering under this Bill.  They are so definite about it that we have made it a condition of their getting any grant for building or improving a house that a person shall make some provision for accommodation for poultry or pigs or for both, unless the Minister is of opinion that, having regard to all the circumstances, the occupier of such a dwelling-house could not be expected to keep either poultry or pigs.  That is the Minister, of course, in consultation with the Minister for Agriculture.  One of the points that have been put up in connection with poultry, pigs, and everything else, is that they require comparatively small capital.  That is from the smallholders' point of view.</P>
    <P>We contemplate from 24 to 30 hens and perhaps a sow or two in the little holding.  The capital would <Col N="293" /> not be extensive and the probable income with care and supervision would be of very considerable importance to that type of holder.  It would put the particular small holder in a position, when applying for the loan that goes with nearly all the grants, of being able to repay. The difference in his income if he had poultry and say a pig, would ensure that he would be able to repay his loan.  That is what is in our mind in this matter.  That some provision of the kind is required is illustrated by the fact I mentioned in the Dáil, that of the 80,000 odd holdings in the Gaeltacht there are only 11,789 who have satisfactory housing for poultry at the moment.  There are 45,810 with unsatisfactory accommodation, and 22,581 with no accommodation whatever for poultry.  The pig situation is similar, if not indeed worse.</P>
    <P>In the Dáil, a Deputy entered into a discussion as to the comparative value of a wooden house or a stone house for poultry.  I do not suppose there is any need to go into a discussion of that kind.  In fact, we are providing for a stone building. Since that discussion in the Dáil, I met a distinguished Senator who breeds a considerable number of poultry.  I think he keeps 400 hens. He is a strong advocate of the wooden house.  Incidentally, he mentioned that he eats 150 of his own young cocks in the year. Senator Milroy, I am sure, will say that he has something to crow about.</P>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. Johnson Mr. Johnson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Johnson</NameTxt>
      <P>Is it the advice of the Department that a stone house is better than a wooden house?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FionanLynch" hpid="Mr. Lynch Mr. Lynch">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lynch</NameTxt>
      <P>I thought it better to consult the Department on that matter.  In the past, the Department insisted on a wooden house for poultry under their Poultry Station Schemes, but after some experience in the Gaeltacht they now refuse to give grants for wooden houses for poultry in the Gaeltacht or in such wind-swept areas.  They say that the proper houses for poultry in the Gaeltacht are stone houses.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The maximum grant for the building of a new house is to be £80, with <Col N="294" /> a possible loan of not greater than £80&mdash;that is, for a standard dwelling house.  I might say that our idea of a standard dwelling-house is an ordinary one-storey house with a large kitchen and three bedrooms&mdash; one for the parents, one for the boys of the family and one for the girls of the family&mdash;and with certain other amenities that can be provided with this particular grant.</P>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasFarren" hpid="Mr. Farren Mr. Farren">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Farren</NameTxt>
      <P>A thatched or slated house?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FionanLynch" hpid="Mr. Lynch Mr. Lynch">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lynch</NameTxt>
      <P>Certainly not thatched. A particular type of cheap slating can be provided.  A great portion of the virtue of this Bill is that there can be a lesser grant for a smaller type of house.  We are not tied down to a particular specification.  If a man builds a slightly worse house than the standard house he may get a grant accordingly.  At least, the house will be better than the one he is living in now.  The measure is more elastic than former housing Acts in that respect.  Under former housing Acts you had definite specifications for a five-roomed house or a three-roomed house; it was cut and dried.  Under this Bill a man can get a grant of £80, or he can get a lesser grant in accordance with the type of house he intends to build.</P>
      <P>The maximum improvement grant is £40.  We are absolutely satisfied that that is a sufficient improvement grant, especially when the man who is going to spend £40 on improvements can always apply for an amount up to £40 as a loan.  The question of giving £60 has been raised.  If one goes to that one might say, &ldquo;Hang it all; one might as well go and build a new house.&rdquo;  When you go beyond the £40, it might be more economical to go for the £80 and build a new house.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Provision is made in the Bill for a grant for the demolition of the old house.  We felt that a grant would induce a great many of them to destroy the old houses.  In many cases the stones in the old houses would be used in the building of the new ones.  At any rate, we wanted some inducement to a man to break down the old house.  If it is worth <Col N="295" /> his while for the amount of the grant, he will destroy the old house if he is not going to use it for cattle &mdash;for a cow, a donkey or a horse. We are not, by the way, going to provide by way of grants the full cost of the dwelling-house, or of the poultry house either.  The most we are doing is to provide by grant something fairly near the amount required. Then the man who wants to build a standard house will have to go for a further £80 by way of loan in order to build that type of house. He will have to give his own labour and his own skill in putting up portion of the house, and in the provision of material.  We believe that the cost of the house will be something like £275.  A rough estimate of the man's labour and materials will be about £95.  £160 will be provided by way of grant and loan.</P>
    <P>I said in the other House that the giving of loans would be very carefully considered.  Loans will only be given where, first of all, we are satisfied that they are necessary in order that a man should build the particular type of house he said he would build.  Number two, we want to see about the man's capacity to repay.  I am entirely against giving loans that mean grants.  If you want to give grants, call them grants.  If they are loans, let them be called loans, and let the person feel that he has the responsibility of repaying.  We hope that a man's income may be so increased by the things specified in this Act and in others, that he will be in a position to repay.  Whether he wants to build this particular type of house or not, we want to make it perfectly clear that when a loan is being given and where a man takes on himself the burden of repaying, it is expected that he will repay.  We are not giving loans as grants.  If we were, we would call them that.</P>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. Johnson Mr. Johnson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Johnson</NameTxt>
      <P>Would the Minister say whether there is any relative sum for loans as compared with grants?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FionanLynch" hpid="Mr. Lynch Mr. Lynch">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lynch</NameTxt>
      <P>Roughly speaking, we <Col N="296" /> calculate that there will be £150,000 in grants, and £100,000 in loans.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasFarren" hpid="Mr. Farren Mr. Farren">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Farren</NameTxt>
      <P>I am sure that the House will welcome this Bill.  There may be some differences of opinion with regard to whether the sum provided is adequate.  We are all agreed, however, that this is a good first effort to deal with a very serious problem in our State.  I do not profess to have a great knowledge of conditions in the Gaeltacht, but I have visited certain portions of it, and when I came home from these particular places I felt ashamed that some of our fellow-countrymen should be condemned to live under such awful conditions.  I think it is no exaggeration to say that some of these unfortunate people are living in houses that are not fit to house swine.  Any farmer who has regard for his cattle would not house them under conditions such as I have seen human beings living in, in certain portions of the Gaeltacht.  For that reason we must welcome this effort on the part of the Government to deal with this sad condition of affairs.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The Minister has explained the provisions of the Bill.  He told us that the Bill provides for £250,000, which will be at the disposal of his Department for the purpose of enabling people who are badly housed in those areas to provide themselves with decent accommodation.  He estimates that the amount of money that will be disbursed in grants will be £150,000, and in loans £100,000. He indicated that it is the desire and the intention of his Department to endeavour to aim at the erection of a standard type of house.  I think the Minister is to be congratulated upon all that.  I am not sure whether he elaborated it, but he mentioned that he has made provision in one section for assistance to be given to people who will be building houses in the direction of procuring lime, sand, and the use of scaffolding and other plant.  It is my intention on the Committee Stage to move an amendment so that that principle will apply to other materials as well. The Minister specifies lime, sand, and <Col N="297" /> the use of scaffolding and other plant, but they are not all the essential requirements in the building of a house.  I think the Minister would be well advised to include other materials.  I will elaborate that point later, and I hope I will satisfy the Minister that my intentions are not to hamper the work of the Department, but rather to assist in the matter about which he is so concerned.</P>
    <P>The Minister explained the conditions to us, and he mentioned the type of individual who would be building these houses.  I think he is called a <i>gobán</i> or in some cases a <i>gobán saor.</i>  Although I am a skilled artisan, I am not going to raise any questions or lines of demarcation with regard to the building of houses.  Our only desire is to see that these people are properly housed as speedily as possible. There are certain things, however, I would like to refer to.  In the course of the discussion in the Dáil, and from his statements here to-day, the Minister indicated that what his Department aims at is a standard type of house, built of whatever type of stone suitable for building exists in the locality.  So far, that is good. It is very desirable that the materials used in the erection of the walls of these houses will be of Irish manufacture.</P>
    <P>The Minister proposes, in order to prevent these unfortunate people being exploited by persons who, realising that a grant or a loan has been issued, will put on the screw and charge more than should be charged for lime, sand and scaffolding, that there will be a systems of combined purchasing arranged by his Department with a consequent reduction in prices to the individual who contemplates building.  There was a similar provision in a former Housing Act with regard to the joint purchasing of building materials, but I am sorry to say it proved to be a dead letter; it was never brought into operation.  I hope that in this instance it will be taken full advantage of.  I suggest that the Minister, on the Committee Stage, <Col N="298" /> should accept an amendment setting out that the assistance to be given shall apply to other materials. Replying to a question, the Minister said that it was not proposed to have the usual thatched roof placed upon these houses and that it was intended they should be roofed with a type of slate.  I suggest that whatever slates are being used, the combined purchasing system should be applied to them and should further be applied to window frames, sashes and other things of that sort.</P>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Cathaoirleach Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Materials and fittings are mentioned specifically in one of the sections.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasFarren" hpid="Mr. Farren Mr. Farren">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Farren</NameTxt>
      <P>They are not mentioned in the section I have in mind.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FionanLynch" hpid="Mr. Lynch Mr. Lynch">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lynch</NameTxt>
      <P>The Senator will find that matter referred to in Section 12 (1).</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasFarren" hpid="Mr. Farren Mr. Farren">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Farren</NameTxt>
      <P>I am glad that the matter has been given consideration in the Bill.  We are all glad that this special effort is being made to preserve the Gaeltacht, to preserve the real Irish-speaking people.  I hope that this is but the first of many such endeavours.  I desire to lay a special emphasis upon the advisability of using Irish manufactured materials.  It would be a regrettable thing if the real Irishman whose culture we are trying to preserve should get up in the morning to find himself confronted with a foreign-made window and its foreign-made sashes or be obliged to walk through a foreign-made door. Let us hope that the roof over his head which will shelter him, and the little ones who, in their time, will help to perpetuate Gaelic civilisation, will not be of foreign manufacture.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I sincerely trust that all the materials used under this scheme will be of Irish production.  Apart from the point of view of sentiment, it is good economy.  The Minister indicated that the labour of the handy man would work out at £50, and that £130 would be spent on materials.  If that £130 is to be sent out of the country for the purchase of foreign materials, it will be bad <Col N="299" /> economy.  I do not want to saddle the unfortunate man in the Gaeltacht with increased prices for Irish manufactured articles.  I speak with some knowledge of the subject when I say that if the Minister carries out in its entirely the provision with regard to joint purchasing and the building of standard houses, it will bring about a situation in this country when manufacturers will be prepared to produce window sashes and doors, and other necessaries in house building, and supply them as cheaply as any foreign-made article.  If these things are made in large quantities, and made according to a standard prescribed by the Combined Purchasing Board, they can be made in this country&mdash;I will not specify any particular district in which they can be made&mdash;more cheaply than any unfortunate individual can go in and buy them, buying one article or so at a time.  They can be bought in that way as cheaply as the foreign made article.  Apart altogether from sentiment, it is very bad economy if the whole of this £250,000 that is to be put at the disposal of these people is going to be sent out of the country.  It is bad economy to import foreign materials of this sort, if through combined purchasing we can get the materials as cheaply at home, thereby giving employment to people in other districts. In that way we will help other areas in the State that are helping to contribute this money.  I think the Minister is to be congratulated for having introduced this Bill.  The amount at his disposal is not sufficiently large to deal with the whole of this terrible problem in the Gaeltacht, but it is at least a commencement, and let us hope that before this money is exhausted the Minister will come here again with another Bill for money when, I hope, every Senator here will be prepared to vote all the money that will be required for dealing with this problem.</P>
    <P>It is an awful thing to consider the amount of money that has been spent on housing in this country <Col N="300" /> within the past few years, and to remember that at least 50 per cent. of that money has gone out of the country in the purchase of foreign materials.  Now, in addition to the other matters I have mentioned, we do manufacture in this country metal pipes and castings that are required in the building of those houses.  I know that they will not be required to any great extent, but I think the combined purchasing arrangement might be availed of there also.  I think we could buy these materials of Irish manufacture in that way as cheaply as we could import them.  In that way we may in some measure stop this continual drain of money out of this country.  Last year there was over a half a million pounds sent out for the purchase of cement alone.  If that drain continues, we will have no money left to spend on the building of houses or anything else.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JosephODoherty" hpid="Mr. O'Doherty Mr. O'Doherty">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Doherty</NameTxt>
      <P>I wish to state on behalf of my Party that we are glad that the Ministry has at last taken these preliminary steps to deal with housing in the Gaeltacht.  In considering the Bill, it is well for us to keep before our eyes that this is not an ordinary housing Bill.  It is a Bill that was designed in the interests of the Fíor-Ghaeltacht, but it is being extended to cover other areas.  In the words of the Minister, this Bill includes any area in the Gaeltacht having a population 25 per cent. of whom, according to the census of 1926, speak Irish.  The amount of money at the disposal of the Minister for the carrying out of the scheme outlined in the Bill is £250,000.  The Schedule attached to the Bill shows that a very wide area is included.  The amount of money that is made available by this Bill, therefore, is not going to produce any very great results in that way. I am convinced that the Minister could get better results with the amount of money at his disposal if the area in the Schedule were curtailed. In Section 11 (4) it is stated that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>So far as may be practicable having regard to the number and <Col N="301" /> local distribution of the cases in which it appears to the Minister to be proper to make grants under this Act and to the foregoing provisions of this section, at least three-fifths of the moneys available for making grants under this Act shall be applied in making grants to occupiers of dwelling-houses situate in district electoral divisions in the Gaeltacht in which the valuation under the Valuation Acts of all hereditaments (other than hereditaments valued at more than twenty pounds) in the district electoral division when divided by the population of the district electoral division according to the census of 1926 yields a sum not exceeding twenty-one shillings.</P>
    <P>I have before me a list of the district electoral divisions in the Schedule with a valuation <i>per capita</i> of twenty-one shillings.  That Schedule comprises fourteen in Cork; 35 in Donegal; 18 in Galway; 13 in Kerry; 28 in Mayo; 9 in Waterford; one in Cavan and one in Limerick.  I can speak with some knowledge of the Northern Gaeltacht, Donegal, having had the privilege of representing the county for ten years, and I would respectfully submit that these 35 electoral divisions with a <i>per capita</i> valuation of twenty-one shillings include in entirely the Gaeltacht area of Donegal.  The Schedule attached to the Bill includes areas which would not or could not properly be described as Gaeltacht areas.  I am anxious that the Schedule attached to the Bill, therefore, should be curtailed, and that instead of spending three-fifths in the electoral divisions with a valuation of twenty-one shillings, five-fifths of the £250,000 should be spent there.  In the Committee Stage, I will introduce an amendment to that effect.</P>
    <P>There is no provision in the Bill excluding those who to my mind should not be entitled at all to grants or loans for building purposes under the terms of this Bill. These are people, for instance, whose valuation would exceed ten pounds, people who are in receipt of a State <Col N="302" /> pension or pension other than Old Age Pension; people who are in receipt of moneys from the State for Post Office work, and so on.  I think that this money should be applied specifically to those in the Gaeltacht who are living under conditions that would make the heart of any Christian, not to say an Irishman, revolt.  It is only in that way that the full benefit of the money at the disposal of the Minister will be made available for the Gaeltacht proper.</P>
    <P>Again, I think that there should be a time limit fixed somehow for the expenditure of this money.  In other words, the Ministry should not be permitted to struggle on year after year expending yearly a small proportion of the money.  I have not given much thought to the date, but I think it might be well to say that inside two years the total amount of the money at the disposal of the Minister should be spent.  The Minister takes to himself the right to alter the Schedule.  I believe that the Schedule should be fixed by us, and that a National Committee, either representative of Parties or non-political, composed of those who are interested in the revival of the language from the national point of view, should act in consultation with the Minister, and inquire into the possibility of extending the fixed Schedule suggested by him.  That would obviate the possibility of any injustice being done to any large part of the Gaeltacht at the present time.</P>
    <P>I heartily endorse the references by Senator Farren to materials required for the building of the houses.  I hope the Minister will keep that matter before him when he is dealing with the matter of joint purchasing.  If it is the decided policy of the Minister to employ in the building nothing but Irish materials, I think it would be an incentive to those engaged in the manufacture of such articles to lower the cost of production.  This would help to lower the cost, for as many as possible of these articles could be produced together, and acquired by the Joint Purchasing Board.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="303" /> Again, I say I am glad the Bill has been introduced.  I trust that the Minister will not have as fixed a mind in the Seanad as he had in the Dáil, but that he will meet the suggestions put forward by way of amendments to the Bill, and accept these amendments in the belief that we are putting forward our views, not as taking away from the full effect of the Bill, but rather for the purpose of strengthening the original intentions of the Bill&mdash; namely, to provide better housing for the people in the Gaeltacht.</P>
    <Speaker pid="McGillycuddyReeks" hpid="The McGillycuddy of the Reeks The McGillycuddy of the Reeks">
      <NameTxt>The McGillycuddy of the Reeks</NameTxt>
      <P>I congratulate the Minister on this Bill.  There is an impression in the West&mdash;it is quite wrong, of course-that very little State money gets further than 20 miles from Dublin. But after this Bill I feel quite sure that when the Minister returns to Cahirciveen he will be accorded a reception like the reception that once before was accorded to another great Irishman.  There are one or two things which I think he will have to be careful about.  The aim of this Bill, as he has told us, is to improve the conditions of life of those in what he calls the bottom strata.  He should be very careful to make some provision in the Bill so that the better educated people, who are well able to make applications, should not come in first and be first served. That is an important and an essential point.  I hope he will pay attention to that.  I quite agree with some of the exceptions made by Senator O'Doherty with regard to appointments. They are the well educated people and will come in first, and I think that should be guarded against. Every possible publicity should be given in the Gaeltacht with regard to the provisions of this Bill.  Otherwise we will not get the right people. With regard to Section 14, I would like to have some explanation from the Minister.  That section states that &ldquo;the Minister shall not exercise any power, determine any matter, or form any opinion under this Act in relation to accommodation for domestic poultry or pigs <Col N="304" /> without previously consulting the Minister for Agriculture in regard thereto.&rdquo;  It seems to me that he is there rather following the example of Esau and the mess of pottage, and that in regard to the sum of £250,000 provided in the Bill he has bound himself heart and soul to the Minister for Agriculture so far as doing anything under the Bill is concerned.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FionanLynch" hpid="Mr. Lynch Mr. Lynch">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lynch</NameTxt>
      <P>No, only so far as poultry and pigs are concerned.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="McGillycuddyReeks" hpid="The McGillycuddy of the Reeks The McGillycuddy of the Reeks">
      <NameTxt>The McGillycuddy of the Reeks</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not think that the £250,000 will go very far.  I think that Senator O'Doherty was wrong in suggesting that we should cut down the area.  I think that in time it will be found that this sum will not go half as far as it is expected to go.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. Johnson Mr. Johnson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Johnson</NameTxt>
      <P>I think there can be no question in any part of the House but that it is desirable to make provision for the housing of the very poor in that part of the country known as the Gaeltacht, particularly that part which is marked green on the map.  My fear in this matter is that this Bill is not going to do very much to effect a remedy.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>took the Chair.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. Johnson Mr. Johnson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Johnson</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister gave us certain figures this afternoon. From these figures it seems to me very unlikely that you are going to get many standard houses erected in that poor Gaeltacht.  The standard house is estimated to be worth £275. The total grant is to be £80.  That leaves a remainder of £195.  How is that £195 to be obtained?  Possibly, £80 may be granted by way of loan, provided that the Minister can be well assured that there is good security for the loan, but even though a person gets that loan there is another £115 worth of labour or material, or both, to be put into the house.  How much of that will be labour and how much material, I do not know, but certainly a moderate proportion of it will be material that will have to be bought.  I gather from the Minister's statement <Col N="305" /> in the Dáil that he does not anticipate a very general grant of loans, that this is to be treated rather as an emergency.  As a matter of fact, I think the Minister said somewhere that he did not expect that more than 50 electoral divisions would be included in this three-fifths provision.  We are really dealing with the poorest of the people, and, as it seems to me, we are making the assurance at the beginning that only non-standard houses, or at least very few of the standard houses, will be erected in the poorest part of the country.  Therefore, it seems to me we are aiming at small grants for the improvement of the existing houses in these the poorest parts of the country.  There is another point that I wish to touch on before I get into the main criticism that I have to make on the Bill.  Under sub-section (2) of Section 16 it is provided that &ldquo;in so far as the provisions of any local Act or of any bye-laws, rules, regulations, or scheme, under whatever authority made, relating to the construction, laying-out, or drainage of new buildings or new streets are inconsistent with the regulation made by the Minister under this Act those provisions shall not apply to a house to which such regulation applies.&rdquo;</P>
      <P>That means that wherever there have been bye-laws regulating the conditions under which houses are to be built, in regard to sanitation, sewerage, lay-out and construction, etc., they will no longer apply.  The Minister's regulations will override them.  That may be right and proper in regard to most of these districts where there are no regulations of the kind, but within the Schedule of this Bill, as drawn, there are two or three places which are urban areas, where there are certain regulations with regard to house construction, drainage and the like in force.  These apparently are to be over-ridden by any general instructions that the Minister may make as affecting the Gaeltacht in general.  I think that is a little bit doubtful and ought to be considered.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>In regard to the Schedule, I am <Col N="306" /> not able to understand the meaning of it at all, and I think it had far better be abandoned.  It is useless. It is likely to excite hopes and expectations that cannot within the scheme be fulfilled.  It is likely to excite all kinds of jealousies and discords and will be very harmful. It will not be beneficial and will be of no value whatever to the scheme. I do not know what difference there may be between the census returns of Irish speakers compared with the Gealtacht Commission's report of Irish speakers.  We have not had the privilege of examining or even seeing the census returns in regard to Irish speakers, as it has not yet been published.  The Minister appears to have had access to these returns.  We have had no such access to them, and therefore are not able to examine them.  But as only eight months elapsed between the taking of the census by the Gaeltacht Commission and the census of April, 1926, one can fairly well take the Gaeltacht Commission's report unless we are to assume that there is a very considerable conflict between the two reports. The Gaeltacht Commission made their examination specifically by the aid of the Gárda Síochána, <i>plus</i> personal observation and <i>plus</i> examination of the 1911 census.  I think when one takes into account the fact that the 1911 census was not in the time of full flood of the Irish movement it would probably record more or less accurately the number of Irish speakers, and that the 1926 census, which followed rather closely on the Gaeltacht Commission's report, if anything, would err on the side of generosity as to the number of Irish speakers, one can fairly well take the Gaeltacht Commission's report as being as reliable as anything else in regard to the density of the Irish-speaking population.</P>
    <P>As far as I can see in this Schedule the districts which, for the purpose of this Act alone, and for no other purpose, are to be deemed the Gaeltacht run very sharply in conflict with the Gaeltacht Commission's <Col N="307" /> report, which was adopted by the Executive Council as determining the course of policy.  The Gaeltacht Commission report indicated certain areas, marked &ldquo;a&rdquo; and &ldquo;b,&rdquo; which taken in combination would be considered the Gaeltacht.  I do not know whether the Minister has examined this closely, but it will be found on examination that the Gaeltacht as defined by the Schedule differs materially from the Gaeltacht as defined by the Gaeltacht Commission's report.  Quite a considerable number of those areas which were marked &ldquo;b,&rdquo; that is partly Irish-speaking, after being examined by the Gaeltacht Commission from personal observation, they are in fact left out of the Schedule, while a considerable number of areas which are put in the Schedule, were not considered to be Gaelic speaking in the Gaeltacht Commission's report.  I find, for instance, by the report that there are 70 areas in Cork which are considered to be Gaelic by the Gaeltacht Commission, ten of them being 80 per cent. or over Irish-speaking, and 60 being between 25 per cent. and 80 per cent., whereas in the Schedule there are 97 such areas.  For Galway the Gaeltacht Commission report gives 130, and the Schedule gives 152.  For Mayo the report gives 88 and the Schedule 104.</P>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Leas-Chathaoirleach Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Are they both district electoral divisions?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. Johnson Mr. Johnson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Johnson</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes.  The Schedule indicates Cavan, Leitrim, Limerick, Louth and Roscommon, whereas the Gaeltacht Commission's report makes no mention of them at all.  I think there is no possibility under this scheme that many of the areas mentioned in the Schedule are ever going to obtain one halfpenny worth of benefit under the Bill, and it is the Minister's intention that they should not.  Why put them in the Schedule?  Are you not exciting hopes in the minds of the residents of those districts that they may get assistance when there is a clear intention on the part of the Ministry, <Col N="308" /> and it is part of the scheme in the Bill that they shall get no such benefit?</P>
      <P>There are 113 district electoral areas marked in the map as being within the poverty region&mdash;below 21 shillings <i>per capita</i> valuation.  47 of these are 80 per cent. and upwards Irish-speaking, 66 of them 25 per cent. to 80 per cent. Irish-speaking, and it is more or less told to us in the Bill that not more than these 113 areas as defined on the map will receive any benefit from this Bill.  Why should we deceive people by putting no less than 658 areas in the Schedule when we are anticipating that only 113 of them will ever receive any benefit from the Bill?  May I point out when taking the Gaeltacht Commission's report as a guide to the Schedule, that of the 658 areas recorded no less than 28 per cent. of the 175 divisions are under the 25 per cent. limit of Irish speakers in the Gaeltacht Commission's report.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The members of the Gaeltacht Commission were not so easily taken in as the Minister seems to have been in drafting the Schedule from the 1926 census, for if, according to the returns they received of Irish speakers, there were 20, 30, or even 40 per cent. Irish speakers, and the Gaeltacht Commission, from their own observation, knew those were not really the Irish districts, that perhaps some enthusiastic Gaelic Leaguer, or perhaps some member of the Dáil, in taking records, wanted to show big in respect of the particular area and returned a large number of Irish speakers for it, if the Commission found those were not in reality Irish-speaking&mdash;they did not mark them as Gaeltacht&mdash;so that the Gaeltacht Commission's report is much more reliable from the point of view of Gaelic-speaking districts than the census returns. Yet no less than 28 per cent. of the districts named in this Schedule comprise less than 25 per cent. of Irish speakers according to the Gaeltacht Commission's report.  There is something even worse from my point of view in this Bill.  Before going on <Col N="309" /> to that, let me remind the House that the Minister has said he does not consider that more than 100 of the areas mentioned in the Schedule will be affected, and that not more than 50 of the electoral areas will be affected or benefited by the three-fifths clause.  That confirms what I have said.  I want to refer to some of the districts which are clearly indicated in the Gaeltacht Commission's report as being Irish-speaking, and which anybody who knows, even superficially, some of the areas, would consider should, without any question, be in the Schedule.  Take Donegal.  There are two divisions, Dawross and Maas.  They are not included because they appear upon the census as having only 10.9 and 6.9 per cent. of Irish speakers.</P>
    <P>But the Gaeltacht Commission, realising the facts, apart from the figures, entered these two districts as being part of the Gaeltacht, and noting also the fact that in the previous census of 1911 there were 43 per cent. and 38 per cent. respectively of Irish speakers there.  I have not gone exhaustively into some of these counties.  In regard to Sligo I find a district which in the Gaeltacht Commission is shown as being 33 per cent. Irish-speaking, marked specifically as being a Gaelic-speaking district, but not shown in the Schedule, while other districts which are shown as having 4 per cent. and 2 per cent. are included. I cannot reconcile that with reason or with the report.</P>
    <P>Take Mayo, which is a county that I have not examined closely&mdash;Aghadower North with 28 per cent. is included, but Aghadower South with 31 per cent. is not included, although clearly marked as being within an Irish-speaking district.  Mountfalcon is not included, although it has 36 per cent. and is marked by the Gaeltacht Commission as an Irish-speaking district.  In Clare there are three districts not included, Kilrush rural, St. Martin's, and Kilkee, although noted as being in the Gaelic-speaking areas by the Gaeltacht Commission report.  In Killadysart rural district, Coolmeen <Col N="310" /> with 5.6 per cent., Killofin with 12.3 per cent. are not included, but Killadysart with 11.9 of Irish-speakers, Kilfiddene with 5.9, Kilmihill with 3.5, Glenmore with 1.7, and Cooraclane with 7.9 are included.  In Cork there are numerous instances of a similar kind, but I had better not delay the House in dealing with them.  Galway is similar, but not quite to the same extent.  Some places are included with 9 per cent. and 7 per cent. of Irish-speakers, not indicated by the Gaeltacht Commission as being Irish-speaking districts, while not included are such places as Moneivea and Colmanstown with 19 per cent. and 25 per cent. respectively indicated as being Irish-speaking districts by the Gaeltacht Commission report, and yet not in the Schedule.</P>
    <P>Another fault that I find with the Schedule is that there are, for instance, in Galway three Cloonkeens, one in Loughrea rural district, one in Mount Bellew rural district, and one in Tuam rural district.  It will be found both in the report and on the map that there is a Cloonkeen in Loughrea, Mountbellew, and Glenamaddy rural districts, but no Cloonkeen in Tuam.  It is on the list, but not on the records.  There is one Aughrim in the Schedule&mdash;in County Galway&mdash;which Aughrim is it?  There is an Aughrim in Ballinasloe district with 15.2 per cent. Irish speakers and an Aughrim in Galway, with 9.2 per cent.&mdash;which is intended? Obviously the people of Ballinasloe will say we are in that district, because we have 15 per cent. of Irish speakers.  But I presume that it is the people in Galway district that are really intended to be included, so that we are exciting hopes in one of these places which cannot be fulfilled. I find that in Clare there is a place with no less than 87 per cent. of Irish speakers&mdash;Glenroe&mdash;not included in the Schedule.  I do not know how to account for that.  Even as far back as 1911, before the enthusiasts for recording got on their feet, they had 52 per cent. of Irish speakers, while in 1925 they had 87 <Col N="311" /> per cent., but they are not included in the Schedule.</P>
    <Speaker pid="RichardWilson" hpid="Mr. Wilson Mr. Wilson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Wilson</NameTxt>
      <P>They do not want houses.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. Johnson Mr. Johnson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Johnson</NameTxt>
      <P>Then I have Kilmurray, in Kildysart rural district, marked as being an Irish-speaking district, and Kilmurray (Kilrush rural district), also marked as an Irish-speaking district.  Kilmurray (Kildysart) has 32 per cent., and Kilmurray (Kilrush) has 16.3 per cent., but there is only one Kilmurray in the Schedule.  Which is intended?  Clooney, in Ennistymon rural district, is marked as an Irish-speaking area by the Gaeltacht Commission, with 54 per cent. of Irish speakers, but there is a Clooney in Tulla rural district, in the same county, with 23 per cent. of Irish speakers.  There is only one Clooney in the Schedule.  Which is it?  And so one can go through the various counties and find that the Schedule is utterly unreliable and of no value whatever, and I submit ought not to be put into the Bill.  It does not do the Bill any good; it does it a good deal of harm.  I suggested earlier that it will deceive the residents of these districts.  Somebody is going to be disappointed and somebody is going to get blamed.  If we were nearer a General Election one might be tempted to say that it was intended as an electioneering dodge. I do not think that that is so, but one can never tell.  I suggest to the Minister that there is no occasion for going outside the hundred or so district electoral areas which he has confessed the Bill is only intended to apply to.  The Gaeltacht Commission's report and the census returns, with the valuation test, fairly well agree as to which parts of the Gaeltacht are in special need of houses under this grant, and it would be very much better.  I think, very much more honest and satisfactory to everybody, if we did not put into the Bill no less than six hundred places. intending as to five hundred of them that the Bill should have no effect at all.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="312" /> I do not think that that limitation would damage the Bill, and if we are determined that there shall be on record in legislation a definition of the area which is to be called henceforth the Gaeltacht, we should not adopt this classification, we should be much more scientific if we are going to embody in legislation an area which shall henceforth be officially known as the Gaeltacht.  I do not know whether that was in the mind of the Minister.  If that is thought necessary I submit that the more scientific enquiry which was undertaken by the Gaeltacht Commission was a more reliable guide for that purpose than the census of 1926.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JanePower" hpid="Mrs. Wyse Power Mrs. Wyse Power">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Wyse Power</NameTxt>
      <P>There is one thing that is not to me very explicit in the Bill, that is in fact not explicit at all.  That is the conditions under which loans may be made.  &ldquo;The Minister for Finance may make regulations in relation to all or any of the following matters.&rdquo;  If you follow that up you will find it is the issuing of loans, making the charging orders and the repayment of loans.  If the Minister knows anything of the conditions under which loans will be granted I think he should throw some light on the matter.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelComynKC" hpid="Mr. Comyn Mr. Comyn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Comyn</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator Johnson has subjected this Schedule to a very close analysis, and I think he has rather brought out the fact, which is obvious to anybody, that these electoral divisions are very much scattered.  Of course, that was inevitable having regard to the fact that the Minister, I suppose, went by the census return.  A good many people who have looked through these electoral areas have come to the conclusion that in many cases the census returns must have been wrong, that a number of people who spoke Irish cannot have been returned as Irish speakers, and, on the other hand, as I am sorry to say, a number of people who know very little Irish, if any, must have been returned as Irish speakers.  That is <Col N="313" /> a fault in the census returns, and I think it is a fault which probably damages this Schedule from the point of view of doing justice to people who are entitled to justice. I think that the Minister should very seriously consider the proposal which was put forward by Senator O'Doherty.  I think you would have there a basis upon which he could be sure that the persons intended to get this small instalment of justice should get it.</P>
      <P>Section 11 says: &ldquo;So far as may be practicable having regard to the number and local distribution of the cases in which it appears to the Minister to be proper to make grants under this Act and to the foregoing provisions of this section at least three-fifths of the money available under this Act shall be applied in making grants to occupiers of dwelling houses situate in district electoral divisions in the Gaeltacht in which the valuation under the Valuation Acts of all hereditaments (other than hereditaments valued at more than twenty pounds) in the district electoral division when divided by the population of the district electoral division according to the census of 1926 yields a sum not exceeding twenty-one shillings.&rdquo; There you have the true Gaeltacht and, moreover, you have it, if I may say so, with a series of ringed fences. You have there the homogeneous area, and instead of applying three-fifths of this money to these particular areas which, <i>prima facie</i>, under the provisions of the Bill you will do, you should apply the five-fifths&mdash;the whole of it&mdash;and Senator Johnson would then not have an opportunity of putting your Schedule through a raking criticism.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>It is a very curious fact that if you take the population and the valuation you will find that the Irish speakers occupy those areas where the valuation per head is lowest. Naturally so, because you are dealing not with paupers and I hope we will not deal with this question of the Gaeltacht as if we were superior beings legislating for the lower stratum; we are legislating now for a pure and a prolific race; we are giving them the first instalment of <Col N="314" /> what is due to them, and I was very happy to understand, from the speeches that have been made by the Minister and others, that we are at last getting a glimpse of how to deal with this situation.  We are not to come like a Lady Bountiful, or a Father Christmas at Christmas time, giving gifts to poverty-stricken people; we are going to give a little instalment of justice to a people to whom justice is due, and who are, in my judgment, the purest race in this country and a superior race.  That is the frame of mind in which I would like the question of the Gaeltacht to be approached.  I noticed that in the speech of the Minister it was approached in that way.  You will succeed if you do approach it with sentiments like those; you will absolutely fail if you deal with it in any other way or from any other point of view.</P>
    <P>It is a good thing to provide good houses for the people of the Gaeltacht, but the main thing in the Gaeltacht is to enable the people to get employment, and the Minister has emphasised that one of his objects in these grants he is making is to enable the people to get employment in building their own houses. I was glad to hear from the Labour benches that no objection is to be made by reason of the fact that the people who will build these houses will not belong to trade unions and will not be skilled tradesmen.  It is a good thing that they should get employment.  That is what is desired. I hope the Minister and those who are helping him in this will regard the employment which is now being given as merely the beginning of a system by which the people in the Gaeltacht will get full employment in industry in their own areas.</P>
    <P>The Gaeltacht people are poor because they have been a prolific race. Their land is exhausted because they had to live and work and provide food for their children out of it. That is your problem in the Gaeltacht&mdash;exhausted land, the want of employment in the main way in which employment can be given there, that is, in the cultivation of the land.  I differ for once from Senator Farren when he referred to <Col N="315" /> this poverty-stricken area, desolate land and bleak and barren mountains. I come from the area, and I can assure the Seanad that the land in the Gaeltacht is by no means inferior, but is, in fact, the most improvable land in Ireland.  That is the way to approach the question. Give a chance to these people, who have been wronged for centuries, to make good in the new conditions in this country.  That is all, I think, that the people of the Gaeltacht ask from you, and I think that they will resent any suggestion or imputation that it is given as charity or given to an inferior people.  There were many things in Senator Farren's speech with which I thoroughly agree.  The building materials for houses ought to be provided locally. When the last housing scheme came before the Seanad we suggested that a comprehensive scheme of house-building should be introduced which would include a commission to be established with a view to providing all materials locally for the building of houses.  It is a terrible thing that half a million pounds should have been paid last year for cement in the construction of houses which, according to some reports, are not quite perfect.</P>
    <P>I am glad that the houses in the Gaeltacht are going to be built of stone and mortar, and I hope that they will be slated with Irish slates, such as the Killaloe slate, but I have no brief for any particular kind.  I hope that the window frames will be made in Ireland, and that the grates and other things will be cast in Ireland. It is, of course, good from the point of view of public health that these houses should be improved.  I think it is a very good suggestion of the Minister's to encourage the tearing down of some of the old houses. That is a valuable provision in the Bill and is only the beginning of what ought to be done.  Whitewashed walls and painted sashes are not enough.  The people of the Gaeltacht must be enabled to live, thrive and multiply in their own land.  It is not a matter of charity.  It is not a gift from a superior people.  It is <Col N="316" /> simple justice.  Approach the matter in that way and you will be successful, but if it is approached in any other way you are doomed to failure.</P>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="The Cathaoirleach The Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>The Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>resumed the Chair.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasFarren" hpid="Mr. Farren Mr. Farren">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Farren</NameTxt>
      <P>I think that Senator Comyn is labouring under a misapprehension. I did not talk about barren tracts of land.  I seldom speak on matters about which I do not know.  I know nothing about land, and I did not refer to barren tracts.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FionanLynch" hpid="Mr. Lynch Mr. Lynch">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lynch</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator Farren expressed the hope that as far as possible Irish materials would be utilised in building houses for which these grants and loans are to be given.  In the first place, it is not we who are going to build the houses, but the people of the Gaeltacht, and each person will suit himself. So far as we are concerned, where the system of joint purchasing comes in&mdash;and it will come in fairly largely, as we will be dealing with areas more or less in pockets, and where we believe it suits, we will strongly urge that Irish materials should be used.  I would be as strong as the Senator, or any other Senator in giving effect to that wish. Senator O'Doherty was anxious that the Bill should be restricted in its entirety to the areas covered by the provisions of Section 11 (4), that is, the areas for which three-fifths of the money is to be allocated.  There is nothing to prevent five-fifths of the money being allocated to these particular electoral areas, but at the same time, I do not wish to tie myself to that, inasmuch as you will have, in the semi-Irish-speaking districts&mdash;that is, with over 25 per cent. Irish speakers&mdash;small pockets of Irish-speaking people who are extremely badly housed and badly off. If you put such areas into that straight-jacket such as the Senator suggests, you could not well extend the Bill to particularly deserving cases living in the circumstances which I have mentioned.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The Senator is rather afraid that under the provisions of the Bill the Minister has power to add to the <Col N="317" /> Schedule.  I do not know whether he seriously suggests that a sort of inter-party commission should consider the Schedule because I cannot imagine anything more fantastic. Section 2 (2) says that &ldquo;the Minister may by order, whenever he considers it expedient so to do on account of local variations in the numbers or distribution of Irish-speaking persons, amend the Schedule ...&rdquo;  The Minister must have some very good basis or information on which he can stand before he attempts to vary the Schedule.  He cannot attempt to remove a place from the Schedule, at any rate, pending the census.  I do not know on what information I could add a place to the Schedule.  If I got representations in regard to a particular area, how could I examine them and satisfy myself that I could stand before the Oireachtas and justify an addition to the Schedule? I do not know on what type of information I could do such a thing. At any rate, I think, that it is far safer to leave the question of adding to the Schedule to the Minister and make him, as the responsible Minister, stand over it and show to the Oireachtas afterwards on what grounds he added to it.  The Senator was also concerned with a time limit for the expenditure of the money.  I am as desirous as the Senator of expending the money in the shortest time possible so long as I am satisfied that it is being well spent.  In my opinion, to put on a time limit of that kind would be an invitation to spend the money anyhow before a particular date.  That is an unsound proposition in the expenditure of money.  The money will be spent as quickly as possible with our eye on the best results.</P>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. Johnson Mr. Johnson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Johnson</NameTxt>
      <P>And with the sanction of the Minister for Finance.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FionanLynch" hpid="Mr. Lynch Mr. Lynch">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lynch</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister for Finance is going to provide £250,000 and he will not be concerned whether it is going to be spent in 1930, 1931 or 1932.  The money is available and he will not be very materially interested once it is voted.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="318" />
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. Johnson Mr. Johnson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Johnson</NameTxt>
      <P>Will it be voted all in one year?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FionanLynch" hpid="Mr. Lynch Mr. Lynch">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lynch</NameTxt>
      <P>I have to make my estimate of what we hope reasonably to spend.  If I thought that I could spend the entire amount in one year I would have no hesitation in doing so but I do not believe for one moment that I could.  Senator Johnson was concerned with the number of places in the Schedule and the hopes that might be raised.  Yet he stressed the fact that I had made it very plain in the speeches I had made that not more than 100 electoral divisions will benefit under the Bill.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. Johnson Mr. Johnson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Johnson</NameTxt>
      <P>The responsibility for the Act will be ours.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FionanLynch" hpid="Mr. Lynch Mr. Lynch">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lynch</NameTxt>
      <P>I would like to know what the Senator's alternative would be.  You must outline some places to which the Bill will apply.  Surely you must get something for which you would have some statutory authority.  The enumeration of 1925 may have been all that Senator Johnson suggests but in fact these are not statutory figures.  I accept the recommendations of the Gaeltacht Commission as the Government accepted them in the White Paper but I question the accuracy of many of those figures.  The strange thing about them is that in many places, to which Senator Johnson referred, the figures of the 1911 census and the 1926 census, are fairly near each other but the enumeration of 1925 is far away from either of them.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. Johnson Mr. Johnson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Johnson</NameTxt>
      <P>In making the Schedule did you take the 1911 figures into account at all?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FionanLynch" hpid="Mr. Lynch Mr. Lynch">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lynch</NameTxt>
      <P>No, I am basing it on 1926 census.  As a matter of fact the figures of the 1911 census and the 1926 census were fairly near each other, taking into account the normal reduction in Irish speakers that one might expect over a period, but the 1925 enumeration was very wide of the mark of the 1911 or the 1926 figures in most cases.  I do not say that the census gave us a true return of the number of Irish-speaking persons in an area.  In fact I am <Col N="319" /> perfectly satisfied that it does not. As Senator Johnson pointed out, an enthusiastic Gaelic Leaguer in any particular area during the time the census returns are being filled, will cause a big number to fill their census forms as Irish speakers when in fact they are not Irish speakers.  I am perfectly certain if the people in many areas knew that such a Bill as this was coming along, you would have a much bigger percentage of Irish speakers returned in 1926. Somebody said that in filling one's income tax return, one does not usually have the Bible by one's elbow.  I think there would be very few who in filling the census returns, consider seriously the question whether or not they are telling the exact truth.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>At any rate I think the 1926 returns are about the only thing on which we could reasonably base the Schedule of the Bill.  The overriding clauses in the Bill point out its limitations to everybody.  Section 11 (4) specified that three-fifths of the expenditure will be devoted to certain areas where the valuations, excluding valuations over £20 when divided by the population of the district electoral division, according to the census of 1926, gives a sum not exceeding 21/-.  Three-fifths will be spent in these areas. Then there is the overriding provision as to Irish-speaking households. That inevitably restricts the Bill, and any thinking person will feel, even though putting in a Schedule of this kind, you may run up 600 odd electoral areas; in fact, the housing grants and loans will not be effective as far as fifth-sixths of them are concerned.  I would not exclude any one of them for the reason I said, that you may find a small pocked of Irish speakers in the Breac-Ghaeltacht where the rest of the population might be well off and the conditions of these Irish speakers might be extremely bad from the point of view of housing. The Senator mentioned the Electoral Division of Cloonkeen.  I understand the map is a little bit out of date and that Clonkeen, which was <Col N="320" /> formerly in the Glenamaddy rural district, is now in the Tuam rural district.</P>
    <P>It is now Cloonkeen, Tuam and it used to be Cloonkeen, Glenamaddy.  The one one the Schedule is the correct one.  The Senator has found a slip in the Schedule in connection with Aughrim.  I had not known that there were two areas called Aughrim in the Co. Galway. It is, unfortunately, a mistake in the Schedule.  The Aughrim in the Schedule refers to Galway rural.  In the 1926 census, Aughrim, Galway rural, returned 37.3 of an Irish-speaking population.  He mentioned Glenroe.  I find the figure for that area for 1911 is 52.4, whereas the enumeration of 1925 shows it to be 97.2, and the census of 1926 23.7. The figure of 23.7 seems extraordinary as showing the change that took place from 1911, but still I should say it is more accurate than the figure of 97.2 in 1925.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelComynKC" hpid="Mr. Comyn Mr. Comyn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Comyn</NameTxt>
      <P>Would the Minister say where is Glenroe?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FionanLynch" hpid="Mr. Lynch Mr. Lynch">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lynch</NameTxt>
      <P>I know it is in Co. Clare.  It is an electoral area there, and if the Deputy was a candidate for that area, he would have to get the register for it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelComynKC" hpid="Mr. Comyn Mr. Comyn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Comyn</NameTxt>
      <P>It is in the Corofin area.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. Johnson Mr. Johnson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Johnson</NameTxt>
      <P>Is a correction not necessary because the people in the second district ought to know that they are excluded?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FionanLynch" hpid="Mr. Lynch Mr. Lynch">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lynch</NameTxt>
      <P>I am afraid I will have to get amendments inserted on the Committee Stage in the Schedule.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. Johnson Mr. Johnson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Johnson</NameTxt>
      <P>This is an amendment that should come from the Minister.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Cathaoirleach Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>If you suggest the substance of the amendment he will embody it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FionanLynch" hpid="Mr. Lynch Mr. Lynch">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lynch</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator Mrs. Wyse Power wanted to know about the loans.  There is no restriction on granting loans except that they are limited to the amount of the grant. <Col N="321" /> No loan can be given of more than the grant for a particular dwelling or improvement.  The regulations to be made by the Minister for Finance will deal merely with the rate of interest and the period of repayment. The period of repayment generally will be thirty-five years. Senator Comyn to a great extent went over many of the points which Deputy O'Doherty raised.  As to the restriction of the area in which three fifths of the money is to be expended, I think they have made a reasonable case why I should not tie myself to that.  Again, may I say that there are parts of the Breac-Ghaeltacht where you have Irish-speaking households&mdash;a little Irish speaking community&mdash;where the conditions are as bad as any inside the Fíor-Ghaeltacht, where, however, they could not come within this, because the valuations, divided by the population, might be over twenty-one shillings and the money might not be applied.  Therefore, I would not like to confine all the money to those areas, because of certain pockets outside.</P>
      <P>I would not like Senator Comyn to take it that it must be entirely stone and mortar that will be used in building.  I hope so, but there may be localities where the getting of the stone will be far more expensive than concrete where stone will not be available.  Therefore, there will have to be some cement buildings, and the man can give practically as much labour by carting and mixing and doing the ordinary work that a labourer does in helping a builder.  I would not like to tie myself down.  Generally speaking, I should say that, in most of the Gaeltacht, I know there will be sufficient stone available to make it unnecessary to use concrete for the buildings, but I would not like to tie myself down and say that it will be entirely stone and mortar that will be used and not concrete.  I think I have answered most of the points made. Any other points that arose can be dealt with in Committee.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamBarrington" hpid="Mr. Barrington Mr. Barrington">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Barrington</NameTxt>
      <P>Is it intended to confine the grants which will be <Col N="322" /> made to Irish-speaking people, even though the necessities of the people who do not speak Irish are greater than those who do?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FionanLynch" hpid="Mr. Lynch Mr. Lynch">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lynch</NameTxt>
      <P>As I pointed out in the beginning, the Bill deals with the Gaeltacht.  It is a Bill to deal with the Irish-speaking area and does not apply to places like Dublin, Limerick, Tipperary, etc.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamBarrington" hpid="Mr. Barrington Mr. Barrington">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Barrington</NameTxt>
      <P>But there are many people in the Gaeltacht who speak English.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FionanLynch" hpid="Mr. Lynch Mr. Lynch">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lynch</NameTxt>
      <P>There are.  There are many people who are bi-lingual. There are many people inside the Gaeltacht area who know no Irish. There may be people even in the Fíor-Ghaeltacht who do not know any Irish.  While a preference should be given in these areas to Irish-speaking households, according to the Bill.  I certainly would say that once you had a man in a given area in the Fíor-Ghaeltacht, whether he was an Irish speaker or not, you could not possibly exclude him from the provisions of the Bill.  Everyone around him would benefit, and to cut him off in all his poverty because he did not happen to speak Irish would be carrying the thing rather too far.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>Committee Stage to be taken on Tuesday, 17th December.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Order of" RHead="Business">
    <Title>Order of Business.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Cathaoirleach Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Items Nos. 5, 6 and 7 will appear on the Order Paper tomorrow. No. 8 will not appear, because, by request, after consultation between the Minister and the Senators, it has been adjourned until next week.  Item No. 9, at the request of the President, will remain over until after Christmas.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Constitution (Amendment No. 11)" RHead="Bill, 1928&mdash;Fifth Stage">
    <Title>Constitution (Amendment No. 11) Bill, 1928&mdash;Fifth Stage.</Title>
    <P>Bill received for final consideration and passed.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="University College, Galway," RHead="Bill, 1929&mdash;Fifth Stage">
    <Title>University College, Galway, Bill, 1929&mdash;Fifth Stage.</Title>
    <P>
      <Col N="323" /> Bill received for final consideration and passed.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Civil Service (Transferred Officers)" RHead="Compensation Bill, 1929&mdash;Fifth Stage">
    <Title>Civil Service (Transferred Officers) Compensation Bill, 1929&mdash;Fifth Stage.</Title>
    <P>Question proposed:&mdash;&ldquo;That the Bill be received for final consideration and do now pass.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. Johnson Mr. Johnson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Johnson</NameTxt>
      <P>On this final stage of the Bill I want to place on record a certain statement, supplementary to what I said on the Second Reading of this Bill.  On that occasion I referred to a certain discussion that took place which led to the reconsideration of the decision of the Judicial Committee of the Privy Council in the Wigg-Cochrane case. I want just now to call attention to a letter which appeared in the &ldquo;Irish Times&rdquo; of February 14th, 1929.  The letter was signed by Mr. Alfred Dickie, K.C., who was leading counsel on behalf of the Civil Servants in the appeal that came before the Privy Council.  In the course of that letter, Mr. Dickie says:&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>&ldquo;Sir,&mdash;In your article in today's &lsquo;Irish Times&rsquo; with reference to the Wigg-Cochrane case you state on his deathbed the late Viscount Cave, who had been chairman of the Judicial Committee, wrote a letter to the British Premier in support of Lord Birkenhead's assertion&mdash;that is to say that the Privy Council had not taken full cognisance of a certain Treasury minute.  This is a statement which has got into the papers owing to observations of Lord Birkenhead in the House of Lords when he stated that &lsquo;Lord Cave in a letter to the Prime Minister previous to his death, had admitted that there was a mistake in his judgment.&rsquo;  Owing to the fact that the matter was coming up for discussion before the Privy Council I did not deny this statement before, but the fact is&rdquo;&mdash;and I may say in parenthesis there is good <Col N="324" /> reason to believe this is a fact that could be verified by evidence&mdash;&ldquo;that twenty-four hours before his death Viscount Cave made the following statement: &lsquo;I have made no mistake.  If there has been any clerical error that has nothing to do with the judgment.&rsquo;  Lord Birkenhead in making his statement led people to believe that Lord Cave had said that his judgment was wrong whereas the opposite was the case, and the Privy Council have since decided that his judgment was absolutely right.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>There are a few further lines in the letter not <i>á propos.</i>  My desire in reading this letter is that it should appear on the official records of proceedings of this House so that for future reference the discussions on the previous occasion and on this occasion may be read together.</P>
    <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Electricity Agreements (Adaptation)" RHead="Bill, 1929&mdash;Second Stage">
    <Title>Electricity Agreements (Adaptation) Bill, 1929&mdash;Second Stage.</Title>
    <P>Order for Second Reading read.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDowdall" hpid="Mr. Dowdall Mr. Dowdall">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dowdall</NameTxt>
      <P>I move that this Bill be now read a second time.  The necessity for it has arisen because when the Cork electricity undertaking was being established an agreement was come to between the promoters and the Cork Corporation that in the event of any dispute which might arise with reference to charges the matter was to be referred to the Minister of Transport. There is no Minister of Transport, and this Bill seeks to substitute the Minister for Local Government and Public Health, so that an arbitration may be held and a decision may be given with regard to the charges.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasLinehan" hpid="Mr. Linehan Mr. Linehan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Linehan</NameTxt>
      <P>I beg to second the motion.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.  Committee Stage ordered for tomorrow.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Dublin City and County (Relief" RHead="of the Poor) Bill, 1929">
    <Title>Dublin City and County (Relief of the Poor) Bill, 1929.</Title>
    <P>The following message was received from the Dáil:</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="325" />&ldquo;Dáil Eireann has made an Order discharging the Order for the Second Stage of the Dublin City and County (Relief of the Poor) Bill, 1929, which was received from Seanad Eireann on the 4th July, 1929.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Cathaoirleach Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>That Bill has been embodied in the Bill we have been discussing.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Joint Committee on Remunerations" RHead="of Ministers, etc">
    <Title>Joint Committee on Remunerations of Ministers, etc.</Title>
    <P>
      <Col N="326" /> Ordered: That the report of the Joint Committee do lie upon the Table.  That the report and the proceedings of the Joint Committee be printed.  (Senator O'Hanlon.)</P>
    <P>The Seanad rose at 7 p.m. until Thursday, 12th December, 1929.</P>
  </MainHeading>
</Debate>