<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE Debate SYSTEM "../Debate.dtd"[]>
<Debate DocTitle="Seanad Debate" Day="Thu" Date="18" Month="Jul" Year="1929" Vol="12" No="24" DateIrish="Déardaoin, 18 Iúil 1929" DateEnglish="Thursday, 18 July 1929" House="S" CommitteeEng="" CommitteeIr="" SubNameEng="" cnum="1441">
  <MainHeading Type="Prelude" LHead="" RHead="">
    <Title>
    </Title>
    <P>
      <Col N="1441" /> Do chuaidh an Cathaoirleach i gceannas ar 3 p.m.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Suspension of" RHead="Standing Orders">
    <Title>Suspension of Standing Orders.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="SamuelBrownKC" hpid="Mr. Brown Mr. Brown">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Brown</NameTxt>
      <P>I move:&mdash;</P>
      <P>That Standing Order 95 (Private Business) be suspended for the purpose of enabling the Fifth Stage of the Bank of Ireland Bill, 1929, to be taken to-day.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EdwardBigger" hpid="Sir E. Coey Bigger Sir E. Coey Bigger">
      <NameTxt>Sir E. Coey Bigger</NameTxt>
      <P>I second.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Private Business. - Bank of Ireland" RHead="Bill, 1929&mdash;Fifth Stage">
    <Title>Private Business. - Bank of Ireland Bill, 1929&mdash;Fifth Stage.</Title>
    <P>Question proposed: That the Bank of Ireland Bill, 1929, be received for final consideration and do now pass.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JosephConnolly" hpid="Mr. Connolly Mr. Connolly">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Connolly</NameTxt>
      <P>Would I be in order in speaking on this Bill at this stage?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Cathaoirleach Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes, on the general principle of the Bill as it is before the House.  There are certain things that I cannot allow the Senator to say on it, but I can allow him to say a good many things.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JosephConnolly" hpid="Mr. Connolly Mr. Connolly">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Connolly</NameTxt>
      <P>As I was one of the main opponents of this Bill in its earlier stages, I feel it is only right that I should say a few words before it passes its final stage.  In the early stages of this Bill I ventured to criticise some of the provisions contained in it.  I suffered a good deal of adverse criticism, personally, for daring to suggest that anything in the Bill could be improved on.  It was said that there was no reason behind the objections that I made to the Bill.  I am glad to say that, when the Bill went before the Joint Committee that was set up to consider it, that not only the Committee, but the directors of the Bank of <Col N="1442" /> Ireland particularly, saw that there were certain amendments suggested to it which were reasonable, and to which they offered no objection.  The amendments made to the Bill in Committee, in the main, satisfy me. The main issue involved in the objections that I made to the Bill was to prevent anything in the nature of foreign control operating in any of our main banking institutions here. The Bank of Ireland have accepted amendments to meet the objections that I put up on earlier stages of the Bill.  I would like to say that, personally, I appreciate, not only the method of their acceptance, but the spirit in which they were accepted. Perhaps I should go a little further and express the hope that if, in future, banking legislation becomes necessary, a like spirit of give and take will be shown by the Bank of Ireland.  I have no doubt but it will.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>While I have no further objection to the Bill in its present form.  I would not like it to be inferred that I am in any sense satisfied with the existing conditions that prevail as regards banking in this country.  I feel, first of all, that the rate of interest charged is unduly high on both agricultural and manufacturing industries.  That is one of the big problems that will face us in the future: how we shall be able to secure adequate resources to administer our agricultural and manufacturing industries at an economic rate so that it will be possible to carry on industry here.  That is one feature in connection with our banking system that has developed in an acute form since we last discussed this Bill here.  I suggest that it emphasises and shows clearly the dangers involved in our present position.  There has not been anything in the way of revolutionary development in industry, either from the point of view of manufacture or in any other way, in this country, and yet we find that we are at present suffering from the imposition of an increased bank rate through no fault or through no activity of ours.  That has come to us, not even from the administration of the <Col N="1443" /> banking system across the water, but purely as a result of speculative activity in New York.  That is one of the anomalies that I see in our present banking system.  It is not for me, at this stage, to say how it is going to be overcome.  I did argue, on the First Stage of this Bill, that the cost of money in this country bore no relation to the ordinary law of supply and demand.  On that stage of the Bill I pointed to the tremendous amount of export capital that we had going out of this country, as well as to the tremendous expense the country had to bear, including our Minister for Finance, in raising loans outside the country.  I still feel that this is an issue which will have to be met sooner or later.  The position is, that we have to pay an abnormal and an unreasonably high rate of interest for such money as is required for the running of the Government and of the country, while these available resources which are the property of the citizens of this State are, through the medium of the banks, being exported from the country.  There is another point that, if in order, I would like to mention.  It is this: that it does not seem to have penetrated the minds of bank directors in this country that, in the main, we are carrying the old overdrafts&mdash;moneys which were loaned or required at the period of highest inflation in this country.  That applies particularly to land.  I suggest to the bankers of this country&mdash;I feel that, following the attitude they have shown in regard to this Bill, they may perhaps consider the suggestion in a reasonable spirit&mdash;that the banks here are carrying this inflated figure in most of their overdraft arrangements at a period when deflation has taken place.  Banking is the one business in the world that I know of that has not written down its stock to anything like its present-day value.  All of us know that throughout the country there are industries, whether they be farms or manufacturing businesses, which are saddled with these old loans contracted <Col N="1444" /> at a time when values were entirely different to what they are to-day.  I suggest that there can be no reasonable hope of real prosperity in the country until our bankers adjust their overdrafts and their balance-sheet figures, in the shape of their ledger accounts, to present-day values.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JohnKeaneBart" hpid="Sir John Keane Sir John Keane">
      <NameTxt>Sir John Keane</NameTxt>
      <P>What about the deposits?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JosephConnolly" hpid="Mr. Connolly Mr. Connolly">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Connolly</NameTxt>
      <P>I am dealing with overdrafts and loans given by the banks.  We will speak of the deposits later, perhaps.  At the moment, that is the position.  We know there are farms having overdrafts of £6,000 and £7,000, and that if these farms were put on the market they would not realise more than £2,000 or £3,000.  That is a regrettable state of affairs.  I doubt very much if it is good banking policy, or if it is, in any sense, good business for the banks to continue to carry on on that basis.  It may be that if the figures were adjusted farms that are uneconomic at present would become economic, and that in the long run the banks would have good accounts instead of having to write off ultimately bad debts.  One other point I want to mention, and it is in the nature of a grievance, perhaps: When the Committee was being set up to consider this Bill, for some reason or another two of the proposed members of the Committee were barred.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Cathaoirleach Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Did the Senator make any objection on that point when the Committee was being formed?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MauriceMoore" hpid="Colonel Moore Colonel Moore">
      <NameTxt>Colonel Moore</NameTxt>
      <P>I made an objection.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JosephConnolly" hpid="Mr. Connolly Mr. Connolly">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Connolly</NameTxt>
      <P>I personally did not make an objection.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Cathaoirleach Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>The Senator would not be in order in dealing with that matter now.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JosephConnolly" hpid="Mr. Connolly Mr. Connolly">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Connolly</NameTxt>
      <P>I bow to your ruling.  I appreciate, as I say, the spirit in which the banking directors met the various arguments put up in regard to the Bill.  So far as the <Col N="1445" /> Bill is concerned, my immediate concern was to prevent foreign control in this country.  That is a menace that exists, and it has been prevented in this Bill.  It is a growing menace.  The next steps that will be taken by international bankers will be to control the finances of the world, and they are under way, We want, as far as possible, to preserve our own institutions and run them for our own welfare.</P>
      <P>Motion put and agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Private Business. - Pier and Harbour Provisional" RHead="Order Confirmation Bill, 1929&mdash;First Stage">
    <Title>Private Business. - Pier and Harbour Provisional Order Confirmation Bill, 1929&mdash;First Stage.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Leas-Chathaoirleach Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I move for leave to introduce a Bill entitled Pier and Harbour Provisional Order Confirmation Bill, 1929.</P>
      <P>Leave granted.</P>
      <P>Second Stage ordered for Thursday, 25th July.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Public Business. - Trim Urban District Council" RHead="(Dissolution) Bill, 1929&mdash;Second and Final Stages">
    <Title>Public Business. - Trim Urban District Council (Dissolution) Bill, 1929&mdash;Second and Final Stages.</Title>
    <P>Question proposed&mdash;That the Trim Urban District Council (Dissolution) Bill, 1929, be read a Second Time&mdash;put and agreed to.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Public Business. - Suspension" RHead="of Standing Orders">
    <Title>Public Business. - Suspension of Standing Orders.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="SamuelBrownKC" hpid="Mr. Brown Mr. Brown">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Brown</NameTxt>
      <P>I move:&mdash;</P>
      <P>&ldquo;That the Standing Orders be suspended for the purpose of taking the remaining stages of the Trim Urban District Council (Dissolution) Bill, 1929, to-day.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDouglas" hpid="Mr. Douglas Mr. Douglas">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Douglas</NameTxt>
      <P>I second.</P>
      <P>Motion put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>The Seanad went into Committee.</P>
      <P>Bill put through Committee Stage without amendment.</P>
      <P>The Seanad went out of Committee.</P>
      <P>Bill reported, put through its final stages, and passed.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Public Business. - Electricity (Finance) Bill, 1929&mdash;Second" RHead="Stage. (Certified by the Ceann Comhairle of the Dáil as a Money Bill)">
    <Title>Public Business. - Electricity (Finance) Bill, 1929&mdash;Second Stage.   (Certified by the Ceann Comhairle of the Dáil as a Money Bill)</Title>
    <Col N="1446" />
    <Speaker pid="JohnKeaneBart" hpid="Sir John Keane Sir John Keane">
      <NameTxt>Sir John Keane</NameTxt>
      <P>There are one or two points in connection with this Bill on which I would like to have information.  I should like the Minister, if he has the figures, to say how much of the estimated final sum of £5,800,000 would be interest and how much expenditure on works.  I should like to know also whether the £156,000 which is going to be voted to the Electricity Supply Board will be all the moneys they will have available and be entitled to use for the payment of interest, apart from receipts from sales.  Is it the position that they will not be allowed to use any of the capital sum of £2,500,000 previously voted for the purpose of paying interest?  There is only £165,000 now being voted for that purpose.  With regard to navigation, there are one or two matters with which I would like to deal.  I think under Section 4 of this Bill the sum of £132,000 is excluded as a burden on electricity, and is going to be subsequently provided for by charges on navigation, or in some other way.  I think the inference is that it is going to be met by navigation. I should like the Seanad to refresh its memory with regard to the charges in navigation.  In a statement made by the Minister for Industry and Commerce in the year 1925, on a resolution practically sanctioning the preliminary stages in this scheme, the Minister indicated that if the people interested in navigation were prepared to use the old method, the existing canals, there would be no charge placed on them at all, that the lock that would be necessary to lift the boats out of the old canal to the higher level would be met by the electricity scheme.  But if other methods of navigation were required, if they were to proceed up to the tail race to be lifted into the head race at Ardnacrusha, the cost of £75,000 would fall upon navigation.  Reading the debate which took place on <Col N="1447" /> that occasion, I think it is clear that the navigation interests were to be allowed to say which they preferred &mdash;the old method or the new or present method.  This is what was said (Official Report, 2nd April, 1925, col. 1763):&mdash;</P>
      <P>&ldquo;if the navigation company desire that new method of navigation, £75,000 would be an additional charge upon them.  If they desire to proceed in the old way, then the power scheme will have to bear the charge for the new lock at a cost of £20,000, and navigation will be as before.&rdquo;</P>
      <P>I should like the Minister to say if the parties interested in navigation were consulted, and whether they did elect for the present scheme, which it was estimated in 1925 was going to cost £75,000.  There is a further matter.  This £75,000, without any explanation in the Dáil&mdash;I hope the Minister will give an explanation now&mdash;is increased to £132,000.  As far as I can judge from the scanty information at my disposal, there are no definite changes in the general character of the new scheme.  It was always intended that the new scheme would involve lifting the boats from the tail race into the head works, and that is all that is being done now. Therefore, one would like to know how that sum has increased by 80 per cent. roughly, whereas generally the works have only increased roughly by ten per cent.  I ask the House to accept the view that this heavy burden should not be placed on navigation.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Minister for Industry and Commerce (Mr. McGilligan) Patrick McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Industry and Commerce (Mr. McGilligan)</NameTxt>
      <P>Why assume that it is going to be on navigation?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnKeaneBart" hpid="Sir John Keane Sir John Keane">
      <NameTxt>Sir John Keane</NameTxt>
      <P>I think the Minister has in effect said so.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>No; I think not.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnKeaneBart" hpid="Sir John Keane Sir John Keane">
      <NameTxt>Sir John Keane</NameTxt>
      <P>If the Minister will say it is not, well and good.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1448" />
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>I have not said that either.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnKeaneBart" hpid="Sir John Keane Sir John Keane">
      <NameTxt>Sir John Keane</NameTxt>
      <P>Assuming that it is to be placed on navigation, it is a very heavy burden.  If it is not, the navigation interests will be quite satisfied.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. Johnson Mr. Johnson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Johnson</NameTxt>
      <P>I was hoping the Minister would repeat for the benefit of the Seanad some of the statements that he made in the Dáil a few days ago.  He made a very interesting and lucid statement full of information&mdash;rather too full for easy understanding of all its aspects, but nevertheless a very valuable statement of the position.  He was astonished that his statement of the position showed so slight a departure from the estimates that were made when the scheme was originated.  I am not going to dilate upon the extent of the increase, whether it is too great or too small, but I want to say that the figures he gave, no matter how closely they may be examined, are not sufficient to enable us to arrive at a true estimate as to whether the increase in the charge was excessive or not.  We would require certain other information. For instance, the £5,210,000 which was originally voted was based upon the Experts' report, which itself allowed for a loss of interest, during the construction period and the period before the scheme became profitable, of fifteen per cent.  I think we would require to know whether that fifteen per cent. has been over-estimated or under-estimated.  Further, there is a figure that runs through the construction estimate of 8¼ per cent. for a possible increase in wages.  Eight and a quarter per cent. was allowed on the total cost of £2,343,000 for a possible increase in wages.  That £2,343,000 was a charge inclusive of the hire of machinery and everything connected with construction. If we assume for a moment that wages amounted to one-half of the total, that is a margin of sixteen and a half per cent. for a possible increase in wages.  We would require to know whether or not that figure has been reached before we could <Col N="1449" /> decide whether or not the increase in the cost of the scheme has been within the ten per cent. that has been mentioned.</P>
      <P>There is a further item which would require to be unveiled.  On page 88 of the Experts' Report dealing with the electrical part, the Experts say:</P>
      <P>The Experts consider the prices to be fair.  The clauses concerning copper notation and wages will probably not have any appreciable effect upon the total cost of the mechanical and electrical parts.  A further rise in the exchange value of the pound will cause a decrease of the cost.</P>
      <P>That, I think, was dated in the latter part of 1924, and I think the stabilisation of the German mark did not take place until some months later than that.  One would therefore require to know whether any allowance has been or ought to have been made in respect of the change in the exchange value of the £, so that the figures that are available are not yet sufficient to enable us to arrive at a fair computation as to whether the Experts' estimate has been exceeded by too much or whether it has been kept within reasonable limits.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>There is another matter that I think ought to be discussed on this Bill&mdash;it is outside the mere technicalities of the scheme, but it touches upon State policy&mdash;and that is in regard to electrical development and the use that is to be made of the electrical power.  The plan is, of course, to hand over the scheme to the Electricity Supply Board, and require of them that they should cover expenses, including interest on capital charges, but not make a profit.  Obviously, the obligation upon the Board is to cover the expenditure. But there is involved in their policy the question as to how they are going to use that power; what will be the influences upon the general economic activities of the country; whether, for instance, they will tend towards encouraging power consumption for industry or for agriculture or for <Col N="1450" /> lighting mainly, and where will their bias lie.  Who will have the influence upon the policy that they will carry through for the purpose of making the scheme pay?</P>
    <P>I made a suggestion at the very inception of the discussion upon this Bill that it would be good policy for the country to throw capital charges upon the National Exchequer. I repeated that in another form on the 1925 Bill, urging that, at least for a period, much longer than the three or four years up to 1932 then suggested, privilege should be given, by way of low charges, to encourage consumption, and that for a much longer period there should be freedom to run the concern at a loss for the purpose of encouraging consumption.  I want to go back to that proposition, and to urge upon the Minister that he should come to an arrangement with the Board, and, with the assistance of the Minister for Finance, embark upon a bold policy of power for production for nothing.</P>
    <P>I think it would be a profitable business for the country.  A quarter of a million or three hundred thousand pounds would be better spent by that method of encouraging industrial production than in any other way.  The Minister for Finance told us a while ago, when dealing with the question of de-rating, that it was a proposition that this country would be bound to meet because of the developments in other countries, and I submit to him for consideration that by way of aiding industrial production, free electrical power would be probably the most advantageous method to the manufacturer, the most beneficial to the country and the least costly.</P>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Cathaoirleach Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I think that the Senator is really talking about electrical policy in general instead of this particular Bill.  The Senator has already talked a good deal on that matter, and I ask him now not to be too long.  This would be relevant to a Bill dealing with electricity, but not to this Bill.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. Johnson Mr. Johnson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Johnson</NameTxt>
      <P>I am not going to continue very long, but I submit it <Col N="1451" /> is important when dealing with the charge that is to be laid upon the Electricity Board.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Cathaoirleach Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>It may be very important, but it is not relevant.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. Johnson Mr. Johnson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Johnson</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not want to go into anything that is not relevant, but I submit, when either seeking to minimise the charge upon the Electricity Board or to increase it, as the case may be, it is really germane to discuss how they are going to utilise the powers and the money granted to them.  I want to submit to the Minister for Industry and Commerce and the Minister for Finance that by the provision of free or almost free power to the electrical user for productive purposes existing industries would be encouraged and new industries would be attracted.  The future of the country depends, I think it will be generally admitted, as much upon the possible development of industrial activities as upon anything.  We heard a good deal of talk recently about a tariff on flour. I find from estimates given as to the amount of power used in the flour mills that free fuel would equal practically one shilling per sack of flour.  Free fuel may be too much, because there is the cost of distribution to be taken into account, but a bulk supply of power for nothing would go very far to meet the legitimate demands of many industrial undertakings.  Taking the reports of the industrial census, one finds that about five per cent. of the net output of productive industry equals the sum paid for fuel.  I am not suggesting for a moment that the whole of that could be met by electricity, but I urge upon Ministers that they should conduct an inquiry into the possibility of industrial development by way of a very cheap supply of power for productive purposes. Taking a very rough estimate, based upon the only figures I have, it would seem to me, from the figures given by the Minister and allowing one penny per unit for bulk supply power for lighting and domestic <Col N="1452" /> purposes, that the cost to the community would not be more than about £300,000 even upon the figures for 1932 and leaving out of account subsequent developments.  The prospect of very cheap power would enable Irish industrialists to meet the very cheap power of Norway, Canada and Switzerland and other places and would enable them to overcome the handicap which Irish manufacturers and industrialists are inevitably bound to encounter.</P>
      <P>I think it will be realised that some of the new electro-chemical and metallurgical industries might possibly be attracted to this country if they were guaranteed a practically free bulk supply of power for these purposes.  One way or another, I urge the Minister to consult with the Supply Board and endeavour to examine this proposition and take into sympathetic consideration how far it would be possible to use the finances of the electrical supply scheme, aided by the revenue, in such a way as to promote industrial activity for the benefit of the country.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>I can only attempt to answer the questions put to me by Senator Sir John Keane at the moment in a rather rough and ready way, but in a way, I hope, that will be sufficient to satisfy the Senator. He asked for a division of the new sum of £5,835,000 as between the moneys actually to be spent on construction and the moneys to be used either for interest charges or to meet losses during the unremunerative years.  I cannot divide that accurately at the moment, but I put this problem to him in return: The old sum of £5,200,000 was divided roughly into £4,600,000 to be spent on construction and £600,000 which was to meet the interest charges plus the loss of revenue during the unremunerative two or three years.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>That division was founded upon the original Siemens-Schuckert project, which set aside a sum for construction and which calculated that 15 per cent. of that should be sufficient to meet interest charges <Col N="1453" /> during the period in which the losses would be incurred.  There was a further division of that 15 per cent. into 12 per cent. for interest and 3 per cent. for the period during which the Shannon scheme would not be paying its way.  If the Senator would take the new sum of £5,835,000 plus the sum of money handed over to the Electricity Supply Board under Section 2, that is £156,000, and make a similar division he will get the answer to his query.  We estimate that £156,000 is 3 per cent. of the capital costs. We are handing that over to the Electricity Supply Board in order to meet the losses of the unremunerative years, as under this Bill the Department will have to meet all interest charges before anything is handed over to the Shannon Board. That is the nearest approach to a reply that I can give the Senator at the moment.</P>
    <P>I would direct the attention of the Seanad to a promise of mine in the Dáil that, for further clarification of all Shannon accounts I would hereafter introduce a Token Vote, when we have the final cost of the whole scheme actually determined.</P>
    <P>With regard to the £156,000, that sum is expressed under Section 2 of the Amending Bill to take the place of sub-section (2) of Section 12.  Sub-section (2) of Section 12 did not provide an exact sum, but it gave a calculation as to a sum to be handed over to meet interest, and the arrears of interest.  Then it went on to say in the third sub-section: &ldquo;The total amount advanced for any purpose, other than to meet liabilities, shall be two and a half millions.&rdquo;  Now instead of an indefinite amount of money in Section 2 we are putting in the definite amount of £156,000.  It seems to me that the two and a-half million cannot be used for the purpose of meeting interest and arrears of interest, but the £156,000 can.  That £156,000 was arrived at by taking 3 per cent. of what we estimated to be the capital cost, and that 3 per cent. will <Col N="1454" /> meet interest and other charges. With regard to navigation, I cannot go into the details of this matter or show how that sum is to be made up or is to be determined. Originally the navigation was estimated to cost £94,000.  It was stated that £20,000 was to be the cost of putting a lock in the weir.  The amount that could be borne by and be equitably put against the users of electricity for interfering with navigation was £20,000. That was the old sum, and that old sum of £20,000 is still here.  The old figure of £5,210,000 did not include the £74,000.  That £74,000 was left out of the calculation altogether.  It was to be met somehow, but the &ldquo;how&rdquo; was not settled.  We simply put in £152,000 in the same way, the figures having risen from £94,000 to £152,000.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JohnKeaneBart" hpid="Sir John Keane Sir John Keane">
      <NameTxt>Sir John Keane</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister said that £58,000 is chargeable against navigation.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>Give me the reference.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnKeaneBart" hpid="Sir John Keane Sir John Keane">
      <NameTxt>Sir John Keane</NameTxt>
      <P>It is on top of column 375, for the 4th July, 1929.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>That was a slip, as will be seen from the context. I think if the Senator will read through the whole speech he will find that I mentioned that as far as the present proposals go we are not charging electricity consumers with the £132,000 but are not deciding who is positively to be charged. In the old scheme, we set out to charge £20,000 against the Shannon navigation.  The only thing determined in this Bill is that this sum of £132,000 is not to be paid back as at present things go by consumers of electricity.  The cost of navigation improvement is not to be charged against the electricity consumers, except the £20,000 previously provided.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>How the £132,000 will be met will have to be decided when we see what are the moneys to be saved to navigation users by the <Col N="1455" /> elimination of the ten or twelve locks and by the saving in the cost of maintenance charges afterwards. In that way we will find out how the navigation users have benefited, by elimination of some of the present charges, and in addition there will be the speed improvement.</P>
    <P>There were two expressions of opinion in the Dáil by members of the same Party as to how this cost should be borne.  One was that it should be borne by the taxpayers, and another expression of opinion equally vehement was that this cost should not be borne by the taxpayers. The determination of that matter will have to wait.  As to why the figure of £94,000 has gone up to £152,000, on that we will have to await the presentation of the final accounts.  Until that time we must postpone final decision as to how it should be charged.</P>
    <P>But I think it will be found hereafter that in one part of the canal the cost more or less went up in the proportion in which these navigation costs show an increase from £94,000 to £132,000.  I think it will be found that the increase was due to the increase in the earth excavating and rock cutting costs.  Again, I would emphasise that anything I have said on the navigation question is hedged round with reservations. But before this matter is settled we will have an opportunity of discussing the proposals in the Oireachtas. Settlement must be either by legislation or by Orders.  I promise to give an opportunity for discussing it before the final determination is made.</P>
    <P>Senator Johnson asked about points of detail.  Again, I will answer in a rough and ready fashion, pointing out that another opportunity will be given hereafter for query and reply.  As to the 10 per cent., whether that is an over or an under-estimate, if one reads the paragraph where the 10 per cent. occurs and applies it exactly as it was meant to be read I think it will be found that we are very definitely under the 10 per cent.  With regard <Col N="1456" /> to the 8½ per cent. addition to meet a possible increase in wages, that was taken into consideration when we were fixing the unit price.  I do not know if I can answer the Senator's question by saying that I have lost on wages, and lost rather badly.</P>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. Johnson Mr. Johnson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Johnson</NameTxt>
      <P>We can only understand these things when we have the contrast.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>I agree.  As regards the exchange value of the mark, that point arose when the contract was being made, and it can only be properly understood if and when the full circumstances of the contract are made clear.  As to who will direct the policy of the Electricity Supply Board, I would like to follow up what Senator Johnson has said, although the Cathaoirleach may rule it out as somewhat irrelevant. Actually, the Electricity Supply Board is in control of all policy, but although we have relieved the Board of the type of inquisition involved in Parliamentary questions, we insist that they submit reports to the Oireachtas.  These reports will give grounds for debate, and in these debates directions on policy may be revealed. Under present legislation these directions could not well be imposed on the Electricity Supply Board, but they could be put in such a way that the Board could not very well ignore them.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>But without special directions the Board must proceed on the lines of an ordinary commercial concern. Their object is to make the scheme pay in the quickest possible time, and with that object they will have to look for consumers, and they will have to conduct affairs on a normal business course.  It will be, of course, the duty of the Executive Council from time to time to direct the Electricity Supply Board if the occasion arises.  If the Board does not follow the policy as outlined to them, then there might have to be a change in the legislation.  The Senator went on to indicate that in his <Col N="1457" /> opinion there should be power granted free to industrial users.  Of course, the Electricity Supply Board could not follow that line.  To enable them to act in this way there would have to be a definite line of policy laid down by the Government, and I will say a little more about that later on.  Senator Johnson previously did make the suggestion that capital charges should be thrown on national funds and, if necessary, the whole scheme should be run at a loss in order to encourage consumption.  A suggestion of that sort must be considered in the light of the new facts. What are the new facts?  The facts are that if there is anything ahead of us it is not a deficit in the Shannon revenues, but rather the opposite. Let us take the calculation that I gave to the Dáil regarding the automatic increase in the consumption of electricity year by year.  Not merely have the prophecies of a few years been upheld, but it would seem that the most sanguine hopes then entertained will be improved upon.  The Electricity Supply Board are in a position to know what the position is.  They have been making arrangements for the supply of electricity, and they estimate that in 1932, instead of the 110 million units originally estimated as the demand on the scheme, the Shannon will have to deliver fully 144 million units.  That will be the demand in 1932 without any activity on the part of the Board.</P>
    <P>Matters of policy will have to be considered hereafter, but unless there is some big problem to be faced, such as would be involved by the encouragement of industries by supplying power free of charge, I would rather like to have the early years of the Shannon scheme unclouded. I would like to have it made a complete and entire success.  I expect a great deal more from the Shannon scheme than merely the sale of so many million units at a certain price.  The whole scheme is a big one.  Young engineeers were put on the work, and have been opposed to foreign engineers of great experience. I would like to have the <Col N="1458" /> greatest revelation made as to how completely they have achieved what was put up to them as an almost insuperable task. I would like to have that revealed in such a way that there can be no mistake about it.</P>
    <P>In contrasting the 144 million units estimated demand in 1932 with the 110 million units generally mentioned as Shannon output it must not be thought that we are going to be 34 million units short in our deliveries. The Shannon will have a greater delivery than 110 million units, but if it sells 110 million units at a certain price, then the scheme pays.  Owing to there being a slight delay in completion, certain additions had to be made to the Dublin plant, and that means that the Dublin plant is a much more powerful stand-by than ever before.  That shows that as distinct from the 110 million units which was prophesied to be the output of the scheme, there will be a bigger sale possible. The figure of 110 million units, if it is sold at a certain price, will leave the revenue equal to the expenditure.</P>
    <P>There is some evidence of the scheme being a very big success at the moment.  We are only now beginning to realise how conservative were the reports of the experts. Originally we based our calculations on a sale of 110 million units&mdash;we took that as a maximum.  But other things must be taken into consideration&mdash;the rainfall over the whole catchment area and the flow out of the Shannon.  Our 110 million units were calculated on statistics obtained in respect of the driest year in a period of forty years, and it was calculated that in a normal year there might be 20 million or 30 million units extra.  When we come to the new development, the second stage, we will have the total output at a fraction of the original cost.  It is calculated that if we sell 110 million units we will have £486,000 per annum in order to make ends meet. When we come to the further stage of development the revenue will be <Col N="1459" /> double, but the cost of production will be increased only by one-third. Every addition made to this scheme will mean the cheapening of the unit cost to everybody.</P>
    <P>A further point was raised by Senator Johnson when he talked about throwing certain costs on the national funds.  There is one very extraordinary point in the whole economics of the Shannon.  The £486,000 per annum required in order to make the scheme pay includes two items, and many people think it wrong that both these items should be included in the annual bill.  It includes payment for interest charges and also a sinking fund which will have repaid the entire sum of money in a period of 40 years, and will have paid interest on this money all the time.</P>
    <P>In addition, every year there is set aside a sufficient sum for renewals and repairs to keep the plant in first class condition. So that as the scheme's finances are at present arranged we are not merely meeting interest and sinking fund charges, but we are setting aside a certain amount for renewals and repairs each year, so that at the end of forty years the users will have a completely new plant in first-class condition, renewed and repaired to the last point, and will have no interest or sinking fund charges to meet.  Interest and sinking fund charges amount to 70 per cent. of the £468,000 that has to be met each year.  It is questionable whether there should not be a better distribution of that, so that instead of throwing it over a period of forty years, the charges for interest and the renewals and repairs should be spaced over a longer period.  It is difficult fully to justify in a scheme of this sort, that we should ask consumers for forty years to bear such charges, and that at the end of that time they will hand over to their successors a plant entirely free from interest and sinking fund charges, a first class plant brought up to the highest perfection. It is doubtful whether that should be carried out in its entirety, <Col N="1460" /> but I would rather go ahead with it as it is for the first few years.  We have a scheme that is very much criticised.  We are told that we will not get the consumption which we need to make the scheme a paying one.  Some estimates put the cost of the scheme at ten, and even fifteen millions.  We were told that the price of the unit will go up so enormously that electricity in this country could not compete with other agents.</P>
    <P>I stressed a figure in the Dáil on the last day and I would stress it again here.  The net result of the extra money I now require is best shown in the new figures that have to be substituted for the table on Page 103 of the Experts' Report.  The Experts previously gave two ways in which interest and charges might be met. One of the ways was that they took the cost of the earthworks and power houses and said: &ldquo;You will have so many units and it will cost so much to get it to this point.&rdquo;  They made a calculation and said: &ldquo;If you get to .41d. it will pay.&rdquo;  They went further and said: &ldquo;At the end of the 100 KV. system you pay your way when selling at .52d.&rdquo;  They added that after reaching 35 KV. transformer stations the charge would increase to .74d. and at the 10 KV. transformer stations it would be .84d. As a result of the new money which we have had to spend certain additions must be made to each of these fractions of a penny.  These charges are to be increased until the .42 becomes .5 and until the .84 becomes .9.  That is the increase. That is one of the variables that is now, more or less, fixed.  The estimate of 110 million units was in the region of prophecy.  It was a prophecy which was based on calculation, and we say, looking back through the years, that our prophecy has been not merely fulfilled but that the consumption is likely to outrun what was estimated.  The automatic increase, if it continues at its present rate, brings us in 1932 nearly up to the point of 110 million units.  The Electricity Supply <Col N="1461" /> Board have gone further and said that in 1932 we shall have a demand for 144 million units.  That being the situation&mdash;unless it is done in a careful, judicious way so that there will be no be-clouding of the estimate&mdash;I would rather have no spacing out of the period in which interest and expenditure on repairs will be met.</P>
    <P>I would rather let the scheme operate as it is until 1932 and, when it is beyond doubt that it is paying and when the enterprise has been justified, we might make certain changes in the finance arrangements. I would not allow any pride with regard to the works to interfere with such a thing as Senator Johnson suggested if good reason be shown for it.  If we are going to do anything of the kind we can always make our arrangements so that the final costs will always appear.  I ask the Senator to consider his previous suggestion in the light of what I have said. We are going on the most conservative basis and we believe that we are going to get the consumption estimated.  We have got one side of the account almost complete.  We know where we are.  The sale price of the unit is now .9d. in contrast to the .84d. previously estimated.  It would be well for the Seanad to read again the report of the experts and to see the basis on which the whole scheme is founded.  It may be the subject of debate afterwards whether the interest and sinking fund charges as well as the cost of renewals and repairs, will be put in full on the consumer of these times or whether repayments shall not be spaced out over a larger period of years.</P>
    <P>Question&mdash;&ldquo;That the Bill be read a Second Time&rdquo;&mdash;put and agreed to.</P>
    <P>Committee Stage fixed for Friday, 19th July.</P>
    <P>The Seanad went into Committee.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Public Business. - Appropriation" RHead="Bill, 1929&mdash;Committee">
    <Title>Public Business. - Appropriation Bill, 1929&mdash;Committee.</Title>
    <P>
      <Col N="1462" /> Sections 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, Schedule (A) and Schedule (B) (Part 1 and Part II.) put and agreed to.</P>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Cathaoirleach Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister for Justice will be very pleased if the House would take the recommendation dealing with Vote No. 31 first, as he wishes to get away.</P>
      <P>Agreed.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JosephConnolly" hpid="Mr. Connolly Mr. Connolly">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Connolly</NameTxt>
      <P>I move:</P>
      <P>Schedule (B) Part III, Vote No. 31.  To delete in column 3 the figures &ldquo;38,869,&rdquo; and to substitute therefor the figures &ldquo;38,769.&rdquo;</P>
      <P>I do not know whether there is anything sinister in the change of programme. However, as the Minister is the Minister all the time, and we have equal pleasure or displeasure in meeting him at all times, we had better get on with the job.  I want to move the reduction stated in the recommendation appearing in my name.  I do this as it is perhaps one of the only available means we have of calling attention to the Minister's attitude in this House yesterday.  In the course of my analysis of the appropriations, I ventured to deal with the Department of the Minister.  I did not make any particular criticism of the Minister's Department, but I did read a statement, and I think the House will agree that I presented that statement with the full qualifications that it was a statement containing allegations which I was not prepared to say definitely were true or false.  Certain of the statements were obviously true, at all events to me, as they were vouched for by Deputy de Valera. The Minister's attitude was not to reply to the statement at all.  Well, we are not surprised at that; the Minister does not reply to any statement as a rule in this House.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I do not know, in view of the experience some of us had yesterday, whether it is desirable to raise any question in this House, or <Col N="1463" /> whether the Minister resents questions. Is he running a Department which is in any sense subject to the will and the authority of the Oireachtas? Is he in any sense subject to his constituents or the Irish people, or is he the new Mussolini arrived in the shape of the &ldquo;Playboy of the Western World,&rdquo; who is going to dominate the whole of the House, the people, and all the functions of law and order in Ireland? I think it is a very serious matter for this House to sit here and be insulted, as the Minister undoubtedly insulted us yesterday.  He did not insult me; that is beyond his power; but he did insult this Chamber, and I submit he insulted you, sir, because of your special plea to him to attend to the business of the House.  When you tried to rule him into order, just as you rule other members into order&mdash;and we try to obey your ruling&mdash;the Minister ignored you, and insulted the House by ignoring the Chairman in this way.  I submit that that is not treatment to which our Chairman should be subjected and it is not treatment to which this House should be subjected.</P>
    <P>What did the Minister do yesterday? I made a perfectly cool, calm, deliberate statement.  It was not my own statement.  It was read quietly and, I hope, listened to attentively by everybody in this House.  The Minister did not attempt to make any reply to me.  He lashed himself into a perfect frenzy and he read a letter which appeared in a newspaper from one of our Bishops, but which had really nothing to do with the issue I had raised.  Some people call that a quibble.  I call it flagrant dishonesty, and I say it in your presence and the Minister's presence.  There are many things I think that the Minister for Justice could learn from that Bishop and from various Bishops, which would be very efficacious to him, as well as the stuff which he brought in from that particular Bishop to this House.  I suggest that that letter did not at all apply to any member <Col N="1464" /> of the House.  I sincerely hope it did not, and I do not believe it did.  He continued to read the letter and entirely ignored the subject brought to his notice in the form of charges and a request for investigation, with the distinct qualification that we did not know how far the charges were true or false but we did suggest and demand that a full investigation should be made.  The Minister's retort in one portion of the speech was that my attitude was a direct encouragement to criminally disposed people, or words to that effect.  I suggest that was not true.  I claim it was false.  I claim that it was a lie, and I made no statement whatever further than reading out the letter.</P>
    <P>It might occur to one that the reverse of that was the case.  The Minister's attitude towards this House&mdash;and it has been consistent in all his activities in this House&mdash; was a direct encouragement to lawlessness on the part of those whom he is supposed to have under control. I suggest that his statement and his appalling attitude were a direct encouragement to anything in the form of lawlessness amongst his own subordinates. I feel that this House was outraged.  I feel that the profession to which the Minister belongs and which he is supposed to adorn was also outraged.  The Minister stated that whether there was going to be an investigation or not was entirely a matter for him.  Now that is a very serious state of affairs.  I wonder how far we are under the heel of this new Mussolini who has arrived?  Is there a Constitution? Is there any law or order, or is Mr. Fitzgerald-Kenney, Minister for Justice&mdash;or should I call him Minister for Injustice?&mdash;going to be the be-all and the end-all, to say who is to live and who is not to live, who is to have freedom and who is not to have freedom, in this country?  I would like to clear that point up, as well as to clear up the direct charges made in the letter read here yesterday.  I put down this recommendation with the one specific object in view, to call attention to the undignified, indecent treatment handed out to us <Col N="1465" /> by the Minister for Justice yesterday. I say here in his presence that he was undignified, that he was indecent, that it was a disgrace to him and to his profession, and an insult and an outrage on this House.  I leave it to Senators, whatever way they may vote, to ask themselves in their hearts and consciences if that was not the feeling of every decent Senator who left the Chamber last evening.</P>
    <Speaker pid="SeamusRobinson" hpid="Mr. Robinson Mr. Robinson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Robinson</NameTxt>
      <P>I beg to second the recommendation.  The recommendation is not moved as a vote of censure on the Government, nor is it intended as a vote of censure on the Minister for Justice, though both deserve censure, but we do wish to censure the Minister for his speech yesterday.  I appeal to Senators to let him see that he will not be allowed to flout the feelings of the Seanad and the country in the way he did yesterday, especially when passing this recommendation it will not necessarily mean the downfall of the Government.  The diatribe, as it was described by Senator Connolly yesterday, certainly astonished me.  I felt, speaking to his friends afterwards, that it rasped the finer feelings of his own friends.  After all, Senator Connolly read out a statement by Deputy de Valera, who is accounted generally the second most important man in the country, one of the men with the greatest amount of responsibility.  It was a statement drawn up by him, having been on the spot and having investigated certain things which he regarded as being an outrage on an individual&mdash;if true, of course.  The Minister was merely asked to have the thing inquired into.  Instead of that, he practically told this House to mind its own business.  Not only that, but from his privileged position here, he acted the part of the <i>agent provocateur.</i>  He told his agents to continue just to do what they liked, that he would see there would be no inquiry into their conduct, no matter how reprehensible.  In fact, he told them to continue, that it was practically his opinion that they should continue exactly as they are doing. <Col N="1466" /> How the Minister expects us or anybody else to have any respect for the institutions of this country after hearing the speech yesterday, passes my understanding.  The vast majority of Republicans have come to the conclusion that they will act as though the institutions of this country had moral sanction.  I hasten to say straight away that we deny there is any moral sanction, except that they are the only alternative to chaos, and that does give a very strong moral sanction, I admit. After listening to the Minister for Justice yesterday, certainly the institution of justice in this country is no alternative to chaos.  The Minister's only suggestion of justice, if I might so call it, the only little thing which showed that he was Minister for Justice, was a recommendation to Mr. Ryan, if he has been treated unfairly, to bring the devil and his agents into his own courts.  That certainly was anything but fair, and I do not think Senators ought to stand by such statements as that. After all, how could Mr. Ryan, unless he was a very rich man, bring those people to the court and succeed? And if he did, he would get no compensation.  Not only that, but all the Republicans in the country, before they would be safe, would have to bring the Minister's agents to court and keep them there permanently, keep their cases <i>sub judice</i> perpetually before they would have any protection whatever. Surely, the Seanad is not going to stand for that sort of nonsense?  I am afraid that the true and only explanation of the Minister's attitude is simply that he is afraid of his own bullies.  No matter what some of us may have thought of the late Mr. Kevin O'Higgins, there was one thing certainly he did try, that was to introduce discipline into the police.  What was the result?  I think the result, the death of Mr. Kevin O'Higgins, is possibly what the present Minister is afraid of.  If that is the case, let him get out and get somebody more strong-minded, who is not afraid.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1467" />
    <Speaker pid="JanePower" hpid="Mrs. Wyse Power Mrs. Wyse Power">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Wyse Power</NameTxt>
      <P>I am not going to vote for this amendment, but I am going to protest against the pointing out in this House of anybody who is under discussion and who has not been tried on the point as the head of a criminal organisation. I think it is most undesirable. There was publicity in the morning papers.  The man is shown by a most responsible man&mdash;the Minister&mdash;to be the head of a criminal organisation.  I think the very fact of his being held out by such an important man as the Minister would prejudice the minds of a jury when he comes to be tried.  I protest against those statements, and that is all I can do.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMilroy" hpid="Mr. Milroy Mr. Milroy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Milroy</NameTxt>
      <P>I have not risen to defend the Minister.  I think he is quite competent to do that himself. I simply rise to express my appreciation of the fact that the members of the Fianna Fáil Party should at last be the champions and defenders of the dignity, good conduct and prestige of this Assembly.  Some of us at one time believed they entered this Chamber as the advance guard of the destroyers of this Chamber. It must be pleasing to all who stand for the State and its institutions and all who have succeeded in preventing the efforts of that Party for which Senator Connolly and Senator Robinson spoke to know that they have at last discovered that this Chamber, this Assembly, does stand for something which should be defended, and that its authority or dignity should not be lightly flaunted.  I could not help thinking, while Senator Connolly was speaking, of a phrase from, I think, Shakespeare's Hamlet: &ldquo;The lady doth protest too much, methinks.&rdquo;  Senator Connolly would have us believe that what he said yesterday no possible exception could be taken to, that he spoke with an innocence that was absolutely disarming, that no single word that escaped from his lips could, in any way, by any stretch of imagination&mdash;Ministerial or otherwise&mdash;in the slightest degree be resented.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1468" />
    <Speaker pid="JosephConnolly" hpid="Mr. Connolly Mr. Connolly">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Connolly</NameTxt>
      <P>Could the Senator quote any statement which I made yesterday that could otherwise be interpreted?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Cathaoirleach Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>The Senator is entitled to interpret you.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMilroy" hpid="Mr. Milroy Mr. Milroy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Milroy</NameTxt>
      <P>What are the facts? I admit fully Senator Connolly's capacity to present a case in that disarming fashion, but it is not the manner of presenting the case; it is the essence of the case he made which calls for consideration.  He makes a statement which he informs us was handed to him by a certain Deputy from the other House.  He has seemed to assume we should take it for granted that the accuracy of that Deputy is beyond all question.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JosephConnolly" hpid="Mr. Connolly Mr. Connolly">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Connolly</NameTxt>
      <P>I qualified it by stating that all I wanted was an investigation and that it was possibly not true.  I think the Seanad will bear me out in that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Cathaoirleach Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I think that is quite clear.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMilroy" hpid="Mr. Milroy Mr. Milroy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Milroy</NameTxt>
      <P>I think the full nature of Senator Connolly's comments is fully within the recollection of the Seanad, at least, it is fully within mine.  This statement was put forward, and one would infer from it that the person in question was a harmless, innocent, ordinary law-abiding citizen who had been subjected to unprovoked, wanton and brutal assaults.  This was given over the name of Deputy de Valera, and because Deputy de Valera sponsors, that statement the Minister for Justice must forthwith empanel a tribunal to investigate these statements. Are those adequate grounds for such a demand?  If the circumstances be so evidently capable of substantiation, is it unreasonable to ask that the person aggrieved should take it to the courts of the country? I want to say this in reference to the statement of Senator Robinson in that connection, that it is a very curious suggestion to make&mdash;to paraphrase a similar statement made in the other House&mdash;&ldquo;go to law with <Col N="1469" /> the devil and hold the court in hell.&rdquo; That was the effect of it.  That has been the attitude, and is to-day expressed as the attitude, of that party, that these courts set up under the authority of this Oireachtas are so biased, so partial, and so prejudiced that the average citizen cannot get justice in them.  I say when a person comes forward to make such a claim, and counters the claim with that qualification against the courts of this country, it at once rules the case he is making out of court.  Will they get up and say definitely and frankly that they believe that the judgments of the judges in these courts are biased, partial and unfair?  Will they produce a single judgment on which they can base that opinion?  They do not deserve the sympathy or support of any impartial citizen when they couch their plea in such a way.</P>
      <P>There is one other matter that I want to refer to.  I think it is sufficiently important to have it referred to in order that we may extract from the Senator who made use of the phrase exactly what he meant.  He said the late Minister for Justice tried to bring into the Civic Guards an element of discipline and he asked what was the result. Then he referred to the death of the late Minister for Justice.  Are we to infer from that that he meant that it was the resentment of what he calls gun-bullies or bullies in the force that was responsible?  Let him state it frankly and not by innuendo.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeamusRobinson" hpid="Mr. Robinson Mr. Robinson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Robinson</NameTxt>
      <P>Frankly, and without any innuendo, I certainly believe that it was his own people who did him in.  There is no proof that it was anybody else.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Cathaoirleach Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>We are not discussing the death of Mr. O'Higgins.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMilroy" hpid="Mr. Milroy Mr. Milroy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Milroy</NameTxt>
      <P>I say, sir, it is better that that should be stated frankly and not by insinuation.  There is no one who believes in the credit of this State and in the stability of its institutions who gives the slightest credence to that slander on the force <Col N="1470" /> over which the Minister for Justice presides.  I think it is appalling that in this Oireachtas which controls the institutions of this State, such a slander should be levelled against one of the forces which has at the moment, in conditions of peace, the major responsibility for maintaining these institutions.  It was that veiled institution that brought me to my feet.  It was mainly to protest against this pretence of indignation at the Minister's conduct of his Department, as voiced by those who took up that attitude and expressed it in those terms against this force, which has a very grave and serious responsibility in maintaining law and order and the stability of this State, that I rose.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOFarrell" hpid="Mr. O'Farrell Mr. O'Farrell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Farrell</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not intend to vote on this motion.  I think that Senator Connolly, having raised it, might not feel it is necessary to put it to a vote.  But I think it is necessary that I should express the views of myself, and, I think, of those with whom I act generally, in regard to the subject under discussion. The attitude of Senator Connolly yesterday in reading the statement that he read, and asking that investigations should take place, was, of course, the normal procedure in most parliaments.  I think he made it plain that these were allegations that he accepted no responsibility for, and he pressed for an investigation, which was a very proper thing to do.  Of course the statement submitted to him was taken by a responsible member of the Oireachtas from the man who had complained.  The reply of the Minister was, in my opinion at all events, very disturbing, and I think a very regrettable type of statement to make.  I do not agree with Senator Robinson at all that the present Government has no moral sanction in the country.  Any Government elected by a majority of the people of this country has a moral sanction, although we may not agree with their policy at all. The very foundations of democracy are threatened if you say that the <Col N="1471" /> Government elected by a majority has no moral sanction.  Therefore, I certainly part company with Senator Robinson and with Senator Connolly, if he takes up a similar stand.  I do say that the moral authority of the Government and of the whole State is threatened and confidence is destroyed generally if the Minister is quite serious in the attitude he took up in reply to the Senator, because he rather indicated &mdash;if he had time to consider it he might not have put it so strongly&mdash; that it was the intention of the Civic Guards to continue to search and research, to arrest and rearrest and do many other things calculated to make a particular man's life a hell upon earth because he was suspected of belonging to a criminal organisation.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>That is a terribly serious suggestion. A man might be a human fiend, but I do not think that would be a justification for that sort of punishment.  If he is a dangerous man to have abroad, I think there are sufficient laws to keep him under lock and key, and if there is enough evidence against him our laws are certainly sufficiently strong to punish him.  I know that at times it is very hard, though there is a moral certainty that a man is a criminal, to mobilise evidence sufficient to convict him, and that a certain amount of surveillance might be necessary to prevent him committing crime.  But I think the Minister should have been a little more guarded in the statements he made, because these statements will be taken as a sort of cue by the Civic Guards and may lead them into irregularities.  After all, if there were a few irregularities in the Civic Guards, that is not uncommon in a police force and does not show that the force is bad. Nobody will say that the London police force as a whole was inefficient or corrupt, and yet there were quite a number of irregularities recently in Scotland Yard, and the Government has had the courage and the sense of responsibility to <Col N="1472" /> take up these cases and deal very severely with them.  If our Government found it necessary to do the same thing here I do not think it would at all destroy the feeling of confidence of the people in the Civic Guards.  In Dublin and throughout the country I have found the Guards a very efficient and a very courteous body of men, and I say that no law-abiding citizen has anything to fear from them.  But even in the case of those who break the law, one would like to think that they were treated according to the ordinary procedure in connection with crime and that the methods of the jungle would not be reverted to.</P>
    <P>It was really to express my very great regret at the speech that the Minister made that I rose, and while I do not propose voting on this amendment.  I do think that the protest was justified, and I hope that the Minister will be able to assure the House that some of the statements that he made yesterday did not correctly express his views, or that the interpretation we took from them is not a correct one; that he will at least tell the House that there is no justification for the amount of concern which his speech has caused in the mind of, I think, most Senators.</P>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasEsmondeBart" hpid="Sir Thomas Esmonde Sir Thomas Esmonde">
      <NameTxt>Sir Thomas Esmonde</NameTxt>
      <P>This debate has taken an unexpectedly serious turn, and I think it is just as well that we should express our views on the particular facet of the situation, which I consider serious. I should not be a member of this Seanad, I should not be a member of any legislature in this country, if I did not believe in constitutional democratic government.  I have spent all my life in trying to obtain an Irish Parliament.  When I was nominated by the first Irish Government for 12 years.  I felt it to be an honour, and I have endeavoured, according to my abilities and according to my honest convictions, to support that Government as I would support any constitutionally-elected democratic Government in this <Col N="1473" /> country.  I know nothing whatever about the details of this particular case.  I did not know that this gentleman was under trial.  If that is so, his case should not have been mentioned in the course of public debates.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JosephConnolly" hpid="Mr. Connolly Mr. Connolly">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Connolly</NameTxt>
      <P>He is not under trial.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasEsmondeBart" hpid="Sir Thomas Esmonde Sir Thomas Esmonde">
      <NameTxt>Sir Thomas Esmonde</NameTxt>
      <P>His case would be <i>sub judice,</i> and the ordinary practice in constitutional countries is to regard a case <i>sub judice</i> as a case on which no public man and no newspaper should express an opinion.  I do not know whether this gentleman is under trial or not, but I say that if he is under trial, or threatened with trial, his case should be regarded as <i>sub judice.</i>  On the other hand, I recognise the importance of constitutional government. This discussion takes place on the Appropriation Bill, which, in my experience, is the most important measure presented annually to a parliament.  If the Appropriation Bill is defeated, it must mean the resignation of the Government.  I am, therefore, in this dilemma: I cannot vote for the upset of this Government unless I know what Government is going to succeed it. I recognise the extraordinarily responsible position at the present time of the Minister for Justice. He is responsible for the due, impartial and fair administration of the civil law.  I am not anxious to place any difficulties in the way of the Minister for Justice of any Government, but I suggest to the Minister, if there is any cause in his mind for an inquiry into the circumstances of this case, that he would be well advised to further it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I do not mean in the smallest degree to pay anything but a compliment to our Civic Guard.  As far as I have met them, I think our Civic Guard is a most admirable organisation and that it can compare favourably with any police force in the world.  I would not like to cast any <Col N="1474" /> slur on that organisation, and I think that this is a matter for the Minister's own discretion.  If he thinks that there are any circumstances in connection with this case, or with any other case, that require to be investigated, he could deal with the matter by a departmental investigation.  If he does not think that there is any cause for such a proceeding on his part, from my knowledge of the Minister, I would be largely guided by his experience.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MauriceMoore" hpid="Colonel Moore Colonel Moore">
      <NameTxt>Colonel Moore</NameTxt>
      <P>As far as I can see, the Minister is out for a scrap. He is going in the right direction to produce murder and outrage throughout the country.  Apparently, he sanctifies the actions of the C.I.D. in many cases where they have been proved before a court to be wrong, as in the case of O'Sullivan in Cork, where he was tried by a judge and condemned.  The Minister, instead of admitting the position, stated in this House that that case was merely a quarrel between two men, that only two men were concerned, and that one got the worst of it, whereas, three men were tried and two of them were condemned by the judge.  He overlooked that, and not only that, but he sent that same man up to County Clare, where there were more beatings, and one man was blown up.  The Minister then said that he was a splendid type of Irishman, and so on, having done all these things.  I fear that serious trouble will arise on account of this kind of behaviour and on account of the backing-up by the Minister of certain acts which I know to have been done.  If that is continued I do not know what will be the result, except a scrap between the two forces.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JosephConnolly" hpid="Mr. Connolly Mr. Connolly">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Connolly</NameTxt>
      <P>Have I the right to reply?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Cathaoirleach Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes, Senator.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesFitzgeraldKenne" hpid="Minister for Justice (Mr. Fitzgerald-Kenney) James Fitzgerald-Kenney">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Justice (Mr. Fitzgerald-Kenney)</NameTxt>
      <P>I have got to speak yet.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1475" />
    <Speaker pid="JosephConnolly" hpid="Mr. Connolly Mr. Connolly">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Connolly</NameTxt>
      <P>I will be all the more pleased if I can have a word after the Minister.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesFitzgeraldKenne" hpid="Mr. Fitzgerald-Kenney Mr. Fitzgerald-Kenney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Fitzgerald-Kenney</NameTxt>
      <P>Even that threat does not perturb me very much.  There was one thing which Senator Connolly said that I must immediately differ from.  He said yesterday that I did not obey your rulings in any way.  That is not an accurate statement.  I obeyed, according to my lights at any rate, every ruling you gave.  The Senator protested that the whole of my speech dealt with him and him only. He seemed to forget that there were other speakers.  He seemed to forget that an attack was made on the Guards generally in County Clare, and that I dealt, not with specific instances, but with the general charges that were made.  I pointed out that the Guards in Clare had the approbation of persons who really counted in Clare, and I think that was perfectly germane to the issue. There was not one question, and one question only raised, but other questions were raised by Senator Comyn. Surely it was not only justifiable, but right and proper, for me to deal with the questions raised by every Senator?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>As far as the particular charges in that statement are concerned, I dealt with them yesterday in this fashion: I said that those charges were absolutely new to me, that yesterday was the first time I had heard them.  I said that I could neither know as to whether they were true or whether they were false, because I had no information, but I did say that, from previous investigation which I had made into other charges I came to the conclusion, <i>prima facie</i>, that there was not very much in it.  I said also that it was the duty of the Civic Guard to prevent crime being hatched out.  It must be borne in mind that there is a small body of men in this country who are trying to upset ordered Government by force.  No one denies that.  Everybody knows that they exist.  Senator Robinson, in the most significant part of his speech, stated that this Government had only a sort <Col N="1476" /> of semi-moral force behind it.  Still it has got the moral force which springs from this, that if this Government goes down chaos must ensue, that if this form of government goes down we will have nothing but chaos.  There are men who are anxious to bring down this form of government; there are men anxious to bring about a condition of complete chaos in this country. We know that although the Guards have recovered a great number of dumps of arms there are still arms in dumps.  Everyone knows that. How is that problem to be dealt with?  There is only one way, and that is to prevent crime being organised, planned and executed. That is just as much, if not more, the duty of the Guards, as to detect crime that has actually been committed. It is better to forestall crime and prevent crime than to punish it; it is better to forestall murder than to punish murder.  What every civilised country wants is peace and quietness. There are persons who are determined that peace and quietness shall not ensue here.  Senator Moore always refers back to certain things. He seems to forget that there was a complete amnesty in this country; he seems to forget that the prison doors were flung open, and that every prisoner who could be called a political prisoner was released; he seems to forget that afterwards Guards were murdered on many occasions.  He seems to forget that the giving of a complete amnesty did not bring about complete peace, that violent methods were resorted to against the Guards, and against members of the Executive after that. Now, Senator Robinson said a very terrible thing, and Senator Milroy has already dealt with the question. He said that the Civic Guards had murdered the late Mr. O'Higgins.  A similar charge to that, not perhaps so clearly expressed&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    <Speaker pid="SeamusRobinson" hpid="Mr. Robinson Mr. Robinson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Robinson</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not think I said the Civic Guards did it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesFitzgeraldKenne" hpid="Mr. Fitzgerald-Kenney Mr. Fitzgerald-Kenney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Fitzgerald-Kenney</NameTxt>
      <P>Who did it?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeamusRobinson" hpid="Mr. Robinson Mr. Robinson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Robinson</NameTxt>
      <P>I simply said your <Col N="1477" /> own agents.  I firmly believe it was done by members of his own organisation. I did not necessarily say the Civic Guards.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesFitzgeraldKenne" hpid="Mr. Fitzgerald-Kenney Mr. Fitzgerald-Kenney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Fitzgerald-Kenney</NameTxt>
      <P>Let us be perfectly clear.  I think the Senator was kind enough to say that the Civic Guards were alleged to be out of hand because I was afraid of being murdered by the Civic Guards. I think that is what the Senator said, plainly and bluntly.  What does that mean, except that the very brilliant man whose position I now occupy was murdered by the Civic Guards?  It can mean that and nothing else.  If he wishes to say that that is not what he meant I would be very pleased to hear it.  If he has been mistaken and wishes to withdraw it nobody would hear that withdrawal with greater pleasure than I would.  That statement shows a terrible spirit against the Civic Guards.  That is what I am protesting against.  It shows a terrible feeling against the Civic Guards, that charges like this, without a single scintilla of evidence, should be levelled against them, charges which, in my humble judgement at any rate, are discreditable to any Senator who makes them.  Let us take the general position as a whole. The Guards have been given a very difficult task to perform.  They have to prevent crime.  There is not a very large number of men who wish to resort to armed violence in this country at the moment.  They are a comparatively small number.  Are we to be under the rule of men who wish to go out with the bomb and the gun?  Will any member of any Party in the Seanad say that we should be under the rule of a small minority who wish to indulge in methods of violence?  The Guards have a difficult task to do. They have to prevent these deeds of violence directed towards the upsetting of the existing institutions of the State. They have to prevent these deeds of violence being committed.  Now, surely that should have the honest, genuine support of everybody who pays not lip-worship to order, not <Col N="1478" /> lip-worship merely to peace in this country, but who really, sincerely and honestly desires peace in this country?  Surely every single person animated by feelings like these should fling himself behind the Guards in their efforts to prevent crime being committed, instead of being carping critics looking for every single opportunity for finding fault with the Guards, and having one single instance pulled up for the fiftieth time in this House because it is thought to be discreditable to the Guards?  Why will not every member of this House, every member of the Oireachtas, and everybody who wishes for real, true peace in this country not fling themselves wholeheartedly behind the Guards?  Why will they not go further?  Why will they not wholeheartedly denounce the persons who are endeavouring to stir up disorder in this country? Why will they not wholeheartedly denounce everybody who commits crime, and who is endeavouring to hatch crime?  Why will they not take up that attitude?  If that attitude were taken up by everybody I believe it would make greatly for peace.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MauriceMoore" hpid="Colonel Moore Colonel Moore">
      <NameTxt>Colonel Moore</NameTxt>
      <P>If the Minister would denounce crime amongst the C.I.D.  I, for one, would willingly denounce it on the other side.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesFitzgeraldKenne" hpid="Mr. Fitzgerald-Kenney Mr. Fitzgerald-Kenney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Fitzgerald-Kenney</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator Colonel Moore gives a conditional denunciation of crime, but I give a denunciation of crime wherever it is found.  I deny that there is crime amongst the C.I.D.  It is very upsetting and, to me really astonishing, to hear from the Senator this conditional denunciation of crime&mdash; that if somebody else denounces one class of crime he will denounce another class of crime.  In my judgment it is the duty of every Senator to denounce every class of crime.  It is the duty of every law-abiding person in the country wholeheartedly and, without any fear, to denounce crime wherever it is found.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JosephConnolly" hpid="Mr. Connolly Mr. Connolly">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Connolly</NameTxt>
      <P>I am not going to say very much on this.  I think <Col N="1479" /> there is very little for me to say. I think that the Minister has said all that he could say, but to an intelligent Seanad, I think the Minister stands condemned.  The Minister talked about crime.  I for one repudiate crime.  I denounce crime in any form, whether it is by the C.I.D., by the Guards, or by any other person, and I think that is the general feeling amongst all decent people.  The Minister has side-tracked his reply with a sort of an appealing note in his voice.  That kind of claptrap was only equalled by his flamboyant aggressiveness here yesterday. I do not think that there is any more to be said.  The Minister stated that he obeyed the ruling of the Cathaoirleach yesterday.  I am not going to labour that point, but <Col N="1480" /> the Cathaoirleach knows whether he obeyed his ruling or not.  I also know, and I think I know, a Chathaoirligh, what you know.  The one outstanding feature in the debate yesterday was not my speech.  It was not the remarks that I made.  It was the statement which I read.  I would like to correct Senator Milroy by saying that I did not make the statement.  I read it, and I want to differentiate between the two.  The Minister, in his so-called reply, said that whether he would investigate that or not was a matter for him.  He has not even yet, at this eleventh and a half hour, promised that he will investigate it. From what I know of the Minister, he will not investigate it.  That is a matter between himself and his conscience, if he has got any.</P>
      <P>Question put.</P>
      <P Just="Center">The Committee divided; Tá, 8; Níl, 28.</P>
      <P Just="Center">Tá</P>
    </Speaker>
    <table pgwide="1">
      <tgroup cols="2">
        <colspec colname="1" colnum="1" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <colspec colname="2" colnum="2" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry rowsep="1">Caitlín Bean Uí Chléirigh.<br />Joseph Connolly.<br />J.C. Dowdall.<br />Michael Duffy.</entry>
            <entry rowsep="1">Thomas Linehan.<br />Seán E. MacEllin.<br />Colonel Moore.<br />Séumas Robinson.</entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
    <P Just="Center">Níl</P>
    <table pgwide="1">
      <tgroup cols="2">
        <colspec colname="1" colnum="1" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <colspec colname="2" colnum="2" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry rowsep="1">Sir Edward Coey Bigger.<br />Samuel L. Brown, K.C.<br />Alfred Byrne.<br />Mrs. Costello.<br />John C. Counihan.<br />The Countess of Desart.<br />James G. Douglas.<br />Sir Thomas Grattan Esmonde.<br />Michael Fanning.<br />Thomas Foran.<br />The Earl of Granard.<br />Henry S. Guinness.<br />Thomas Johnson.<br />Sir John Keane.</entry>
            <entry rowsep="1">Patrick W. Kenny.<br />Francis MacGuinness.<br />James MacKean.<br />John MacLoughlin.<br />Seán Milroy.<br />James Moran.<br />Joseph O'Connor.<br />John T. O'Farrell.<br />M.F. O'Hanlon.<br />Bernard O'Rourke.<br />James J. Parkinson.<br />Siobhán Bean an Phaoraigh.<br />Thomas Toal.<br />Richard Wilson.</entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
    <P>Mr. Linehan, when his name was called, replied: &ldquo;I will not vote.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Cathaoirleach Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>The Senator, according to our Standing Orders, must vote, as he is in the Chamber.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasLinehan" hpid="Mr. Linehan Mr. Linehan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Linehan</NameTxt>
      <P>Then I vote &ldquo;Tá.&rdquo;</P>
      <P>Question declared lost.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasLinehan" hpid="Mr. Linehan Mr. Linehan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Linehan</NameTxt>
      <P>I move:&mdash;</P>
      <P>Schedule (B), Part III., Vote No. 8.  To delete in column 2 the words &ldquo;and to make repayment to the British Government in respect of local loans outstanding&rdquo; and to delete in column 3 the figures &ldquo;935,000&rdquo; and to substitute therefor the figures &ldquo;335,000.&rdquo;</P>
      <P>In sub-section (1) of Section 27 of the Government of Ireland Act, 1920, it is laid down:</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The power of collecting and enforcing the payment of sums due on account of loans made before the appointed day to authorities <Col N="1481" /> and persons in Southern Ireland or Northern Ireland out of the Local Loans Fund, the Development Fund and the Road Improvement Fund or other public fund, shall be transferred to the Governments of Southern Ireland and Northern Ireland respectively, and the amounts so collected by them shall be paid into their respective Exchequers.</P>
    <P>That section is still the law of the land here.  I doubt if it is legal for us to pay this money which is mentioned. The Minister made the point that the appointed day for bringing this section into force was never fixed, and he also said that even if it had been fixed it would not apply to the Free State.  In the Government of Ireland Act, 1920, the appointed day is very clearly fixed. In fact, it is more clearly stated in that Act than I have seen it in any other Act.  Not alone is the date mentioned, but the day of the week is also mentioned.  I will quote the section which refers to the commencement of the Act and the appointed day.  The following is sub-section (1) of Section 73:</P>
    <P>This Act shall, except as expressly provided, come into operation on the appointed day, and the appointed day for the purposes of this Act shall be the first Tuesday in the eighth month after the month in which this Act is passed, or such other day not more than seven months earlier or later, as may be fixed by Order of His Majesty in Council.</P>
    <P>I hold that in the absence of any Order being made extending or retarding the date that the first Tuesday in the eighth month after the passing of the Act is the appointed day for the purpose of the Act.  I wish also to point out that the making of the Order is optional.  It says, &ldquo;or such other day not more than seven months earlier or later, as may be fixed by Order of His Majesty in Council.&rdquo; There is nothing in the section to show that such an Order shall be made, and it is only natural to conclude that in the absence of any <Col N="1482" /> such Order the date originally fixed in the section should be the date on which the Act would come into force.  I do not quite understand the Minister's point when he states that even though this Act came into force on the appointed day, as fixed in Section 27, that it would not refer to the Free State.  Perhaps the Minister might plead that Southern Ireland and the Irish Free State are different territories.  At any rate, I think the point involved in this Vote greatly affects the financial capacity of this country, and as there is such a considerable divergence of opinion amongst even members of the legal profession as to the legality of payments such as this and the land annuities it would be very desirable that the matter should be cleared up by appointing a Special Committee of both Houses to go into the question.  That suggestion was made in the Seanad a few years ago and it was defeated only by the casting vote of the then Chairman.  I think I have said sufficient to enable the House to see that there is a very important point involved in this matter.</P>
    <Speaker pid="HenryGuinness2" hpid="Mr. Guinness Mr. Guinness">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Guinness</NameTxt>
      <P>I should like to ask a question in regard to this. The Local Loans Fund, I understand, represents money advanced by the British Exchequer for certain works undertaken and, therefore, became a debt in so far as it was money due from one person to another or from an individual to the State, and had nothing to say to the general debt of the country. If that is so, I take it that this motion is a repudiation of an honest and straightforward debt.  I should like to get confirmation of that from the Minister.  If that is so, I cannot call it anything else than a dishonest suggestion that a true debt should be repudiated.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasEsmondeBart" hpid="Sir Thomas Esmonde Sir Thomas Esmonde">
      <NameTxt>Sir Thomas Esmonde</NameTxt>
      <P>This Local Loans Fund really represents loans from the Board of Works to farmers for the building of houses and hay-barns and we cannot, therefore, support a motion of that kind.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1483" />
    <Speaker pid="MauriceMoore" hpid="Colonel Moore Colonel Moore">
      <NameTxt>Colonel Moore</NameTxt>
      <P>It is really not worth while going into this again, because the matter is now before the country and the results will be seen one of these days.  I think if Senator Guinness had studied the question he would not have made the remark he made.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="HenryGuinness2" hpid="Mr. Guinness Mr. Guinness">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Guinness</NameTxt>
      <P>I was only asking a question.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MauriceMoore" hpid="Colonel Moore Colonel Moore">
      <NameTxt>Colonel Moore</NameTxt>
      <P>I am not saying anything against the Senator.  The argument for this, to put it shortly, is that it was a part of the National Debt which was wiped out when Article V. of the Treaty was wiped out.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ErnestBlythe" hpid="Mr. Blythe Mr. Blythe">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Blythe</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not want to speak at any great length about this, because I think it is largely a waste of time.  The arguments advanced by Senator Linehan strike me as being quite absurd and indicate that he himself has given no attention to the matter.  He suggests that Clause 27 of the Government of Ireland Act, 1920, came into effect on the 2nd August, 1921, in the absence of an Order in Council fixing a later date.  He suggests that there was no such Order in Council.  There was an Order in Council.  There was first the Order in Council on 24th March, 1921, bringing into operation certain provisions of the 1920 Act, except provisions relative to financial matters. There were, with certain exceptions. Then later on there was an Order in Council on 25th July, 1921.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelComynKC" hpid="Mr. Comyn Mr. Comyn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Comyn</NameTxt>
      <P>Does the Minister suggest that that Order is valid?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ErnestBlythe" hpid="Mr. Blythe Mr. Blythe">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Blythe</NameTxt>
      <P>I am not going to argue the matter any more than to answer the one point that Senator Linehan put up.  There was an Order then postponing the appointed day. So that if it can be said that that particular provision of the Government of Ireland Act never came into operation it would have come into operation on 2nd March, 1922, but, of course, the Treaty had intervened, which really, so far as the area of the Free State is concerned, swept <Col N="1484" /> away the Government of Ireland Act, except in so far as the Government of Ireland Act was preserved in the Treaty.  It is my opinion, and it is the opinion of most of the followers of Senator Moore, that this is just a debt honestly due and that it was advanced by the British Government. I am not going to argue the question of the National Debt, but I do not think that either this or the land annuities depend on the question of the National Debt, although that has been brought in.  It was money advanced by the British Government to individuals or corporations, and it is due from these individuals or corporations to the lenders, and no persons can have a right to get payment of that money unless they have the right transferred to them by the lenders.  The right was not transferred to this Government by the lenders, and we have no right to it.  The people who borrowed the money have no right to escape repayment.</P>
      <P>This annuity of £600,000 a year represents an arrangement that we came to with the British Government whereby, instead of collecting the amounts year by year as they fell due and paying them over to the British Government as long as any of the money remained due, we pay this £600,000 a year for twenty years, but we will continue to collect the annuities ourselves as long as any of the money remains due.  The argument used against the payment of these annuities to the British Government is somewhat the same as the argument against the payment of the land annuities.  Ninety-nine per cent. of those who use that argument use it absolutely dishonestly and without any belief in it.  They use it merely for political reasons and to cover their desertion from the old ship &ldquo;Republic.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasLinehan" hpid="Mr. Linehan Mr. Linehan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Linehan</NameTxt>
      <P>As regards the Minister's point about paying the moneys borrowed to the lenders, I entirely agree with him, but I should like to point out that in the Articles of Agreement for a Treaty, the 1920 Act was the basis for that Treaty.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1485" />
    <Speaker pid="ErnestBlythe" hpid="Mr. Blythe Mr. Blythe">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Blythe</NameTxt>
      <P>Nonsense.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasLinehan" hpid="Mr. Linehan Mr. Linehan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Linehan</NameTxt>
      <P>Because if you read through these 18 Articles which formed the Articles of Agreement you will find that in several of them the 1920 Act was brought in so that it was clearly before the minds of the negotiators of the Treaty that the 1920 Act would be the basis upon which they would go; and the Treaty itself is really an amendment of the 1920 Act.  We find in this 1920 Act a certain section which tells us to collect these local loans and to pay them into our own Exchequer.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ErnestBlythe" hpid="Mr. Blythe Mr. Blythe">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Blythe</NameTxt>
      <P>Into what Exchequer? <Col N="1486" /> Not into the Exchequer of the Free State?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelComynKC" hpid="Mr. Comyn Mr. Comyn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Comyn</NameTxt>
      <P>The Exchequer of Southern Ireland.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ErnestBlythe" hpid="Mr. Blythe Mr. Blythe">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Blythe</NameTxt>
      <P>It never came into being.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelComynKC" hpid="Mr. Comyn Mr. Comyn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Comyn</NameTxt>
      <P>The Twenty-six Counties?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ErnestBlythe" hpid="Mr. Blythe Mr. Blythe">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Blythe</NameTxt>
      <P>That is a different thing entirely.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasLinehan" hpid="Mr. Linehan Mr. Linehan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Linehan</NameTxt>
      <P>I think as long as the section is there and until some legal decision is given, this matter will come up frequently for discussion both in the Seanad and in the country.</P>
      <P>Question put.</P>
      <P Just="Center">The Committee divided: Tá, 9; Níl, 30.</P>
      <P Just="Center">Tá</P>
    </Speaker>
    <table pgwide="1">
      <tgroup cols="2">
        <colspec colname="1" colnum="1" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <colspec colname="2" colnum="2" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry rowsep="1">Caitlín Bean Uí Chléirigh.<br />Michael Comyn, K.C.<br />Joseph Connolly.<br />J. C. Dowdall.<br />Thomas Linehan.</entry>
            <entry rowsep="1">Seán E. MacEllin.<br />Colonel Moore.<br />Joseph O'Doherty.<br />Séumas Robinson.<br /></entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
    <P Just="Center">Níl</P>
    <table pgwide="1">
      <tgroup cols="2">
        <colspec colname="1" colnum="1" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <colspec colname="2" colnum="2" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry rowsep="1">Sir Edward Coey Bigger.<br />Samuel L. Brown, K.C.<br />Alfred Byrne.<br />Mrs. Costello.<br />John C. Counihan.<br />William Cummins.<br />The Countess of Desart.<br />James G. Douglas.<br />Michael Duffy.<br />Sir Thomas Grattan Esmonde.<br />Thomas Farren.<br />The Earl of Granard.<br />Henry S. Guinness.<br />P.J. Hooper.<br />Thomas Johnson.</entry>
            <entry rowsep="1">Sir John Keane.<br />Cornelius Kennedy.<br />Patrick W. Kenny.<br />Francis MacGuinness.<br />James MacKean.<br />John MacLaughlin.<br />Seán Milroy.<br />James Moran.<br />Joseph O'Connor.<br />M. F. O'Hanlon.<br />Bernard O'Rourke.<br />James J. Parkinson.<br />Siobhán Bean an Phaoraigh.<br />Thomas Toal.<br />Richard Wilson.</entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
    <P>Question declared lost.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JohnKeaneBart" hpid="Sir John Keane Sir John Keane">
      <NameTxt>Sir John Keane</NameTxt>
      <P>I move as a recommendation:&mdash;</P>
      <P>Schedule (B), Part 3.  To delete Vote 11.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I only put this down as a matter of form in order to correct an error which crept into the very few words that formed my statement yesterday in regard to the closing of the Phoenix Park.  I was wrong when I stated that in connection with the closing for a limited period of three days or less the order made by the Commissioners should be laid upon the Tables of both Houses of the Oireachtas.  An order to close for three days or less can be made by the Commissioners without laying the order on the Table.  But I still say they have no power to close the whole Park as they did on the occasion of the motor races.  It is suggested that because a small space about twice the size of this Chamber was left unenclosed between the gates and the turnstile the whole Park was not closed.  I do not know whether anybody would seriously stand over that point of view.  I hope the Government, on any similar occasion again will move <Col N="1487" /> carefully, because people feel very strongly about this and think that it might lead to a loss, as it might be challenged in the courts.</P>
    <Speaker pid="ErnestBlythe" hpid="Mr. Blythe Mr. Blythe">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Blythe</NameTxt>
      <P>Though I have not seen any legal opinion myself, I know that legal opinion was obtained, and that the Commissioners of Public Works were satisfied that they were acting entirely within the statute.  With reference to objections to letting the Park for motor races, it may be that there is considerable opinion existing against it, but I have not heard of it, and no such opinion has taken any of the ordinary means of manifesting itself.  It was very well known for a considerable period that the Phoenix Park was going to be let for these motor races, and so far as I know, no protests were sent in.  On the general question I recognise fully that the Park should not be closed to the public for very many days in the year, no matter what occasion for closing it might arise.  It has never been contemplated that it shall be closed to the public more than two or three days in the year.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JanePower" hpid="Mrs. Wyse Power Mrs. Wyse Power">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Wyse Power</NameTxt>
      <P>Could we know from the Minister how much was paid for the use of the Park on those days?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ErnestBlythe" hpid="Mr. Blythe Mr. Blythe">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Blythe</NameTxt>
      <P>Nothing.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnKeaneBart" hpid="Sir John Keane Sir John Keane">
      <NameTxt>Sir John Keane</NameTxt>
      <P>I ask leave to withdraw my recommendation.</P>
      <P>Recommendation, by leave, withdrawn.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MauriceMoore" hpid="Colonel Moore Colonel Moore">
      <NameTxt>Colonel Moore</NameTxt>
      <P>My recommendation is: In Schedule (B), Part III., Vote No. 16.  To delete in column 3 the figures &ldquo;1,777,400&rdquo; and to substitute therefor the figures &ldquo;677,400.&rdquo; That is really reducing it by the amount paid in pensions to the R.I.C., new and old.  I think I may as well say at the start that it would be more decent for the Minister for Finance not to go about stating that I was talking lies about this matter. The Minister for Finance and the Minister for Agriculture have gone publicly about making that statement and the Minister for Finance <Col N="1488" /> now repeats it in the House, which I think adds to the offence especially as we know that what I have stated is quite correct.  We have got the opinion from seven or eight very well-known K.C.'s who have maintained on this matter the same attitude as I have.  It is absurd for the Minister to go on using bad language about me.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Yesterday the Minister for Finance made a statement that I was talking nonsense when I said that the police pensions were part of the national debt.  I am very glad that the Minister for Agriculture is here because I can read one or two quotations which will show him and the House how very much he and the Minister for Finance disagree on this matter. On one occasion I asked a question here whether the public debt was the same as the national debt.  The Minister for Finance made a considered statement then because he had been warned beforehand.  He said they were two entirely different things and that nobody could consider them to be the same.  He said that the public debt was smaller than the national debt.  We were satisfied with that.  I did not quarrel with it.  But the other day the Minister for Agriculture when making an announcement in the Dáil on that subject made a very different statement which I would like to read to the House.  Here is what he said: &ldquo;With regard to one point Deputy de Valera can be quite easy in his mind.  It has never been denied that the public debt and the national debt are the same thing.  Everybody knows that.&rdquo;  But the Minister for Finance does not know it.  Then the Minister for Agriculture went on and said:&mdash;&ldquo;They are the same terms.  The Deputy opposite is merely pushing an open door.&rdquo;  So we have these two Ministers sitting side by side differing on this financial question and actually, I will not say calling each other liars, but disagreeing with each other.  The Minister for Agriculture then proceeded to define what, in his opinion, is the national debt of any country or the public debt of any country. He says they are the same.  He said: <Col N="1489" />&ldquo;This definition of a public debt can be verified by consulting authorities such as Lord Halsbury and various decided cases and various statutes.  The Deputy can make his mind easy.  I can give him statute law.  The public debt is a debt due by the public taxpayer.  The public debt is a debt in respect of which the taxpayer is liable, in respect of which he has no remedy and in respect of which he has no security. That is a public debt.&rdquo;  So that is the definition of the Minister for Agriculture.  The Minister for Finance made a statement yesterday and he said that the pensions of the police could not possibly be part of the national debt and that it would be ridiculous to say that they were part of the national debt.  They exactly fit the very words that the Minister for Agriculture used, that he considered the public debt fits exactly the case of the police pensions.  Let us see. The public debt is defined as a debt in respect of which the taxpayer is liable.  The taxpayer has to pay over.  There is no question about it; in respect of it he has no remedy; in respect of it he has no security, not a bit of security.  He may have land under the land purchase annuities, possibly, but not in the case of the police pensions.  He has no security for them at all.</P>
    <P>That is only one instance of the diversity of opinion between our Ministers.  The Minister for Finance made a very reasonable statement yesterday, and I wish that the other Ministers would refrain from some gibes which they make from time to time.  He made quite a reasonable statement.  But I think that all these things should have been explained long ago, many years ago, instead of being kept bottled up for seven or eight years, after they were decided without anybody knowing what they are about, and with the people having no voice in the matter.  The Minister stated that on this question there were other things besides a Treaty which governed the various payments.  That I traverse altogether, and I have asked lawyers about it.  The lawyers agree with <Col N="1490" /> me.  They say it is a matter of common law that when a contract is entered into between two persons or two nations and certain financial statements are laid down that these and these alone can be gone into and followed up afterwards and that no new things can be put into them; and that these things absolutely exclude the others.  That is a matter of common law.  There is a particular law phrase which governs it.  I do not know now what that phrase is.</P>
    <P>So that the only thing we have to consider in these matters is Clause 10 of the Treaty.  Clause 5 has been wiped out.  The Minister says that Clause 5 did not deal with the pensions or compensation.  It did not deal with the pensions at all, for we are not liable for them.  It deals with compensation.  I presume it means compensation for pensions, because sometimes the two words are put together.  I maintain we are not bound to pay them.</P>
    <P>The Minister made a statement in which he quoted from a speech of the President.  I remember that speech very distinctly.  I read it once or twice.  I would be ashamed to read it in public.  The Minister read it in public and he should have been ashamed so to read it; anybody in this country ought to be ashamed to read it in public because it was a statement of utter prostration. The President said he went over to London and practically threw himself at the feet of the Ministers there.  He said: &ldquo;You may charge us whatever way you like; we cannot help ourselves.  You may bankrupt us as you like.  We have nothing to do but to obey what you say.  But please, my good masters, will you not bankrupt us altogether?  It would not pay you to bankrupt us.  We are poor people and we have not the money to pay.&rdquo;  There could be nothing more contemptible than that from the head of the Government here. I should feel ashamed to quote the President's statement if the Minister for Finance had not already done so.</P>
    <P>The Minister pointed out that if we raise any of these questions the <Col N="1491" /> whole matter of Article V. will have to come up again.  The only authority he gives is the President's statement saying that we owe Britain certain things.  That has nothing to do with the law at all. We are told that if we open up certain matters the whole Treaty will be opened up.  The Minister said that that was the basis of the whole arrangement.  He goes on a little further and he finds himself on rather soft ground.  He certainly is on soft ground, because he says that certain things have been handed over and therefore we must pay. Again he tells us that it is not really fair to go into any particular items. He says that we should not pick up things here and there that seem rather doubtful, but that we should take the whole thing altogether. The reason why we go into this matter at all is because the whole arrangement at that time, including those pensions and everything else, tends simply to bankrupt the State, and it renders grossly unfair our relations with England.</P>
    <P>This question of financial relations does not arise for the first time.  It came up already on two different occasions, and the circumstances were investigated very carefully by two Treasury Commissions, one in 1896 and another in 1912-13. All the Treasury officials were present at those Commissions.  The members of the Financial Relations Committee appointed by the British Government, of which Mr. Childers, a former Chancellor of the Exchequer, was Chairman, reported unanimously in 1896: (1) That the Act of Union imposed on Ireland a burden she could not bear; (2) that the increase of taxation laid on Ireland between 1853 and 1860 was not justified; (3) that identity of rates of taxation does not involve equality of burden, and (4) that while the actual tax revenue of Ireland is about one-eleventh of Britain, the relative taxable capacity is very much smaller, and is not estimated by any of us as exceeding one-twentieth and, some said, much less.  The Chairman of the Financial Relations <Col N="1492" /> Committee pointed out that on the revenue returns for 1893-1894 Ireland had paid £2,750,000 more than her share to England and suggested that on this account Ireland, in any separation of the Treasuries, should receive a contribution from the finances of Britain of £2,750,000 each year.</P>
    <P>Practically the same thing happened a few years afterwards, when we had the Primrose Commission. The Primrose Commission was purely a Treasury Commission; there was only one Irishman on it. That Commission reported also to the effect that Ireland had paid some £2,750,000 a year too much to England.  The argument, therefore, is that now that the Treasuries are separate England should be paying £3,000,000 a year to Ireland, or, in other words, she should take over the old age pensions and pay them. The English people themselves admit that Britain ought to pay that sum to Ireland.  That is a very clear statement.  What has happened? Twenty-six Counties of Ireland are paying £5,000,000 a year to England, and that is a sum set out in the Ultimate Financial Settlement.  How can that possibly be a reasonable adjustment of finances between the two countries?  Are we not perfectly justified in raising the whole of this question whenever we get a chance? We are really entitled to discuss this matter from every aspect.  We will not be sorry to break up the payment of £5,000,000 a year, and we can discuss the question of paying our share when England gives us the £2,750,000 a year to which we are entitled.  I am sure the Ministers read my pamphlet on this subject.  I know that the first six copies of the pamphlet were sold to Ministers. They were very careful to say nothing about that.  They were not able to contradict a word of it, and they never dared to contradict it.</P>
    <P>The Minister stated in the Dáil that the British Treasury had estimated the taxable capacity of the Free State and Britain as 1.5 in 100. I do not suppose the British Treasury erred on their own side. British taxation comes to about <Col N="1493" /> £800,000,000 a year.  I calculate that 1.5 of that would come to about £12,000,000.  Our taxation is £24,000,000, and therefore we are taxed twice as high as England in proportion to our taxable capacity. The President tried to cover those matters by talking of taxation at so much a head.  Of course everyone knows that is so much nonsense, because a poor man cannot pay as much as a rich man, and a poor nation cannot pay as much as a rich nation.  Apart altogether from England, Ireland is paying more per head than half a dozen great European countries.  The figures are: Ireland, £7 6s. per head; France, £6; United States, £6; Germany, £5, and Italy, £4 5s. These questions ought to be reopened. We are getting into debt every year; we cannot pay our way and we are becoming bankrupt. Debts are piling up and, as everybody knows, the cost of living has gone far above the cost of living in Britain, and that is a sign of the indebtedness of the country under the present financial system.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelComynKC" hpid="Mr. Comyn Mr. Comyn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Comyn</NameTxt>
      <P>I beg to support the recommendation proposed by Senater Moore, and I wish to join with him in saying that the speech made by the Minister yesterday was very illuminating.  I am waiting for the printed report of that speech in order to study it more closely, because the Minister stated a few things which I think should be known generally by the Irish people and which, as far as we can do so, will be made known. Senator Moore proposes that £1,100,000, the amount of money paid for the pensions of the R.I.C., be taken out of this Vote.  I think he is absolutely right constitutionally both under the Treaty and under an agreement made between Mr. Cosgrave and Mr. Baldwin in December, 1925, which was duly ratified by the Parliaments of both countries and which is a binding agreement.  Why do I say that?  I say that so far as the police officers who retired before the Treaty are concerned their pensions were payable <Col N="1494" /> out of moneys voted and to be voted by the Imperial Parliament. Their pensions were, therefore, at the date of the Treaty, part of the public debt of England.  So far as the policemen who were disbanded, let us say, as a result of the Treaty, are concerned, they were not disbanded by the Provisional Government. They never came under the control of the Provisional Government. They were disbanded by the British Parliament, and in the Act disbanding them it is expressly stipulated that their pensions shall be paid out of funds to be voted by the Imperial Parliament.  Therefore, these pensions, both of the men who retired before the Treaty and as a result of the Treaty, are part of the public debt, according to any definition whatever which may be given of that debt.  I do not accept in its entirety the definition given by Mr. Hogan.  I think that it was a definition <i>ad hoc,</i> if I may say so.  According to any definition of the public debt these pensions payable to the R.I.C. are part of that public debt. As such, they came under Article V of the Treaty and as such they were disposed of by the agreement made between Mr. Cosgrave and the British Prime Minister which was ratified by both Parliaments and which is a legal document.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>It is no use for Mr. Blythe to come up and say that any arguments of that kind are ridiculous. That does not answer the argument. The reason that I say that his speech was illuminating is that it lets the cat out of the bag.  It is coming out by the tail.  Mr. Blythe said that from the 6th December, 1921, until 1925 there was a series of little treaties.  There were little agreements.  There was a little agreement to pay to England the money which has been referred to by Senator Linehan. There was a little agreement to pay to England a sum corresponding to the pensions of the police force. There was another little agreement to pay to England the proceeds of land annuities which by the Act of 1920 England had given to the Exchequer of Southern Ireland, <Col N="1495" /> which is the same territory as is now being administered by the Free State Government.  I would submit that it is very reasonable that the terms of these little agreements should be made known and, when they are made known, I will make the further suggestion that they are not valid because they are not validated either by the Parliament of England or by that of the Free State.  Ministers here have shown now that they are acting, and have acted for the past four or five years, in a wholly unconstitutional manner.  Their conduct in regard to matters of finance has been absolutely unconstitutional.  When Mr. Cosgrave came back after that agreement he said that he had got a clean slate, that he had explained the position of the country, and that he had got rid of the obligations under Article V.  What he really did do was to beg to be placed under a contribution corresponding to a national debt of £166,000,000 because five millions a year, on the basis of the payments which England is making to America, a three per cent. basis, represents a capital international debt of £166,000,000.</P>
    <P>According to Mr. Cosgrave that is really the obligation which he undertook, if he did undertake it&mdash;we say that he did not.  We say that these little treaties and these little agreements to hand over these sums to England are without any force whatever, that English statesmen and officials may place no reliance on them, and further, that these payments which were made before that settlement was arranged were conditional payments in the interval that elapsed pending the final settlement, and they should not be paid after that settlement had been arrived at.  Another observation which the Minister made in reference to the speech of Senator Linehan&mdash; a well-informed speech, as I submit it was&mdash;was that the Act of 1920 does not govern the case, and that it was not in operation.  He said that the Treaty was a separate and different document and was not based on the Act of 1920.  It was <Col N="1496" /> based on the Act of 1920, and that Act, as Senator Linehan said, is referred to seven times in the Treaty. Ministers know, or at least some of them know&mdash;and there are Ministers in this House listening to me who know&mdash;that the Provisional Government expressly operated under the Act of 1920.  Where is the use of telling us who know these things that the Act of 1920 was not in operation?  There is another matter which was referred to by the Minister. It may be a matter in which lawyers will disagree, and I do not say that the Minister is not entitled to his opinion, but the Minister said that the Order in Council of the 21st July, 1921, is a valid order.  The Act of 1920 provided that certain functions of government should come into actual operation only when an Order in Council was made by the King fixing the date.  On the 20th July the King made an Order in Council, not fixing the date but giving himself parliamentary powers by subsequent order to fix the date.</P>
    <P>We say that that was an invalid order, and that the Act of 1920 came into full force and effect on the first Tuesday in August.  That is our position and it may be well for Ministers to know it.  I do not think that that is a ridiculous argument. As Senator Moore reminds me, one of the Free State judges, Judge Meredith, has given a judgment which shows that that is the true legal position.  Ministers cannot go on, as they have been going on, jeering and smiling at arguments on this question.  It is a very serious question as it represents £166,000,000 of national debt on a poor country.  In point of law there is no justification or defence for these little treaties that are alleged to have been made after 1921 and before the final settlement.  The substance of these treaties has never been disclosed to the people of Ireland.  They are not valid, either in Ireland or in England.  English Ministers never intended that they should be valid, or that they should obtain for one hour longer&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. Johnson Mr. Johnson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Johnson</NameTxt>
      <P>Does the Senator <Col N="1497" /> contend that validity depends on formal ratification?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelComynKC" hpid="Mr. Comyn Mr. Comyn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Comyn</NameTxt>
      <P>I contend that in the case of payments amounting to £1,100,000 in this case, to £3,000,000 in the case of land annuities, and to £600,000 in the case of local loans, no agreement is valid except it is ratified by Parliament.  Certainly I contend that.  Further, I say that little treaties are dangerous things. When Mr. Parnell on one occasion had to refer to the conduct of one of his colleagues, who subsequently filled a high place in the Free State, he said: &ldquo;Tim is always making little treaties.&rdquo;  That is what they have been doing for the last four or five years, always making little treaties which are absolutely invalid and which we will question as soon as we can.  What we do say now is that it is perfectly open to the present Executive to revise the financial arrangements, to put their house in order, to pay what is legally payable, and to refuse payment of what is not legally payable, because our taxes are too high and the country cannot exist if we are going to continue as we are.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. Johnson Mr. Johnson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Johnson</NameTxt>
      <P>I would like to make my position clear on this Vote and on the previous Vote.  I voted against the last recommendation dealing with local loans and I propose to vote against this one.  I think that the method of approach is not a wise one.  I do not think that big questions of this kind of international significance can be decided wisely by a debate of the kind that is in progress.  I do not think that the Seanad, or the Dáil for that matter, would be well advised in coming to decisions on such questions after such debates and with such information as is made public through such a debate. The question under discussion, as the other, depends apparently on the validity or otherwise of the Ultimate Financial Settlement.  Now there may be a case for questioning whether that was a wise settlement or not, but to recommend to the Dáil that they should refuse to sanction payments to the British <Col N="1498" /> Government in respect of these pensions or in respect of local loans, on the arguments stated here, to my mind is unwise politically and very unlikely to lead to political success. The case, to say the least of it, is not proven, and we should not be led into voting for so important a proposal unless we have very clear grounds for our decision.</P>
      <P>The Senator who last spoke said, and previously it has been often stated, that these &ldquo;little treaties&rdquo; as he called them are invalid, that it is unconstitutional to have entered into these agreements and to have acted according to them until they have been ratified by the Oireachtas on the one hand and the British Parliament on the other.  I suggest to Senators who are responsible for those statements that it is bad strategy to stress that point.  Even if it is true that the agreements have no validity until ratified by Parliament, by pressing them on the present Ministry, they are challenging them to get them ratified.  After they are ratified, their case falls to the ground&mdash;if they have a case.  I do not think it is true that they are invalid until they are ratified.  I know no constitutional law or practice which prevents a Ministry entering into an agreement with another Ministry of another country, even though that involves financial obligations. As far as the legality of the case is concerned, I think it would be quite legitimate for the Government to enter into an agreement with the United States of America to pay one hundred millions a year, if it were possible to do so.  So far as legal validity goes they have authority to do it until the question arises of making payments.  An agreement they can make but they cannot pay money until the Dáil votes it away.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I think that there is an entire mistake in arguing as though it were an illegal act on the part of the Government here to make an agreement with the Government of Great Britain which involves the payment of money.  If the Oireachtas refuses to vote the monies, consequent upon the agreement, that is an entirely <Col N="1499" /> different matter, and when the Oireachtas has voted these monies it implements, to use a phrase that has become popular, the agreement and its necessary consequences.  I would not be afraid to raise these questions because of any fear that it might mean the cancellation of the Ultimate Financial Settlement.  I think that the Ultimate Financial Settlement will have to be reconsidered, but I would be very slow to challenge the issue until I had had a very close examination, from the Irish Free State side of the question, and its implications, a very close examination by experts who are able to weigh up the probable results of an arbitration.  As far as I can see, and I do not pretend to be an expert at all, I think the balance would be in our favour, probably considerably in our favour, but I would not go the way of making a political campaign on the question until I had very sure grounds for my belief.  In any case such reopening should be reopened by diplomatic methods first and not as a result of a rousing political campaign of a party character within this country.</P>
    <P>That, to my mind, prejudices the chances of getting anything valuable out of a reconsideration of the Ultimate Financial Settlement.  The fact that it is eventually to be raised, merely as the result of a party struggle within this country and following upon the defeat of one Government by another Government which has made the question an issue, makes it very difficult indeed for the successful party to raise the question with any prospect of success in diplomatic negotiations.  It is because I hold that view that I look with regret at the method that has been chosen to get these issues into the public mind.  It is in the nature of things impossible for the present Ministry to raise this question. Because they entered into it and praised it as beneficent and generous they cannot very well turn round at any point in their career and say: &ldquo;We made a mistake, we ought not to have entered into this settlement. <Col N="1500" /> we ought not to have agreed to pay these pensions.  We ought not to have agreed upon this, that, or the other.&rdquo;  So it inevitably follows that it must be a succeeding Government that must raise the question, and if they have come into power by virtue of agitation of a party nature upon such an issue, I say their chances of doing any good by diplomatic negotiation are very much lessened and are unlikely to bring financial benefit to this country.</P>
    <P>The question, therefore, that is involved in this Vote is bound up with a wider issue, and it is prejudicing the chances of a fair examination of the question, first, by our own experts, who will advise as to whether it will be wise to scrap the financial settlement and go back to the Treaty position.  If they decided it was wise, that the risk was a good one, I think that the refusal to pay these moneys over at this stage and until the financial settlement is being reconsidered would be inadvisable and prejudicial to the best interests of the country.  Therefore, I shall vote against the motion.</P>
    <Speaker pid="ErnestBlythe" hpid="Mr. Blythe Mr. Blythe">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Blythe</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not want to go into this matter again.  I dealt with it yesterday and I dealt with it previously in the Dáil.  I will just repeat. As I said yesterday, the Treaty was a short document.  If it were only a man and his wife quarrelling and entering into a legal separation a much longer document would be necessary if everything was to be covered.  The Treaty dealt with principles and points of importance. Many other matters remained to be settled between Governments in order to put the Treaty into effect.  Subsidiary matters of various kinds, and agreements of various kinds, had to be arranged. It was absolutely necessary if the Treaty was to be carried into effect that these should be entered into, and the only obligation on the Government was that they should be in accordance with the spirit and the principles of the Treaty.</P>
      <P>I will deal with just one other point that I think was not touched on yesterday.  Senator Colonel.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="1501" /> Moore said the country was becoming bankrupt and that we were going into debt every year.  The country is not becoming bankrupt. There has been some increase of debt partly because we are still paying for the damage caused by the civil war and partly because of the carrying out of constructive works, such as the Shannon scheme and the big drainage schemes, like the Barrow scheme, which really should not be paid out of revenue, but which should be provided for by the raising of debt.  There is no suggestion at all in any figures that I have been supplied with, or that I have been able to get hold of, that the country is becoming bankrupt. On the contrary I am satisfied that progress, although slow progress, is being made.  I would only say in conclusion that in my opinion the financial settlement that has been effected between the two countries is a very fair financial settlement.  I pay little attention to some of the most fissiparous critics, because they are the people who, before Article V was wiped out, were estimating that we would pay annually sums up to 30 millions.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MauriceMoore" hpid="Colonel Moore Colonel Moore">
      <NameTxt>Colonel Moore</NameTxt>
      <P>Not I.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ErnestBlythe" hpid="Mr. Blythe Mr. Blythe">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Blythe</NameTxt>
      <P>There are others besides Senator Colonel Moore. Very big sums were estimated by some of the people who are now the loudest in their demands for reopening the agreements that were entered into.  Anything that falls upon the taxpayer in respect of these arrangements is small.  Land annuities is an entirely different question, and does not fall upon the taxpayer.  The annuity which the individual paid is in respect of a bargain entered into whereby he became the possessor of his own land.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MauriceMoore" hpid="Colonel Moore Colonel Moore">
      <NameTxt>Colonel Moore</NameTxt>
      <P>Would the Minister answer the question as to whether we are taxed higher than in Britain?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ErnestBlythe" hpid="Mr. Blythe Mr. Blythe">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Blythe</NameTxt>
      <P>I think it has absolutely nothing to do with the point raised.  The question of taxation <Col N="1502" /> depends not merely upon the capacity to pay but on services rendered.  I think that nearly all the talk we hear with regard to the amount people ought to be paying is absurd for this reason&mdash;that the amounts which are suggested as the revenue which ought to be raised here would not provide for services such as Old Age Pensions, education and other matters.  The question of what ought to be paid on taxable capacity is a matter for debate itself and a big matter.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MauriceMoore" hpid="Colonel Moore Colonel Moore">
      <NameTxt>Colonel Moore</NameTxt>
      <P>May I say one word in reply to Senator Johnson? These matters were raised originally not as a big agitation but they were raised quietly in the Seanad.  We could get no answer here.  We were refused an inquiry and a reasonable answer.  I do not see how the matter can be brought forward at all according to Senator Johnson.  If he requires everybody to sit quiet, say nothing and allow these things to go on indefinitely there is no doubt we will continue to pay.  How Senator Johnson wishes to come at the matter of producing a Government which will go into this matter I really do not know.  It seems to me that he talks in the air, as if these things will come of their own accord.  Unless you fight your corner you will get nothing.  I am not going to divide the Seanad on this point, but I think all these things have to go to the country in spite of what Senator Johnson says, because it is only the country that will decide these matters.</P>
      <P>Recommendation put and declared lost.</P>
      <P>Question proposed &ldquo;That Schedule B stand part of the Bill.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. Johnson Mr. Johnson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Johnson</NameTxt>
      <P>I had suggested raising a question on the Vote for Local Government.  I had thought of putting down a formal recommendation, but on consideration and advice I desisted.  But I want to raise the question I indicated in regard to the administration of relief in Dublin and the responsibilities of the Minister in that respect.  I would remind the House of a procedure that <Col N="1503" /> took place regarding the Bill which was passed in the Seanad, the Dublin City and County (Relief of the Poor) Bill.  That had its genesis in the fact that Senator Byrne brought to the notice of the Seanad the great distress that exists in the city and the difficulties that were being experienced in respect to the provision of relief.  All Senators who live in Dublin are aware of the extent of the poverty, the distress that arises from that poverty, and the difficulties that are experienced in relieving it.  A Committee was set up to examine into the question as to whether the inability to provide relief was due to any legal barrier and certain proposals were made with regard to the removal of the barrier which was found to exist. One must remind the House that the old Poor Law has had unanimous condemnation of all authorities for many years who had ever gone into the subject&mdash;the Poor Law Commission of about twentyfive years ago, a Commission of the old Dáil, and of the present Minister for Finance when he was Minister for Local Government.  If ever a proposition had unanimous support it was the proposition that the Poor Law that had been established in 1847 was not suitable for this country and required a change.  One of the chief points of criticism on which there was general agreement was that the provision which forced able-bodied persons into the workhouse before they could obtain relief should be abolished.  That view found expression in the proceedings of the County Councils under the old Dáil before the Free State was established, and it is known that a large number of county schemes were set up.  Those county schemes practically destroyed the old Poor Law system in respect of all counties where schemes were established, and the 1923 Act was passed making those schemes valid.  In March, 1923, the Bill was passed&mdash;it was to expire in March, 1924&mdash;with the assurance that there would be a comprehensive Local Government Bill introduced.  New schemes were <Col N="1504" /> propounded and sanctioned by the Ministry for certain counties&mdash; Waterford, Cork, and other counties. These schemes became law after the passing of the 1923 Act. That Act makes it mandatory, as some legal authorities assert&mdash;I think it is unquestionable&mdash;upon a county council to prepare a scheme in accordance with the provisions of the Act, though the section says: &ldquo;A council of any county to which no existing county schemes relate may prepare a scheme in accordance with the provisions of this Act and for the relief of the poor in that county.&rdquo;  It is pointed out that the &ldquo;may&rdquo; in that section really has a mandatory effect in law, inasmuch as it is coupled with a duty in the public interests.  Notwithstanding that, for six years the City and County Borough of Dublin have been allowed to proceed without putting any scheme into effect, and the position to-day is that the law relating to the relief of the poor, which has had the condemnation of every authority for many years, remains in existence with all its disabilities and defects, and there is no sign at the moment of its being remedied.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The position, therefore, is, as we have been told on authority, that there are not less than 5,000 families in the city of Dublin who ought to be getting assistance&mdash;they are otherwise eligible for assistance, which means to say that they must be in a state of destitution&mdash;who are not allowed to get assistance under the law.  An attempt was made by the Seanad to remedy that defect and, unfortunately&mdash;I am not going to try to lay blame&mdash;the Bill was not proceeded with in the Dáil.  The Minister found reason for not supporting the Second Reading and, therefore, the Dáil did not have an opportunity to consider the Bill, because the Minister announced that he had to oppose the Second Reading. I may say, parenthetically, that the Bill would have had a great deal more explanation, discussion and advertisement in this House but for the fact that it already had the support and the assurance that <Col N="1505" /> the Minister himself would father it in the Dáil and endeavour to get it passed.  However, new circumstances arose and the Minister was persuaded that it would be inadvisable to proceed with the Bill at this stage.  The position, therefore, is that these 5,000 families in the city of Dublin are to remain in a state of destitution or rely upon charity.  It is still outside the law for the relieving officers to provide any relief for them.  It may be said, as has been pointed out by the Committee itself, that the Commissioners for the Relief of the Poor have, in fact, been proceeding in an extra legal or illegal manner to give assistance to the poor outside the workhouse, that able-bodied persons have been enabled to get assistance outside the workhouse by virtue of an arrangement made with some charitable organisations and promises given to those charitable organisations that they would be indemnified and recouped for any expense they were put to in the way of relieving those persons.  It is clear that the Poor Law Commissioners cannot be allowed to be surcharged under that head.  Some financial provision will have to be made some day to implement that promise, because it was made with the sanction of the Minister, and it satisfies, I think, the public conscience.  The question, then, has arisen as to why this Bill that we submitted to the Dáil has not been passed.  It was pointed out that there are certain questions of the incidence of the rates&mdash;that a great deal of the charge which would accrue by virtue of the aggregation of poor people in the city of Dublin would fall upon some parts of the county, because of the delimitation of boundaries.  May I point out, in reply to that objection, that whatever is true in regard to the Bill is surely equally true in regard to those illegal assurances and the payments that have been made under the promise of the Minister and the Commissioner, and that will have to be refunded.  If those are liable to fall upon the Dublin Union, which includes some part of the county, the <Col N="1506" /> county will, no doubt, have something to say upon the matter, and will be just as vocal in its opposition as it is in respect of the possible incidence of the charge in the Bill that was proposed by the Seanad.  So that, whenever the financial question is going to be solved, and a proper agreement is made under the one head, it can be made the occasion for solving the financial difficulty under any other head.</P>
    <P>I desire to ask the Seanad to bring such influence as it can to bear on the Minister to get him to agree to support the action which the Seanad took in passing this Bill because of the need of the poor in the City.  Now that we have been made cognisant of the fact, now that we are aware that the responsibility is a legislative one, we cannot any longer allow the relieving officers to shelter themselves behind the fact that they have no power.  It is our duty to give them power, and the manner in which we proposed to do it was as simple as possible. In raising the matter in this manner I feel that the Minister ought to have encouragement from the Seanad to the end that he should take advantage of the meeting of the Dáil on the 31st that is said to have been arranged to obtain sanction for this Bill so that the relief of the poor for the next six months may be proceeded with in due form and may be made valid and legal.</P>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Cathaoirleach Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I must point out to the Senator that his ten minutes have been exceeded, and I cannot allow him to proceed any further. His statement is very interesting, no doubt, but we must have some regard for the Standing Orders.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MauriceMoore" hpid="Colonel Moore Colonel Moore">
      <NameTxt>Colonel Moore</NameTxt>
      <P>I should like to say something about quite a different matter&mdash;the National Museum.  The state of the Museum is getting very serious.  There are a number of vacancies on the staff&mdash;I think there are seven vacancies in one section&mdash;the Museum cannot be looked after, and the geological section has to be closed down because there is no one to look after it.  Not only that, but the money that is paid <Col N="1507" /> for it is paid subject to the decision of a number of clerks, instead of allowing the place to be run by the head of it.  He is not allowed to spend money unless it is arranged by clerks who knew nothing about the whole matter and who are merely accountants.  I would like the Minister to look after the Museum, because it would be a very serious loss if it fell into decay, as it will if these vacancies are not filled.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ErnestBlythe" hpid="Mr. Blythe Mr. Blythe">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Blythe</NameTxt>
      <P>With reference to the point that Senator Johnson raised, the Minister for Local Government asked me to express his regret to the Seanad that he was not able to remain until this matter was raised. It has been engaging the attention of the Department of Local Government and of other Departments.  I would not like to agree with the statement that illegal things are being done.  Whether anything illegal is being done or not will remain to be tested at the audit, and I would suggest that that will depend to some extent on the interpretation of the provisions in regard to provisional relief in urgent and necessitous circumstances, under the Act of 1847.  However, that is a matter that I cannot deal with at length, unfortunately.  With regard to the Museum, I have no direct information, but I know that arrangements are being made for recruiting additional staff for it at an early date. I know that because certain propositions have been before the Department of Finance, and in certain cases sanctions have been given; so that while I am not sufficiently familiar with the matter to deal with it at length, I know that certain steps have been taken.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JanePower" hpid="Mrs. Wyse Power Mrs. Wyse Power">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Wyse Power</NameTxt>
      <P>Might I say, in support of what Senator Johnson has said, that I think it very necessary that any pressure or influence that we can bring to bear to see that between this and November&mdash; I presume that the Bill will not be touched until then&mdash;or any influence that the Committee can bring to bear on the Minister should be exercised to get him to justify the <Col N="1508" /> Commissioners in giving out what the Minister does not like to call illegal relief, but for which I can find no other word, the continuance of which would be of enormous advantage to the poor.  Everybody who spoke on the Bill, and everyone who was on the Committee that went into these things, knows that there is a crying need in the city and the county of Dublin for this relief, and that the law at present does not meet that need.  Because of a very small thing the Bill has been postponed to satisfy a particular council, and I think that everything should be done to induce the Commissioners to continue the system that has been in practice up to the present until it is legalised by the Bill which we have passed.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Cathaoirleach Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I think that the Seanad, by its action in passing the Bill, showed very great sympathy with the poor of Dublin and that they desired that everything possible should be done for them.  They proved that by passing the Bill.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JanePower" hpid="Mrs. Wyse Power Mrs. Wyse Power">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Wyse Power</NameTxt>
      <P>I would even go so far as to say that the Committee should see the Minister.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Cathaoirleach Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>That would be very wise.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>Title put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>Report Stage ordered for Friday, 19th July.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Public Business. - Copyright (Preservation)" RHead="Bill, 1929&mdash;Fifth Stage">
    <Title>Public Business. - Copyright (Preservation) Bill, 1929&mdash;Fifth Stage.</Title>
    <P>Question&mdash;&ldquo;That the Copyright (Preservation) Bill, 1929, be received for final consideration and do now pass&rdquo;&mdash;put and agreed to.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Public Business. - Agricultural" RHead="Credit Bill, 1929&mdash;Second Stage">
    <Title>Public Business. - Agricultural Credit Bill, 1929&mdash;Second Stage.</Title>
    <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That the Agricultural Credit Bill, 1929, be read a Second Time.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. Johnson Mr. Johnson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Johnson</NameTxt>
      <P>I would like a little information about this Bill.  Could the Minister give us some information as to the purposes and intentions of the Bill?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1509" />
    <Speaker pid="ErnestBlythe" hpid="Mr. Blythe Mr. Blythe">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Blythe</NameTxt>
      <P>There are two purposes in the Bill.  As I explained in the Dáil there were originally two Bills but they have been welded into one.  The purpose in part is financial, really to provide money for the Agricultural Credit Corporation otherwise than by calling up the unpaid ten shillings on the shares that have been issued.  Instead of calling up that money it has been decided to issue an additional £500,000 in shares and to leave the ten shillings unpaid on the old share capital, that ten shillings to be called up only in the case of the winding up of the Corporation.  Instead of calling up the ten shillings outstanding on the shares the object is to leave the uncalled portion so as to give the Corporation certain facilities in the matter of temporary borrowing. Another change that has been made has been to divide the shares into A and B shares.  The B shares are shares upon which interest will not be paid for the first few years. The position at present is that dividends are payable on all shares, irrespective of the profits made by the Corporation.  The result is that the Department of Finance has to pay out of the Exchequer the money required for the payment of dividends on the shares held by the Minister for Finance.  That creates a false appearance in the balance sheet, and it is thought desirable to make arrangements which, after one year, will, I think, provide that no dividend shall be paid except a dividend paid out of profits.  Generally that is the extent of the financial section of the Bill.  There are other sections which are designed to make it easier for the Corporation to obtain a good charge upon certain classes of land than at present.  That is part of what was originally the second Bill which was being promoted by the Minister for Agriculture. Amendments were introduced in the Dáil which slightly widened the class of objects for which loans might be made by the Corporation.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasEsmondeBart" hpid="Sir Thomas Esmonde Sir Thomas Esmonde">
      <NameTxt>Sir Thomas Esmonde</NameTxt>
      <P>This is a double-barrelled Bill.  I am not concerned with the financial provisions <Col N="1510" /> of the Bill; the methods of the Corporation for raising finance do not concern me, and I intend to speak only on the question of assistance for farmers.  Perhaps the Minister for Agriculture would be better able to explain this matter to the Seanad than the Minister for Finance, because he has been very much interested in the question of agricultural credit, and has taken some very important and, to my mind, some very satisfactory steps in that direction. This is really one of the most important Bills this Session has produced, and I do not think that I should miss this opportunity of congratulating the Minister for Agriculture on the continuing success of his policy, because I think his policy is really the foundation of the prosperity of the country, recognising as I do that the whole prosperity of Ireland depends on the industry of the farmer.</P>
      <P>There are one or two points to which I would like to draw the attention of the Minister for Finance &mdash;they are more or less departmental points&mdash;that occurred to me because I have been interested in agricultural co-operation for a great many years, and I have studied it in a great many countries.  But I would prefer not to delay the Bill, as I know it is an excellent Bill and one that the farmers require, and I would prefer to make these suggestions to the Minister privately, if that would be agreeable to him.  I do not want to delay the Bill more than is necessary, but there are certain points which, I think, would be useful to the farmers' organisation and might lead to a satisfactory solution of this branch of the problem, which is not confined to this country, but which affects many other countries.  It is vitally important for this country, and I am glad to say this country has been the pioneer of this movement for the assistance of agriculture all over the world.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. Johnson Mr. Johnson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Johnson</NameTxt>
      <P>It would perhaps save time on the Committee Stage if we could get some explanation from the Minister for Agriculture as to <Col N="1511" /> the purport of Section 23 and its effect, regarding the limitations on the lending of money by the Corporation, and enlarging its powers. In regard to Section 29, will the Minister explain the purpose of this section?  It seems to make valid rules of agricultural societies, which, without this Bill, would be invalid but under which they have been lending money to individual members of the societies without a particular class of security.  It is made valid only in respect of money which the Corporation has advanced.  I am not criticising this, because I do not understand it, but I think it would be well if the Minister would give some explanation of these two points, so that it may save discussion, and perhaps attempts at amendment for the purpose of elucidation, on the Committee Stage.  It would probably shorten the proceedings if we had the position regarding these two section made clear by the Minister.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickJHogan" hpid="Minister for Agriculture (Mr. Hogan) Minister for Agriculture (Mr. Hogan)">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Agriculture (Mr. Hogan)</NameTxt>
      <P>With regard to Section 23, it may look very formidable, but the point covered in it is quite simple.  In the original Agricultural Credit Corporation Act, the Corporation was entitled to lend money to a person for certain purposes.  The purposes specified in paragraphs (a), (b), (c) and (d) are exactly the purposes specified in the original Act. After some experience in the working of the original Act, it was found that a situation like this might arise: a loan is incurred by a farmer for a purely agricultural purpose, say for the purpose of purchasing seeds.  After two or three years that farmer dies and his son takes out administration.  A loan could not be made to the son because it was not the son that made himself liable for the original loan.  At least, it was doubtful whether the Agricultural Credit Corporation were entitled to make a loan to a son in respect of a debt incurred by his father.  A position like that is met under Section 23.  Paragraph (a) provides that it shall be lawful for <Col N="1512" /> the Agricultural Credit Corporation to make a loan</P>
      <P>(a) to any person (other than a co-operative society) for the purpose of paying off a loan which was originally made to another person before the passing of the Principal Act wholly or mainly for the purpose of purchasing land for agricultural purposes;</P>
      <P>(b) to any person (other than a co-operative society) for the purpose of paying off a loan or other liability which was originally obtained or incurred, whether before or after the passing of this Act, by him or any other person...</P>
      <P>That is the vital clause in the section, and the same thing applies to every single one of them.  The only point in that section is to ensure that a loan made by the Agricultural Credit Corporation shall be valid even though that loan is made now to a person who had nothing to do with the original purpose.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>In regard to Section 29, certain things could be done and certain things could not be done under the Industrial and Provident Societies Act of 1893.  It is thought that the Agricultural Credit Corporation should have the power, notwithstanding anything contained in the Industrial and Provident Societies Act, to do the things set out in paragraphs (a), (b) and (c) of Section 29 in this Bill.  The Agricultural Credit Corporation are there being given the powers to do certain things.  It was thought right to clear up the matter, and to make sure that the Agricultural Credit Corporation could take power to advance money for the purposes set out in paragraphs (a), (b) and (c) of Section 29.  Under paragraph (b), where the Agricultural Credit Corporation lends money through a co-operative society to individuals who are members of co-operative societies, a new situation is created, and we want to make absolutely sure, notwithstanding anything contained in the Industrial and Provident Societies Act, that the co-operative societies may be a valid and a legal guarantor for a loan <Col N="1513" /> made to an individual shareholder. That arises out of the scheme which the co-operative societies are perfecting at the present moment.  It will enable the Agricultural Credit Corporation to lend money to members of co-operative societies, leaving the societies the guarantors.  It is fairly certain that there is not legal power to do that at present, that is, to make a loan of money in that way.  We think that it is desirable to do so.</P>
    <P>Senator Johnson is right when he says that there are a number of other points and matters arising out of the Industrial and Provident Societies Act which it might be well to have cleared up.  That Act was never meant to meet the situation that we have at present.  It was principally meant to deal with quite different sorts of societies.  At present we propose to change the Industrial and Provident Societies Act only in so far as it affects the Agricultural Credit Corporation.  So far as it affects co-operation as a whole, we propose to change that particular Act in a great many respects by the Co-operative Bill, which is an extremely difficult measure to draft, <Col N="1514" /> and which I am hoping we will be able to introduce in the autumn session.</P>
    <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
    <P>Committee Stage ordered for Friday, 19th July.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Public Business. - Juries (Protection)" RHead="Bill, 1929&mdash;Fifth Stage">
    <Title>Public Business. - Juries (Protection) Bill, 1929&mdash;Fifth Stage.</Title>
    <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That the Juries (Protection) Bill, 1929, be received for Final Consideration and do now pass.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. Johnson Mr. Johnson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Johnson</NameTxt>
      <P>I am against this Bill, and I challenge a division.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MauriceMoore" hpid="Colonel Moore Colonel Moore">
      <NameTxt>Colonel Moore</NameTxt>
      <P>On a point of order&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Cathaoirleach Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>There can be no point of order, as a division has been called.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MauriceMoore" hpid="Colonel Moore Colonel Moore">
      <NameTxt>Colonel Moore</NameTxt>
      <P>I was told this Bill was put off until to-morrow.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Cathaoirleach Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not know who told the Senator that it was put off until to-morrow.  I did not tell him any such thing.</P>
      <P Just="Center">The Seanad divided: Tá, 19; Níl, 12.</P>
      <P Just="Center">Tá</P>
    </Speaker>
    <table pgwide="1">
      <tgroup cols="2">
        <colspec colname="1" colnum="1" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <colspec colname="2" colnum="2" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry rowsep="1">Sir Edward Coey Bigger.<br />Samuel L. Brown, K.C.<br />Alfred Byrne.<br />Mrs. Costello.<br />John C. Counihan.<br />The Countess of Desart.<br />James G. Douglas.<br />Sir Thomas Grattan Esmonde.<br />Michael Fanning.<br />P.J. Hooper.</entry>
            <entry rowsep="1">Patrick W. Kenny.<br />James MacKean.<br />John MacLoughlin.<br />Seán Milroy.<br />James Moran.<br />Joseph O'Connor.<br />M.F. O'Hanlon.<br />Bernard O'Rourke.<br />James J. Parkinson.<br /></entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
    <P Just="Center">Níl</P>
    <table pgwide="1">
      <tgroup cols="2">
        <colspec colname="1" colnum="1" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <colspec colname="2" colnum="2" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry rowsep="1">Caitlín Bean Uí Chléirigh.<br />Michael Comyn, K.C.<br />Joseph Connolly.<br />William Cummins.<br />Michael Duffy.<br />Thomas Foran.</entry>
            <entry rowsep="1">Thomas Johnson.<br />Colonel Moore.<br />Joseph O'Doherty.<br />John T. O'Farrell.<br />Siobhán Bean an Phaoraigh.<br />Séumas Robinson.</entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
    <P>Motion declared carried.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Public Business. - Land Bill," RHead="1929&mdash;Second Stage">
    <Title>Public Business. - Land Bill, 1929&mdash;Second Stage.</Title>
    <P>Permission granted to Mr. Roddy, Parliamentary Secretary to the Minister for Lands and Fisheries, to attend and take charge of the Bill.</P>
    <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That the Land Bill, 1929, be read a Second Time.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelComynKC" hpid="Mr. Comyn Mr. Comyn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Comyn</NameTxt>
      <P>Before the Bill is read a Second Time, I wish to draw <Col N="1515" /> attention to one or two matters which I hope the Minister will see his way to have rectified.  Judging from various sections, it appears to be a measure intended to facilitate the vesting of land.  A good many of its provisions are useful.  I notice that each section is apparently framed in view of cases which have actually occurred.  For instance, Section 3 provides for fishing rights appurtenant to holdings, and fisheries on rivers passing through or by land are deemed to be appurtenant to the holding if the fishing right is vested in the tenant or his superior landlord. That is intended to meet a case which occurred on the River Louth, where the fishery in part of that river was held not to be appurtenant to the holding adjoining the river.  I mention that matter for the purpose of suggesting that every section of this Bill is framed with a view to meeting difficulties in cases that have arisen. Therefore, I am most anxious to know why Section 5, sub-section (1) is framed in the terms in which it is.</P>
      <P>Let me read it:&mdash;</P>
      <P>(1) Where a fishery or fishing right is vested (whether before or after the passing of this Act) in the Land Commission under Section 45 of the Land Act, 1923 (No. 42 of 1923), as amended by this Act and another fishery or fishing right (hereinafter referred to as the ancillary fishery or fishing right) which is not so vested is, in the opinion of the Land Commission, necessary for the proper user and enjoyment of the first-mentioned fishery or fishing right, the Land Commission may purchase such ancillary fishery or fishing right for such price, payable in four and one-half per cent. land bonds of equal nominal value, as shall be agreed upon between the Land Commission and the owner of such ancillary fishery or fishing right.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Suppose that a considerable stretch of fishery is vested in the Land Commission and there is part of that fishery adjoining a stream vested in a private owner, it is <Col N="1516" /> called in this section an ancillary fishery.  I wish to know why is not that ancillary fishery placed in the same position as a tenant or landlord. The Land Commission are asking for public money to buy out ancillary fishermen at their own price.  If a case has arisen calling for that section I would like to know what the case is.  I would also like to know why the ancillary fisherman is getting his own price, because these are the words of the section:</P>
    <P>The Land Commission may purchase such ancillary fishery or fishing right for such price, payable in four and one-half per cent. land bonds of equal nominal value, as shall be agreed upon between the Land Commission and the owner of such ancillary fishery or fishing right.</P>
    <Speaker pid="SamuelBrownKC" hpid="Mr. Brown Mr. Brown">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Brown</NameTxt>
      <P>That is not his own price.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelComynKC" hpid="Mr. Comyn Mr. Comyn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Comyn</NameTxt>
      <P>He need not sell, and he will not sell, unless he gets his price.  I would like to know whether any cases have arisen to which that section is directed, and what are these cases, or whether public money is to be voted for the purpose of giving fancy prices to ancillary fishermen?  I do not wish to be critical.  I only wish to understand what the meaning of that section is and why it is in case of disagreement as to price the power is not vested in the Land Commission to fix a price just as a price is fixed in the case of landlords and tenants. There is another matter which I think should receive the attention of those concerned with this Bill.  It relates to Section 4.  The Land Commission take power to acquire fisheries, and they also in Section 4 take power to refuse to acquire fisheries.  That is a matter of administration and a matter in which they are the best judges, but this question arises: In case they elect to take a fishery, of course they get under sub-section (5) of Section 45 of the Principal Act, the statutory right to go along the banks of a river and fish.  In case they do not elect to take up the fishery, do <Col N="1517" /> they propose to make any provision in regard to the right of entry for the purpose of fishing?  That is a matter that I wish to put before those in charge of the Bill for consideration. The fishing industry is very important, and whatever legislation can do should be done towards making the law in regard to the fisheries as perfect as possible. It is by no means perfect. This Bill is an attempt to make it perfect, just as it is an attempt to make any other little matters in the land code workable.  There was a case some time ago where a man had a right to fish on a river and had the common law right to go on the bank to fish, but the owner of the land put a mad bull into the field with the result that when the fisherman was luring the wily trout the bull sent the trout back to the stream and the fisherman after it.  These are matters which should be considered if the Land Commission take over the fisheries.  Of course, under sub-section (5) of Section 45 of the Principal Act they take the right to go on the bank, but if they do not take the fishery, what are they going to do in reference to the right of approach?  These are two questions to which I should like to call attention before this Bill gets a Second Reading.  Perhaps when they are considered by the Parliamentary Secretary he will be able to explain the difficulties which are in my mind.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MartinRoddy" hpid="Parliamentary Secretary to the Minister for Lands and Fisheries (Mr. Roddy) Parliamentary Secretary to the Minister for Lands and Fisheries (Mr. Roddy)">
      <NameTxt>Parliamentary Secretary to the Minister for Lands and Fisheries (Mr. Roddy)</NameTxt>
      <P>In reply to Senator Comyn, it is not anticipated that compulsory powers will be necessary for the purpose of Section 5 of this Bill.  It is not considered necessary to give the Land Commission compulsory powers for the purpose, especially in a matter which is really not one of its principal functions.  I only know one such case as Senator Comyn has referred to, and in that case the owner was quite willing to sell the ancillary rights to the Land Commission.  It is a very unlikely thing that such a case will arise again, and if it does, it will not arise for a very considerable time.  If the <Col N="1518" /> Land Commission find as a result of experience in dealing with the acquisition of fishing rights that it is necessary to obtain compulsory powers, they will have no hesitation in approaching the Oireachtas again for the requisite powers.</P>
      <P>Perhaps I should explain that these sections in this Bill relating to fishing rights were introduced for the purpose really of explaining a word&mdash;the word &ldquo;appurtenant&rdquo;&mdash; which was used in Section 45 of the Act of 1923.  That explanation was necessary because of a recent judicial decision.  According to that judicial decision the meaning of the word &ldquo;appurtenant&rdquo; was given quite a different meaning from that which the Minister intended when introducing the Act of 1923.  The decision was to the effect that a right appurtenant to a holding must mean in law some right in connection with the enjoyment of the holding and could not be extended to include a right of property which was separated therefrom and was not enjoyed by the tenant or necessary for the enjoyment of his holding. That decision, in fact, means that the word &ldquo;appurtenant&rdquo; should not have been used in the Act of 1923 or, if used, that it should have been interpreted in exactly the same way as Section 41 of the Act of 1927, which states quite definitely and explicitly that the Land Commission have power to acquire or purchase the fishing rights on any river or water adjoining the tenant's holding.  Hence these sections in this Bill are necessary in order to explain the meaning and to give the Land Commission the power which the Minister when introducing the Act of 1923 obviously intended the Land Commission should have.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelComynKC" hpid="Mr. Comyn Mr. Comyn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Comyn</NameTxt>
      <P>Is he going to sell the ancillary rights at a fair price?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MartinRoddy" hpid="Mr. Roddy Mr. Roddy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Roddy</NameTxt>
      <P>The question of price has not arisen at all yet.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. Johnson Mr. Johnson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Johnson</NameTxt>
      <P>I was hoping that someone more conversant with the law and practice of land purchase would have raised a question that <Col N="1519" /> was discussed in the Dáil as to the amount fixed in the Bill under Section 2 (1), which says that the standard purchase annuity in respect of Part II. of the First Schedule to the Land Act, 1923, shall be an annuity of an amount equivalent to 65 per cent. of the rent payable in respect of the holding, provided there is no appeal. The matter was discussed in the Dáil.  I have since read the debates and I am not satisfied that the Minister's defence for putting in these figures is satisfactory.  The evidence that has been presented shows that where cases have been laid before the Land Commission in recent years&mdash;the last two or three years&mdash; the average reduction fixed has been considerably more than the 35 per cent. which is indicated in the section. My information is that in the five years 1923-28 the average reduction fixed by the Land Commission has been 37 per cent., so that the equivalent in the Bill ought to be 63 per cent. instead of 65 per cent.  Last year the average has been almost 38 per cent.  So that the figure of 65 per cent. in the Bill seems to be too high in respect to the particular class of tenancy in question.  As it appears, from information placed in my possession that, in the main, these are the poorer tenants a lower figure than 65 per cent. should be fixed, and if there is a dispute, if there is a question involved, the initiative should be taken by the landlord in appealing to the Commissioners and not by the tenant.  I am stating the case, as I say, without very much knowledge or experience of the processes, but I have read the debates and I am not at all satisfied that the Parliamentary Secretary's case is a strong one, or that he has a right in the Bill to fix 65 as against the proposal of 60, which was the amendment of Deputy Derrig, or of 62½ per cent., which was suggested in the public Press.  Unless the Parliamentary Secretary is able to produce very much more definite evidence I think the House should have an opportunity of deciding whether 65 <Col N="1520" /> should remain, or whether it should be replaced by 60.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MartinRoddy" hpid="Mr. Roddy Mr. Roddy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Roddy</NameTxt>
      <P>It is not quite accurate to say, as Senator Johnson has said, that the average is lower than 35 per cent.  The average figure is actually 35.1 per cent.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. Johnson Mr. Johnson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Johnson</NameTxt>
      <P>Over what period?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MartinRoddy" hpid="Mr. Roddy Mr. Roddy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Roddy</NameTxt>
      <P>That is the average figure for the cases already fixed.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. Johnson Mr. Johnson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Johnson</NameTxt>
      <P>That included voluntary agreements.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MartinRoddy" hpid="Mr. Roddy Mr. Roddy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Roddy</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes, that would include voluntary agreements.  You must get an average figure, and if you are to get an average figure you must take cases where the figure was fixed by agreement between owners and tenants as well as cases where the figure was fixed by the Land Commission.  That is the only way I know of getting an average.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardWilson" hpid="Mr. Wilson Mr. Wilson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Wilson</NameTxt>
      <P>What has been the average in the case in which disputes have arisen and in which the figure was fixed by the Land Commission apart from agreement between the parties?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MartinRoddy" hpid="Mr. Roddy Mr. Roddy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Roddy</NameTxt>
      <P>Annuities were fixed in 12,500 cases.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardWilson" hpid="Mr. Wilson Mr. Wilson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Wilson</NameTxt>
      <P>By the Land Commission?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MartinRoddy" hpid="Mr. Roddy Mr. Roddy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Roddy</NameTxt>
      <P>No.  In 9,000 cases the annuities were fixed by agreement and in 3,500 by the Land Commission.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardWilson" hpid="Mr. Wilson Mr. Wilson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Wilson</NameTxt>
      <P>What was the average in the 3,500 case?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MartinRoddy" hpid="Mr. Roddy Mr. Roddy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Roddy</NameTxt>
      <P>Up to the 31st March this year the average standard purchase annuities where the figure was agreed upon between the owners and the tenants was 33.4 and the average fixed by the Land Commission was 37.9.  That was up to the 31st March this year.  I want to point out to Senators that the average figure fluctuates a good deal.  The possibility is that at the <Col N="1521" /> end of this year the figure may be considerably lower.  Since we began to fix the standard figure the average has varied as between 33 and 35 per cent.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. Johnson Mr. Johnson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Johnson</NameTxt>
      <P>What was the average per year for each of the five years?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MartinRoddy" hpid="Mr. Roddy Mr. Roddy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Roddy</NameTxt>
      <P>The average per year was something like 34 per cent.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. Johnson Mr. Johnson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Johnson</NameTxt>
      <P>How did the Parliamentary Secretary arrive at 37.9 for five years?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Cathaoirleach Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>The Senator must allow the Parliamentary Secretary to proceed with his statement.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MartinRoddy" hpid="Mr. Roddy Mr. Roddy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Roddy</NameTxt>
      <P>The average, as a matter of fact, in cases fixed by the Land Commission increased somewhat during the first three months of this year, but, as I say, that average figure fluctuates, and probably at the end of the next six months it may be lower than 35.  But at all events the average has never exceeded 35.  If you are to arrive at an average you must be guided by experience gained in fixing the standard annuity in respect of cases already dealt with.  If you look at the figures under the Land Act of 1903 and 1909 you will find that the average figure is higher under the 1903 Act and the 1909 Act than those I have given.  I find that under the 1903 Act the average for non-judicial tenants was 33.7 and under the 1909 Act 35.9, or the average in respect of both was 33.7.  Even taking into consideration those figures under the 1903 Act and the 1909 Act, those which we mentioned here in this Bill must be regarded as a fair average.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamCummins" hpid="Mr. Cummins Mr. Cummins">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cummins</NameTxt>
      <P>Is it not a fact that but for the inclusion of voluntary agreements when arriving at the average that average would be lower?  These were poor men rushed into agreements which they say were inequitable.  Voluntary agreements were entered into in <Col N="1522" /> order to save the time and trouble of vesting and all the costs of these arrangements.  Those who entered into the voluntary agreements now find that they were not equitable. They were the poorer farmers, farming only about 24 acres of land. They formed the great bulk of the agreements, which means that the average reduction is considerably lower than it ought to be.  The first and second term judicial tenants have much better bargains, and these non-judicial tenants should not be put on the same footing as first and second term tenants, and it is very strongly urged that these people should not be asked to pay 65 per cent. of their rent just the same as their very much better-placed neighbours.  They complain that that is not just. and that these voluntary agreements should not be reckoned in the average.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardWilson" hpid="Mr. Wilson Mr. Wilson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Wilson</NameTxt>
      <P>I should like to say &mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Cathaoirleach Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>The Senator has spoken already.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardWilson" hpid="Mr. Wilson Mr. Wilson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Wilson</NameTxt>
      <P>No.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Cathaoirleach Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes, the Senator has already intervened.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardWilson" hpid="Mr. Wilson Mr. Wilson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Wilson</NameTxt>
      <P>I only made an interjection.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Cathaoirleach Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I shall allow the Senator to speak on this occasion, but he must not speak twice on Second Reading motion.  An interjection is a speech.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardWilson" hpid="Mr. Wilson Mr. Wilson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Wilson</NameTxt>
      <P>The question of the amount of the annuities should be fixed in the Bill, and I contend that 65 per cent. is too high a figure and that the figure should be 60 or 62½.  The Parliamentary Secretary takes the figures under the Land Acts of 1903 and 1909, but these Acts were passed in the British Parliament and there was no force in the British Parliament to secure conditions of fair play that there are in this Parliament where the farmers of the country and the people generally are directly represented. They should get better conditions here than could possibly be obtained in an assembly of over 600 <Col N="1523" /> persons in the British Parliament where the farmers' interests were practically nil.  That is a point of view that has been neglected.  If they were able to get reductions of 25 or 32 per cent. from the British Parliament why should they not get 40 per cent. here?  I settled several cases of non-judicial tenancies and I never accepted less than 40 per cent. or 8/- in the £1.  The Minister should have agreed to the figure 60 or 62½ per cent. in the Bill.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MartinRoddy" hpid="Mr. Roddy Mr. Roddy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Roddy</NameTxt>
      <P>I should like to remind Senator Wilson that even if the Acts of 1903 and 1909 were passed by the British Parliament, the British Parliament had nothing to do with the fixing of the price. In the majority of cases here the prices are fixed by agreement between the landlords and the owners.  If any tenant is not satisfied with the annuity of 65 per cent. he has a right to object and the Land Commission will fix the annuity.  We have made provision in such cases. Even assuming that the tenants are charged exorbitant rent, and assuming that everything that Senator Cummins said is true, they, at any rate, have the right to come into court and have their annuities fixed by the Land Commission.  As a matter of fact, we had these cases in view when we said they should have the right to object to the automatic arrangement.  Under this section either the tenant or the landlord shall have the right to object. Senators can rest assured that all such cases are covered and they will also realise from the cases fixed by the Land Commission the tenants have been exceptionally well treated so far.</P>
      <P>Question&mdash;&ldquo;That the Bill be now read a Second Time&rdquo;&mdash;put and agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMilroy" hpid="Mr. Milroy Mr. Milroy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Milroy</NameTxt>
      <P>I move: &ldquo;That the Standing Orders be suspended for the purpose of taking the remaining stages of the Land Bill, 1929, to-day.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1524" />
    <Speaker pid="SamuelBrownKC" hpid="Mr. Brown Mr. Brown">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Brown</NameTxt>
      <P>I second the motion.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. Johnson Mr. Johnson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Johnson</NameTxt>
      <P>I oppose this motion because I think it is quite unnecessary. There must be some discussion upon the question raised on the Second Reading and there must be an amendment put forward in respect of the figures in the Bill. As the House is to meet to-morrow there is no necessity for taking the remaining stages of this Bill to-day. I should be quite willing as soon as the Committee Stage is passed to allow the remaining stages to be taken, but I think they should not be taken to-night.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMilroy" hpid="Mr. Milroy Mr. Milroy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Milroy</NameTxt>
      <P>If Senator Johnson, as I gather, proposes to table an amendment, then undoubtedly we must give him time to do so.  I do not think it would be fair in the circumstances to press this motion if that is his intention.</P>
      <P>Motion, by leave, postponed.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Public Business. - Trade Loans (Guarantee)" RHead="(Amendment) Bill, 1929&mdash;Second Stage">
    <Title>Public Business. - Trade Loans (Guarantee) (Amendment) Bill, 1929&mdash;Second Stage.</Title>
    <P>Question&mdash;&ldquo;That the Bill be read a Second Time&rdquo;&mdash;put and agreed to.</P>
    <Speaker pid="SamuelBrownKC" hpid="Mr. Brown Mr. Brown">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Brown</NameTxt>
      <P>I move: &ldquo;That the Standing Orders be suspended for the purpose of taking the remaining stages of the Trade Loans (Guarantee) (Amendment) Bill, 1929, to-day.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelFanning" hpid="Mr. Fanning Mr. Fanning">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Fanning</NameTxt>
      <P>I second.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. Johnson Mr. Johnson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Johnson</NameTxt>
      <P>Surely it is due to the Seanad that some explanation should be given, or that some justification should be given for this Bill? It asks us to extend the period of the operation of this Act, which has been extended one time and another already.  The last information that I read about the matter, apart from what I saw in the newspapers, was that the Minister was in favour of bringing the operations of this Act to an end.  It is due to the Seanad, before we are asked to extend the period of its operations, that some <Col N="1525" /> explanation should be given, and I think it is quite wrong not only to ask the Seanad to agree to a Second Reading, but to take up all the stages of the Bill without further explanation. I protest against that course.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMilroy" hpid="Mr. Milroy Mr. Milroy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Milroy</NameTxt>
      <P>I am sure that there are grounds for Senator Johnson's remarks.  I was informed before this matter was reached that the Minister was unavoidably absent, and I was asked to suggest to the House what were the reasons for this Bill and the more or less urgency for the passing of the Bill now.  I do not intend to say more than a word or two.  It is due entirely to the fact that certain applications, not necessarily new applications, but old applications have been revived the consideration of which will necessitate legislation.  The Minister in the Dáil, speaking on the Second Reading of this Bill, said: &ldquo;I announced on the Vote for my own Estimate that in my view the Trade Loans (Guarantee) Acts had seemed to have outlived their utility.  I based that view on the fact that no new applications were coming forward. I stated that had new applications come forward, or were likely to come forward, we would have brought in the usual legislation. Since I spoke three applications, amounting to a sum of £4,000, which had been approved by the two Ministers concerned, but were waiting completion of official formalities, have taken on new life.  It looked at one time as if one was going to be withdrawn, and we were told that it was very doubtful if the second one would be proceeded with.  The third was in a peculiar position.  We have now been informed that two are likely to be proceeded with.  In addition, there was a very old application which had been received by the Advisory Committee and reported on favourably, but it had not at that time been accepted by me.&rdquo; As far as I understand it that Act expires every year and this Bill is to re-enact the Principal Act.  I think this is a sufficient illustration of the outlook of the Minister with <Col N="1526" /> regard to these cases for which new legislation would be necessary. Such legislation is embodied in this Bill, and these are the reasons why the Minister has introduced it.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>Bill passed through Committee without amendment, reported, received for final consideration and passed.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Public Business. - Children" RHead="Bill, 1928&mdash;Second Stage">
    <Title>Public Business. - Children Bill, 1928&mdash;Second Stage.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Cathaoirleach Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>This is a Private Senator's Bill.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SamuelBrownKC" hpid="Mr. Brown Mr. Brown">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Brown</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes.  It is a Bill which originated in this House.  It was introduced by Senator Brady when he was a member of the House, and it was backed by Senator Hooper and myself.  It passed through this House and went to the Dáil, where an amendment was introduced. Owing to the peculiar nature of a certain Article of the Constitution when a Bill initiated in the Seanad goes to the Dáil and comes back here amended it has to be treated as if it originated in the Dáil, and hence it is sent here again for a Second Reading, though it has already passed this House.  The object of the Bill is to remove a blot from the existing Children Act of 1908.  Under that Act the position of a destitute child whose parents or whose surviving parent were not in a position to support him or her was that in order to be sent to an industrial school it had first to be convicted of begging.  Now, that was highly objectionable.  It started the child in its career as a criminal.  The object of this Bill was to remove that blot from the Act of 1908.  That was done by this Bill as it left this House.  It went to the Dáil.  In the Dáil the Government would not accept any responsibility for it.  The Minister for Education, speaking on behalf of the Government, said they would not object to it provided an amendment was inserted in the Dáil requiring the consent of the parent or parents.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1527" />
    <Speaker pid="JanePower" hpid="Mrs. Wyse Power Mrs. Wyse Power">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Wyse Power</NameTxt>
      <P>That was the blot on the Bill as it left here.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SamuelBrownKC" hpid="Mr. Brown Mr. Brown">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Brown</NameTxt>
      <P>I think an amendment of that nature was suggested by Senator Mrs. Wyse Power.  That is the only change that has been made in the Bill since it left this House.  I need scarcely say that so far as we are concerned, having first introduced the Bill, we are perfectly satisfied to have that amendment inserted. I now move the Second Reading of the Bill.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JanePower" hpid="Mrs. Wyse Power Mrs. Wyse Power">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Wyse Power</NameTxt>
      <P>I am satisfied with the Bill as it comes from the Dáil.  It not only gives what we were looking for, but it gives a guarantee that the parent can get the child out when required.  This Bill can never be called a Brady Bill.  It is a different Bill altogether.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasEsmondeBart" hpid="Sir Thomas Esmonde Sir Thomas Esmonde">
      <NameTxt>Sir Thomas Esmonde</NameTxt>
      <P>This is a most admirable Bill and one which we are all supporting.  As Senator Mrs. Wyse Power has stated, it has been greatly improved in the Dáil. I would like to enter a protest against the ridiculous proceeding of having to go over all the stages of the Bill again in this House, although we have already passed it. I think the Standing Orders should be amended in that respect so that we shall not have the same trouble again.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SamuelBrownKC" hpid="Mr. Brown Mr. Brown">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Brown</NameTxt>
      <P>The position is not due to our Standing Orders.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasEsmondeBart" hpid="Sir Thomas Esmonde Sir Thomas Esmonde">
      <NameTxt>Sir Thomas Esmonde</NameTxt>
      <P>It can be done by a suggestion from the Seanad and there is no earthly reason why the present conditions should continue to exist.  We can do it in consultation with the Dáil. There is no earthly reason why we should be the only Legislature in the world where all the stages of a Bill have to be gone through twice when we have already agreed to the measure.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Cathaoirleach Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>This procedure is <Col N="1528" /> governed by the Constitution, and if you prefer to amend the Constitution, well and good.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasEsmondeBart" hpid="Sir Thomas Esmonde Sir Thomas Esmonde">
      <NameTxt>Sir Thomas Esmonde</NameTxt>
      <P>It has been amended in a great many particulars and we might amend it in this instance if it is necessary.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. Johnson Mr. Johnson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Johnson</NameTxt>
      <P>I wish to call attention to another anomaly in this connection. The Bill comes to us from the Dáil, where it was passed unanimously, and yet the Minister who spoke to the Bill, and the chief opposition, speaking in relation to the Bill, declared that they accepted no responsibility for it.  It comes to us as a Bill from the Dáil for which nobody there is responsible, either the Government or the Opposition! They will have nothing to do with the child, but they will leave it to the Seanad.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SamuelBrownKC" hpid="Mr. Brown Mr. Brown">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Brown</NameTxt>
      <P>Is it not well there is a Seanad?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JosephOConnor" hpid="Mr. O'Connor Mr. O'Connor">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Connor</NameTxt>
      <P>I wish to support this Bill.  We paid a very high compliment to Senator Brady when he introduced the Bill here.  It was passed with the approval of every member of this House, because it took up the case of the defenceless children, who are not responsible for the position they are placed in. We are now in a position to bring a good Bill to fruition.  It is a measure that received a good deal of earnest consideration here.  It had the approval of everybody and we are glad to see it now approaching the Final Stages.</P>
      <P>Question&mdash;&ldquo;That the Bill be now read a Second Time&rdquo;&mdash;put and agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SamuelBrownKC" hpid="Mr. Brown Mr. Brown">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Brown</NameTxt>
      <P>I move: &ldquo;That the Standing Orders be suspended for the purpose of taking the remaining stages of the Children Bill, 1928, to-day.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelFanning" hpid="Mr. Fanning Mr. Fanning">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Fanning</NameTxt>
      <P>I second that proposal.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="1529" /> Question put and agreed to.</P>
    <P>Bill passed through Committee without amendment, reported, received for final consideration, and passed.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Public Business. - Cobh" RHead="(Queenstown) Gas Order, 1929">
    <Title>Public Business. - Cobh (Queenstown) Gas Order, 1929.</Title>
    <P>Debate resumed on the following motion:&mdash;</P>
    <P>&ldquo;That the Cobh (Queenstown) Gas Order, 1929, proposed to be made by the Minister for Industry and Commerce and laid in draft before the Seanad on the 5th day of July, 1929, under sub-section (4) of Section 10 of the Gas Regulation Act, 1920, be approved.&rdquo;&mdash;(Senator Milroy.)</P>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMilroy" hpid="Mr. Milroy Mr. Milroy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Milroy</NameTxt>
      <P>On the last occasion when this was raised Senator Johnson objected to the matter being dealt with without allowing opportunity for discussion.  I probably was at fault, because when formally proposing the motion I should have given some outline of the purpose of this Order.  This motion is asking the Seanad to approve of an Order dealing with the Cobh (Queenstown) Gas Company.  That order tends to authorise the reconstruction of the existing capital and the raising of additional capital.  This Gas Company has operated under a private Act passed in 1879.  The capital of the Company and its borrowing powers were defined by that Act and by The Capital Issues Consent Order of 1921.  The financial powers were confined to the issue of shares to the amount of £25,000 and the borrowing of an additional sum of £12,500. The Company, it appears, has been hampered in its development by the financial restrictions which limited its operations.  Accordingly it is proposed to make an order in the form which has lain on the Tables of the Oireachtas for a considerable time.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>It is proposed to revise the financial powers within the following limits: (a) to convert the existing shares into £20,500 Consolidated Stock; (b) to create and issue additional <Col N="1530" /> stock from time to time as required up to the maximum amount of £25,000; (c) to raise by borrowing for special purposes up to an amount not exceeding one-half the value of the paid-up stock.  The opportunity has been taken to include in the Order a number of general provisions which appear in practically all modern private Acts and Orders for the purpose of defining the powers of and the obligations of the Company. The prices chargeable by the Company for gas supplied are required by the Order to be those prescribed for the time being by the Minister for Industry and Commerce under the provisions of Section 1 of the Gas Regulation Act, 1920.</P>
    <P>That is an outline of the purpose of the Order.  The necessity for this being approved before the Oireachtas adjourns is that the appointed day on which this Order comes into effect is as near as the 20th September next.  If the Oireachtas adjourns for the Recess it will not reassemble until after that date, and it is therefore important that the Seanad, before it adjourns, should give its approval to this Order, if it is to be approved at all.  For that reason I am moving the motion I have tabled.</P>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. Johnson Mr. Johnson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Johnson</NameTxt>
      <P>I have pleasure in seconding it.  I would like to say one word, and that is, that it gives me satisfaction to know that in the Order there is an obligation put upon the Company that it shall not charge to small consumers&mdash;that is, the users of prepaid meters&mdash;a higher price per therm unit than is charged to the ordinary users.  Now that is a provision very useful and valuable, and I thank the Minister for having inserted it in the Order.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Public Business." RHead="- Friday Sitting">
    <Title>Public Business. - Friday Sitting.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMilroy" hpid="Mr. Milroy Mr. Milroy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Milroy</NameTxt>
      <P>I move that Standing Order 11 be suspended for the purpose of enabling the House to sit at 12 noon to-morrow.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="AlfredByrne" hpid="Mr. Byrne Mr. Byrne">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Byrne</NameTxt>
      <P>I second that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="1531" /> Question put and agreed to.</P>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMilroy" hpid="Mr. Milroy Mr. Milroy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Milroy</NameTxt>
      <P>Would it be possible if we could know now at what time the House will adjourn to-morrow?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1532" />
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Cathaoirleach Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>We will not be sitting for a very long time.</P>
      <P>The Seanad adjourned at 8 o'clock.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
</Debate>