<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE Debate SYSTEM "../Debate.dtd"[]>
<Debate DocTitle="D&aacute;il Debate" Day="Fri" Date="22" Month="Mar" Year="1991" Vol="406" No="9" DateIrish="Dé hAoine, 22 Márta 1991" DateEnglish="Friday, 22 March 1991" House="D" CommitteeEng="" CommitteeIr="" SubNameEng="" cnum="0">
  <MainHeading Type="Prelude" LHead="" RHead="">
    <Title>
    </Title>
    <P>
      <Col N="2061" /> Chuaigh an Ceann Comhairle i gceannas ar 10.30 a.m.</P>
    <P Just="Center">
      <i>Paidir.</i>
    </P>
    <P Just="Center">
      <i>Prayer.</i>
    </P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Order of" RHead="Business">
    <Title>Order of Business.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="CharlesJHaughey" hpid="The Taoiseach Charles J. Haughey">
      <NameTxt>The Taoiseach</NameTxt>
      <P>It is proposed to take Nos. 11 and 12.  It is also proposed, subject to the agreement of the House that (1) the proceedings on the Report and Final Stages of Nos. 11 and 12, if not previously concluded, shall be brought to a conclusion at 2.30 p.m. and 4 p.m., respectively, by one question in each case which shall be put from the Chair and which shall, in relation to amendments, include only amendments set down by the member of the Government in charge of the Bill; (2) the Dáil at its rising today, shall adjourn until 10.30 a.m. on Wednesday, 17 April 1991.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanTreacy" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Seán Treacy">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>In respect of item No. 1, are the proposals for dealing with items Nos. 11 and 12 agreed?  Agreed. Is the proposal that the Dáil adjourn until 10.30 a.m. on Wednesday, 17 April agreed?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="2062" />
    <Speaker pid="DickSpring" hpid="Mr. Spring Mr. Spring">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Spring</NameTxt>
      <P>On the proposal that the Dáil adjourn until 10.30 a.m. on 17 April, let me say that we are closing a session which has not been spectacular in terms of legislation.  The House needs more time to consider legislation.  I suggest that the Dáil should reconvene on Tuesday, 9 April, to give us more time to consider legislation, particularly as we are still waiting for the Roads Authority Bill, the Environmental Protection Agency Bill has not been brought before this House and we are expecting legislation on local government reform.  Sir, I ask that the Taoiseach reconvene the House on Tuesday, 9 April.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="CharlesJHaughey" hpid="The Taoiseach Charles J. Haughey">
      <NameTxt>The Taoiseach</NameTxt>
      <P>We have had a long and tough session since January, we are facing into an equally long and tough session until the summer recess, and I think this Easter break is very reasonable in all the circumstances.  Without being in any way hypocritical about the matter, I must say I am looking forward to it and I am sure every Deputy in the House is too.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Deputies Deputies">
      <NameTxt>Deputies</NameTxt>
      <P>Hear, hear.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnBruton" hpid="Mr. J. Bruton Mr. J. Bruton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J. Bruton</NameTxt>
      <P>I would be willing to accept this recess if the Government had established the committees they had promised, namely, the foreign affairs and crime committees, which would allow the House to do its work during the recess. In view of the fact that the Government have not established a proper committee system, which can process work more quickly, I believe the House has no option but to support Deputy Spring's proposition that the House resumes its activities earlier.</P>
      <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That the date proposed to be deleted stand.&rdquo;</P>
      <P Just="Center">The Dáil divided: Tá, 64; Níl, 51.</P>
      <P Just="Center">Tá</P>
    </Speaker>
    <table pgwide="1">
      <tgroup cols="2">
        <colspec colname="1" colnum="1" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <colspec colname="2" colnum="2" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry rowsep="1">Ahern, Bertie.<br />Ahern, Dermot.<br />Ahern, Michael.
<Col N="2063" />Brennan, Mattie.<br />Brennan, Séamus.<br />Browne, John (Wexford).<br />Burke, Raphael P.<br />Callely, Ivor.<br />Clohessy, Peadar.<br />Connolly, Ger.<br />Coughlan, Mary Theresa.<br />Cowen, Brian.<br />Cullimore, Séamus.<br />Daly, Brendan.<br />Davern, Noel.<br />Dempsey, Noel.<br />Dennehy, John.<br />Fahey, Frank.<br />Fahey, Jackie.<br />Flood, Chris.<br />Gallagher, Pat the Cope.<br />Geoghegan-Quinn, Máire.<br />Haughey, Charles J.<br />Hillery, Brian.<br />Hilliard, Colm.<br />Hyland, Liam.<br />Jacob, Joe.<br />Kelly, Laurence.<br />Kenneally, Brendan.<br />Kirk, Séamus.<br />Kitt, Michael P.<br />Kitt, Tom.</entry>
            <entry rowsep="1">Barrett, Michael.<br />Brady, Gerard.<br />Brady, Vincent.
<Col N="2064" />Lenihan, Brian.<br />Leonard, Jimmy.<br />Leyden, Terry.<br />Lyons, Denis.<br />Martin, Micheál.<br />McCreevy, Charlie.<br />McDaid, Jim.<br />McEllistrim, Tom.<br />Molloy, Robert.<br />Nolan, M.J.<br />O'Connell, John.<br />O'Dea, Willie.<br />O'Donoghue, John.<br />O'Hanlon, Rory.<br />O'Keeffe, Ned.<br />O'Leary, John.<br />O'Rourke, Mary.<br />O'Toole, Martin Joe.<br />Power, Seán.<br />Quill, Máirín.<br />Roche, Dick.<br />Smith, Michael.<br />Treacy, Noel.<br />Tunney, Jim.<br />Wallace, Dan.<br />Wallace, Mary.<br />Walsh, Joe.<br />Woods, Michael.<br />Wyse, Pearse.</entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
    <P Just="Center">Níl</P>
    <table pgwide="1">
      <tgroup cols="2">
        <colspec colname="1" colnum="1" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <colspec colname="2" colnum="2" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry rowsep="1">Allen, Bernard.<br />Belton, Louis J.<br />Boylan, Andrew.<br />Browne, John (Carlow-Kilkenny).<br />Bruton, John.<br />Byrne, Eric.<br />Connaughton, Paul.<br />Cosgrave, Michael Joe.<br />Creed, Michael.<br />Currie, Austin.<br />D'Arcy, Michael.<br />Deasy, Austin.<br />Doyle, Joe.<br />Dukes, Alan.<br />Durkan, Bernard.<br />Farrelly, John V.<br />Fennell, Nuala.<br />Ferris, Michael.<br />Flaherty, Mary.<br />Flanagan, Charles.<br />Foxe, Tom.<br />Gilmore, Eamon.<br />Gregory, Tony.<br />Higgins, Michael D.<br />Hogan, Philip.<br />Howlin, Brendan.</entry>
            <entry rowsep="1">Kavanagh, Liam.<br />Kemmy, Jim.<br />Lowry, Michael.<br />McCormack, Pádraic.<br />McGahon, Brendan.<br />McGinley, Dinny.<br />Mac Giolla, Tomás.<br />McGrath, Paul.<br />Mitchell, Gay.<br />Moynihan, Michael.<br />Nealon, Ted.<br />Noonan, Michael. (Limerick East).<br />O'Brien, Fergus.<br />O'Shea, Brian.<br />O'Sullivan, Gerry.<br />Owen, Nora.<br />Quinn, Ruairí.<br />Rabbitte, Pat.<br />Ryan, Seán.<br />Sheehan, Patrick J.<br />Sherlock, Joe.<br />Spring, Dick.<br />Stagg, Emmet.<br />Timmins, Godfrey.<br />Yates, Ivan.</entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
    <P Just="Center">Tellers: Tá, Deputies V. Brady and Clohessy; Níl, Deputies Howlin and Flanagan.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="2065" /> Question declared carried.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JohnBruton" hpid="Mr. J. Bruton Mr. J. Bruton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J. Bruton</NameTxt>
      <P>May I ask the Taoiseach if the Government will provide time today for the Minister for Finance to make a statement on the consequences of the now admitted Government's illegal act in continuing to confiscate goods under the 48 hour rule, after that rule had been struck down as illegal in the European Court, especially in view of the fact that the Government are responsible for enforcing the law and should not be seen to be breaking it?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanTreacy" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Seán Treacy">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>The matter to which the Deputy refers is hardly related to the Order of Business.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnBruton" hpid="Mr. J. Bruton Mr. J. Bruton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J. Bruton</NameTxt>
      <P>Sir, on a point of order, would the House not agree that this House is responsible for making the law and the Government are responsible for respecting and enforcing it and that if the Government are breaking the law that brings this House and its activities into disrepute?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanTreacy" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Seán Treacy">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>There are procedures for dealing with such matters, let us conform to them.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DickSpring" hpid="Mr. Spring Mr. Spring">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Spring</NameTxt>
      <P>May I seek some clarification from the Taoiseach and, perhaps, from the Minister for Tourism, Transport and Communications?  Over the last number of weeks this House has been informed that the Minister has requested NESC to report to him in relation to the threatened closure of 550 rural sub-post offices and the loss of 1,500 jobs.  We are now informed publicly that NESC will not carry out this report.  I would ask the Minister for Tourism, Transport and Communications if he does not feel it is incumbent on him to come into this House and clarify the situation.</P>
      <P>As late as Wednesday the Minister informed the House that NESC had been requested to carry out this report.  It is now public knowledge that NESC will not, in fact, carry out this report.  I would ask the Taoiseach&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="2066" />
    <Speaker pid="SeanTreacy" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Seán Treacy">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>I allowed Deputy Spring some latitude in order that he might develop a point which I thought might be relevant to the Order of Business, but clearly it is not.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DickSpring" hpid="Mr. Spring Mr. Spring">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Spring</NameTxt>
      <P>This is very relevant to this country and also to the 1,500 people who will lose their jobs.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanTreacy" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Seán Treacy">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>That may be so.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DickSpring" hpid="Mr. Spring Mr. Spring">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Spring</NameTxt>
      <P>I would ask the Taoiseach to allow his Minister an opportunity to correct the record of this House and to do so before 4 p.m. this afternoon.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BrendanHowlin" hpid="Mr. Howlin Mr. Howlin">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Howlin</NameTxt>
      <P>A Cheann Comhairle&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="AustinCurrie" hpid="Mr. Currie Mr. Currie">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Currie</NameTxt>
      <P>Will the Taoiseach give&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanTreacy" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Seán Treacy">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>The Chair will not compel any Member of this House to speak.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="AustinCurrie" hpid="Mr. Currie Mr. Currie">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Currie</NameTxt>
      <P>&mdash;&mdash;the Minister an opportunity to apologise for deliberately misleading this House by being economical with the truth and to defer making a decision until after the local government elections?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanTreacy" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Seán Treacy">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>Deputy Currie, a Member of this House should not state that another Member deliberately misled the House.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="AustinCurrie" hpid="Mr. Currie Mr. Currie">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Currie</NameTxt>
      <P>There is no other way of doing it.</P>
      <P>
        <i>(Interruptions.)</i>
      </P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanTreacy" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Seán Treacy">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>It is not in order and all my predecessors have said so.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DickSpring" hpid="Mr. Spring Mr. Spring">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Spring</NameTxt>
      <P>I am merely seeking that the Minister for Tourism, Transport and Communications should have the opportunity to come into this House before we adjourn this afternoon to clarify the situation.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="2067" />
    <Speaker pid="SeanTreacy" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Seán Treacy">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>Deputy Spring has made his point.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DickSpring" hpid="Mr. Spring Mr. Spring">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Spring</NameTxt>
      <P>That is a very reasonable request.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EricJByrne" hpid="Mr. Byrne Mr. Byrne">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Byrne</NameTxt>
      <P>In the light of the plans to bring before the House the bus competition Bill, can the Taoiseach or the Minister for Tourism, Transport and Communications use their good offices, in the interests of the travelling public, to attempt to unravel the chaotic industrial relations prevailing in CIE at present where there are three different disputes running simultaneously?  It is imperative that the Minister for Tourism, Transport and Communications discuss the situation with his colleague, the Minister for Labour, to unravel the very complex difficulties&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanTreacy" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Seán Treacy">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>Please, Deputy Byrne, I thought the Deputy was raising something relevant.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EricJByrne" hpid="Mr. Byrne Mr. Byrne">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Byrne</NameTxt>
      <P>&mdash;&mdash;in the context of a planned bus competition Bill coming before this House.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanTreacy" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Seán Treacy">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>Deputy Farrelly is offering.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnVFarrelly" hpid="Mr. Farrelly Mr. Farrelly">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Farrelly</NameTxt>
      <P>May I ask the Taoiseach if the Government have any intention of introducing legislation to privatise the driver testing section of the Department of the Environment, taking into consideration that there are 62,000 applicants on the waiting list?  All those applicants who have provisional driving licences are paying between £300 and £500 extra&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanTreacy" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Seán Treacy">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>Deputy Farrelly, a question would clarify the matter.  I am calling Deputy Ryan.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnVFarrelly" hpid="Mr. Farrelly Mr. Farrelly">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Farrelly</NameTxt>
      <P>May I ask the Taoiseach if he would introduce legislation on this matter?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanTreacy" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Seán Treacy">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>I take it there is no legislation promised in this area.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="2068" />
    <Speaker pid="SeanRyan" hpid="Mr. Ryan Mr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>May I ask the Taoiseach when the Government propose to bring before this House the promised mental health legislation?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanTreacy" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Seán Treacy">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>Is this promised legislation?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanRyan" hpid="Mr. Ryan Mr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>It is indeed.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="CharlesJHaughey" hpid="The Taoiseach Charles J. Haughey">
      <NameTxt>The Taoiseach</NameTxt>
      <P>I am not sure that any specific legislation has been promised but it will not be before the summer recess.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanRyan" hpid="Mr. Ryan Mr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>Will there be a White Paper on the matter?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RuairiQuinn" hpid="Mr. Quinn Mr. Quinn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Quinn</NameTxt>
      <P>I understand that the order was made yesterday for the Second Stage of the Finance Bill.  May I ask the Taoiseach when that document will be circulated to Members?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="CharlesJHaughey" hpid="The Taoiseach Charles J. Haughey">
      <NameTxt>The Taoiseach</NameTxt>
      <P>On 17 April.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RuairiQuinn" hpid="Mr. Quinn Mr. Quinn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Quinn</NameTxt>
      <P>In view of the fact that the order has been made, is it not possible that it could be circulated sooner to facilitate a more enlightened debate?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="CharlesJHaughey" hpid="The Taoiseach Charles J. Haughey">
      <NameTxt>The Taoiseach</NameTxt>
      <P>I am quite certain the debate will be very enlightened.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BrendanHowlin" hpid="Mr. Howlin Mr. Howlin">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Howlin</NameTxt>
      <P>That is the extent of the U-turns?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="CharlesJHaughey" hpid="The Taoiseach Charles J. Haughey">
      <NameTxt>The Taoiseach</NameTxt>
      <P>If it can be brought forward before that date I will try to ensure that&mdash;but, my information is that it will not be ready before 17 April.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelNoonan" hpid="Mr. Noonan (Limerick East) Mr. Noonan (Limerick East)">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Noonan</NameTxt>
      <P>
        <i>(Limerick East):</i> May I ask the Taoiseach if the Finance Bill will make provision for a rebate of the VAT deducted illegally by the Government by the misapplication of the 48 hour rule? Does the Taoiseach intend&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanTreacy" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Seán Treacy">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>We should await the debate on the Bill.  It is not in order now.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelNoonan" hpid="Mr. Noonan (Limerick East) Mr. Noonan (Limerick East)">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Noonan</NameTxt>
      <P>
        <i>(Limerick East):</i>&mdash;&mdash; to bring in a Supplementary Estimate to <Col N="2069" /> make provision for the rebate of VAT which was deducted illegally by the Government's misapplication of the 48 hour rule?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanTreacy" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Seán Treacy">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>I have already ruled on that matter.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BernardAllen" hpid="Mr. Allen Mr. Allen">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Allen</NameTxt>
      <P>Would you please investigate for me the fact that access to this House is being denied to Members at present by a petty rule and that Members' duties are being impeded by our being classified as security risks at one of the back gates of this House?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="CharlesJHaughey" hpid="The Taoiseach Charles J. Haughey">
      <NameTxt>The Taoiseach</NameTxt>
      <P>That is entirely appropriate.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PJSheenan" hpid="Mr. Sheehan Mr. Sheehan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Sheehan</NameTxt>
      <P>Are you afraid there would be some leaked documents?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanTreacy" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Seán Treacy">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>I would have much preferred had the Deputy brought this matter to my notice.  Had he done so I would now be in a position to give him a considered reply.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BernardAllen" hpid="Mr. Allen Mr. Allen">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Allen</NameTxt>
      <P>I did not raise the matter because&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanTreacy" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Seán Treacy">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>Nevertheless, I shall have the matter investigated.  There are too many Deputies offering.  I am going on to the Order of Business soon.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PaulConnaughton" hpid="Mr. Connaughton Mr. Connaughton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Connaughton</NameTxt>
      <P>May I ask the Taoiseach when the Minister for the Environment will announce the results of a nationwide survey on water quality?  I understand it is in the Department but it appears he is afraid to make it public because of the bad results.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanTreacy" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Seán Treacy">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>That matter clearly does not arise now.  I am calling Deputy McCormack.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PaulConnaughton" hpid="Mr. Connaughton Mr. Connaughton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Connaughton</NameTxt>
      <P>It is very difficult to see the Minister for the Environment these days.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnVFarrelly" hpid="Mr. Farrelly Mr. Farrelly">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Farrelly</NameTxt>
      <P>He is in a pothole.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="2070" />
    <Speaker pid="SeanTreacy" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Seán Treacy">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>Deputy McCormack, I shall not call you a third time.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PadraicMcCormack" hpid="Mr. McCormack Mr. McCormack">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McCormack</NameTxt>
      <P>May I ask the Taoiseach when the Committee Stage of the Fisheries (Amendment) Bill, 1990, will be continued?  Will we have to go through another tourist season without this matter being resolved?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="CharlesJHaughey" hpid="The Taoiseach Charles J. Haughey">
      <NameTxt>The Taoiseach</NameTxt>
      <P>It will be taken next session.</P>
      <P>
        <i>(Interruptions.)</i>
      </P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanTreacy" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Seán Treacy">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>Deputy Howlin.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BrendanHowlin" hpid="Mr. Howlin Mr. Howlin">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Howlin</NameTxt>
      <P>Yesterday on the Order of Business the Taoiseach indicated that he was hopeful the National Roads Authority Bill would be circulated before the Easter recess.  Is the Taoiseach still hopeful that we will have sight of the Bill before 4 o'clock this afternoon or is that hope gone?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RuairiQuinn" hpid="Mr. Quinn Mr. Quinn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Quinn</NameTxt>
      <P>It has got lost down a pothole.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="CharlesJHaughey" hpid="The Taoiseach Charles J. Haughey">
      <NameTxt>The Taoiseach</NameTxt>
      <P>I am afraid it is receding slightly into the distance.  There is still a chance that it will be out before Easter.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RuairiQuinn" hpid="Mr. Quinn Mr. Quinn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Quinn</NameTxt>
      <P>There is no truth in the rumour that lifeguards are now minding the potholes.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PhilipHogan" hpid="Mr. Hogan Mr. Hogan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hogan</NameTxt>
      <P>May I ask the Minister for Tourism, Transport and Communications if the Government have decided to reject proposals put forward by Telecom Éireann in respect of charges for local calls?  It is important in the context&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanTreacy" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Seán Treacy">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>The Deputy will have to pursue this matter in the normal way.  Deputy Emmet Stagg.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PhilipHogan" hpid="Mr. Hogan Mr. Hogan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hogan</NameTxt>
      <P>It is important that these proposals are clarified for the benefit of people&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="2071" />
    <Speaker pid="SeanTreacy" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Seán Treacy">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>Sorry, Deputy Hogan, not now.  There are other ways and means of raising this matter.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PhilipHogan" hpid="Mr. Hogan Mr. Hogan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hogan</NameTxt>
      <P>This matter should be clarified&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanTreacy" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Seán Treacy">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>Deputy Hogan will now desist.  The Chair will facilitate him&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PhilipHogan" hpid="Mr. Hogan Mr. Hogan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hogan</NameTxt>
      <P>The Government are misleading the public by postponing their decision until after the local elections. They should now come clean&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanTreacy" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Seán Treacy">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>I must ask you, Deputy, to resume your seat.  Deputy Emmet Stagg.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PhilipHogan" hpid="Mr. Hogan Mr. Hogan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hogan</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister should clarify the position for the general public&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanTreacy" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Seán Treacy">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>Deputy Hogan, resume your seat or leave the House.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PhilipHogan" hpid="Mr. Hogan Mr. Hogan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hogan</NameTxt>
      <P>The public&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanTreacy" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Seán Treacy">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>I am sorry that the Deputy should behave in this fashion. The Deputy will now leave the House or else resume his seat.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PhilipHogan" hpid="Mr. Hogan Mr. Hogan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hogan</NameTxt>
      <P>I will leave the House.</P>
      <P>
        <i>(Interruptions.)</i>
      </P>
      <P>
        <i>Deputy Hogan withdrew from the Chamber.</i>
      </P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EmmetStagg" hpid="Mr. Stagg Mr. Stagg">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Stagg</NameTxt>
      <P>May I ask the Minister for Education when a decision will be made on the renewal of grants to youth organisations? These grants are due for renewal on 7 April and they will go out of existence if they are not renewed.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanTreacy" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Seán Treacy">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>The Deputy should raise that in another way.  Deputy Quinn.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EmmetStagg" hpid="Mr. Stagg Mr. Stagg">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Stagg</NameTxt>
      <P>I am sure you will agree <Col N="2072" /> that it is a very important and urgent matter.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanTreacy" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Seán Treacy">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>I am going on to the business ordered shortly.  I have already called Deputy Quinn.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EmmetStagg" hpid="Mr. Stagg Mr. Stagg">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Stagg</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister should indicate to the House when these grants will be renewed.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanTreacy" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Seán Treacy">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>Deputy Quinn.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RuairiQuinn" hpid="Mr. Quinn Mr. Quinn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Quinn</NameTxt>
      <P>In view of the announcement in relation to the sale of milk by a major retail unit today and its implications for the retail trade generally, can the Taoiseach give any indication when the competition Bill will be brought before this House?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanTreacy" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Seán Treacy">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>That is questioned virtually every day.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BrendanHowlin" hpid="Mr. Howlin Mr. Howlin">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Howlin</NameTxt>
      <P>But we have not got an answer.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelNoonan" hpid="Mr. Noonan (Limerick East) Mr. Noonan (Limerick East)">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Noonan</NameTxt>
      <P>
        <i>(Limerick East):</i> Has the Taoiseach any control over that Minister?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="CharlesJHaughey" hpid="The Taoiseach Charles J. Haughey">
      <NameTxt>The Taoiseach</NameTxt>
      <P>As I said yesterday, the Bill is very well advanced and is imminent any day now.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RuairiQuinn" hpid="Mr. Quinn Mr. Quinn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Quinn</NameTxt>
      <P>It has been imminent for the past six months.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BernardJDurkan" hpid="Mr. Durkan Mr. Durkan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Durkan</NameTxt>
      <P>May I ask the Taoiseach when he expects the report on the insurance industry, which is promised, to be referred to the Government?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanTreacy" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Seán Treacy">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>A question would elicit that information.  Deputy John Bruton has been offering and I will call Deputy Gay Mitchell for a final question.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="A Deputy A Deputy">
      <NameTxt>A Deputy</NameTxt>
      <P>A Cheann Comhairle&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanTreacy" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Seán Treacy">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>I am going on to the business ordered when I hear Deputy Gay Mitchell.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="2073" />
    <Speaker pid="JohnBruton" hpid="Mr. J. Bruton Mr. J. Bruton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J. Bruton</NameTxt>
      <P>May I ask the Taoiseach when it is proposed to take item No. 8 on today's Order Paper in the name of his Minister of State?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="CharlesJHaughey" hpid="The Taoiseach Charles J. Haughey">
      <NameTxt>The Taoiseach</NameTxt>
      <P>This is not strictly in order but as the Deputy knows I have promised to try to get these committees into being as soon as possible.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnBruton" hpid="Mr. J. Bruton Mr. J. Bruton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J. Bruton</NameTxt>
      <P>When will the Taoiseach make a definitive response to the letter I wrote to him about these matters?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BrendanHowlin" hpid="Mr. Howlin Mr. Howlin">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Howlin</NameTxt>
      <P>He wants a penpal.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnBruton" hpid="Mr. J. Bruton Mr. J. Bruton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J. Bruton</NameTxt>
      <P>This is a serious matter.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanTreacy" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Seán Treacy">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>It has been raised here so many times&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnBruton" hpid="Mr. J. Bruton Mr. J. Bruton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J. Bruton</NameTxt>
      <P>When is it proposed to establish a foreign affairs committee and a crime committee?  I have written to the Taoiseach outlining my views on this matter but he has not responded to my letter.  He has suggested that the matter should be dealt with by the Whips but he has not given his Whip any instructions in the matter.  There is a total stalemate.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="CharlesJHaughey" hpid="The Taoiseach Charles J. Haughey">
      <NameTxt>The Taoiseach</NameTxt>
      <P>The stalemate in regard to the crime committee was brought about by the Deputy's party who dishonoured an agreement they made in regard to the Chair.  This is why we do not have a crime committee at this stage.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanTreacy" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Seán Treacy">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>Deputy Gay Mitchell.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnBruton" hpid="Mr. J. Bruton Mr. J. Bruton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J. Bruton</NameTxt>
      <P>That is simply not true&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanTreacy" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Seán Treacy">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>Deputy Bruton, this may not lead to argument or disorder.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnBruton" hpid="Mr. J. Bruton Mr. J. Bruton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J. Bruton</NameTxt>
      <P>&mdash;&mdash;and I ask you, Sir, to ask the Taoiseach to withdraw that statement.</P>
      <P>
        <i>(Interruptions.)</i>
      </P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="2074" />
    <Speaker pid="JohnBruton" hpid="Mr. J. Bruton Mr. J. Bruton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J. Bruton</NameTxt>
      <P>On a point of order, considering your great concern for order on this side of the House, may I ask you to ask the Taoiseach to withdraw that statement?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanTreacy" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Seán Treacy">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>The Deputy may not attribute any element of partisanship to this Chairman.</P>
      <P>
        <i>(Interruptions.)</i>
      </P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnBruton" hpid="Mr. J. Bruton Mr. J. Bruton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J. Bruton</NameTxt>
      <P>May I ask you to demonstrate that by asking the Taoiseach to withdraw his statement?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanTreacy" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Seán Treacy">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>I will demonstrate that in my own fashion and I will not be dictated to, Deputy.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnBruton" hpid="Mr. J. Bruton Mr. J. Bruton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J. Bruton</NameTxt>
      <P>The Taoiseach has made an incorrect statement in regard to my party and I ask that he withdraw it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanTreacy" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Seán Treacy">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>I have no knowledge&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="VincentBrady" hpid="Minister of State at the Department of the Taoiseach (Mr. V. Brady) Minister of State at the Department of the Taoiseach (Mr. V. Brady)">
      <NameTxt>Minister of State at the Department of the Taoiseach (Mr. V. Brady)</NameTxt>
      <P>It is true. Ask Deputy Dukes, he knows all about it.</P>
      <P>
        <i>(Interruptions.)</i>
      </P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnBruton" hpid="Mr. J. Bruton Mr. J. Bruton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J. Bruton</NameTxt>
      <P>They have not honoured their agreements.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanTreacy" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Seán Treacy">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>Deputy Gay Mitchell.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GayMitchell" hpid="Mr. G. Mitchell Mr. G. Mitchell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. G. Mitchell</NameTxt>
      <P>May I ask the Taoiseach if he will bring forward the promised legislation on the updating of the powers of the Comptroller and Auditor General during the next session since this matter is now becoming urgent?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="CharlesJHaughey" hpid="The Taoiseach Charles J. Haughey">
      <NameTxt>The Taoiseach</NameTxt>
      <P>We will make a special effort to do this.  The Bill is at drafting stage at the moment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnVFarrelly" hpid="Mr. Farrelly Mr. Farrelly">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Farrelly</NameTxt>
      <P>A Cheann Comhairle&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="2075" />
    <Speaker pid="SeanTreacy" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Seán Treacy">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>I am now proceeding to deal with the Social Welfare Bill, 1991, Report Stage.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Social Welfare Bill, 1991:" RHead="Report and Final Stages">
    <Title>Social Welfare Bill, 1991: Report and Final Stages.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="DickSpring" hpid="Mr. Spring Mr. Spring">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Spring</NameTxt>
      <P>Is there any possibility of discussing my amendment No. 1?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanTreacy" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Seán Treacy">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>I have conveyed my decision in relation to the matter. Your amendment is out of order for the obvious reason, it involves a potential charge on the Revenue.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DickSpring" hpid="Mr. Spring Mr. Spring">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Spring</NameTxt>
      <P>I always look forward to receiving communications from you, a Cheann Comhairle, but on this occasion I regret that you had to inform me that my amendment had been ruled out of order.  May I address two very brief remarks to the Minister for Social Welfare in relation to this amendment?</P>
      <P>As a result of the discussion which took place on Committee Stage, I believe the Minister is well aware of my concern, as voiced by Deputy Stagg, in regard to the differential treatment of people in the PAYE sector as opposed to those in the self-employed sector.  I ask the Minister for Social Welfare, before the Bill is debated in the Seanad, to look at the disparity which exists.  This is a moot point, with which I am sure the Minister is familiar, that dependent spouses in the self-employed sector are entitled to have their allowances annualised over a 52 week period whereas spouses in the PAYE sector have any six week period in the year taken against them.  Unfortunately, this discriminates against spouses in the PAYE sector.  I ask the Minister to look at this issue before the Bill is debated in the Seanad.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelJWoods" hpid="Minister for Social Welfare (Dr. Woods) Michael J. Woods">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Social Welfare (Dr. Woods)</NameTxt>
      <P>Strictly speaking, I am out of order in replying to the Deputy because his amendment cannot be moved.  The Deputy asked me if I would keep this issue in mind&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="2076" />
    <Speaker pid="SeanTreacy" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Seán Treacy">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>The Chair is anxious to have matters clarified in any event.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelJWoods" hpid="Dr. Woods Dr. Woods">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Woods</NameTxt>
      <P>The position is that the adult dependant regulations are designed to take account of the most up-to-date earnings data in determining weekly earnings for the purposes of applying the limit.  However, due to the different nature of employment and self-employment it is not possible to use the same periods in determining the most up-to-date earnings.</P>
      <P>Sub-article (1) of article 5 of the 1985 Adult Dependant Regulations provides that the weekly earnings of an employed contributor are calculated by reference to the average earnings in the previous six or eight weeks, depending on the period for which the person is being paid. This six-eight week test is designed to provide the most up-to-date information concerning the current normal weekly earnings of employed persons.  These earnings can be verified by the production of wage slips or statements from employers.  A similar system is used in determining weekly earnings for entitlement to family income supplement.</P>
      <P>However, such a system would not be practical in determining the current normal weekly earnings of self-employed persons.  For this reason the earnings in the last complete income tax year which are the latest verifiable details of earnings of self-employed persons, are used.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Because different periods are used in determining the average weekly earnings of employed and self-employed contributors, sub-article (2) of article 5 of the regulations provide that, where a deciding officer or an appeals officer considers that the periods provided for in article 5 (1) are not appropriate for determining the average weekly earnings, he can take any other period which he considers appropriate into consideration.  This provision is used where the periods specified in sub-article (1) of article 5 do not give an accurate reflection of normal weekly earnings of either employed or self-employed persons.  Sub-article (2) of article 5 also ensures that a consistent <Col N="2077" /> approach is adopted in determining the average weekly earnings of employed and self-employed contributors.  As the Deputy will be aware, this arrangement was introduced in 1985 because of the practicalities of implementing the regulations. In addition, these may arise in exceptional circumstances.</P>
    <P>
      <i>Deputy Spring rose.</i>
    </P>
    <Speaker pid="SeanTreacy" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Seán Treacy">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>I allowed the Deputy to seek clarification.  A debate cannot arise on an amendment which is technically out of order.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DickSpring" hpid="Mr. Spring Mr. Spring">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Spring</NameTxt>
      <P>I wish to make one final point but I do not wish to hold up the debate.  The Minister is probably unaware that he has written to me on about three occasions during the past six to eight months stating what he has just said.  Under the 1985 legislation, a self-employed person may earn up to £2,860 per year whereas if a PAYE taxpayer earns around £340 during a six week period they will be deemed ineligible for the allowance.  This anomaly should be corrected.  I ask the Minister to take a look at this before the Seanad debate.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelJWoods" hpid="Dr. Woods Dr. Woods">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Woods</NameTxt>
      <P>I will do that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanTreacy" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Seán Treacy">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>I am now proceeding to amendment&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesCTunney" hpid="Mr. Tunney Mr. Tunney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Tunney</NameTxt>
      <P>Could I ask your indulgence to look for a minute of the House's time?  This is not entirely related to the point made by Deputy Spring but I would like to ask the House, and the Minister, in considering this legislation to spare a thought for people who are brothers and sisters and are, apparently, overlooked in the matter of welfare.  We might consider, where appropriate, extending social welfare provisions to people who are called religious and who give their lives to other people but who, apparently, for some unknown reason, are excluded from the provisions of this legislation.  I refer especially to the carer's allowance.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelJWoods" hpid="Dr. Woods Dr. Woods">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Woods</NameTxt>
      <P>Religious in an institution <Col N="2078" /> or convent are not eligible to receive the carer's allowance.  I appreciate the point made by the Leas-Cheann Comhairle that a situation may arise where a member of a religious order would be cared for by another member.  While there are differences in the case of an institution I will examine this matter.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesCTunney" hpid="Mr. Tunney Mr. Tunney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Tunney</NameTxt>
      <P>Thank you.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PaulConnaughton" hpid="Mr. Connaughton Mr. Connaughton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Connaughton</NameTxt>
      <P>May I ask a question?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanTreacy" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Seán Treacy">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>The Chair is very anxious to get the debate on an even keel.  I allowed Deputy Spring to seek clarification but I had hoped it would not give rise to a debate.  However, if Deputy Connaughton has a comment to make I will be glad to hear him.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PaulConnaughton" hpid="Mr. Connaughton Mr. Connaughton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Connaughton</NameTxt>
      <P>I am grateful to Deputy Tunney for raising this matter. May I take it that the religious, priests, nuns and so on are entitled to apply for the old age pension on reaching the age of 66, like everybody else?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelJWoods" hpid="Dr. Woods Dr. Woods">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Woods</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes.  An incapacitated person within an institution may receive the appropriate social welfare pension, which means that that side of the equation is covered, but the person providing the care is not covered even though that person may have no income.  That is a question I can look at.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PaulConnaughton" hpid="Mr. Connaughton Mr. Connaughton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Connaughton</NameTxt>
      <P>I have never seen a retired priest draw his pension at a post office.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelJWoods" hpid="Dr. Woods Dr. Woods">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Woods</NameTxt>
      <P>Christian Brothers, who have given great service over the years, are an example.  In some cases the person concerned is quite elderly and has virtually no income.  I will look at the matter.</P>
      <P>Amendment No. 1 not moved.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EmmetStagg" hpid="Mr. Stagg Mr. Stagg">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Stagg</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 2:</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="2079" /> In page 9, between lines 6 and 7, to insert the following:</P>
    <P>&ldquo;(3) The Minister shall, in consultation with the Minister for Finance, make regulations in relation to Family Income Supplement to ensure that all persons qualified to receive payment under Family Income Supplement are automatically paid.'.&rdquo;.</P>
    <P>I wish to thank your office, a Cheann Comhairle, for getting this amendment back in a form which is acceptable.  I was puzzled by your ruling yesterday that the amendment, because of the way it was worded, involved a potential charge on the Revenue.  The amendment proposes, and I think it finds favour with the Minister, that he should ensure that those entitled to a family income supplement receive that payment.  Since yesterday, I checked what information the Revenue Commissioners require of a family or any applicant when they apply for a tax free allowance which they must do annually. The applicant must give details of his spouse, a partner, if any, the number and ages of children.  The applicant is then given a tax free allowance.  As a result of this information, the Revenue Commissioners are aware of the family's circumstances, gross income and net income, following deductions for PRSI and income tax.</P>
    <P>The point I am trying to make is that, effectively, information is available to the Minister and the Government which would allow them to make the payment automatically.  The information available to me indicated that there was only a 30 per cent uptake of the family income supplement but the Minister told me that my figure was not accurate and that in fact there is a 50 per cent uptake of this payment.  However, there must be something radically wrong with the scheme which has been designed to be of assistance to families in need if there is only a 50 per cent uptake.  I intend pressing my amendment to ensure that the payment is made automatically.  I am also suggesting a <i>modus operandi</i> to facilitate the <Col N="2080" /> Minister in making the payment automatically.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelJWoods" hpid="Dr. Woods Dr. Woods">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Woods</NameTxt>
      <P>There is a longstanding principle in relation to all social welfare payments that the claimant must make a claim.  This need not necessarily be applied in all cases as we might come to the stage where it will be possible to facilitate people in making a claim by sending them a claim form to complete, sign or verify.  That is one possibility in the medium term.</P>
      <P>Second, as was pointed out yesterday, considerable difficulties could be encountered by the Revenue in seeking information on the family.  Some families are separated, others claim their tax allowances separately and there can be a variety of differences in claims made to the Revenue as compared to claims made to us.  The best thing to do is to inform people of their rights.  I like to simplify things as much as possible.  If applicants use the appropriate ready reckoner they will see exactly what they are entitled to.  This will encourage them to make a claim.  This is being done at present. Deputies will notice that a note is being included with tax forms to make people aware of the family income supplement. The Revenue Commissioners have also included a reference to the family income supplement in their advertisements and indicated clearly the amounts a person may be entitled to.  It is not so much a question of people knowing about the scheme; a great deal of information has been issued on the scheme.  We have found that certain conditions affect the take-up of the scheme and we are improving them at present.  The scheme itself is very simple.  People receive a book similar to the child benefit book we talked about yesterday.  This matter has been discussed with the social partners, the Revenue Commissioners, the Department of Social Welfare and the various joint labour committees who have undertaken to contact people who, in their opinion, should apply for the scheme. That is being done currently and perhaps there will be some improvement from that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="2081" />
    <Speaker pid="PaulConnaughton" hpid="Mr. Connaughton Mr. Connaughton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Connaughton</NameTxt>
      <P>I support the principle of Deputy Stagg's amendment.  It makes a great deal of sense.  I cannot see why it is not possible for the Department to know who is entitled to this supplement. If we take the issue of travel passes to old age pensioners on reaching the age of 66, it is my understanding that nobody has to apply for that pass.  They receive it automatically on reaching that age.  Deputy Stagg's amendment proposes that people who are entitled to the family income supplement should be so informed or they should receive it automatically. Perhaps the Department of Social Welfare should contact potential recipients and tell them the supplement is available to them.  Why does the Minister think that 50 per cent of the potential applicants for family income supplement do not apply for it?  He knows there are 6,500 families who do without this supplement. It is difficult to understand why so many people who are entitled to this supplement do not apply for it.  It must be because they do not know the scheme is tailor made for them.</P>
      <P>I must compliment the Minister &mdash; I forgot to do so yesterday &mdash; on the literature and pamphlets issued by his Department. There has been a huge improvement in that area over the years; another speaker also mentioned that matter earlier in the week.  There is no doubt but the information is very graphic and quite easy to read.  I understand the Minister has a great personal interest in that side of the business, but that is of little good to a person who does not have access to the information.  There is little point talking about these pamphlets if the people do not know they are there. Obviously if families knew they were entitled to the supplement they would apply for it.  That is why Deputy Stagg's amendment makes a great deal of sense.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Surely the Department of Social Welfare or the Revenue Commissioners must know the income of a family in the previous tax year.  Will we ever arrive at the point where there will be a very close relationship between the Department of Social Welfare and the Revenue Commissioners in relation to this matter? <Col N="2082" /> What is the position in that regard?  I assume this is something that cannot be done overnight, but what Deputy Stagg is speaking about is the principle of bringing this about in the near future.  Nothing the Minister has said so far convinces me that this cannot be done.</P>
    <Speaker pid="EricJByrne" hpid="Mr. Byrne Mr. Byrne">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Byrne</NameTxt>
      <P>I support the sentiments expressed by the previous speakers.  We are trying to assist people by giving them this benefit.  In attempting to target the poorest families we are failing miserably because there is only a 50 per cent take up.  That indicates quite clearly that there is something fundamentally wrong with the way the scheme is administered.  As only one out of every two families entitled to this supplement apply for it, it is time we looked at the issue to see where we are failing and why the system is not working as it was intended.  Many poor families are entitled to money from the State but because of the way the system is devised, 50 per cent of them are not receiving it.</P>
      <P>The Minister said that in order to receive this supplement people must apply and fill in an application form.  He implied that the automatic payment system as advocated in the amendment is somehow flawed because we would be obliging people to make the claim in the first instance.  Part of the reason people do not apply for this supplement is probably that they have difficulties dealing with bureaucracy and filling in forms. Some people find it difficult to deal with officials in Departments and this possibly prevents them from taking up the scheme.</P>
      <P>We should, so far as we can, inform people of their right to claim for this supplement.  That is being done to some degree but we have to resolve the problem of the 50 per cent of people who do not claim the supplement for whatever reason, through ignorance of the existence of the scheme, difficulty in complying with the scheme, filling in forms or communicating with the Department. I think the amendment would adequately address this problem and I support it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="2083" />
    <Speaker pid="JohnBrowne1" hpid="Mr. Browne (Carlow-Kilkenny) Mr. Browne (Carlow-Kilkenny)">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Browne</NameTxt>
      <P>
        <i>(Carlow-Kilkenny):</i> First I would advise you, a Cheann Comhairle, that instead of drinking plain water you should be drinking a hot whiskey to fight off the cold you are obviously suffering from.  However that is not part of the Social Welfare Bill.  I too agree with the principle of this amendment.  Whether the take up of this scheme is 30 per cent or 50 per cent is immaterial.  The fact is that only half the families who should be gaining from the scheme are doing so.  We said yesterday that we must encourage people who are working to continue working.  This scheme would be a bonus for the people entitled to it.  The Minister suggested that the Revenue Commissioners might include an information slip when sending out the P60 forms and the scheme could be advertised in that way.  Despite our educational system, many people do not read newspapers, much as we like to think that every speech printed in the paper is read very carefully by constituents.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelJWoods" hpid="Dr. Woods Dr. Woods">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Woods</NameTxt>
      <P>Only the headlines are read.  Some marvellous articles very often are not read.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnBrowne1" hpid="Mr. Browne (Carlow-Kilkenny) Mr. Browne (Carlow-Kilkenny)">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Browne</NameTxt>
      <P>
        <i>(Carlow-Kilkenny):</i> Even local papers that outline special opinions are losing out.  Local radio is one very effective means of communication.  If the Minister undertakes an advertising campaign, I would ask him to consider including local radio.  It is amazing what you hear at clinics as a result of people listening to local radio.  I should also like to link this with the surreptitious discussion yesterday of the net income, not the gross income.  It would not automatically lead to extra costs because, obviously, the figures can be adjusted.  We will have to face the fact that net income is what counts because gross income is a complete distortion.  I ask the Minister to advertise the fact that family income supplement is available and to include local radio in the campaign; of course an advertisement on television would also be very effective.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelJWoods" hpid="Dr. Woods Dr. Woods">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Woods</NameTxt>
      <P>The points made are all <Col N="2084" /> relevant to the general problem and we know that there are difficulties in this regard.  We have done many extra things to try to advertise the family income supplement and Deputy Browne put his finger on it when he talked about the difficulty of trying to get people to understand what you are saying, it is almost a one to one job in many cases.  I find, as a local representative, that with the assistance of a ready reckoner it is easier to show people what is involved.  The more inhibitors we remove, the better the scheme will be.  In that context we did a pilot study in selected areas on medical card holders and we found, in practice, that many did not qualify because they were in receipt of another income.  Fewer people than we expected qualified, not because people did not apply but because their income was higher than anticipated.</P>
      <P>Our research was sizeable and took some time to complete; it showed that the main reason people on a low income did not apply for the family income supplement was that there was another income involved.  People did not want to apply because they did not want to talk about the other income.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnBrowne1" hpid="Mr. Browne (Carlow-Kilkenny) Mr. Browne (Carlow-Kilkenny)">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Browne</NameTxt>
      <P>
        <i>(Carlow-Kilkenny):</i> Was it because somebody in the same house was working?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EmmetStagg" hpid="Mr. Stagg Mr. Stagg">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Stagg</NameTxt>
      <P>Is the Minister talking about nixers?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelJWoods" hpid="Dr. Woods Dr. Woods">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Woods</NameTxt>
      <P>No, I am talking about the applicant.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EmmetStagg" hpid="Mr. Stagg Mr. Stagg">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Stagg</NameTxt>
      <P>That income would be taxed.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelJWoods" hpid="Dr. Woods Dr. Woods">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Woods</NameTxt>
      <P>The income was higher from other sources.  We look at all these figures and things are not as perfect in practice as they might be.  When we examined these questions we found that people were reluctant, for different reasons from the ones we considered relevant, to apply for the family income supplement. That may be why a strong link with the Revenue Commissioners may <Col N="2085" /> not be the best idea, although providing information through the Revenue Commissioners may be the most direct method from that point of view.</P>
      <P>Deputy Browne said that we should advertise the scheme on local radio.  I now insist that local radio is used for imparting most of our social welfare information.  Indeed, some of our staff have been on radio stations round the country informing people of their rights. After we launch a scheme our staff try to get the message across throughout the country.  Our campaign is now being improved which should result in higher numbers participating in the scheme.  I have always felt that higher FIS payments were needed at the lower end of the scale and they have now been increased, which will bring more people into the scheme because it becomes worthwhile.  The minimum amount of £5 at the lower end of the scale will also make it worthwhile. With the improvements in this Bill, I am confident that the numbers applying will increase still further, and we will also look at the other ideas suggested.</P>
      <P>To rely directly on the Revenue Commissioners might suit some people&mdash;but not others &mdash; because you would be dealing with the last year's income, or maybe that of the year before; people may have had a high income in one year and very little in another.  We found, in practice, that the best way to get people into the scheme was to allow them to declare their income for the last two months.  If people run into a bad patch they can declare their income for that time and claim support; if their situation improves later they can drop out of the scheme.</P>
      <P>I appreciate the point made by Deputy Stagg that if the system was perfect, it would be a very convenient way of delivering this scheme but I do not think it would work.  Of course, the child related tax exemptions are being increased and will work through the tax system, but that too has its imperfections which were pointed out in the commission's report and are now coming to light.  At present we are doing it both ways, we are delivering it through the tax system and separately.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="2086" /> I did not have a chance to reply in any detail last night to Deputy Connaughton's point about the self-employed and the farmers.  We pay a farm income supplement to smallholders. If the family income supplement was also given its structures would have to be changed to accommodate self-employed people.  As Members know, a sum of £1 million has been specifically allocated for small farms and discussions in relation to this are in progress.  I am sure Deputy Connaughton will be very conscious that the&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    <Speaker pid="EmmetStagg" hpid="Mr. Stagg Mr. Stagg">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Stagg</NameTxt>
      <P>On a point of order, what in the name of all that is parliamentary has that the Minister said to do with the amendment with which we are dealing?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelJWoods" hpid="Dr. Woods Dr. Woods">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Woods</NameTxt>
      <P>I am talking about the family income supplement.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EmmetStagg" hpid="Mr. Stagg Mr. Stagg">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Stagg</NameTxt>
      <P>It has nothing to do with the amendment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesCTunney" hpid="An Leas-Cheann Comhairle Jim Tunney">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Cheann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister referred to this and I hope &mdash; as Deputy Stagg and the House hope&mdash;that it will not be an extended reference but just a passing one.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PaulConnaughton" hpid="Mr. Connaughton Mr. Connaughton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Connaughton</NameTxt>
      <P>Many people would like to hear more about the family income supplement.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesCTunney" hpid="An Leas-Cheann Comhairle Jim Tunney">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Cheann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>That would not make it in order.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelJWoods" hpid="Dr. Woods Dr. Woods">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Woods</NameTxt>
      <P>I am just trying to be helpful. The amendment referred to the way we pay family income supplement and its automatic payment.  Within those discussions on how best to support small farmers, we will be staying very closely in contact with it.  We will consider the Deputy's point in that context.  This issue is very much alive at the moment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Finally, on the question of automatic payment by the Revenue, I do not think this is practical or realistic.  I appreciate the point but I do not think it would meet the objective the Deputy has in mind. We have a very simple requirement in <Col N="2087" /> relation to the claims and what we are doing in this Bill will make it easier to avail of the scheme.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PearseWyse" hpid="Mr. Wyse Mr. Wyse">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Wyse</NameTxt>
      <P>On Second Stage I mentioned families who run into a bad patch. Many families ran into a bad patch recently because of increases in rents and a family in a local authority house is not entitled to a family income supplement in that case.  I stressed that point on Second Stage.  Community welfare officers cannot supplement a family's income to meet rent increases and thousands of local authority tenants are now in dire need of that kind of help.  I would like the Minister to comment on that.  I know tenants who have to meet increases of £5, £6 and £8 and it would be futile for them to go to a community welfare officer and say they cannot afford to pay this rent and ask for a supplementary welfare allowance.  Under the Bill they cannot get it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesCTunney" hpid="An Leas-Cheann Comhairle Jim Tunney">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Cheann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>Deputy Wyse, let me direct you to the amendment and advise you that you are only courting disorder if you invite the Minister to reply because he cannot do so. He has already made two contributions and he cannot reply.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PearseWyse" hpid="Mr. Wyse Mr. Wyse">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Wyse</NameTxt>
      <P>We are talking about the family income supplement and I am referring to a very important and sensitive area for local authority tenants.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PaulConnaughton" hpid="Mr. Connaughton Mr. Connaughton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Connaughton</NameTxt>
      <P>The recent increases are Government policy.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesCTunney" hpid="An Leas-Cheann Comhairle Jim Tunney">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Cheann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>Deputy Stagg to reply and to refer only to what is relevant.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EmmetStagg" hpid="Mr. Stagg Mr. Stagg">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Stagg</NameTxt>
      <P>Sir, as a result of your assistance yesterday when in the Chair this amendment is in order today, and I would like to pay tribute to the Bills Office for assisting me in that matter.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I would draw the Minister's attention to the new amendment before us.  It is <Col N="2088" /> not the old one that was before us yesterday. It is a nice new, shiny amendment and many of the things the Minister referred to as objectionable, undesirable and unacceptable are not in it; they have been taken out.  All we are asking in this is that the Minister make regulations whenever he likes, before he retires as Minister if he wishes.  There is no time delay, no cut off, no time span put on that.  It is simply a matter of making regulations in consultation with his colleague, the Minister for Finance, which I believe is normally required, and that these regulations should make the payment automatic. We are looking for whatever system the Minister thinks is best.</P>
    <P>The reason for the amendment is that at present we have a system under which people do not get their entitlements.  On the Minister's word 50 per cent do not get their entitlements.  The information available to me is that only 30 per cent are getting their entitlements under this heading.  The arguments the Minister has made do not hold water, they do not stand up because he is arguing against a case that is not being made.  He is rejecting the principle of automatic payment no matter what system might be agreed.</P>
    <P>It is not true, as the Minister said, that this is a simple scheme.  It is most complicated and people are confused about whether they are entitled to benefit under it.  When they come to me, even if I use the ready reckoner I carry around with me, I am not sure if they qualify. Even if they bring me a pay slip I find it very difficult to work out whether they qualify.  It is a complicated scheme.</P>
    <P>We have computers nowadays and after the lessons I had on the machine over two days I am convinced I could write a programme which would deal with this, make it automatic and ensure 100 per cent would get their entitlement. We have all sorts of technical expertise in the Department of Social Welfare and other Government Departments and a programme could be written which would be fool-proof, would safeguard against all the things the Minister suggested and ensure people got their full entitlement.</P>
    <P>All we are asking is that the Minister <Col N="2089" /> make regulations, without including a date, that would allow for the automatic payment.  There is general acceptance of that principle on this side of the House. The Minister seems to recognise the problem but he is not putting forward a <Col N="2090" /> solution.  In the meantime 50 per cent of those entitled to benefits under this heading are not getting them.  In the absence of the Minister accepting the amendment I will be pressing it to a vote.</P>
    <P>Amendment put.</P>
    <P Just="Center">The Dáil divided: Tá, 52, Níl, 64.</P>
    <P Just="Center">Tá</P>
    <table pgwide="1">
      <tgroup cols="2">
        <colspec colname="1" colnum="1" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <colspec colname="2" colnum="2" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry rowsep="1">Allen, Bernard.<br />Barnes, Monica.<br />Barrett, Seán.<br />Belton, Louis J.<br />Boylan, Andrew.<br />Browne, John (Carlow-Kilkenny).<br />Bruton, John.<br />Byrne, Eric.<br />Connaughton, Paul.<br />Cosgrave, Michael Joe.<br />Creed, Michael.<br />Currie, Austin.<br />D'Arcy, Michael.<br />Deasy, Austin.<br />Doyle, Joe.<br />Dukes, Alan.<br />Durkan, Bernard.<br />Farrelly, John V.<br />Fennell, Nuala.<br />Ferris, Michael.<br />Flaherty, Mary.<br />Flanagan, Charles.<br />Higgins, Michael D.<br />Howlin, Brendan.<br />Kavanagh, Liam.<br />Kemmy, Jim.<br /></entry>
            <entry rowsep="1">Lowry, Michael.<br />McCormack, Pádraic.<br />McGahon, Brendan.<br />McGinley, Dinny.<br />Mac Giolla, Tomás.<br />McGrath, Paul.<br />Mitchell, Gay.<br />Mitchell, Jim.<br />Moynihan, Michael.<br />Nealon, Ted.<br />Noonan, Michael. (Limerick East).<br />O'Brien, Fergus.<br />O'Shea, Brian.<br />O'Sullivan, Gerry.<br />Owen, Nora.<br />Quinn, Ruairí.<br />Rabbitte, Pat.<br />Reynolds, Gerry.<br />Ryan, Seán.<br />Sheehan, Patrick J.<br />Sherlock, Joe.<br />Spring, Dick.<br />Stagg, Emmet.<br />Taylor, Mervyn.<br />Timmins, Godfrey.<br />Yates, Ivan.<br />Yates, Ivan.</entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
    <P Just="Center">Níl</P>
    <table pgwide="1">
      <tgroup cols="2">
        <colspec colname="1" colnum="1" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <colspec colname="2" colnum="2" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry rowsep="1">Ahern, Bertie.<br />Ahern, Dermot.<br />Ahern, Michael.<br />Barrett, Michael.<br />Brady, Gerard.<br />Brady, Vincent.<br />Brennan, Mattie.<br />Brennan, Séamus.<br />Browne, John (Wexford).<br />Burke, Raphael P.<br />Callely, Ivor.<br />Clohessy, Peadar.<br />Connolly, Ger.<br />Coughlan, Mary Theresa.<br />Cowen, Brian.<br />Cullimore, Séamus.<br />Daly, Brendan.<br />Davern, Noel.<br />Dempsey, Noel.<br />Dennehy, John.<br />Fahey, Frank.<br />Fahey, Jackie.<br />Fitzpatrick, Dermot.
<Col N="2091" />O'Dea, Willie.<br />O'Donoghue, John.<br />O'Hanlon, Rory.<br />O'Keeffe, Ned.<br />O'Leary, John.<br />O'Rourke, Mary.<br />O'Toole, Martin Joe.<br />Power, Seán.<br />Quill, Máirín.</entry>
            <entry rowsep="1">Flood, Chris.<br />Gallagher, Pat the Cope.<br />Geoghegan-Quinn, Máire.<br />Haughey, Charles J.<br />Hillery, Brian.<br />Hilliard, Colm.<br />Hyland, Liam.<br />Jacob, Joe.<br />Kenneally, Brendan.<br />Kirk, Séamus.<br />Kitt, Michael P.<br />Kitt, Tom.<br />Lawlor, Liam.<br />Lenihan, Brian.<br />Leonard, Jimmy.<br />Leyden, Terry.<br />Lyons, Denis.<br />Martin, Micheál.<br />McCreevy, Charlie.<br />McDaid, Jim.<br />McEllistrim, Tom.<br />Nolan, M.J.<br />O'Connell, John.
<Col N="2092" />Roche, Dick.<br />Smith, Michael.<br />Treacy, Noel.<br />Tunney, Jim.<br />Wallace, Dan.<br />Wallace, Mary.<br />Walsh, Joe.<br />Woods, Michael.<br />Wyse, Pearse.</entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
    <P Just="Center">Tellers: Tá, Deputies Howlin and Flanagan; Níl, Deputies V. Brady and Clohessy.</P>
    <P>Amendment declared lost.</P>
    <P>Amendments Nos. 3 to 6, inclusive, not moved.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JamesCTunney" hpid="An Leas-Cheann Comhairle Jim Tunney">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Cheann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>Amendment No. 7 is in the name of Deputy Stagg.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PaulConnaughton" hpid="Mr. Connaughton Mr. Connaughton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Connaughton</NameTxt>
      <P>On a point of order, several times this morning and yesterday we touched on aid for families, particularly the carer's allowance.  Could we be allowed to make a few points on the carer's allowance?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesCTunney" hpid="An Leas-Cheann Comhairle Jim Tunney">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Cheann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>We are obliged to stick rigidly to the amendments before us.  It would be a matter for the Deputy with whatever ingenuity he might apply in addressing himself to these amendments to keep himself within order in referring to any matter which is regarded as appropriate.  We could not have a separate arrangement.  If the House decided to expedite Report Stage, it would be possible on Fifth Stage to make those points.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PaulConnaughton" hpid="Mr. Connaughton Mr. Connaughton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Connaughton</NameTxt>
      <P>I bow to your ruling.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnBrowne1" hpid="Mr. Browne (Carlow-Kilkenny) Mr. Browne (Carlow-Kilkenny)">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Browne</NameTxt>
      <P>
        <i>(Carlow-Kilkenny):</i> The first amendment in Deputy Spring's name was out of order but the Ceann Comhairle allowed him to raise it and then allowed the Minister to be out of order because he wanted clarification.  We have an amendment which has been ruled out of order.  There is no difference.  The Ceann Comhairle went out of his way to allow Deputy Spring to raise a matter which was out of order.  Even the Minister acknowledged he was out of order. I do not see how the Chair can rule out reference to a very important amendment in those circumstances.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesCTunney" hpid="An Leas-Cheann Comhairle Jim Tunney">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Cheann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>That is the problem we have if the Chair at any stage departs from the rigidity of Standing Orders.  It would appear that if the Chair is considerate towards any Member&mdash;and that consideration often extends from side to side&mdash;it is taken as a precedent and the Chair gets very little thanks for it.  The lesson for the Chair would be to apply the rule of Standing Orders rigidly without fear or favour on all sides from now on.  That is what we will do.  Amendments Nos. 8 and 10 are related to amendment No. 7.  It is proposed for discussion purposes to take amendments Nos. 7, 8 and 10 together, if that is satisfactory.  Agreed.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EmmetStagg" hpid="Mr. Stagg Mr. Stagg">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Stagg</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 7:</P>
      <P>In page 13, line 6, to delete &ldquo;£19,300&rdquo; and substitute &ldquo;the yearly income&rdquo;.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>These amendments refer to the crazy situation where we have a form of tax called PRSI on income up to a certain level and not beyond that level.  It is a most regressive form of taxation, arising from that cut-off point for people on higher incomes.  All major reports on the issue from the Commission on Social Welfare, the Commission on Taxation and from NESC have recommended the abolition of the ceiling.  NESC recently projected that if the ceiling were abolished this would fund the reduction of the PRSI levies and thereby help middle <Col N="2093" /> income groups.  The abolition of the ceiling would also fund the exemption of the first £3,000 of income from PRSI levies, which would turn the PRSI levies system into a progressive income tax.  At present it is a regressive form of taxation under which people on lower income pay a higher percentage of income on PRSI than those on high incomes.</P>
    <P>The PRSI system introduces unacceptable regressive features into the overall taxation system.  A married couple on £10,000 per annum face a marginal tax rate of nearly 37 per cent, while a couple with twice that income face a tax rate of about 31 per cent.  The abolition of the ceiling would remove the regressive feature of the system.  It would also allow the Minister the option of providing income relief through reform of the PRSI system.</P>
    <P>I am also seeking to ensure that the first £60 of income is not just exempt as at present but should remain exempt regardless of whether earnings go beyond £60.  This £60 exemption creates a particular poverty trap.  If a person earns £61 per week he or she has to pay PRSI on that £61, not on £1.  A person earning £60 a week who receives an increase of £1 will face a cost of £3.50.  This is extraordinary. If my amendment were accepted and if the Minister were to take his courage in his hands and take this money which is available to him he could exempt completely from this taxation those on low income.  He could reform it in the middle and taper it upwards.</P>
    <P>There is no argument for the self-employed to be treated any differently from those in the PAYE sector.  At one time there were many benefits available to the PAYE sector which were not available to the self-employed, particularly farmers.  There is no good reason they should have a cut-off point.  The same argument applies to the PAYE sector. We could have the farcical situation where somebody on £65 a week would be paying a considerably higher percentage of gross income in PRSI, which is effectively another form of taxation, than a consultant earning £38,000 a year from the State and at least £25,000 from <Col N="2094" /> private practice.  That person earning about £60,000 per annum would pay a lesser amount of his income in PRSI under the present system than somebody earning £61 per week.</P>
    <P>I am sure the Minister does not want that situation to continue, and I recommend that he take the opportunity to remove the ceiling on PRSI and introduce at the same time, without cost an exemption from PRSI on the first £60 per week or £3,000 per annum per person paying PRSI.  I commend the amendments to the House.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelJWoods" hpid="Dr. Woods Dr. Woods">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Woods</NameTxt>
      <P>The danger in these amendments is that we attempt a return of this year's budget.  These are the considerations when the overall budget package is designed for the year.  There are inter-related effects.  We could decide that everybody was exempt from PRSI on income up to £60 instead of having an exemption for those whose income is below £60.  The difficulty, and I can illustrate it very easily, is the cost&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EmmetStagg" hpid="Mr. Stagg Mr. Stagg">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Stagg</NameTxt>
      <P>On a point of order, Sir, I was probably out of order in referring to the £60 provision because my amendment had been ruled out of order and I may have misled the Minister.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesCTunney" hpid="An Leas-Cheann Comhairle Jim Tunney">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Cheann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>Even though the amendment has been ruled out of order, a Deputy is entitled to make a passing reference to the contents of what was ruled out of order.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelJWoods" hpid="Dr. Woods Dr. Woods">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Woods</NameTxt>
      <P>I am speaking in the context of the amendments.  The provisions of the amendments cannot really be seen on their own ultimately.  I am sure the Deputy does not want simply to impose additional charges on workers without that having some redistribution or reorganisational benefit from the point of view of the workers and the self-employed. For example, if the ceiling for PRSI contributions was increased to £30,000, the increased cost to the employer for each worker would be £1,305, and the increased cost to the employee would be £660.  The Deputy <Col N="2095" /> will be aware that the ceiling on the health charges was removed in this year's budget, which of course means an increased health charge contribution. Obviously extra money was needed urgently for the health services.  This was very necessary and the money can be directed to improving the health services generally.</P>
      <P>My approach to these measures would be to take them within the context of the benefits that could be applied to the contributors.  If we were to waive the PRSI on the first £3,000, it would cost £357 million whereas the effect of abolishing the ceiling on PRSI contributions, which is what the Deputy has proposed here, would bring in an additional £86 million.  The Deputy will see straightaway that one would not balance out the other and we would be into the general question of a tax and PRSI package.  This kind of development would have to be considered as part of a total package.</P>
      <P>A number of changes have already taken place in that regard, but these are matters that must be considered further in other budgets.  We must bear in mind the imposition these changes would place on employers and on employees and set that against the benefits that could be provided in the PRSI system generally. Naturally, as Minister for Social Welfare I have my own ideas about what could be done to improve the PRSI system. Needless to say, I have done costings on different aspects; but these are matters that fall to be considered within the budget and therefore they are not appropriate at this time.  The Government have taken their steps for this year and have given us benefits in the form of reduced taxation and removed the ceiling from the health charges.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>It has been the practice to increase the PRSI ceiling broadly in line with the movement in wages and inflation.  This has been the practice in order to keep the social insurance fund intact and to ensure that it can meet the demands placed on it.  The Bill provides for an increase of £700 in the ceilings.  In the 1991-92 tax year the ceiling for employees will be <Col N="2096" /> £18,000 and £19,300 for employers.  The total abolition of the ceilings would impose a very high additional cost on workers and indeed on employers, whose incomes were above the ceilings, without any corresponding increase in benefits. The amendments should be considered within that context.</P>
    <P>In recent years very considerable progress has been made in reducing the income tax burden.  The <i>Programme for Economic and Social Progress</i> contains a commitment to implement further tax reductions and in particular to reduce the standard rate of tax to 25 per cent and to move towards a single higher rate.  If the PRSI ceiling was abolished the tax gains of the middle and higher income earners would be eroded by the increased PRSI. The abolition of the ceilings, particularly the ceiling on the employers' contribution, would have an adverse effect on costs and profitability in sectors where wages are high and this could affect employment in those industries.  I mention these facts to make it clear to the Deputy that the type of change he is suggesting in the amendments cannot be considered on its own and must be taken within the overall budgetary context. These are matters to be considered in future budgets.</P>
    <Speaker pid="WillieODea" hpid="Mr. O'Dea Mr. O'Dea">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Dea</NameTxt>
      <P>I can see a certain logic in much of what Deputy Stagg has said.  I wish we could go a little further towards meeting the objectives he is seeking to achieve in his amendment.  Unfortunately, there are practical as well as financial difficulties.</P>
      <P>With regard to taxation generally, some politicians seem to have a tendency to emulate the sheep in George Orwell's <i>Animal Farm</i> where &ldquo;progressive&rdquo; means good and &ldquo;regressive&rdquo; means bad. This is not necessarily so.  It depends on what one is trying to achieve.  Equity is one of the objectives we are trying to achieve.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EmmetStagg" hpid="Mr. Stagg Mr. Stagg">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Stagg</NameTxt>
      <P>I am always talking about &ldquo;good progressive&rdquo; measures.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WillieODea" hpid="Mr. O'Dea Mr. O'Dea">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Dea</NameTxt>
      <P>Equity is one of the goals <Col N="2097" /> of any responsible Minister who is administering the tax system, but there are other competing goals.  When you have conflicting objectives, everybody will understand that sometimes you will have to accept less of one and more of another.</P>
      <P>One of our main economic problems is the problem of unemployment.  Despite the better economic indicators, the containment of public expenditure, the stabilisation of the national debt and increased economic growth etc., we still have a stubbornly high unemployment level.  One effect of abolishing the PRSI ceiling, as Deputy Stagg's amendment suggests, would be to increase considerably the tax on employment and this would increase considerably the cost of employers of taking on employees. Surely that is something that all parties in this House have no wish to do.  To exempt the first £3,000 from PRSI would cost £357 million.  The abolition of the ceiling would yield revenue of £86 million.  The gains from abolishing the ceiling would be only a drop in the ocean compared with the cost of what Deputy Stagg seeks to achieve.  Deputy Stagg may suggest instead exempting the first £1,000, but the lower we go the more likely it is that that income would be exempt from tax anyway in the hands of the taxpayer because of the exemption limits.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EmmetStagg" hpid="Mr. Stagg Mr. Stagg">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Stagg</NameTxt>
      <P>On a point of order, I am not arguing that at all.  I am not allowed to argue it.  I could only make a passing reference to it because it has been disallowed by the Ceann Comhairle's office. It is not before us for discussion so I am not arguing the case.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesCTunney" hpid="An Leas-Cheann Comhairle Jim Tunney">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Cheann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>Deputy O'Dea has not gone too deeply into the discussion yet, but we would encourage him to move on to some other aspect.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WillieODea" hpid="Mr. O'Dea Mr. O'Dea">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Dea</NameTxt>
      <P>The final point I want to make is in relation to the abolition of the ceiling.  The people who would be affected by the abolition of the ceiling are invariably people who are on the top <Col N="2098" /> marginal tax rate of 52 per cent.  Everybody applauded the Minister for Finance for reducing the top marginal tax rate in the budget.  Indeed, we came in for a lot of criticism because the Minister did not reduce it further, and we all recognise the need to reduce it further to encourage initiative and create employment etc. Removing the ceiling and bringing down the top marginal rate are two conflicting objectives.  From that point of view I would not support that proposal.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EmmetStagg" hpid="Mr. Stagg Mr. Stagg">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Stagg</NameTxt>
      <P>What we are doing here today is dealing with the budget from the point of social welfare.  The Minister's annual Social Welfare Bill arises directly from the budget.  As social welfare spokesman this is my opportunity to deal with the budget.</P>
      <P>The Minister should not feel bound by amendments that have been ruled out of order.  We will not be attempting at this stage to get them into legislation.  The amendments before us are simply to remove the top ceiling for PRSI.  Despite the professional advice from Deputy O'Dea, all of the Government agencies and commissions dealing with this area have recommended that this matter be dealt with in the way I am proposing. The Minister for Finance, in his Bill, has attempted to deal with the £60 margin and the Minister for Social Welfare has recognised the poverty trap by having a temporary cut-off where people, when they gain £1, pay £3.55.  That is a very severe type of poverty trap.  If they gain £2 they still have more than 100 per cent marginal tax rate but if they gain £3 in their income they will be losing because they got an increase.  That is serious and something the Minister in charge of the abolition of poverty here should seek to redress.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The Government have taken a step in the right direction in regard to the health charges the Minister has referred to.  If it is good sense in that regard, why is it not good sense for the rest of the PRSI? There seems to be a contradiction in the argument being made by the Minister.  It also seems that he agrees in principle with this.  In proposing taxation from these <Col N="2099" /> benches I am offering the Minister a gift horse &mdash; not a Trojan horse &mdash; that he should warmly welcome.  I am offering him another £86 million which will be at the disposal of his Department to spend on any of the projects on which he would like to spend that money and we are not suggesting in our amendments how he should do it; we are giving him a free hand to use this money that he would take from people at about five per cent on the income they earn above £20,000 per annum.</P>
    <P>I submit they can well afford to pay it. <Col N="2100" /> If the people earning less than £20,000 can afford to pay it, I do not see why the people above £20,000 cannot afford to pay.  I strongly suggest to the Minister that he does not look a gift horse in the mouth, that he takes this additional revenue of £86 million and puts it to good use on many of the good projects the Minister has in mind that he has not enough money for.  I propose that the amendments be accepted with whatever wording is required.</P>
    <P>Question put: &ldquo;That the figure proposed to be deleted stand.&rdquo;</P>
    <P Just="Center">The Dáil divided: Tá, 66; Níl, 17.</P>
    <P Just="Center">Tá</P>
    <table pgwide="1">
      <tgroup cols="2">
        <colspec colname="1" colnum="1" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <colspec colname="2" colnum="2" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry rowsep="1">Ahern, Bertie.<br />Ahern, Dermot.<br />Ahern, Michael.<br />Barrett, Michael.<br />Brady, Gerard.<br />Brady, Vincent.<br />Brennan, Mattie.<br />Brennan, Séamus.<br />Browne, John (Wexford).<br />Burke, Raphael P.<br />Callely, Ivor.<br />Clohessy, Peadar.<br />Connolly, Ger.<br />Coughlan, Mary Theresa.<br />Cowen, Brian.<br />Cullimore, Séamus.<br />Daly, Brendan.<br />Davern, Noel.<br />Dempsey, Noel.<br />Dennehy, John.<br />Fahey, Frank.<br />Fahey, Jackie.<br />Fitzpatrick, Dermot.<br />Flood, Chris.<br />Gallagher, Pat the Cope.<br />Geoghegan-Quinn, Máire.<br />Haughey, Charles J.<br />Hillery, Brian.<br />Hilliard, Colm.<br />Hyland, Liam.<br />Jacob, Joe.<br />Kelly, Laurence.<br />Kenneally, Brendan.</entry>
            <entry rowsep="1">Kirk, Séamus.<br />Kitt, Michael P.<br />Kitt, Tom.<br />Lawlor, Liam.<br />Lenihan, Brian.<br />Leonard, Jimmy.<br />Leyden, Terry.<br />Lyons, Denis.<br />Martin, Micheál.<br />McCreevy, Charlie.<br />McDaid, Jim.<br />McEllistrim, Tom.<br />Molloy, Robert.<br />Nolan, M.J.<br />O'Connell, John.<br />O'Dea, Willie.<br />O'Donoghue, John.<br />O'Hanlon, Rory.<br />O'Keeffe, Ned.<br />O'Leary, John.<br />O'Rourke, Mary.<br />O'Toole, Martin Joe.<br />Power, Seán.<br />Quill, Máirín.<br />Roche, Dick.<br />Smith, Michael.<br />Treacy, Noel.<br />Tunney, Jim.<br />Wallace, Dan.<br />Wallace, Mary.<br />Walsh, Joe.<br />Woods, Michael.<br />Wyse, Pearse.</entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
    <P Just="Center">Níl</P>
    <table pgwide="1">
      <tgroup cols="2">
        <colspec colname="1" colnum="1" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <colspec colname="2" colnum="2" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry rowsep="1">Byrne, Eric.<br />Ferris, Michael.<br />Higgins, Michael D.<br />Howlin, Brendan.<br />Kavanagh, Liam.<br />Kemmy, Jim.
<Col N="2101" />Ryan, Seán.<br />Sherlock, Joe.<br />Spring, Dick.</entry>
            <entry rowsep="1">Mac Giolla, Tomás.<br />Moynihan, Michael.<br />O'Shea, Brian.<br />O'Sullivan, Gerry.<br />Quinn, Ruairí.<br />Rabbitte, Pat.
<Col N="2102" />Stagg, Emmet.<br />Taylor, Mervyn.<br /></entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
    <P Just="Center">Tellers: Tá, Deputies V. Brady and Clohessy; Níl, Deputies Howlin and Ferris.</P>
    <P>Question declared carried.</P>
    <P>Amendment declared lost.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PaulConnaughton" hpid="Mr. Connaughton Mr. Connaughton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Connaughton</NameTxt>
      <P>On a point of order, I thought amendments Nos. 7, 8 and 10 were being taken together.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelJWoods" hpid="Dr. Woods Dr. Woods">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Woods</NameTxt>
      <P>They were discussed together but will now be put.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EmmetStagg" hpid="Mr. Stagg Mr. Stagg">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Stagg</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 8:</P>
      <P>In page 13, line 8, to delete &ldquo;£18,000&rdquo; and substitute &ldquo;the yearly income&rdquo;.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeSherlock" hpid="Acting Chairman (Mr. Sherlock) Acting Chairman (Mr. Sherlock)">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman (Mr. Sherlock)</NameTxt>
      <P>Is the Deputy pressing the amendment?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EmmetStagg" hpid="Mr. Stagg Mr. Stagg">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Stagg</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes.</P>
      <P>Question: &ldquo;That the figure proposed to be deleted stand&rdquo; put and declared carried.</P>
      <P>Amendment declared lost.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Acting Chairman Acting Chairman">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman</NameTxt>
      <P>Amendment No. 9 has been ruled out of order.</P>
      <P>Amendment No. 9 not moved.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Acting Chairman Acting Chairman">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman</NameTxt>
      <P>We now come to amendment No. 10 which has already been discussed.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EmmetStagg" hpid="Mr. Stagg Mr. Stagg">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Stagg</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 10:</P>
      <P>In page 13, to delete lines 48 to 51, and in page 14, to delete lines 1 to 3.</P>
      <P>Question put: &ldquo;That the words proposed to be deleted stand&rdquo;.</P>
      <P Just="Center">The Dáil divided: Tá, 65; Níl, 17.</P>
      <P Just="Center">Tá</P>
    </Speaker>
    <table pgwide="1">
      <tgroup cols="2">
        <colspec colname="1" colnum="1" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <colspec colname="2" colnum="2" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry rowsep="1">Ahern, Bertie.<br />Ahern, Dermot.<br />Ahern, Michael.<br />Barrett, Michael.<br />Brady, Gerard.<br />Brady, Vincent.<br />Brennan, Mattie.<br />Brennan, Séamus.<br />Burke, Raphael P.<br />Callely, Ivor.<br />Clohessy, Peadar.<br />Connolly, Ger.<br />Coughlan, Mary Theresa.<br />Cowen, Brian.<br />Cullimore, Séamus.<br />Daly, Brendan.<br />Davern, Noel.<br />Dempsey, Noel.<br />Dennehy, John.<br />Fahey, Frank.<br />Fahey, Jackie.<br />Fitzpatrick, Dermot.<br />Flood, Chris.<br />Gallagher, Pat the Cope.<br />Geoghegan-Quinn, Máire.<br />Haughey, Charles J.<br />Hillery, Brian.<br />Hilliard, Colm.<br />Hyland, Liam.
<Col N="2103" />Treacy, Noel.<br />Tunney, Jim.<br />Wallace, Dan.<br />Wallace, Mary.</entry>
            <entry rowsep="1">Jacob, Joe.<br />Kelly, Laurence.<br />Kenneally, Brendan.<br />Kirk, Séamus.<br />Kitt, Michael P.<br />Kitt, Tom.<br />Lawlor, Liam.<br />Lenihan, Brian.<br />Leonard, Jimmy.<br />Leyden, Terry.<br />Lyons, Denis.<br />Martin, Micheál.<br />McCreevy, Charlie.<br />McDaid, Jim.<br />McEllistrim, Tom.<br />Molloy, Robert.<br />Nolan, M.J.<br />O'Connell, John.<br />O'Dea, Willie.<br />O'Donoghue, John.<br />O'Hanlon, Rory.<br />O'Keeffe, Ned.<br />O'Leary, John.<br />O'Rourke, Mary.<br />O'Toole, Martin Joe.<br />Power, Seán.<br />Quill, Máirín.<br />Roche, Dick.<br />Smith, Michael.
<Col N="2104" />Walsh, Joe.<br />Woods, Michael.<br />Wyse, Pearse.<br /></entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
    <P Just="Center">Níl</P>
    <table pgwide="1">
      <tgroup cols="2">
        <colspec colname="1" colnum="1" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <colspec colname="2" colnum="2" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry rowsep="1">Byrne, Eric.<br />Ferris, Michael.<br />Higgins, Michael D.<br />Howlin, Brendan.<br />Kavanagh, Liam.<br />Kemmy, Jim.<br />Mac Giolla, Tomás.<br />Moynihan, Michael.<br /></entry>
            <entry rowsep="1">O'Shea, Brian.<br />O'Sullivan, Gerry.<br />Quinn, Ruairí.<br />Rabbitte, Pat.<br />Ryan, Seán.<br />Sherlock, Joe.<br />Spring, Dick.<br />Stagg, Emmet.<br />Taylor, Mervyn.</entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
    <P Just="Center">Tellers: Tá, Deputies V. Brady and Clohessy; Níl, Deputies Howlin and Ferris.</P>
    <P>Question declared carried.</P>
    <P>Amendment declared lost.</P>
    <P>Amendments Nos. 11 to 13, inclusive, not moved.</P>
    <Speaker pid="SeanTreacy" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Seán Treacy">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>We now proceed to deal with amendment No. 14 in the name of Deputy Eric Byrne.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EmmetStagg" hpid="Mr. Stagg Mr. Stagg">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Stagg</NameTxt>
      <P>On a point of order, I seek your guidance.  On Committee Stage the Minister indicated that he would change the regulations concerning part-time workers by reducing the amount from £40 to £25.  Amendments Nos. 11, 12 and 13 which have been ruled out of order dealt with this section.  How will this change be introduced&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanTreacy" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Seán Treacy">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>I am anxious to help the Deputy but it is not one for the Chair.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EmmetStagg" hpid="Mr. Stagg Mr. Stagg">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Stagg</NameTxt>
      <P>Perhaps the Minister will clarify the position.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelJWoods" hpid="Dr. Woods Dr. Woods">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Woods</NameTxt>
      <P>The Bill provides for the benefits which will be applied.  I already have the power by way of regulation to make the other amendment.  Obviously this is related to the benefits.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EricJByrne" hpid="Mr. Byrne Mr. Byrne">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Byrne</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 14:</P>
      <P>In page 22, to delete lines 27 to 33 and substitute the following:</P>
      <P>&ldquo;(2)  Where it is proposed to make an order under this section, a draft of the order shall be laid before each of the Houses of the Oireachtas, and shall not come into effect until a motion approving of the draft has been passed by each such House.&rdquo;.</P>
      <P>I want to first assure the Minister that I am not being negative about Part IV. I welcome this Part of the Bill which provides for amendments to the contribution conditions for old age contributory pension and retirement pensions to enable PRSI contributions paid by public servants at the modified rates to be taken into account along with PRSI contributions at the full class A rate in determining entitlement to pension.  The amended conditions which will be brought into operation by way of regulations provide that a <i>pro rata</i> pension will be payable to persons with a mix of social insurance records and that this will be proportionate to the periods of insurance completed at the full class A rate.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I think most TDs are familiar with the lobbying which has been carried out on behalf of the CIE workers.  Many bus drivers and conductors who had paid their full stamp found when they were promoted to inspector and other grades that they did not have the full qualifying entitlements for a pension.  I am glad that <Col N="2105" /> this problem is being addressed in this part of the Bill.  The Commission on Social Welfare referred to this problem in their 1985 report.  They said they were deeply concerned at the situation which permitted an individual who became a social insurance contributor for the first time in 1974 to qualify for a pension while an individual with a similar post-1974 insurance record might not qualify by reason of having made social insurance contributions before 1974.  They considered this system to be inequitable and said it should be remedied.</P>
    <P>While I welcome the Minister's attempt to rectify this inequity, I take exception to section 26 which gives the Minister power to remove difficulties. Section 26 is an extensive section.  Given that a guillotine has been applied to this debate we cannot explore many of the areas covered by this section.  Deputy Connaughton sought to refer to certain aspects of the legislation but was not allowed to do so.  The purpose of my amendment is to delete subsection (2). Apart from the time factor, the reason I put forward this amendment is that the Minister has proposed giving himself the power in subsection (1) to make orders. That subsection reads:</P>
    <P>If in any respect any difficulty arises in bringing this Part into operation, the Minister may, with the consent of the Minister for Finance, by order do anything which appears to be necessary or expedient for bringing this Part into operation....</P>
    <P>It is unacceptable that the Minister can walk out of this House today and then come back, once the Bill has been passed, with an order.  This in effect is putting the cart before the horse or working the legislation from back to front.  Our amendment states that where it is proposed to make an order under this section, a draft of the order shall be laid before each of the Houses of the Oireachtas, and shall not come into effect until a motion approving of the draft has been passed by each House.  I suggest that is the proper way to proceed.  The Minister should remember that if any <Col N="2106" /> specific difficulty arises it would not be a difficulty which would face him alone, it would also face the House.  Therefore, he should not have the right to produce an order automatically even though I am aware a certain procedure has to be gone through.  However, the House will be put at a disadvantage.  I ask the Minister to change that and accept the amendment.</P>
    <Speaker pid="DanWallace" hpid="Mr. D. Wallace Mr. D. Wallace">
      <NameTxt>Mr. D. Wallace</NameTxt>
      <P>First, I put it to Deputy Byrne that we would have had far more time to discuss amendments and sections if so many ridiculous votes had not been called on amendments.  In effect it is only time wasting.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EmmetStagg" hpid="Mr. Stagg Mr. Stagg">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Stagg</NameTxt>
      <P>On a point of order, the amendments I have tabled have been judged by the Ceann Comhairle to be proper.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeSherlock" hpid="Acting Chairman (Mr. Sherlock) Acting Chairman (Mr. Sherlock)">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman (Mr. Sherlock)</NameTxt>
      <P>That is accepted by the Chair.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EmmetStagg" hpid="Mr. Stagg Mr. Stagg">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Stagg</NameTxt>
      <P>We were not wasting time.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DanWallace" hpid="Mr. D. Wallace Mr. D. Wallace">
      <NameTxt>Mr. D. Wallace</NameTxt>
      <P>I directed my comments to Deputy Byrne.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EricJByrne" hpid="Mr. Byrne Mr. Byrne">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Byrne</NameTxt>
      <P>I have not pressed any amendment to a vote.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Acting Chairman Acting Chairman">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman</NameTxt>
      <P>I would advise the Deputy that this is Report Stage and he should address the amendment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DanWallace" hpid="Mr. D. Wallace Mr. D. Wallace">
      <NameTxt>Mr. D. Wallace</NameTxt>
      <P>I welcome this section of the Bill.  The Minister should be given as much scope as possible as we are all very much aware of the problems associated with mixed insurance.  Deputy Byrne made reference to CIE workers.  I would like to pay tribute to the old age pensioners' association in Cork who campaigned for years on this issue.  It would be a pity if we were to tie the Minister's hands, as he wants to accommodate those people and bring them within the social welfare system.  The House should unite and give the Minister the power to introduce orders in trying to alleviate the problem we have faced over a long period.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="2107" />
    <Speaker pid="PaulConnaughton" hpid="Mr. Connaughton Mr. Connaughton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Connaughton</NameTxt>
      <P>I have no difficulty in agreeing with the Minister's proposal. However, I am concerned about the way in which he will use the power.  I am grateful to Deputy Byrne for putting down the amendment as it gives us the chance to mention what the Minister might do once he has the power to make such orders.</P>
      <P>In relation to the question of mixed insurance, I spoke at length on Second Stage about the extension of the PRSI scheme to provide cover for the self-employed. It now appears an anomaly exists in relation to the payment of the contributory old age pension to self-employed persons under the 1988 Act. Under the terms of that scheme, there is a minimum contribution period of ten years.  It has now been acknowledged that about 15,000 self-employed persons, including farmers, carpenters and so on, were born too soon and will not have the required number of contributions on reaching the age of 66.  They will still be required however under the law of the land, to pay their contributions.  As I understand it, they will get a refund of these contributions but they will not qualify for a contributory old age pension.</P>
      <P>Given that we cannot propose an amendment which would involve a potential charge on the Revenue, I ask the Minister to consider allowing these contributors to continue paying contributions, beyond the age of 66, until they have the required number of contributions. In other words, they would continue to pay contributions but would not be allowed to claim a pension until they have reached the age of 67, 68 or 70.  That would be the penalty imposed on them.  I understand, having consulted with a large cross-section of these people throughout the country, that the great majority would like to do this.  Not long ago I asked the Minister if he had carried out an actuarial assessment of the cost involved.  In reply to a parliamentary question the figure I was given was, I think, £734 million&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="2108" />
    <Speaker pid="MichaelJWoods" hpid="Dr. Woods Dr. Woods">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Woods</NameTxt>
      <P>The figure was £756 million.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PaulConnaughton" hpid="Mr. Connaughton Mr. Connaughton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Connaughton</NameTxt>
      <P>As far as I was concerned, it was a telephone number.  I presume this figure was calculated by professional assessors on behalf of the Minister. If the figure that I have mentioned is correct &mdash; 15,000 &mdash; we may take it that in future years the figure will not be as high.  More importantly, if the concession I propose is granted, most will not draw payments from the Exchequer for as long as those who have the required number of contributions at the age of 66.  The matter would sort itself out in three to five years.</P>
      <P>The system is a good one and it is time the self-employed were brought into the PRSI scheme.  However these people, simply because they are the wrong age, will be deemed ineligible on reaching the age of 66.  I have a bee in my bonnet about this and believe that someone will have to grasp the nettle.  I am not suggesting that people should be allowed to buy into the scheme, because the net cost to the State would be enormous, but I cannot see the rationale in their not being allowed to continue to receive this money after the age of 66.  They would then have to pay their minimum contribution in the same way as everybody else.  These people are being fined, as it were, on the basis that they will have to wait two, three or four years for a pension which everybody else who is deemed eligible receives years earlier.  If this suggestion is taken on board at least they will get value for money and will be treated equally.  I would like the Minister to give some indication as to what he would like to see done in this area.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="NualaFennell" hpid="Mrs. Fennell Mrs. Fennell">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Fennell</NameTxt>
      <P>I would like to make a passing reference to an amendment that has been ruled out of order.  I would ask the Minister to consider the subject of an amendment put down on Committee Stage in the names of Deputy Flaherty, Deputy Barnes and myself.  In view of the fact that section 26 gives the Minister power to deal with difficulties where they occur, I would ask him to consider the <Col N="2109" /> army of women who had to leave public service employment by virtue of their marital status.  Up to 1973 it was accepted that when women got married they would look after the home and their children and it was only in 1973 that the freedom of choice was given to women.  Many women have suffered in the context of their entitlement to benefits.  I know that submissions and recommendations have been made to the Minister to look fairly at this problem in view of the fact that it was through a discriminatory measure they had to leave their jobs.  Many of these women are coming back into the workforce, and it is not correct that they should be so unfairly penalised.  I would ask the Minister to indicate in his reply what he thinks is possible as regards this group of women.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnBrowne1" hpid="Mr. Browne (Carlow-Kilkenny) Mr. Browne (Carlow-Kilkenny)">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Browne</NameTxt>
      <P>
        <i>(Carlow-Kilkenny):</i> I join with my colleague, Deputy Connaughton, regarding the ten-year limit for contributory pensions.  I suggest that even if the Minister cannot accede to my colleague's request he might give a <i>pro rata</i> pension to these people &mdash; for example, if a person had seven years' contributions he would get seven-tenths of the pension.  In the long run these people are in a position where they are neither fish nor flesh.  They are paying contributions but may receive nothing at the end of the day.  Therefore if they have contributed for seven-tenths of the time they should be given seven-tenths of the pension.  I would ask the Minister to consider that matter.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EmmetStagg" hpid="Mr. Stagg Mr. Stagg">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Stagg</NameTxt>
      <P>I want to refer to an amendment that was ruled out of order, the amendment I had tabled concerning the standardisation of maternity provisions. A considerable number of women who previously were fully entitled to maternity benefit will not receive it in future unless they are working.  Even if they have a good history of work, if they have become unemployed or have been on disability benefit they will now be disenfranchised by this measure.  Perhaps this is not the Minister's intention because he seems to be improving the <Col N="2110" /> position for others.  Quite a number of people will be affected by this measure because women are regularly ill before the maternity period.  By my reading of this section, those people will now be excluded from the benefit, and this is a retrograde step.</P>
      <P>The existing maternity allowance was more beneficial to more people.  It is detrimental that women will now have to be working at least eight hours a week before they can receive this benefit. Many people have no income during this period and will have to pretend that they are available for work even though they are not capable of working.  The dole offices and unemployment exchanges will probably turn a blind eye to the fact that they are in the late stages of pregnancy and unable to work for various health reasons arising from their condition.  I would ask the Minister to reconsider this matter because it affects many people.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MonicaBarnes" hpid="Mrs. Barnes Mrs. Barnes">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Barnes</NameTxt>
      <P>I also want to take the opportunity to refer to the amendment. We had hoped to be able to elaborate on it but unfortunately that is not possible. The Minister should be made aware of a particular group of people who are the victims of downright discrimination based on sex and marital status.  The Minister is well aware that in all recent legislation regarding women in employment the bottom line is that any discrimination based on sex and marital status is illegal and is not acceptable. Previously women were discriminated against &mdash; this never occurred in any other member state &mdash; by virtue of their marital status and this practice was not changed until 1973.  Women who have returned to the workforce find that the years previous to their dismissal &mdash; that is what is was because they had no choice &mdash; will be added to the years in which they paid their full contribution after reentry to the workforce, and this makes them ineligible for contributory old age pension.  I have been made aware by many women paying full PRSI that they are not informed that that contribution is null and void because the years in the intervening period, when they were <Col N="2111" /> forced out of the workforce, will be taken into consideration.</P>
      <P>In the light of recent judgments at European level on discrimination in regard to social security where compensation was granted retrospectively, this is a case that will be taken to Europe because it discriminates against women on the basis of sex and marital status. Women are being discriminated against by the State and this should be examined. I would ask the Minister to deal with this. We should remember that the number of women concerned is dwindling in so far as since 1973 women have had the choice of participating fully in the workforce and paying full contributions.  For the women to whom that was denied by a State discrimination there is a glaring injustice.  I have been informed by women threatened with this discrimination that they will take the case to Europe.  I would like to think that once again we will not find ourselves embarrassed and ashamed that cases on behalf of women in this country have to be judged at European level.  I appeal to the Minister to take this matter on board and do something about it as quickly as possible.  I want to serve notice in this House today that if something is not done the matter will be taken to Europe.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelJWoods" hpid="Dr. Woods Dr. Woods">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Woods</NameTxt>
      <P>I am sure the Chair will forgive me if I return briefly to the amendment.  We have reverted more or less to a Second Stage debate, with wide-ranging discussion.  I know I am out of order in replying to the points made by various speakers but I will just mention them briefly.  Deputy Wallace rightly said that the pensioners in Cork have played a very prominent role in pursuing the question of mixed insurance.  Deputy Connaughton referred to the ten-year period built into the provision of pensions for the self-employed.  I should like to make it clear that this was not done by regulation, it has been in the system for everybody since 1961, when it was introduced. It is a feature of the whole system.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PaulConnaughton" hpid="Mr. Connaughton Mr. Connaughton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Connaughton</NameTxt>
      <P>It can be changed.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="2112" />
    <Speaker pid="MichaelJWoods" hpid="Dr. Woods Dr. Woods">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Woods</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes, but it has implications for the whole system, not just for those people.  If I recall correctly, a sum of £156 million was provided but it was a net sum allowing for the contributions which would be made.  I know it is hard to understand how people who are slightly in arrears can cost so much.  The reason is that anyone who came in on a ten-year basis did exceptionally well because one really needs about 40 years' contributions to justify it.  The whole package was of great benefit at that stage.  However, it is something I will keep under consideration and if I can resolve any difficulties I will be anxious to do so.  I appreciate Deputy Connaughton's concern in that respect.</P>
      <P>Deputy Fennell and Deputy Barnes brought up the subject of women in that situation pre-1973; it is a very big question which would mean giving credits and pension entitlements over a long period which, obviously, would mean an enormous financial cost.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MonicaBarnes" hpid="Mrs. Barnes Mrs. Barnes">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Barnes</NameTxt>
      <P>The years previous to 1973 should not be counted.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Acting Chairman Acting Chairman">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister, without interruption, please.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelJWoods" hpid="Dr. Woods Dr. Woods">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Woods</NameTxt>
      <P>Deputy Stagg raised the question of the extension of the maternity allowance but the number involved would be extremely small because we are now extending it to every woman, down to those earning £25 per week, which is a very large extension.  At any rate, people in such situations may be covered by disability or other benefits.  I am sure Deputy Stagg realises this is a major extension of the full benefits under the scheme.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Deputy Browne also raised the question of <i>pro rata</i>&mdash; he is getting smart at using the sections.  He mentioned farmers in relation to <i>pro rata</i>, which is another possibility worthy of consideration.  I will certainly bear his points in mind.  Deputy Byrne has been very patient as we drifted from his amendment.  However, there are two things I should like him to note, the <Col N="2113" /> first is that the subsection following the one to which he refers points out that this is just for one year because of the complexity and need to deal urgently with what would really be minute, technical matters.  The relevant matters are identified and covered and we know what we will be dealing with.  It is to avoid delay that there is a limitation of one year.  It is a very important section in that we are solving, once and for all, the problem of people with mixed insurance which will be of great benefit to workers such as those in CIE who were mentioned by Deputy Byrne and Deputy Wallace.</P>
    <P>The issues involved are very complex and there may not be sufficient time to have a sitting of the Dáil to discuss them. In practice, it is not necessary because they are largely minor, technical amendments. However, if Deputy Byrne, or any other Deputy, does not agree with an amendment there is power to have it brought back to this House.  Deputy Byrne brings this up every time because, as I said before, he never trusts us in these situations, nevertheless he has never had to bring an amendment back to the House.</P>
    <P>As I said, this will benefit workers in CIE who have lost out because of promotion over the years.  The mixed insurance can also arise where a person has been insured for periods under Irish social welfare legislation and who goes to work in another EC member state.  They must be facilitated under the new arrangements.  There could also be people with a career spanning 40 years, who were insured in Ireland for maybe ten years and insured somewhere else for another period, within the EC.  We have completed an agreement with Austria and Canada in relation to the interchange of pensions and I hope, by the time the Dáil again meets, to have signed an agreement with Australia; indeed, I hope it will not be too long before we sign an agreement with America.  In doing all these things so urgently and rapidly, we need certain flexibility.  These reciprocal arrangements are being fitted in on a <i>pro rata</i> basis.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="2114" /> There are many technical considerations and that is why the section is drafted in this way.  I have a document on the real complexities but I will not bother Deputies with them because they are all minor, technical and administrative things&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    <Speaker pid="PaulConnaughton" hpid="Mr. Connaughton Mr. Connaughton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Connaughton</NameTxt>
      <P>We will leave it in the Minister's good hands.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MonicaBarnes" hpid="Mrs. Barnes Mrs. Barnes">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Barnes</NameTxt>
      <P>We trust him.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelJWoods" hpid="Dr. Woods Dr. Woods">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Woods</NameTxt>
      <P>Deputies have looked for a section of this kind for some time and it has been discussed many times in the past.  It is 30 years this year since the old age contributory pension scheme was introduced in 1961 and I am happy to be introducing this reform in relation to people who have mixed insurance; it is a very valuable development and benefit and a nice way of commemorating the 30th anniversary of the introduction of a pension scheme.  I know that Deputy Barnes and Deputy Fennell would like to see further developments and I will keep their points in mind.  However, I oppose the amendment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryFlaherty" hpid="Miss Flaherty Miss Flaherty">
      <NameTxt>Miss Flaherty</NameTxt>
      <P>I welcome this opportunity to make three points.  I very much welcome the fact that the Minister in the Bill is giving effect to the changes and extending <i>pro rata</i> pensions to the group of mixed contributors whose situation we debated at length the last time a Social Welfare Bill was before the House.  I am glad the Minister was convinced by the telling arguments made by this side of the House and that he found a solution to the problems which he thought were insoluble.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelJWoods" hpid="Dr. Woods Dr. Woods">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Woods</NameTxt>
      <P>I never thought the problems were insoluble.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryFlaherty" hpid="Miss Flaherty Miss Flaherty">
      <NameTxt>Miss Flaherty</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister previously said it was a very difficult problem.  I was encouraged to come into the House and row in behind my colleagues who are now raising the issue of another group, women affected by the marriage bar.  Inevitably in the rationalisation of <i>pro rata</i> pension <Col N="2115" /> entitlements and equivalent contributions, if we bring in one group every other group is excluded.  It is anomalous.</P>
      <P>We want to prioritise a group of women who have suffered from a bar from employment on marriage.  We would like that looked at in the next round of improvements in this legislation.  I was interested to hear Deputy Wallace localising it after I had had a phone call from one of the members of a Dublin pensioners group who is badly affected. Those members retired on a small pension and this will make a great difference to them.  I tried to reassure them, and I would like the Minister to reassure us and them.  Will he clarify the date he has in mind?  I am sorry I was not involved in the detailed discussion but I ask him to indicate when he intends to implement this provision.  It may be that all the contributors are entitled to this.  They are concerned about the date in 1991 and its relationship to them.  Will they qualify from the date of the implementation of the legislation for <i>pro rata</i> pensions exactly similar to the intermittent contributors who were awarded <i>pro rata</i> pensions?  I hope that will be a reality for them during this financial year.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EricJByrne" hpid="Mr. Byrne Mr. Byrne">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Byrne</NameTxt>
      <P>This debate has covered a wider range of issues than the amendment before us.</P>
      <P>
        <i>(Interruptions.)</i>
      </P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EricJByrne" hpid="Mr. Byrne Mr. Byrne">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Byrne</NameTxt>
      <P>The Deputies are looking resplendent sitting nicely over there.  I am very conscious of the time.  I disagree with the Minister but I am not going to fight with him.  However, it is incorrect that we should give him the right to bring in orders on such an important issue.  I will not be pushing this amendment to a vote; I will be pushing it to a verbal vote, if that is permissible.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I want to refer briefly to another matter which has been ruled out of order, a standardising of the maternity provision. I want to record my opposition to that move which provides for the abolition of an allowance.  I feel it is in breach of <Col N="2116" /> the <i>Programme for Economic and Social Progress</i> which calls for an increase in rates of social welfare benefits.  The abolition of that scheme will affect many women who are clearly entitled to maternity&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    <Speaker pid="JamesCTunney" hpid="An Leas-Cheann Comhairle Jim Tunney">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Cheann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>Deputy Byrne, initially you were inclined to castigate people who went outside Standing Orders but your good resolution has disappeared.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EricJByrne" hpid="Mr. Byrne Mr. Byrne">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Byrne</NameTxt>
      <P>May I add one final sentence? I have been so tolerant of everybody else.  Many women will not be entitled to any payments at childbirth when they most need financial support.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesCTunney" hpid="An Leas-Cheann Comhairle Jim Tunney">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Cheann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>The question is: &ldquo;That the words proposed to be deleted stand&rdquo;.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EmmetStagg" hpid="Mr. Stagg Mr. Stagg">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Stagg</NameTxt>
      <P>Amendment No. 16 has been ruled out of order and we were advised by the Ceann Comhairle&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesCTunney" hpid="An Leas-Cheann Comhairle Jim Tunney">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Cheann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>We have not come to amendment No. 16 yet.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelJWoods" hpid="Dr. Woods Dr. Woods">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Woods</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 15:</P>
      <P>In page 22, line 40, to delete &ldquo;proposes&rdquo; and substitute &ldquo;purposes&rdquo;.</P>
      <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesCTunney" hpid="An Leas-Cheann Comhairle Jim Tunney">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Cheann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>Amendment No. 16 has been ruled out of order.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelJWoods" hpid="Dr. Woods Dr. Woods">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Woods</NameTxt>
      <P>May I say one word?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EmmetStagg" hpid="Mr. Stagg Mr. Stagg">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Stagg</NameTxt>
      <P>The Ceann Comhairle ruled that we may make a passing reference to amendments that were ruled out of order.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesCTunney" hpid="An Leas-Cheann Comhairle Jim Tunney">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Cheann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>That was in an exceptional case.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EmmetStagg" hpid="Mr. Stagg Mr. Stagg">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Stagg</NameTxt>
      <P>No, it was not.  He made <Col N="2117" /> an exception early in the debate and said subsequently that Deputies who had amendments ruled out of order might make a passing reference to the amendments.</P>
      <P>
        <i>(Interruptions.)</i>
      </P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EmmetStagg" hpid="Mr. Stagg Mr. Stagg">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Stagg</NameTxt>
      <P>The point I wish to make is that at present somebody may be deliberately misleading the Department of Social Welfare or giving false information. Over-payments cannot be recovered where the Department make a mistake and pay, say, £1 per week to somebody for ten years.  The person may not know he or she was being overpaid. Will the Minister give a direction on that?  It was dealt with in our amendment which was ruled&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesCTunney" hpid="An Leas-Cheann Comhairle Jim Tunney">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Cheann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>The Deputy's is a voice crying in the wilderness.  The Minister cannot reply.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EricJByrne" hpid="Mr. Byrne Mr. Byrne">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Byrne</NameTxt>
      <P>He cannot hear.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesCTunney" hpid="An Leas-Cheann Comhairle Jim Tunney">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Cheann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>The Deputy is using his ingenuity.  It is entirely out of order that we address ourselves to amendments that are ruled out of order. The occupant of the Chair decides what is appropriate in the mind of the occupant of the Chair.  The amendment is not in order now, bearing in mind that we have less than one hour to go to refer to what is in order.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EricJByrne" hpid="Mr. Byrne Mr. Byrne">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Byrne</NameTxt>
      <P>I wish to record my opposition.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelJWoods" hpid="Dr. Woods Dr. Woods">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Woods</NameTxt>
      <P>We are talking to the media.  The Deputies are misrepresenting matters and I cannot reply to what they are saying.  I am making a protest.  We have rules and we should stay within those rules.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EmmetStagg" hpid="Mr. Stagg Mr. Stagg">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Stagg</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister broke the rules on Second Stage and Committee Stage.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EricJByrne" hpid="Mr. Byrne Mr. Byrne">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Byrne</NameTxt>
      <P>I suggest we stay within the rules now.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="2118" />
      <i>(Interruptions.)</i>
    </P>
    <Speaker pid="JamesCTunney" hpid="An Leas-Cheann Comhairle Jim Tunney">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Cheann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>Let us compose ourselves again for private meditation.  Let him or her who is without sin&mdash;&mdash;</P>
      <P>Amendment No. 16 not moved.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PaulConnaughton" hpid="Mr. Connaughton Mr. Connaughton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Connaughton</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 17:</P>
      <P>In page 28, between lines 41 and 42, to insert the following:</P>
      <P>&ldquo;41.&mdash;The Department of Social Welfare shall appoint an officer to counsel bereaved persons on the cost of funerals, especially in the Dublin region, and to assist them in any way possible.&rdquo;.</P>
      <P>We had a wide-ranging debate yesterday and will have an even more wide ranging one now.  We are going from womb to tomb.</P>
      <P>
        <i>(Interruptions.)</i>
      </P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesCTunney" hpid="An Leas-Cheann Comhairle Jim Tunney">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Cheann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>We will see to it that Deputy Connaughton does not spell that Tuam and localise it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MonicaBarnes" hpid="Mrs. Barnes Mrs. Barnes">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Barnes</NameTxt>
      <P>He would if he could.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PaulConnaughton" hpid="Mr. Connaughton Mr. Connaughton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Connaughton</NameTxt>
      <P>This very serious amendment was tabled by my colleague, Deputy Gay Mitchell who has been making noise about it for a long time.  The amendment asks that the Department of Social Welfare appoint an officer to counsel bereaved persons on the costs of funerals especially in the Dublin region. I would extend that to the whole country and that the officer assist in any way possible.  There is no doubt in anybody's mind that exorbitant profits are made on funerals.  It would appear that at a time when families are extremely vulnerable and under great pressure and are not in a position to think straight, there are unnecessary costs.  It has become the norm now to charge huge prices.  There is no need for me to itemise the costs. People within the trade tell me that there <Col N="2119" /> is as much as £400 mark-up per coffin between the coffin maker and the undertaker who supplies it to the family.  There is also the cost of supplying hackney cars and taxis, which must be the dearest taxi service in Europe per mile.  We are not talking about a few pounds but about a couple of hundred pounds for taxis.  The Department of Social Welfare are in a position to give information so that people would know to what extent they are being ripped off.  It would be difficult to stop it if people wanted to pay that sort of money out, but some people do not.</P>
      <P>Surely the Director of Consumer Affairs and Fair Trade should have a role where exorbitant profits are being made. While I am not calling for price control it seems that if this is left to market forces things will not improve because there does not appear to be real competition between undertakers.  This is not confined to Dublin.  It seems that undertakers are masters of their own patch and for some strange reason there is no competition in that area.  I note that where undertakers tried to get off the ground, to give a new service in a new area, the failure rate is extremely high.  It is almost impossible for a new undertaker to make a success of this business.  They are nobbled before they get a chance to make a name for themselves.  The lack of competition is a serious matter for families at their most vulnerable.  I was told recently not to get upset about the cost of funerals having regard to what couples spend when they are getting married.  One cannot equate the two because at the marriage stage, they have a choice.</P>
      <P>A counselling service is very important. There should be some access to the Office of the Director of Consumer Affairs and Fair Trade to ensure that people get value for money and that they are not ripped off.  That is a reasonable request.  I hope the Minister will take it on board and do what is possible, thousands of families will be ever grateful to him.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>There are two things in Ireland that are <Col N="2120" /> taboo &mdash; death and the cost of funerals, graves and so on.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MonicaBarnes" hpid="Mrs. Barnes Mrs. Barnes">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Barnes</NameTxt>
      <P>There are a couple of other taboos as well.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PaulConnaughton" hpid="Mr. Connaughton Mr. Connaughton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Connaughton</NameTxt>
      <P>There is, Deputy, but we will not go into that today.  Things relating to death are taboo probably out of respect for the after life, but a funeral is very costly at the moment.  This issue should be taken extremely seriously.  I have no doubt that if the Minister can do something about it he will only be too glad to do it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesCTunney" hpid="An Leas-Cheann Comhairle Jim Tunney">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Cheann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>I would advise the House that I have intimations from so many Deputies that if we do not have brevity the Report Stage will be buried with this amendment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WillieODea" hpid="Mr. O'Dea Mr. O'Dea">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Dea</NameTxt>
      <P>I agree with much of what Deputy Connaughton said, but I wonder if the amendment as drafted is the best way to solve this very real problem.  Is it a proper function from the Department of Social Welfare to appoint an officer to advise people about the cost of funerals and so on?  Deputy Connaughton suggested that there seems to be a cartel operating in various regions.  If that is true, and there is a considerable body of evidence to support it, it is illogical to appoint an officer from the Department of Social Welfare to advise people.  If a cartel is operating, and prices are fixed between these undertakers, what would be the function of the officer appointed by the Department?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I would argue that the amendment as drafted is unconstitutional because it is based on the supposition that Dublin was the equivalent of Ireland.  I represent a city where we encounter the same type of problems to which Deputy Mitchell and Deputy Connaughton have rightly drawn attention.  The cost of funerals in Limerick city has gone out of all proportion in the last few years.  The best way to solve this is to increase the death grant and to increase the funeral grant for people who do not qualify for a death grant because of insurance record.  We <Col N="2121" /> should bring the death grant more into line with the cost of the funeral.  The cost in Limerick city bears no relationship to the amount of the death grant.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PaulConnaughton" hpid="Mr. Connaughton Mr. Connaughton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Connaughton</NameTxt>
      <P>Would not that be a subsidy for the undertaker, Deputy?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WillieODea" hpid="Mr. O'Dea Mr. O'Dea">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Dea</NameTxt>
      <P>Some other Minister might be able to do something to control prices. Perhaps this Minister can do something about it.  However some sort of price control should be imposed in this area as it is causing a real problem.  I want the Minister to bear that in mind.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EmmetStagg" hpid="Mr. Stagg Mr. Stagg">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Stagg</NameTxt>
      <P>The amendment was put down to deal with a specific Dublin situation described in detail in the House on Second Stage by Deputy Mitchell.  He said there is a cartel operating in this city and a person can pay £2,500 for a funeral which should only cost £800 to £1,000. The amendment is to deal with that situation. I am not sure if it is appropriate, but I can see what the Deputy is trying to do.  In Kildare there is decent competition among people who provide this service.  We also have a system of putting the clamps on them if they do not do the right thing.  There are a number of mortality societies who effectively put a curb on cartel activities.  The mortality society in my area was 250 years old in 1975.  They have quite a large membership and they vet the rates from various undertakers and their wares, on a voluntary basis.  They then tell their members who provides the best value. We take in some Dublin undertakers as well.  The price of a funeral is about £750 in Kildare.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>When people are bereaved they certainly need assistance and they regularly get counselling assistance from public representatives.  People may also visit them a few days after the funeral to look after their needs, but that does not always happen.  Politicians do not know everybody who dies.  Relatives are sometimes left without assistance.  I would see health board social workers having a role rather than the Department of Social Welfare. <Col N="2122" /> The death grant is very welcome assistance towards costs.  When supplementary welfare allowance is needed, the health board are involved.  I am not sure that this amendment should be pressed.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JohnBrowne1" hpid="Mr. Browne (Carlow-Kilkenny) Mr. Browne (Carlow-Kilkenny)">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Browne</NameTxt>
      <P>
        <i>(Carlow-Kilkenny):</i> I urge that the Minister should accept the first part of the suggestion, namely, that the Department of Social Welfare should appoint an officer to counsel bereaved persons.  People are at their most vulnerable at a time of bereavement.  Very intelligent people become almost irrational and unable to make decisions. There should be a person who can be called upon to help them.  Health board officers may be over-worked but they are in a position to give advice.  We can never prepare for death.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesCTunney" hpid="An Leas-Cheann Comhairle Jim Tunney">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Cheann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>Deputy Ivor Callely.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EricJByrne" hpid="Mr. Byrne Mr. Byrne">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Byrne</NameTxt>
      <P>On a point of order, with due respect I challenge your choice of speaker.  I am the spokesman on Social Welfare for The Workers' Party.  Spokesmen should be called before back benchers.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesCTunney" hpid="An Leas-Cheann Comhairle Jim Tunney">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Cheann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>In respect of Report Stage debate, preference is given to the party in whose name an amendment appears.  After that the proportion of Deputies in respect of the parties is taken into account.  Having called a Deputy from the Government side, I will call Deputy Byrne.  I have already called the spokesperson for the third major party.  Surely what Deputy Byrne has to say will not go cold.  I call Deputy Callely.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="IvorCallely" hpid="Mr. Callely Mr. Callely">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Callely</NameTxt>
      <P>I appreciate the sentiments expressed in Deputy Mitchell's amendment and I congratulate him on his work in this area.  We can all share Deputy Connaughton's sentiments with regard to the cost of funerals.  Funeral costs in the Dublin area range from £1,500 to £2,500.  It must be recognised that the cost is related to the services provided.  Deputy Connaughton did not <Col N="2123" /> refer to that point.  He quoted a figure of £400 as the profit on a coffin.</P>
      <P>I agree that people may become irrational at a time of bereavement when organising a funeral.  Members of the family may come from abroad and have to be provided with transport.  This may necessitate hiring three mourning cars and a hearse and they may opt for additional services which are offered in the Dublin area.  It must be recognised that many funeral undertakers are left with uncollected debts.  Families arrange more elaborate funerals than they can afford and they then seek assistance in recovering the costs.  Speakers have referred to the high profits made by undertakers but many of us recognise the good work they do.  It might not be appropriate for the Department of Social Welfare to appoint an officer to counsel bereaved persons, but when families are organising funerals some indication of the costs should be given.</P>
      <P>I would make a special plea to the Minister regarding money which most elderly people have saved to pay for their funerals.  Perhaps this should not be taken into account by the Department of Social Welfare when carrying out means tests for non-contributory old age pensions. The Minister might accommodate that suggestion by allowing people to set aside a reasonable and appropriate amount to cover the cost of a funeral.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EricJByrne" hpid="Mr. Byrne Mr. Byrne">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Byrne</NameTxt>
      <P>Community welfare officers will no doubt have briefed the Minister as to the incredible demand for assistance by bereaved families.  The cost of funerals in Dublin city is astronomical and absolutely disproportionate to the expenses incurred by the funeral organisers. There is a sad commercialisation in the events surrounding a death.  The bereaved are offered a wide range of fittings for coffins, at high prices.  The coffins are very often veneered chipboard that looks like solid mahogany to the untrained eye.  People are tempted by the salespersons in the funeral home with a range of items to adorn the coffin and it is only when the bills arrive after the <Col N="2124" /> funeral that they get the real shock and discover the cost.  The irony is that the cost of dying is no problem to the rich but it is a problem for the poor.  The old traditional method of carrying the coffin shoulder high to the church and often, depending on its proximity, to the cemetery has died out to a large degree. People have drifted towards using funeral parlours, where the body reposes for a number of days.  People are offered all sorts of additional services, such as embalming and unfortunately they feel obliged to use these services.  The poorer people in the community cannot afford cars and generally in their circle of family and friends, many people would not have motor cars at their disposal.  By implication they are forced to use the funeral home's cars at an extremely prohibitive rate.</P>
      <P>The amendment has merit.  We should certainly examine why the death grant is disproportionate to the overall cost of burial.  The death grant has fallen considerably. If there was a proper national insurance system covering everyone in the State, we might be able to overcome that problem.  We might consider whether it is possible that the local authorities, who own and manage the cemeteries, might provide the whole range of services that are needed.  Competition in this area should make the service more cost effective.  This would be of great benefit to all, especially disadvantaged families, in burying their dead.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GayMitchell" hpid="Mr. G. Mitchell Mr. G. Mitchell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. G. Mitchell</NameTxt>
      <P>I hope we will not have to press this matter to a division.  I hope there will be agreement in the House on it.  I know I am right &mdash;&ldquo;dead right&rdquo; if I may use that term.  In my amendment I refer to the cost of funerals &ldquo;especially in the Dublin region&rdquo;.  There may be a problem outside Dublin but I know it is a particular problem in Dublin.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The maximum cost of an average funeral in Dublin &mdash; although the undertakers will tell you there is no such thing as an average funeral &mdash; should be £800 for a hearse, one mourning car and a coffin.  It should range somewhere <Col N="2125" /> between £600 and £800.  There are undertakers on the periphery of Dublin, in Sallynoggin or Swords or outside the county in Blessington who will do a funeral for a maximum of £800 but people in the city are paying at a minimum twice or three times the amount.  It is very difficult to break into the undertaking business and provide competition.  If you were to set up as an undertaker in the morning you would have to hire limousines for occasional use because it would not be cost effective to buy them.  That is what undertakers do, However, if somebody is honest enough to hire out their limousines to somebody new to the business, the other undertakers will have nothing more to do with him.  That is how they freeze people out of the business and operate their monopoly.</P>
    <P>I brought this matter to the attention to the House reluctantly, having failed to have a debate or a discussion with the funeral directors in Dublin who, I have to say were arrogant and treated me with disdain.  They have given me licence to raise this matter in this way &mdash; and on their heads be it.  I will not let this matter rest today.  I intend to pursue this matter. It is outrageous that when people are at their lowest ebb and vulnerable and often alone, and when all they want is the best for their loved one who has passed away, they are not given the opportunity to have this service provided in Dublin city, in particular, at a reasonable cost.  This is wholly unacceptable.  I would advise people to shop around, to go to the periphery of the county or to adjoining counties and they will find they do not have to pay the huge sums one has to pay to undertakers in the city.</P>
    <P>I would ask the undertakers to come clean.  Why do they not open their books and say what they are charging?  Why do they not debate this issue?  Why have they this arrogant attitude that they have nothing to say on the matter and they intend to continue as they are?  I do not intend that they be allowed to continue as they are.  I ask the House to approve this amendment so that independent counselling will be available for bereaved persons and they can be advised about <Col N="2126" /> the funeral arrangements, instead of somebody with a funeral face, like a tailor's dummy, coming to them and offering them sympathy and taking their money.  The funeral undertakers of Dublin city are taking money which they should not be taking in order to keep themselves in the lifestyle they have become used to.</P>
    <P>The cost of a hearse and a mourning car in Dublin is about £420, as I have already said on Second Stage.  The journeys in Dublin, unlike the country, are very short.  The longest distance would be from the city centre to Deansgrange, more often it is Crumlin or somewhere on the south side to Mount Jerome, or somewhere on the north side of Glasnevin and these are very short distances. People are asked to pay £420 for what in reality is a short taxi ride &mdash; the hiring of a vehicle to carry the remains of the loved one and a vehicle for the others.  In all honesty, if anybody asked you for £420 for a taxi ride, you would send for the Garda.  It is really far too much.  I regret having to raise this issue in this House because there are certain sensitivities in these matters.  We have all been through bereavement, some more than others but every citizen will face it for certain, every family will face it at some time.  I find it unacceptable that a sector in the city in particular can ignore this House and ignore public representatives and arrogate into themselves the power to decide what they will charge in a situation where citizens are vulnerable.  That is not in the public interest.  I ask the Minister to accept this amendment.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JamesCTunney" hpid="An Leas-Cheann Comhairle Jim Tunney">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Cheann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>I am calling Deputy Kitt.  I would like to remind him that I hope to call Deputies Browne, Wyse and Boylan and, of course, the Minister, before we conclude.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TomKitt" hpid="Mr. T. Kitt Mr. T. Kitt">
      <NameTxt>Mr. T. Kitt</NameTxt>
      <P>I appreciate that fact, a Leas-Cheann Comhairle.  Deputy Mitchell has raised a very legitimate issue on which he will find agreement across party lines today.  However, I question whether he is dealing with it in the right way by asking us to amend the Social Welfare <Col N="2127" /> Bill to deal with this issue.  To his credit, by raising this issue both in the House and outside it, I hope he has gone some way in taking on the undertakers in the Dublin region who obviously are over-charging.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EricJByrne" hpid="Mr. Byrne Mr. Byrne">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Byrne</NameTxt>
      <P>Are you excluding Deputy Stafford from that?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TomKitt" hpid="Mr. T. Kitt Mr. T. Kitt">
      <NameTxt>Mr. T. Kitt</NameTxt>
      <P>The Deputy has a reputation of taking on vested interests in his capacity as a Dáil Deputy.  That is a legitimate thing to do and other Deputies should be encouraged to do so also. There is a problem with the cost of funerals in the Dublin region.  Deputies in neighbouring counties have given examples of the minimal cost involved outside the Dublin region.  Families are hit with this problem suddenly when a bereavement takes place and they are at their most vulnerable.  It is not the role of a State Department to carry out this function which amounts, basically, to advising people on the cost of funerals.  As other Deputies have also said, counselling is very important for a family faced with bereavement.  Counselling should be extended after the bereavement to help a family overcome the loss of a loved one and the health boards should be involved in that area because the health board have staff on the ground who know the people locally.  To involve the Department in a formal or statutory way would be going about it the wrong way.  I say that while recognising that this is an important issue that should be addressed.</P>
      <P>The health boards could fulfil this role in regard to costs in a very simple way by issuing a price list which the Minister for Social Welfare with his colleague the Minister for Health could draw up and have displayed in the local health centre so that people would be aware of what is involved.  Counselling takes place afterwards in a natural way with priests, neighbours, family friends and, as Deputy Stagg said, politicians, who visit families after funerals.  That type of conselling should be part and parcel of any service.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The undertakers themselves might take a look at the service they provide. <Col N="2128" /> I know many good undertakers and I certainly hope we are talking here about just a few who are taking advantage of the situation.  The undertakers might look formally at the service they provide and include within that service some type of counselling in the aftermath.</P>
    <P>I hope the Director of Consumer Affairs will be noting this debate.  We are talking about the marketplace and, at the end of the day, I hope the public will be aware of the wide differences nationally in prices of funerals.  I also feel that the tax system should be used in a more liberal and progressive way to ease the burden of the costs on those who have to pay these very astronomical bills.  Deputy Mitchell has raised a legitimate point but I do not share his view that we should include this provision in a Bill.  This is a lobby group for a particular area and there are others.  The Social Welfare Bill is complex enough without including specific measures to involve a State Department in providing this counselling service.  It is a desirable objective but not one that should be slotted into this type of statutory function.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PearseWyse" hpid="Mr. Wyse Mr. Wyse">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Wyse</NameTxt>
      <P>I agree totally.  I do not think this could be included in the Social Welfare Bill because it covers a very wide field now.  However, I am glad that we are highlighting an abuse that is going on throughout the country where undertaking is concerned.  Not all undertakers are involved.</P>
      <P>I would like to see the voluntary community councils involving themselves in this kind of work.  Community councils are parish organisations and they should be involved in educating the community about their rights and the cost of funerals within their own parish.  I make this suggestion because I know the work of community associations who do so much on a vuluntary basis and they could be of tremendous help to people in this area.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnBrowne2" hpid="Mr. Browne (Wexford) Mr. Browne (Wexford)">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Browne</NameTxt>
      <P>
        <i>(Wexford):</i> This has been debated.  There seems to be a serious problem in Dublin with regard to the cost of funerals.  We should not, however, <Col N="2129" /> give the impression that this is widespread. In the south-east we have honourable and decent undertakers and the average cost of funerals in that region is about £700.  For people in receipt of social welfare benefit funeral undertakers will do a funeral for as low as £450.  If the problem is so widespread in Dublin perhaps Deputy Mitchell and the other Deputies should compile a list of those who are overcharging and have it publicly displayed so that people will know what undertakers not to deal with.  I would not like the impression to go from this House that all undertakers around the country are ripping people off.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="AndrewBoylan" hpid="Mr. Boylan Mr. Boylan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Boylan</NameTxt>
      <P>The Government are totally missing the point that Deputy Mitchell has made.  He has put forward a valid case for counselling for families who are bereaved.  Broadly speaking, undertakers are honourable and decent people. I certainly find that to be the case in my county of Cavan.  They will do proper undertaking and so on for bereaved families and they will outline the costs involved.</P>
      <P>There is a commendable desire on the part of families who are bereaved to do the decent thing and do it well and not to be seen to be shoddy in their treatment of the deceased person.  In some cases, the undertaker having outlined the costs, people will go for the best when they cannot afford it and it is only in the weeks afterwards that the realisation that they went overboard dawns.  That is where counselling at the time of bereavement would help to advise people of the costs involved.  It would be wrong to comment specifically on families on social welfare, but they seem to be more vulnerable in cases like this and less aware of the fact that at the end of the day the total costs will have to be met.  These people will later be coming back to the Department of Social Welfare looking for help to pay these costs, so counselling at the time of bereavement would save the taxpayer and the Department money.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>There is an added problem in my county of Cavan.  Previously when a person died at home the undertaker came <Col N="2130" /> and there was the usual organisation of the burial, the notification for the papers, organising the grave and the grave diggers, providing a hearse and a car if necessary, and all this is quite costly.  Now there is the added expense of organising the road to the chapel and the road to the graveyard.  It is now commonplace in Cavan for the undertaken, who takes on all the work involved in a funeral, to organise neighbours and Cavan County Council to come out and do a hurried job on the road to fill the potholes so that the hearse can travel with some dignity without hobbling and wobbling.  Deputies may think this is a joke, but it is an added cost.  Of course neighbours will sometimes do it voluntarily, but at the same time there has to be some appreciation of the work they have done by way of a few drinks or a few pounds set aside for them.  That is an added cost because the Government do not care what is happening in the country.  The social workers could get involved in that again because this is a fact of life now.  Not to take away from Deputy Mitchell's case&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelJWoods" hpid="Dr. Woods Dr. Woods">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Woods</NameTxt>
      <P>Whose motion is about Dublin only.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="AndrewBoylan" hpid="Mr. Boylan Mr. Boylan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Boylan</NameTxt>
      <P>I am only developing the point for the Minister's benefit because there is a reluctance here to discuss any issue that concerns the country in this House.  There is a problem which may not altogether be the making of the undertakers but of families who get carried away at a time when a counsellor would advise them to take it easy, that a certain amount will do and that they are doing the decent thing.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DanWallace" hpid="Mr. D. Wallace Mr. D. Wallace">
      <NameTxt>Mr. D. Wallace</NameTxt>
      <P>Had Deputy Boylan read the amendment he might have made a rather different contribution because we are being asked here to legislate for Dublin which we cannot do.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Deputies Deputies">
      <NameTxt>Deputies</NameTxt>
      <P>Hear, hear.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="AndrewBoylan" hpid="Mr. Boylan Mr. Boylan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Boylan</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not have to take chastisement from Deputy Wallace.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="2131" />
    <Speaker pid="DanWallace" hpid="Mr. D. Wallace Mr. D. Wallace">
      <NameTxt>Mr. D. Wallace</NameTxt>
      <P>I compliment Deputy Gay Mitchell &mdash; one of the most outspoken Members of this House &mdash; because it is important that an issue such as this be brought to the attention of the public, not necessarily the Minister. Sometimes when one speaks out the people involved, in this case the undertakers, do listen.  If there is a particular problem in Dublin it should be dealt with.</P>
      <P>I have heard no complaints in Cork. It could well be said that all aspects of funerals today have changed; probably the only aspect that has remained unchanged is the requiem mass.  It would appear to me that some speakers have missed the point &mdash; talking about social workers, health boards and community welfare officers &mdash; because those people are responding already in a very positive manner to a very sensitive need.</P>
      <P>Ireland is not composed of Dublin alone and, if there is a problem there it should be dealt with.  Certainly it is not for the Minister to introduce legislation to deal with this problem.  There are procedures to deal with people who are not sufficiently sensitive or caring in treating people at such times.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DermotFitzpatrickFF" hpid="Dr. Fitzpatrick Dr. Fitzpatrick">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Fitzpatrick</NameTxt>
      <P>Unfortunately my constituency colleague is not here to represent his interests.  Nonetheless I felt a few words would be appropriate to defend&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EmmetStagg" hpid="Mr. Stagg Mr. Stagg">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Stagg</NameTxt>
      <P>Is he offering bargains?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DermotFitzpatrickFF" hpid="Dr. Fitzpatrick Dr. Fitzpatrick">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Fitzpatrick</NameTxt>
      <P>&mdash;&mdash;undertakers who, from my experience, treat people with sensitivity and care at times of bereavement. Deputy Gay Mitchell's constituency, not being the premier one in the country, encounters problems with undertakers there.  I can say they are excellent in my constituency.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I might add that the Department of Social Welfare, through their community welfare officers, help people in meeting undertakers' bills which may or may not be widely known.  On occasion I have had to contact a community welfare officer on behalf of constituents and I have found <Col N="2132" /> them extremely helpful in a social and financial sense at such difficult times.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelJWoods" hpid="Dr. Woods Dr. Woods">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Woods</NameTxt>
      <P>Deputy Kitt raised a question about the tax allowance.  There is an extra tax allowance of £4,100 being granted this year to widows or widowers &mdash; as distinct from the immediate costs of a funeral &mdash; covering the period after the bereavement.  I am quite sure Deputy Gay Mitchell will feel this amendment has been sufficiently aired and that there is a good deal of support for the views he was expressing.</P>
      <P>As a number of Deputies have pointed out, in its entirety, this is not an appropriate amendment on this Bill.  For instance, that part of it that refers to counselling I would regard as forming part of our information and support service as we develop our one-stop shops and general support for the community. I would see us having a very definite role there.  On the competition aspect &mdash; which is what the Deputy is speaking of principally &mdash; it is a matter of the cost and the immediacy of the problem.  No matter who is in a social welfare office or in a health board there will be a difficulty about the immediacy of the problem.</P>
      <P>Deputy Stagg brought an interesting point to bear on the discussion when he spoke about mortality societies.  Deputy Wyse also asked: what can the community itself do on a voluntary basis locally? In that way people may be advised or may receive information which can be passed around about prices and become involved in the competitive element. There is no doubt but that counselling is needed at the point of bereavement but a question does arise about costing.  As some Members have said, through health boards and community welfare officers, arrangements can be made.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>As I understand it, one of the difficulties encountered by health boards is that people do not approach them soon enough.  Consequently, such bereaved people are not aware even of some of the contract-type arrangements health boards make; it may not be until after the event that somebody points them in the direction of the health board.  This is <Col N="2133" /> all tied in with the very nature of bereavement and its attendant difficulties.  We are doing a number of things to help people in those circumstances, for example, the continuing payments, following on death, for dependent spouses or children for six weeks.  That recognises the need for assistance at the point of bereavement.</P>
    <P>I am very much in tune with Deputy Gay Mitchell in that we need to increase the information available through our offices.  This is the kind of matter I would see departmental officers being involved in, particularly immediately after the event but, because of the immediacy, it is very difficult for anyone to be right on the spot.  We do everything we can to facilitate early and simple payment and to continue payments such as invalidity, or others, for six weeks.  We have done quite a number of things in that regard.</P>
    <P>Members may be interested to know that we have also undertaken a study, in conjunction with the National Association of Widows of Ireland, of bereavement and its effects, and what actually happens in practice.  That was with a view to providing the right advice before and afterwards so far as we can.  Incidentally, nowadays many parishes have bereavement counselling sessions, reverting to the point raised by Deputy Wyse.  I would appeal to funeral undertakers to advise relatives at the time of death.  Very often it will be a relative who will approach the undertaker saying: we want to do the best for the family which may entail three cars and various other services for them.  I know that in some cases they have been very helpful where bills have had to be paid subsequently.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="2134" /> The major element of Deputy Mitchell's concern expressed in his amendment is competition.  Some Members raised the question of there not being proper competition and control.  As the House will know, price control was abolished by the then Government in 1986. Consequently people now feel that there is not the kind of control they would like to see obtain in given circumstances.</P>
    <P>Even though I have a lot of sympathy with what Deputy Mitchell says, I cannot accept his amendment.  As some Members on his side of the House have said, there are two aspects to it.  On that of counselling we will be doing more to improve advice, assistance and the sensitivity of dealing with widows, widowers and bereaved people generally after the event once it is brought to our notice. The health boards have a statutory role to play in that regard.  I have no doubt but that they will take on board the many points made here on this section.  I would not want Deputy Gay Mitchell to think that I am not sympathetic to the views he has expressed.  I am very sympathetic. I just do not think it is appropriate to incorporate his amendment in this Bill. As far as the general intent is concerned, I will do everything I can to progress the views he has expressed.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JamesCTunney" hpid="An Leas-Cheann Comhairle Jim Tunney">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Cheann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>In accordance with the Order of the Dáil of this day, I must now put the following question: &ldquo;That the amendments set down by the Minister for Social Welfare and not disposed of are hereby made to the Bill; that Fourth Stage is hereby completed and that the Bill is hereby passed.&rdquo;</P>
      <P>Question put.</P>
      <P Just="Center">The Dáil divided: Tá, 63; Níl, 52.</P>
      <P Just="Center">Tá</P>
    </Speaker>
    <table pgwide="1">
      <tgroup cols="2">
        <colspec colname="1" colnum="1" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <colspec colname="2" colnum="2" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry rowsep="1">Ahern, Bertie.<br />Ahern, Dermot.<br />Ahern, Michael.<br />Barrett, Michael.<br />Brady, Gerard.<br />Brady, Vincent.<br />Brennan, Mattie.<br />Browne, John (Wexford).
<Col N="2135" />de Valera, Síle.<br />Fahey, Frank.<br />Fahey, Jackie.<br />Fitzpatrick, Dermot.<br />Flood, Chris.<br />Foxe, Tom.<br />Gallagher, Pat the Cope.<br />Haughey, Charles J.<br />Hillery, Brian.<br />Hilliard, Colm.<br />Hyland, Liam.<br />Jacob, Joe.<br />Kelly, Laurence.<br />Kenneally, Brendan.<br />Kirk, Séamus.<br />Kitt, Michael P.<br />Kitt, Tom.<br />Lawlor, Liam.<br />Lenihan, Brian.<br />Leonard, Jimmy.<br />Leyden, Terry.<br />Lyons, Denis.<br />Martin, Micheál.<br /></entry>
            <entry rowsep="1">Burke, Raphael P.<br />Callely, Ivor.<br />Clohessy, Peadar.<br />Coughlan, Mary Theresa.<br />Cullimore, Séamus.<br />Daly, Brendan.<br />Dempsey, Noel.<br />Dennehy, John.
<Col N="2136" />McCreevy, Charlie.<br />McDaid, Jim.<br />McEllistrim, Tom.<br />Molloy, Robert.<br />Nolan, M.J.<br />O'Connell, John.<br />O'Dea, Willie.<br />O'Donoghue, John.<br />O'Hanlon, Rory.<br />O'Keeffe, Ned.<br />O'Leary, John.<br />O'Rourke, Mary.<br />O'Toole, Martin Joe.<br />Power, Seán.<br />Quill, Máirín.<br />Roche, Dick.<br />Smith, Michael.<br />Treacy, Noel.<br />Tunney, Jim.<br />Wallace, Dan.<br />Wallace, Mary.<br />Walsh, Joe.<br />Woods, Michael.<br />Wyse, Pearse.</entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
    <P Just="Center">íl</P>
    <table pgwide="1">
      <tgroup cols="2">
        <colspec colname="1" colnum="1" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <colspec colname="2" colnum="2" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry rowsep="1">Allen, Bernard.<br />Barnes, Monica.<br />Barry, Peter.<br />Belton, Louis J.<br />Boylan, Andrew.<br />Browne, John (Carlow-Kilkenny).<br />Bruton, John.<br />Byrne, Eric.<br />Connaughton, Paul.<br />Cosgrave, Michael Joe.<br />Creed, Michael.<br />Currie, Austin.<br />D'Arcy, Michael.<br />Doyle, Joe.<br />Dukes, Alan.<br />Durkan, Bernard.<br />Farrelly, John V.<br />Fennell, Nuala.<br />Ferris, Michael.<br />Flaherty, Mary.<br />Flanagan, Charles.<br />Garland, Roger.<br />Gilmore, Eamon.<br />Gregory, Tony.<br />Higgins, Michael D.<br />Howlin, Brendan.</entry>
            <entry rowsep="1">Kavanagh, Liam.<br />Kemmy, Jim.<br />Lowry, Michael.<br />McCormack, Pádraic.<br />McGahon, Brendan.<br />Mac Giolla, Tomás.<br />McGrath, Paul.<br />Mitchell, Gay.<br />Nealon, Ted.<br />O'Shea, Brian.<br />O'Sullivan, Gerry.<br />O'Sullivan, Toddy.<br />Owen, Nora.<br />Pattison, Séamus.<br />Quinn, Ruairí.<br />Rabbitte, Pat.<br />Reynolds, Gerry.<br />Ryan, Seán.<br />Shatter, Alan.<br />Sheehan, Patrick J.<br />Sherlock, Joe.<br />Stagg, Emmet.<br />Taylor, Mervyn.<br />Taylor-Quinn, Madeleine.<br />Timmins, Godfrey.<br />Yates, Ivan.</entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
    <P Just="Center">Tellers: Tá, Deputies V. Brady and Clohessy; Níl, Deputies Flanagan and Howlin.</P>
    <P>Question declared carried.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Radiological Protection Bill, 1990:" RHead="Report Stage (Resumed) and Final Stage">
    <Title>Radiological Protection Bill, 1990:    Report Stage (Resumed) and Final Stage.</Title>
    <P>Debate resumed on amendment No.6:</P>
    <P>In page 21, between lines 44 and 45, to insert the following:</P>
    <P>&ldquo;(9)  The Minister shall by order regulate the entry into Irish territorial waters of any foreign State ship, submarine, or hovercraft, and <Col N="2137" /> the passage through Irish airspace of any foreign State aircraft by requiring, prior to any grant of permission for such entry or passage, the production of a certificate from the relevant foreign State authority that the ship, submarine, hovercraft, or aircraft in question does not carry any nuclear explosive device.&rdquo;.</P>
    <P Just="Right">&mdash;(Deputy R. Bruton).</P>
    <Speaker pid="SeanTreacy" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Seán Treacy">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>Deputy Richard Bruton, who moved the amendment, and Deputy Roger Garland have already spoken.  Deputy Tomás Mac Giolla was in possession when the debate was adjourned.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TomasMacGiolla" hpid="Tomás Mac Giolla Tomás Mac Giolla">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Mac Giolla</NameTxt>
      <P>I was referring to my amendment No. 7 which is being taken with amendment No. 6 for discussion purposes.  Amendment No. 7 proposes that it shall be unlawful for any vessel to enter our territorial waters or for any aircraft to fly over or land in the State while carrying nuclear weapons.  It also proposes that the relevant foreign government must provide the Minister for Foreign Affairs with a written statement certifying that the vessel or craft is not carrying nuclear weapons.  This will replace the present procedure which has been in existence since the fifties.  Under this procedure the United States Government have neither to confirm nor deny that their vessels or aircraft are carrying nuclear weapons.  They are never requested to give a guarantee or statement in that regard.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>As I said the last day, Greenpeace, at great expense to themselves, have examined the records of United States vessels. Under the US Freedom of Information Act these records are freely available to the public.  There is certainly far more information available on these vessels in the United States than there is in Ireland, Britain or most countries in Europe. They examined the records of the US naval vessels which had visited Sweden. Following presentation of that information to the Swedish Government, the controversy which arose there and the <Col N="2138" /> various political decisions which have been taken, Sweden will seek guarantees after 1992 that US vessels are not carrying nuclear weapons.  The Soviet Government Procedure was not to confirm or deny: apparently they just denied it.</P>
    <P>Greenpeace also examined the records of the US vessels that visited ports in Ireland and they presented their report to Members of the House last October or November.  They found that 14 vessels had visited Irish ports between 1982-89, that ten had nuclear capability while the remainder had not.  Apparently the attitude of the Government is that there was no evidence to show that they were carrying nuclear weapons when they entered Irish ports and that is so.  The only way one can find this out is by inspecting the vessels when they enter the ports.  Greenpeace carried out an extraordinarily thorough examination of the <i>USS Conyngham</i> which visited Cobh from 8-11 July 1988 and gave information on every movement of that vessel during the six month period prior to entering Cobh on 8 July.</P>
    <P>According to the report, the hard work paid off as the <i>USS Conyngham</i> successfully completed a nuclear technical proficiency inspection with outstanding final grades prior to arriving at Cobh.  It is most likely that nuclear weapons were carried on board.  The funny thing was an Irish stowaway was discovered on board on their way home from Ireland.  It was stated in a report on the stowaway girl by Seán Cronin, in Washington, in <i>The Irish Times</i> 28 July 1988:</P>
    <P>Since the <i>USS Conyngham</i> is a guided missile destroyer, this correspondent asked the Navy spokesman whether it was armed with nuclear weapons when in Irish waters.  He gave the standard reply &mdash;&ldquo;we neither confirm nor deny that our ships have nuclear weapons.&rdquo;  However a source close to the Immigration and Naturalisation Service said that this matter came up at an INS staff meeting on Tuesday in a report which said that the State Department was keeping the incident under wraps because the destroyer had <Col N="2139" /> nuclear capability and should not have been in Irish waters.</P>
    <P>This shows that one cannot take these matters on trust.  It is clear that the nuclear powers are not going to confirm whether nuclear weapons are being carried on board and their ships will enter our ports, when allowed to do so, for the benefit of the crews and so on.  It is essential, therefore, that guarantees be sought, and certificates given, from foreign Governments when they seek permission for visits to our ports by ships with nuclear capability.  If the Government seek guarantees in writing, that would certainly be an improvement.</P>
    <P>If the Government do their homework as Greenpeace have done &mdash; this could be done with the help of our embassy in Washington &mdash; they would know which ships have nuclear capability and, consequently, which ships they would have to inspect.  All they need do is their homework. In addition, some years there can be up to 11,000 overflights while the average is approximately 7,000.</P>
    <P>I do not want to take up the time of the House as we dwelled on this matter at length on Committee Stage but there is one other point I would like to make. There are more nuclear reactors in the seas around our coasts than on land in Britain and possibly the rest of Europe. Submarines and aircraft carriers have nuclear reactors on board.  We do not know how they dispose of their waste nor do we have information on the damage they cause in the seas.  Apart from the constant danger of radioactive waste being dumped in our seas, there is also the danger of accidents similar to that involving the <i>USS Nathaniel Green</i> in 1986.  An accident could occur in fog at any time around our coast and should a nuclear powered boat or ship be involved, there is a grave danger that we could have a mini-Chernobyl.</P>
    <P>The Bill does not take any of these factors into account.  It deals only with the civil use of small amounts of radioactive material and makes no reference to nuclear weapons or nuclear powered <Col N="2140" /> boats.  I intend to press my amendment and will also support Deputy Flaherty's amendment No. 6 but which is not quite so specific because it is essential that we receive guarantees when permission is sought for overflights or visits to our ports by ships.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MaryFlaherty" hpid="Miss Flaherty Miss Flaherty">
      <NameTxt>Miss Flaherty</NameTxt>
      <P>Like Deputy Mac Giolla, I will try to avoid dealing with matters covered at an earlier stage.  I support the amendment in my name and that of Deputies Bruton and Garland which is similar to the amendment put forward by Deputy Mac Giolla.  The Minister will probably argue that traditionally this has been a matter for the Department of Foreign Affairs and he does not intend to alter this.  While a number of foreign affairs matters are involved, in making an attempt to tighten the position in this legislation we should not come into conflict with the Department of Foreign Affairs having regard to stated public policy.  A number of serious questions have been asked about this policy. Deputy Mac Giolla made reference to the Greenpeace investigation and stated that the matter is taken on trust.  It is also clear that it is the policy of countries with nuclear weapons not to give out information.  This leaves countries such as Britain, France and the United States with a free hand to act as they see fit.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Officially, our policy is much clearer. Authorisation is normally granted by the Department of Foreign Affairs for visits to our ports by foreign naval vessels provided that such vessels are not carrying nuclear weapons and do not form part of a naval exercise.  What we have proposed should not present the Department of Foreign Affairs with any great difficulty as this has been the policy of successive Governments.  Furthermore, we have to legislate for the present.  Any change in our status, which my party foresee in the context of European defence, is a matter for another day.  For now we have to introduce proper radiological protection legislation and we will not complete the job if we ignore this matter.  We suggest <Col N="2141" /> that the Minister should clear up the confusion and give some teeth in this legislation to what is, after all, official Government policy.</P>
    <P>To neglect this matter which comes under the aegis of the Department of Foreign Affairs is to leave a gaping hole in any legislation that proposes to protect this country from radiological hazard. This is a complex area and there are many ramifications.  In the context of stated Irish foreign policy at present, there should be no problem accepting an amendment along those lines which simply gives more strength to what is official policy.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelDHiggins" hpid="Mr. M. Higgins Mr. M. Higgins">
      <NameTxt>Mr. M. Higgins</NameTxt>
      <P>I support the remarks of previous speakers.  When one addresses this amendment either in terms that it comes within the ambit of another ministry or it is a matter that need not be considered within the pure view of the legislation as drafted, one is not dealing with the real world.  This amendment provokes attention between illusion and reality in a rather dramatic way.  On a number of occasions at Question Time when questions were asked about the degree of traffic entering our airspace or waters as Deputy Mac Giolla has pointed out, there have always been difficulties. The screen that has been thrown up has more or less taken the following shape: notification is required and in so far as no notification has been given we know nothing, and in knowing nothing there is no question to be answered.  The accountability of this House has been called into question several times.  Evidence has been provided to Deputies and Deputies have placed it on record that there were breaches of the law, but people have taken refuge, as Deputy Flaherty has said, in what has been an understanding, and that understanding has been abused in practice again and again.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>My second point is that, sticking tightly to the terms of this legislation, it is only to the merit of the legislation that it anticipates a situation where there would be far more accountability in the general context of politics, particularly in the context of foreign affairs, and that is likely <Col N="2142" /> to be the case.  Why should this legislation be seen as something within which attempts have been made to make it accurate and accountable while at the same time it is a cork in a sea of non-accountable nuclear abuse?  In that sense, the legislation, if it is to be valuable, must address a situation where there will be more accountability in relation to these previously normative understandings that have no force and that have been abused, as has been pointed out.  Equally if the legislation is changed as the proposed amendment suggests it will more easily fit with a better context of nuclear regulation.</P>
    <P>Another feature of the replies given again and again has been that these are matters for moral suasion, as if a large number of non-nuclear powers had the same capacity when they enter different chambers and fora where these matters are discussed as the people who have nuclear carrying capacity, which is markedly not so.  Another answer has been that these matters can be the subject of a future international conference and need not be the matter of legislative scrutiny.</P>
    <P>At the end of the day, Deputies in this House have to respond to the best of their knowledge.  The kind of information being put forward is not defeated by saying we have no official knowledge of it.  The dogs in the street know it.  We have to take account of what the facts are and that the public by and large is very concerned not only for the ecological implications but also for what a nonsense this is making of even larger issues, such as the sovereignty of this country.  For all these reasons it seems that the correct thing to do &mdash; even if the Minister cannot respond to the broad framework of the arguments put forward for the amendment in terms of its foreign policy implications &mdash; is at least to have this legislation with the merit that it has been prepared in the aspiration that we will have far more accountable use of our waters and our air space.  We, in the Labour Party, support the arguments put forward in favour of these amendments.</P>
    <Speaker pid="TomKitt" hpid="Mr. T. Kitt Mr. T. Kitt">
      <NameTxt>Mr. T. Kitt</NameTxt>
      <P>There is a major dilemma <Col N="2143" /> here for politicians from all sides.  I have just heard Deputy Higgins, Deputy Flaherty and others making a very legitimate case for the movement of nuclear submarines through international waters, but the question we must address is, can you deal with that issue within the context of this Radiological Protection Bill?  We are moving into a decade when we will have a more open approach at UN and EC levels to military matters, particularly to nuclear capacities.  Let us hope we have learned one lesson from the Gulf war, that is, that we must have a more open approach in this whole area.</P>
      <P>We had been making very good progress internationally on the whole question of verification of nuclear capacities, particularly between the super powers.  I know the Minister will say that this is outside his remit, and I can see the logic of that argument, but as a member of the Government the Minister should be conscious of the feelings of people, including myself, who would like to see an opening where measures could be introduced into our law concerning the passage of ships and aircraft with nuclear capacity through Irish waters and air space.</P>
      <P>In saying that, this is a broader question and this Bill is not the appropriate one to deal with it.  With all due respect to this Bill, it is too big an issue to be dealt with here.  The Bill addresses specific matters.  I do not know why this matter is such a secret.  Why can we not have a much more open approach, particularly to the passage of nuclear submarines through Irish waters?  I would ask the Minister to take into account the very legitimate views expressed here today.</P>
      <P>I heard Deputy Bruton last night refer to the non-nuclear approach to defence. In Fine Gael's view in an EC context, there must be a non-nuclear approach to defence.  Many people on this side would not agree with that approach.  It is a mixed bag coalition when Deputy Garland, my constituency colleague, takes a different approach to this matter from that of Fine Gael.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="2144" /> There has been a very wide ranging debate on this matter, and I thank you, a Cheann Comhairle, for allowing me to broaden it a little.  On earlier Stages a very legitimate point was made which I support.  We have a very proud tradition on disarmament at UN level.  Deputies have been saying that we must clear the lines with regard to the secretive nature of the passage of aircraft and nuclear ships through Irish waters.  The Irish Government and the Irish people must give a very clear message to the international community that we want to see a more open regime.  I accept that there are international implications, but what we are speaking about today is the global nature of this subject matter, particularly in the context of our European relations into the next decade.</P>
    <P>I would ask the Minister to take on board the view that this issue will have to be addressed in future legislation.  I accept his position but he should accept the goodwill of Deputies that there is a foreign policy matter to be addressed and that the Irish Government should have a key role to play.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MonicaBarnes" hpid="Mrs. Barnes Mrs. Barnes">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Barnes</NameTxt>
      <P>In his fine and lucid speech &mdash; as usual &mdash; Deputy Higgins referred to illusion and reality; Deputy Tom Kitt seemed to be confused in regard to both in his contribution.  We are talking about radiological protection and we must concentrate in this Bill &mdash; regardless of other Bills and foreign policy &mdash; on the invasion of the waters and air space of this country, which claims to be non-nuclear. Some years ago our people went to great democratic lengths to ensure that we did not have a nuclear plant in this country and, in doing that, they endorsed the fact that we should not be invaded &mdash; with secrecy and aggression &mdash; by large nuclear powered weapons.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>As spokesperson on the Marine for Fine Gael, I feel particularly outraged about the fact that our waters have been consistently invaded by aggressive, nuclear forces on what they call routine surveillance and deterrence, which has nothing to do with this country or our foreign policy.  Like Deputy Mac Giolla, <Col N="2145" /> I should like to pay tribute to Greenpeace because they have exposed the secrecy and mysticism shrouding nuclear weapons to the detriment of us all and in spite of the hostility of these greater aggressive nations.  Thankfully, we are now in a period when it is acceptable to ensure that we flush out the secrecy of the invasion of air and water space.  Over the years, for a variety of reasons such as foreign policy and nuclear accidents which dangerously affect people, we have had open discussion on the deployment of nuclear weapons on land.</P>
    <P>During the fifties and sixties &mdash; during the Cold War &mdash; opposition to nuclear power was seen as heresy, treachery, a selling out of sovereignty.  However, because of the trading of secrets which went on then, through an evolution of history and painful acceptance of what nuclear weapons and plants can do, we have, thankfully, reached the stage where there is freedom of information, to a great extent, on the deployment of nuclear weapons on land and the beginnings of disarmament; there is also the totting up of dangerous weapons all over the world.  It is up to us in this House &mdash; and in every other capacity &mdash; to draw attention to the fact that, while that has been done on land, the powers have retained their &ldquo;neither confirm nor deny&rdquo; policy and secrecy with regard to what is in the world's waters.</P>
    <P>Not alone must we be vigilant with regard to surveillance, we must also monitor accidents at sea.  I remind the Minister we are also talking about the only comparatively environmentally free and protected area in the world because we have destroyed the land area of our planet.  The last area to be preserved and protected for the future of all species on this planet is the seas and the fact that the subject is allowed to be shrouded in such mystery and to be invaded by such dangerous chemical and nuclear weapons is an affront to the planet's future and to people's right to know.  We have a responsibility to pass on this planet and to ensure, in so far as our powers extend, that its destruction will not be condoned, excused, or accepted by Members of this <Col N="2146" /> House.  Bills emanating from any Department should have a basic bottom line with regard to the protection of our seas and our air space.</P>
    <P>Not alone do we have the &ldquo;neither confirm nor deny&rdquo; policy of ships capable of nuclear deployment visiting our ports &mdash; which has been taken on and dealt with &mdash; we have the great example and model of New Zealand which, in economic terms, risked far more than we did by its isolation geographically in banning ships which would neither confirm nor deny whether they were carrying nuclear warheads.  New Zealand has a population comparable with ours of 3.5 million, it is a small country in a competitive world and it had the guts and courage to do that.  There were threats by the United States of economic retaliation against them but they held firm.  If a small, isolated, economically open competitive market economy, such as New Zealand, can make a stand against this successfully, we can do the same.</P>
    <P>I also pay tribute to Sweden which not alone has started dismantling its nuclear plant but, as Deputy Mac Giolla said, will, by 1992, have brought in the necessary policies and procedures not to allow invasion of their waters.  We know that it was through the paranoia of the United States' Navy the &ldquo;neither confirm nor deny&rdquo; policy was first introduced; we also know that a very high number of nuclear submarines travel the seas at all times.  In July 1987 Greenpeace pointed out that the Warsaw Pact deployed about 340 submarines, that NATO had 260 and that some 300 belonged to other states.  The five nuclear powers now have more than 9,000 offensive nuclear weapons in their submarine forces.  They went on to say &mdash; which is relevant to us &mdash; that submarines are the most invisible element of the naval arms race.  We have a hidden force mysteriously beneath the sea, neither confirming nor denying that they carry nuclear warheads, and having the arrogance to demand that that is accepted from them; we also have, again and again in our waters, submarines interfering with the fishing of peaceful people following a <Col N="2147" /> traditional, environmentally friendly occupation.</P>
    <P>For all those reasons, it is not just a matter of debate whether it is relevant to the Bill, it is not a matter of debate whether our foreign policy should also be approached in future years to be changed; it is our responsibility and duty to protect our people.  We have declared ourselves to be nuclear free, we took a great economic energy risk back in the sixties to ensure that we would not have a nuclear plant and we lived with the consequences, as it happened happily; as most wise people knew, it was the best decision we could have made.  At present countries which have contaminated themselves are trying to dismantle their nuclear plants at very great economic and environmental cost.  As we know, the environmental cost will not be known for the next 1,000 years.  In the light of all this, of disarmament throughout the world, because of our need for clean seas in regard to our environment and our competitiveness and integration in Europe, it would be irresponsible not to include this in the Bill.</P>
    <P>Let us put the marker down here and extend it to all the other Bills and policies. As politicians, we have a right on behalf of the people of this country to ensure we monitor each Bill as it goes through the House.</P>
    <Speaker pid="IvorCallely" hpid="Mr. Callely Mr. Callely">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Callely</NameTxt>
      <P>Listening to the last speaker and reading the amendment before us it is very difficult to disagree with anything that has been said.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TomasMacGiolla" hpid="Tomás Mac Giolla Tomás Mac Giolla">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Mac Giolla</NameTxt>
      <P>There is no difficulty. Just agree with it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="IvorCallely" hpid="Mr. Callely Mr. Callely">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Callely</NameTxt>
      <P>That would be even more difficult for me.  I am on the record of this House as expressing my concerns about nuclear energy.  We all know the experiences of the past and how we as a nuclear free country, as Deputy Barnes said, have been affected by nuclear accidents many thousands of miles from our shores. This poses a question I have posed in the past, and I have communicated my <Col N="2148" /> concerns to the Minister for Energy.  I have communicated with him in a separate capacity as to whether there should be recognisable national boundaries at all when we talk of nuclear energy.  We know there is no such thing as a national boundary for nuclear energy.</P>
      <P>I cannot disagree with the amendment before the House.  On the other hand, I understand the Bill before the House is to put in place a framework for protection, and that we welcome, but we also have to recognise that the amendment would interfere with international law and this is an area which causes some difficulty.  If there are international laws and we are to recognise them &mdash; as we do &mdash; one could not support the amendment, but that poses a further question.  Maybe through the EC the Minister can try to make the necessary amendments to international law to give recognition to the sentiments expressed in the amendment. That would be a step in the right direction and would meet what I have said, that there should be no recognition of national boundaries when we talk of nuclear energy.  If we can get that accepted and written into international law I think the Minister would be quite satisfied to accept an amendment of this nature if it was not interfering with international law.  However, I do not want to pre-empt the Minister in what he might say on that.</P>
      <P>I would like to express a number of other concerns but I am restricted to the amendment before the House.  Related to that amendment is the development of the Sellafield plant that has been spoken of frequently particularly in relation to the development of the THORP plant.  If that development goes ahead I fear we will again be bound by international law. Can the Minister, the Government, we as legislators, as the elected people of the nation, do something about nuclear energy, national boundaries and international law?  I think there will be general agreement in the House that we should try to make inroads in that area, and the sooner the better.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanRyan" hpid="Mr. Ryan Mr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>I support this amendment. If we are to do something to protect the <Col N="2149" /> people of Ireland from the hazards of radiation we can only look at the legislation before us and at the needs of the people.  By and large the people would favour the type of amendment before us.</P>
      <P>Fianna Fáil TDs make me smile.  They are all things to all men.  They can get up here, as did Deputy Callely and Deputy Kitt, the only two Fianna Fáil Deputies here this afternoon, see great merits in the legislation and say that it is required, but what can we do about it?  It is not the mechanism to meet the needs and problems that exist.  We as legislators must assume the responsibility of bringing in the type of legislation which will deal with the problem.  All we have now is the legislation before us to deal with our seas and airways.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="IvorCallely" hpid="Mr. Callely Mr. Callely">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Callely</NameTxt>
      <P>If you are to give consideration to the EC and our involvement in international matters you cannot deny the rules and regulations that are there in international law.</P>
      <P>
        <i>(Interruptions.)</i>
      </P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanRyan" hpid="Mr. Ryan Mr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>It is up to us to look at the situation and bring in legislation to meet our requirements and if necessary stand up to the EC and tell them this is what we want.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="IvorCallely" hpid="Mr. Callely Mr. Callely">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Callely</NameTxt>
      <P>Ask your colleague now.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanRyan" hpid="Mr. Ryan Mr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>I come from the Dublin North constituency which includes the towns of Balbriggan, Skerries and Lough-shinny. I am being parochial but it is the same elsewhere: everyday trawlers go out from these places on to the Irish Sea and time and again accidents occur, trawlers are lost, fishermen lose their lives.  What would happen if a submarine was damaged when it was carrying nuclear bombs or something like that?  How would we deal with that kind of incident?  When a ship comes into an Irish port, Cork for instance, and there are protests as to the kind of materials it may be carrying, the Department of Foreign Affairs say they do not know what is happening, or what is on board.  Is it not time <Col N="2150" /> that the Government knew what was on board?</P>
      <P>This is not a radical amendment.  It tries to deal with the problems on the ground at the moment.  If we are meeting the requirements of the people we represent we must take on board some hard decisions and we must also take on board the type of amendment we have here.  I hope that on the basis of the contributions made here, particularly from the Opposition and in the light of the sentiments expressed by the Government the Minister can recognise the logic of this.  I do not want to go on and on about what was brought up here at another stage, but as a TD representing a constituency in which there is a great interest in the Irish Sea in terms of the livelihood of a large number of people, I urge that his amendment be taken on board.  The Bill will not be sufficiently strong to deal with the problems unless the amendment is accepted.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasFoxe" hpid="Mr. Foxe Mr. Foxe">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Foxe</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister says that this Bill is not the appropriate one for the inclusion of those amendments.  He might tell us what Bill may be going through the House in the very near future which may be more appropriate to have at least the spirit of those amendments included. If no such Bill is contemplated I respectfully suggest to the Minister that he take on board the spirit at least of those two amendments.</P>
      <P>The Minister's colleagues in Government, although not of his own party, spoke in favour of the amendment and possibly deep down the Minister will agree with it.  At one time we thought we knew quite a lot about nuclear power but the extent of our knowledge soon came to light after the Chernobyl disaster when national and international boundaries were not recognised and animals here were affected and infected by nuclear fallout.  Those animals were the sheep on our mountains.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I agree we must fall in line with international law but why should international law not fall in line with our thinking?  I respectfully ask the Minister to have the <Col N="2151" /> spirit of the amendments included in the Bill.</P>
    <Speaker pid="RobertMolloy" hpid="Minister for Energy (Mr. Molloy) Robert Molloy">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Energy (Mr. Molloy)</NameTxt>
      <P>I thank all the Deputies who contributed to this discussion.  It is important that I state clearly at the outset that the Irish Government's position with regard to nuclear energy and nuclear weaponry is very clear.  There is a long established history of Irish Government opposition to nuclear weaponry and Ireland has played a very prominent role in the movement for nuclear disarmament.</P>
      <P>The discussion we had here may be relevant to the Bill in the sense that we are trying to establish an institute which will have a professional capacity to deal with any disaster that may arise in regard to radiation as a result of a nuclear accident or a nuclear attack within a distance that could affect us, and to deal with radiation matters in other areas of life. Deputies opposite do not really believe this is the correct Bill in which the kind of changes in law they are advocating should or could be implemented.  These matters relate to international law.</P>
      <P>The amendment relates to international matters, to territorial waters covered by international law and this is not a matter for the Minister for Energy in the strict sense, but a matter for the Minister for Foreign Affairs.  We had a long discussion on this matter on Committee Stage and it was also discussed on Second Stage.  I thought I had dealt with all the issues raised on how Ireland's position was protected both in legislation and in our arrangements with foreign Governments.  This is not a matter for the Minister for Energy but for the Minister for Foreign Affairs.  However, in view of its overall relevance I will take the opportunity to put as much information as I can on record in an effort to reply to some of the points raised by Deputies.  I pointed out already that this legislation was not the appropriate medium for the arrangements being suggested in this amendment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="2152" /> The intent of the proposed amendments is to allow the ministerial regulation of the entry into Irish territorial waters of any foreign state ship, submarine or hovercraft and the passage through Irish airspace of any foreign state aircraft by requiring, prior to any grant of permission for such entry or passage, the production of a certificate from the relevant foreign state authority that the ship, submarine, hovercraft or aircraft in question does not carry any nuclear explosive device.</P>
    <P>I am satisfied that existing legislation and Government policy in this area are quite adequate and that further measures are not called for.  I would make the following points: Under the Air Navigation (Foreign Military Aircraft) Order 1952, the permission of the Minister for Foreign Affairs is required for overflights by foreign military aircraft, while the permission of the Department of Foreign Affairs is required for visits to Irish ports by foreign naval vessels.  Thus, these matters do not come within the jurisdiction of the Minister for Energy.  The proposed amendment has serious implications for Ireland's national obligations under the rules of international law and I would emphasise this point to Deputies.  Under international law, a foreign naval vessel has the right of innocent passage through the territorial waters of another state. Permission or prior notification is not required and the question of a declaration does not, therefore, arise.  The proposed amendment would involve a very serious deviation from the rules of international law and would have major international implications.</P>
    <P>I am sure that Deputies on the opposite side do not for one minute suggest that an amendment of this kind to a Radiological Protection Bill is the appropriate way to make that sort of fundamental change in Ireland's participation in the international law of the sea, which would have wide-ranging repercussions for the shipping trade not alone here but throughout the world.</P>
    <P>As I indicated, the permission of the Department of Foreign Affairs is required for visits to Irish ports by foreign <Col N="2153" /> naval vessels.  Permission for a visit will normally be granted provided that the visit does not form part of a naval exercise and the vessel is not carrying nuclear weapons.  Thus, it has been Government policy over the last two decades not to permit nuclear weapons to enter Irish ports and the Government are not aware of any reason to doubt that our policy in this area is not being respected.</P>
    <P>The entry of foreign military aircraft into Irish airspace and landings of such aircraft in the State are already covered under existing legislation.  The strict controls which exist under the Air Navigation (Foreign Military Aircraft) Order, 1952, provide that no foreign military aircraft shall fly over Ireland unless at the express invitation or with the express permission of the Minister for Foreign Affairs.  In addition any aircraft involved must comply with any stipulations as the Minister may make.  Information such as identification numbers and aircraft types must be provided.  In seeking permission it is also necessary to state whether the aircraft comply with certain conditions, the most important of which are that they are unarmed, carry no arms, ammunition of intelligence &mdash; gathering equipment and do not form part of any military exercise or operation.  It is Government policy not to permit nuclear weapons to enter our airspace.</P>
    <Speaker pid="TomasMacGiolla" hpid="Tomás Mac Giolla Tomás Mac Giolla">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Mac Giolla</NameTxt>
      <P>Why did they come in, then?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RobertMolloy" hpid="Mr. Molloy Mr. Molloy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Molloy</NameTxt>
      <P>Ireland is not a member of any military alliance and thus remains free from any commitment, in particular to admit nuclear weapons, that such membership might entail.  Foreign Governments are well aware of our policy on ships' visits and overflights and are reminded of this policy on a regular basis.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>One of the effects of the proposed amendment would be that naval vessels of certain foreign Governments would cease to visit Irish ports.  We have generally welcomed such visits as part of the network of relations and contacts among <Col N="2154" /> friendly countries.  There is also an economic benefit involved for the ports concerned, but that is not a major consideration.</P>
    <P>Finally, I would again make the point, as I did in Committee, that the proposal from Deputies to amend the Bill to include a provision which would bring nuclear weapons under its terms of reference &mdash; in other words, to declare Ireland a nuclear-free zone &mdash; is doubtful, because I am firmly of the opinion that the Radiological Protection Bill is not the appropriate medium, given its primary aims of establishing the institute, providing for radiation protection measures and giving effect to international conventions. The question is of a military nature and more pertinent to the diplomatic arena, the area of international relations and the responsibilities of the Department of Foreign Affairs.  That is the responsibility of the Minister for Foreign Affairs and his Department.</P>
    <P>Deputies raised the question of accountability and the need for clarity regarding our position.  Deputy Higgins stated that we must take account of the facts.  I heard Deputy Mac Giolla saying certain things but adding the qualifying statement that the evidence is not there to prove them.  We have a cross-party policy which is crystal clear.  We are adamant that it is prohibited to enter Irish territory and ports with nuclear weapons on board.  The Government fully share the concern expressed here and in many other places regarding the dangers and risks posed by mobile nuclear power stations, namely submarines.  It should not be necessary for me to have to repeat that the Government have raised this issue at every possible opportunity at various international fora, particularly at the UN.  It has also been raised at Community level and with the International Maritime Organisation.</P>
    <P>Amendment No. 6 states:</P>
    <P>In page 21, between lines 44 and 45, to insert the following:</P>
    <P>&ldquo;(9)  The Minister shall by order regulate the entry into Irish territorial <Col N="2155" /> waters of any foreign State ship, submarine, or hovercraft, and the passage through Irish airspace of any foreign State aircraft by requiring, prior to any grant of permission for such entry or passage, the production of a certificate from the relevant foreign State authority that the ship, submarine, hovercraft, or aircraft in question does not carry any nuclear explosive device.&rdquo;.</P>
    <P>The Government do not and will not grant permission for naval vessels carrying nuclear weapons to visit Irish ports, nor will they consent to overflights of aircraft carrying such arms.  That, however, is not the point at issue in the amendment.  The amendment proposes that Ireland introduce a policy which would have serious implications for our obligations under international law. Under international law a foreign vessel has the right of innocent passage through our territorial waters.  The question of granting permission for such passage does not arise, nor does the question of the production of a certificate.  This is the key point in the amendment, not the Government's policy on nuclear weapons, which is clear and unequivocal.  Regarding the regulation of entry of nuclear weapons into Irish territorial waters and air space the Government's position is firm and consistent and it would be wrong to convey any other impression from this discussion.  There is a general prohibition against foreign naval vessels carrying nuclear weapons when visiting Irish ports and the Government believe that this prohibition is observed.  We take every opportunity to make known our position on this issue.  I have already outlined the conditions which strictly regulate overflights by foreign military aircraft.</P>
    <P>The amendment is not only inappropriate from an international legal point of view and unnecessary for the purpose of this Bill but more importantly would serve to confuse the basic issue of the categorical prohibition on the entry into our ports of any naval vessel carrying nuclear weapons or the overflight of our territory by any aircraft carrying such <Col N="2156" /> arms.  Our policy position on this issue relates to visits to our ports, not entry into territorial waters, which is covered by international law.</P>
    <P>I wonder if some of the Deputies who put their names to this amendment were aware of the serious effects of its acceptance. There would be chaos in regard to international shipping.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MonicaBarnes" hpid="Mrs. Barnes Mrs. Barnes">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Barnes</NameTxt>
      <P>What about the chaos of a nuclear accident?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RobertMolloy" hpid="Mr. Molloy Mr. Molloy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Molloy</NameTxt>
      <P>If this House wishes to take some positive steps to deal with the matter which has been raised here and by the Government at international fora it should not be done by way of inserting an amendment in the Radiological Protection Bill but by way of a motion or a Bill brought forward by the Minister for Foreign Affairs, which would be followed through by other Ministers at international fora where international laws have been agreed, without which world trade and shipping could not operate. There would be serious implications for us if we were to adopt this type of amendment. I am convinced Fine Gael gave no consideration to its implications.  It contains the same wording as the amendment tabled by Deputy Garland.  It was an amendment posted in to the spokespersons by an outside organisation.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TomasMacGiolla" hpid="Tomás Mac Giolla Tomás Mac Giolla">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Mac Giolla</NameTxt>
      <P>There are two amendments before us, Nos. 6 and 7.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RobertMolloy" hpid="Mr. Molloy Mr. Molloy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Molloy</NameTxt>
      <P>I recognise that Deputy Mac Giolla has an amendment as well. Deputies from all parties have spoken but I am directing most of my comments at my colleague on the Fine Gael benches.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryFlaherty" hpid="Miss Flaherty Miss Flaherty">
      <NameTxt>Miss Flaherty</NameTxt>
      <P>Does the Minister expect a higher level of sanity from us?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RobertMolloy" hpid="Mr. Molloy Mr. Molloy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Molloy</NameTxt>
      <P>I am suggesting to her, although without any evidence, that possibly she agreed to run with this amendment. I doubt if she has put it formally to her party and I will be surprised if she has the considered support of Fine Gael, <Col N="2157" /> in view of the chaos that would result if it were adopted.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MonicaBarnes" hpid="Mrs. Barnes Mrs. Barnes">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Barnes</NameTxt>
      <P>How is it there was not world chaos when New Zealand did it?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RobertMolloy" hpid="Mr. Molloy Mr. Molloy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Molloy</NameTxt>
      <P>They did not do it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TomasMacGiolla" hpid="Tomás Mac Giolla Tomás Mac Giolla">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Mac Giolla</NameTxt>
      <P>They banned nuclear ships.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RobertMolloy" hpid="Mr. Molloy Mr. Molloy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Molloy</NameTxt>
      <P>Deputy Mac Giolla spoke at some length about a Greenpeace report entitled <i>US Navy Warships in Irish Ports.</i> Is that so?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TomasMacGiolla" hpid="Tomás Mac Giolla Tomás Mac Giolla">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Mac Giolla</NameTxt>
      <P>Correct.  It covers the years 1980 to 1990.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RobertMolloy" hpid="Mr. Molloy Mr. Molloy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Molloy</NameTxt>
      <P>I have already expressed my views on this study on Committee Stage.  It is detailed and extensive but does not provide any evidence that there have been nuclear weapons on board vessels visiting Irish ports.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TomasMacGiolla" hpid="Tomás Mac Giolla Tomás Mac Giolla">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Mac Giolla</NameTxt>
      <P>There is <i>prima facie</i> evidence.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RobertMolloy" hpid="Mr. Molloy Mr. Molloy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Molloy</NameTxt>
      <P>We have recently seen a happy conclusion to a long running problem in regard to certain unfortunate people who were incarcerated in the prisons of an adjoining state on evidence which was shown not to stand up.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TomasMacGiolla" hpid="Tomás Mac Giolla Tomás Mac Giolla">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Mac Giolla</NameTxt>
      <P>The Government extradite people on <i>prima facie</i> evidence.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RobertMolloy" hpid="Mr. Molloy Mr. Molloy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Molloy</NameTxt>
      <P>We of all people want to be certain that when we make allegations we have evidence to substantiate them.  I have always tried to be open in regard to my responsibilities.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TomasMacGiolla" hpid="Tomás Mac Giolla Tomás Mac Giolla">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Mac Giolla</NameTxt>
      <P>It is up to the Minister to find the evidence.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RobertMolloy" hpid="Mr. Molloy Mr. Molloy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Molloy</NameTxt>
      <P>I have always tried in this House to be open about my responsibilities, as the Deputy acknowledged on a few occasions.  Wherever evidence is supplied to me, I will be the first person to take some positive action on it.  There <Col N="2158" /> has been no evidence provided to substantiate the claim made by the Deputy in regard to this matter.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TomasMacGiolla" hpid="Tomás Mac Giolla Tomás Mac Giolla">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Mac Giolla</NameTxt>
      <P>I have to insist on this.  There is <i>prima facie</i> evidence in this report.  The only further evidence missing is photographic evidence.  Somebody would have to actually see it, and only the Minister can authorise that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesCTunney" hpid="An Leas-Cheann Comhairle Jim Tunney">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Cheann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>Deputy Mac Giolla cannot interrupt the Minister, and I am sure he appreciates that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RobertMolloy" hpid="Mr. Molloy Mr. Molloy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Molloy</NameTxt>
      <P>I have only ten minutes more in which to reply.  On close examination, this report contains largely circumstantial evidence and Deputies will be aware that the Government cannot act simply on the basis of assumptions.  I would like to emphasise this point since the Deputy appears to be claiming that a nuclear weapon state has infringed our prohibition on carrying nuclear weapons when visiting an Irish port.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Deputy Mac Giolla also referred to what he described as the decision of the Swedish Government to change their policy on this issue in 1992.  I do not want to misinterpret the Deputy but that is what I understood he was saying because Deputies in the Fine Gael party started to refer to the same point as if it was a fact.  I would like to clarify this point since Deputy Mac Giolla may misunderstand Swedish policy in this area.  I have had the matter checked out and have been informed that there has been no change in Swedish policy on port visits.  Their policy, like ours, consists of a general prohibition on the visits of ships carrying nuclear weapons.  The only evidence that could be found as to how Deputy Mac Giolla arrived at that belief is that a motion was adopted by the Swedish Social Democrat Party at their annual party congress, or annual &ldquo;Árd Fheis&rdquo; in September 1990, but there has been no government decision on the issue.  There has been no change in Swedish policy. In the Swedish Parliament recently, the Minister for Foreign Affairs Mr. Sten <Col N="2159" /> Andersson, pointed out the serious consequences that would result from a unilateral Swedish decision on this issue.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelDHiggins" hpid="Mr. M. Higgins Mr. M. Higgins">
      <NameTxt>Mr. M. Higgins</NameTxt>
      <P>We did not say it was in breach of international law.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RobertMolloy" hpid="Mr. Molloy Mr. Molloy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Molloy</NameTxt>
      <P>Let us deal with what is before us.  There was a long dissertation in this House today and on Wednesday last from Deputy Mac Giolla where he indicated that the Swedish Government had reacted to the Greenpeace report by changing the law of that country to take effect in 1992.  I am simply stating that on my verification of the facts, this statement does not stand up and it is not true.  In fact, it is the opposite to the statement by the Swedish Minister for Foreign Affairs.</P>
      <P>Deputy Mac Giolla referred also to the visit of the <i>USS Conyngham</i> and the Greenpeace allegations that the vessel was carrying nuclear weapons when it paid a visit to Cobh.  The visit of the <i>USS Conyngham</i> was conducted in compliance with our policy.  Nuclear capability is not synonymous with the carriage of nuclear weapons.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TomasMacGiolla" hpid="Tomás Mac Giolla Tomás Mac Giolla">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Mac Giolla</NameTxt>
      <P>I know that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RobertMolloy" hpid="Mr. Molloy Mr. Molloy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Molloy</NameTxt>
      <P>Neither is the evidence submitted by Greenpeace in relation to the <i>USS Contyngham</i> categorical.  The Greenpeace report contains many probabilities. Greenpeace have also been found to be wrong before in such matters, as in Sweden in 1989 when Greenpeace staked their honour on the assertion that there were nuclear weapons on board the US ship <i>Ticonderoga</i>, and this was not the case as was subsequently verified. Greenpeace themselves freely admit today to their mistake.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TomasMacGiolla" hpid="Tomás Mac Giolla Tomás Mac Giolla">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Mac Giolla</NameTxt>
      <P>There is no reason that we cannot inspect the ships and find out if they are carrying nuclear weapons.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RobertMolloy" hpid="Mr. Molloy Mr. Molloy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Molloy</NameTxt>
      <P>I am merely trying to keep this debate on a rational and factual level. We cannot substantiate a case on facts <Col N="2160" /> that do not stand up or where there is no evidence to verify them.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TomasMacGiolla" hpid="Tomás Mac Giolla Tomás Mac Giolla">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Mac Giolla</NameTxt>
      <P>How can they be verified &mdash; only the Government can verify the facts.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesCTunney" hpid="An Leas-Cheann Comhairle Jim Tunney">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Cheann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>In the matter of this debate, the Deputy could be accused of throwing Scuds, and this is not allowed.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RobertMolloy" hpid="Mr. Molloy Mr. Molloy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Molloy</NameTxt>
      <P>We all share a common concern in this matter.  I do not disagree with the reasons that Deputies are giving for the need for greater international control in these matters.  I am merely saying that the Radiological Protection Bill is not the legislation through which this can be done and I am not the Minister with particular responsibility at Cabinet to do these things&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryFlaherty" hpid="Miss Flaherty Miss Flaherty">
      <NameTxt>Miss Flaherty</NameTxt>
      <P>God forbid.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RobertMolloy" hpid="Mr. Molloy Mr. Molloy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Molloy</NameTxt>
      <P>In many of the cases, as I pointed out, it is not a matter solely for this House.  Where we subscribe to international law in these matters there is another forum where these matters have to be thrashed out if we are going to get agreement.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The British Nuclear Fuel authorities spoke about expanding their facility for reprocessing nuclear waste.  When they sought business around the world and ships with this nuclear waste began to ply the Irish Sea to the port where they discharge the waste, they can enter into Irish territorial waters.  I made the most minute scrutiny of the law in this area, with the assistance of my colleague, the Minister for the Marine, to see if there was any way in which we could act in order to protect our people against the obvious dangers of vessels carrying nuclear waste travelling up close to the Irish coast.  We do not have the power on our own to opt out of the situation because of international law in this matter, unless we want to become a country in total isolation from the rest of the world.  I do not think that is what the Deputies are suggesting.  That is why I <Col N="2161" /> suggest the parties opposite have not given this matter the serious consideration it deserves.</P>
    <P>Deputy Barnes suggested that the New Zealand prohibition referred to territorial waters.  That is not correct.  The New Zealand reaction referred to their own ports and internal waters and not to their territorial waters.  I am sure the Deputy is aware the amendment tabled by her party relates to territorial waters and not to ports and to internal waters. The New Zealand action is not similar to the action the Deputy is proposing in this amendment.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MaryFlaherty" hpid="Miss Flaherty Miss Flaherty">
      <NameTxt>Miss Flaherty</NameTxt>
      <P>Is the Minister saying he would be willing to accept an amended version of our amendment to cover the ports?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RobertMolloy" hpid="Mr. Molloy Mr. Molloy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Molloy</NameTxt>
      <P>No, I am not.  I am suggesting that the party opposite have a foreign affairs spokesperson who could sponsor legislation in this area.  They have also a marine spokesperson who may wish to change the international law of the sea and could probably start it from the benches of this House.  It would be a long hard battle but it is something which cannot really succeed unless there is agreement at international level.  I have experience of how difficult it is to get <Col N="2162" /> international agreement on the nuclear issue.  There are countries that are very dependent on nuclear energy, and even the members of the European Community have differing views.</P>
      <P>There are member countries of the European Community who are very pronuclear energy.  In our attempts to have a Europewide inspectorate of nuclear installations established, we have found it very difficult to get the other member countries to support even that much of a change.  Ireland is standing out as a shining light in world fora in continuing to state its position clearly and unequivocally, in advocating greater nuclear safety throughout the world and the abolition of all nuclear weapons.  We have a long proud tradition in that whole area.  I would not like, in opposing this amendment, to be interpreted in any other way than as fully supporting the continuation of Government policy in this area.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesCTunney" hpid="An Leas-Cheann Comhairle Jim Tunney">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Cheann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>As it is now 4 o'clock I am required, by order of the House today, to put the question. The question is: &ldquo;That Fourth Stage is hereby completed and that the Bill is hereby passed.&rdquo;</P>
      <P>Question put.</P>
      <P Just="Center">The Dáil divided: Tá, 66; Níl, 17.</P>
      <P Just="Center">Tá</P>
    </Speaker>
    <table pgwide="1">
      <tgroup cols="2">
        <colspec colname="1" colnum="1" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <colspec colname="2" colnum="2" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry rowsep="1">Ahern, Bertie.<br />Ahern, Dermot.<br />Ahern, Michael.<br />Barrett, Michael.<br />Brady, Gerard.<br />Brady, Vincent.<br />Brennan, Mattie.<br />Brennan, Séamus.<br />Browne, John (Wexford).<br />Burke, Raphael P.<br />Callely, Ivor.<br />Clohessy, Peadar.<br />Coughlan, Mary Theresa.<br />Cowen, Brian.<br />Cullimore, Séamus.<br />Daly, Brendan.<br />Dempsey, Noel.<br />Dennehy, John.<br />de Valera, Síle.
<Col N="2163" />Leonard, Jimmy.<br />Leyden, Terry.<br />Lyons, Denis.<br />Martin, Micheál.<br />McCreevy, Charlie.<br />McDaid, Jim.<br />McEllistrim, Tom.<br />Molloy, Robert.<br />Nolan, M.J.<br />O'Connell, John.<br />O'Dea, Willie.<br />O'Donoghue, John.<br />O'Hanlon, Rory.<br />O'Keeffe, Ned.</entry>
            <entry rowsep="1">Fahey, Frank.<br />Fahey, Jackie.<br />Fitzpatrick, Dermot.<br />Flood, Chris.<br />Flynn, Pádraig.<br />Foxe, Tom.<br />Gallagher, Pat the Cope.<br />Haughey, Charles J.<br />Hillery, Brian.<br />Hilliard, Colm.<br />Hyland, Liam.<br />Jacob, Joe.<br />Kelly, Laurence.<br />Kenneally, Brendan.<br />Kirk, Séamus.<br />Kitt, Michael P.<br />Kitt, Tom.<br />Lawlor, Liam.<br />Lenihan, Brian.
<Col N="2164" />O'Leary, John.<br />O'Rourke, Mary.<br />O'Toole, Martin Joe.<br />Power, Seán.<br />Quill, Máirín.<br />Roche, Dick.<br />Smith, Michael.<br />Treacy, Noel.<br />Tunney, Jim.<br />Wallace, Dan.<br />Wallace, Mary.<br />Walsh, Joe.<br />Woods, Michael.<br />Wyse, Pearse.</entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
    <P Just="Center">Níl</P>
    <table pgwide="1">
      <tgroup cols="2">
        <colspec colname="1" colnum="1" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <colspec colname="2" colnum="2" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry rowsep="1">Byrne, Eric.<br />Gilmore, Eamon.<br />Gregory, Tony.<br />Higgins, Michael D.<br />Howlin, Brendan.<br />Kavanagh, Liam.<br />Kemmy, Jim.<br />Mac Giolla, Tomás.<br /></entry>
            <entry rowsep="1">O'Shea, Brian.<br />O'Sullivan, Toddy.<br />Pattison, Séamus.<br />Quinn, Ruairí.<br />Rabbitte, Pat.<br />Ryan, Seán.<br />Sherlock, Joe.<br />Stagg, Emmet.<br />Taylor, Mervyn.</entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
    <P Just="Center">Tellers: Tá, Deputies V. Brady and D. Ahern; Níl, Deputies Howlin and Sherlock.</P>
    <P>Question declared carried.</P>
    <Speaker pid="CharlesJHaughey" hpid="The Taoiseach Charles J. Haughey">
      <NameTxt>The Taoiseach</NameTxt>
      <P>May I, a Cheann Comhairle, wish your good self and all the Members of the House a very happy and pleasant Easter.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryFlaherty" hpid="Miss Flaherty Miss Flaherty">
      <NameTxt>Miss Flaherty</NameTxt>
      <P>On behalf of Fine Gael I thank the Taoiseach for his good wishes and hope he and his Ministers have a restful and enjoyable holiday also.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BrendanHowlin" hpid="Mr. Howlin Mr. Howlin">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Howlin</NameTxt>
      <P>Let me reciprocate for the Labour Party.</P>
      <P>The Dáil adjourned at 4.15 p.m. until 10.30 a.m. on Wednesday, 17 April 1991.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
</Debate>