<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE Debate SYSTEM "../Debate.dtd"[]>
<Debate DocTitle="Seanad Debate" Day="Thu" Date="17" Month="Jul" Year="1924" Vol="3" No="15" DateIrish="Déardaoin, 17 Iúil 1924" DateEnglish="Thursday, 17 July 1924" House="S" CommitteeEng="" CommitteeIr="" SubNameEng="" cnum="895">
  <MainHeading Type="Prelude" LHead="" RHead="">
    <Title>
    </Title>
    <P>
      <Col N="895" /> Do chuaidh an Cathaoirleach i gceannas ar a h-aon deug a clog.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="PRIVATE BUSINESS. - DUBLIN UNITED" RHead="TRAMWAYS BILL, 1924&mdash;SECOND STAGE">
    <Title>PRIVATE BUSINESS. - DUBLIN UNITED TRAMWAYS BILL, 1924&mdash;SECOND STAGE.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDouglas" hpid="Mr. DOUGLAS Mr. DOUGLAS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. DOUGLAS</NameTxt>
      <P>I move the Second Reading of</P>
      <P>A Bill to authorise the Dublin United Tramways Company (1896), Limited, to maintain omnibus services in the city and county of Dublin and counties of Wicklow and Kildare and to amend certain Acts relating to that company and for other purposes.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JanePower" hpid="Mrs. WYSE POWER Mrs. WYSE POWER">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. WYSE POWER</NameTxt>
      <P>I object.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="AN CATHAOIRLEACH AN CATHAOIRLEACH">
      <NameTxt>AN CATHAOIRLEACH</NameTxt>
      <P>When is it proposed to put the Bill down again?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDouglas" hpid="Mr. DOUGLAS Mr. DOUGLAS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. DOUGLAS</NameTxt>
      <P>The next time the Seanad sits.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="PUBLIC BUSINESS. - LOCAL OFFICERS COMPENSATION" RHead="(WAR PERIOD) BILL, 1924&mdash;SECOND STAGE">
    <Title>PUBLIC BUSINESS. - LOCAL OFFICERS COMPENSATION (WAR PERIOD) BILL, 1924&mdash;SECOND STAGE.</Title>
    <P>Bill read a Second Time.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="PUBLIC BUSINESS. - INTERMEDIATE EDUCATION" RHead="(AMENDMENT) BILL, 1924&mdash;SECOND STAGE">
    <Title>PUBLIC BUSINESS. - INTERMEDIATE EDUCATION (AMENDMENT) BILL, 1924&mdash;SECOND STAGE.</Title>
    <P>Bill read a Second Time.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="PUBLIC BUSINESS. - LOCAL GOVERNMENT (RATES ON" RHead="AGRICULTURAL LAND) BILL, 1924&mdash;FOURTH STAGE">
    <Title>PUBLIC BUSINESS. - LOCAL GOVERNMENT (RATES ON AGRICULTURAL LAND) BILL, 1924&mdash;FOURTH STAGE.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="JohnKeaneBart" hpid="Sir JOHN KEANE Sir JOHN KEANE">
      <NameTxt>Sir JOHN KEANE</NameTxt>
      <P>I would like to ask the Minister if he can form any idea of the counties that are likely to avail themselves of the provisions of this measure.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="896" />
    <Speaker pid="PatrickJHogan" hpid="MINISTER for LANDS and AGRICULTURE (Mr. Hogan) MINISTER for LANDS and AGRICULTURE (Mr. Hogan)">
      <NameTxt>MINISTER for LANDS and AGRICULTURE (Mr. Hogan)</NameTxt>
      <P>So far as I know, all the County Councils who up to the present have considered the matter have passed resolutions agreeing to accept the benefits conferred with the exception, I think, of one.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="AN CATHAOIRLEACH AN CATHAOIRLEACH">
      <NameTxt>AN CATHAOIRLEACH</NameTxt>
      <P>That is to say, all the County Councils who have considered it up to the present are in favour of the Bill except one?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. HOGAN Mr. HOGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. HOGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>So far as I know.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="AN CATHAOIRLEACH AN CATHAOIRLEACH">
      <NameTxt>AN CATHAOIRLEACH</NameTxt>
      <P>I think what the Senator is anxious to know is how many County Councils have agreed to accept it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnKeaneBart" hpid="Sir J. KEANE Sir J. KEANE">
      <NameTxt>Sir J. KEANE</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes, a general idea. I can understand that the Minister may not know, because some County Councils may not have dealt with the measure.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. HOGAN Mr. HOGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. HOGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>I think only five or six have considered it as yet.  I do not say that information is very accurate, but it is as far as I know.</P>
      <P Just="Center">SECTION 5.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardButler" hpid="Mr. BUTLER Mr. BUTLER">
      <NameTxt>Mr. BUTLER</NameTxt>
      <P>The following amendment standing in my name was left over from the Committee Stage:&mdash;</P>
      <P>Immediately before Section 5 to insert a new Section 5 as follows:&mdash;</P>
      <P>5.&mdash;Any ratepayer in a county may, during the hours that the office of the County Council is open, on payment of a fee of one shilling, inspect any books or returns of the County Council, showing the rates which have been paid in the county.</P>
      <P>I understand that as the law stands at present ratepayers have most of the powers mentioned in the proposed new section.  Under these circumstances, I ask leave to withdraw it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SamuelBrownKC" hpid="Mr. BROWN Mr. BROWN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. BROWN</NameTxt>
      <P>Perhaps I ought to explain that I kept my promise and looked into this matter.  Under the existing law&mdash;that is the Poor Law Act of I and II.  Victoria&mdash;everybody who is interested has a right at all reasonable times to an inspection of the rate-book and taking copies and extracts. The rate-book is kept in such a way that it shows what rates have been <Col N="897" /> paid up to within about a fortnight before inspection, because the Secretary of the County Council is bound to enter up in a column that is provided, the collection of the rates up to about a fortnight before.  The collector has to send in his returns every fortnight, and the result of that fortnight's collection is put into the rate-book by the Secretary. Therefore, the ratepayer has all the advantage that the Senator desires, and the additional advantage that he gets it for nothing instead of paying 1s.</P>
      <P>Amendment, by leave, withdrawn.</P>
      <P>Bill ordered for Final Stage.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="PUBLIC BUSINESS. - CRIMINAL JUSTICE" RHead="(ADMINISTRATION) BILL, 1924&mdash;FOURTH STAGE">
    <Title>PUBLIC BUSINESS. - CRIMINAL JUSTICE (ADMINISTRATION) BILL, 1924&mdash;FOURTH STAGE.</Title>
    <P>SECTION 6.</P>
    <Speaker pid="KevinChristopher" hpid="MINISTER for JUSTICE (Mr. O'Higgins) Kevin O'Higgins">
      <NameTxt>MINISTER for JUSTICE (Mr. O'Higgins)</NameTxt>
      <P>When this Bill was being considered yesterday I was asked to look into the question, whether the words occurring in Section 6, sub-section 1, &ldquo;having regard to the merits of the case&rdquo; were useful or necessary in the context.  It was suggested that inasmuch as the section mentions &ldquo;Where, before trial, or at any stage of a trial, it appears to the court that the indictment is defective, the court shall make such order for the amendment,&rdquo; and inasmuch as the words &ldquo;before trial&rdquo; occur that the expression &ldquo;having regard to the merits of the case,&rdquo; is somewhat anomalous, as the court would not have very much knowledge of the merits of the case before it had actually started hearing it. I am advised the words &ldquo;having regard to the merits of the case&rdquo; need not be taken as qualifying the words &ldquo;before trial,&rdquo; but refer rather to the words that come after them, &ldquo;or at any stage of a trial.&rdquo;  On the whole, perhaps it would be better to leave the section as it stands.  That would be a matter of opinion.  We regard the words that are objected to, or called in question, as practically equivalent thereto &ldquo;in all the circumstances,&rdquo; rather than referring too literally to the actual merits of the matter in dispute.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="898" />
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="AN CATHAOIRLEACH AN CATHAOIRLEACH">
      <NameTxt>AN CATHAOIRLEACH</NameTxt>
      <P>Unfortunately, the words compel the judge to have regard solely to the merits of the case.  It is not to the circumstance but to its merits.  That is the only condition that he can have regard to.  He cannot have regard to circumstances unless they affect the merits.  I think it is a pity, and I am sure there will be trouble over it.  I think the sub-section could be very easily amended.  I cannot understand what they are wanted for at all.  If you put in &ldquo;unless the required amendment cannot in the opinion of the court be made without injustice,&rdquo; that would cover every conceivable case.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SamuelBrownKC" hpid="Mr. BROWN Mr. BROWN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. BROWN</NameTxt>
      <P>They cover everything that ought to be covered.  I suggested to the Minister that he will probably get into trouble with this section.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="KevinChristopher" hpid="Mr. O'HIGGINS Mr. O'HIGGINS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'HIGGINS</NameTxt>
      <P>The words are contained in the British Act for nine years, and I am not aware that any particular trouble has arisen with regard to them.  I see that it would be a question of interpretation, and I see the possibilities that An Cathaoirleach refers to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="AN CATHAOIRLEACH AN CATHAOIRLEACH">
      <NameTxt>AN CATHAOIRLEACH</NameTxt>
      <P>I may say for my countrymen from experience of both that they have a greater ingenuity to discover points in courts of justice than they have on the other side of the Channel.  They have a more subtle brain in that direction.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="KevinChristopher" hpid="Mr. O'HIGGINS Mr. O'HIGGINS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'HIGGINS</NameTxt>
      <P>I would not object to the alteration suggested either by Senator Brown or by you, sir.</P>
      <P>Amendment&mdash;&ldquo;Section 6, sub-section (1), line 5, to omit the words `having regard to the merits of the case,' and substitute therefor `in the opinion of the court' &rdquo;&mdash;put and agreed to.</P>
      <P Just="Center">SECTION 13.</P>
      <P>The following Government amendments were put and agreed to:&mdash;</P>
      <P>1.  Section 13.  Immediately after the word &ldquo;Court&rdquo; in line 34 to insert the words &ldquo;or a Peace Commissioner.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>2.  Section 13.  At the end of line 41 and within the bracket to insert <Col N="899" /> the words &ldquo;or a Peace Commissioner.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>3.  Section 13.  Immediately after the word &ldquo;Justice&rdquo; in line 54 to insert the words &ldquo;or a Peace Commissioner.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="AN CATHAOIRLEACH AN CATHAOIRLEACH">
      <NameTxt>AN CATHAOIRLEACH</NameTxt>
      <P>In the same section, lines 60 and 61, there is a Government amendment to insert before the word &ldquo;indictment&rdquo; the words &ldquo;such charge or.&rdquo;  I understand that that was agreed to yesterday, so that it is not necessary to put it now.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="KevinChristopher" hpid="Mr. O'HIGGINS Mr. O'HIGGINS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'HIGGINS</NameTxt>
      <P>Very good, sir.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="AN CATHAOIRLEACH AN CATHAOIRLEACH">
      <NameTxt>AN CATHAOIRLEACH</NameTxt>
      <P>That is to say, the House understands that we are inserting in lines 60 and 61 before the word &ldquo;indictment&rdquo; the words &ldquo;such charge or,&rdquo; and leaving out the words &ldquo;by the Attorney-General of Saorstát Eireann&rdquo;; so that the sentence will then run: &ldquo;and plead to such charge or indictment as may be preferred against them.&rdquo;  The next amendment is also to Section 13, to add at the end of the section the words: &ldquo;<i>(The foregoing condition may be adapted as circumstances may require).</i>&rdquo; That is a Government amendment also, and it is proposed to put it in at the end of the section?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="KevinChristopher" hpid="Mr. O'HIGGINS Mr. O'HIGGINS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'HIGGINS</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes, sir.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="AN CATHAOIRLEACH AN CATHAOIRLEACH">
      <NameTxt>AN CATHAOIRLEACH</NameTxt>
      <P>Is not that a little awkward.  Would it not be better, Mr. O'Higgins, to put it in at the beginning?  &ldquo;Every recognisance entered into by way of appeal before a District Justice shall be in the following form, or in such similar form as may suit the circumstances.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="KevinChristopher" hpid="Mr. O'HIGGINS Mr. O'HIGGINS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'HIGGINS</NameTxt>
      <P>I think that would be better.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="AN CATHAOIRLEACH AN CATHAOIRLEACH">
      <NameTxt>AN CATHAOIRLEACH</NameTxt>
      <P>The amendment is to omit the words &ldquo;that is to say,&rdquo; and insert &ldquo;or in such similar form as the circumstances may require.&rdquo;</P>
      <P>Amendment, as amended, put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>Bill ordered for Final Stage.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="PUBLIC BUSINESS. - CRIMINAL JUSTICE" RHead="(EVIDENCE) BILL, 1924&mdash;REPORT STAGE">
    <Title>PUBLIC BUSINESS. - CRIMINAL JUSTICE (EVIDENCE) BILL, 1924&mdash;REPORT STAGE.</Title>
    <Col N="900" />
    <Speaker pid="JamesDouglas" hpid="Mr. DOUGLAS Mr. DOUGLAS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. DOUGLAS</NameTxt>
      <P>I think, in view of the extreme speed with which we got through the last Bill, the Minister should be congratulated on having found some errors during such a short period.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="AN CATHAOIRLEACH AN CATHAOIRLEACH">
      <NameTxt>AN CATHAOIRLEACH</NameTxt>
      <P>I am not quite sure he would admit that they were errors.  You will remember, Mr. O'Higgins, that some trouble was suggested about Section 2 of this Bill.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="KevinChristopher" hpid="Mr. O'HIGGINS Mr. O'HIGGINS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'HIGGINS</NameTxt>
      <P>I have looked into that in the meantime, and I find that Sections 2 and 3 should really be taken and considered together.  The object aimed at is to secure that when the accused person avails of the right which the Bill gives him of giving evidence in his own defence, it shall not affect the existing right of counsel for the defence to have the last word where no evidence is called.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="AN CATHAOIRLEACH AN CATHAOIRLEACH">
      <NameTxt>AN CATHAOIRLEACH</NameTxt>
      <P>In other words, it would be the same as if he called no evidence?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="KevinChristopher" hpid="Mr. O'HIGGINS Mr. O'HIGGINS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'HIGGINS</NameTxt>
      <P>That is the purpose of the amendment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="AN CATHAOIRLEACH AN CATHAOIRLEACH">
      <NameTxt>AN CATHAOIRLEACH</NameTxt>
      <P>The thing ought then to be in the one section, I think.  However, it does not really matter.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="KevinChristopher" hpid="Mr. O'HIGGINS Mr. O'HIGGINS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'HIGGINS</NameTxt>
      <P>I would have no objection to making it one section, with two sub-sections.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="AN CATHAOIRLEACH AN CATHAOIRLEACH">
      <NameTxt>AN CATHAOIRLEACH</NameTxt>
      <P>Then you would have to alter the whole enumeration. I think it is plain enough now. It would hardly be worth your while to alter the whole enumeration of the clauses.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SamuelBrownKC" hpid="Mr. BROWN Mr. BROWN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. BROWN</NameTxt>
      <P>Another point, Sir, raised by me on section 5&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="AN CATHAOIRLEACH AN CATHAOIRLEACH">
      <NameTxt>AN CATHAOIRLEACH</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes, that is an important matter.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SamuelBrownKC" hpid="Mr. BROWN Mr. BROWN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. BROWN</NameTxt>
      <P>As to whether the words &ldquo;criminal proceedings&rdquo; include prosecutions under the Licensing Acts, the Children's Acts, and so forth. I looked into the matter last night, and I find that it was unnecessary to <Col N="901" /> raise this point.  The Bill is practically word for word a copy of the English Act of 1898, and this very section came up for consideration on a case stated in 1904.  There was a prosecution against a father for cruelty to his children under the Act for the Prevention of Cruelty to Children.  I think he was asked in cross-examination if he had been previously convicted of a similar offence.  He admitted that he had, and he was convicted and sentenced.  A case was stated by the justices, and it came before the King's Bench.  They held that the words in Section 5, &ldquo;criminal proceedings,&rdquo; included criminal proceedings of every kind and in every court, and that, therefore, the conviction was bad; that though it was possible to ask him a question of that kind under the Act under which he was convicted, it was not possible after this Act was passed to have him cross-examined as to his previous conviction. Therefore, it would be quite unnecessary to define &ldquo;criminal proceedings.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="AN CATHAOIRLEACH AN CATHAOIRLEACH">
      <NameTxt>AN CATHAOIRLEACH</NameTxt>
      <P>I am afraid that I do not quite follow that.  You are assuming that the Irish courts would take the same view as the English?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SamuelBrownKC" hpid="Mr. BROWN Mr. BROWN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. BROWN</NameTxt>
      <P>I am assuming that they would follow that decision.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="AN CATHAOIRLEACH AN CATHAOIRLEACH">
      <NameTxt>AN CATHAOIRLEACH</NameTxt>
      <P>Is not that a very violent assumption?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SamuelBrownKC" hpid="Mr. BROWN Mr. BROWN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. BROWN</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not think so, Sir, if you read the Act.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="AN CATHAOIRLEACH AN CATHAOIRLEACH">
      <NameTxt>AN CATHAOIRLEACH</NameTxt>
      <P>The thing would be completely got over if you said that it shall apply to every criminal proceeding of every nature.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SamuelBrownKC" hpid="Mr. BROWN Mr. BROWN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. BROWN</NameTxt>
      <P>I am quite willing to move that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="AN CATHAOIRLEACH AN CATHAOIRLEACH">
      <NameTxt>AN CATHAOIRLEACH</NameTxt>
      <P>I think it ought to be made plain.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SamuelBrownKC" hpid="Mr. BROWN Mr. BROWN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. BROWN</NameTxt>
      <P>It will make it absolutely clear.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="AN CATHAOIRLEACH AN CATHAOIRLEACH">
      <NameTxt>AN CATHAOIRLEACH</NameTxt>
      <P>Because, you see, in some of these matters it is very difficult to say whether they are civil proceedings or criminal prosecutions, I mean cases in which there is only a fine or a penalty attached.  It is <Col N="902" /> not always easy to say whether it is a civil or criminal matter, I think.  Are you satisfied with that as it stands, Mr. O'Higgins?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="KevinChristopher" hpid="Mr. O'HIGGINS Mr. O'HIGGINS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'HIGGINS</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes, sir, but I would not object to the insertion of the other words if they are considered desirable.  My advice is that the words in the Bill will cover all summary prosecutions and offences punishable with imprisonment, or imprisonment in default of the payment of a fine, and that a definition would be difficult and would scarcely serve any useful purpose.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="AN CATHAOIRLEACH AN CATHAOIRLEACH">
      <NameTxt>AN CATHAOIRLEACH</NameTxt>
      <P>I think a definition would be difficult unless it is a definition to say that it would cover criminal proceedings of all kinds, and I think that is involved in the word &ldquo;all.&rdquo;  Probably it is wiser to leave it alone.</P>
      <P>Bill ordered for Final Stage.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="PUBLIC BUSINESS. - DEFENCE FORCES (TEMPORARY PROVISIONS) ACT," RHead="1923 (CONTINUANCE AND AMENDMENT) BILL, 1924&mdash;REPORT STAGE">
    <Title>PUBLIC BUSINESS. - DEFENCE FORCES (TEMPORARY PROVISIONS) ACT, 1923 (CONTINUANCE AND AMENDMENT) BILL, 1924&mdash;REPORT STAGE.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="AN CATHAOIRLEACH AN CATHAOIRLEACH">
      <NameTxt>AN CATHAOIRLEACH</NameTxt>
      <P>There are 42 sections in this Bill, but there has been no amendment either in Committee or put down for this stage, so that I do not propose to dwell further on it unless any Senator wishes to refer to a particular section.  If not, we will pass from it.</P>
      <P>Bill ordered for Final Stage.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="PUBLIC BUSINESS. - LOCAL ELECTIONS POSTPONEMENT" RHead="(AMENDMENT) BILL, 1924.&mdash;REPORT STAGE">
    <Title>PUBLIC BUSINESS. - LOCAL ELECTIONS POSTPONEMENT (AMENDMENT) BILL, 1924.&mdash;REPORT STAGE.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="AN CATHAOIRLEACH AN CATHAOIRLEACH">
      <NameTxt>AN CATHAOIRLEACH</NameTxt>
      <P>This is a purely formal Bill which consists of two sections only.  I take it that no Senator wishes to speak on it.</P>
      <P>Bill ordered for Final Stage.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="PUBLIC BUSINESS. - INDEMNITY" RHead="BILL, 1924.&mdash;REPORT STAGE">
    <Title>PUBLIC BUSINESS. - INDEMNITY BILL, 1924.&mdash;REPORT STAGE.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasLinehan" hpid="Mr. LINEHAN Mr. LINEHAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. LINEHAN</NameTxt>
      <P>The amendment on the Paper in my name is slightly inaccurate, and I would ask permission to change the year, so that it would read as follows:&mdash;Section 1, sub-section (4). To delete in line 29 the words &ldquo;11th <Col N="903" /> day of June, 1924,&rdquo; and to substitute therefor the words &ldquo;1st day of March, 1922.&rdquo;  As it appears on the Paper it is &ldquo;1919,&rdquo; and I ask permission to change that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="AN CATHAOIRLEACH AN CATHAOIRLEACH">
      <NameTxt>AN CATHAOIRLEACH</NameTxt>
      <P>There is something peculiar about that, Senator, because is not this an amendment that you moved in Committee?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasLinehan" hpid="Mr. LINEHAN Mr. LINEHAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. LINEHAN</NameTxt>
      <P>It is somewhat similar, but it is not the exact date.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="AN CATHAOIRLEACH AN CATHAOIRLEACH">
      <NameTxt>AN CATHAOIRLEACH</NameTxt>
      <P>Had you amended it when you gave it in?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasLinehan" hpid="Mr. LINEHAN Mr. LINEHAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. LINEHAN</NameTxt>
      <P>I gave in a verbal notice of the amendment for Report Stage.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="AN CATHAOIRLEACH AN CATHAOIRLEACH">
      <NameTxt>AN CATHAOIRLEACH</NameTxt>
      <P>I understand. You then gave it as 1922.  I am sure the House will give you permission to move it in that form.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasLinehan" hpid="Mr. LINEHAN Mr. LINEHAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. LINEHAN</NameTxt>
      <P>This amendment deals with the sub-section which is concerned with the voiding of judgments already given by the courts, but the period during which these judgments could be voided would be from 11th June, 1924, until the passing of the Bill.  That is a very short period, and my proposition is to go somewhat further back to cover other judgments that were given previously and which would be on the same footing as the judgments given after the 11th June, 1924.  If my amendment is not accepted, or an amendment with similar objects, it will be the disagreeable duty of the Government to enforce certain of those judgments which are not just or equitable in themselves, but which are legally correct.  From the remarks of the President in the debate on yesterday, I can infer that he meant I wanted to curtail the power of the Ministry, whereas the opposite is the fact.  This amendment gives increased power to the Minister dealing with this Bill to bring up judgments that are already given, and if the cases in which they were passed fulfilled the conditions in the earlier part of Section 1, they can be voided and compensation paid to any person who has been injuriously affected thereby.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="904" />
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="AN CATHAOIRLEACH AN CATHAOIRLEACH">
      <NameTxt>AN CATHAOIRLEACH</NameTxt>
      <P>What do you mean by &ldquo;compensation paid&rdquo;? Who is to pay it?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasLinehan" hpid="Mr. LINEHAN Mr. LINEHAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. LINEHAN</NameTxt>
      <P>There is provision in this Bill for compensation.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="AN CATHAOIRLEACH AN CATHAOIRLEACH">
      <NameTxt>AN CATHAOIRLEACH</NameTxt>
      <P>You mean in the case in which judgment is set aside?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasLinehan" hpid="Mr. LINEHAN Mr. LINEHAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. LINEHAN</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes, I would imagine so.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="AN CATHAOIRLEACH AN CATHAOIRLEACH">
      <NameTxt>AN CATHAOIRLEACH</NameTxt>
      <P>Where does that appear?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasLinehan" hpid="Mr. LINEHAN Mr. LINEHAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. LINEHAN</NameTxt>
      <P>In Section 6.  As regards the matter of judgments being voided, especially when there is compensation to be paid, it is not a very revolutionary proceeding, considering that we had at a very recent meeting of the Seanad agreed to the voiding of a judgment of the House of Lords without any compensation.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="AN CATHAOIRLEACH AN CATHAOIRLEACH">
      <NameTxt>AN CATHAOIRLEACH</NameTxt>
      <P>That was not your fault, Senator.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasLinehan" hpid="Mr. LINEHAN Mr. LINEHAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. LINEHAN</NameTxt>
      <P>My object in bringing forward this amendment is to cover a well-known case in the County Cork, where judgment has been given and where the Executive Government, if they enforce the judgments of the courts, will have to incur a very disagreeable duty in carrying out a judgment which the public at large know is unjust and inequitable, although it may be legally correct.  I do hope, therefore, that this amendment will be accepted, and I put it forward for the purpose of assisting the Government.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardButler" hpid="Mr. BUTLER Mr. BUTLER">
      <NameTxt>Mr. BUTLER</NameTxt>
      <P>I second the amendment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EarlofKerry" hpid="EARL of KERRY EARL of KERRY">
      <NameTxt>EARL of KERRY</NameTxt>
      <P>I am not quite clear on the question of a date.  One date was proposed in Committee, there is another one down to-day, and Senator Linehan wishes now to substitute a third.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="AN CATHAOIRLEACH AN CATHAOIRLEACH">
      <NameTxt>AN CATHAOIRLEACH</NameTxt>
      <P>I think it would be wise if the Senator would expound this a little more fully, because most of the Senators are probably in a fog about it.  I know I am myself. If you turn to Section 1 of the Bill you will see that the dates in it are the same <Col N="905" /> dates that you want to have inserted in sub-section 4.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasLinehan" hpid="Mr. LINEHAN Mr. LINEHAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. LINEHAN</NameTxt>
      <P>These are the dates on which the action would occur.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="AN CATHAOIRLEACH AN CATHAOIRLEACH">
      <NameTxt>AN CATHAOIRLEACH</NameTxt>
      <P>Oh, no. &ldquo;No action shall be instituted in any court of law in respect of any act, matter, or thing done after the 21st day of January, 1919, and before the 28th day of June, 1922.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasLinehan" hpid="Mr. LINEHAN Mr. LINEHAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. LINEHAN</NameTxt>
      <P>That is quite all right, but what I am referring to is the date of the judgment, not the date when the deed was done.  This sub-section, which voids judgments given at a certain period, does not take any account of similar judgments given prior to the 11th June, 1924.  My object is to bring in a further period prior to that, and to place in the hands of the Executive Council the power of voiding such judgments given if, in their opinion, they are unjust.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="AN CATHAOIRLEACH AN CATHAOIRLEACH">
      <NameTxt>AN CATHAOIRLEACH</NameTxt>
      <P>That was very violently resisted yesterday by the President as going far beyond anything the Government contemplated or intended.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasLinehan" hpid="Mr. LINEHAN Mr. LINEHAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. LINEHAN</NameTxt>
      <P>I think the President misunderstood my remark, because if you read the paper this morning you will see that he thought my object was to go back to some period prior to 1919, whereas, of course, there was no such thing as any judgment affecting these cases.  I fear I cannot further elucidate the matter, and I leave it to the Seanad.  I fear when the Government goes to execute some of these judgments they will be very sorry they did not accept my amendment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDouglas" hpid="Mr. DOUGLAS Mr. DOUGLAS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. DOUGLAS</NameTxt>
      <P>I think this is a clear case of the futility of taking the Report Stage immediately after the Committee Stage, when the Orders of the Day cannot be circulated.  Ministers do not know what additional amendments have been put down, and, therefore, we cannot get all the facts.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="AN CATHAOIRLEACH AN CATHAOIRLEACH">
      <NameTxt>AN CATHAOIRLEACH</NameTxt>
      <P>With regard to that, the President is quite aware of this amendment.  I have received <Col N="906" /> an intimation just now that he is on the way across to deal with it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDouglas" hpid="Mr. DOUGLAS Mr. DOUGLAS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. DOUGLAS</NameTxt>
      <P>There, again, that illustrates my point&mdash;the extreme speed with which the President is coming.  He cannot keep up with it, and I personally do not blame him.  I think in that case we should postpone it until he comes.  I was going to suggest that we should postpone the Report Stage until next week.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasLinehan" hpid="Mr. LINEHAN Mr. LINEHAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. LINEHAN</NameTxt>
      <P>I thoroughly agree with that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="AN CATHAOIRLEACH AN CATHAOIRLEACH">
      <NameTxt>AN CATHAOIRLEACH</NameTxt>
      <P>We will leave it over for the present.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="AN CATHAOIRLEACH AN CATHAOIRLEACH">
      <NameTxt>AN CATHAOIRLEACH</NameTxt>
      <P>As the President is here now we will resume discussion on Senator Linehan's amendment. The Senator thinks that the President misunderstood him yesterday when speaking on this amendment, and he says that he is really bringing it forward in the interests of the Government. He hopes, therefore, that the President will view it in a more favourable light to-day than he did yesterday.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>I have not anything further to add to what I said yesterday on the subject.  I have been in conference with Senator Linehan on this matter, and he has not been able to shake my opinion on it.  In my opinion the insertion of this amendment would practically make inoperative the security that we propose to give to persons who are being penalised. In the case of the British indemnity that we gave, we dated that for the date of the passing of the Bill, although at the time, I think there was only one post within the area of our jurisdiction which was occupied by British troops, and I do not suppose that a single one of them was affected by it. We gave it generously, covering the whole of them up to the last date.  The insertion of this amendment, as far as I can understand it, would bring in all those cases&mdash;the complaints of persons who, acting under orders, took certain property.  The case put forward by Senator Linehan, as I understand it, is an agricultural case, and from the information he has given me the eviction took place in 1893.  Well during the period when Dáil Eireann <Col N="907" /> was functioning under difficulties, from its inception about 1919 down to the Truce&mdash;I am speaking now from recollection and subject to correction, but I do not think I am making any mistake whatever&mdash;the Ministry of Home Affairs at the time refused absolutely to deal with cases in which there were agricultural disputes for any period earlier than 10 years before the setting up of Dáil Eireann.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>That would bring us into the year 1909.  In this case the dispute, as I understand it, occurred in 1893.  It was not without consideration of the size of the problem that we were dealing with that we refused to bring in cases for a longer period than 10 years. In this case, if there were reasons for its insertion, those reasons are not to be found in any authority that we assumed during that period, and if this particular case were to be allowed in why not others, and there may have been many others.  In these circumstances, I do not think I would be justified in accepting on behalf of the Government an amendment which would benefit one particular case, and which might involve a large number of persons in decrees and leave them open for liability.  In the circumstances of the case, we would not be justified in leaving them under such a liability.  Whatever responsibility there was at the time, it rested upon Dáil Eireann and upon the Executive appointed by Dáil Eireann.  Whatever views may be held upon that, and I know there are many who dispute its right and authority and so on, the circumstances have placed us in the position of seeing that those who acted under our authority should not now be made to suffer for what was our responsibility at the time.  We accept the fullest responsibility for it, and in some cases some of our friends paid a very high price for assuming that responsibility. Now a time comes when we have got to protect the persons who acted in good faith during that period, and in these cases where property was taken or other acts were performed, we are giving them that protection.  A very large number of cases are listed for hearing.  I do not know what the effect of this amendment would be, but <Col N="908" /> a very large number of these cases could be gone on with, and therefore the protection which we pretend to give in this case would be discounted. On that account I am afraid, that on behalf of the Government I could not accept the amendment.</P>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasLinehan" hpid="Mr. LINEHAN Mr. LINEHAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. LINEHAN</NameTxt>
      <P>I am in entire agreement with the President as far as seeing that these people who acted in good faith in these times will not suffer any loss, and that they should be relieved of any liability that they incurred. The case I am referring to is the case of an evicted holding.  The tenant was evicted in the year 1893, and from that period up to 1916 the evicted holding had to be held by a force of constabulary, who were in residence on the farm.  The Volunteers of that district decided that it would help to terminate the British rule in this country by bringing back the evicted tenant from America.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="AN CATHAOIRLEACH AN CATHAOIRLEACH">
      <NameTxt>AN CATHAOIRLEACH</NameTxt>
      <P>Seems farfetched !</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasLinehan" hpid="Mr. LINEHAN Mr. LINEHAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. LINEHAN</NameTxt>
      <P>And placing him on the farm.  That was done by persons who were qualified under the first section of this Act as persons employed &ldquo;in any capacity whatsoever or in any service, military or civil.&rdquo;  They acted in good faith in doing that, and my object in moving this amendment is to see that they in no way suffer for their action in that respect.  They did it with the object to help to end the struggle that was then going on, and I cannot imagine any greater means of doing so than the reinstatement of an evicted tenant in his holding, especially when that holding had to be held by a force of constabulary during the whole period of twenty years. Judgment has now been given in that case against the evicted tenant, and I presume it will be the duty of the Executive Government to execute that judgment.  I am moving this amendment with the object of giving the Government an opportunity to look into the facts of this case and to ascertain whether this was done under the conditions specified under Section 1 of this Bill.  I have here the names of the military officers who carried out this proceeding.  They were Lieutenant <Col N="909" /> Tumbleton and Commandant Leahy, of Midleton.  Under this Act the Minister can investigate this case, and see whether this action was done for the public good or merely for the benefit of an individual.  I leave the matter there. I am sorry that the President could not see his way to accept the amendment.  I have done my part in trying to bring about an amicable arrangement, so that the Government would not be put to the necessity of enforcing this most unpopular judgment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not know, even if we agreed to insert this amendment, that this particular case would fall under Section 1 of this Act.  I have been fairly candid on this question. It was not our intention in connection with this Act to validate every irregular action that was committed during that period.  I know quite a number of them.  I recollect in one case where officers exceeded their duty and they were pulled up by the Minister for Defence for doing so.  There was a charge of £1,000 made for collecting £3,000 in rates, and as I was responsible for Local Government at the time I drew the attention of the Minister for Defence to the matter, and pointed out that it was an exorbitant charge which could not be justified. The excuse made by the officers was that by reason of their collection of £3,000 a sum of £30,000 came in later, and they claimed that they were entitled to this £1,000 in payment of the £30,000 which were subsequently collected.  In that case, as Minister for Local Government, I put a charge on my estimate for £750, and I said we will only ask the officers to pay back the balance of £250.  It was not paid back, but it is not my intention to validate that seizure, for which these men should have been prosecuted in our own courts.  From what I have heard from Senator Linehan, the officers he refers to did not act under orders and were not justified in giving the orders they gave, nor were they justified in the action they took in that case.  Even if this amendment were inserted in the place where it is proposed to insert it, I do not think there is authority given in the main section, <Col N="910" /> which proposes to validate certain acts done, to validate this particular act. Even if the amendment were put in, I do not think it will effect the purpose the Senator has in view.</P>
      <P>Amendment put and declared lost.</P>
      <P>Indemnity Bill ordered for Fifth Stage.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="PUBLIC BUSINESS. - TELEPHONE" RHead="CAPITAL BILL, 1924 REPORT">
    <Title>PUBLIC BUSINESS. - TELEPHONE CAPITAL BILL, 1924 REPORT.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="AN CATHAOIRLEACH AN CATHAOIRLEACH">
      <NameTxt>AN CATHAOIRLEACH</NameTxt>
      <P>This is a certified Money Bill.  No recommendations were made in Committee upon it, and if no Senator wishes to make any observations on it, I think we might pass this Report Stage.</P>
      <P>Bill ordered for Fifth Stage.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="PUBLIC BUSINESS. - TRADE LOANS" RHead="(GUARANTEE) BILL, 1924&mdash;REPORT">
    <Title>PUBLIC BUSINESS. - TRADE LOANS (GUARANTEE) BILL, 1924&mdash;REPORT.</Title>
    <P>Bill received for final consideration, and ordered for Fifth Stage.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="PUBLIC BUSINESS. - FISHERIES (ELECTION OF CONSERVATORS" RHead="POSTPONEMENT) BILL, 1924&mdash;REPORT">
    <Title>PUBLIC BUSINESS. - FISHERIES (ELECTION OF CONSERVATORS POSTPONEMENT) BILL, 1924&mdash;REPORT.</Title>
    <P>Bill received for final consideration, and ordered for Fifth Stage.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="PUBLIC BUSINESS. - OIREACHTAS WITNESSES'" RHead="OATHS BILL, 1924&mdash;REPORT">
    <Title>PUBLIC BUSINESS. - OIREACHTAS WITNESSES' OATHS BILL, 1924&mdash;REPORT.</Title>
    <P>Motion made and question proposed that&mdash;&ldquo;The Bill be now received for final consideration.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="AN CATHAOIRLEACH AN CATHAOIRLEACH">
      <NameTxt>AN CATHAOIRLEACH</NameTxt>
      <P>This Bill was referred by the Seanad to a Select Committee of the House under the chairmanship of Senator Douglas.  The Select Committee has now reported that it took the Bill into consideration and desires to report same to the Seanad without amendment.  As there is no amendment on this Report Stage, and as the whole Bill is a formal one, I will now put the motion.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>Bill ordered for the Fifth Stage.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="PUBLIC BUSINESS. - PRIVATE" RHead="BILL&mdash;COSTS BILL, 1924&mdash;REPORT">
    <Title>PUBLIC BUSINESS. - PRIVATE BILL&mdash;COSTS BILL, 1924&mdash;REPORT.</Title>
    <P>
      <Col N="911" /> Motion made and question proposed &mdash;&ldquo;That this Bill be now received for final consideration.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="AN CATHAOIRLEACH AN CATHAOIRLEACH">
      <NameTxt>AN CATHAOIRLEACH</NameTxt>
      <P>This Bill was also referred to the same Select Committee, and they have returned it with a number of amendments which have been circulated with the papers sent out to Senators.  The Bill, as it stands now, includes these amendments inserted in Committee.  I do not know that any Senator wishes to say anything upon the Bill or the amendments. It is really in its essence a formal Bill, and deals with technical matters.  As I understand it, the intention in the Bill discloses that the matter is to be reconsidered later on when an Omnibus Bill dealing with the whole subject will be introduced.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDouglas" hpid="Mr. DOUGLAS Mr. DOUGLAS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. DOUGLAS</NameTxt>
      <P>The Committee went through all the references and took up all the Acts, and the whole matter was carefully considered.  The amendments are of a verbal character.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>Bill ordered for Fifth Stage.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="PUBLIC BUSINESS. - DUBLIN POLICE" RHead="BILL, 1924&mdash;FIFTH STAGE">
    <Title>PUBLIC BUSINESS. - DUBLIN POLICE BILL, 1924&mdash;FIFTH STAGE.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="AN CATHAOIRLEACH AN CATHAOIRLEACH">
      <NameTxt>AN CATHAOIRLEACH</NameTxt>
      <P>The question is: &ldquo;That this Bill be now received for final consideration, and do now pass.&rdquo;</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="PUBLIC BUSINESS. - DAIL EIREANN (WINDING-UP) ACT," RHead="1923, AMENDMENT BILL, 1924&mdash;FIFTH STAGE">
    <Title>PUBLIC BUSINESS. - DAIL EIREANN (WINDING-UP) ACT, 1923, AMENDMENT BILL, 1924&mdash;FIFTH STAGE.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="AN CATHAOIRLEACH AN CATHAOIRLEACH">
      <NameTxt>AN CATHAOIRLEACH</NameTxt>
      <P>The question is: &ldquo;That this Bill be received for final consideration and do now pass.&rdquo;</P>
      <P>Agreed.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="PUBLIC BUSINESS. -" RHead="BUSINESS OF THE SEANAD">
    <Title>PUBLIC BUSINESS. - BUSINESS OF THE SEANAD.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="AN CATHAOIRLEACH AN CATHAOIRLEACH">
      <NameTxt>AN CATHAOIRLEACH</NameTxt>
      <P>As the President is here, perhaps he would allow me to take the opportunity to ask him whether he can give any idea of the course of business for next week.  I <Col N="912" /> ask that with a view to making arrangements for the sitting of the Seanad next week.  I do not know whether the President is yet in a position to tell us what the intentions of the Government are as to the conclusion of business and the winding-up of the session.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>I was in hopes that we would have been able to adjourn to-day after having taken the Appropriation Bill, but some business that has transpired since makes it unlikely that we can adjourn this week. I do not know that we will be in a position to present the Appropriation Bill this week.  I hope that there may be some measures passed this week that are non-contentious, but which we should be very glad to have passed, but I am not in a position just now to give you the information.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDouglas" hpid="Mr. DOUGLAS Mr. DOUGLAS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. DOUGLAS</NameTxt>
      <P>Does that mean in substance that the Appropriation Bill would not be taken until the week after next?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>It is possible it may be passed in the Dáil next week.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="PUBLIC BUSINESS. - NATIONAL HEALTH" RHead="INSURANCE BILL, 1924&mdash;FIFTH STAGE">
    <Title>PUBLIC BUSINESS. - NATIONAL HEALTH INSURANCE BILL, 1924&mdash;FIFTH STAGE.</Title>
    <P>Question&mdash;&ldquo;That this Bill be received for final consideration, and do now pass&rdquo;&mdash; put and agreed to.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="PUBLIC BUSINESS. - AGRICULTURAL PRODUCE" RHead="(EGGS) BILL, 1924&mdash;FIFTH STAGE">
    <Title>PUBLIC BUSINESS. - AGRICULTURAL PRODUCE (EGGS) BILL, 1924&mdash;FIFTH STAGE.</Title>
    <P>Question&mdash;&ldquo;That this Bill be received for final consideration and do now pass&rdquo;&mdash;put and agreed to.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="PUBLIC BUSINESS. -" RHead="MOTION OF DR. SIGERSON">
    <Title>PUBLIC BUSINESS. - MOTION OF DR. SIGERSON.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="AN CATHAOIRLEACH AN CATHAOIRLEACH">
      <NameTxt>AN CATHAOIRLEACH</NameTxt>
      <P>The next item is a motion standing in the name of Senator Sigerson, who is not here. Out of respect to him and having regard to the interest which he takes in the subject matter of this motion, perhaps the House will consent to its standing over.</P>
      <P>Agreed.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="PUBLIC BUSINESS. -" RHead="BUSINESS OF THE SEANAD">
    <Title>PUBLIC BUSINESS. - BUSINESS OF THE SEANAD.</Title>
    <Col N="913" />
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="AN CATHAOIRLEACH AN CATHAOIRLEACH">
      <NameTxt>AN CATHAOIRLEACH</NameTxt>
      <P>Before we adjourn to-day we have to determine our sittings for next week.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDouglas" hpid="Mr. DOUGLAS Mr. DOUGLAS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. DOUGLAS</NameTxt>
      <P>There is a matter which Senator Sir John Keane asked me to raise when we were considering the business for next week.  He asked me if it were possible to reach some kind of understanding in regard to the consideration of the Appropriation Bill.  It is usual, I think, and is understood that the general discussion of the Estimates takes place in this House on the consideration of the Appropriation Bill.  It is reasonably certain that we cannot expect the whole Ministry to attend here during that discussion, but, on the other hand, the raising of a point on the Estimates would not be of very great value if the questions raised were not answered.  Senator Sir John Keane asked me to suggest without prejudice to the right of members to discuss any point on general discussion that notices might be sent out to members of the Seanad intimating that if they desired to raise any particular point notice should be given to the Seanad office the day before so that the Minister concerned could be notified.  I am not sure that this would be the best arrangement, but for this year possibly his suggestion is a good one.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="AN CATHAOIRLEACH AN CATHAOIRLEACH">
      <NameTxt>AN CATHAOIRLEACH</NameTxt>
      <P>That could be met in this way.  When we could definitely determine what day the Appropriation Bill will reach us we could arrange that any Senator who wishes to raise any particular point on any particular Estimate should hand in an intimation to the Clerk that upon consideration of the Appropriation Bill he proposes to call attention to such and such a matter.  That would be an intimation to the particular Minister engaged.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDouglas" hpid="Mr. DOUGLAS Mr. DOUGLAS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. DOUGLAS</NameTxt>
      <P>I think he meant that when the Orders for the Day for next week are going out a note might be appended, saying that the Appropriation Bill would probably reach us next week or the week after.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="AN CATHAOIRLEACH AN CATHAOIRLEACH">
      <NameTxt>AN CATHAOIRLEACH</NameTxt>
      <P>It will require <Col N="914" /> a little attention in the drafting, but I will see that some notice of that kind is put on the agenda.  The only other question that we have to decide is when we shall meet next week; Wednesday is our normal day of meeting. There is no exceptional advantage to be gained by meeting on Tuesday.  Possibly, it will be better for us to adhere to our normal day.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnMacLoughlin" hpid="Mr. McLOUGHLIN Mr. McLOUGHLIN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McLOUGHLIN</NameTxt>
      <P>I think we should not meet until Thursday.  It is scarcely possible that business will not reach us on Tuesday.  There is something happening on Wednesday, and if we are to meet on that date it should be at 11 o'clock.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="AN CATHAOIRLEACH AN CATHAOIRLEACH">
      <NameTxt>AN CATHAOIRLEACH</NameTxt>
      <P>Is there any reason why we should not meet at 11.30?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SamuelBrownKC" hpid="Mr. BROWN Mr. BROWN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. BROWN</NameTxt>
      <P>In Leinster House?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="AN CATHAOIRLEACH AN CATHAOIRLEACH">
      <NameTxt>AN CATHAOIRLEACH</NameTxt>
      <P>That would be at 10.30.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JanePower" hpid="Mrs. WYSE POWER Mrs. WYSE POWER">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. WYSE POWER</NameTxt>
      <P>What is the particular reason for meeting at 11 o'clock instead of three?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="AN CATHAOIRLEACH AN CATHAOIRLEACH">
      <NameTxt>AN CATHAOIRLEACH</NameTxt>
      <P>There have been mysterious hints and suggestions from various quarters.  Senator McLoughlin had something on his mind.  I think it is rather a mistake in view of the possibility of work that we should not meet before Thursday.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDouglas" hpid="Mr. DOUGLAS Mr. DOUGLAS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. DOUGLAS</NameTxt>
      <P>I take it that we have the remaining stages of about half of these nineteen Bills to get through, but that might not take very long.  I do not think that there is going to be much more business ready for us.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="AN CATHAOIRLEACH AN CATHAOIRLEACH">
      <NameTxt>AN CATHAOIRLEACH</NameTxt>
      <P>Do you think that the House is likely to take any interest in the Dairy Produce Bill?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDowdall" hpid="Mr. DOWDALL Mr. DOWDALL">
      <NameTxt>Mr. DOWDALL</NameTxt>
      <P>From what I hear, I do not think that it will reach us this Session.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDouglas" hpid="Mr. DOUGLAS Mr. DOUGLAS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. DOUGLAS</NameTxt>
      <P>I spoke to the Minister about it, and he expressed doubt about the Seanad being called upon to discuss it before the adjournment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="915" />
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="AN CATHAOIRLEACH AN CATHAOIRLEACH">
      <NameTxt>AN CATHAOIRLEACH</NameTxt>
      <P>It is a very long Bill.  In that event the House will meet at 11 o'clock on Thursday morning. I hope to see as many Senators as <Col N="916" /> possible at Leinster House at half-past ten on that day.</P>
      <P>The Seanad adjourned until 11 o'clock on Thursday, 24th July, 1924.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
</Debate>