<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE Debate SYSTEM "../Debate.dtd"[]>
<Debate DocTitle="D&aacute;il Debate" Day="Thu" Date="25" Month="Mar" Year="1954" Vol="145" No="2" DateIrish="Déardaoin, 25 Márta 1954" DateEnglish="Thursday, 25 March 1954" House="D" CommitteeEng="" CommitteeIr="" SubNameEng="" cnum="0">
  <MainHeading Type="Prelude" LHead="" RHead="">
    <Title>
    </Title>
    <P>
      <Col N="169" /> Do chuaigh an Ceann Comhairle i gceannas ar 3 p.m.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions. Oral" RHead="Answers. - Passenger Movements">
    <Title>Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions.   Oral Answers. - Passenger Movements.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMacBride" hpid="Mr. MacBride Mr. MacBride">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacBride</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Taoiseach if he will give particulars for the year 1953 of the number of persons (1) entering and (2) leaving the State, together with the balance of passenger movements, by (a) sea, (b) rail, (c) air and (d) road.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DonnchadhOBriain" hpid="Parliamentary Secretary to the Taoiseach (Donnchadh Ó Briain) (for the Taoiseach) Donnchadh Ó Briain">
      <NameTxt>Parliamentary Secretary to the Taoiseach (Donnchadh Ó Briain) (for the Taoiseach)</NameTxt>
      <P>It is not possible to state the total number of persons who entered the State and left the State in 1953.  The total inward passenger movement by sea, rail, air (excluding transit traffic) and road (motor omnibus service only) in that year was 2,048,162 while the outward passenger movement by the same modes of travel in the year was 2,068,105.  In 1953 the balance of passenger movement by sea was 31,113 outward, by rail it was 3,502 inward, by air (excluding transit traffic) it was 3,022 outward and by road (motor omnibus service only) it was 10,690 inward.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BrendanCorish" hpid="Mr. Corish Mr. Corish">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Corish</NameTxt>
      <P>Could the Parliamentary Secretary say what the total is?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DonnchadhOBriain" hpid="Donnchadh Ó Briain Donnchadh Ó Briain">
      <NameTxt>Donnchadh Ó Briain</NameTxt>
      <P>Which total?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonDeValera" hpid="The Taoiseach Eamon de Valera">
      <NameTxt>The Taoiseach</NameTxt>
      <P>The pluses and minuses, is it?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DonnchadhOBriain" hpid="Donnchadh Ó Briain Donnchadh Ó Briain">
      <NameTxt>Donnchadh Ó Briain</NameTxt>
      <P>Twenty-six thousand.*</P>
      <P>*Later the Parliamentary Secretary made the following correction:&mdash;I gave an incorrect calculation.  I said 26,000.  The actual figure is 19,943.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions. Oral" RHead="Answers. - Unemployment Statistics">
    <Title>Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions.   Oral Answers. - Unemployment Statistics.</Title>
    <Col N="170" />
    <Speaker pid="SeanMacBride" hpid="Mr. MacBride Mr. MacBride">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacBride</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Taoiseach if he will state the average number of persons registered on the live register of unemployment for each of the years 1950 to 1953, inclusive.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DonnchadhOBriain" hpid="Donnchadh Ó Briain Donnchadh Ó Briain">
      <NameTxt>Donnchadh Ó Briain</NameTxt>
      <P>The average numbers of persons on the live register at a date at the end of each month were: 53,794 in 1950; 51,639 in 1951; 60,797 in 1952 and 69,973 in 1953.  The content of the figures in 1953 differs from that of previous years due to the changes effected by the Social Welfare Act, 1952.  It is not possible to give a precise measure of the effect of these changes in increasing the live register.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonDeValera" hpid="The Taoiseach Eamon de Valera">
      <NameTxt>The Taoiseach</NameTxt>
      <P>Between 7,000 and 8,000.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions. Oral" RHead="Answers. - Cork Airport Facilities">
    <Title>Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions.   Oral Answers. - Cork Airport Facilities.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickDesmondLehane" hpid="Mr. Lehane Mr. Lehane">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lehane</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Industry and Commerce if he is aware that private enterprise is prepared to provide all the capital and facilities necessary for an airport at Cork and whether in view of the fact that helicopters will shortly be used for comparatively short flights, he will now consider granting a permit for scheduled flights from Cork in the event of suitable facilities being provided.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Minister for Industry and Commerce (Mr. Lemass) Seán F. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Industry and Commerce (Mr. Lemass)</NameTxt>
      <P>All the relevant factors were considered before the Government reached their decision to provide at Cork a State airport suitable for internal, cross-Channel and European scheduled air services.  I am satisfied that the requisite facilities for scheduled services cannot be provided in any other way.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickDesmondLehane" hpid="Mr. Lehane Mr. Lehane">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lehane</NameTxt>
      <P>Is the Minister prevented by some international agreement from giving permission for scheduled flights from Cork to a privately controlled aerodrome?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>No, the only objection I have to the airport at Farmers Cross is that it is not safe for scheduled air services.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="171" />
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGrath" hpid="Mr. McGrath Mr. McGrath">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGrath</NameTxt>
      <P>Can the Minister show any reason why Cork is not entitled to a modern up to date airport as well as Dublin or Shannon?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. O'Higgins Mr. O'Higgins">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Higgins</NameTxt>
      <P>Up Cork!</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamNorton" hpid="Mr. Norton Mr. Norton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norton</NameTxt>
      <P>It wants a modern lord mayor too.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions. Oral" RHead="Answers. - Rural Electrification">
    <Title>Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions.   Oral Answers. - Rural Electrification.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="RichardBarry" hpid="Mr. Barry Mr. Barry">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Barry</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Industry and Commerce if he will state when the rural electrification scheme will be extended to the Kildorrery and Ballindangan areas, County Cork.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>I am informed by the E.S.B. that the Kildorrery and Ballindangan areas were not successful when considered in January in conjunction with other areas awaiting development in the board's Cork No. 2 District for development under the rural electrification scheme.  The board is unable to state when development is likely to take place but suggests that the prospects of early selection could be improved by an increase in the numbers of householders in the areas willing to take supply.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions." RHead="Oral Answers. - E.S.B. Charges">
    <Title>Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions.   Oral Answers. - E.S.B. Charges.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasNJByrne" hpid="Mr. T. Byrne Mr. T. Byrne">
      <NameTxt>Mr. T. Byrne</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Industry and Commerce whether, in view of the general dissatisfaction with the new E.S.B. charges to consumers, he will arrange that consumers affected may individually or as organised groups petition the Prices Advisory Body to review the increased charges for electricity; and, if not, if he will state why the E.S.B. should be so protected when a similar undertaking, viz., the Alliance and Dublin Consumers Gas Company, had to appear before the Prices Advisory Body some 18 months ago when they were about to bring in increased charges for gas.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>The answer to the first part of the question is in the negative.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>As regards the remainder of the question, I would remind the Deputy that, unlike other public utility undertakings, the E.S.B. has no share capital to be remunerated by the distribution of annual dividends.  On the <Col N="172" /> contrary, there is an obligation imposed on the E.S.B. by statute to fix its charges at such a level as will ensure that its revenue will be sufficient, and only sufficient, to enable the board to pay its way.</P>
    <P>As I informed the Deputy on the 25th February, the E.S.B. has stated that the recent change is designed to secure a simpler and more equitable system of charges which, while bringing the whole country closer to a uniform tariff, would not yield any additional net revenue to the board.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions. Oral" RHead="Answers. - Import Duty on Coal">
    <Title>Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions.   Oral Answers. - Import Duty on Coal.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMacBride" hpid="Mr. MacBride Mr. MacBride">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacBride</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Industry and Commerce if he will state in regard to the import duty recently imposed on coal imported from countries other than Great Britain (1) the date on which this duty was imposed; (2) the amount of the duty, and (3) the reason for its imposition.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>The customs duty on coal imported from countries other than Britain and Canada came into effect on 19th May, 1938.  The amount of the duty is 3/- a ton and it was imposed in consequence of Article 16 of the agreement concluded with Britain in 1938.  It has, however, been suspended since March, 1947 with the consent of the British Government, and will remain suspended until 1st April, 1954.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions. Oral" RHead="Answers. - Stationery Office Contract">
    <Title>Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions.   Oral Answers. - Stationery Office Contract.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="RobertBriscoe" hpid="Mr. Briscoe Mr. Briscoe">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Briscoe</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Finance if he is aware that the Stationery Office advertising contract has been transferred from the contractor who has held it for over 30 years to a new advertising agency; and, if so, if he will state by whom the contract was placed and, if the transfer was made on the basis of a lower tender, whether the difference was such as to justify a change from the former contractor who has handled the business for 30 years and built up and maintained a highly specialised organisation specially to service this account and if he will further state whether the new contractor has given an assurance that he will hand back <Col N="173" /> to the Stationery Office the whole or any part of the commission which would normally be paid to him by the papers carrying Government advertisements and, in this event, what assurance he has had that the new contractor will be in a position to fulfil this undertaking.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Minister for Finance (Mr. MacEntee) Seán MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Finance (Mr. MacEntee)</NameTxt>
      <P>I am aware that on the recent termination of the contract for an agency for Government advertising in newspapers and periodicals the new contract was placed with a firm other than the firm which had previously held it.  The contract was placed by the Controller of the Stationery Office with the prior approval of the Government Contracts Committee.  In the light of assurances sought from and given by the successful tenderer, it appeared to the Stationery Office and the Government Contracts Committee that his tender would be substantially more advantageous to the State than that of any other effective tenderer.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RobertBriscoe" hpid="Mr. Briscoe Mr. Briscoe">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Briscoe</NameTxt>
      <P>Might I ask whether it is a fact that the previous contractor held this contract for a period of 30 years?  Further, was the proposal to change from this contractor submitted to the Minister for his approval or sanction?  In addition, the Minister refers to certain assurances. Could he tell the House what were the specific assurances given by this new contractor which would be more advantageous than those given by the previous contractor?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BrendanCorish" hpid="Mr. Corish Mr. Corish">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Corish</NameTxt>
      <P>Could the Minister further say if the assurances were part of the contract?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>As to the first of the supplementary questions, I cannot say for how long the previous contractor held this contract, but I know that it was for quite a considerable number of years; in fact, I think for well over 20 years.  The matter, as I pointed out in my reply to the House, did not come before the Minister for Finance personally.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>On a point of order.  Is there any precedent for a Minister <Col N="174" /> disclaiming personal responsibility for a matter in respect of which he purports to answer to the House?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickHogan" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Patrick (Clare) Hogan">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>I did not understand the Minister to disclaim responsibility.  He said the matter did not come before him.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>That is all.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>It is a new departure.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickHogan" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Patrick (Clare) Hogan">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>It is not.  As far as I know the Minister is just saying that the matter did not come before him.  That is not renouncing responsibility of any kind.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>It is next door to it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not know what Deputy Dillon's attitude in this matter betokens.  I have answered the question put to me as to whether it was personally submitted to me.  I said &ldquo;No.&rdquo;  That is not a disclaimer of responsibility.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RobertBriscoe" hpid="Mr. Briscoe Mr. Briscoe">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Briscoe</NameTxt>
      <P>I asked the Minister if he could tell the House what were the specific assurances given by this new contractor which would be more advantageous to the State than the previous contractor was able to give?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>The question as to whether the assurance would be more advantageous to the State would be a matter of opinion and I do not think there is anything I can usefully add to the answer I have already given.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RobertBriscoe" hpid="Mr. Briscoe Mr. Briscoe">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Briscoe</NameTxt>
      <P>I wish to give notice that I propose to raise this matter on the Adjournment because I am not satisfied.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickHogan" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Patrick (Clare) Hogan">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>I will communicate with the Deputy.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions. Oral Answers." RHead="- Repairs to Áras an Uachtaráin">
    <Title>Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions.   Oral Answers. - Repairs to Áras an Uachtaráin.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickODonnell" hpid="Mr. O'Donnell Mr. O'Donnell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Donnell</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Finance if he will state the estimate or contract price of the repairs which are at present being carried out at Áras an Uachtaráin, Phoenix Park, Dublin.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="175" />
    <Speaker pid="PatrickBeegan" hpid="Parliamentary Secretary to the Minister for Finance (Mr. Beegan) Patrick Beegan">
      <NameTxt>Parliamentary Secretary to the Minister for Finance (Mr. Beegan)</NameTxt>
      <P>It is presumed that the question refers to the remodelling of the east wing of the main building and other improvements at present being carried out at Áras an Uachtaráin.  The total estimated cost of that work is £44,500.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions. Oral" RHead="Answers. - Survey of River Suck">
    <Title>Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions.   Oral Answers. - Survey of River Suck.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="MarkKillileaSnr" hpid="Mr. Killilea Mr. Killilea">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Killilea</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Finance if he will state what steps he has taken to implement the promise made by him during the debate on the Estimate for Public Works and Buildings on the 22nd October, 1953 (Volume 152, column 464) that he would make a recommendation to the Government that the River Suck be next for survey.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickBeegan" hpid="Mr. Beegan Mr. Beegan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Beegan</NameTxt>
      <P>A survey of the River Suck catchment for the purpose of preparing a scheme under the Arterial Drainage Act, 1945, for that catchment began in February last.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions. Oral" RHead="Answers. - County Kerry Boat Slip">
    <Title>Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions.   Oral Answers. - County Kerry Boat Slip.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickWPalmer" hpid="Mr. Palmer Mr. Palmer">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Palmer</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Finance if he will have a survey made of the boat slip at Clonee Lake, Tuosist, Kenmare, with a view to its repair in view of the fact that the pier is essential for anglers, local and otherwise, in waters which are free for all fishermen and in which angling competitions are carried on annually.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickBeegan" hpid="Mr. Beegan Mr. Beegan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Beegan</NameTxt>
      <P>I have no function regarding the initiation of a scheme such as that proposed.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions. Oral Answers. -" RHead="Arranmore Island: Appointment of Medical Officers">
    <Title>Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions.   Oral Answers. - Arranmore Island: Appointment of Medical Officers.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickODonnell" hpid="Mr. O'Donnell Mr. O'Donnell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Donnell</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Health if he will state the number of medical officers appointed by the Local Appointments Commission to Arranmore dispensary, County Donegal, between the 1st January, 1930, and the 1st February, 1954, and if he will indicate the respective periods which each appointee held this appointment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickODonnell" hpid="Mr. O'Donnell Mr. O'Donnell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Donnell</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Health if in view of the fact that it is impossible to get any medical officer <Col N="176" /> appointed to the Arranmore dispensary, County Donegal, to spend more than a very brief period in residence on the island, he will recommend to the Donegal County Council the urgent necessity for the erection of a doctor's residence on the island.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickODonnell" hpid="Mr. O'Donnell Mr. O'Donnell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Donnell</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Health if in view of the fact that medical officers appointed to the Arranmore dispensary district, County Donegal, by the Local Appointments Commission, spend but brief periods in such appointments, he will leave the future appointments of dispensary doctors to the island in the hands of the Donegal County Council.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Minister for Health (Dr. Ryan) James Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Health (Dr. Ryan)</NameTxt>
      <P>With your permission, a Cheann Comhairle, I propose to take Questions Nos. 11, 12 and 13 together.</P>
      <P>Nine medical officers have been appointed through the Local Appointments Commission to Dungloe No. 3 dispensary district (which comprises the island of Arranmore) since 1930. The periods during which they served are indicated in a tabular statement which, with your permission, I will circulate with the Official Report.</P>
      <P>I have twice recommended to the Donegal County Council that a residence for the medical officer should be provided on the island but the council have informed me that they do not propose to accept the recommendation.</P>
      <P>The Local Authorities (Officers and Employees) Act, 1926, applies to this post and accordingly the selection of candidates for permanent appointment must be made under Section 5 or Section 6 of the Act.  The Local Appointments Commissioners select candidates for posts filled under Section 6.  Under Section 5 a local authority can, with my permission, fill a vacancy by transfer of a permanent medical officer from another dispensary district.  Should Donegal County Council propose to fill any future vacancies in the post under Section 5 of the Act I will be prepared to sanction such proposal.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Following is the tabular statement referred to in the reply: <Col N="177" /> Dates during which permanent medical officers served in this district.</P>
    <P>(1)  18-3-1930 to 30-11-1934</P>
    <P>(2)  15-7-1935 to 31-12-1935</P>
    <P>(3)  15-6-1936 to 30-11-1936</P>
    <P>(4)  21-6-1937 to 16-10-1937</P>
    <P>(5)  20-6-1938 to 31-5-1940</P>
    <P>(6)  8-4-1941 to 1-7-1942</P>
    <P>(7)  19-7-1944 to 22-1-1946</P>
    <P>(8)  26-11-1947 to 8-2-1951</P>
    <P>(9)  28-7-1952 to 17-10-1953</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions. Oral Answers. -" RHead="Trend of Employment and Unemployment Report">
    <Title>Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions.   Oral Answers. - Trend of Employment and Unemployment Report.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMacBride" hpid="Mr. MacBride Mr. MacBride">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacBride</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Social Welfare if he will state the reason for the delay in the publication of the report on the trend of employment and unemployment for the years 1950 and 1951 and if he will indicate when this report will now be published.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Minister for Social Welfare (Dr. Ryan) James Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Social Welfare (Dr. Ryan)</NameTxt>
      <P>Changes in the form and contents of this document have involved delay in its preparation.  It is now hoped to publish next month a report covering the years 1950, 1951, 1952 and part of 1953.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions. Oral" RHead="Answers. - County Roscommon Lands">
    <Title>Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions.   Oral Answers. - County Roscommon Lands.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="JohnMcQuillan" hpid="Mr. McQuillan Mr. McQuillan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McQuillan</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Lands if he will state what progress has been made by the Land Commission towards the acquisition of the O'Malley farm, Rathconnor, County Roscommon, for the purpose of division amongst deserving applicants.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasDerrig" hpid="Minister for Lands (Mr. Derrig) Thomas Derrig">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Lands (Mr. Derrig)</NameTxt>
      <P>The Land Commission have called for a detailed report on, and valuation of, this estate.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnMcQuillan" hpid="Mr. McQuillan Mr. McQuillan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McQuillan</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Lands if he will state what progress has been made by the Land Commission towards the acquisition of the Watson estate, formerly the Hanley estate, Mountveagh, Strokestown.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnMcQuillan" hpid="Mr. McQuillan Mr. McQuillan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McQuillan</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Lands if he will state what progress has been made by the Land Commission towards the acquisition of <Col N="178" /> Mr. John McNaughton's lands of approximately 400 acres, on the Thomastown demesne, County Roscommon.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasDerrig" hpid="Mr. Derrig Mr. Derrig">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Derrig</NameTxt>
      <P>I propose, with the permission of the Ceann Comhairle, to take Questions Nos. 16 and 18 together.</P>
      <P>The Land Commission obtained possession of both these estates in recent weeks.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnMcQuillan" hpid="Mr. McQuillan Mr. McQuillan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McQuillan</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Lands if he will state whether the Land Commission have yet prepared a scheme for the division of the Carroll and Henry farms, Aughlahard Lackin, Strokestown, County Roscommon; and, if so, when the scheme is likely to be put into operation.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasDerrig" hpid="Mr. Derrig Mr. Derrig">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Derrig</NameTxt>
      <P>It is hoped to allot these lands at an early date.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnMcQuillan" hpid="Mr. McQuillan Mr. McQuillan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McQuillan</NameTxt>
      <P>Is the Minister in a position to give an idea as to what the Land Commission's interpretation of &ldquo;an early date&rdquo; is, or would that be an embarrassing question for them?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasDerrig" hpid="Mr. Derrig Mr. Derrig">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Derrig</NameTxt>
      <P>It is not embarrassing in this particular instance.  A composite scheme has been approved and it is hoped to have the land allotted before the end of the present month.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions. Oral" RHead="Answers. - County Tipperary Bogs">
    <Title>Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions.   Oral Answers. - County Tipperary Bogs.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="JohnFanning" hpid="Mr. Fanning Mr. Fanning">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Fanning</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Lands if he will state whether the Land Commission propose to take over the Shanagher and Redwood bogs for division amongst the people of those areas in view of the fact that these people have no turbary of their own.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasDerrig" hpid="Mr. Derrig Mr. Derrig">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Derrig</NameTxt>
      <P>The Land Commission have a substantial area of turbary on hands in the townland of Redwood on the Trench estate, Record No. S.463. This bog will be made available as soon as practicable.  The Shanagher bog cannot be readily identified, but if the Deputy gives further particulars I shall have the matter re-examined.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions. Oral" RHead="Answers. - County Wexford Lands">
    <Title>Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions.   Oral Answers. - County Wexford Lands.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOLeary1943" hpid="Mr. O'Leary Mr. O'Leary">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Leary</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Lands if he will state when the Land Commission propose to divide the land at Galbally, Enniscorthy, County Wexford, <Col N="179" /> amongt small-holders and landless men.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasDerrig" hpid="Mr. Derrig Mr. Derrig">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Derrig</NameTxt>
      <P>It is not possible at present to state when the lands in possession of the Land Commission in the townland of Galbally can be allotted but there will be no avoidable delay.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOLeary1943" hpid="Mr. O'Leary Mr. O'Leary">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Leary</NameTxt>
      <P>Is it a good policy for the Land Commission to take over farms and let them by conacre instead of giving them to the people who are waiting for land in the area?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasDerrig" hpid="Mr. Derrig Mr. Derrig">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Derrig</NameTxt>
      <P>If that were the policy of the Land Commission I would say it would not be a good one, but it is not the policy.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesEverett" hpid="Mr. Everett Mr. Everett">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Everett</NameTxt>
      <P>It is the practice.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasDerrig" hpid="Mr. Derrig Mr. Derrig">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Derrig</NameTxt>
      <P>It is not.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOLeary1943" hpid="Mr. O'Leary Mr. O'Leary">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Leary</NameTxt>
      <P>It was published in the local paper.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasDerrig" hpid="Mr. Derrig Mr. Derrig">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Derrig</NameTxt>
      <P>Possession of one of the estates in question was only taken on the 16th October, 1953.  It comprises 259 acres 1 rood and 12 perches.  The Deputy will realise that it takes a certain amount of time to prepare a scheme, to submit it to the commissioners and, when it has been approved by the commissioners, to get houses built or have whatever improvements that are necessary made before it can be put into operation.  I am sure he will recognise if he is familiar with the procedure that it would have been impossible to put it into operation in the present spring season.  In fact, however, I do not think there will be any great loss locally because any lettings that have been made are to locals and I understand it is locals also who will benefit from the scheme when this division takes place.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions. Oral" RHead="Answers. - An Bord Uchtála Report">
    <Title>Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions.   Oral Answers. - An Bord Uchtála Report.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasNJByrne" hpid="Mr. T. Byrne Mr. T. Byrne">
      <NameTxt>Mr. T. Byrne</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Justice if he will state whether he has received an annual report for the last year from An Bord Uchtála; and, if so, when it is proposed to publish it; and, if not, whether he will now make <Col N="180" /> a statement on the work done or the progress made by the board to date.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeraldBoland" hpid="Minister for Justice (Mr. Boland) Gerald Boland">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Justice (Mr. Boland)</NameTxt>
      <P>I understand that An Bord Uchtála hopes to present its first annual report in the very near future.  As provided in the Adoption Act, 1952, the report will be published and laid before each House of the Oireachtas.  That will be done with the minimum of delay.</P>
      <P>Three hundred and eighty-one adoption orders were made during 1953, and 26 applications were rejected. One thousand, one hundred and three applications were under consideration at the end of the year.  Since 1st January, 1954, 257 adoption orders were made and 19 applications were rejected.  Applications are, therefore, now being dealt with at a much faster rate&mdash;last year the organisation had to be set up and a good deal of preliminary work done before any applications could be considered.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions. Oral Answers." RHead="- County Wexford Stationing of Troops">
    <Title>Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions.   Oral Answers. - County Wexford Stationing of Troops.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOLeary1943" hpid="Mr. O'Leary Mr. O'Leary">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Leary</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Defence if he will consider having troops stationed at the old fort, Duncannon, County Wexford, which is at present lying vacant and causing concern to the ratepayers of County Wexford.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OscarTraynor" hpid="Minister for Defence (Mr. Traynor) Oscar Traynor">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Defence (Mr. Traynor)</NameTxt>
      <P>It is not proposed to have troops stationed at Fort Duncannon.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOLeary1943" hpid="Mr. O'Leary Mr. O'Leary">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Leary</NameTxt>
      <P>This fort was taken over during the emergency and troops were stationed in it.  A lot of money was spent on it installing bathrooms, toilets, and so on, and it is lying there as a white elephant.  I think it would be a good policy to have troops stationed there because it would give more encouragement to young men to join the Army whose objection is that they are sent to the Curragh where there is nothing but plains and sheep to be seen.  This fort is a waste of money and a burden on the rates as well.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions. Oral" RHead="Answers. - Military Service Pensions">
    <Title>Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions.   Oral Answers. - Military Service Pensions.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOLeary1943" hpid="Mr. O'Leary Mr. O'Leary">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Leary</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Defence if he will state the number <Col N="181" /> of persons drawing pensions in County Wexford in respect of 1916 service, 1922 service and also under the Military Service Pensions (Amendment) Act, 1949.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OscarTraynor" hpid="Mr. Traynor Mr. Traynor">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Traynor</NameTxt>
      <P>The total number of persons resident in County Wexford who have pensions under the Military Service Pensions Acts is 341.  Of this number, 142 had service in the 1916 period and 63 were awarded pensions as a result of the Military Service Pensions (Amendment) Act, 1949.  The balance were awarded pensions in respect of pre- and post-truce service under the Military Service Pensions Acts, 1924 and 1934.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMacBride" hpid="Mr. MacBride Mr. MacBride">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacBride</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Defence if he will state in regard to Old I.R.A. military service pension applications dealt with by the Referee since the 1st January, 1954, the number of such applications which have been (1)  granted by the Referee; (2) rejected by the Referee; (3) adjourned by the Referee for further consideration, and if he will further state the number of cases in which, although the applications have been considered and rejected by the Referee, no notification of rejection has yet been communicated to the applicants.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OscarTraynor" hpid="Mr. Traynor Mr. Traynor">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Traynor</NameTxt>
      <P>Since the 1st January, 1954, and up to 23rd March, 1954, the Referee and the Board of Assessors have made 4,317 reports to me.  Of these, seven were favourable and 4,310 unfavourable.  The majority of the persons in whose cases unfavourable reports were received have not yet been notified, for the reason that the departmental staffing arrangements permit of notifications being issued at a limited rate only.  The bulk of the unfavourable reports relate to petitions under the Military Service Pensions (Amendment) Act, 1949, where applications had previously been rejected under either the Military Service Pensions Acts of 1924 or 1934, thus confirming the decisions originally reached in these cases.</P>
      <P>The number of cases examined by the Referee and the Board of Assessors since the 1st January, 1954, and in which they have not yet reported to me, is 152.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions. Oral Answers." RHead="- Army Recruits from County Donegal">
    <Title>Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions.   Oral Answers. - Army Recruits from County Donegal.</Title>
    <Col N="182" />
    <Speaker pid="PatrickODonnell" hpid="Mr. O'Donnell Mr. O'Donnell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Donnell</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Defence if he will state the number of recruits received into the Irish Army from County Donegal from the 1st January, 1954, to date and the cost of the recruiting drive in this county during the same period.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OscarTraynor" hpid="Mr. Traynor Mr. Traynor">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Traynor</NameTxt>
      <P>The number of recruits received in the Army from County Donegal from the 1st January, 1954, to the 22nd instant was eight.</P>
      <P>The cost involved in recruiting in that county during the same period was approximately £59.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions." RHead="Oral Answers. - Army Strength">
    <Title>Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions.   Oral Answers. - Army Strength.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickODonnell" hpid="Mr. O'Donnell Mr. O'Donnell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Donnell</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Defence if he will indicate the strength of personnel of the National Army as at the present date.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OscarTraynor" hpid="Mr. Traynor Mr. Traynor">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Traynor</NameTxt>
      <P>The effective strength of the Defence Forces on the latest date for which audited figures are available, i.e., the 28th February, 1954, was 32,123, made up as follows:&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <table pgwide="1">
      <tgroup cols="2">
        <colspec colname="1" colnum="1" colwidth="40*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <colspec colname="2" colnum="2" colwidth="10*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <thead>
          <row>
            <entry rowsep="1">Permanent Force</entry>
            <entry rowsep="1">10,582</entry>
          </row>
        </thead>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry>The Reserve&mdash;1st Line</entry>
            <entry>3,662</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>An Fórsa Cosanta Áitiúil</entry>
            <entry>17,497</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>An Slua Muirí</entry>
            <entry>382</entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions. Oral" RHead="Answers. - Fermoy National School">
    <Title>Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions.   Oral Answers. - Fermoy National School.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="RichardBarry" hpid="Mr. Barry Mr. Barry">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Barry</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Education if he will state when it is intended to start work on the building of the proposed new national school at Clondulane, Fermoy.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMoylan" hpid="Minister for Education (Mr. Moylan) Seán Moylan">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Education (Mr. Moylan)</NameTxt>
      <P>I am advised that a tender for the erection of the proposed new national school at Clondulane, County Cork, has been accepted by the Commissioners of Public Works and that it is expected that the work will commence very soon.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardBarry" hpid="Mr. Barry Mr. Barry">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Barry</NameTxt>
      <P>Would the Minister make sure this work will be started? I understand the tenders have been in for six or seven months.  As there is grave need for the work, on account of the unemployment in Clondulane as the result of the closing of the mill, I am asking the Minister to make sure <Col N="183" /> the work will be put in hands straight away.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMoylan" hpid="Mr. Moylan Mr. Moylan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Moylan</NameTxt>
      <P>I will let the Deputy know.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions. Oral" RHead="Answers. - School Hours and Holidays">
    <Title>Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions.   Oral Answers. - School Hours and Holidays.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasNJByrne" hpid="Mr. T. Byrne Mr. T. Byrne">
      <NameTxt>Mr. T. Byrne</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Education if he will state whether the question of standardising school hours and holidays has been under recent consideration by his Department and if he will consider the advisability of issuing a directive to the managers of all schools in the matter.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMoylan" hpid="Mr. Moylan Mr. Moylan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Moylan</NameTxt>
      <P>The conditions governing hours of attendance and school holidays for national schools are published in the Department's regulations. In regard to hours of attendance for these schools, it is laid down that the schools shall be opened for the reception of the pupils not later than 9.30 a.m., and provision be made in the time-table for secular instruction to be given for not less than four hours daily.  The arrangement of the time-tables is a matter for the school managers, who are free to decide whether the school day shall consist of one or two meetings, depending on the circumstances of the particular school.</P>
      <P>In the matter of the arrangement of school holidays for national schools, the regulations provide that in the County Boroughs of Dublin, Cork, Limerick and Waterford, and in the Borough of Dún Laoghaire, the period of summer vacation shall commence on the first Monday in July and extend for not more than eight weeks from that day.  In all other areas of the country, the summer vacation shall commence not later than the third Monday in July.</P>
      <P>In secondary schools, all of which are privately-owned institutions, the arrangements for school vacations and the drawing-up of the time-tables are matters for the conductors of these schools.  Normally, the period of summer vacation in these schools commences on or before the first day of July and extends to the end of August or the first week in September.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>In the case of vocational schools, the <Col N="184" /> period of summer vacation extends from 1st July to the end of August.</P>
    <P>The foregoing arrangements provide reasonable facilities for the planning of family holidays and outings, and I do not consider that it is desirable or necessary to issue any further directives to the managers or conductors of schools in the matter.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions. Oral" RHead="Answers. - Mount Merrion Petrol Station">
    <Title>Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions.   Oral Answers. - Mount Merrion Petrol Station.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="LiamCosgrave" hpid="Mr. Cosgrave Mr. Cosgrave">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cosgrave</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Local Government if he has received an appeal against a prohibition order made by the Dublin County Council on the erection of a petrol filling station at Mount Merion; if he is aware of the opposition to the proposed station and if he will state if he has reached a decision in the matter.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ErskineHamiltonChild" hpid="Minister for Posts and Telegraphs (Mr. Childers) (for the Minister for Local Government) Minister for Posts and Telegraphs (Mr. Childers) (for the Minister for Local Government)">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Posts and Telegraphs (Mr. Childers) (for the Minister for Local Government)</NameTxt>
      <P>The planning authority on the 23rd February, 1954, made orders under the Town and Regional Planning Acts probihiting the further proceeding with this work and declaring any contravention of the prohibition to be unlawful.  On the 20th instant an appeal against the declaration was received and on the 22nd instant the planning authority was asked to submit copies of the documents in connection with which the appeal was made.  I am aware of the opposition to the work in the area.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LiamCosgrave" hpid="Mr. Cosgrave Mr. Cosgrave">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cosgrave</NameTxt>
      <P>Could the Minister say when a decision will be reached on the appeal?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ErskineHamiltonChild" hpid="Mr. Childers Mr. Childers">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Childers</NameTxt>
      <P>As early as possible.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions. Oral" RHead="Answers. - Foxrock Sewerage Scheme">
    <Title>Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions.   Oral Answers. - Foxrock Sewerage Scheme.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="LiamCosgrave" hpid="Mr. Cosgrave Mr. Cosgrave">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cosgrave</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Local Government if he is in a position to state when work will commence on the Foxrock-Killiney sewerage scheme.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ErskineHamiltonChild" hpid="Mr. Childers Mr. Childers">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Childers</NameTxt>
      <P>I am not in a position to indicate when work may commence on this scheme.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Preliminary plans for the scheme as a whole, which is to be carried out by Dublin County Council and Dún Laoghaire Borough Corporation, have <Col N="185" /> been generally approved, as have contract documents for two urgent sections which the local authorities desire to execute in advance of the main scheme.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions. Oral" RHead="Answers. - Cork County Water Supply">
    <Title>Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions.   Oral Answers. - Cork County Water Supply.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="RichardBarry" hpid="Mr. Barry Mr. Barry">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Barry</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Local Government if he is aware that at present there is a serious complaint in the Kildorrery and Rockmills district, County Cork, from residents who have to use river water for domestic purposes because they believe that the sewage from Kildorrery village is being discharged into this river without being properly treated; and, if so, if he will state what action he proposes to take in the matter.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardBarry" hpid="Mr. Barry Mr. Barry">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Barry</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Local Government if there are plans in his Department for the provision of a water supply for Kildorrery and Rockmills, County Cork; and, if so, if he will state when work on these schemes is likely to commence.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ErskineHamiltonChild" hpid="Mr. Childers Mr. Childers">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Childers</NameTxt>
      <P>I propose, with your permission, a Cheann Comhairle, to take Questions Nos. 31 and 32 together. I have no information on the complaint mentioned by the Deputy.  Plans and specification for a combined water supply scheme to serve these villages have been approved, and final documents are now awaited.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardBarry" hpid="Mr. Barry Mr. Barry">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Barry</NameTxt>
      <P>I wonder if the Minister for Local Government would inquire from Dr. Connolly, the medical officer for County Cork, if there is a complaint regarding the disposal of sewage into the river at Kildorrery?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ErskineHamiltonChild" hpid="Mr. Childers Mr. Childers">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Childers</NameTxt>
      <P>As far as I am aware, the complaint has been disposed of to the satisfaction of everyone concerned.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions. Oral" RHead="Answers. - Dublin County Constituency">
    <Title>Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions.   Oral Answers. - Dublin County Constituency.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="EamonnRooney" hpid="Mr. Rooney Mr. Rooney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Rooney</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Local Government if he will state (a) the estimated number of electors who will be entitled to vote for candidates for Dáil Éireann in the Dublin County constituency after 15th April, 1954; (b) the estimated quota on the basis of the present three seats if 80 per cent. <Col N="186" /> of the electors cast a vote, and (c) if, in view of the large increase in the population of the constituency due to housing development, he will introduce proposals for legislation to increase the number of representatives to accord with the terms of the Constitution regarding parliamentary representation.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ErskineHamiltonChild" hpid="Mr. Childers Mr. Childers">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Childers</NameTxt>
      <P>I am not in a position to give an estimate of the number of electors who will be entitled to vote for candidates for Dáil Éireann in the Dublin County constituency after the 15th April, 1954.  The second part of the question does not, therefore, arise. It is not proposed during the present session of the Dáil to introduce legislation to revise Dáil constituencies.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>How can it be that the Minister for Local Government cannot provide an estimate of the number of electors entitled to vote in the Dublin County constituency after April 16th, seeing that the voters list, which is the uncorrected proof of the register, has been in the hands of the public for the past six months?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>It has not.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>Well, for a protracted period.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DonnchadhOBriain" hpid="Donnchadh Ó Briain Donnchadh Ó Briain">
      <NameTxt>Donnchadh Ó Briain</NameTxt>
      <P>It is not printed yet.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>No one need get hot about it.  How can the Minister for Local Government find himself unable to give an estimate of the number of voters entitled to vote in the Dublin County constituency in a fortnight's time?  Surely that is daft.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>The answer is surely why should he.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>That is another question. I understood the Minister for Posts and Telegraphs, speaking on behalf of the Minister for Local Government, to say that he was unable to give an estimate.  The Minister for Finance says: &ldquo;Why the hell should he?&rdquo;  The answer is because he is getting £2,500 a year just to do that&mdash; and divil the much else he is fit to do.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions. Oral" RHead="Answers. - Prices for Bacon Pigs">
    <Title>Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions.   Oral Answers. - Prices for Bacon Pigs.</Title>
    <Col N="187" />
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Agriculture whether he is aware that current prices for bacon pigs will show no profit to the producer unless the price of feeding stuffs is reduced; and, if so, whether he has any statement to make on this matter.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasWalsh" hpid="Minister for Agriculture (Mr. Walsh) Thomas Walsh">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Agriculture (Mr. Walsh)</NameTxt>
      <P>The answer to the first part of the question is in the negative.</P>
      <P>On and from the 26th April next, the price of maize sold by Grain Importers (Éire) Limited, will be reduced by £2 a ton to £27 a ton, carriage paid to purchaser's nearest railway station. The present proportions of 50 per cent. maize and 50 per cent. barley will be maintained.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions. Oral" RHead="Answers. - Price of Creamery Milk">
    <Title>Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions.   Oral Answers. - Price of Creamery Milk.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Agriculture whether he has any statement to make on the price of creamery milk in the coming season, consequent upon his discussions with the Irish Creamery Milk Suppliers' Association's deputation on 16th March.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. Walsh Mr. Walsh">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Walsh</NameTxt>
      <P>I have nothing to add to what I have said on this matter in the House on a number of occasions during the past few months.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>Has the Minister's attention been drawn to the fact that a report was published of an interview with a deputation from the Irish Creamery Milk Suppliers' Association after they had called on the Minister and they had indicated that they had asked him for an increase in price <i>ad interim</i> until the costings committee had given their report?  I think they discussed with him when the report would be available.  Could the Minister gave us any information?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. Walsh Mr. Walsh">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Walsh</NameTxt>
      <P>I am answering a question regarding the report.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>Can the Minister tell us when the costings committee&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. Walsh Mr. Walsh">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Walsh</NameTxt>
      <P>I am answering a question.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonnRooney" hpid="Mr. Rooney Mr. Rooney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Rooney</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for <Col N="188" /> Agriculture whether he has agreed to increase the price payable to creamery milk suppliers for milk; and, if so, whether he will indicate the amount of the increase.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. Walsh Mr. Walsh">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Walsh</NameTxt>
      <P>I have nothing to add to the reply which I gave to a question on this subject asked by Deputy P. O'Reilly on the 2nd December last.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions. Oral" RHead="Answers. - Milk Costings Commission">
    <Title>Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions.   Oral Answers. - Milk Costings Commission.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="SeanCollins" hpid="Mr. S. Collins Mr. S. Collins">
      <NameTxt>Mr. S. Collins</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Agriculture if he will indicate the progress made by the Milk Costings Commission.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. Walsh Mr. Walsh">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Walsh</NameTxt>
      <P>I understand that the very considerable volume of necessary data collected by the technical director of the investigation is now being collated by him for the purpose of preparing his report.  Present indications are that the report will not be ready for several weeks yet.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>We will not see the report until after the general election.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>A shilling a gallon.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>It is just like the Health Act payments&mdash;we will not see them until after the general election.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonnRooney" hpid="Mr. Rooney Mr. Rooney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Rooney</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Agriculture if he has received the report on the findings of the Milk Costings Commission, whether the report in question has been considered; and, if so, what action he proposes to take thereon.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. Walsh Mr. Walsh">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Walsh</NameTxt>
      <P>The answer to the first part of the question is &ldquo;No,&rdquo; and the other parts do not, therefore, arise.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions. Oral" RHead="Answers. - Imported Butter">
    <Title>Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions.   Oral Answers. - Imported Butter.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="EamonnRooney" hpid="Mr. Rooney Mr. Rooney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Rooney</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Agriculture if he will state the quantity and cost of butter imported prior to 31st July, 1953, which has not yet been disposed of.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. Walsh Mr. Walsh">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Walsh</NameTxt>
      <P>The quantity of butter imported prior to 31st July, 1953, and held in stock by the Butter Marketing Committee on 20th March, 1954, was 15,022 cwt.  The cost of this butter was 382/6 per cwt. c.i.f. Dublin.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions. Oral" RHead="Answers. - Repeated Use of Butter Boxes">
    <Title>Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions.   Oral Answers. - Repeated Use of Butter Boxes.</Title>
    <Col N="189" />
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Agriculture whether the supply position will now permit of the abolition of the system of repeated use of butter boxes in the wholesale distribution of butter.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. Walsh Mr. Walsh">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Walsh</NameTxt>
      <P>While the timber supply position would permit of the reversion to the pre-war position in which creameries were not permitted to use butter boxes more than once for the packing of creamery butter sold in bulk, such reversion would result in an appreciable increase in creameries' packing costs at a time when every effort must be made to reduce creameries' manufacturing costs generally.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>Does the Minister think it desirable to reduce production costs by practices which cannot reflect credit on the industry?  Is it not true that, except in times of acute emergency, in no country in the world is the practice of repeated use of boxes for butter adopted?  Would the Minister not consider recommending to the creameries that, if they cannot use wooden butter boxes only once for transport of butter, they should consider some less expensive container provided they could get rid of the practice of repeated use of boxes, which, as the Minister I think knows now, often do not appear to be clean?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. Walsh Mr. Walsh">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Walsh</NameTxt>
      <P>If the Deputy were observant he would know that there is no more suitable material than timber for the storage of butter.  I do not know what he would suggest for cold storage, for instance.  I wonder if he does know that using butter boxes only once would mean a reduction of one-third of a penny per gallon for milk or an increase of ¾d. a lb. in butter?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>That is what he wants.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>There is no need to get cross about it.  May I ask the Minister would he consider asking a competent authority to inquire into the question as to whether some fiberite or other material could be employed <Col N="190" /> for boxes of this kind on a non-returnable basis?  As the Minister is aware, a great deal of liquid milk and ice cream is now distributed in the United States in fiberite non-returnable boxes.  If it is suitable for the preservation of milk it ought to be suitable for the preservation of butter, particularly when the butter is consigned to a retail distributor.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickHogan" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Patrick (Clare) Hogan">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>This is a speech, Deputy.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>All I am asking the Minister is to consider an alternative so that these boxes would not be going to and fro from distributing houses.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions. Oral" RHead="Answers. - Greyhound Industry">
    <Title>Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions.   Oral Answers. - Greyhound Industry.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="DenisOSullivan" hpid="Mr. D.J. O'Sullivan Mr. D.J. O'Sullivan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. D.J. O'Sullivan</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Agriculture if he is now in a position to state when the findings of the advisory committee on the greyhound industry will be implemented and to what extent.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. Walsh Mr. Walsh">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Walsh</NameTxt>
      <P>The Government have authorised the preparation of legislation to implement various recommendations of the advisory committee on the greyhound industry, in particular the establishment of a control board for the industry.  A Bill is being prepared accordingly and will be introduced as soon as the draft is settled.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>Did not it take you a long time?  God bless the general election.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions. Oral" RHead="Answers. - Supply of Seed Wheat">
    <Title>Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions.   Oral Answers. - Supply of Seed Wheat.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickDesmondLehane" hpid="Mr. Lehane Mr. Lehane">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lehane</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Agriculture if he is aware that farmers who wish to grow wheat this year find that they cannot get imported or home-grown seed suitable for their land from any of their usual suppliers; and, if so, if he will make arrangements to have supplies made available.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. Walsh Mr. Walsh">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Walsh</NameTxt>
      <P>Ample supplies of seed wheat of the principal variety grown are available.  I am, however, aware that some farmers have had difficulty in getting particular varieties.  To meet this situation, licences are being <Col N="191" /> granted to farmers and merchants for the importation of seed.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions. Oral" RHead="Answers. - Artificial Insemination">
    <Title>Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions.   Oral Answers. - Artificial Insemination.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickDesmondLehane" hpid="Mr. Lehane Mr. Lehane">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lehane</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Agriculture if he will arrange to have Polled Angus bulls placed at the Clonakilty artificial insemination station.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. Walsh Mr. Walsh">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Walsh</NameTxt>
      <P>A number of Aberdeen Angus bulls recently purchased by my Department for location at artificial insemination stations will be located at the stations, including Clonakilty station, at an early date.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions. Oral" RHead="Answers. - Liscannor Harbour">
    <Title>Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions.   Oral Answers. - Liscannor Harbour.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickJohnHillery" hpid="Dr. Hillery Dr. Hillery">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Hillery</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Agriculture if he will state what steps are being taken to expedite the reconstruction of the harbour at Liscannor, County Clare.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeraldBartley" hpid="Parliamentary Secretary to the Minister for Agriculture (Mr. Bartley) Gerald Bartley">
      <NameTxt>Parliamentary Secretary to the Minister for Agriculture (Mr. Bartley)</NameTxt>
      <P>The Clare County Council were asked on 16th January, 1954, to furnish an outline plan of certain works proposed by them in December, 1953, for the improvement of Liscannor harbour, together with an indication of the amount they would be prepared to contribute towards the cost of the project. These particulars have not yet been received and no further steps can be taken in the matter by my Department without them.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions. Oral Answers." RHead="- Portaleen (County Donegal) Harbour">
    <Title>Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions.   Oral Answers. - Portaleen (County Donegal) Harbour.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="DanielMcMenamin" hpid="Mr. McMenamin Mr. McMenamin">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McMenamin</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Agriculture if he will state whether a firm decision has been arrived at regarding the construction of a breakwater on the harbour at Portaleen, County Donegal; and, if so, if he will indicate its nature.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeraldBartley" hpid="Mr. Bartley Mr. Bartley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Bartley</NameTxt>
      <P>A final decision as to the nature of the improvements to the harbour facilities at Portaleen which can be effected has not yet been made. The matter is still the subject of examination between the engineers of the Office of Public Works and the Donegal county engineer.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="192" />
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>Is the Parliamentary Secretary aware that four years ago his colleagues were denouncing me vigorously in this House for not having arrived at a decision in regard to that matter?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. Walsh Mr. Walsh">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Walsh</NameTxt>
      <P>You were sleeping on it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>If I was, you are dying on it.  You are dead but you will not lie down.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions. Oral" RHead="Answers. - Fish-Meal Plants">
    <Title>Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions.   Oral Answers. - Fish-Meal Plants.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. Coburn Mr. Coburn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Coburn</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Agriculture if he will request An Bord Iascaigh Mhara to consider the question of the erection of a fish-meal plant at the fishing port of Clogherhead, County Louth.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanCollins" hpid="Mr. S. Collins Mr. S. Collins">
      <NameTxt>Mr. S. Collins</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Agriculture if he will state what progress has been made towards the establishment of a fish-meal plant in West Cork.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeraldBartley" hpid="Mr. Bartley Mr. Bartley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Bartley</NameTxt>
      <P>With your permission, a Cheann Comhairle, I propose to take Questions Nos. 46 and 47 together.</P>
      <P>An Bord Iascaigh Mhara has at present in operation a fish-meal plant at Killybegs.  The location of any additional plants which it may be decided to erect with the aid of State funds will be a matter for decision having regard to the board's experience with the plant at Killybegs and the availability of adequate and regular supplies of suitable fish at the various fishing centres around the coast.  The Deputies may be assured that the suitability of Clogherhead and fishery centres in West Cork will receive every consideration by the board.  I may add that there is no restriction as far as the fishery authority is concerned on the establishment of such plants by private enterprise.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions. Oral" RHead="Answers. - Boats for Inshore Fishermen">
    <Title>Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions.   Oral Answers. - Boats for Inshore Fishermen.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="SeanCollins" hpid="Mr. S. Collins Mr. S. Collins">
      <NameTxt>Mr. S. Collins</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Agriculture if he will indicate the programme for the coming year for the distribution of boats to inshore fishermen.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="193" />
    <Speaker pid="GeraldBartley" hpid="Mr. Bartley Mr. Bartley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Bartley</NameTxt>
      <P>I am informed by An Bord Iascaigh Mhara that they expect to be in a position to issue 14 motor fishing boats in the period stated.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>Are they 50 foot boats?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeraldBartley" hpid="Mr. Bartley Mr. Bartley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Bartley</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions. Oral" RHead="Answers. - Inshore Fishermen's Anxiety">
    <Title>Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions.   Oral Answers. - Inshore Fishermen's Anxiety.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="AnthonyCEsmonde" hpid="Dr. Esmonde Dr. Esmonde">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Esmonde</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Agriculture if he is aware of the growing anxiety among inshore fishermen because State-subsidised trawlers are encroaching on the free enterprise of these fishermen to the detriment of their livelihood; and, if so, if he will make a statement on the matter.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeraldBartley" hpid="Mr. Bartley Mr. Bartley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Bartley</NameTxt>
      <P>I presume that the question refers to the three vessels operated by An Bord Iascaigh Mhara. I am not aware that there exists among the general body of fishermen any such anxiety as he suggests.  The fact is that the supply of fish from our present fleet of inshore boats is not, except at seasonal peaks, equal to the demand and prices have been good for a long time past for all varieties of good quality on offer from inshore fishermen.  The three vessels in question are intended to supplement the catches of inshore fishermen, thus helping towards reducing the present need for fish imports, and their operations are governed by the policy that the interests of the inshore fishermen will be safeguarded.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="AnthonyCEsmonde" hpid="Dr. Esmonde Dr. Esmonde">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Esmonde</NameTxt>
      <P>Does the Parliamentary Secretary not agree that, when there is a glut of fish, the catches landed from State trawlers, that have all the resources of the State behind them, have priority in the market over and above the catches of the inshore fishermen who are engaged in private enterprise?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeraldBartley" hpid="Mr. Bartley Mr. Bartley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Bartley</NameTxt>
      <P>The board recognises that it has a responsibility in respect of the marketing of the inshore fishermen's catches and, where necessary, they hold back the catches of the boats operated by themselves, on the occasion of peak supplies, so that these catches will not interfere with the profitable marketing of the inshoremen's catches.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="194" />
    <Speaker pid="AnthonyCEsmonde" hpid="Dr. Esmonde Dr. Esmonde">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Esmonde</NameTxt>
      <P>Am I to take it from the reply that the Parliamentary Secretary is guaranteeing that the inshore fishermen will be allowed to dispose of their fish in all cases before the catches of the State-sponsored trawlers are put on the market?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeraldBartley" hpid="Mr. Bartley Mr. Bartley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Bartley</NameTxt>
      <P>No. I am not giving any such guarantee.  I am telling the Deputy that the board keeps in sufficiently close touch with the market to take whatever precautions are necessary to ensure that the catches of vessels operated by the board will not interfere with the profitable marketing of the inshoremen's catches.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions. Oral" RHead="Answers. - Harbour Freezing Plants">
    <Title>Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions.   Oral Answers. - Harbour Freezing Plants.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="AnthonyCEsmonde" hpid="Dr. Esmonde Dr. Esmonde">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Esmonde</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Agriculture if he will state how many harbours in this country have freezing plants available for the processing of catches landed by our fishermen, and if the existing plants are capable of dealing with such supplies as are landed in all seasons.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeraldBartley" hpid="Mr. Bartley Mr. Bartley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Bartley</NameTxt>
      <P>There is only one fishing harbour adequately equipped with the facilities referred to.  The need for such facilities at harbours as part of the general scheme for the development of the fishing industry is recognised.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="AnthonyCEsmonde" hpid="Dr. Esmonde Dr. Esmonde">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Esmonde</NameTxt>
      <P>Would the Parliamentary Secretary care to indicate which harbour it is that has the facilities?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeraldBartley" hpid="Mr. Bartley Mr. Bartley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Bartley</NameTxt>
      <P>Killybegs.  I may inform the Deputy that there are facilities privately owned in Dublin, Cork and Sligo.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="AnthonyCEsmonde" hpid="Dr. Esmonde Dr. Esmonde">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Esmonde</NameTxt>
      <P>Would the Parliamentary Secretary care to indicate if it is proposed to install such facilities in Kilmore, County Wexford, in the near future?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeraldBartley" hpid="Mr. Bartley Mr. Bartley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Bartley</NameTxt>
      <P>It is the intention of the board to proceed with the installation of these facilities at all the wellknown strategic fishing points around the coast but, as the Deputy will recognise, the process is obviously a slow one.  The procurement of the machinery is a special difficulty, I understand.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="195" />
    <Speaker pid="AnthonyCEsmonde" hpid="Dr. Esmonde Dr. Esmonde">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Esmonde</NameTxt>
      <P>Could the Parliamentary Secretary give any indication as to when these facilities will be extended. The answer appears to be that only one harbour&mdash;Killybegs&mdash;has such facilities.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeraldBartley" hpid="Mr. Bartley Mr. Bartley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Bartley</NameTxt>
      <P>I understand that the board will begin the installation of a second station in the next couple of months.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Order of" RHead="Business">
    <Title>Order of Business.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="An Tánaiste Seán F. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>An Tánaiste</NameTxt>
      <P>Business will be taken in the following order as set out on the Order Paper: No. 7 and then No. 5.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BrendanCorish" hpid="Mr. Corish Mr. Corish">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Corish</NameTxt>
      <P>Can the Tánaiste say whether or not it is intended to sit to-morrow and whether or not it is intended to sit next week?  If it is intended to sit next week, can the Tánaiste give the House an idea of the business to be dealt with?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="An Tánaiste Seán F. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>An Tánaiste</NameTxt>
      <P>It is not proposed to sit to-morrow.  We shall sit next week.  I hope the Defence Bill will be completed by then.  We will have the Housing Bill, the Committee Stage of the Electricity (Supply) Amendment Bill, perhaps any remaining stages of the Superannuation Bill and the Confirmation of Orders Bill.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamNorton" hpid="Mr. Norton Mr. Norton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norton</NameTxt>
      <P>Is it intended to sit on Friday of next week?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="An Tánaiste Seán F. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>An Tánaiste</NameTxt>
      <P>I think we will be able to complete that business on the two days next week.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Superannuation Bill," RHead="1954&mdash;Second Stage">
    <Title>Superannuation Bill, 1954&mdash;Second Stage.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Minister for Finance (Mr. MacEntee) Seán MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Finance (Mr. MacEntee)</NameTxt>
      <P>I move that the Bill be now read a Second Time.  I think the purpose of this Bill is clear on the face of it and I assume that the House will not expect me to dilate on it unnecessarily.  The main purpose of the Bill is to provide women civil servants with superannuation benefits similar to those available to male civil servants.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamNorton" hpid="Mr. Norton Mr. Norton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norton</NameTxt>
      <P>I thought the Minister would explain the reasons which induced him to be so expansive in heart, even if he was brief in tongue when introducing this Bill.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="196" /> I welcome this Bill because it removes a discrimination which has long been felt by women civil servants.  The pensions of all civil servants are, in the main, related to the Superannuation Act of 1859.  When that Act was introduced, provision was made for the payment of pensions on the basis of 1/60th for each year of service, subject to a maximum of 46 years.  No lump sum was then provided for the civil servants concerned, whether they were males or females.  Subsequently, in 1909, a new Superannuation Act was passed.  The new Superannuation Act provided that civil servants would have their pensions calculated on the basis of 1/80th of their salary and emoluments for each year of service subject to a maximum of 40/80ths.  It also provided for payment of 1/30th of salary and emoluments for each year of service subject to a maximum of 45/30ths.  In addition, that Act provided coverage for the next-of-kin in the event of the death, whilst in the Civil Service, of the civil servants concerned.</P>
    <P>That Act was generally regarded as a useful piece of reformation so far as the pensions of civil servants were concerned.  However, the authorities at the time declined to extend the provisions of that Act to female civil servants.  The result is that you have had this rather peculiar anomaly that the pensions of women civil servants were calculated under the Superannuation Act of 1859&mdash;which gave them no lump sum on retirement and which gave their next-of-kin no coverage in the event of death&mdash;while the superannuation of male civil servants was calculated under the 1909 Act which gave a lesser pension, a lump sum on retirement and coverage for the next-of-kin in the event of the death of the civil servant while in the Civil Service.</P>
    <P>Since 1909, there has been keen agitation by female civil servants that they should not be discriminated against by being excluded from the provisions of the 1909 Act.  For more than 40 years, keen agitation has been maintained by women civil servants that their pensions should be calculated on the same basis as male civil servants.  That agitation is now drawing <Col N="197" /> to a satisfactory conclusion.  This Bill removes the discrimination which has operated against women civil servants for so long because it extends the provisions of the 1909 Act, which are applicable now only to male officers, to female civil servants.</P>
    <P>This Bill will be welcomed generally by civil servants and, as it represents agreement between the staff organisations and the Minister for Finance, I presume it has the goodwill and the support of the House.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>I should like to ask the Minister for Finance why he thought it unnecessary to give us the information which Deputy Norton has now given us.  Does it not rather demean the proceedings of the House to present a Bill of this kind and simply say: &ldquo;The Bill speaks for itself.  I have nothing to add&rdquo;?  Manifestly, the Bill does not speak for itself.  There is a long history behind this whole story.  Does the Minister for Finance not think he should have told the House that story?  Now, I agree that when a gladiator is about to die in the arena, the dignified thing is to appear to die willingly.  I hope the Minister for Finance will be spared to shed the radiance of his personality upon us for many a long year to come and when I speak of death in this context I think only of political demise. May I urge upon him that the shadow of his pending political dissolution should not so far depress him as to paralyse his tongue in this House?  He is still very welcome to speak here and we always muster an audience, albeit a small one, to hear what he has to say.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickHogan" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Patrick (Clare) Hogan">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>Will Deputy Dillon now come to the Bill which is before this House?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>I cannot do that because the Minister did not do so.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickHogan" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Patrick (Clare) Hogan">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>The Bill is before the House.  What has to be discussed is the Bill.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>I am asking the Minister why he did not talk of it.  I am asking him if he is suffering from paralysis of the tongue or paralysis of the <Col N="198" /> spirit.  I cannot imagine that what he did was out of a bland desire to affront the House.  I have heard nothing from the Minister for Finance about this Bill.  The only thing I have heard about it is what Deputy Norton has told us.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickHogan" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Patrick (Clare) Hogan">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>The Bill is before the House.  Whether or not the Minister spoke to it is no concern of mine.  What is to be discussed is the Bill.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>But it is my business, and I am asking the Minister why he did not talk.  I am saying to the Minister that I was entitled to hear him talk on this Bill.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickHogan" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Patrick (Clare) Hogan">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>I have allowed the Deputy to go as far as I will permit him to go on that matter.  Deputy Dillon will now discuss the Bill.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>Why did the Minister not tell us that this Bill is an extension of the Superannuation Act of 1909?  Why did the Minister not tell us that this Bill is to bestow on female civil servants benefits which male civil servants have enjoyed since the Superannuation Act of 1909?  Why did he not tell us that this Bill represents an agreed solution of an old difficulty between himself and the staff associations? Why did the Minister not tell us whether or not this Bill will impose any additional burden on the Treasury; and, if so, how much?  Why did the Minister tell us nothing at all? I think we are entitled to know.  Will the Minister now tell us?  May we assume that Deputy Norton's summary of the history leading up to this Bill is correct, according to the Minister's information?  Can he tell us does this involve any additional charge; and, if so, is it a matter of substance?  And can he, within the rules of relevance, tell us, as he is concluding, why he has been silent up to now?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>It is quite unusual for me to receive a tribute such as Deputy Dillon has just paid me.  He has actually urged me to make a speech.  I think there were times when Deputy Dillon would prefer that I should remain silent.  He has asked <Col N="199" /> me a number of questions, all of which can be answered in one sentence.  It is quite impossible, of course, for Deputy Dillon to deal with any matter, whether major or minor, in one sentence. What we are discussing here on the Second Reading of the Bill is the principle of the Bill.  And the principle of this Bill, as stated by me, is to give to women civil servants the same pension rights as are enjoyed by men.  Whether that involves a change in the circumstances which have existed here since 1859 is, I think, quite irrelevant&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>Do you?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>&mdash;&mdash;unless I was going to worsen the position of the female civil servants.  Therefore, I take it I have fully and succinctly dealt with the heart of the matter, when I have said as I already indicated, that this Bill will give to women civil servants precisely the same superannuation rights as are at present enjoyed by men.  If Deputy Dillon takes exception to that, he is at liberty to vote against the principle.  He would be voting against that principle, and for a man like Deputy Dillon for whom principle always comes before expediency, I think the number of minor details like the number benefiting by it or the cost of the Bill would be almost irrelevant.  He might, in his more prudent moments, in the moments when he is not spending millions of dollars in an afternoon, think of mundane matters like pounds, shillings and pence, but if he did, knowing Deputy Dillon as we know him here on the floor of the House, we should all be much surprised.</P>
      <P>I have given the House all the information that is necessary at this stage.  On the Committee Stage of the Bill I will be prepared to deal with any query which Deputy Dillon may wish to bring up but I put it to him that at this stage what he has to do is to endorse the principle that women are entitled to the same superannuation rights and terms as men.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>I would like to ask a question: does the Minister for Finance <Col N="200" /> seriously state in this House that in bringing forward a Superannuation Bill it is supererogatory on his part to tell the House what it is likely to cost because if we reach that stage bedlam is indeed upon us?  If the Minister for Finance at this stage thinks that the House should accept and pass the Superannuation Act without any reference to what it costs, then&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickHogan" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Patrick (Clare) Hogan">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>The Deputy is only entitled to ask a question.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>I will ask the question&mdash; are you going to give the cost, or do you declare that is irrelevant?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>I have said that that would be irrelevant at this stage.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>Well, you are daft.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>If the Deputy will just hold his horses.  The Deputy is well aware that the Committee Stage of this Bill cannot be taken until the Dáil has discussed the Money Resolution. On the Money Resolution I will inform the House what the Bill is likely to cost and on the information then given to him Deputy Dillon can decide whether he is going to retreat from acceptance of the principle, as I assume he will accept it on the Second Reading of this Bill.  He is quite at liberty then when the Money Resolution is before the House&mdash;which I would suggest is the more appropriate occasion to discuss the financial aspects of the Bill&mdash;to take whatever course he thinks fit.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>You know the cost and you will not tell us?</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickHogan" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Patrick (Clare) Hogan">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>Next stage?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>If Deputy Dillon is prepared to allow me&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>No, Sir.  Let it be taken next week.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>Committee Stage will be taken next Wednesday.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>You would have got your Bill to-day if you had behaved <Col N="201" /> yourself.  You never get anything through this House if you kick up your heels.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>I would have got my Bill to-day if you had not blocked it.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Defence Bill, 1951&mdash;Report" RHead="Stage (Resumed)">
    <Title>Defence Bill, 1951&mdash;Report Stage (Resumed).</Title>
    <P>Discussion on the following amendment resumed:&mdash;</P>
    <P>In page 106, to delete Section 240, lines 1 to 39.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PeadarCowan" hpid="Captain Cowan Captain Cowan">
      <NameTxt>Captain Cowan</NameTxt>
      <P>When the Dáil adjourned last night I had been dealing with the proposal to delete Section 240 which in effect gives power to District Courts to investigate charges against members of the Reserve for purely Reserve offences, such as failing to appear at the place of parade without reasonable excuse or using threatening language or behaving in an insubordinate manner to a person who, if both were subject to military law, would be his superior officer. Apparently if in the course of a football match between two teams a person who is a private in the Reserve behaves in an insubordinate manner to another footballer on the opposing team who is a corporal or a sergeant or of higher rank in the Reserve, that man under this section could be subject to investigation by a District Court and the reservist could be fined up to £25.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Similarly, a reservist who answered a notice in regard to the Reserve in a manner that might be considered insubordinate or who did not comply with Defence Force regulations can be brought before a District Court and can be fined a sum not exceeding £25. The section additionally provides that he may be taken into military custody or he may be, on the directions of an officer, taken into the custody of a member of the Garda Síochána.  I made the case last night and I just repeat it now for the purpose of concluding what I have to say on this section, that if the Minister finds it necessary, or if the Army authorities find it necessary, to deal with the <Col N="202" /> Reserve in this way, I think it is a confession that all is not well.</P>
    <P>The Minister last night dealt with the difference in Britain between a volunteer army and a compulsory service army.  In this case, we are dealing with volunteers, with young men who are delighted to be part of the defence machine of the country, young men who volunteer their spare time to make themselves proficient as soldiers and who are proud to serve in the Reserve in whatever rank their abilities fit them for.  I think a very poor opinion is held of these men when it is considered necessary to treat them like petty offenders in the District Court.  In a volunteer force, such as our Reserve, we want that Reserve to be manned, as it is, by the very best types of our young citizens.  We want them to be there on the basis of giving voluntary, patriotic and national service.  We do not want to have them serving in the manner that, having signed a form of enlistment, they can be subjected to this type of petty pin-pricking.</P>
    <P>If you get a decent young boy down the country who is a corporal or a private in the Reserve, and you bring him up in the District Court, that, as far as he is concerned, is the end of his Reserve service, and that, as far as his friends and neighbours are concerned, is the end of the Reserve. When a man joins the Reserve, let us deal with him when he is subject to military law, under the provisions of military law, by the military methods that are laid down in this Act, but I think it is humiliating to the Reserve, as such, and is humiliating to the Defence Forces, that he should be subject to being brought before the District Court and liable to a fine of £25 for being absent without reasonable excuse from a parade or for acting in what is considered to be an insubordinate fashion under the section. This section supports the view that I have about many other sections in the Act, that it has not been viewed from the point of view of a modern 1952, 1953 or 1954 Bill.  It is the oldest type of old provision that was associated with the very old militia of our young days, and I do not want to see it incorporated in this new Bill.</P>
    <Col N="203" />
    <Speaker pid="OscarTraynor" hpid="Mr. Traynor Mr. Traynor">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Traynor</NameTxt>
      <P>I am sure that Deputy Cowan has spoken for almost half an hour on this already.  I must say that I am more than astonished at the case that he has been making in this respect. If he wants to injure the recruiting campaign there is no better method of doing it than the method that he has adopted in discussing this Bill, and especially this particular section.  He has made misstatement after misstatement in the course of the discussion on this.  I find it very difficult to sit here and listen, without interrupting continually, while he has been making these misstatements.  He talked about the soldier on the football field, of the private coming up against the sergeant and of the sergeant taking it out of the private because of something that happened. If the Deputy had studied the section he would see that paragraph (b) provides that:&mdash;</P>
      <P>&ldquo;Where a reservist uses threatening or insulting language or behaves in an insubordinate manner to any officer or non-commissioned officer who, in pursuance of Reserve Defence Force regulations, is acting in the execution of his office&rdquo;</P>
      <P>and not on a football field.  He would not be acting in the execution of his office if he was playing football, nor would he be acting in that capacity if he was having a drink in a &ldquo;pub,&rdquo; as the Deputy suggested two of them might be, a private and a corporal. There would be no question then of his acting in the execution of his office. This, undoubtedly, is intended where reservists are being called up, where a corporal is acting in some statutory capacity under which rights are conferred on him by reason of the fact that he is acting under this particular sub-section.  It astonishes me to hear the sort of case that is being made by the Deputy.  It is not that he does not understand the Act because I am sure he does.  It surprises me, and shocks me sometimes, when I hear that sort of case being stated, a case that has no relation whatever to the facts.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>This matter also was discussed at great length in the Special Committee, <Col N="204" /> as most of the other sections were. Arising out of the discussions that we had there on this particular section, I undertook to bring it to the attention of the Army authorities and I did so, and the Army authorities were insistent that it should remain.  The Army authorities that I am referring to are not the enemies of the rank and file and, as far as I know them, have never been.  But, listening to Deputy Cowan on this, one would think that there was one group continually at war with another, one section endeavouring to hurt another section, but that is not so.</P>
    <P>Furthermore, this section has been in the Act since 1923.  The only paragraph that is new is paragraph (c), and the paragraph relating to trial by a civil court instead of either by court-martial or a civil court.  When Deputy Cowan was speaking last evening he talked about reservists from Ballydehob or Ballinalee being called up to attend a parade at 20 hours, which is normally 8 o'clock.  Lest by any chance anyone might read into that that this affects the F.C.A., I want to emphasise the fact that it does not. The F.C.A. is a voluntary body which comes up for weekly, monthly or periodic training, as the case may be, and it is only if they were called out on permanent service that they would be affected by this.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PeadarCowan" hpid="Captain Cowan Captain Cowan">
      <NameTxt>Captain Cowan</NameTxt>
      <P>Is what the Minister is saying now in the Act?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OscarTraynor" hpid="Mr. Traynor Mr. Traynor">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Traynor</NameTxt>
      <P>I am not saying that. I am saying that it does not apply to them.  If the Deputy was attempting to imply that it did, I am trying to correct that.  That is all that I am saying.  It does not, in fact, apply to them.  They are only on service when they go into their halls to attend a parade or something like that.  I appeal to the Deputy to moderate his language in relation to this particular Bill.  It has taken me by surprise that this section should be selected by the Deputy for such a long attack.  Anyone who reads the section will see that it would be practically impossible for the Army to carry on if some such section was not there.  It is not because there is anything wrong with the Army&mdash;and the Deputy has <Col N="205" /> suggested that there must be something seriously wrong&mdash;that this provision has to be included; the Deputy knows himself there is nothing seriously wrong.  The Deputy knows, as I know, that the cases of this kind that have taken place over a long period of years are very few in number&mdash;so few that it would almost seem unnecessary to put the section in; but, nevertheless, the section must be there to provide the means for dealing with the few cases that might occur.  That is all that has taken place here.  I would recommend Deputies who have listened to this discussion to read Section 240 and read Deputy Cowan's speech in conjunction with and in juxtaposition to the section and they will see how necessary my remarks have been in relation to his speech.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PeadarCowan" hpid="Captain Cowan Captain Cowan">
      <NameTxt>Captain Cowan</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister has a happy knack of avoiding the main issue.  The main issue in this instance is whether it is right that persons who join the Defence Forces as volunteers in order to serve the Reserve section of the Army should be subjected to being brought before a District Court and fined a sum of £25 for failing to attend a parade.  The Minister has avoided that issue.  Why should such an individual be brought before the district court?  That is my objection.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OscarTraynor" hpid="Mr. Traynor Mr. Traynor">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Traynor</NameTxt>
      <P>Why should the Deputy have to bring it up now after almost 30 years?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOLeary1943" hpid="Mr. O'Leary Mr. O'Leary">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Leary</NameTxt>
      <P>Did it ever happen?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PeadarCowan" hpid="Captain Cowan Captain Cowan">
      <NameTxt>Captain Cowan</NameTxt>
      <P>That I do not know.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GenSeanMacEoin" hpid="General MacEoin General MacEoin">
      <NameTxt>General MacEoin</NameTxt>
      <P>That is not a good argument: because it has been there for a long time is not a sound argument for retaining it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OscarTraynor" hpid="Mr. Traynor Mr. Traynor">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Traynor</NameTxt>
      <P>Is the Deputy in favour of wiping this out?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GenSeanMacEoin" hpid="General MacEoin General MacEoin">
      <NameTxt>General MacEoin</NameTxt>
      <P>There is a good deal to be said against bringing a reservist before the District Court.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OscarTraynor" hpid="Mr. Traynor Mr. Traynor">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Traynor</NameTxt>
      <P>I am merely asking the Deputy a question.  Is the Deputy in favour of wiping this out?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="206" />
    <Speaker pid="GenSeanMacEoin" hpid="General MacEoin General MacEoin">
      <NameTxt>General MacEoin</NameTxt>
      <P>I am in favour of dealing with an offender against military law through the medium of a court-martial.  Because he fails to turn up at a parade, I do not think it is wise to haul him before a District Court.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OscarTraynor" hpid="Mr. Traynor Mr. Traynor">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Traynor</NameTxt>
      <P>He is a reservist.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GenSeanMacEoin" hpid="General MacEoin General MacEoin">
      <NameTxt>General MacEoin</NameTxt>
      <P>I know he is.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PeadarCowan" hpid="Captain Cowan Captain Cowan">
      <NameTxt>Captain Cowan</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister says this provision has been there for 30 years.  The Minister must realise that the Reserve established under the 1923 Act was a different type of Reserve from that which will be established under this measure.  Under the 1923 Act the Reserve consisted of the Reserve of Officers and the Reserve of men.  The Reserve of Officers was composed of those officers who had retired from the permanent forces on pension at the end of their service and it was part of their obligation as officers on pension that they would be subject to recall until they reached a certain age.  The Reserve of men under the 1923 Act was limited to soldiers of the Defence Forces; it consisted of non-commissioned officers and men who, having served in the forces, were transferred to the Reserve in pursuance of Part II, Chapter V of the 1923 Act.  They were men who joined originally for a certain period in the Army and in the Reserve and, at the expiration of their period of regular service, they were transferred to the Reserve in accordance with their original contract.  They were in receipt of some form of pension and some form of pay. Now this Bill introduces a different type of Reserve altogether, namely, the men who join the Reserve direct or the F.C.A.  I understood that the F.C.A. was part of the Reserve.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OscarTraynor" hpid="Mr. Traynor Mr. Traynor">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Traynor</NameTxt>
      <P>Second Line Reserve.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PeadarCowan" hpid="Captain Cowan Captain Cowan">
      <NameTxt>Captain Cowan</NameTxt>
      <P>But they are part of the Reserve?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OscarTraynor" hpid="Mr. Traynor Mr. Traynor">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Traynor</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes,</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PeadarCowan" hpid="Captain Cowan Captain Cowan">
      <NameTxt>Captain Cowan</NameTxt>
      <P>As reservists, they are subject to military law.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OscarTraynor" hpid="Mr. Traynor Mr. Traynor">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Traynor</NameTxt>
      <P>If called out on permanent service.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="207" />
    <Speaker pid="PeadarCowan" hpid="Captain Cowan Captain Cowan">
      <NameTxt>Captain Cowan</NameTxt>
      <P>They are subject to military law as reservists.  When they wear uniform they are subject to military law under this measure.  I am dealing with what is in the Act, not what is in the mind of the Minister or in the minds of those who advise him. This measure says they are subject to military law.  It says further that if they do not attend a parade they can he brought before the District Court. I do not think that provision should appear in this Bill.  There is a completely new conception in relation to the Reserve abroad now but, although that new conception is there, the old sections which related to the old militia have been superimposed; the idea behind the new Reserve is forgotten but the punitive provisions are there.  The Minister asks how can we run the Reserve without them?  If the Minister or anybody else brings a reservist up in the District Court for failing to appear on a parade he will destroy the Reserve.  This provision should not appear in this Bill.  The Minister says my criticism in relation to a football match or a public-house is exaggerated.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OscarTraynor" hpid="Mr. Traynor Mr. Traynor">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Traynor</NameTxt>
      <P>It is not in conformity with the section anyhow.  The Deputy should read paragraph (b).</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PeadarCowan" hpid="Captain Cowan Captain Cowan">
      <NameTxt>Captain Cowan</NameTxt>
      <P>I have read it and I have interpreted it in the form in which I know these things have been interpreted.  The words &ldquo;acting in the execution of his office&rdquo; are put in. What do they mean?</P>
      <P>
        <i>Notice taken that 20 Deputies were not present; House counted, and 20 Deputies being present,</i>
      </P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PeadarCowan" hpid="Captain Cowan Captain Cowan">
      <NameTxt>Captain Cowan</NameTxt>
      <P>I was making the point that the operation of a section such as this would destroy the Reserve.  Therefore, wisdom would suggest that it should not be in the Bill.</P>
      <P>Amendment put and declared negatived.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PeadarCowan" hpid="Captain Cowan Captain Cowan">
      <NameTxt>Captain Cowan</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 178:&mdash;</P>
      <P>In page 106, Section 241 (1), line 43, to delete &ldquo;as may be allowed in the prescribed manner&rdquo;.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="208" /> This section deals with the non-attendance of a reservist called out for training or on permanent service.  It says:&mdash;</P>
    <P>&ldquo;When a reservist is called out for training or on permanent service or in aid of the civil power, and such reservist, without leave lawfully granted or such sickness or other reasonable excuse as may be allowed in the prescribed manner, fails to appear at any time and place at which he is required upon such calling out to attend,&rdquo;</P>
    <P>he may be guilty of desertion or absence without leave and he may be subject to be tried by court-martial or by a District Court and he may be punished as provided in the section.  I object to the words &ldquo;as may be allowed in the prescribed manner&rdquo;. If he is absent owing to sickness or has any other reasonable excuse that should be sufficient for the court.  But, again, the provisions of the Bill are pushed to the extent that, even if he has a reasonable excuse, unless it is an excuse that has been laid down in regulations as being acceptable, then it is no defence in a court of law.</P>
    <P>I do not want the Minister to say that I am exaggerating in regard to that or any other section.  Here we have a case where a man is sick or he has a resonable excuse for not attending, an excuse that the court trying him would consider reasonable, but unless that excuse has been laid down in regulations beforehand as a prescribed excuse it cannot be taken into account in his defence.  I should like to see the Minister or anybody else telling a district justice that that was the Army law which he had to apply, that even though the defendant before the court had a reasonable excuse it was not a reasonable excuse prescribed by the Minister and therefore the court could not take it into consideration. As I say, it is another of these sections which show that the rules of law and the principles of justice have meant nothing in the drafting of these sections.</P>
    <Speaker pid="OscarTraynor" hpid="Mr. Traynor Mr. Traynor">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Traynor</NameTxt>
      <P>This is another of the sections which I undertook to have examined.  I did examine it from the <Col N="209" /> point of view of the words to which the Deputy objects, &ldquo;as may be allowed in the prescribed manner&rdquo;. On looking into that I felt at the time that unless there was some clarification somewhere that difficulty would arise.  But, when I did get down to examine the matter, I found that what would happen is that the type of illness or other excuse which will be regarded as justifying the non-attendance will be set out in the regulations. It will be made clear to the persons concerned what a resonable excuse for not turning up will be and I think that that should meet the objection which the Deputy has stated.  It will be clearly set out.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PeadarCowan" hpid="Captain Cowan Captain Cowan">
      <NameTxt>Captain Cowan</NameTxt>
      <P>I must say that whoever drafted that section and put in these words deliberately endeavoured to get across the principles of law or knew nothing about the principles of justice, because in any case that comes before a court the court is always given a discretion, if a man has a reasonable excuse, to deal with the case on that basis.  But this says that it does not matter two hoots if you have an excuse that the court may consider reasonable, that it is no good unless it is laid down in the regulations that that excuse is to be accepted.  I do not know what sort of regulations will be laid down.  Is it to be prescribed that if a doctor thinks a man is unfit to travel that is a reasonable excuse?  Is it proposed to lay down this type of illness, that type of illness or the other type of illness?  The whole thing is absurd.  If a man has a reasonable excuse, then that is his defence; but to try to say: &ldquo;Your defence is very reasonable but you are suffering from this new disease caused by dust falling from an atomic explosion and we have not provided for that and therefore it is not a reasonable excuse,&rdquo; is absurd.</P>
      <P>Amendment put and declared negatived.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PeadarCowan" hpid="Captain Cowan Captain Cowan">
      <NameTxt>Captain Cowan</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 179:&mdash;</P>
      <P>In page 107, Section 241, to delete sub-section (3), lines 1 to 5.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="210" /> That sub-section says that:&mdash;</P>
    <P>&ldquo;Any offence committed by a reservist which under this section is punishable on conviction by court-martial shall for all purposes of and incidental to the arrest, trial and punishment of the offender, including the summary dealing with his case by his commanding officer, be deemed to be an offence against military law.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>Again, we have laid down when is a person subject to military law.  We have laid down a whole schedule of offences in the Act, and in case there might be some escape we find there are very peculiar provisions inserted.  The section as a whole provides that absence may be desertion or absence without leave, that is if he is called out on permanent service or to the aid of the civil power, if he does not turn up it may be desertion or absence without leave; and if called up for training he will be guilty of absence without leave.  Then it says that he can be tried either by court-martial or by the District Court.  That is followed by this sub-section.</P>
    <P>First and foremost, in the earlier part of the section, they provide that he can be court-martialled.  In case they might have any doubt as to whether it was an offence against military law he committed, then they put in this clause making it an offence against military law, as well as being an offence against civil law.  I think it is wrong that that sub-section should be in, and I am opposed to it being there.</P>
    <Speaker pid="OscarTraynor" hpid="Mr. Traynor Mr. Traynor">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Traynor</NameTxt>
      <P>I cannot accept this amendment.  The section provides that reservists who fail to come out when called may be tried either by court-martial or in the District Courts. If they are tried by court-martial, the offence must be capable of being deemed an offence against military law, so as to give jurisdiction to the court-martial and as a natural consequence to summary dealing by the commanding officer.  This is another of these questions which I discussed with the military people concerned, and they were satisfied that this particular section, the section in general, would be required.  I might point out <Col N="211" /> to Deputy Cowan and the other members of the House that the section is identical, or almost identical, with the section in the 1923 Act.  It is made up of a number of other sections in the 1923 Act and they are brought together into this section, which is now 241.</P>
      <P>Amendment put and declared lost.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PeadarCowan" hpid="Captain Cowan Captain Cowan">
      <NameTxt>Captain Cowan</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 180:&mdash;</P>
      <P>In page 107, Section 241, to delete sub-section (4), lines 6 to 10.</P>
      <P>This amendment is to delete the following sub-section of the same section, which says:&mdash;</P>
      <P>&ldquo;A person charged with an offence which under this section is cognisable both by a court-martial and by the District Court, shall not be liable to be tried both by a court-martial and the District Court, but may be tried by either of them as may be directed by the prescribed military authority.&rdquo;</P>
      <P>The prescribed military authority can say: &ldquo;This man is to go before the district justice&rdquo; or &ldquo;This man is to go before a court-martial.&rdquo;  Again, the matter is being pushed to what one might term the logical extreme.  If he is subject to military law he may be tried by court-martial for this purely military offence, but do not be sending him out to the District Court, and certainly do not be giving a military officer the right to order that a reservist be tried in the local District Court, because it is completely contrary to our concept of how people are brought before a district justice, on a charge or on a summons, that you have military officers directing that a case be tried by the district justice.  I think this is very wrong.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OscarTraynor" hpid="Mr. Traynor Mr. Traynor">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Traynor</NameTxt>
      <P>I might inform the House that it is not the practice to charge reservists who failed to come up for annual training; but I presume this is an effort to anticipate a difficulty that might be likely to arise.  My information, anyhow, is that it might be possible that a very large number of men would fail to respond to the call-up, and then, if that should <Col N="212" /> happen, the question would arise: &ldquo;How can they be dealt with?&rdquo;&mdash;and it is felt that it would be more feasible to deal with it in this manner, by either dealing with them through the civil court or, if it was possible, by a military court.  As far as I am aware, anyhow, the section is merely to ensure that it will be possible to deal with that if it should ever happen that a large number would refuse at any one time to come up together.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PeadarCowan" hpid="Captain Cowan Captain Cowan">
      <NameTxt>Captain Cowan</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister, of course, can see a very grave objection to it.  It depends on who is being charged.  If a man is guilty of desertion and brought before a court-martial, a court-martial is always very severe in a matter of desertion; but if you want to let him off, you send him down to the District Court and it may give him a fine up to £25.  A court-martial may send him away for a couple of years' imprisonment if the situation was serious; but if some prescribed military authority, for one reason or another, wants to let the man off, he sends him down to the district justice who, probably, will fine him 10/-.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GenSeanMacEoin" hpid="General MacEoin General MacEoin">
      <NameTxt>General MacEoin</NameTxt>
      <P>Five shillings.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PeadarCowan" hpid="Captain Cowan Captain Cowan">
      <NameTxt>Captain Cowan</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes, 5/-.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OscarTraynor" hpid="Mr. Traynor Mr. Traynor">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Traynor</NameTxt>
      <P>Deputy Cowan knows that that is happening every time there is a call-up&mdash;that men who are called up fail to turn up and nothing happens.  They are not charged.  They are not brought before a civil court or a military court.  We are trying to foresee something that has not happened yet.  All I am pointing out to Deputy Cowan is that, at the present time at least, when reservists do not turn up they are not prosecuted.  Nobody goes after them, or anything like that.</P>
      <P>Amendment put and declared lost.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PeadarCowan" hpid="Captain Cowan Captain Cowan">
      <NameTxt>Captain Cowan</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 181:&mdash;</P>
      <P>In page 107, Section 243 (b) (ii), lines 47 and 48, to delete &ldquo;tried may, whether it convicts him of the offence or not&rdquo; and substitute &ldquo;convicted shall order him to return the article to the Minister or in default may order him to pay to the Minister the value of the article.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>This is a very small amendment and I <Col N="213" /> do not think that there can be very much objection to it.  The section deals with the wrongful sale of equipment by a member of the Reserve Defence Force.  It provides that if any such person fails to deliver up an article to the Minister, he shall be guilty of an offence and liable to a fine not exceeding £5.  There is then the addition that the court by which he is tried, whether it convicts him of the offence or not, may order him to pay to the Minister the value of the article.  That is certainly going very far. I only wish that some of these cases would come before the District Courts at some time so that we might have some pronouncement on them from the district justices.  The proposal is that where a man is charged with making away with an article, whether the court convicts him or not of the offence, it will have power to order him to pay the Minister the value of the article.  My suggestion is that we should insert instead the provision that the court by which he is convicted &ldquo;shall order him to return the article to the Minister or in default may order him to pay to the Minister the value of the article.&rdquo;  In other words if the district justice finds he has the article or has made away with it, the court convicting him may order him to return that article to the Minister or pay the Minister the value of it.  In addition a maximum fine of £5 is provided.  It seems to me that it is monstrous to write into the section that whether the court convicts him or not, it may order him to pay the value of the article.  You might get a mad district justice who would do a thing like that but I do not think that we should make provision for a district justice who happens to be <i>non compos mentis.</i></P>
    <Speaker pid="GenSeanMacEoin" hpid="General MacEoin General MacEoin">
      <NameTxt>General MacEoin</NameTxt>
      <P>It does appear on its face to be a rather peculiar provision that if a person is found not guilty of the offence, we may say to him: &ldquo;Whether you took it or not, you have to pay for it.&rdquo;  I agree with Deputy Cowan that it is rather farfetched to suggest that a district justice would order payment to be made for the article, after finding a person not guilty of having destroyed <Col N="214" /> it or having done any of the things that are mentioned in the section.  I should like to hear the Minister give some reasons as to why such a provision is included.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OscarTraynor" hpid="Mr. Traynor Mr. Traynor">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Traynor</NameTxt>
      <P>First of all, we must remember that we are dealing here with public property, for the protection of which every one of us is responsible in varying degrees.  At first glance, the position may seem to be as Deputy Cowan has put it, a position about which Deputy MacEoin also seems to have some doubts.  The situation, as I conceive it, is that when a case of this kind comes before the district justice, the district justice generally realises that he is dealing with a decent type of man, a man of some character and the property missing may not be value to any great amount.  He may then decide to let the man off but there is no means of getting compensation for the missing article.  The district justice in the goodness of his heart says: &ldquo;That is all.  Go off now and do not do it again.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GenSeanMacEoin" hpid="General MacEoin General MacEoin">
      <NameTxt>General MacEoin</NameTxt>
      <P>The district justice should go the whole way then and not allow him to be penalised for the value of the article.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OscarTraynor" hpid="Mr. Traynor Mr. Traynor">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Traynor</NameTxt>
      <P>That illustrates the type of case that could possibly arise. I do not know whether it has ever happened or whether we can produce any precedents for this proposal but this clause is brought in to meet cases where the man charged may be a decent type of man.  Whether, however, he be a decent type of man or a rogue, if the property is stolen or done away with, it is State property and so far as it is possible to get some compensation for the State, I think an effort should be made to do so.  It is with that end in view that we want to have this section in the Bill.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PeadarCowan" hpid="Captain Cowan Captain Cowan">
      <NameTxt>Captain Cowan</NameTxt>
      <P>While everybody should be concerned about the protection of property, whether it be public property or private property, I must say that if the man is not guilty of the offence of taking it or making away with it, there should be no <Col N="215" /> question of giving the district justice power, even though he may find the person charged not guilty of the offence, to order him to pay the value of the article to the Minister.  It is a very objectionable proposal and I regret that some of the distinguished lawyers we have as members of the House are not available to assist the Minister on such a section as this. This section applies only to a person who is a member or a former member of the Reserve Defence Force.  I had a case one time concerning a former member of the Reserve who was living at home.  Somebody checking up somewhere came to the conclusion that through some neglect of his several pairs of boots were missing and of course the Department of Defence, with their usual ideas about law and justice, decided to stop his pension to the extent of the value of the boots.  It had to be pointed out to them very clearly and specifically that they could do no such thing.  A provision like this put into the Bill gives me the impression that there is no respect or regard for law&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OscarTraynor" hpid="Mr. Traynor Mr. Traynor">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Traynor</NameTxt>
      <P>Were the boots on issue?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PeadarCowan" hpid="Captain Cowan Captain Cowan">
      <NameTxt>Captain Cowan</NameTxt>
      <P>They were on issue.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OscarTraynor" hpid="Mr. Traynor Mr. Traynor">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Traynor</NameTxt>
      <P>They could not possibly be charged against him then.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PeadarCowan" hpid="Captain Cowan Captain Cowan">
      <NameTxt>Captain Cowan</NameTxt>
      <P>This man had responsibility in regard to the boots.  He was at home a couple of years when on some audit or investigation it was discovered that there was a deficiency or an apparent deficiency of a certain number of boots.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OscarTraynor" hpid="Mr. Traynor Mr. Traynor">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Traynor</NameTxt>
      <P>That is different.  That is the reason I asked the question if they were on issue.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PeadarCowan" hpid="Captain Cowan Captain Cowan">
      <NameTxt>Captain Cowan</NameTxt>
      <P>I understand.  I do not want to say anything that would identify the man.  There was an apparent deficiency and the Army authorities said to themselves apparently: &ldquo;It does not worry us whether we have the right to make a deduction from this man's pension or not; we are doing it.&rdquo;  They wrote to him and said: &ldquo;We are stopping your <Col N="216" /> pension until all the boots are paid for.&rdquo;  They were told just where they got off on that occasion. What I feel is that if this practice were allowed, this practice of deducting money from a pension whether the law allows it or not, or if they can come barefacedly into the Dáil with a provision such as this, that even whether the district justice finds a man guilty or not of the offence, he can still order him to pay for the article missing, it would be a negation of all justice.  The whole idea appears to be that whether a man is right or wrong, guilty or innocent, he must pay up.  I would ask the Minister not to leave the section in.  It is an affront to justice and if ever a case should come before the District Court under it, the Dáil and everybody connected with it will be held up in a very sorry light.  Let a judge of the High Court get at that and what will he say?  I should feel humiliated in reading or hearing what a judge of the High Court would say about a provision such as this in a country which is supposed to be ruled by law.</P>
      <P>What I suggest is very simple: if he is convicted, the court shall order him&mdash; I put it even more strongly&mdash;to pay the value of the article to the Minister.  I am concerned about public property in the way in which I put it there, but I am concerned with it on the basis of law and I very strongly press the Minister to accept the amendment. The Minister said that the court might want to let a decent man off, but what happens always is&mdash;it happens every day of the week&mdash;that the justice says: &ldquo;I will adjourn this case for a month or six months.  Will the money be paid then?&rdquo;  I am aware of a case this morning which was adjourned a week ago in which three people had to pay between them a sum of £20.  They paid it up to-day and the justice said: &ldquo;Be good boys in the future.&rdquo;  The court always uses its discretion and deals properly with all these cases.  I am honestly ashamed of this section with this provision in it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OscarTraynor" hpid="Mr. Traynor Mr. Traynor">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Traynor</NameTxt>
      <P>I am not accepting the amendment, but I will have it reexamined.</P>
      <P>Amendment, by leave, withdrawn.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="217" />
    <Speaker pid="OscarTraynor" hpid="Mr. Traynor Mr. Traynor">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Traynor</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 182:&mdash;</P>
      <P>In page 108, to delete Section 245 (c), lines 18 to 20.</P>
      <P>This amendment is moved in pursuance of a promise made in the Special Committee.</P>
      <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OscarTraynor" hpid="Mr. Traynor Mr. Traynor">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Traynor</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 183:&mdash;</P>
      <P>In page 109, Section 246 (i), lines 55 and 56, to delete &ldquo;or being a regulation or rule made by the Minister under this Act&rdquo;.</P>
      <P>This amendment is to remove some unnecessary words from the section.  I understand we will be able to deal with the matter through other means.</P>
      <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PeadarCowan" hpid="Captain Cowan Captain Cowan">
      <NameTxt>Captain Cowan</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 184:&mdash;</P>
      <P>In page 111, Section 249 (1), line 5, to delete &ldquo;or an absentee&rdquo;.</P>
      <P>This section deals with the apprehension of suspected deserters and absentees and I seek by this amendment to have a couple of words deleted from both sub-sections&mdash;sub-sections (1) and (b) (ii) (1).  The section provides:&mdash;</P>
      <P>&ldquo;Where an officer or man or a member of the Garda Síochána has reasonable grounds for suspecting that any person is a deserter or an absentee, he may without warrant arrest such person...&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Thereupon, certain provisions come into effect.  Then follows the provision that such person may make a demand in regard to his arrest and, if he so demands, may be brought before a district justice or a peace commissioner and the district justice or peace commissioner shall inquire into the arrest, and, if satisfied that he is a deserter or an absentee, shall cause him to be delivered into service custody and in the meantime to be kept in a Garda barracks.  There has always been a very big difference between desertion and absence without leave.  Every soldier at some time in his career is absent without leave for either a short or a long period, but desertion is a different thing.  It <Col N="218" /> means absence with the intention of not returning to the Defence Forces or of escaping a particular duty.  I do not want to go in detail into the definition, but the main thing is that there must be the intention of not returning.  In other words, the person is absconding entirely from the Defence Forces or evading a very serious duty.</P>
    <P>I have no objection to the provision in regard to deserters or suspected deserters, but to operate that provision against persons suspected of being absent without leave could cause the greatest trouble and annoyance, because if a soldier is out of barracks at 12.15 a.m. when he should have been in at midnight, he is an absentee without leave, and he may, without warrant, be arrested by an officer or member of the Defence Forces, or by a member of the Garda Síochána.  The Minister will say that it is not intended to operate that provision but once it is put there, a Garda can arrest a man who he knows is at a dance without leave and can bring him before a peace commissioner or district justice and have him thrown into a Garda lock-up.</P>
    <P>I see no necessity for this.  It will cause a tremendous lot of confusion and it may be abused.  If the Minister says it will not be operated and is not intended to be operated, I say: &ldquo;Do not have it there.&rdquo;  I have no objection, as I say, to the provision with regard to people who are deserters, or even suspected of being deserters, but I certainly have an objection to all that machinery in regard to a person who takes a couple of hours off without leave to go to a dance, to go for a few drinks, or to do one or other of the things that human beings, in their youth, are likely or liable to do.  I ask the Minister to delete these words from the section.</P>
    <Speaker pid="OscarTraynor" hpid="Mr. Traynor Mr. Traynor">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Traynor</NameTxt>
      <P>I should have thought that normally Deputy Cowan would have insisted on these words being inserted, if they were not there.  I say that seriously, because the Deputy knows that the type of absence to which he refers arises every day and every night in the week, every month <Col N="219" /> of the year and has been going on for years and years and will probably continue in the future.  The case which this is intended to deal with is the case of the individual who, if he is away on furlough or on leave, overstays his leave by a considerable period.  In these circumstances, the Garda in the district from which he comes are notified and they naturally will call on the individual if he is to be found at home.  If he is at home, he will be apprehended and all that usually happens is that he is returned to his unit.  Very often there is a reasonable excuse.  There may be, perhaps, some family illness at home or something like that.  That is held to be a reasonable excuse.  I have known cases where, even after a man had been arrested and the facts reported, he was given extended leave in order to facilitate him in his home, the condition being guaranteed by the Garda of the district.  So that, in effect, in this particular case the use of the word &ldquo;absentee&rdquo; ensures that the man will not be taken in as a deserter.  If he is arrested as a deserter, he will certainly be tried by court-martial but if he is arrested as an absentee it is quite possible that all that happens is he is brought back to his base and the case summarily dealt with.  If the case was such as I have stated the effects may be exactly as I have suggested that they are in a number of cases.  I think the Deputy should withdraw the amendment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GenSeanMacEoin" hpid="General MacEoin General MacEoin">
      <NameTxt>General MacEoin</NameTxt>
      <P>I think the provision is required but, of course, there is always the danger that it will be abused.  I am aware of a person being arrested for being absent without leave by an officer who got a lift from the person he arrested.  When he got to Dublin he got the man arrested and showed in.  Of course, when the case was dealt with next day, the officer who accused the serving member was himself placed on a charge because he had counselled the absence without leave.  It is that sort of thing which is a danger.  The Provost Marshal or somebody else may know that a soldier <Col N="220" /> is an hour or a half-an-hour absent without leave.  He can subject the soldier to a grave indignity by having him arrested by a Civic Guard and brought before a peace commissioner.</P>
      <P>On the other hand, I am perfectly satisfied that there is a very big number of cases where the leave is overstayed and if there is not some provision to deal with it the danger is that there would be many more who would overstay their leave.  The temptation would be to say: &ldquo;I can chance it.&rdquo;  But, as I say, it is one of these things where there is no danger if it is dealt with in the proper spirit. But it would be very hard to deal with an absentee who is a considerable distance away or where there is no military post but for this provision so that the Civic Guard could be notified that Johnny White was absent for the past 48 hours, was at home and could be picked up.  That is one of the ways in which that can be dealt with expeditiously.  I feel that the police or the Army authorities must have the provision here.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PeadarCowan" hpid="Captain Cowan Captain Cowan">
      <NameTxt>Captain Cowan</NameTxt>
      <P>This section deals only with serving officers or serving soldiers or persons who would be subject to military law on permanent services or otherwise.  Taking it broadly in regard to members of the Defence Forces if a person is absent without leave he can be tried for that by his commanding officer or by his company commander or he might be court-martialled if the necessity arose.  The usual punishment is a small fine but he forfeits pay for every day's absence. That is the usual punishment.  It may be dealt with in that way.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Desertion is a completely different thing.  When a person absents himself for a particular period, generally 21 days, a court of inquiry is held and that court of inquiry declares him to be a deserter, having received whatever available evidence there is in regard to absence.  His kit is collected and whatever is collected is subtracted from whatever he should have and he is declared deficient of the remaining articles of military property on charge to him.  When that machinery has been put into operation, the Guards are <Col N="221" /> notified that such and such a person is a deserter.  Then they have authority to arrest him as a deserter.  There is no trouble about that.</P>
    <P>But there is trouble about the person who is absent without leave for a short period, a day, a week or even a fortnight.  If he is at home, the military authorities know his home address and they are entitled to go out and arrest him and take him into military custody and bring him back to the barracks.  There is no trouble about that.  The trouble arises in regard to this sort of civilian form of arrest, apprehending him without a warrant.  An officer may see a man in the streets of Westport or some other town where there is no military post. He may know he is an absentee.  He can go over, apprehend him and hand him into the custody of a member of the Garda who would put him in the lock-up. Then you have all this machinery put into operation.  I do not think it is right that should apply to a person unless he is a deserter or a suspected deserter.  I do not think these provisions should apply to a person who simply overstays his leave or takes French leave.  I want three words deleted from the two sections:&mdash;&ldquo;or an absentee&rdquo;.</P>
    <P>Absence of the type I mention is never very serious and, in fact, it is not abused very much but you can have a considerable amount of humiliation placed on a soldier who just happens to be absent a few hours or a day or so if the provisions of this section are put into effect.  I do not think that any other State force has this sort of provision.  If a civil servant absents himself for a day or a couple of days or a week he does not have guards going round apprehending him, putting him in the lock-up or bringing him before a district justice.  I am not too sure of what happens in regard to members of the Garda Síochána but I doubt very much if they can be summarily apprehended in the fashion that is here.</P>
    <Speaker pid="GenSeanMacEoin" hpid="General MacEoin General MacEoin">
      <NameTxt>General MacEoin</NameTxt>
      <P>They can get themselves fired.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PeadarCowan" hpid="Captain Cowan Captain Cowan">
      <NameTxt>Captain Cowan</NameTxt>
      <P>They may get themselves <Col N="222" /> fired.  The soldier may be fired over it.  He is subject to the very same risk.  The civil servant may be fired over it but the strange thing about it is that we do not use these punitive measures to deal with the civil servant who is a public officer or the Garda in this humiliating way.  We just keep it for the unfortunate soldier. I want to limit it to the fellow who commits the very serious and heinous crime of desertion or to the person who is suspected of desertion. I want the ordinary absentee treated in the same way as other public servants. That is why I put down these three amendments.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="CormacBreslin" hpid="An Leas-Cheann Comhairle Cormac Breslin">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Cheann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>Is the Deputy withdrawing the amendment?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PeadarCowan" hpid="Captain Cowan Captain Cowan">
      <NameTxt>Captain Cowan</NameTxt>
      <P>No.  Please put it.</P>
      <P>Amendment put and declared negatived.</P>
      <P>Amendment No. 185 not moved.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OscarTraynor" hpid="Mr. Traynor Mr. Traynor">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Traynor</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 186:&mdash;</P>
      <P>In page 111, Section 250, to delete line 59, and substitute &ldquo;a fine not exceeding twenty pounds or, at the discretion of the court, to imprisonment for any term not exceeding three months or to both such fine and imprisonment.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="CormacBreslin" hpid="An Leas-Cheann Comhairle Cormac Breslin">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Cheann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>Amendments Nos. 186 and 187 may be taken together.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OscarTraynor" hpid="Mr. Traynor Mr. Traynor">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Traynor</NameTxt>
      <P>I promised the Special Committee to go into this matter and it is now proposed to delete the last line in the first paragraph of Section 150: &ldquo;imprisonment for any term not exceeding three months&rdquo; and to insert &ldquo;a fine not exceeding £20 or, at the discretion of the court, to imprisonment for any term not exceeding three months or to both such fine and imprisonment&rdquo;.  Amendments Nos. 186 and 187 are identical.</P>
      <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OscarTraynor" hpid="Mr. Traynor Mr. Traynor">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Traynor</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 187:&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>In page 111, Section 251, lines 63 and 64, to delete &ldquo;imprisonment for <Col N="223" /> any term not exceeding three months&rdquo; and substitute &ldquo;a fine not exceeding twenty pounds or, at the discretion of the court, to imprisonment for any term not exceeding three months or to both such fine and imprisonment.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PeadarCowan" hpid="Captain Cowan Captain Cowan">
      <NameTxt>Captain Cowan</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 188:&mdash;</P>
      <P>In page 112, Section 253 (a), lines 18 and 19, to delete &ldquo;or absent himself without leave&rdquo;.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="CormacBreslin" hpid="An Leas-Cheann Comhairle Cormac Breslin">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Cheann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>Amendments Nos. 188 to 193 deal with cognate matters and may be discussed together.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PeadarCowan" hpid="Captain Cowan Captain Cowan">
      <NameTxt>Captain Cowan</NameTxt>
      <P>Substantially the same idea is in this section as in the last one I moved in regard to an absentee without leave.  Section 253 provides, according to the side heading, for &ldquo;punishment for inducing,&rdquo; etc., &ldquo;members of the Defence Forces to desert.&rdquo;  I have no objection in the world to that if it was limited to what is contained in the title at the side of the Bill.  However, when we look at the section we find it says:&mdash;</P>
      <P>&ldquo;(a)  procures or persuades or attempts to procure or persuade any person subject to military law to desert or absent himself without leave, or</P>
      <P>(b)  procures or persuades or attempts to procure or persuade any reservist to desert or absent himself without leave within the meaning of Section 241, or</P>
      <P>(c)  knowing that a person subject to military law is about to desert or absent himself without leave, aids or assists him in deserting or absenting himself without leave, or</P>
      <P>(d)  knowing that a reservist is about to desert or absent himself without leave within the meaning of Section 241, aids or assists him in so deserting or absenting himself without leave, or</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>(e)  knowing any person subject to military law to be a deserter or an absentee, conceals such person <Col N="224" /> or aids or assists in concealing him or aids or assists in his rescue, or</P>
    <P>(f)  knowing any reservist to be a deserter or an absentee without leave within the meaning of Section 241, conceals such man or aids or assists in concealing him or aids or assists in his rescue.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>I have no objection whatever to these provisions being there in regard to desertion, but I think it is a bit too much to put into the section that, if the mother of a soldier who is absent for a couple of hours or days without leave conceals him when the military police come and puts him into the cupboard or under the bed, she should be brought up in court and fined a sum not exceeding £50.  The same principle I referred to previously is involved here, and I am not going to waste time on it; but there ought to be some little sense in this regard.  Provision ought to be made just for desertion and not for these simple absences without leave that we hear of every day of the week. The same point was made before: that it is a section which in so far as it may be applied to absentees, can be abused.</P>
    <Speaker pid="OscarTraynor" hpid="Mr. Traynor Mr. Traynor">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Traynor</NameTxt>
      <P>If the matter were as simple as Deputy Cowan has stated, it would not be necessary at all to utilise the section.  This section is the same as the section in the 1923 Act and I do not think it is operated in the way in which the Deputy has suggested. It stands to reason that the people with whom it is intended to deal are people who would deliberately incite a soldier to desert, not turn up at the end of leave, or something of that kind.  It has operated over all the years and I do not think Deputy Cowan, myself or anybody else would be able to cite a case in which a mother was prosecuted for concealing her son or for inducing him not to turn up.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GenSeanMacEoin" hpid="General MacEoin General MacEoin">
      <NameTxt>General MacEoin</NameTxt>
      <P>This is the section in regard to which the Curragh officer was convicted for inducing the other person to be absent without leave.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OscarTraynor" hpid="Mr. Traynor Mr. Traynor">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Traynor</NameTxt>
      <P>This is like a lot of the other sections in the Act that we have been discussing over the last few <Col N="225" /> months.  It is an effort to ensure that every leakage will be repaired, that there will be no possibility of not being able to deal with the type of person who would be likely to commit that type of act flagrantly, with malice, so to speak, knowing that he was inducing somebody to do one or other of these acts.  It is not intended at all to deal with the mother, the wife or anybody like that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PeadarCowan" hpid="Captain Cowan Captain Cowan">
      <NameTxt>Captain Cowan</NameTxt>
      <P>I must say, as I said last night, that the Minister is most disarming when he takes up this attitude &ldquo;it is not intended.&rdquo;  It is our duty as the Dáil to ensure that the power cannot be exercised improperly by anybody.  That is our duty.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OscarTraynor" hpid="Mr. Traynor Mr. Traynor">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Traynor</NameTxt>
      <P>Lawyers are great men for precedent.  A precedent of many years' standing has showed it never happened.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PeadarCowan" hpid="Captain Cowan Captain Cowan">
      <NameTxt>Captain Cowan</NameTxt>
      <P>In the relevant section of the 1923 Act we had three sub-sections and they were never used. &ldquo;Desuetude&rdquo;, I think, is the word that might be used in regard to them, but the Minister now gives them an injection of new life and makes six sub-sections out of the three.  Then he says: &ldquo;We had it in the 1923 Act, but we did not operate it.&rdquo;  But it has grown from (a), (b), (c) to (a), (b), (c), (d), (e), (f).  I think argument is of no use.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="CormacBreslin" hpid="An Leas-Cheann Comhairle Cormac Breslin">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Cheann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>Is the Deputy withdrawing the amendment?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PeadarCowan" hpid="Captain Cowan Captain Cowan">
      <NameTxt>Captain Cowan</NameTxt>
      <P>No.  Please put it.</P>
      <P>Amendment put and declared negatived.</P>
      <P>Amendments Nos. 189, 190, 191, 192 and 193 not moved.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OscarTraynor" hpid="Mr. Traynor Mr. Traynor">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Traynor</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 194:&mdash;</P>
      <P>In page 112, to delete Section 254 (1) (a), lines 43 and 44, and substitute the following:&mdash;</P>
      <P>(a)  acts or purports to act as a recruiter or a person authorised to enlist recruits, or</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>In the Special Committee, this section <Col N="226" /> was described, I think, as being archaic.  This is an effort to meet that point and to bring it up to standard, so to speak.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PeadarCowan" hpid="Captain Cowan Captain Cowan">
      <NameTxt>Captain Cowan</NameTxt>
      <P>It does not go as far as we want, but we will agree to it.</P>
      <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OscarTraynor" hpid="Mr. Traynor Mr. Traynor">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Traynor</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 195:&mdash;</P>
      <P>In page 113, to delete Section 257, lines 46 to 52, and substitute the following:&mdash;</P>
      <P>Where regulations made by the Minister under Section 97 provide for proving, by statutory declaration, the identity of the recipient of any payment under the regulations, such declaration may be taken and received by any person specified in that behalf by the regulations.</P>
      <P>This is another of the Special Committee points.  The amendment proposes the introduction of a new section which differs from the existing one in that no reference is made to the taking of an oath or to perjury.  I undertook at the Special Committee to introduce this amendment.</P>
      <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PeadarCowan" hpid="Captain Cowan Captain Cowan">
      <NameTxt>Captain Cowan</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 196:&mdash;</P>
      <P>In page 114, to delete Section 258 (3), lines 45 to 55.</P>
      <P>This section deals with the penalty for any person who purchases certain military property.  Military property is given the very widest definition.  It includes:&mdash;</P>
      <P>&ldquo;(a)  any arms, ammunition (including bombs, grenades or similar missiles), equipment, instruments or clothing issued for the use of members of the Defence Forces, or</P>
      <P>(b)  any military decoration of a member of the Defence Forces, or</P>
      <P>(c)  any furniture, bedding, blankets, sheets, utensils or stores in military charge, or</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>(d)  any provisions or forage issued for the use of a member of the Defence Forces or his horse, or <Col N="227" /> (e)  any horse or vehicle employed in the service of the Defence Forces.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>That is military property.  Then, if any person&mdash;</P>
    <P>&ldquo;(1)  buys, exchanges, takes in pawn, obtains or receives from any person, on any pretence whatsoever, any military property, or</P>
    <P>(ii)  solicits or entices any person to sell, exchange, pawn or give away any military property, or</P>
    <P>(iii)  assists or acts for any person in selling, exchanging, pawning or making away with any military property,</P>
    <P>such person shall be guilty of an offence under this section and shall be liable on summary conviction thereof to a fine not exceeding £20 together with treble the value of any military property of which he has become possessed by means of the offence or, at the discretion of the court, to imprisonment for any term not exceeding six months or to both such fine and imprisonment.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>I was just wondering what the treble value of a military decoration would be&mdash;but I suppose that is for the future.  The section says:&mdash;</P>
    <P>&ldquo;Where a person is charged with an offence under this section it shall be a good defence to prove that&mdash;</P>
    <P>(i)  at the time he did the act alleged in the charge, he was unaware that the property in respect of which the charge was made was in fact military property, or</P>
    <P>(ii)  the said property was sold by Order or with the consent of the Minister or some competent military authority, or</P>
    <P>(iii)  the said property was the personal property of a person who had ceased to be a member of the Defence Forces or of the legal personal representatives of a deceased member of the Defence Forces.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>Obviously these would be and must be <Col N="228" /> good defences.  The section continues with sub-section (3)&mdash;and this is the sub-section I want to delete, along with sub-section (4):&mdash;</P>
    <P>&ldquo;(3)  Where any military property is found in the possession or keeping of any person, such person may be brought or summoned before a justice of the District Court, and if such justice has reasonable ground to believe that the military property so found was stolen, or was bought, exchanged, taken in pawn, obtained or received in contravention of this section, then, if such person does not satisfy such justice that he came by the military property so found lawfully and without any contravention of this Act, he shall be liable on summary conviction to the same penalties as are specified in sub-section (2) of this section in the case of a contravention of that sub-section.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>In other words, the law as we know it is not good enough when the Department of Defence operates.  It is not the ordinary case of someone proving that a man is guilty.  We have the provision here that the man must prove he is innocent.  That, again, is contravening one of the fundamental principles of ordinary justice, that if you allege a man is guilty of an offence you must prove he is guilty of it before he can be convicted.  In all such cases, the jury is warned and it is the practice of judges, in the case of doubt, to give the benefit of the doubt to the accused. Why should we, in respect of a soldier's blanket or sheet, change the fundamental principles of law?  There is adequate law&mdash;the law of larceny, the law of receiving an article knowing it to be stolen or otherwise unlawfully obtained.  In regard to &ldquo;buying, exchanging or obtaining,&rdquo; as in this section, there is plenty of law at present. Apparently in the Defence Forces we are not satisfied unless we upset every known principle of law.  I hope some jurist one day will examine this Bill and write an article or thesis on it and show it up in its nakedness for what it is.  Every principle that we have established in regard to law, and every principle of law in regard to criminal charges, is thrown overboard.  It says <Col N="229" /> here that if any military blanket, or something alleged to be a military blanket, is found, you must prove that you came by it lawfully.  Sub-section (4) says:&mdash;</P>
    <P>&ldquo;A person found committing an offence under this section may be arrested without warrant, and brought, together with the military property which is the subject of the offence, before a justice of the District Court, and any person to whom any such property is offered to be sold, pawned or delivered, who has reasonable cause to suppose that the same is offered in contravention of this section, may arrest without warrant the person offering such military property and deliver him and such military property into the custody of a member of the Garda Síochána to be dealt with according to law.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>In other words, if a person offers a groundsheet which appears to be military property&mdash;the sort of thing you see a &ldquo;bellman&rdquo; wearing, and which obviously has belonged to some army somewhere at some time&mdash;the person to whom it is offered may arrest without warrant the person offering it to him and lug him down to the Garda station.  I think there is adequate law in the ordinary criminal code to deal with this.  There is plenty of law in the section to make him guilty of an offence.  If he:&mdash;</P>
    <P>&ldquo;(i)  buys, exchanges, takes in pawn, obtains or receives from any person, on any pretence whatsoever, any military property, or</P>
    <P>(ii)  solicits or entices any person to sell, exchange, pawn or give away any military property, or</P>
    <P>(iii)  assists or acts for any person in selling, exchanging, pawning or making away with any military property,</P>
    <P>such person shall be guilty of an offence under this section and shall be liable on summary conviction thereof to a fine not exceeding £20 together with treble the value of any military property <Col N="230" /> of which he has become possessed by means of the offence or, at the discretion of the court, to imprisonment for any term not exceeding six months or to both such fine and imprisonment.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>One would think there was enough law, enough punishment, enough provision regarding any such offence.  But no, we have to proceed in the way we are proceeding all the time, throwing overboard all the canons of justice and reversing them as far as a military article or something alleged to be a military article is concerned.  It may even be a military utensil&mdash;such as boy scouts go around with.  We oblige the person to prove that he obtained the property lawfully.</P>
    <P>I have no objection to a discussion in this House on the principles governing justice, whether we are to have the French system or any other system rather than what is known as the English system under which we operate, where the accused is considered innocent until he is proved to be guillty.  I have no objection to that being considered, but I have the greatest objection to nibbling in and biting into the principles of law as we have it, as is done in this section and in this Bill. This is one of the examples.</P>
    <P>The Minister will say: &ldquo;We have to protect public property.&rdquo;  Public property, private property or any other property is not as sacrosanct as the principles of justice, because on the principles of justice are based the freedom of the individual.  If we deprive the individual of his freedom through interfering with the principles of justice, we nullify our constitutional provisions. For that reason, I object to that type of section in this or any other Bill.</P>
    <Speaker pid="OscarTraynor" hpid="Mr. Traynor Mr. Traynor">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Traynor</NameTxt>
      <P>Every time I hear Deputy Cowan dissertating on the legal iniquities of this Bill, I ask myself what sort of legal advisers the Government have, because if the Bill is as bad as Deputy Cowan appears to believe it is, it must be unconstitutional.  If it is unconstitutional, somebody should try to prove that.  The funny thing about it is that this particular section and even the sub-sections to which the Deputy has taken exception are old sections <Col N="231" /> that have been there for years.  I am not saying that that is a reason why they should never be altered.  They should be altered if there is a good reason for altering them.</P>
      <P>We are all taught to believe that the most iniquitous person is the person who is described as a receiver.  Is not that so?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PeadarCowan" hpid="Captain Cowan Captain Cowan">
      <NameTxt>Captain Cowan</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes, if he is proved to be a receiver.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OscarTraynor" hpid="Mr. Traynor Mr. Traynor">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Traynor</NameTxt>
      <P>He is the greatest danger, the source of all crime.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PeadarCowan" hpid="Captain Cowan Captain Cowan">
      <NameTxt>Captain Cowan</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes, if he is proved to be a receiver.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OscarTraynor" hpid="Mr. Traynor Mr. Traynor">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Traynor</NameTxt>
      <P>Of course, if he is not proved to be a receiver, he is set free. This section merely attempts to deal with the receiver.  It does not deal with the soldier.  The soldier can be dealt with by the normal military law. If the soldier is got at by some nefarious individual outside who can induce that soldier to take out State property, whether it is the sheets that Deputy Cowan referred to or equipment or foodstuffs, that is the man who should be got after immediately. No punishment would be too severe for that type of person, because he is the main source of crime.  For that reason, I think the section should remain.  The section has been there through all the years.  I do not know if it has had to operate to any extent. During the emergency, which was an abnormal time, there was a number of cases which had to be dealt with and, if my memory serves me correctly, at that particular period receivers were pretty severely dealt with.  I thought at the time that it stopped a particular type of crime that was developing and was assuming a very serious proportion.  When the source was discovered, that stopped; the State saved a lot of money, and, I am sure, many decent men's characters were saved.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I see no reason for deleting these sections as suggested by the amendment. There are ample safeguards against anything in the nature of an injustice being done.  I am not certain about this, but I understand that in <Col N="232" /> the ordinary civil law the onus is on the receiver to show that he came into the property lawfully.  I think that is correct.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PeadarCowan" hpid="Captain Cowan Captain Cowan">
      <NameTxt>Captain Cowan</NameTxt>
      <P>Correct?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OscarTraynor" hpid="Mr. Traynor Mr. Traynor">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Traynor</NameTxt>
      <P>If he can prove to the court that he has lawfully come into the property that he is charged with receiving, the matter ends there.  If the onus is on him and he fails to prove that he came into the property lawfully, he will be dealt with in the manner indicated in this particular section.  I do not think anyone should shed any tears for that type of individual. If he deals in that sort of crime he should take whatever is coming to him.</P>
      <P>Amendment put and declared lost.</P>
      <P>Amendment No. 197 not moved.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="CormacBreslin" hpid="An Leas-Cheann Comhairle Cormac Breslin">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Cheann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>Amendments Nos. 198 and 199 may be debated together.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PeadarCowan" hpid="Captain Cowan Captain Cowan">
      <NameTxt>Captain Cowan</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 198:&mdash;</P>
      <P>In page 116, Section 263 (1), line 15, to delete &ldquo;upon that uniform&rdquo; and substitute &ldquo;on the Defence Forces&rdquo;.</P>
      <P>This is a very simple thing.  Sub-section (1) of Section 263 says:&mdash;</P>
      <P>&ldquo;If any person wears any uniform of the Defence Forces or any dress, having the appearance of, or bearing any of the regimental or other distinctive marks of, any such uniform, in such a manner or in such circumstances as to be likely to bring contempt upon that uniform, such person shall be guilty of an offence under this sub-section.&rdquo;</P>
      <P>I do not like that expression &ldquo;contempt upon the uniform&rdquo; because I do not think it means anything.  I have substituted the words &ldquo;on the Defence Forces&rdquo;.  I think a person can be guilty of bringing contempt on the Defence Forces.  I do not think a person could reasonably be convicted of being guilty of bringing contempt upon a uniform.  It is a small drafting matter. I think my words are better than the Minister's.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="233" />
    <Speaker pid="OscarTraynor" hpid="Mr. Traynor Mr. Traynor">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Traynor</NameTxt>
      <P>In this case I have been asked specially by the Army authorities to ensure that this section will stand in the Bill.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PeadarCowan" hpid="Captain Cowan Captain Cowan">
      <NameTxt>Captain Cowan</NameTxt>
      <P>I have no objection to the section.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OscarTraynor" hpid="Mr. Traynor Mr. Traynor">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Traynor</NameTxt>
      <P>I have been asked to ensure that it would not be altered. The amendments would alter it.  The Army authorities inform me that one of the first things they endeavour to inculcate in the minds of recruits to the Army or to the officer corps is pride in their uniform.  The men are taught that anything that would be likely to bring contempt on that uniform should be regarded as a very serious matter.  The Army authorities pointed out to me that we are endeavouring to do the same thing in regard to the flag&mdash;we are endeavouring to create pride in the national flag. The effort is to create pride in the uniform that will ensure that any man wearing the uniform will not do anything to bring the uniform into contempt. It is because the Army authorities feel so strongly about that, that they mentioned the matter to me personally and that I just mention the matter here.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PeadarCowan" hpid="Captain Cowan Captain Cowan">
      <NameTxt>Captain Cowan</NameTxt>
      <P>I have no very strong views: I just think my wording is better.  As a matter of fact, I think that, on reflection, the Army authorities would realise that anything that brings contempt on the Defence Forces should be punished.  The uniforms may change from week to week or from month to month, but the Defence Forces will continue. Anyone who brings contempt on the Defence Forces certainly ought to be punished, but I cannot see how you could bring contempt on a uniform.  If the Minister thinks his wording is the better of the two, I will not press my amendment.</P>
      <P>Amendment, by leave, withdrawn.</P>
      <P>Amendment No. 199 not moved.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PeadarCowan" hpid="Captain Cowan Captain Cowan">
      <NameTxt>Captain Cowan</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 200:&mdash;</P>
      <P>In page 116, Section 264 (2), to insert &ldquo;serviceable&rdquo; after &ldquo;any&rdquo;, in lines 40 and 43.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="234" /> This section deals with dyeing and conversing of uniforms, and so forth.</P>
    <P>&ldquo;If any person, except under and in accordance with a permit issued by or on behalf of the Minister (a) dyes, or receives for the purpose of dyeing, any service textile article or any article which he has reasonable grounds for believing is a service textile article or a converted textile article, or (b) converts into another article or receives for the purpose of conversion into another article any service textile article, such person shall be guilty of an offence under this section and shall be liable on summary conviction thereof to a fine not exceeding £10.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>Sub-section (2) of this section reads as follows:&mdash;</P>
    <P>&ldquo;In this section&mdash;</P>
    <P>the expression `service textile article' means any article of a textile nature issued to or for the use of members of the Defence Forces; the expression `converted service textile article' means any service textile article which has been converted into another article.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>I agree that if serviceable articles which are on issue to the Defence Forces are mutilated or dyed it should be an offence and, in fact, this section provides that it is an offence.  However, we must consider circumstances in which the articles have ceased to be serviceable&mdash;circumstances in which they are sold, circumstances in which an officer retires and brings with him parts of his uniform, circumstances in which an old greatcoat is cut down to a smaller greatcoat.  One often sees leather buttons on uniform coats that have been dyed.  If articles have only a very short life and cease, in fact, to be the property of the Minister for Defence, surely there should be no charge in regard to them.</P>
    <P>This section is so wide that once an article has ever been a military article it is still the subject of an offence under this section, because a &ldquo;service textile article&rdquo; means any article of a textile nature issued to or for the use of members of the Defence Forces. Therefore, once it was issued to or for the use of members of the Defence <Col N="235" /> Forces it is a &ldquo;service textile article&rdquo; and remains such <i>in sxcula sxculorum</i>, or while it exists.</P>
    <P>We ought to be reasonable.  We know that the country is full of service textile articles that at one time were issued for the use of members of the Defence Forces.  Every coalman you see around Dublin has an old Army greatcoat on him.  You see such coats worn at fairs and by people all over the country.  If we limit it to articles in use or in service, I think we are not doing anything wrong but if we widen it, as it appears in the section, anybody can be arrested and charged with having in his possession, dyeing or altering or converting an article that was issued at some time for the use of the Defence Forces.</P>
    <Speaker pid="OscarTraynor" hpid="Mr. Traynor Mr. Traynor">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Traynor</NameTxt>
      <P>Again, this is getting down to the basis of the thief.  We all know that there are people who would like to get hold of articles other than uniforms or things of that kind.  There are other textile articles which are Army property &mdash; articles such as blankets, sheets and covers of one kind or another&mdash;and which could very easily be taken out and dyed so that it would be almost impossible to identify some of them.  We must provide some form of protection, even in the case of uniforms.</P>
      <P>When I got this first, and read it, my reaction was that it was reasonable and I asked myself why should we not insert &ldquo;serviceable&rdquo;.  However, when I took up the matter with my officials, it was pointed out to me that the onus would be on us to prove that an article was serviceable.  I could imagine a long debate in court on the question of whether or not an article was serviceable.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>It is true to say, and I think it is a pity that it is true, that very large numbers of people are working every day in this city and in the fields throughout the country wearing uniforms which are State property and which they got, I feel, rather too easily.  However, that does not come within this matter.  They got these uniforms and they gave a certain amount of service.  They dropped out <Col N="236" /> and now these articles are more or less their property; they are not legally their property, but we do not make any very great effort to recover them.</P>
    <P>Here, we are endeavouring to deal with the type of offence where someone would take out a number of these articles in bulk, even old uniforms, and pass them over to somebody else who would have them dyed and disguised in such a way that it would be impossible to identify them or to state whether they were State property at all.  It is to try and stop that sort of thing that we have deliberately, I have been informed, framed the words as they appear in this section&mdash;</P>
    <P>&ldquo;the expression `service textile article' means any article of a textile nature issued to or for the use of members of the Defence Forces,&rdquo;</P>
    <P>&mdash;not any &ldquo;serviceable&rdquo; article.  I think it is a good safeguard, and I think Deputy Cowan would be prepared to agree that you must have a safeguard of that kind, as otherwise you will be placed in the difficult position, if you have to go to court, of endeavouring to prove that the article was serviceable.  In general, I think that we are on the safe side by leaving it the way it is.</P>
    <P>Amendment put and declared lost.</P>
    <Speaker pid="CormacBreslin" hpid="An Leas-Cheann Comhairle Cormac Breslin">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Cheann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>Amendment No. 201 will be taken after amendment No. 205.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OscarTraynor" hpid="Mr. Traynor Mr. Traynor">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Traynor</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 202:&mdash;</P>
      <P>In pages 133 and 134, to delete Section 300, lines 34 to 48, on page 133, and lines 1 to 26 on page 124.</P>
      <P>The purpose of this amendment is to delete Section 300.  I had this section inserted on the Committee Stage because it was not then clear when the Social Welfare Bill would be enacted. It has since become law and Section 300 is, therefore, unnecessary.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PeadarCowan" hpid="Captain Cowan Captain Cowan">
      <NameTxt>Captain Cowan</NameTxt>
      <P>That is the whole section?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OscarTraynor" hpid="Mr. Traynor Mr. Traynor">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Traynor</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="237" /> Amendment agreed to.</P>
    <Speaker pid="OscarTraynor" hpid="Mr. Traynor Mr. Traynor">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Traynor</NameTxt>
      <P>I move:&mdash;</P>
      <P>In page 134, Section 301 (b), line 34, to insert &ldquo;continuously&rdquo; after &ldquo;employed&rdquo;.</P>
      <P>The purpose of this amendment, as I already explained in the case of a previous amendment, is to make it clear that the section applies to a Reserve officer only when he is on full-time service.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PeadarCowan" hpid="Captain Cowan Captain Cowan">
      <NameTxt>Captain Cowan</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not like an amendment of the Electoral Act to go through without knowing what exactly it means.  May I take this as meaning that from the point of view of postal voting a member of the Defence Forces on permanent service will be entitled to vote by post, and, similarly, a reservist, on permanent service? Because it is an amendment of the Electoral Act its clear provisions should be stated.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OscarTraynor" hpid="Mr. Traynor Mr. Traynor">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Traynor</NameTxt>
      <P>It is to make it clear that the section applies to a Reserve officer only when he is in full-time service.</P>
      <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OscarTraynor" hpid="Mr. Traynor Mr. Traynor">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Traynor</NameTxt>
      <P>I move:&mdash;</P>
      <P>In pages 135 and 136, to delete Section 307, lines 49 to 62, on page 135 and lines 1 to 50 on page 136.</P>
      <P>The purpose of this is to delete Section 307, which is now also unnecessary, having regard to the Social Welfare Act.</P>
      <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OscarTraynor" hpid="Mr. Traynor Mr. Traynor">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Traynor</NameTxt>
      <P>I move:&mdash;</P>
      <P>In page 137, Section 309 (1) (b), lines 14 to 17, to delete &ldquo;(not being the Unemployment Insurance Act, 1941 (No. 3 of 1941), the Unemployment Insurance Act, 1945 (No. 23 of 1945) or the Unemployment Insurance Act, 1946 (No. 37 of 1946) )&rdquo;.</P>
      <P>The purpose of this amendment is to make some textual alterations in Section 309 consequent on the passing of the Social Welfare Act.</P>
      <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="238" />
    <Speaker pid="OscarTraynor" hpid="Mr. Traynor Mr. Traynor">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Traynor</NameTxt>
      <P>I move:&mdash;</P>
      <P>In page 140, Section 318 (1) (b), line 19, to substitute &ldquo;Part III&rdquo; for &ldquo;Part II.&rdquo;</P>
      <P>This merely corrects a typographical error.</P>
      <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OscarTraynor" hpid="Mr. Traynor Mr. Traynor">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Traynor</NameTxt>
      <P>I move:&mdash;</P>
      <P>In page 142, to insert at the end of and as part of the First Schedule the following:&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <table pgwide="1">
      <tgroup cols="3">
        <colspec colname="1" colnum="1" colwidth="10*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <colspec colname="2" colnum="2" colwidth="30*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <colspec colname="3" colnum="3" colwidth="10*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry rowsep="1">No. 2 of 1952.</entry>
            <entry rowsep="1">Defence Forces (Temporary Pro- visions) Act, 1952.</entry>
            <entry rowsep="1">The whole Act.</entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
    <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
    <Speaker pid="OscarTraynor" hpid="Mr. Traynor Mr. Traynor">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Traynor</NameTxt>
      <P>I move:&mdash;</P>
      <P>In page 142, to insert at the end of and as part of the First Schedule the following:&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <table pgwide="1">
      <tgroup cols="3">
        <colspec colname="1" colnum="1" colwidth="10*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <colspec colname="2" colnum="2" colwidth="30*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <colspec colname="3" colnum="3" colwidth="10*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry rowsep="1">No. 1 of 1953.</entry>
            <entry rowsep="1">Defence Forces (Temporary Pro- visions) Act, 1953.</entry>
            <entry rowsep="1">The whole Act.</entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
    <P>The amendment adds the Defence Forces (Temporary Provisions) Act, 1953, to the list of enactments to be repealed when this Bill becomes law and comes into operation.</P>
    <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
    <Speaker pid="OscarTraynor" hpid="Mr. Traynor Mr. Traynor">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Traynor</NameTxt>
      <P>I move:&mdash;</P>
      <P>In page 142, to insert at the end of and as part of the First Schedule the following:&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <table pgwide="1">
      <tgroup cols="3">
        <colspec colname="1" colnum="1" colwidth="10*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <colspec colname="2" colnum="2" colwidth="30*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <colspec colname="3" colnum="3" colwidth="10*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry rowsep="1">No. 5 of 1954.</entry>
            <entry rowsep="1">Defence Forces (Temporary Pro- visions) Act, 1954.</entry>
            <entry rowsep="1">The whole Act.</entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
    <P>This amendment adds the Defence Forces (Temporary Provisions) Act, 1954, to the list of enactments repealed by this Bill when it becomes law and comes into operation.</P>
    <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PeadarCowan" hpid="Captain Cowan Captain Cowan">
      <NameTxt>Captain Cowan</NameTxt>
      <P>I move:&mdash;</P>
      <P>In page 143, at Reference No. 6 of the Second Schedule for &ldquo;Commandant&rdquo;, to substitute &ldquo;Major&rdquo;.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>We are on the last amendment and this is an old topic.  The amendment is to substitute the rank of major for the <Col N="239" /> rank of commandant.  I know that in making a recommendation such as this I would be very strongly opposed by the Minister and I am not too sure whether Deputy General MacEoin would be in opposition or not. Since the Defence Forces were established we have had alterations from time to time in ranks. In the armies of other countries there are well-defined and well-known ranks of officers.  As far as our N.C.O.s and men are concerned their ranks and the ranks of the Navy follow the generally-accepted lines in regard to title and if one of our soldiers, a corporal, a sergeant, a company-sergeant or a sergeant-major meets a person of the same status in another army, he finds they have the same rank and there is not very much trouble about it. Similarly in regard to our officer ranks, we have general, lieutenant-general, major-general; we have colonel, lieutenant-colonel, captain, lieutenant, second-lieutenant and these follow the generally-accepted ranks hierarchy in all other armies.  We had in the Army here the rank of major and it was a rank senior to that of commandant.  It was found by experience that to hold the rank of major was considered to be in international gatherings of military officers just a step above captain.  And to that extent our officers who travelled abroad and met officers of other armies, who have been to schools and instruction in military colleges&mdash;in all of which, as we all know, they represented this country and our Army with the greatest distinction&mdash;but found that the rank of major as superior to commandant left them in an embarrassing position because they were considered to be a rank junior to what, in fact, they were.  Very wisely&mdash;I think it was at the instance of the present Minister&mdash;the rank of major was abolished and the rank of lieutenant-colonel substituted.  That aspect of it has been put right.</P>
    <P>In regard to the rank of commandant&mdash;commandant in actual fact is not a rank.  It is not what is generally known as a recognised rank.  It is a title or appointment and you may have, as you would have, say, a general a commandant of a military <Col N="240" /> college, or a colonel commandant of a military college or a captain a camp commandant, or a lieutenant-colonel as a camp commandant.  The word is more related to position or appointment than it is to rank.  The position of commandant may be occupied by a person of any rank depending on what the particular position is and the rank that is required or prescribed for it. In international gatherings of officers this rank of commandant that we have is not understood.  It is not understood that it is the equivalent of the rank of major in armies with whose officers our officers may be in contact for one reason or another, and to that extent it seems to me to be desirable that we should avail of this opportunity of getting our ranks into those internationally recognised.  We have over the last 30 years eliminated all other distinctions there were but we have left this old position there.  It has been left there because of its association with what one may term the Army that achieved our freedom.  The rank of commandant, as we know it, means a good deal particularly to officers of the I.R.A. in the past, and there has been a desire, I think, to retain that particular rank of commandant for that purpose.  But, where we have an internationally recognised hierarchy of ranks, I think it is just as well that we should follow the generally accepted trend, and that, in regard to the rank of commandant, we should abolish it as a rank and substitute for it the rank of major, because that is the internationally recognised rank that is equivalent to our rank of commandant. If this rank of commandant was peculiar to us because of our language, because it had a significance as a well-recognised and accepted Irish name, and if we use that Irish title or name as equivalent to the rank of major in another country, it would possibly be all right, but commandant is an English word which represents an appointment rather than a rank.  It does not seem to fit in.  I am availing of the opportunity of this Act going through to recommend very strongly to the Dáil that we remove commandant as a rank and substitute for it the rank of major.</P>
    <Col N="241" />
    <Speaker pid="GenSeanMacEoin" hpid="General MacEoin General MacEoin">
      <NameTxt>General MacEoin</NameTxt>
      <P>It is true to say that commandant represents more an appointment than a rank.  At the same time, in ordinary military terms, the word has a special significance in the history of this country which I think we should not lightly cast away. From time to time various suggestions have been made that this particular rank in the Irish Army should be changed.  I have never heard anyone suggest that it be given up and cut away from the other ranks until I heard Deputy Cowan do so to-day.  It is the first time, I think, that I have heard an old-timer argue that, because of the international wording of the various ranks, we should keep in line with them.</P>
      <P>I think that this particular rank marks our own distinctiveness.  The word itself has the meaning of a special rank, and, in various other Acts, it has been referred to from time to time.  It is the rank given for the exercise of certain statutory functions in the case of certain eventualities, such as war or civil commotion.  Therefore, because of its former history, I think it would be a pity to remove the rank from the Irish Army.  Very few people realise, of course, that from the inception of the Army the highest rank was that of commandant.  As regards appointments, it was, for example, Commandant Pearse.  The other leaders in 1916 also held the rank of commandant.  It was at a later stage that the title of general was added, but we had the rank of commandant of a brigade and commandant of a battalion.  Because of all that, it has a special meaning so far as our national struggle is concerned. I think it would be a pity to remove the rank of commandant from our vocabulary.  So long as it remains, it will be there as a memorial to the time that has passed.  For these reasons I think Deputy Cowan should not ask the Minister or the Dáil to alter that particular rank.  I say, leave it there as an honoured word in the ranks of our Army, and let us hope that all who will occupy or hold that rank will always live up to the responsibilities which it carries.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OscarTraynor" hpid="Mr. Traynor Mr. Traynor">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Traynor</NameTxt>
      <P>The outline which Deputy Cowan has given of the history <Col N="242" /> of the ranks is correct.  These ranks internationally, are as he has stated Before we changed the rank of major to that of lieutenant-colonel, there was a certain amount of upset when officers of this nation met officers of, say, the British, the American and, in some cases, the French nations because our major was the equivalent of that of lieutenant-colonel.  But major, generally, in the international sense of the word, was, as Deputy Cowan has stated, a rank next to captain.  The result was, of course, that lieutenant-colonels who were talking to our majors thought they were talking to officers carrying an inferior rank to themselves.  That was a source of some embarrassment to our officers.  It was for that reason that I altered that rank some time towards the end of the emergency.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>When it came to the question of changing the rank of commandant I must confess that, like Deputy MacEoin, I based my decision on sentiment, and sentiment alone.  I felt that it would clarify the position more between visiting officers if a major knew that he was talking to a major, and if a lieutenant-colonel knew he was talking to a lieutenant-colonel.  I think we have now created a situation in which the word commandant is accepted internationally as meaning what it is, the equivalent of major.  I know that the difficulties which existed heretofore do not exist now and from that point of view I think that a good job of work has been completed.  I am not prepared to accept the amendment put down by Deputy Cowan for the same reasons as those which have been given by Deputy MacEoin.  I think the historical facts connected with the rank, the numbers of soldiers of the Republican Army who died in that rank, giving service in it right from 1916 up to the Truce, would almost preclude us from ever removing the title of commandant from our Army.  It is possible that when we pass on, sentiment will not be quite so strong and the probability is that in order to equalise ranks internationally the title of commandant may be removed.  It is like a lot of things which still persist here <Col N="243" /> mainly because of sentiment; so long as our generation survives I doubt if that particular rank will in fact be changed.  It was not difficult to change the rank of major because we never had such a rank; neither had we the rank of lieutenant-colonel; sentiment did not therefore enter into those changes at all.  Speaking for myself, I would say that the only reason why I do not clarify the situation still more is solely from the point of view of sentiment.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PeadarCowan" hpid="Captain Cowan Captain Cowan">
      <NameTxt>Captain Cowan</NameTxt>
      <P>I accept that the Minister's approach to this matter is entirely based on sentiment and on the historical significance of the rank. There is a good deal of historical significance in the weapons that were used in the past, the pike and so on; those weapons played their part at the right time but, as the military profession improved and established itself, new weapons were introduced.</P>
      <P>The world is changing rapidly.  It is becoming smaller every day.  Officers of our Army fly to Sweden, France, Italy, Germany, America and elsewhere in the performance of their ordinary duties.  There is a well-recognised hierarchy of ranks in other armies and it is a pity that these armies should require a dictionary for reference purposes in order to find out exactly to what rank this Irish commandant is equivalent.  Officers from all over the world assemble in these staff and command colleges, or schools, and invariably the rank of commandant has to be explained.  This Irish commandant is equivalent to a major; he is above a captain, but he is not as high as a lieutenant-colonel.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Sentiment is all right in its own place, but the opportunity has now arrived of bringing our ranks into relationship with those internationally recognised.  I appreciate the Minister's and Deputy MacEoin's feelings and the feelings of all the old-timers, if I may so describe them, in relation to the title and rank of commandant but I do not think it would be right to let this Bill pass without having the matter mentioned and discussed so that our Army will at least know that the matter was discussed and that it <Col N="244" /> was deliberately decided that the rank of commandant should be maintained for the reasons stated by both the Minister and Deputy MacEoin.</P>
    <P>Amendment put and declared negatived.</P>
    <P>Question&mdash;&ldquo;That the Bill, as amended, be received for final consideration&rdquo;&mdash;put and agreed to.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PeadarCowan" hpid="Captain Cowan Captain Cowan">
      <NameTxt>Captain Cowan</NameTxt>
      <P>I would ask that the Final Stage be not taken now.  We have made a considerable number of amendments in the Bill and I would like to see the Bill, as amended, before I would be in a position to speak to the House in relation to it. I think on the last stage I am limited to speaking on the Bill as it is.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OscarTraynor" hpid="Mr. Traynor Mr. Traynor">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Traynor</NameTxt>
      <P>I would appeal to the Deputy to take the Final Stage now. I do not think that seeing the Bill in its final form will make any difference to the Deputy's concluding speech.  I am sure he has his views.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PeadarCowan" hpid="Captain Cowan Captain Cowan">
      <NameTxt>Captain Cowan</NameTxt>
      <P>I feel I will condense my speech if I am given time. If I have no time I may ramble.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OscarTraynor" hpid="Mr. Traynor Mr. Traynor">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Traynor</NameTxt>
      <P>May I put this point? We have this opportunity of utilising another couple of hours usefully, and we ought to avail of the opportunity, especially in view of the fact that between now and next week we will be getting the Bill printed and will be approaching the position when we can get it introduced into the Seanad. When it reaches that stage it will be on its &ldquo;run up the straight&rdquo; so to speak.  When we get it to that stage it will not have died; if we get it out of this House now it will live.  If by any chance we do not get it out of this House and this House ceases to be, the Bill dies with it.  It would be a pity if that happened, and from that point of view I appeal to Deputy Cowan, Deputy MacEoin and any other Deputies who might feel they should delay it a little longer to deal with the matter now.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PeadarCowan" hpid="Captain Cowan Captain Cowan">
      <NameTxt>Captain Cowan</NameTxt>
      <P>As far as I am concerned, if I get an opportunity of having a cup of tea, I am prepared to go on to-night; but I would prefer to see the Bill in its final print.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="245" />
    <Speaker pid="GenSeanMacEoin" hpid="General MacEoin General MacEoin">
      <NameTxt>General MacEoin</NameTxt>
      <P>There has been considerable amendment by both Deputy Cowan and by the Minister. Now this is a very important Bill.  I have purposely avoided taking much part in the Report Stage but, having listened to the arguments&mdash;arguments about which I am not too happy&mdash;I would like to have an opportunity of going through the Bill before we take the Final Stage.  I admit that it would be a very grave situation if the Bill lapsed through any fault of ours after so much parliamentary time has been devoted to it.  But there is also the other House to consider it and if they amend it, are we not still in the same position, unless the Minister takes the view that the Seanad is just going to rubber stamp everything done here? I do not think they will, because there are points in it that are bound to require consideration and very probably there will be amendments carried even by members of the Minister's own Party.  Therefore, I think we would not be losing anything if the Minister left the Final Stage over until Wednesday. I think he would get the Bill very speedily then.  The Seanad could meet on Thursday.  I think that would be more satisfactory.  I do not think there is any amendment we can make in it now.  If the Minister, however, is keen on getting the Bill through this evening, I will not prevent him from getting it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OscarTraynor" hpid="Mr. Traynor Mr. Traynor">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Traynor</NameTxt>
      <P>Looking at it from the logical point of view, seeing the Bill in its final form will not mean anything to the Deputy because we cannot do anything with it on that stage. It may be very nice to see the Bill, which has taken such a very long time to get through the Dáil, in its final form.  I do not want to force my point of view on the House.  If the House feels that it should be held over until next week, that is all right; I will not press my point.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GenSeanMacEoin" hpid="General MacEoin General MacEoin">
      <NameTxt>General MacEoin</NameTxt>
      <P>I will not force that either.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OscarTraynor" hpid="Mr. Traynor Mr. Traynor">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Traynor</NameTxt>
      <P>I am only thinking in terms of time.  We have a few hours still left and we could even adjourn for an hour if necessary.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="246" />
    <Speaker pid="PatrickHogan" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Patrick (Clare) Hogan">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>Adjourn till 7 o'clock and then resume?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PeadarCowan" hpid="Captain Cowan Captain Cowan">
      <NameTxt>Captain Cowan</NameTxt>
      <P>Say 7.30.  I can tell the Minister that I had thought my concluding speech would have run into something like two parliamentary days, but if I had time to look into it I could condense that very considerably. That is what I have in mind.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OscarTraynor" hpid="Mr. Traynor Mr. Traynor">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Traynor</NameTxt>
      <P>If you get two hours, will not that be sufficient?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickHogan" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Patrick (Clare) Hogan">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>Will we adjourn until 7.30?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GenSeanMacEoin" hpid="General MacEoin General MacEoin">
      <NameTxt>General MacEoin</NameTxt>
      <P>Perhaps the Deputy could condense his speech to half an hour.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OscarTraynor" hpid="Mr. Traynor Mr. Traynor">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Traynor</NameTxt>
      <P>So far as we are concerned, the Bill is finished; we can do nothing further to it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickHogan" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Patrick (Clare) Hogan">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>That is right.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GenSeanMacEoin" hpid="General MacEoin General MacEoin">
      <NameTxt>General MacEoin</NameTxt>
      <P>I think you could put the question: &ldquo;That the Bill do now pass.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PeadarCowan" hpid="Captain Cowan Captain Cowan">
      <NameTxt>Captain Cowan</NameTxt>
      <P>I would be in a better frame of mind if I had a cup of tea.  It would rather annoy me if I had to start on a two-day speech at this hour.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickHogan" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Patrick (Clare) Hogan">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>I take it the Dáil will adjourn until 7.30 and then take the Final Stage of the Bill?</P>
      <P>Agreed.</P>
      <P>
        <i>Sitting suspended at 6.25 and resumed at 7.30 p.m.</i>
      </P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickHogan" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Patrick (Clare) Hogan">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>Defence Bill, 1951.  Final Stage of the Bill.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GerardSweetman" hpid="Mr. Sweetman Mr. Sweetman">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Sweetman</NameTxt>
      <P>I understood that it had been agreed between the Parliamentary Secretary to the Taoiseach's office and ourselves that the Fifth Stage would not be taken until next week.  I do not know if the Minister was aware that representations had been made in respect of the matter.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OscarTraynor" hpid="Mr. Traynor Mr. Traynor">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Traynor</NameTxt>
      <P>I was not so aware.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GerardSweetman" hpid="Mr. Sweetman Mr. Sweetman">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Sweetman</NameTxt>
      <P>I think that if the Minister checks with the Office of the Parliamentary Secretary to the Taoiseach he will find that that was stated early on.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="247" />
    <Speaker pid="OscarTraynor" hpid="Mr. Traynor Mr. Traynor">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Traynor</NameTxt>
      <P>The Deputy does not want it taken, then?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GerardSweetman" hpid="Mr. Sweetman Mr. Sweetman">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Sweetman</NameTxt>
      <P>We had indicated certain reasons why we thought it desirable to leave over the Fifth Stage of the Bill till next week.  Is there any special reason why it should be taken to-night?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OscarTraynor" hpid="Mr. Traynor Mr. Traynor">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Traynor</NameTxt>
      <P>No, I expressed the reasons why I was asking for the Bill. I merely made an appeal that we would take the Final Stage now in view of the fact that we had this time available to us and if we did not take it the House would adjourn and public time would thus be lost, that as nothing in the nature of an amendment could be taken at this particular stage the viewing of the Bill in its final form would mean very little to the Deputies concerned, and that if the Bill was taken this evening I felt that it would not take very long, that the concluding speeches would not be of any very great length and we might then possibly be in a position to have the Bill sent to the Seanad next week.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GerardSweetman" hpid="Mr. Sweetman Mr. Sweetman">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Sweetman</NameTxt>
      <P>My only difficulty is that following the discussion I had with Deputy Ó Briain's office I informed my people that the Final Stage would not be taken to-night.  I gather that the Dáil will have to meet next week anyway, and in fact, on the basis on what there is there would seem to be considerable time next week to take the Fifth Stage.  If the Tánaiste is quite satisfied that that is a fact&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="An Tánaiste Seán F. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>An Tánaiste</NameTxt>
      <P>I would not like to leave the House under the impression that any agreement has not been observed.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GerardSweetman" hpid="Mr. Sweetman Mr. Sweetman">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Sweetman</NameTxt>
      <P>I am quite satisfied with that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="An Tánaiste Seán F. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>An Tánaiste</NameTxt>
      <P>If the Deputy is under the impression that there was an agreement&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GerardSweetman" hpid="Mr. Sweetman Mr. Sweetman">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Sweetman</NameTxt>
      <P>I am not suggesting that there was any bad faith in it at all, for a second.  I would be more specific if I thought that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="248" />
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="An Tánaiste Seán F. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>An Tánaiste</NameTxt>
      <P>If there is a substantial objection to taking the Final Stage&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GerardSweetman" hpid="Mr. Sweetman Mr. Sweetman">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Sweetman</NameTxt>
      <P>My only difficulty is that I informed our people that that would be the position, that the Final Stage would not be taken to-night.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GenSeanMacEoin" hpid="General MacEoin General MacEoin">
      <NameTxt>General MacEoin</NameTxt>
      <P>If you will recollect, I asked that it would be left over until next week, and I did put forward reasons why I thought it should be The Minister made an appeal that he would prefer to get it to-night, and, being in an accommodating mood&mdash;I suppose that would be the best word I could use&mdash;I reluctantly agreed, but I was not aware that our people had been told&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OscarTraynor" hpid="Mr. Traynor Mr. Traynor">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Traynor</NameTxt>
      <P>I was not aware either.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GenSeanMacEoin" hpid="General MacEoin General MacEoin">
      <NameTxt>General MacEoin</NameTxt>
      <P>&mdash;&mdash;that the Whips had agreed to postpone it to next week, and that being so I think that my arguments in favour of postponing until next week still stand.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OscarTraynor" hpid="Mr. Traynor Mr. Traynor">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Traynor</NameTxt>
      <P>If there is any objection then I cannot do anything about it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PeadarCowan" hpid="Captain Cowan Captain Cowan">
      <NameTxt>Captain Cowan</NameTxt>
      <P>It is better, I suppose, that there should be an agreement. I felt that it should be adjourned but in view of the Minister's appeal I was prepared, once we had a short break, to finish it.  I think I would have been able to finish it to-night if we had got going.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GerardSweetman" hpid="Mr. Sweetman Mr. Sweetman">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Sweetman</NameTxt>
      <P>I think it is better. Somebody might rely on what I told them.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickHogan" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Patrick (Clare) Hogan">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister ought to move the Fifth Stage now to keep the House right as to the order and then adjourn it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OscarTraynor" hpid="Mr. Traynor Mr. Traynor">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Traynor</NameTxt>
      <P>I move that the Bill do now pass.</P>
      <P>Debate adjourned.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Adjournment Debate&mdash;Government" RHead="Advertising Contract">
    <Title>Adjournment Debate&mdash;Government Advertising Contract.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickHogan" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Patrick (Clare) Hogan">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>On the motion for the adjournment Deputy Briscoe <Col N="249" /> gave notice that he would raise the subject matter of Question No. 7 on the Order Paper to-day.  This is the usual adjournment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RobertBriscoe" hpid="Mr. Briscoe Mr. Briscoe">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Briscoe</NameTxt>
      <P>I take it that I can go on for 20 minutes?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickHogan" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Patrick (Clare) Hogan">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RobertBriscoe" hpid="Mr. Briscoe Mr. Briscoe">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Briscoe</NameTxt>
      <P>Can I go longer than that to-night?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Minister for Finance (Mr. MacEntee) Seán MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Finance (Mr. MacEntee)</NameTxt>
      <P>No, no.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickHogan" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Patrick (Clare) Hogan">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>The Deputy has only the same time as for the ordinary adjournment debate.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RobertBriscoe" hpid="Mr. Briscoe Mr. Briscoe">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Briscoe</NameTxt>
      <P>I thought I could go on until half-past ten to-night.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickHogan" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Patrick (Clare) Hogan">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>Oh, no.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RobertBriscoe" hpid="Mr. Briscoe Mr. Briscoe">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Briscoe</NameTxt>
      <P>The question, No. 7 on to-day's Order Paper which I had better read, was:&mdash;</P>
      <P>&ldquo;To ask the Minister for Finance if he is aware that the Stationery Office advertising contract has been transferred from the contractor who has held it for over 30 years to a new advertising agency; and, if so, if he will state by whom the contract was placed and, if the transfer was made on the basis of a lower tender, whether the difference was such as to justify a change from the former contractor who has handled the business for 30 years and built up and maintained a highly specialised organisation specially to service this account and if he will further state whether the new contractor has given an assurance that he will hand back to the Stationery Office the whole or any part of the commission which would normally be paid to him by the papers carrying Government advertisements and, in this event, what assurance he has had that the new contractor will be in a position to fulfil this undertaking.&rdquo;</P>
      <P>The Minister in his reply said:&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>&ldquo;I am aware that on the recent termination of the contract for an agency for Government advertising in newspapers and periodicals the new contract was placed with a firm <Col N="250" /> other than the firm which had previously held it.  The contract was placed by the Controller of the Stationery Office with the prior approval of the Government Contracts Committee.  In the light of assurances sought from and given by the successful tenderer, it appeared to the Stationery Office and the Government Contracts Committee that this tender would be substantially more advantageous to the State than that of any other effective tenderer.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>At the outset, I want to say that there is a certain amount of criticism of the manner in which this particular transaction has been carried out.  I have stated that this firm held this particular business for 30 years&mdash;for 30 years and eight months to be precise &mdash;and during the whole period of the carrying out of their operations on behalf of the Departments of State concerned, they never received one penny by way of fee.  I want to say, first of all, that since raising this question, I have been able to get certain information.  I should like the Minister to consider how this contract was first of all terminated.  At the end of the 12 months' period the firm was asked to carry on operations for another month and the firm did so. There was a letter written to them on the 5th February from the Controller of the Stationery Office, in the following terms:&mdash;</P>
    <P>&ldquo;I beg to refer to my telephone conversation with the principal of the firm&rdquo;&mdash;</P>
    <P>I am not mentioning the name&mdash;</P>
    <P>&ldquo;&mdash;on the 1st January, 1954, regarding the contract for Government advertising in newspapers and periodicals and to inform you that it has been decided to extend the existing contract for a further period of one month.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>Then on the 1st March&mdash;it is dated 1st March but the envelope shows that it was posted on March 2nd&mdash;the following further communication was received by the firm:&mdash;</P>
    <P>&ldquo;I beg to refer to your tender of 4th December, 1953, for the agency for Government advertising in newspapers and periodicals and to inform <Col N="251" /> you that it has not been found possible to place the contract with you and accordingly the existing contract with your company will terminate on 6th March.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>Three and a half days' notice to a firm that has carried out Government business for 30 years!  They say this also in the letter:&mdash;</P>
    <P>&ldquo;I should like to take this opportunity to express the thanks of this office for the courteous and helpful manner in which you have carried out this contract in the past.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>I asked in the question to-day what assurances were given or what advantages the new contractor was able to give over the old one.  The Minister has stated that the matter did not come before him, that there was this contracts committee set up so that a contractor tenders for Government requirements through this committee. The idea is that there is not supposed to be any political influence and that the State is able to get the very best for its money.  Deputy Corish to-day, by way of a supplementary question, asked whether the assurances to which the Minister referred were included in the contract.  I want to add to that: if they are not included in the contract are they legally enforceable?  If a tender form is sent out to other people to send in their quotations, is it now to be taken that over and above what is specified in the tender form, there may be a certain understanding and that a person who tenders can have a private understanding with a particular Department of State to give the State some extra benefit not made known to others who are tendering? That is the first question I should like to ask.</P>
    <P>I have here before me a document which was presented to all agencies of this kind by the newspaper offices in 1927.  The <i>Irish Press</i> was not then in existence but the other papers&mdash;the <i>Evening Mail,</i> the <i>Independent</i> newspaper and the <i>Irish Times</i> issued a notice stating that these papers</P>
    <P>&ldquo;require that from this date, June, 1927, advertising agents shall not under any condition whatever split the commission or discount allowed <Col N="252" /> by these papers on advertisement orders and that such advertising agents shall not make any rebate either in cash or materials which would result in an advertiser paying a lower figure than that actually charged by these newspapers. Further, that each agent having furnished a list of the contracts involving allowance of rebate or discount at present held by him, shall undertake that on the expiration of such contracts, such allowance shall be immediately discontinued.</P>
    <P>Running contracts&mdash;contracts indefinite in regard to period of time must be determined at the end of six months from this date.</P>
    <P>Any advertising agent who fails to comply with these requirements shall be removed by these newspapers from the list of recognised agents and no longer receive the privileges now accorded them.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>There is a space then for a signature prefaced by the following paragraph:&mdash;</P>
    <P>&ldquo;We herewith supply the required list of contracts with dates of expiration and hereby agree to the terms set out in this memorandum.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>This was in 1927, and the particular contractor who ran that business for 30 years and who was then the contractor refused to sign this document. The company were presented on the 23rd November, 1932, with a letter from the Dublin Newspapers Managers' Committee which read:&mdash;</P>
    <P>&ldquo;I am instructed by the Dublin Newspapers Managers' Committee to inform you that unless you immediately sign the agreement of June, 1927 (which stipulates that advertising agents shall not under any condition whatever split the commission or discount allowed by these newspapers on advertisement orders, or make any rebate either in cash or materials which would result in an advertiser paying a lower figure than that actually charged by these newspapers) you will cease to be recognised as an advertising agent by any of the newspapers represented on my committee.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="253" /> Under these conditions all discounts hitherto allowed you as advertising agents will be discontinued as and from the 31st December, 1932.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>Now it would appear from that, that all advertising agents entered into this form of agreement so that they cannot possibly give an undertaking that they will remit to a Government Department, part or the whole of the commission which they receive, because if they do they will not be in a position to carry out their contract.  There is this honourable firm that has been for so long dealing with this matter and they wrote on the 4th December as they had written in previous years:&mdash;</P>
    <P>&ldquo;We enclose our tender for the Government advertising contract, period January, 1954, to December, 1956.  We also enclose a list marked `A' of provincial papers who are not members of Associated Irish Newspapers, together with a list of miscellaneous publications who may receive Government advertising from time to time.  None of these publications on list `A' have intimated their intention to present a `Split Commission' agreement to advertising agencies, nor have the <i>Cork Examiner</i> group of papers. Consequently the full commission on all advertising placed with these publications would become the property of the Stationery Office.</P>
    <P>The position with regard to the `Split Commission' agreement remains the same as it was in 1951.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>Now, Sir, that means that this concern, which previously handled this business, undertook to pay, and did in fact pay, over to the Government Department every penny of commission which they received from the papers not in this organisation and which disagreed with this method. They were satisfied with what they earned as commission on other business from papers over and above those contained in this list which I do not propose to read.  Then a new firm comes along which was established in the year 1946.  There appears to be something very peculiar in the fact that this new firm now holds advertising contracts from Aer Lingus, An <Col N="254" /> Tóstal, C.I.E., and I believe from Fogra Fáilte.  That for a firm that started in 1946 is not bad progress. If there is going to be some underhand method&mdash;and I use that phrase deliberately&mdash;by which these people will be able to monopolise Government advertising, there is no guarantee that they will be able to fulfil a great part of it, if the other papers carry out the threat implied in the giving of that undertaking to each other and to all advertising agencies.</P>
    <P>There is a section, Section 18, in the contract which I have seen which provides for the signing of a bond, if necessary.  The firm which had this business previously was always willing to enter into a bond, if called upon, but they were never so requested.  I take it that one of the answers which the Minister may give the House as a result of information given to him is that this new firm is signing a bond. The other firm was never requested to do so&mdash;its reputation and its behaviour were such that the Departments dealing with it never thought it necessary to ask that a bond be signed.</P>
    <P>What has been the reaction generally? I do not intend to bore the House with a lot of material, but I will read one letter which I think is very important, because the public are beginning to think that this decision is the decision of a political Party, when, in fact, it is the decision of a group of civil servants who did not pay the Minister the courtesy of consulting him, as the Minister pointed out when he said to-day that he had not been consulted in this matter.  <i>Independent</i> newspapers wrote this firm on 4th March as follows:&mdash;</P>
    <P>&ldquo;I have learned with deep regret that you will soon relinquish acting as Government advertising agent after all these years.</P>
    <P>I should like to say, having been privileged to claim your personal friendship apart altogether from our business association...&rdquo;</P>
    <P>I want the Minister to mark these words:&mdash;</P>
    <P>&ldquo;...that it will be difficult to find anyone who will give a finer service or act with greater rectitude in his <Col N="255" /> dealings with Government and newspapers.</P>
    <P>Through all the years I have known you, I have been impressed by the example which you always gave in this respect...&rdquo;</P>
    <P>There is a cut in the last few words and this is what I want to put on record so that the public will know.</P>
    <P>&ldquo;...and might well serve as a model for public life.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>Here we have one of our prominent newspapers writing that letter, possibly in the firm belief that it was the Minister for Finance who did not have that rectitude in public life which he should have had in relation to the manner in which this transaction was handled.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickHogan" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Patrick (Clare) Hogan">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister for Finance, as head of the Department, is answerable to this House.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RobertBriscoe" hpid="Mr. Briscoe Mr. Briscoe">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Briscoe</NameTxt>
      <P>The public will blame the Government or the particular Minister for any decision taken.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickHogan" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Patrick (Clare) Hogan">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister is responsible to the House and to nobody else.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RobertBriscoe" hpid="Mr. Briscoe Mr. Briscoe">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Briscoe</NameTxt>
      <P>I am asking the Minister to answer to the House and I hope he will do so in a satisfactory way. There are many of us here who, outside the House, as members of local authorities, have to take note of the manner in which our requirements are met by contractors on the basis of tender, and it has always been thought that if you leave the matter of dealing with tenders to non-political people, you are going to be free from all kinds of &ldquo;pull&rdquo; and can confidently look for service to the community from the officials dealing with them.  I say that if this transaction is allowed to go through and if this change is allowed to be made, unless adequate evidence is given to the House that the State is going to benefit and to benefit substantially from it, confidence in Government Departments in dealing with matters such as tenders will be very much shaken.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>If, for 30 years and eight months, on the basis of merit and reliability, you <Col N="256" /> have had from particular people the service you would expect, surely that meritorious conduct on the part of a commercial firm, at least so long as they are competitive, entitles them to continuity.  I do not know what other information the Minister will give us, but I have asked specific questions.  I want to know what advantages the State is going to get by the change to the new contractor which could not be had from the old contractor.  I want to know if the assurances cover the handing over to the State of part of the commission in breach of their agreement signed as recently as November, 1944, if they are not in a position to fulfil it.</P>
    <P>Finally I want to say that I have made inquiries about the responsibilities of such an agency and I am told that this particular firm has over all the years acted as adviser to the Department as to what papers were suitable for certain advertisements and kept the Department informed as to the circulation of each paper.  In all the years, their conduct has been such that they have felt it their responsibility to save the State money and not to embark on indiscriminate advertiseing for the sake of getting a commission. I thought at one time that the State paid, over and above the commission they got, a percentage for their services, but I now have the assurance that this firm never received one penny fee over and above what they earn from the commissions that came to them from the associated newspapers which paid them the commissions or part of them and that further they handed over to the State every penny of commission they received from the papers who were not bound by an agreement of this kind.</P>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Minister for Finance (Mr. MacEntee) Seán MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Finance (Mr. MacEntee)</NameTxt>
      <P>I find myself in a very awkward position in this matter because I have a great deal of sympathy with the contractor who has been displaced.  He has a name which is well known to those of us who remember Arthur Griffith and Sinn Féin in the early days.  It is a name which carried a definite appeal and there is no tribute that could be paid to the former contractor, on either personal or commercial <Col N="257" /> grounds, that I would not heartily assent to.  I have to speak here, however, on behalf of the Government Contracts Committee.  As you have reminded Deputy Briscoe, Sir, I am answerable to the House for the Stationery Office and for the Government Contracts Committee, and I think that, while there may be two opinions as to the coercive factors involved in the transfer of this account, they did what appeared in their view to be in the best interests of the State.</P>
      <P>The Government Contracts Committee are in a very difficult position. They are bound, whenever contracts are opened for tender, to place the contract with the lowest tender, provided they are satisfied that he will be in a position to fulfil the contract.</P>
      <P>Deputy Briscoe referred to the numerous organisations for which the successful tenderer is at the present moment advertising agent and the mere enumeration of them, I think, will dispose of any suggestion that the new contractor is not competent to fulfil the contract.  The question does, of course, arise as to whether he would be able to fulfil the financial requirements of the contract, to give effect to those assurances which on the figures as they have been submitted to me enabled him to quote a tender which was, shall I say, lower by some hundreds of pounds than the former contractor.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PeadarCowan" hpid="Captain Cowan Captain Cowan">
      <NameTxt>Captain Cowan</NameTxt>
      <P>Would not that be difficult in view of what Deputy Briscoe said?  It would be very difficult to quote anything lower.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>When the Deputy puts that question to me, he is asking me to pass judgment upon the manner in which certain decisions have been arrived at.  I think he will recognise that that might be unfair to two parties.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PeadarCowan" hpid="Captain Cowan Captain Cowan">
      <NameTxt>Captain Cowan</NameTxt>
      <P>I appreciate the Minister would be in a difficulty.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>Undoubtedly if the assurances which have been given by the contractor to the Stationery Office and to the contracts committee prove to be unfounded, then it is&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="258" />
    <Speaker pid="RobertBriscoe" hpid="Mr. Briscoe Mr. Briscoe">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Briscoe</NameTxt>
      <P>Could the Minister tell me anyway how can an assurance outside of a contract be binding on the contractor?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>I was coming to that if the Deputy had permitted me.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RobertBriscoe" hpid="Mr. Briscoe Mr. Briscoe">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Briscoe</NameTxt>
      <P>I am sorry.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>As I was saying, if these assurances prove to be unfounded, the financial basis on which the assumptions of the contract were based will prove to be equally unfounded and the contract will prove not to be as advantageous to the State as the contracts committee in their view believed it would be.  That is merely a case of mistaken judgment. I do not think that the committee acted otherwise than upon a fair basis.  I think they acted according to their best lights and in their opinion they did what was best for the State.</P>
      <P>On the questions which Deputy Briscoe asked which I think go more or less to the root of the matter, there are three which, perhaps, I will answer.  What advantages will the State get from the new contractor?  So far as services are concerned, I should say none.  In so far as those services will be provided at a lower figure the State will get that amount.  Are the assurances legally enforceable?  Well now, I should not like to answer that question very definitely.  Quite frankly, speaking as a layman, I would have doubts.  I propose to have the papers and the matters submitted to the Attorney-General to ask how we shall stand.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RobertBriscoe" hpid="Mr. Briscoe Mr. Briscoe">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Briscoe</NameTxt>
      <P>Hear, hear!</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>With regard to the question of a bond which Deputy Briscoe also raised, I should say that it was not necessary to ask the former contractor for a bond because he had been so long associated with this business and had given satisfaction from year to year.  With regard to the new contractor, quite frankly I do not see what value the bond is because he is a man in an established business, as Deputy Briscoe pointed out, and there <Col N="259" /> cannot be any doubt about his competence to undertake the work.  I do not see how the State can blame him if the assurances which he has given are not legally enforceable.  No contract was given for the bond.  My view is that I think it was a work of supererogation without very much binding effect.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RobertBriscoe" hpid="Mr. Briscoe Mr. Briscoe">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Briscoe</NameTxt>
      <P>Are the differences due to a hand-over of the commission?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>That is a matter on which, again, there is a conflict of opinion.  I understand that the new contractor takes the attitude that he will not have to forego any of the commissions which he would be normally entitled to.  I do not say &ldquo;forego&rdquo;. &ldquo;Retire&rdquo;, I think, is the word used. I do not think he will have to retire any of the commissions which he would normally be entitled to under <Col N="260" /> any existing advertising agency.  That is a matter I cannot determine.  It is one for the advertising agencies on the one hand and the newspapers on the other.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RobertBriscoe" hpid="Mr. Briscoe Mr. Briscoe">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Briscoe</NameTxt>
      <P>It is as consistent as reducing taxation and the cost of living at the same time.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not think there is anything else I have to answer.  On the question of the short notice, I regret very much that, having regard to the fact that the existing contractor had been asked to carry on for a month and then two months, much longer notice was not given to him to adjust his affairs.  Again, in this matter, the officials acted with a superabundance of zeal to save the State, as they thought, some reasonably significant sum of money.</P>
      <P>The Dáil adjourned at 8.10 p.m. until 3 p.m. on Wednesday, 31st March, 1954.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
</Debate>