<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE Debate SYSTEM "../Debate.dtd"[]>
<Debate DocTitle="Seanad Debate" Day="Wed" Date="2" Month="Dec" Year="1931" Vol="14" No="40" DateIrish="Dé Céadaoin, 2 Nollaig 1931" DateEnglish="Wednesday, 2 December 1931" House="S" CommitteeEng="" CommitteeIr="" SubNameEng="" cnum="2333">
  <MainHeading Type="Prelude" LHead="" RHead="">
    <Title>
    </Title>
    <P>
      <Col N="2333" /> Do chuaidh an Cathaoirleach i gceannas ar 3 p.m.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Auctioneers, Valuers, House and Estate Agents" RHead="Bill, 1931.&mdash;Joint Committee Approved">
    <Title>Auctioneers, Valuers, House and Estate Agents Bill, 1931.&mdash;Joint Committee Approved.</Title>
    <P>Message from the Dáil:&mdash;</P>
    <P>Dáil Eireann has passed the following Resolutions, in which the concurrence of Seanad Eireann is desired:&mdash;</P>
    <P>&ldquo;That it is expedient that a Joint Committee of both Houses, to be nominated in accordance with the provisions of Standing Order 61 (Private Business), be appointed to consider the Auctioneers, Valuers, House and Estate Agents Bill, 1931.</P>
    <P>That all Petitions against the Auctioneers, Valuers, House and Estate Agents Bill, 1931 presented three clear days before the date fixed for the sitting of the Joint Committee on the Bill be referred to the Joint Committee; that the Petitioners be heard either personally or by their Counsel or Agents against the Bill; and that Counsel or Agents be heard in support of the Bill.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasEsmondeBart" hpid="Sir Thomas Esmonde Sir Thomas Esmonde">
      <NameTxt>Sir Thomas Esmonde</NameTxt>
      <P>I move that the Seanad concur with the resolutions passed by Dáil Eireann.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasFarren" hpid="Mr. Farren Mr. Farren">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Farren</NameTxt>
      <P>I beg to second.</P>
      <P>Motion agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Finance (Customs Duties) (No. 4) Bill, 1931" RHead="(Certified Money Bill)&mdash;Second Stage">
    <Title>Finance (Customs Duties) (No. 4) Bill, 1931 (Certified Money Bill)&mdash;Second Stage.</Title>
    <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That the Bill be now read a second time.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. Johnson Mr. Johnson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Johnson</NameTxt>
      <P>Perhaps the House could be informed as to the reason why this Bill should be introduced and what its effect is likely to be.  I think, before we pass the Second Reading, <Col N="2334" /> we ought to have some information in regard to the measure.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ErnestBlythe" hpid="Minister for Finance (Mr. Blythe) Ernest Blythe">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Finance (Mr. Blythe)</NameTxt>
      <P>There is nothing to add to what I have already stated in connection with the Income Tax Bill.  The two Bills were introduced for the purpose of providing revenue to meet a substantial part of the deficit which is anticipated.  The remaining part will have to be found by some other method.</P>
      <P>Question agreed to.  Committee Stage fixed for Thursday, 3rd December.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Expiring Laws Bill," RHead="1931&mdash;Second Stage">
    <Title>Expiring Laws Bill, 1931&mdash;Second Stage.</Title>
    <P>Question&mdash;&ldquo;That the Bill be now read a second time&rdquo;&mdash;agreed to. Committee Stage fixed for Thursday, 3rd December.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Mines and Minerals Bill," RHead="1931&mdash;Second Stage">
    <Title>Mines and Minerals Bill, 1931&mdash;Second Stage.</Title>
    <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That the Bill be now read a second time.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="MauriceMoore" hpid="Colonel Moore Colonel Moore">
      <NameTxt>Colonel Moore</NameTxt>
      <P>There is one matter to which I wish to draw attention. Under the heading of Definitions on page 3 of the Bill I observe in section 1, line 38, the following words: &ldquo;the expression &lsquo;minerals&rsquo; includes all minerals and substances in or under land obtainable by underground or surface working.&rdquo;  The word &ldquo;substances&rdquo; seems to me very indefinite. What it actually means I do not know. It is used here and throughout the Bill. I looked in the dictionary to see what the word &ldquo;substance&rdquo; means, and I find that it covers practically everything. It might refer to trees, turf, gravel, stones, or anything above the ground or under the ground.  If this Bill deals with everything we have in this country above and below the ground I do not really know where we are.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I will give the Seanad some of the definitions of the word that I found in the dictionary.  The dictionary describes as a substance that in which qualities or attributes exist.  That is pretty wide.  Another definition is the existence to which qualities belong. <Col N="2335" /> That is not very clear.  The third definition is that substance constitutes anything&mdash;what it is.  The fourth definition is that it is the essential part of anything.  Other definitions describe it as body, matter, property, estate, foundation, ground, confidence, corporeal, material.  The word comes from the Latin <i>substare</i>, to be under or present, to stand under.  It seems to me that the word ought to be taken out and some better word substituted for it which would have some relation to minerals.  I am not questioning the object of the Bill, but that word seems to me to be an extraordinary one to use.</P>
    <P>In Ireland we have a lot of turf and the people depend largely upon it as a fuel.  That is certainly under the earth, and when turf is cut the cutters sometimes go to a depth of fifteen or twenty feet.  Are all the bogs to come within the scope of this Bill?  Are all the trees to come under it?  Will all the gravel that is used for building come under it?  In sub-section (3) of section 1 the following appears: &ldquo;references to working minerals shall include references to working carrying away, treating and converting minerals; the word &lsquo;surface&rsquo; when used in relation to land includes any buildings, works, or things erected, constructed or growing on such land.&rdquo;  Everything is included whether under or over the earth; everything comes under the heading of substance.</P>
    <P>If we look at page 8 of the Bill we will find the following: &ldquo;Where, in the opinion of the Minister, minerals are owned in such small parcels that they cannot be properly or conveniently worked by themselves and that by reason of that fact there is a likelihood that such minerals will be left permanently unworked.&rdquo;  That would cover all the turbary land in Ireland, where people have small pieces of turbary.  I would like to know if one is correct in assuming that all these things will come under the Bill.  I will not develop the matter very much more.  What I have referred to ought to be corrected or explained.</P>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasLinehan" hpid="Mr. Linehan Mr. Linehan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Linehan</NameTxt>
      <P>I agree with Senator <Col N="2336" /> Colonel Moore that there ought to be some explanation given as to what the word &ldquo;substances&rdquo; includes.  In the 1903 Land Act, which dealt with minerals, certain substances were excluded such as sand, gravel, stones and clay.  Under this Bill the privilege of dealing with those substances, which up to this the occupant of the land enjoyed, appears to me to be in grave danger of being taken from him.  That may not be the intention, but it would be well to have an explanation from the Minister as to what is meant by including all these things as minerals.</P>
      <P>There is another point in connection with this Bill to which I would like to refer.  What I have in mind is the reference to the creation of a new Board.  When we were under the British régime we had the grievance that the number of Boards in this country was far in excess of the number necessary for carrying on the work.  I would have no objection to the establishment of a Board now if I had some assurance, or there was even a prospect, that the Board would develop the minerals in the country wherever they exist.  That would tend to provide employment and would become a valuable asset for the State.  I know that this question of minerals and their development has been under consideration by our own Department of Agriculture and its predecessor under the former régime for at least a quarter of a century.  I am aware that a special section of the Department of Agriculture has the duty of investigating reports about minerals wherever they are found to exist.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>As a matter of fact, under the Land Act of 1903, by which the minerals practically became the property of the State, it was the duty of Land Commission inspectors to report upon any minerals which they might discover while carrying out their ordinary operations in different parts of the country.  Those reports went to the Land Commission, and I understand the practice was to transfer them to gentlemen who were dealing with minerals in the Department of Agriculture. <Col N="2337" /> I have never seen any reports as to how that work was carried out, whether any minerals were discovered, or whether, if they were discovered, they were developed.  I understand that this branch of the Department of Agriculture is still in existence.  It does not appear to be the intention under this Bill to abolish this branch or to transfer its functions to the new Board that we are to establish.</P>
    <P>This new Board will cost a good deal of money.  I imagine if there are three members of the Board they, with a staff of officials and inspectors, will cost something like £10,000 a year. Once a Board is established it is very hard to abolish it, even if there is no work to do.  The branch of the Department of Agriculture which has been selected for the purpose of dealing with minerals has not, so far as I can observe, been doing very much work, yet the officials are drawing their salaries.  It may be that the same thing will occur if we establish this new Board.  It may be that even though they will discover that they can do no good they will still retain their positions.  Those are matters that should be explained by the Minister. He should tell us what he proposes to do with the members of the staff already dealing with minerals, whether it is intended to retain them, whether the two bodies will be kept working together or whether one will be absorbed by the other.</P>
    <Speaker pid="OliverGogarty" hpid="Dr. Gogarty Dr. Gogarty">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Gogarty</NameTxt>
      <P>Under the British Government men were engaged for many years carrying out a most exhaustive mineral survey of Ireland. This culminated in the display in what was known as the Curved Gallery.  In that Gallery every single piece of mineral-bearing earth was exhibited, and the districts from which each exhibit came were clearly set out on a label attached to it.  The collection and classification of all those minerals must have cost hundreds of thousands of pounds.  It took many years to survey the whole country, collect various classes of minerals, often from the very remotest districts, classify them and subsequently arrange them for exhibit. Anybody interested in the minerals of the country had merely to go to the <Col N="2338" /> Curved Gallery.  There were to be found examples of Galway's mineral resources, the famous black marble of Kilkenny and numerous other interesting things.  I would like to know what has happened to that wonderful collection, which must have been worth hundreds of thousands of pounds.  It was a veritable mineral dictionary, and it has disappeared.  I, and I am sure very many others, would like to know where it is.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ErnestBlythe" hpid="Mr. Blythe Mr. Blythe">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Blythe</NameTxt>
      <P>With regard to the question asked by Senator Gogarty, I understand that various specimens which were formerly in the Curved Gallery were carefully packed away.  I have not been in touch with the matter for a considerable time, but I am given to understand that the stones and pieces of earth which were exhibited in the different cases and labelled were packed away with such care that it would be possible without any difficulty, when a suitable place is found, to re-arrange them in their cases.  The fact is that no damage at all has been done to the collection.  With regard to the cost of making that collection, I have no doubt it was considerable, but the figure was not perhaps as high as the Senator suggests.  I understand that no loss has resulted by reason of the removal of the collection, except that the various exhibits are not at the moment available to the public, and will not be until a suitable place is found for them.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Minister for Industry and Commerce (Mr. McGilligan) Patrick McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Industry and Commerce (Mr. McGilligan)</NameTxt>
      <P>I understand a point has been raised about some Board already in existence.  That Board, it is alleged, has functions very much the same as are suggested for the Board it is proposed to establish under this measure.  I know of no such Board with functions like these, and, consequently, I see no possibility of any overlapping.  The Board proposed under this Bill will have certain judicial functions in regard to the non-State mines and minerals, and certain small matters will be referred to it. It will have certain advisory functions in some cases and certain judicial functions in other cases.  The judicial functions will almost entirely follow with regard to non-State mines and <Col N="2339" /> minerals.  It is an entirely new Board with absolutely new functions.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. Johnson Mr. Johnson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Johnson</NameTxt>
      <P>Perhaps the Minister will give us a general statement relating to the intentions of the Bill?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasEsmondeBart" hpid="Sir Thomas Esmonde Sir Thomas Esmonde">
      <NameTxt>Sir Thomas Esmonde</NameTxt>
      <P>This question of minerals and their development was one to which my old Party gave considerable attention.  It was considered advisable then as now that the minerals should be regarded as the property of the nation.  I think it is quite proper that the nation should own the minerals that exist in the country.  Senator Gogarty made some inquiries about the geological survey of this country.  I am sure that is a matter about which the Minister for Industry and Commerce will be able to give full information. The Minister for Finance is sure to know something about it, too, because any survey of that kind entails expenditure. It may be that the geological surveys have not been sufficiently progressive. I do not think there are many minerals in this country, but whatever minerals there are they should belong to the State, to the people of the country.  In the undeveloped portions of the globe minerals belong to whoever finds them.  The result is that many fortunes have been diverted from the pockets of the ratepayers. I am sure many people would object to that as applied to the taxpayers of Ireland.  The Minister for Finance may be able to tell us how the geological survey of this country is progressing.  I do not expect they will find many minerals.  They will, no doubt, find some in Wicklow, in the North of Ireland, in Cork and some other places, but on the whole there are not sufficient minerals to make it worth the while of the taxpayers to monopolise them.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MauriceMoore" hpid="Colonel Moore Colonel Moore">
      <NameTxt>Colonel Moore</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister was not present when I was speaking. What I am anxious to get from the Minister is the meaning of the word &ldquo;substances.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>I understood the custom of the House was that Second Reading speeches, on the part of <Col N="2340" /> Ministers, were more or less taken as having been previously made, and that consequently there was no necessity for such usual introductory speech as is common in the other House.  The purpose of the Bill, leaving out the intricacies, the machinery and the details, may be simply stated in this way: under certain of the old Land Purchase Acts mineral rights on sale did not pass to the tenant purchaser. They were reserved to the Irish Land Commission.  That is a general statement which will cover the majority of cases.  There will be exceptions with regard to certain substances which did pass to the tenant purchaser as well as in regard to mines which were being worked at the date of sale. They still remain in a particular owner's possession.  The general result of the Land Acts was that mines and minerals not being worked at the date of sale passed to the Irish Land Commission. Under the Constitution, these lands are caught by Article 11.  In addition to these, what are described as mines royal, gold and silver, are held for the State.  There may be, in addition, other lands which were in the possession of a State Department. All these things are controlled by Article 11 of the Constitution, which reads:&mdash;</P>
      <P>All the lands and waters, mines and minerals, within the territory of the Irish Free State (Saorstát Eireann) hitherto vested in the State, or any Department thereof, or held for the public use or benefit, and also all the natural resources of the same territory (including the air and all forms of potential energy), and also all royalties and franchises within that territory shall, from and after the date of the coming into operation of this Constitution, belong to the Irish Free State (Saorstát Eireann):</P>
      <P>that is the complete vesting of ownership.</P>
      <P>subject to any trusts, grants, leases or concessions then existing in respect thereof, or any valid private interest therein,</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I call attention to that phrase because <Col N="2341" /> it is probably the one that will hereafter be most disputed in courts of law when actions affecting pieces of land come before the courts.  The Article continues:</P>
    <P>and shall be controlled and administered by the Oireachtas, in accordance with such regulations and provisions as shall be from time to time approved by legislation...</P>
    <P>There is the final proviso that the lease granted shall not extend for more than 99 years.  Up to date the State held a certain amount of mines and minerals in its possession which came to it either through the Land Commission or some other Government Department. Except in the case of the State Lands Act, which does not affect mines or minerals, no provision has been made in accordance with the latter part of Article 11 of the Constitution. No regulations have been approved by legislation, and it is to fill that gap in Article 11 that this Bill has, for the main part, been introduced.  Under it we want to get the approval of the Oireachtas for the regulations to be made for the disposal of mines and minerals which have come into the possession of the State.  That is the main reason for introducing the Bill.</P>
    <P>Part III deals with the leasing of State mines and minerals, and Part II with the establishment of the Mining Board.  As far as numbers and personnel are concerned and in relation to other matters set out it gives certain powers. Under Part III the Board may be made use of in a certain limited way. Under Part IV considerable use is made of the Board.  I now come to deal with the difficulties that have been represented to us as hindering the working of mines and minerals, owned privately, upon which Article 11 of the Constitution will have no repercussions whatever.  It has been frequently represented to us that owing to the fact that, say, deposits are found lying under certain lands that are held in separate ownership they cannot be worked: the mineral may be lying under one land, but the land which gives proper access to it is in the possession of another party, and owing to the difficulty of getting agreement between private parties holding <Col N="2342" /> land in separate ownership there has been, we are told, that lack of development that might otherwise have been expected.</P>
    <P>Under Part IV of the Bill we do seek to interfere to a certain degree with private property, recognising private property in land, but when we do interfere we surround that interference with a great deal of restriction.  Section 18 speaks mainly of the grant of mining rights in non-State mines and minerals.  The sub-sections which follow indicate the motives that would be behind such interference with private property.  The first sub-section states: &ldquo;Where minerals are comprised in or lying under land subject to a lease, exception, reservation, restriction, covenant or condition or otherwise incapable of being worked without the concurrence of two or more persons,&rdquo; then if there is a likelihood that the minerals will be left permanently unworked, the Minister may, in accordance with the provisions of the Act, grant to any person who has an interest in such minerals and who, either by himself or through his lessees, desires to work such minerals, a right to work such minerals.  Sub-section (2) refers to minerals that are owned in such small parcels that they cannot be worked properly or conveniently by themselves and must be worked under an amalgamation.  The greatest interference with the recognised rights of private ownership in mines and minerals occurs in sub-section (4) of section 18, and is phrased in this way:</P>
    <P>(4) Where, in the opinion of the Minister, minerals are not being worked or are not being worked efficiently and no satisfactory reason is shown by the person having an interest therein to the Minister for not working such minerals or for not working such minerals efficiently, the Minister may, subject to and in accordance with this Part of this Act, grant to any person who desires, either by himself or through his lessees, to work such minerals, a right (in this Part of this Act referred to as a mining (unworked minerals) right) to work such minerals.</P>
    <P>There is a notable difference there <Col N="2343" /> from the other sub-sections in two respects.  The first is it will only come into operation for the general reason that the mines or minerals are shown not to be worked or are not being worked efficiently; and, secondly, the lease in this case may be given to any person, whereas in the other sub-sections it will be given to a person having an interest in or adjacent to other small parcels and so on. Although that seems a rather arbitrary interference with private rights Senators will see if they read through other parts of Part IV that there is considerable preservation of the ordinary right.  There has to be, first of all, a reference to the Mining Board and to the report received from the Mining Board on the matter.  In considering that report the Minister must take into his consideration, first of all, the public interest: that the public interest cannot be served except by granting the lease, and secondly, he must satisfy himself that there is no other way of getting the minerals in that particular area worked except in the way suggested.</P>
    <P>That is so far as interference with private rights is concerned.  The exercise of such interference is subject to a great deal of restraint.  Over all there has to be consideration of the question whether the public interest demands it or not.  In addition to the power to grant a right to work minerals power is also given to grant ancillary rights in the case of a person who owns minerals and cannot work them because of certain difficulties. There are certain ancillary rights which may be sought and granted.  They amount to the right to interfere with property that may be standing on the ground beneath which the minerals lie. The ordinary ancillary right would give the right to a supply of water and to do the other things set out.</P>
    <P>There is a later section which turns rather in the opposite direction.  It is the restriction placed under Part V of the Bill which deals with the working of minerals required for support: where a person has the right to work <Col N="2344" /> a mineral and where the working of this mineral may destroy property that, for instance, stands above the mineral, in such cases certain restrictions may be imposed.</P>
    <P>The main point to which attention ought to be directed in the Bill is in Part III, which deals with the leasing of State mines and minerals.  It is not proposed to consult the Mining Board except in certain small particulars with regard to the right of entry and compensation. It is not proposed to consult the Board as to whether or not a lease should be given or to consult either House of the Oireachtas whether or not before the event that lease should be given on terms and conditions to be stated.  It is considered that no business in the development of mines and minerals would occur through such a procedure.  The right is given here, if the legislation is passed in its present form, to the Minister if he considers it in the public interest that he should then grant a lease, the only reservation being that the grant cannot go outside the terms of Article 11 of the Constitution.  It cannot be for a longer term than 99 years.  There has to be a return made of the leases completed in any half year after that half year has passed. The granting of a lease of State mines and minerals under the provisions of this Act will lie entirely with the Minister.  If he has to make a report then he will have to make it after the event.  Neither House of the Oireachtas can query the conditions and the terms upon which such a lease is given, or seek to vary its terms.  That is distinctly left to the responsibility of the Minister, which involves the responsibility of the Executive Council. That policy has been adopted because the only other suggestion that could be taken up in this matter would be to follow the procedure laid down under the State Lands Act.  Under that Act where leases are proposed to be made they are laid on the Table of the two Houses for so many days and the granting of them may be refused, if objection be taken.  We consider that procedure would not be suitable to apply to a measure dealing with mines and minerals.  It would hamper <Col N="2345" /> development if development is likely in the case of the mines and minerals in the country.  The distinction ought to be quite clear.  In the case of ordinary property a piece of land may be wanted for the ordinary use to which land is put.  The value of that can be estimated.  There is nothing secret about it.  It is quite one thing to lay proposals in regard to that on the Table of the two Houses, but it would be quite a different thing to ask a man who through his own enterprise and scientific knowledge has discovered that there are minerals in a certain portion of the country to make him come before both Houses with his proposals, to have these proposals bandied as between the two Houses with the chance of their being thrown out or of enabling other people to come forward and make a better offer on the result of that man's scientific knowledge and his courage.  We propose to keep control of these leases entirely in the hands of the Minister, making him give publicity after the event on anything that has to be done in the way of a lease relating to State mines or minerals.  The other portions of the Bill, dealing with the machinery and detail can be discussed on Committee.</P>
    <Speaker pid="OliverGogarty" hpid="Dr. Gogarty Dr. Gogarty">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Gogarty</NameTxt>
      <P>I would like the Minister to deal with sub-section (4) of Section 18 and to explain to the House the bearing of it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>That portion of the Bill deals with the granting of rights in non-State mines and minerals.  It has no application whatever to mines and minerals in the possession of the State.  This has peculiar reference to mines and minerals in private ownership.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OliverGogarty" hpid="Dr. Gogarty Dr. Gogarty">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Gogarty</NameTxt>
      <P>Can the State step in if there is an attempt to block development in this country?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>Under this section it is going to have that bearing.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnBagwell" hpid="Mr. Bagwell Mr. Bagwell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Bagwell</NameTxt>
      <P>There is not a great deal of mining being done in this country.  There are probably very few in this House who really have any first-hand knowledge of mining in its various forms.  Senators, therefore, will neither be very enthusiastic nor <Col N="2346" /> hostile to a measure of this kind.  In view, however, of the fact that we have got to pass the Bill, we take on ourselves a certain amount of responsibility. Legislation of this kind will involve a certain amount of expenditure. I listened very carefully to the Minister's statement.  What he did not appear to tell the House was the reason for this Bill.  If the Minister could give the House one or two examples to show that it is necessary to have legislation of this kind, then I think the House would give the Bill a Second Reading with a great deal more enthusiasm.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeorgeCrosbie" hpid="Mr. Crosbie Mr. Crosbie">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Crosbie</NameTxt>
      <P>I want to ask the Minister whether this Bill deals merely with the minerals of the country. What I am anxious to know is would it not be possible in case there was a discovery of such a valuable commodity as fire clay to have it protected. There are certain qualities of clay&mdash;I am told are of very great value&mdash;that have recently been found within the vicinity of Cloyne.  I am anxious to know whether these would be included in the term &ldquo;minerals.&rdquo;  I would be glad if the Minister would deal with that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OliverGogarty" hpid="Dr. Gogarty Dr. Gogarty">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Gogarty</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister has satisfied me by the statement he has made with reference to one of the most valuable mineral deposits that we have in Ireland.  There is not much china clay of any sort to be had anywhere. It is a rare commodity.  Some valuable deposits of china clay have been found at Portnacloy in the County Mayo.  I met a French geologist there who was of the opinion that the deposit was very valuable. Some American financiers came over to Cornwall and merged the three companies engaged in the china clay mining business.  The position with regard to china clay is that the demand for it exceeds the supply.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The reason that I put a question to the Minister was that it is quite conceivable that these companies formed in Cornwall would acquire Portnacloy for the purpose of keeping the large deposits to be found there out of the market in order to enhance the price <Col N="2347" /> of the Cornish deposits.  When discussing this Mayo finding it was estimated that it would take about £300,000 to work it thoroughly.  The deposits are deep and dirty.  A small harbour would be required for the development at the deep water port of Portnacloy.  This is one of the most important discoveries that have been made in recent years.  If any attempt were to be made by outside companies to prevent development in Ireland there it would be a very serious matter.  But the Minister's exposition of sub-section (4) of section 18 has satisfied me.</P>
    <Speaker pid="HonJameson" hpid="Mr. Jameson Mr. Jameson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Jameson</NameTxt>
      <P>Would the Minister say if oil is included?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator Bagwell asked the reason for this Bill.  Part III of the Bill has been required for many years.  I have had complaints addressed to me because legislation to effect the way of disposing of minerals outlined in Article 11 of the Constitution had not been brought in earlier than this.  We felt that it was preferable to deal with non-State mines and minerals as well as mines and minerals brought in under Article 11 of the Constitution in the same Bill.  There is an absolute necessity for Part III of the Bill.  Article 11 of the Constitution did grip certain property, but that property has not been disposable because the Oireachtas had not approved by legislation of regulations for the disposal and working of it.  My Department has had some 30 or 40 applications which we have been asked to register pending the passage of this Bill.  There are other people who desire to have rights granted to them in State property such as State mines and minerals.  I cannot say that these cases were sufficiently well examined to enable me to state that had there been legislation leases would automatically have followed.  All that we could do was to tell these people that they would be registered as from the date on which they wrote, and that the matters dealt with could be considered when the legislation we had in view was passed.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>In regard to non-State mines and minerals we have received a variety of complaints from people.  Some people <Col N="2348" /> have said that they have been unable to work minerals for the benefit of the owners and of the country because of the recalcitrant attitude adopted by some individual owner.  Cases of that kind will fall under sub-section (4) of Section 18, for determination as to whether the public interest is involved or not.  Other instances have come before me of people holding only a small portion of a mineral area who represent that it is not worth while embarking on the expense of working the mineral unless they can be sure that the whole area will be left open for them for complete development. There has been a demand for Part III of the Bill arising out of the fact that Article 11 of the Constitution is there. It always looked to a proposal of this type to deal with the disposal of the rights therein mentioned.  Cases have been brought to our notice in which it was represented that hardship had resulted in connection with privately-owned mines and minerals because of the absence of legislation to deal with them.</P>
    <P>Senator Crosbie talked about fire-clay. In so far as the Bill makes provision for the development of fire-clay I think it will be found entirely up to the Senator's expectations. Whether the fire-clay is in the possession of the State, or whether it is held under private right, in either event, on the proper conditions being satisfied, there is power, I think, to grant a lease to anybody proposing to work it. There may be a necessity for putting in restrictions upon people working certain clays so as to prevent them taking these clays out of the country rather than having manufacturing work done here.  That is not directly aimed at in this Bill, but it arises out of one of the clauses.  For instance, when a lease is to be granted under Part III of the Bill, sub-section (4) of Section 11 provides:&mdash;</P>
    <P>Every such lease as aforesaid shall be made subject to and shall contain such covenants, conditions and agreements (other than for the renewal of the lease) as the Minister shall consider proper or desirable in the public interest or otherwise and shall agree upon with the person to whom such lease is granted.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="2349" /> As a matter of fact, the clause, as drafted, is so wide that I think any restriction it is considered desirable to make in the public interest can be imposed on people who desire to avail of this provision.  Senator Dr. Gogarty's main point is met by sub-section (4) of Section 18, which relates especially to mines and minerals in private ownership.  Again, there may seem to be there a complete interference with private rights, but I would like to point out that there are quite a number of restrictions.  I do not think these will unduly hamper anyone, but will tend rather to ensure that justice is done as between certain parties.</P>
    <P>There has been a reference to the Board.  It is provided in Section 20 that &ldquo;neither a mining right nor an ancillary right shall be granted unless it is shown that it is not reasonably practical to obtain such right by private arrangement for any of the following reasons,&rdquo; and the reasons are then set out.  The fact is that when the Minister is considering the report of the Board he is bound to consider any representations made to him.  The whole thing is to be ruled by the one criterion: Is it in the public interest that such a grant should be made?</P>
    <P>Senator Jameson spoke about oil. We intended to cover oil, petroleum, and such things.  If Senators refer to the definition section they will find that the expression &ldquo;minerals&rdquo;&ldquo;includes all minerals and substances in or under land obtainable by underground or surface working.&rdquo;  I think that will be found wide enough to cover most things.</P>
    <P>As far as Part III of the Bill is concerned, we do not set out there even to be as precise as in the definitions, for the reason that Article 11 of the Constitution grips what are called minerals, but what &ldquo;mineral&rdquo; means under Article 11 of the Constitution has not been defined, and we do not propose to define it.  In any case that would arise, therefore, there would be the question to be decided, first, is the property in State possession by reason of the fact that it is what is <Col N="2350" /> called a mineral under Article 11 of the Constitution, and, secondly, do we give in a proper way the right to dispose of it?  That will have to await judgment and settlement by ordinary case law.  We think that the phrasing of the matter in Part III is wide enough.  We do not, by any mischance, leave out anything that may be gripped by Article 11 of the Constitution.</P>
    <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
    <P>Committee Stage fixed for Wednesday, 9th December.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Housing (Miscellaneous Provisions)" RHead="Bill, 1931&mdash;Second Stage">
    <Title>Housing (Miscellaneous Provisions) Bill, 1931&mdash;Second Stage.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="Minister for Local Government and Public Health (General Mulcahy) Richard (General) Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Local Government and Public Health (General Mulcahy)</NameTxt>
      <P>Following the circumstances from 1922 down to date, a period during which a considerable sum of money was put, by way of free grants on the part of the State, into housing, resuscitating the building construction industry, to make good some of the shortage in ordinary housing in the country, we are now introducing a Bill that turns our housing policy in a somewhat different direction, a direction, considering the amount of work that requires to be done and the financial resources of the country to which, in our opinion, our housing efforts and the moneys that are available should be put.  From 1922 to date the State put by way of free grant two and a half million pounds into housing.  Local authorities put into housing another two and a half millions, a considerable amount of which will be returned through rents. As a result of the policy of grants pursued by the Government, about £6,000,000 of private capital was induced into housing too.  So that during that period about £11,000,000 has been spent on the type of housing to which the Government has directed its policy.  During that time, as would naturally be expected, a certain reduction in costs has taken place.  The square foot cost of houses built in 1922 or 1923 would be between 14/- and 15/-. The cost of a comparable type of house at the present moment would be about 10/6, and in the case of satisfactory housing schemes, in areas such as Thurles and Monaghan, the cost has been reduced approximately to 8/- per <Col N="2351" /> square foot and in one case to 7/8½.  So that the costs have been substantially reduced.  During that time the number of houses that have been actually constructed in urban areas by private persons is 3,568; public utility societies, 1,156, and local authorities, 8,195, being a total of 12,919.  During the same time in rural areas the number of houses erected by private persons was 11,084; public utility societies, 178, and local authorities, 385, making a total of 11,647, the sum total being about 24,500 houses.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>With regard to the housing policy, statements have been made that the policy has not made any impression on the housing of the very poor or the housing of those who are in very insanitary areas.  That is quite realised and it was quite realised during the period of the application of the past policy.  But to attempt to approach the housing of the very poor or the clearing of insanitary areas and replacing them by houses for the poor working classes at a time when building costs were so high was simply to fail in our object.  By directing the policy to the provision of houses for the better-paid working classes and the middle classes generally and at the same time inducing capital to the building industry for the purpose of putting it on its feet again after the post-war stagnation we prepared the ground for the present policy.  The change, as I say, is brought about purposely, so that we move over to a position in which public moneys will be devoted to endeavouring to house the poorer working classes and those workers who are living in insanitary areas.  Private persons building within certain restricted dimensions have been given grants from 1924.  At the 1st April last persons were entitled to a £45 lump sum grant.  In answering certain questions subsequent to 1st April I said that we would provide the same grant to private persons in respect of houses that were built in the meantime and until this legislation had been passed.  So that private persons who have begun the building of houses since 1st April and will complete them before the end of February next will <Col N="2352" /> get a grant of £45.  Private persons beginning to build now will be given a reduced grant of £20 contingent on the local authority providing a grant of an equal amount, and private persons will get a remission of two-thirds rates for seven years.  That is a transition to the time when private persons will not get any grant.</P>
    <P>Criticism has been made of that proposal, that local authorities will not provide moneys to private persons. When you take into consideration the amount of work that has been done under the eyes of local authorities throughout the country and the improvement that is supposed to have been brought about by them, I submit it is not asking local authorities too much in the transition period if they realise that the work is valuable work that they will make a contribution towards the private person.  If the circumstances of the area are such that they do not consider it reasonable to put a burden on the rates for that purpose, then I think we must come to the conclusion that in that area, at any rate, public opinion has reached a point of deciding that private persons should not get grants.  No very great burden will be placed on local authorities in providing a £20 grant for private persons considering the extent to which building has gone on in most of these areas up to the present.  In County Roscommon they can subsidise building to the present extent by a rate of 1d. in the £ in the county health area.  In Galway, it will probably be 1s. 1d.; it may be less in Cork.  In places like Mayo it may run into 4d. or 5d., but in Mayo the Gaeltacht Act is working.  Ordinarily, local authorities may be expected to bear that burden where, in their opinion, the circumstances are such that private persons ought to continue to get grants.</P>
    <P>In the case of public utility societies, immediately before the 1st April last they were getting £60.  They will get the £45 grant.  That will be applicable to private persons building from 1st April until the passing of this Act, but for the purposes of this Bill in future a public utility society will not be a public utility society that was contemplated <Col N="2353" /> under the Act of 1924 when public utility societies were extended beyond the definition of public utility societies in the Housing Act of 1919.  In the Housing Act of 1919 a public utility society meant a society registered under the Industrial and Provident Societies Acts of 1893 to 1913, where rules restricted the interest on the grant to 6 per cent. per annum.  It is that particular type of registered public utility society that we intend to deal with in future.  These public utility societies will be given the same type of grant as will be given to local authorities building houses for the working classes apart from building them to replace houses that have been demolished under a clearance scheme. So that in future public utility societies instead of getting a grant will get an annual sum over a period of years towards the redemption of principal and interest and they may get 75 per cent. of the total capital amount required for building houses.  They may get that amount of money on loan from the State.</P>
    <P>In the case of rural sanitary authorities additional facilities in the matters of grants and loan will be given in respect of the erection of labourers' cottages.  Hitherto rural sanitary authorities got a grant of £50.  Now they will get the equivalent of £60, that is, if the cost of the labourer's cottage is £300, they will get an annual grant towards the principal and interest the present worth of which would be about £60 and the Local Loans Fund will be open to them.  They will get capital to enable them to carry out their work at the same rates as urban bodies have got it up to the present.</P>
    <P>On the urban side, the Bill contains special provisions for the clearing of insanitary areas, for the acquisition of derelict sites for the purposes of the Housing Act, powers to improve sanitary areas and extended powers to control insanitary dwellings.  The principal idea in the clearance area is that, having satisfied the Minister that if they make a clearance area they can provide out of their own resources for the housing of the people who will be displaced, the local authority may pass a resolution declaring a particular area to be a clearance area.  A clearance <Col N="2354" /> area will be an area in which that local authority have decided that all the buildings in it are in such a state that they must be completely demolished. A clearance area may contain islands of houses that will not be demolished. There may be in an unhealthy area certain houses that the local authority consider might stand.  These houses will not be properly regarded as being in such a clearance area.  A clearance area will be an area of these houses that are to be destroyed.</P>
    <P>The local authority prepares that order and the Minister after the necessary precaution with regard to the giving of notice to all authorities interested, after the necessary holding of an inquiry and after the necessary amending or modifying of the order, may confirm that order.  Hitherto, the courts could be invoked on the merits of the order that it was proposed to make.  Now the only approach to the courts will be as to whether the Minister has exceeded his powers under the Act, or whether anything that was required to be done under the Act has been left undone.  The compensation to be awarded in respect of a clearance area acquired by the local authority will be the value of the cleared site less the cost of clearance. It will be possible for a local authority in dealing with a clearance area to take any additional land which it requires for the proper opening out of the clearance area when it is being redeveloped. Compensation will be paid in respect of additional land so acquired in the same way as at present under an ordinary compulsory purchase scheme.  If the local authority deciding the area is a clearance area does not so acquire that area itself it may cause the owners to acquire that area, and if the owners do not acquire it the local authority can come in and acquire it.</P>
    <P>There are analogous provisions for dealing with individual insanitary houses.  The financial assistance to be given to local authorities in urban areas carrying out a clearance area, re-housing the people that have been disturbed or building ordinary houses for the working class is as follows: State contributions will be paid to <Col N="2355" /> municipal authorities for the erection of dwelling houses of two or more tenements (commonly known as flats or apartment dwellings) on lands comprised in or surrounded by or adjoining a clearance area, or with the consent of the Minister on any other land.  The rates of subsidy will be: 40 per cent. of the annual loan charges over a period not exceeding fifteen years, and 33? per cent. for a further continuous period not exceeding 22 years.</P>
    <P>The regulations made under sub-section (5) of Section 60 will provide that the cost of these flats for subsidy purposes will be limited to a maximum of £450 per flat and within this limit the State contribution to the expenses of the local authority is equivalent to 36 per cent. of the capital cost.  Suppose a flat cost £450.  The present value equivalent of the Government subsidy is £162.  Ordinarily it is contemplated that the State will bear 36 per cent. of the cost of such dwelling, that the local authority would bear 36 per cent. of the cost and that the occupier, in rent, would bear 28 per cent., that is, in respect of apartment dwellings that it might be necessary to build in central parts of large urban areas or cities. There will also be a case in which persons disturbed from an insanitary area or an overcrowded area will be housed in single family houses.  In the case of the erection of dwellings containing only one tenement&mdash;that is a single family house&mdash;for the purpose of accommodating persons who are displaced by any operations of the local authority under the Housing of the Working Classes Acts, the rates of subsidy will be 30 per cent. of the annual loan charges for a period not exceeding 15 years; and 20 per cent. for a further continuous period not exceeding 15 years.  The maximum cost of these houses for subsidy purposes will be fixed at £350 per house and within this limit the State contribution is equivalent to 24 per cent. of the capital cost. In the case of house building in that way exceeding £350, the value of the Government subsidy in terms of present value is £82 and the percentages borne by the different parties are the <Col N="2356" /> State 24, the local authority 24, and the occupier 52 per cent.  Considering the amount of work that requires to be done, even in smaller urban districts, in replacing the insanitary houses, the amount of work that will be done in this third class of house will not be very great compared with the other class of building.  In the case of the erection of dwelling houses for other members of the working classes of a higher paying capacity the rate of subsidy will be 15 per cent. of the loan charges for a period not exceeding 20 years.  The maximum cost of these houses for subsidy purposes will be fixed at £400 per house.  Schemes for the erection of houses coming within this category but which were undertaken between 1st April last and the passing into law of this Bill will get the equivalent of £45; that is, they get a subsidy based on 20 per cent. of the annual loan charges for a period not exceeding 13 years and fifteen per cent. over a subsequent period not exceeding five years.  A public utility society building houses in future would get the same financial assistance as local authorities building the third class of houses, that is, they will be paid a subsidy equivalent to fifteen per cent. of the loan charges for a period not exceeding 20 years.</P>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. Johnson Mr. Johnson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Johnson</NameTxt>
      <P>What is the equivalent value of that?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General Mulcahy General Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>General Mulcahy</NameTxt>
      <P>£45.  Local authorities up to 1st April have been getting £60.  They will get the equivalent of £60.  The local authorities building after the passing of this Bill will get the equivalent of £45.  The local loans that have been made up to the present to the urban authorities have been on an annual plan; in future they will be on the instalment plan. That is the reason why a bigger percentage of the loan charges is borne by the State in the earlier years when loan charges are high.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>As regards the assistance to private persons as it bears somewhat on our general housing outlook a few words perhaps are necessary.  Under Section 63, sub-section (3) (d), private persons building houses in urban areas with a 950 square foot area will get a grant <Col N="2357" /> of £20 plus £20 that the local authorities give as well as two-thirds remission of rates for seven years.  If they are building between 750 square feet and 1,200 square feet they will get no grant, but they will get a two-thirds remission of rates for seven years.  If they are building above 1,250 square feet a house not valued for more than £1,000 they get the ordinary five years remission of rates under the Local Government Act of 1927, but they will get an advance under the Small Dwellings Acquisition Act to the value of £1,000.  Very considerable facilities will be provided in future for getting capital to build houses.  The State will provide any capital necessary for local authorities, including Dublin city if it is found that Dublin city cannot in its own way borrow money at rates equivalent to those at which the State would lend it.  Private persons building a house up to a value of £1,000 may be advanced through the local authorities up to 90 per cent. of the value of the house.  The Bill provides that an advance may be made during the progress of building, but such advance will not be more than 50 per cent. of the value of the work actually done at the time.  Public utility societies will be able to get advances up to 75 per cent. of the total cost of their work.</P>
    <P>The main point about the Bill is that it changes the orientation of our attack on our housing problem and brings us to the time when the whole of our housing effort will be applied in the direction in which we are of opinion it ought to be applied, that is the housing of the poorer classes and doing away with the slum areas.</P>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMacEllin" hpid="Mr. MacEllin Mr. MacEllin">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEllin</NameTxt>
      <P>I must say, from a countryman's point of view, I am very definitely opposed to this Bill, because it seems to me that it wipes out all the assistance and encouragement that was given in the past in rural areas. As far as I can see, this Bill deals only with the larger towns and cities and while it is giving great consideration to those places I am afraid it has forgotten what are called the rural slums, and which are a bigger problem, in my opinion, than even the city slums.  As <Col N="2358" /> far as I can see the Bill seems to be framed around four points: the clearance area, the improvement area, the derelict site and what are called insanitary houses.  In none of these four could it be said that the Bill is of any benefit to the rural population, except perhaps from the point of view of insanitary houses.  Even in the case of insanitary houses I do not know that any benefits would be got under this Bill, so far as I can see, except the local authority is prepared to give assistance.</P>
      <P>The Minister refuses to recognise the claims of country people.  Section 63 gives £20 of a free grant for a house built in a rural area by a private builder, but that £20 is only subject to the local authority giving a similar amount.  From our experience of what local authorities are prepared to do, or, to be more correct, can afford to do, they will refuse to put any further burdens on the rates to provide money of this sort.  If we examine the relative positions of the rural areas and the towns and cities we find that the population living in one-roomed houses in the towns and cities is 138,808, and in the rural areas it is well over a million.  The number living in two-roomed houses in towns and cities is 168,897 and in rural areas 279,236.  In Connacht as a whole you have only 16,000 odd people living in one, two and three-roomed houses, while you have in the rural areas 344,000 odd living in one or two-roomed houses.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>If you take those figures into consideration you will observe that the claims of the rural areas are far greater than the claims of the cities and towns.  In face of that greater claim, what treatment is being meted out to the small farmers?  All the assistance previously given to private builders and to small farmers has been almost completely wiped out.  Under the 1929-30 Housing Act, £45 was given as a subsidy, and in the case of public utility societies the amount was £60. It seems now, and I make this statement subject to correction, that the operations of the public utility societies will be confined to cities and towns and they will not be able to <Col N="2359" /> give any facilities in future to the rural areas.  Consequently I feel that this Bill is a retrograde step because it completely ignores the claims of the country people.  Perhaps it is a further demonstration of what centralising authority in Dublin means.</P>
    <P>The Minister mentioned something about Mayo having received special grants under the Gaeltacht Housing Act.  On paper that Act sounded very good, but we cannot say that we have observed any great developments as the result of its operations.  So far the operations of that measure seem to have been very limited.  They have been confined almost wholly to the Western seaboard and, judging by the progress so far, it will be ten or fifteen years at least before the Act will give benefit to the people included in its schedule.  When I mention the schedule of the Gaeltacht Housing Act it occurs to me that it might be possible to introduce in this measure a similar schedule for certain counties. So far as some counties are concerned the people are living under wretched conditions.</P>
    <P>In Mayo there are people living in the towns, in one-room houses, to the number of 455; the number of people occupying two-room houses is 1,514, and three-room houses 1,388.  In the rural areas you have in one-room houses 4,255, in two-room houses 41,665, and in three-room houses 81,147.  It is obvious from figures of that description that there is great need for remedial measures.  Let us make a comparison with a county like Kilkenny. In Kilkenny, in the urban areas, there are one-room houses to the number of 183, two-room houses to the number of 1,824, and three-room houses to the number of 1,261.  In the rural areas in the same county there are 653 one-room houses, 5,675 two-room houses, and 1,874 three-room houses.  It is very obvious, when you consider a comparison like that, that counties like Mayo are entitled to some consideration.  There should be some provision made in order to take the people out of the practically uninhabitable houses in which they are living.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="2360" /> Great use has been made of previous Acts in order to avail of the grants given by the Government.  During the last five years there were upwards of 2,000 new houses built in Mayo.  If these grants are not continued in the case of the farming community I am afraid it will mean the complete holdup of progress in the rural areas.  I am of the opinion that this measure should be definitely opposed until it is amended to include some provision favourable to those people of whom I have spoken.</P>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General Mulcahy General Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>General Mulcahy</NameTxt>
      <P>The Senator mentioned one figure which I would not care to let go unchallenged.  I understood the Senator to say that there were 138,000 odd persons living in one-room houses in urban areas, and that there were at least 1,000,000 living in one-room houses in the rural districts.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMacEllin" hpid="Mr. MacEllin Mr. MacEllin">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEllin</NameTxt>
      <P>I am quoting figures from the census of population taken in 1926.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General Mulcahy General Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>General Mulcahy</NameTxt>
      <P>I think the Senator will find that the number is about one-fiftieth of that figure&mdash;less than 20,000.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMacEllin" hpid="Mr. MacEllin Mr. MacEllin">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEllin</NameTxt>
      <P>The figures I gave were taken from the census of population.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General Mulcahy General Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>General Mulcahy</NameTxt>
      <P>I think the figure of 1,000,000 the Senator mentioned should certainly be challenged, and if the Senator examines the figures once more he will find he was mistaken.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMacEllin" hpid="Mr. MacEllin Mr. MacEllin">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEllin</NameTxt>
      <P>Does the Minister not agree that the number of people living in one-room and two-room houses in the rural areas is as great as, if not greater than, the number of people similarly housed in the cities and towns?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General Mulcahy General Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>General Mulcahy</NameTxt>
      <P>The number of people in one-room houses in the rural areas is very much less than the number in urban areas.  The number living in two rooms in the rural areas is appreciably less than the number living in two rooms in urban areas; but the number living in three-room houses in the country is about <Col N="2361" /> twice the number in the urban areas. It is the figure of 1,000,000 that I challenge.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. Johnson Mr. Johnson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Johnson</NameTxt>
      <P>I have here some figures that may be helpful.  The number of persons living in one-room tenements in Dublin City is 78,920; the number in other county boroughs 11,097; and the number in the rest of Saorstát Eireann is 50,044, making a total of 140,061.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasFarren" hpid="Mr. Farren Mr. Farren">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Farren</NameTxt>
      <P>I am compelled to support this Bill.  I agree that the time has arrived when something should be done to build houses for the slum dwellers.  It must be admitted by any impartial observer that the 26,000 houses that have been built since 1922 have not solved very appreciably the real housing problem as affecting the people in the slums. I do not suggest that the houses that were built by local authorities from 1922 onwards were too good for the working-class people to dwell in, but I do say that the houses erected by the local authorities&mdash;and I am speaking now of local authorities in the immediate vicinity, the place with which I am most familiar&mdash;more especially by the Dublin Corporation, since 1922, have not touched upon the problem of the real slum dweller because of the fact that the rents charged for those houses were out of all proportion to what the slum dweller could afford to pay.  Therefore, all the Housing Acts passed by the Oireachtas and all the money allocated by way of grants have not touched even the fringe of the housing problem as we in Dublin know it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Under this Bill an attempt is made to get nearer to the problem of the housing of the slum dwellers.  This Bill is worthy of every support by reason of the inclusion in it of a section which gives power to local authorities to clear slum areas.  It is largely because of that section that I heartily support the Bill.  Those familiar with the conditions under which many people in Dublin have to live must be painfully aware of the difficulties that had to be confronted and the obstacles that blocked the <Col N="2362" /> path of the local authorities when they attempted to do anything in the way of clearing slum areas.  The Minister proposes to give the local authority power under this Bill to schedule an insanitary area.  Heretofore a local authority had power to declare an insanitary area.  They had power to condemn houses as being unfit for human habitation, but there their powers ended.  Under this Bill the local authorities will have power to declare an insanitary area.  They will notify the Minister and he will have power to enable the local authority to order the clearance of the area.  The local authority can then serve notice on the owners of the insanitary dwellings to take down those dwellings and clear the site. The cost of the site then will be the value of the land, less the cost of clearance.  This is the first real attempt made to grapple with that part of the problem.  Because that section is embodied in it, I feel myself bound to support the Bill.</P>
    <P>There is one section dealing with financial matters with which I am not satisfied.  The Bill proposes to induce the local authorities to build tenement flats.  That is being done deliberately and I think it is a blot on the Bill.  I hope before the Bill leaves this House the Minister will agree to a remedy in that respect.  I know it is almost impossible to secure a sufficient amount of land in the immediate vicinity of Dublin upon which to erect houses to accommodate the people living in the tenements.  There is, however, a certain amount of land available upon which small family houses could be erected.  I think the Minister should not persist in making the State grant less in the case of the small house as against the flat.</P>
    <P>Let us assume that the municipality of Dublin decides upon a clearance scheme in respect of an insanitary area. They must satisfy the Minister that they propose to clear the area.  All the preliminaries are gone through.  They want to re-house the people who are taken out of the insanitary area that is to be cleared.  They must have virgin land somewhere in order to erect houses for these people.  Before they <Col N="2363" /> get permission they have to prove to the Minister's satisfaction that they propose to re-house the people taken out of the insanitary area and therefore there must be houses built on virgin land.  Instead of building flats the municipality may find it cheaper to build dwellings of a small type.  I think on examination that will be found to be correct.  The Minister will not deny that certain flats were built in Dublin within recent years and it cost more to build a flat than it would cost to build a house.</P>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General Mulcahy General Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>General Mulcahy</NameTxt>
      <P>Very nearly as much.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasFarren" hpid="Mr. Farren Mr. Farren">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Farren</NameTxt>
      <P>Not very nearly at all, but it actually cost more.  I think the figures will prove that, and I am sure the Minister knows the flats to which I am referring.  The flats are very fine, no doubt, but I have yet to meet the decent man and woman who would not prefer having their own little house to any tenement flat.  From every point of view the small house is more desirable.  That is the result of our experience in Dublin with regard to the people who are removed from the dirty slums into small houses of their own. Even the President has referred to the change in the habits of the people who were moved from tenement dwellings to small houses.  Anyone who knows these people cannot fail to observe the great change for the better since they were taken from the slums and put into their own little homes.  The woman who is put into one of these little houses realises that the responsibility is upon her to keep it in proper order and everything pertaining to the careful management of the home is her concern.  There is no reason at all why there should be such a distinction as is made in the Bill between the proposed flats and the small houses.  No doubt there must be flats built, but in certain cases it would be cheaper to build small houses.  I appeal to the Minister not to allow the Bill to go through without remedying the distinction that is made in Section 64.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>With regard to the question of the reduction of the subsidy to speculative builders or to people anxious to build their own houses, I think those people <Col N="2364" /> have had ample opportunity since 1924 to take advantage of the very decent terms that were offered.  They got a very fair innings.  The poor people have had to wait in the meantime.  I think the Government is well advised to take off a slice in order to endeavour to meet the real housing problem which concerns the poor people who have to reside in the slums.</P>
    <P>I am not dealing with this Bill from the same point of view as Senator MacEllin dealt with it.  He concentrated upon rural housing conditions.  I am speaking only for the area with which I am familiar.  I do know, however, that in certain cities and towns in Ireland the housing conditions are nearly as bad as they are in Dublin.  I am dealing with the position of Dublin City principally.  I trust the Minister will agree to alter the arrangement as it exists in the Bill between the flat and the small house.  If he does that I think that on the whole the Bill will be considered as fairly satisfactory.  It does not go all the distance that Senators would like, but I suppose we have to be satisfied with small mercies. The Bill certainly goes a long way with regard to the clearing of sites, and that is decidedly a step in the right direction.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JosephConnolly" hpid="Mr. Connolly Mr. Connolly">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Connolly</NameTxt>
      <P>I also wish to support this Bill.  I feel it is a desirable move in the right direction.  I would like, however, to raise one or two points in connection with it.  I have every sympathy with Senator Farren's attitude with regard to small houses as against flats.  I would like to see small houses encouraged rather than big apartment dwellings.  It is to be assumed that we will have these large tenements.  I wonder would the Minister consider any suggestion relative to what has been adopted in other countries?  In Holland they have this difficulty with regard to slums. They found, what might or might not be found in Ireland, that slum dwellers in many cases going into apartment houses and not being used to modern conveniences in their previous dwellings, frequently do not avail themselves to the full of the benefits that the new apartment houses offer.  The <Col N="2365" /> system was adopted in Holland of having an inspection carried out and a certain amount of education was imparted relative to the use of the various facilities offered in the new dwellings.</P>
      <P>I do not know whether there is much in the idea or whether sensitive Irish people would resent a local authority appointing such instructors or inspectors. It has been the experience of property-owners that in some cases baths were used as wash tubs.  Those of us who have experience of small house property know that the maintenance of the sanitary arrangements in these small houses is a very big source of loss to the owner, and often an otherwise good house is rendered unhygienic and insanitary.  I offer that suggestion for all it is worth, and I would like to hear the Minister's views upon the matter.</P>
      <P>I wish to ask the Minister if, in working out the grants and subsidies, the officials in his Department have attempted to work out any schedule of what would be the economic rent under all the conditions embodied in the Bill for various types of houses, either apartment houses or small single houses.  I think that would be very helpful to us when we are considering the Bill in Committee.  It would be well to know, for instance, that under this arrangement of a subsidy by the State and a grant by the local authorities we could provide a house of three rooms and a kitchen for a family at a rent that would not exceed 5s., 6s., 7s., or 8s.  We would then have an idea of the extent to which, under this legislation, we can produce a dwelling which the average labouring man in Dublin or elsewhere could afford to occupy.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I have every sympathy with the points raised by Senator MacEllin, but I am not in sympathy with him to the extent that I would be prepared in any way to hold up the operation of this measure.  I feel that the housing problem in this State is one that must be faced as quickly as possible.  I know that in the rural districts, and, what is worse, in the small towns, the housing conditions are in many cases extremely bad, to say the least of it. <Col N="2366" /> I think the time has passed when subsidies ought to be offered to speculative builders.  It seems to me if there is any subsidy going to be provided, either by the State or by the local authority, it should not be passed on to private ownership.  It is almost inevitable if a speculative builder, or even a private owner building for his own convenience, is afforded this subsidy that it will simply become a profit factor in the development of his building schemes, and that should not be so.  I think any houses that are going to be subsidised by the State or by the local authority should be connected with some public scheme and be either State or locally-owned property.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JohnKeaneBart" hpid="Sir John Keane Sir John Keane">
      <NameTxt>Sir John Keane</NameTxt>
      <P>It was my intention to ask, like the last speaker, that we should be given some idea of what rents tenant occupiers will be asked to pay so that we can judge whether they will be fairly economic rents.  There is one point in the Bill to which I would like to draw attention.  I do so not in any hostile spirit.  It is with regard to clearing areas.  In a housing scheme of which I had experience it was found expedient not to clear the whole area straight away.  I do not know if that is possible under this Bill. It was found convenient to clear the area piecemeal, to keep occupiers in other portions of the area so as to make the demands on alternative housing as light as possible.  The chief difficulty is the alternative housing, but with the resources of the State behind the scheme I do not see why alternative housing should be an insuperable matter.  We had experience during the Great War of hutments being utilised for the purpose of housing people and they were found satisfactory.  There might be, for instance, a continual use of small huts of that description, a sort of revolving scheme under which these temporary buildings could be placed on a temporary site and could be used for the accommodation of families during the process of rebuilding.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I hope the Minister will consider the point as to whether it would be convenient to acquire the whole area or acquire only portions at a time in view <Col N="2367" /> of the difficulty of alternative housing during the transition period.  I am also anxious to know if the Minister could not give preference to public utility societies in the matter of financial assistance, preference over local authorities, because there is a very great necessity for the human touch in regard to occupiers.  I think everybody will agree that where there is a large voluntary element, such as you find in public utility societies, they will be much more sympathetic and have much more influence with the tenants. They will have a more pleasant way of dealing with personal difficulties. In the matter of rent collecting, they do not approach the tenants in the spirit of the ordinary rent collector with the power of the law always to the forefront; they will collect the rents, having due regard to the difficulties and the personal positions of the tenants.  It is very necessary, if there is going to be full social benefit coming from these schemes, that the human touch should be present, and I do not know that you will get it in the same way from the ordinary official rate collector as you will from the workers on behalf of the public utility societies.</P>
    <P>With regard to the clearance of areas, I do not think it is fair that the owner of dwellings pronounced insanitary should be asked to be out of pocket in the matter of the cost of clearance.  After all, he is entirely in the hands of the authorities with regard to what may be deemed insanitary. If the Minister wishes to set a high standard a certain amount of injustice may creep in.  There might, for instance, be dwellings which none of us, perhaps, might like to live in, but which at the same time are not quite as bad as they might be.  These might be regarded as insanitary and the owner would have to bear the expense of clearing them.  I think the Government should be satisfied with the acquisition of the premises, their demolition, compensation and site value.  It must be remembered that the owner is making very big sacrifices. I do not stand up to defend the owner of insanitary property, but I wish to emphasise that on the question <Col N="2368" /> of what is insanitary he is entirely in the hands of the local authorities.  If he is in the hands of some of the medical officers of health, I am indeed sorry for him.  Some of them come hot-foot from their schools of hygiene with peculiar ideas as to what is insanitary. To them everything is insanitary that smells.</P>
    <P>I think as we are committed to a very considerable amount of socialism on this housing question&mdash; it is quite impossible as housing costs are so high for the matter to be handled by private enterprise&mdash;this is certainly a wise and a good direction in which this socialistic policy should be applied.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JanePower" hpid="Mrs. Wyse Power Mrs. Wyse Power">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Wyse Power</NameTxt>
      <P>I think everyone must agree that this is a genuine attempt to deal with the housing of the very poor who can only pay a few shillings a week rent.  Section 4 is one of the most interesting sections in the Bill.  Under it utility and philanthropic societies can take up a good house&mdash;it may not be suitable owing to the amenities surrounding it for a number of people&mdash;and have an advance of some hundreds of pounds from the Department to put it in repair.  That can occur in the case of a number of old Georgian houses.  Water and sanitary arrangements can be put on each landing. We have had a very good example of that kind of work in the City of Dublin.  I hope it is going to be followed in this Bill and that this section will be availed of.  A social scheme of that kind has I think been undertaken by a society up around Summerhill. The society took some houses there. They were not in very good repair. They put water and other accommodation in on the landings and set the houses to decent people.  I think they have been able to get their own money back out of the scheme, but whether it has been able to pay interest on the money or not I do not know.  Some of those associated with the work have told me that they have not been out of pocket as a result of carrying out that very good class of work.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Help is now going to be given on a larger scale under this Bill.  Had what is being proposed under this Bill been done fifteen or sixteen years ago quite <Col N="2369" /> a number of magnificent old houses would have been saved from falling into disrepair.  That is particularly true of the north side of the city.  Under a scheme such as is now proposed much valuable work in that direction could have been done around Gloucester Street and Gardiner Street.  Many of these houses might have been saved from becoming tenements.  I agree with Senator Farren that this is a good Bill for those who can only afford to pay a few shillings a week rent.  Everyone must wish to see these people in clean decent dwellings.  There are reasons, as Senators know well, why it would not be possible to place certain classes of people in separate dwellings. Most of these people can only afford to pay 2/6 and 3/- a week, and everyone knows it is not possible to build houses for that class of person.  Another reason is that many of these poor workers must live near their work.  Many of them find employment in some of the larger hotels and in other places where it is absolutely essential for them to be at their work at 5 or 6 o'clock in the morning.  Decent tenement flats which could be let at a rent of a few shillings a week would be of enormous advantage to people so circumstanced.  Those who can afford to pay more can avail of the houses built on virgin soil.  I think that the provision of a good type of tenement flat is a serious want in the City of Dublin.  I hope that problem will be tackled at a very early date.</P>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasForan" hpid="Mr. Foran Mr. Foran">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Foran</NameTxt>
      <P>I must congratulate Senator Sir John Keane on seeing the light even at this late hour of the day.  I have been a socialist all my life.  The Senator is a convinced one now, and believes that this housing question can only be solved along socialistic lines.  I am in agreement with him on that.  I think that no matter what opinions people may hold everyone will welcome the attempts made to solve the awful housing conditions that exist in parts of this country and particularly in this city.  A commission some few years ago placed it on record that only in Constantinople could worse slums be found than in the City of Dublin.  It is not many years since <Col N="2370" /> the Commission made that report. The Corporation made great efforts to do away with that condition of things, but its efforts have made very little impression on the slum problem as it exists in this city.  There are 30,000 families living in one-roomed dwellings in this city, and 2,000 living in cellar dwellings.  The Dublin Corporation cannot find the money necessary to house these people properly&mdash;to remove them from their present horrible, insanitary conditions.</P>
      <P>It is the great desire of every one of these people to get out of these slums so that their children may be reared up under decent conditions.  I cannot emphasise that better than by relating what happened a few weeks ago when the mother of a family living in a cellar dwelling received the announcement that a sweep ticket purchased by her husband had drawn a horse.  Her first exclamation was not that she would buy a motor car or do anything like that, but it was this: Thank God we can now get a little house for ourselves.  That expression of thankfulness on the part of that woman reflects the mind of those who live in these slum dwellings. I submit that we cannot solve the slum problem on borrowed money. That is out of the question.  Borrowed money in the case of an ordinary house represents a weekly rental of ten shillings, allowing for interest and sinking fund charges.  The average slum dweller could not afford to pay that rent.  I would like to put this to the Minister: If one and a half million pounds were placed at his disposal free of interest for a period of four years what effect, in his opinion, would that have on the slum problem in this country?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General Mulcahy General Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>General Mulcahy</NameTxt>
      <P>Would you have to give it back at the end of four years?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasForan" hpid="Mr. Foran Mr. Foran">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Foran</NameTxt>
      <P>No, to have it handed over free gratis.  One and a half million pounds free of interest for a period of four years.  I know where that money could be got.  I know that it would be serving a more useful purpose than it is at present although I have no objection to the purpose it is serving now.  I believe it is well spent, <Col N="2371" /> but I think it could be better spent by preventing disease than by attempting to cure it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeamusRobinson" hpid="Mr. Robinson Mr. Robinson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Robinson</NameTxt>
      <P>I think it is a fair criticism of the Bill to say that the initiative in connection with it is left entirely too much in the hands of other people.  The scheme of the Bill depends too much on the Local Government Department and on speculative or private builders.  The local bodies are supposed to be the most suitable people to deal with this housing problem.  I do not quite agree with that.  This is not so much a housing problem as a menace.  Therefore, it ought to be treated by the central Government as a menace&mdash;as an outside menace would be treated. The Bill is more or less intended to clear away some of the slum areas.  I agree with the last speaker that it will do practically nothing in that respect, for the reason that the majority of the people there cannot afford to pay a higher rent than two or three shillings a week.  That indicates the difficulty of the problem.  I would like to know whether the Minister has considered what is to be done with the people living in an area in respect of which a clearance order is made.  How are they going to find temporary accommodation? Surely some place will be required to put these people in before you clear an area of the inhabitants living there.  I do not think it will be possible to carry out that part of the measure.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>In view of the magnitude of the problem that has to be dealt with, the amount of money provided is infinitesimal.  I referred earlier to an outside menace.  If we had such a thing threatening the country I am sure there would be no difficulty in raising £40,000,000 or even £100,000,000 to deal with it.  Here you have an internal menace and coupled with it unemployment.  It may be asked, where are we to get the £40,000,000 or the £100,000,000 required to deal with it?  I have a solution which I should say is my own, and I put it forward though it may be that no one will back me up.  I have an idea that the credit of the country is money.  It is really <Col N="2372" /> nothing else.  What is that credit? It is all that we have and all that we can produce.  Senators may contradict my statement, but I think that our credit is worth anything up to £1,000,000,000.  The British people owe twice that amount.  Surely we ought to be able to find £100,000,000&mdash;in other words, ten years' purchase of what our credit is worth.  If we can so arrange it that we shall not have to issue script it will be so much the better.</P>
    <P>Unfortunately people cannot get over the idea of insisting on taking money from somebody else to utilise it for Government purposes.  What that amounts to is taking money out of circulation &mdash;money that ought to be doing its ordinary work.  I wish some Government would go into the matter and see whether or not they could not raise money&mdash;that is issue money, create money so to speak.  By that means we could do away not only with this housing menace, but with unemployment as well.  What is behind the present issue of money?  It is only printed.  I know there are a good many difficulties to be considered in connection with this. If we did not balance our trade and our money was going out of the country, then I realise we would be in some difficulty, but if all our people here were fully employed we could not only balance our trade, but have a balance in our favour.</P>
    <P>In this part of Ireland we have a population of about 2¾ millions.  More than half that number is composed of women.  Children represent one-fifth. Then we have civil servants, police, army, teachers.  All these people are non-productive.  If you eliminate all these I think you will find that you have not more than 500,000 effectives in the country.  What are they doing? They have to pay for our imports, which run up to about £60,000,000 a year. They have to pay the £20,000,000 a year which goes to the upkeep of Government. They have to feed not only themselves and their families, but the whole country.  Everything depends on them.  I suppose they must be producing up to £100,000,000 a year.</P>
    <P>If you had a proper building scheme in operation involving an expenditure <Col N="2373" /> of £40,000,000 or £50,000,000 a year, consider how many people would be employed and how many more industries would be set going.  You would have brick yards, cement works and foundries working to full capacity. I put that forward as an idea of my own and suggest that it ought to be considered.  It is not a new idea, but I think it is something that ought to be faced up to.  If we cannot raise money by loans in the ordinary way then I think we would be justified in trying to raise it in the way that I suggest.  This housing problem is a very serious matter.  It was serious before the ban was put on emigration. The operation of that ban means that you have now 30,000 people more annually to cater for.  That gives an idea of what the housing problem is going to be in the future.</P>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. Johnson Mr. Johnson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Johnson</NameTxt>
      <P>I think it is incumbent on the Seanad to give a Second Reading to this Bill and eventually to pass it, if only for the sections in it which deal with the clearance and the rehousing of the people in the slum area.  The desire of the cities and of corporations to do that has been thwarted by the difficulties experienced under past procedure.  The procedure is considerably simplified and made much easier by the provisions in this Bill.  For that, and for one or two other proposals in the Bill which are very valuable, this is a measure which should be supported in general.  But I am not so confident, in fact I am very doubtful, whether the aim that we are all seeking to achieve is likely to be accomplished to any degree by this Bill.  If we were to follow the advice of Senator MacEllin and oppose the Bill, then we have to ask ourselves what is left.  There will be no legislation in operation, and, therefore, there will be no stimulus for building.  For that reason alone we must support the Bill.  We have, however, the right to ask ourselves what are likely to be the effects of the scheme of the Bill.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>In view of the fact that the Bill is introduced mainly to deal with the problem as it affects Dublin City, there <Col N="2374" /> is no harm in reminding the Seanad of this fact that in ten wards of the city, comprising a little more than half the population, 31 per cent. of that population live more than four persons per room.  One-third of the population in half the City of Dublin live more than four persons per room.  There is not much sign, in spite of all the building that has been going on during the last few years, that there is any lessening of that problem.  That alone compels the Government and the Oireachtas especially to attack the problem of Dublin City and similar areas in other parts of the country. It is, unfortunately, true that, in very many of the small towns, quite apart from the cities, you have similar slums and similar problems.  Tennyson's &ldquo;Northern Farmer&rdquo; said: &ldquo;The poor in a lump is bad.&rdquo;  It is very bad in this city, and it is relatively bad in many parts of the country.</P>
    <P>We have to ask ourselves whether this Bill is going to be effective in remedying the evil.  I admit it is going to make the machinery much more satisfactory than it has been hitherto, but whether it will accomplish the end I am very doubtful.  The questions that have been asked by Senator Connolly and Senator Sir John Keane require to be answered before we can judge whether this Bill is likely to be effective.  With regard to the financial provisions of the Bill, what expectation have we of the ability of the occupants of the cleared areas to pay rent as well as of the working classes of the little better-off type that are expected to be housed in a single family cottage?  We have to have some idea of their capacity to pay.  It seems to me that the financial provisions of this Bill are built upon the expectation of a rent-paying capacity which is not at all likely to be achieved.</P>
    <P>No doubt the Minister has in mind certain figures at which money may be borrowed and, quite apart from percentages, what amount of the capital charges will be against the tenant of the £450 tenement house, the £350 cottage, the £400 cottage, or the £600 cottage.  As far as I can work it out, based on such <Col N="2375" /> figures as I have been able to obtain, I cannot see a £450 tenement being let at much less than 10s. a week.  The State is bearing an annual charge of about ten guineas and the local authority is bearing an annual charge of about ten guineas per tenement, the tenant paying somewhere about 10s. a week.  If we reduce the rent to be drawn from the tenants of these tenement cottages, then we are going to put something more than 10 guineas per year upon the local authority.  How much more than the 10 guineas per year per tenement are we going to ask the local authority to bear?  If we take a £350 house, I make a calculation which seems to require about 12s. 3d. per week from a person who is at present resident in the slums and is being cleared and rehoused in a new cottage.  That again assumes the local authority bearing 10 guineas per year subsidy for 20 years.  If the tenant cannot pay this 12s. 3d. per week then the local authority will have to pay something more than 10 guineas per year.  These figures may be inaccurate. They are an estimate based on a 6½ per cent. cost, meaning interest and amortisation, and allowing for one per cent. per annum depreciation which, I understand, is the practice insisted on by the Local Government Department.</P>
    <P>I am only putting these figures forward as my own estimate.  They are subject to correction.  I think at least we must have an idea of what is in the mind of the Ministry as to the amount that is to be drawn from the tenant in the shape of rent before we come to any conclusion as to whether this financial scheme is likely to result in any great re-housing campaign.  We have what is called the better-off type of workman, the workman who wants a little better house than a slum dwelling. The proposal is that men of that class should bear 15 per cent. of the annual loan charges for a period of 20 years.  I would like to know what the Minister's expectation is of the ability of the type of workman expected to take these houses to pay as rent. Does he think that a 15/- or a 16/- a week rental in the case of a £400 house is going to be a solution of the housing <Col N="2376" /> problem?  The Minister knows very well that, under many of the housing schemes of the Dublin Corporation, one of the problems to-day is the creation of new slums in the new cottages. That is to say, people cannot afford to pay a rental of 15/-, 16/-, 18/- or 20/- a week with the result that you have two families in the one house, thereby creating a new over-crowding problem simply to secure the rental. The proposal in the Bill is to continue that charge for a long time over this class of house.  Perhaps even in Dublin, but certainly in the smaller towns, I think it will be found difficult to get the local authority to tackle their particular slum problem on the basis of this Bill.  In so far as semi-urban areas are concerned, areas which are under the county councils and boards of health, what is the chance of this Bill coming to their aid based on the assumption that the local authority will raise a considerable rate?  We have only to consider the action of the Government itself in its remission of rates on agricultural land and the necessity that was shown for that to realise how difficult it is going to be to get the local authorities to saddle themselves with a housing rate for a larger sum than they are paying at present for housing purposes.  It is a significant thing&mdash;I say this in parenthesis&mdash;to note from the census returns that the class of workers who are engaged in building houses are amongst the people who live in these over-crowded dwellings.  I find, for instance, in respect of builders' labourers in Dublin that 75 per cent. of them live in one and two-roomed dwellings, and that 33 per cent. of the carpenters in the City of Dublin live in one and two-room dwellings.  One feels somewhat inclined to say on reading a Bill of this kind that to speak of these cheap houses as housing for the working classes is a very clear condemnation of the whole system under which we are living, that the working classes should be expected, in the natural order of things, to live in these cheap houses while the non-working classes are expected to live in the better, the roomier and the costlier houses.</P>
    <P>I want to put this to the Minister, <Col N="2377" /> unless he can give us some reasons that will inspire confidence in the expectation that this financial scheme will be taken up immediately and promote a great deal of housing in respect of clearance and improvement areas&mdash; that is to say the re-housing of the slum population&mdash;we are going to have, in the next spring, a very great slump in the building trade.  I believe, that, without any question, the first call on State and municipal aid in respect of housing is the tackling of the slum problem and that all efforts should be concentrated upon that, if we can see our way to accomplishing it, and if we are prepared to take the necessary financial steps to ensure that that job will be tackled.  But I am very doubtful whether there is a willingness to tackle that problem in the way in which it ought to be tackled, if it is to be dealt with satisfactorily and with certainty of success.  I think it is not being dealt with satisfactorily and I am of opinion that there is going to be a very great slump in the house building operations in and around this city and throughout the country generally.  We see already a very considerable development in the number of unemployed in the building trades in Dublin.  In official returns circulated this morning, I read that between October, 1930, and October, 1931, there were more than 50 per cent. more unemployed workmen in the building trades this year than last year.  That, I think, is likely to increase. All signs are that in respect of the building trade, other than housing, there will be a curtailment of activities, and if what I foresee in this Bill comes true there is going to be a very considerable decline in the building of dwellings other than working-class dwellings.  I feel, therefore, that the question of building operations, from the point of view of employment, has to be taken into account as well as from the point of view of housing.  From the point of view of employment, I think that the scheme as outlined in the Bill is going to mean the disemployment of a considerable number of men who have been employed, more or less regularly during the last few years in house building.  I am now speaking of speculative <Col N="2378" /> building and of building by public utility societies and people of that class.  I am one of those who believe that every house that was built during the last few years, while not directly attacking the slum problem, had some effect by relieving the pressure and in that way it prevented the slum problem getting steadily worse.  In the case of every 100 new houses that have been built there has been something in the way of easing the pressure on the slum areas.  I am speaking of £800, £900 or £1,000 houses built by speculative builders, or public utility societies.  If that is continued it will, at least, continue to ease the slum problem and it will help to prevent the threatened slump in the building trades.</P>
    <P>I do not think that the scheme outlined is going to encourage the building of the class of houses that the Minister spoke of in the Dáil, the £600 house by the public utility societies, and I want to make a suggestion to the Minister that it is worth while, without spending any more money than is offered in the Bill for that class of house, to give greater assistance and encouragement to the building trade in that direction, by continuing the remission of rates for 20 years instead of the 7 years that is proposed in the Bill.  I suggest to the Minister for consideration that it would be a good proposition from the point of view of municipal finances to continue the method of the 19/20ths remission in the first year to the 1/20th in the last year, as against 2/3rds for the seven years.  I would suggest that the £20 local authority grant should be cancelled and that in its place the old system of remission of rates should be substituted.  I say it would be advantageous to the local authority, because I believe under that system houses would be built which will not be built under the proposed scheme.  I am fairly well advised that that is a likely result.  If there are no houses built, or if the number of new houses is going to be reduced considerably, there is going to be an absence of revenue by way of rates to the local authority. They, at least, would get an increasing amount of rates year by year, if houses <Col N="2379" /> are built and rates remitted, as in the case of the old system.  I think that maintaining the building trades workmen in employment has to be taken into account, when dealing with unemployment insurance and so on, by the State in reckoning the merits of one scheme against the other. I firmly believe that the financial provisions in this Bill will not be taken advantage of in the present circumstances of finance by the local authority to enter upon any big schemes of housing and that, in so far as the private builders are concerned, because of the reduction in assistance there will be a slowing up of building operations in the type of houses that have been hitherto engaged in.  As a whole, I think, whether in Dublin or in the country, the prospects are that you may have to slow up operations in the way of clearance in the cities, but in the small towns you will have a distinct slowing up, and that for private persons and utility societies you will have a certain reduction in the number of houses that are being built annually as compared with those that have been built in recent years.  Consequently, I feel that the Bill is a real disappointment, especially in view of the hopeful notes that were struck a few weeks ago in various quarters.</P>
    <P>It is quite true to say, as Ministers have said, that compared with pre-war activities in house building the building of houses in Dublin, and in the Saorstát generally, since 1922, has been gratifying and valuable, but I think it is not well to claim too much in regard to house building activities.  After all, these things are relative to what has been done in other places and in that respect we have a right to be ashamed of what has been done in the way of house building since the Saorstát came into being.  The Minister read to-day certain figures showing that there have been built since 1922 12,919 houses in urban areas and 11,647 in rural areas, and the President gave a figure of 6,500 houses built in Dublin.  I have not the latest figures, but I have some figures for the ten years ending September 30th, 1929, <Col N="2380" /> which might be compared with our Dublin figure of 6,500.  I take the City of Birmingham.  In the ten years ending September, 1929, there were built there no less than 45,403 houses; Liverpool, 25,035; Manchester, 21,000; Sheffield, 15,000; Leeds, 15,000; Bristol, 10,000; Leicester, 10,000, and so on.  Those are cities comparable, more or less, with Dublin.  It will be seen that relatively to these cities Dublin's effort for housing has been very feeble indeed.  I know quite well all the difficulties, and, making all the allowances that are required, we have no right to pride ourselves unduly upon the effort that has been made in this city and in the country towards building, particularly rehousing the working classes.  I am afraid that we will have to say that this Bill is produced in circumstances and at a time which do not give us ground for confidence that any great improvement is going to be made in the solution of the housing problem.  I hope that before the Committee Stage of the Bill is through we shall have some greater reason for confidence that the Minister's scheme is going to achieve the end that it seeks.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>I wish to express sympathy with this measure.  My reason for getting up, however, is principally to support the recommendations that have been made with regard to the rural areas.  The condition of affairs in these areas, in my opinion, is a standing reproach, not alone since 1922, but for many years before that. While saying that, I desire fully to support this measure.  Everything that has been said on behalf of the slum dwellings in the city might be said with equal emphasis with regard to rural areas.  In my own district I could point to a place where upwards of twenty sites for labourers' cottages were acquired twenty years ago and they remain there still as a reproach to the authorities, both central and local.  There is nothing more depressing than to see such sites in the rural areas, while young men and young women crowd into the cities and towns when they think of married life. I suggest that in the Committee Stage of this Bill some effort should be made <Col N="2381" /> to double the assistance, or if necessary to treble it, so that such conditions might be removed.</P>
      <P>I gathered from the Minister that there were 385 houses built in rural areas by the local authorities&mdash;I assume that these were labourers' cottages&mdash;while there has been a total of over 24,000 other houses built since the year 1922.  Agricultural labourers and rural dwellers generally have borne their share of the assistance that has been given by way of subsidy in building these houses in city areas and now it ought to be their turn to receive some assistance.  I put it to the Minister, and to this House, that something should be done in the Committee Stage to remedy the present state of affairs.  I strongly support the representations that have been made by Senator MacEllin.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOFarrell" hpid="Mr. O'Farrell Mr. O'Farrell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Farrell</NameTxt>
      <P>I just want to raise one particular point with regard to this Bill.  The aim and principal object of the Bill is, of course, an attempt at the clearance of the slums and the substitution of new buildings and new streets.  As everybody knows, the slums of Dublin, particularly, which have become notorious are situated in the oldest portion of the city.  They are quite adjacent to some of the principal and busiest thoroughfares.  O'Connell Street is fringed on a couple of sides by them.  They are adjacent to the Custom House, the Four Courts, Stephen's Green and to all the principal thoroughfares of our city.  The clearance of these slums involves, of course, some regard to traffic regulation and to the amenities of the city as a whole and to its subsequent appearance as a metropolis worthy of the name.  To that extent I think it is absolutely essential, before any clearance on a large scale and rebuilding should take place, that the local authority, or the City Manager, should have the power which can only be conferred on him by a Town Planning Bill.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The Minister, when dealing with the Bill that was introduced here by Senator Johnson, promised to introduce a Bill of his own at an early date. Unfortunately he has not given effect so far to that promise.  I would urge <Col N="2382" /> upon him the great desirability and indeed the necessity of introducing that Bill and of endeavouring to make it an Act before any clearance of slums on a large scale is embarked on.  Many of these slum streets are narrow and winding.  Their entrances and approaches require consideration and their relationship to the other thoroughfares and main traffic routes in the city have got to be considered. Certain powers which can only be given through this Town Planning Bill will be essential, if when rebuilding this ancient part of Dublin particularly, and Cork to a lesser extent, we have some regard to the requirements of the position and the importance of these cities.</P>
    <P>With Senator Johnson, I regret that there should be a withdrawal of facilities in regard to building that now exist.  It would seem as if the Bill is endeavouring to concentrate a great blinding searchlight on the slums in an attempt to wipe them out.  But the danger associated with the Bill is that it might confine house building very largely to the reducing of certain of the slum areas.  The clearance must, of necessity, be of a gradual type for financial reasons, and because of the fact that alternative accommodation must be only of a relatively limited character.  If we are going to have a slowing down of all other types of buildings because of the restrictions in this Bill and the withdrawal of subsidies, then we shall simply be robbing Peter to pay Paul.  We shall be taking steps, undoubtedly, to eliminate the greatest blot on our civilisation, but whilst doing that I think it is very undesirable that there should be a slowing down of operations in any other direction.  When we pride ourselves on what has been done for housing it is rather disappointing to find that in the last nine or ten years the local authorities and public utility societies have built altogether less than 10,000 houses whilst private enterprise has built over 14,500.  It is true that most of the private enterprise houses were built on subsidies that were less than those given to local authorities.  These figures show that no attempt at all commensurate with the magnitude of <Col N="2383" /> the problem has been made either by the State or the local authorities to deal with the housing question. Senator Johnson has given figures of what has been done in certain cities in Great Britain.  They enable us to view in a proper perspective our contribution to this problem.</P>
    <P>There is one other item in regard to this clearance problem that requires consideration and that is the fall in the £ sterling.  A certain proportion, at all events, of building materials come from countries outside of Great Britain and to the extent that there will be a very considerable rise in their purchase price if the £ sterling remains at its present figure or falls lower there should be an incentive to us to encourage the manufacture of building materials here such as cement, slate, brick and so on.  That is a matter that the Minister might take into consideration although I doubt if it can be dealt with in this Bill.  It certainly is going to be a matter of moment in the solution of the housing problem.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JosephOConnor" hpid="Mr. O'Connor Mr. O'Connor">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Connor</NameTxt>
      <P>While I do not know much about the problem in the cities and towns I certainly know a good deal about the cottages that were built under the Labourers Acts.  I have built three or four cottages myself for my own workers in preference to getting the work done through building schemes.  I consider that there has been a good deal of unreasonable expenditure on certain of those cottages that could have been avoided.  I think one of the most essential things in connection with these cottages, from a health point of view, is that they should have concrete foundations and I would put that to the Minister for consideration.  I have had that done myself.  People can live in comfort in such cottages and with benefit to their health and at the same time it is an economy in the building.  I put up a cottage at a cost of £130 and it is fit for anyone to live in.  I would invite inspection if anyone doubts what I am saying.  There has been a <Col N="2384" /> good deal of unreasonable cost attached to building in many cases.</P>
      <P>Another thing I would urge is that more encouragement should be given in the use of our own materials.  The brick industry is one that could be extended.  I think the Minister should make it a condition of all contracts that home-made bricks should be used and that concrete foundations should be put in.  I strongly object to tenement buildings.  It is like going from Purgatory to Heaven for a man living in a tenement to get into a cottage of his own with his family. Preference should be given to single houses for working people.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General Mulcahy General Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>General Mulcahy</NameTxt>
      <P>I appreciate the point made by Senator O'Farrell in regard to the necessity of having a Town Planning Bill when local authorities are approaching clearing work under this Bill.  I have such a Bill back from the draftsman in its final stages and it probably would have already seen the light if I had not been in the position of having to call on my own Department to do the actual drafting in connection with this Housing Bill because of the pressure of business in the draftsman's office. I am indebted to the great efforts on the part of officials in my own Department for the drafting of this Bill in time to get it passed before Christmas.  Perhaps that alone is the reason why the Town Planning Bill has not been introduced before this. I still have hopes that it might be possible to introduce it before the Dáil rises, if not to give it final consideration.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. Johnson Mr. Johnson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Johnson</NameTxt>
      <P>You could take its first reading.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General Mulcahy General Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>General Mulcahy</NameTxt>
      <P>I would be prepared to do that, but I would like to have a particular type of consideration given to it by the Executive Council before doing that. My hope is strong in that direction; it will probably happen, but I would not like to enter into any guarantee that it will happen.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>With regard to the question of rural housing referred to by Senator MacEllin and others, I know that <Col N="2385" /> there is a problem in rural housing analogous to the problem that there is in the urban districts, but I see nothing in the discussions that have taken place or in the approaches of the various local bodies responsible for housing in rural areas&mdash;I see nothing in what has been said or suggested by them that suggests there is any kind of a clear understanding as to what the problem is or how it should be tackled.  I have, as I mentioned on another occasion, got the same criticism of the provisions in regard to rural housing in this Bill from representatives of Wexford as I have got from representatives of Leitrim or Mayo where conditions are radically different.  I think the figures are that in the County Wexford about 20 per cent. or less of the inhabited houses there are houses of three rooms and under, whereas in Leitrim, Mayo, Galway and Roscommon you have 100,000 inhabited houses of which 70,000 houses are of three rooms and under.  It is the same criticism we get of our policy from Wexford people as from Mayo and Leitrim people.</P>
    <P>Where labourers' cottages have been built in rural areas definitely for the agricultural labourer and definitely as a contribution to the better economy of the farming community, everything that has been disclosed recently in connection with reports from local bodies would tend to show that the interests of the agricultural labourer in the distribution of a very big percentage of these cottages have been entirely forgotten and these cottages have been put into the hands of other than agricultural labourers by the farmers' representatives on local bodies.  So far as my information and my present mind on the matter go, I realise there is a problem there.  I realise that you cannot scheme out a policy that will be as definite in its approach and as definite in its finance as this Bill is towards urban areas in respect of rural areas until we have a lot more information and a lot more understanding of what really does require to be done in rural areas.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="2386" /> I would like to have some more examination of the situation by the county medical officers of health who have been appointed recently in some areas.  I think we are shaping towards getting that information.  Senators must realise that in four counties in the West of Ireland there are 100,000 houses, 70,000 of which have three rooms, two rooms or one room.  There is a problem there that on the financial side alone would make one halt a bit before one actually suggests how finance ought to be applied.  It really raises the question as to whether, by reason of its economic condition, a large part of the country, where you have housing conditions like those, is able to pay for improved housing. There is no doubt the country is able to pay for improved housing in rural areas, but, in so far as public money has to be applied to it, it has to be applied in order to relieve insanitary conditions.  Of course it cannot be applied without being related in some way to the capacity of the people to pay, to the capacity of the country as a whole to provide the money.</P>
    <P>In this Bill we are giving the rural sanitary authorities what they have not had up to the present since 1911. We are giving fairly satisfactory loan facilities.  They will get money over the same periods and at the same price as urban authorities will get it.  The financial assistance we are giving them is approximately £60, as compared with £50 up to the present.  I seriously suggest that local authorities ought very favourably to consider the giving of the £20 as against the State's £20 in order to continue the type of building by private persons that has been going on.  It is pretty clear that in many parts of the country small groups of men have been stimulated to organise themselves as builders of private houses of a type suitable to rural conditions. We particularly want that type of development of handicraft and industry in our rural areas.</P>
    <P>Senator Connolly suggests a particular type of inspection with a view to seeing that people not used to modern houses and modern equipment and passing into occupation of a house constructed on modern lines will be <Col N="2387" /> able to take the fullest possible advantage without damage to the house. From what I have seen elsewhere, I do favour a kind of woman inspector who may, if you like, be a rent collector and who can get closer down to the woman of the house and the general economy of families in these houses than can the ordinary rent collectors. With a development on a larger scale of housing schemes in the interests of the poorer classes, no doubt the local authorities will realise the value of inspection by women who are capable of associating with their inspection helpful instruction.  I think that would be of the greatest possible value.</P>
    <P>Senator Johnson is, I think, just to the measure when he says that it is providing a better machine, and he is probably also just when he says there will be difficulties and that results may not be as rosy as some people would like to expect.  It does give a better machine and, after all, to give a better machine is a very great contribution in dealing with a problem to which there are very many sides and in connection with which very many difficulties must be met.  I am confident enough that local authorities like Dublin and Cork will make a real, definite, systematic approach to the working of this measure and out of their efforts, whether or not they will be able to break through all the difficulties that will confront them, we will have at any rate a considerable amount of constructive work done and we will have experience that will enable us, perhaps, to take steps in other directions to overcome the difficulties that lie around the solution of this problem, as far as cities are concerned.  So far as the smaller urban authorities are concerned, they have a considerable amount of work to do.  It is very difficult to get figures, but probably about 13,000 houses in all, outside Dublin, are available for removal and for replacement.</P>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. Johnson Mr. Johnson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Johnson</NameTxt>
      <P>In urban areas?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General Mulcahy General Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>General Mulcahy</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes.  On the question of rents, the Senator takes 6½ per cent. as the rate upon which he made his calculation with a view to arriving <Col N="2388" /> at what the rents under this Bill are likely to be in respect of the three types of houses.  The calculations I have made are for 35 years at 5½ per cent.  I do not know whether there are any reasons why the Minister for Finance would not be able to provide money at that figure at the present time.  Let us calculate giving money for 35 years at 5½ per cent., and work out certain figures on the sliding scale of falling grants to local authorities. Let us take into consideration the repayment of interest and sinking fund on the instalment system and the upkeep and collection charges.  Let us assume that we are dealing with rents for the £400, for the £350 house, and for the £450 flat replacing a slum dwelling.  I estimate the £400 house can be rented at 9/- a week plus rates, the rates being from 20 to 25 per cent. That is as against Senator Johnson's estimate of 15/- or 16/-.  I anticipate the £350 house will be able to be rented at 5/10 plus rates, as against the Senator's 12/3.  The £450 flat, I anticipate, will be able to be rented at 7/6, inclusive of rates.  That 7/6 is, I understand, the figure the Dublin Corporation proposes in connection with a current scheme.  Perhaps the Corporation will have to bear a heavier charge than is intended under this Bill for this particular scheme, but that is a matter that has to be faced until there is some reduction of the standard of the flat that is to be provided as against the standard that the Dublin Corporation are actually providing in this particular case, and also until there is some reduction in the building costs.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>We cannot shut our eyes to the effects that the building costs are going to have on the question of rents that will have to be paid and on the carrying on of the building industry.  When we deal with the building and construction industry I think we are dealing with perhaps the most important industry in the country, the most important if you judge from the point of view of wage-earners employed.  I think it is a most important industry. I do not know whether railways might come near it; perhaps they do not at the present moment.  If we judge it on the net annual value of its output, the <Col N="2389" /> brewing industry is definitely more valuable than the building industry. At least it produces more.  The bread industry might come a little above it. The position is that the product of that industry has to be sold at such a price that even the higher-paid workers in the industry are supposed not to be able to pay for a reasonable standard house.</P>
    <P>I think that we have to make every effort to force the building industry up against circumstances that will make it so organise itself as to produce at a more reasonable cost.  If we are put in the position that an important industry in the country is so circumstanced, then I do not know where it is going to lead us.  If we have in that position an industry dominating such an important part of our social life as the housing industry does, I do not know where it is going to lead us.  I do anticipate that when local authorities settle down with the machinery of this measure in their hands to deal with their problems, they will approach those problems in such a way that it will bring down building costs.  Building costs have been materially brought down.  They have been brought down by systematic and thorough-going watchfulness on the part of the Department and a rather less systematic examination of the question by local authorities.  A lot can be done by local authorities who are close up against the situation.  The representatives of the local authorities are drawn from every rank in the country, and they are aided by skilled officials.  They ought to be able thoroughly to examine the work that is being done under their building schemes and the prices for which that work is being carried out.</P>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. Johnson Mr. Johnson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Johnson</NameTxt>
      <P>Does the Minister take note of the fact that only 16.7 per cent. of the output of the building industry in 1929 was in respect of working class dwellings?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General Mulcahy General Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>General Mulcahy</NameTxt>
      <P>If their other business is as uneconomic as is the building of their working class houses, then not only is this country paying in a very big way for the high cost of the building industry and for building houses for the working classes, but it <Col N="2390" /> must be paying enormously and unnecessarily in other directions for the remaining 84 per cent. of the work done by that industry.  I think that a really serious duty devolves on ourselves and on the local authorities to see that every method of examination is utilised in order to reduce building costs.  I do not know if the reduction in the cost of building working-class dwellings from 1922 to date is in any way reflected in the reduction of other building costs, but if it is I would like to claim on behalf of the Department of Local Government that they have contributed materially in reducing costs here.</P>
      <P>I think it was Senator Sir John Keane who made reference to temporary houses.  I do not like houses to be called temporary houses, and I do not know whether we can say in the Department that we have experience of them.  I can, however, visualise what is meant by a temporary house. The question has been fully considered, and it has been found that the difference in cost between a house that would be called a temporary house and a normal house of reduced standard would not make it worth while building a temporary house.  We have done a considerable amount to reduce the standard of houses without in any way making the houses a shoddy affair, not fit to be lived in.  We have reduced the standard in order to reduce building costs.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnKeaneBart" hpid="Sir John Keane Sir John Keane">
      <NameTxt>Sir John Keane</NameTxt>
      <P>When I was speaking I had in mind huts such as were utilised during the Great War, in which those who would be displaced during building operations could be temporarily housed.  Because of their nature these huts could not pretend to be anything like permanent.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General Mulcahy General Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>General Mulcahy</NameTxt>
      <P>That point was raised as a possible solution of the difficulty in clearing slum areas.  It is not anticipated that the slums will be cleared unless, during the clearance of them, the local authority can find alternative accommodation either of a permanent or temporary character for the persons displaced.  In fact the accommodation will be for those who are most fitted to avail of it <Col N="2391" /> financially, and they will probably receive permanent accommodation. The temporary accommodation, I imagine, would only mean a transfer to another building of the type that was going to be demolished.  All that, however, is a question of organisation.  One of the safeguards in the Bill is that a local authority, before it declares in favour of clearing an area, has to satisfy the Minister that it has plans for providing alternative accommodation for the persons going to be displaced.</P>
      <P>On the question of a possible creation of unemployment by a stoppage of building as a result of the changes in the financing of private persons and public utility societies, I had a considerable amount of discussion with persons interested.  On behalf of the builders, generally, I find the desire to remain building around the £1,000 figure or the £900 or £950 figure. One of the things that I would have in mind in the changes that are being brought about here is that the building industry would be forced down to building a £600 or a £700 house.  Anyone in touch with people looking for houses will find that these people are mostly paying rents in very bad slum areas.  They must find it very hard to understand the attitude of the building industry in not building houses at a £600 figure.  The better paid workers are terribly anxious to get homes, and they are prepared to pay any kind of a reasonable rent for them.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. Johnson Mr. Johnson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Johnson</NameTxt>
      <P>My informant tells me that that cannot be done for less than £1 a week, and the average workman cannot pay that without encroaching unduly upon his wages.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General Mulcahy General Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>General Mulcahy</NameTxt>
      <P>The situation in respect of that type of person is such that we cannot afford at present to allow the building industry to hang around the £1,000 house; that is the house that most money can be made out of.  We are facilitating them to this extent, that we are doing for them in respect of that house a thing that has not been done before for them, in so far as building for private persons <Col N="2392" /> is concerned.  The local authority may not give them exactly up to 90 per cent. of the value of the house, because they may anticipate a fall in values; but we are giving them authority in this Bill to pay up to 90 per cent. of the houses where they are building not more than £1,000 houses.  That is a very considerable assistance to builders, so far as I can learn from them.  If they are building to 1,250 square feet and between that and 950 square feet they get the seven years' remission of rates and the grant.</P>
      <P>If the builders are going to complain now that in 1931 we are taking away grants that enabled them to keep working I think they are quite unreasonable.  There is one remarkable thing about this.  If the builders have this grievance it must be remembered that the Bill has passed through five Stages in the Dáil, we have this Stage here, and yet I had not heard the builders' voice raised in the matter.  That is a very remarkable thing if we are in any way interfering with the industry.  It is remarkable particularly if we are interfering with it in such a way as to throw some of the men they are interested in out of employment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I think the Senator's fears are scarcely well-founded.  I think it is worth an effort to try to do something, whether or not it is the right thing to try to do.  We ought to try to bridge the gap between the building of the £900 or the £950 house and the type of house that the local authorities are building.  Until we do that we are not going to have an advance along any kind of a normal front providing houses for different classes of people who require them. The phrase &ldquo;the housing of the working classes&rdquo; has been mentioned. This Bill is a Bill that is very much legislation by reference.  It has been suggested that there ought to have been a codification of our Housing Acts.  I want to say that it is a precursor of a codifying Bill but I would not like to see that Bill introduced until we have had experience of the actual operation of this measure and can compare the results with our experience of previous Housing Acts. <Col N="2393" /> I would not be inclined to call such a Bill a Bill for the Housing of the Working Classes.  That is a phrase that has come to us from other Acts. A codified Housing Bill here should show plainly that it was a Bill for the housing of the poorer classes and particularly for the prevention of insanitary areas.</P>
    <P>Question agreed to.</P>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Cathaoirleach Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>It has been suggested that the Committee Stage should be fixed for 16th December.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General Mulcahy General Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>General Mulcahy</NameTxt>
      <P>If the Committee Stage is being left until this day fortnight perhaps the Seanad will agree to take the remaining Stages of the Bill in the same week in order that it may become law before Christmas?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDouglas" hpid="Mr. Douglas Mr. Douglas">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Douglas</NameTxt>
      <P>It might be better to take the Committee Stage next week. Very often points arise that require to be looked into and that would give an opportunity to Senators to consider those points perhaps the following week.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. Johnson Mr. Johnson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Johnson</NameTxt>
      <P>There is a good deal in this Bill that requires to be looked into.  There is also a good deal of work to be considered between now and next week.  One week is not a very long time in which to examine the Bill in the light of what the Minister has said and to prepare amendments. It must be remembered that there are many other items to come under our consideration.  It may be as well to remark here that if we have a repetition this year of a spate of Bills coming upon us within the last few weeks of the session, and we have to consider them only in the light of statements made in the Dáil and by Ministers who introduce them here, there will not be very much time allowed Senators for the proper consideration of those measures.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General Mulcahy General Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>General Mulcahy</NameTxt>
      <P>In reply to Senator Johnson, I would like to say that I am not treating the Seanad in this manner as badly as I have treated the Dáil.  I explained that I had to get this Bill drafted in my own Department, <Col N="2394" /> and the Committee and Final Stages of the Bill in the Dáil were, after a week's interval from the Second Reading, taken consecutively on a Thursday and Friday.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. Johnson Mr. Johnson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Johnson</NameTxt>
      <P>I would be quite satisfied if the Minister would say Thursday next.  That would give a little time for the preparation of amendments.</P>
      <P>Committee Stage ordered for Thursday, 10th December.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Town Tenants Bill," RHead="1930&mdash;Report Stage">
    <Title>Town Tenants Bill, 1930&mdash;Report Stage.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Cathaoirleach Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Amendment 1 is a Government amendment, as follows:&mdash;</P>
      <P>Section 5, sub-section (3).  To insert before the sub-section two new sub-sections as follows:&mdash;</P>
      <P>&ldquo;(3)  The Minister may, after consultation with the committee mentioned in Section 65 of the Court of Justice Act, 1924 (No. 10 of 1924), make rules of court for the purposes of this Act and, in particular, for regulating the practice and procedure under this Act.</P>
      <P>(4)  Every rule of court made under this section shall be laid before each House of the Oireachtas as soon as may be after it is made, and if either such House shall, within the next twenty-one days on which such House has sat after such rule is laid before it, pass a resolution annulling such rule, such rule shall be annulled accordingly but without prejudice to the validity of anything previously done thereunder.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EileenCostello" hpid="Mrs. Costello Mrs. Costello">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Costello</NameTxt>
      <P>I second the amendment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesFitzgeraldKenne" hpid="Minister for Justice (Mr. Fitzgerald-Kenney) James Fitzgerald-Kenney">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Justice (Mr. Fitzgerald-Kenney)</NameTxt>
      <P>This amendment makes clear what was not clear.  I relied on Section 7 as giving sufficient power to make rules.  As a matter of fact the section gives power to make regulations and not rules.  This amendment makes it clear that the Rule-making Authority will make the rules, and that can be done as expeditiously as Senator Comyn wishes.</P>
      <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
      <P>The following amendment appeared on the Order Paper in the name of Senator Comyn:&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="2395" /> Section 6.  After the word &ldquo;tenement&rdquo; in line 8 to insert the words &ldquo;or becomes tenant thereof.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="JosephConnolly" hpid="Mr. Connolly Mr. Connolly">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Connolly</NameTxt>
      <P>I am sorry that I cannot speak to this amendment on behalf of Senator Comyn.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. Johnson Mr. Johnson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Johnson</NameTxt>
      <P>Can I speak in favour of the amendment?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Cathaoirleach Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>As it has not been moved I do not think the Senator can.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesFitzgeraldKenne" hpid="Mr. Fitzgerald-Kenney Mr. Fitzgerald-Kenney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Fitzgerald-Kenney</NameTxt>
      <P>The amendment is perfectly unnecessary.</P>
      <P>Amendment not moved.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Cathaoirleach Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Government amendment No. 3:</P>
      <P>Section 11, sub-section (1).  After the word &ldquo;case&rdquo; in line 52 to insert the words &ldquo;shall be such sum as may be agreed on between the landlord and the tenant and in default of such agreement.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EileenCostello" hpid="Mrs. Costello Mrs. Costello">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Costello</NameTxt>
      <P>I second.</P>
      <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
      <P>Amendment 4 not moved.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Cathaoirleach Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Government amendment No. 5:</P>
      <P>Section 12, sub-section (3).  After the word &ldquo;lease&rdquo; in line 42 to insert the words &ldquo;for a life or lives in being (either without a term of years or with a concurrent term of which less than twenty-five years are unexpired) or under a lease for a term.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EileenCostello" hpid="Mrs. Costello Mrs. Costello">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Costello</NameTxt>
      <P>I second.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesFitzgeraldKenne" hpid="Mr. Fitzgerald-Kenney Mr. Fitzgerald-Kenney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Fitzgerald-Kenney</NameTxt>
      <P>Simply through a drafting error these words were omitted.</P>
      <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SamuelBrownKC" hpid="Mr. Brown Mr. Brown">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Brown</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment 6:&mdash;</P>
      <P>New section.  Before Section 13 to insert a new section as follows:&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>13.&mdash;(1)  Where a sanitary authority serves under the Public Health Acts, 1878 to 1931, or the Housing of the Working Classes (Ireland) Acts, 1890 to 1921, a notice on the tenant of a tenement requiring the execution by such tenant of any work which is an improvement within the meaning of this Act, such tenant shall within <Col N="2396" /> three days after the service of such notice on him serve on the landlord of such tenement a notice (in this Act referred to as a sanitary work notice) in the prescribed form stating the fact of the service of such notice by such sanitary authority and stating the material portions of such notice.</P>
    <P>(2)  Where a sanitary work notice is served on the landlord of a tenement such landlord may, within three days after such service, serve on the tenant of such tenement a notice (in this Act referred to as a sanitary work undertaking) in the prescribed form undertaking to execute such work in consideration of either (as such landlord shall state in such notice) a specified increase of rent or an increase of rent to be fixed by the court.</P>
    <P>(3)  Whenever the landlord of a tenement has served under and in accordance with this section a sanitary work undertaking on the tenant of such tenement the following provisions shall have effect, that is to say:&mdash;</P>
    <P>(a)  the service of such undertaking shall have the same effect as the service on such tenant of an improvement undertaking, and the provisions of this Act in relation to an improvement undertaking shall apply accordingly; and</P>
    <P>(b)  such tenant may serve on the sanitary authority a copy of such sanitary work undertaking and thereupon the obligation to comply with the notice served by the sanitary authority and the liability for failure to comply with such notice shall be transferred to and become and be the obligation and liability of such landlord in exoneration of such tenant.</P>
    <P>(4)  Where a tenant has served a sanitary work notice on his landlord and such landlord has not, within three days after such service, served on such tenant a sanitary work undertaking in respect of such sanitary work notice, such tenant shall be entitled to execute as an improvement the work mentioned in the notice the service of which by the <Col N="2397" /> sanitary authority occasioned the service of such sanitary notice.</P>
    <P>This new section, the subject of this amendment, is very technical.  It deals with the work that is done by a tenant under the order of a sanitary authority. Now both the landlord and the tenant are liable to the sanitary authority when an order has been made for sanitary work to be done under the Public Health Acts and the other Acts.  The form that the notice takes is that it is addressed to the occupier or owner, the occupier for all practical purposes meaning the tenant and the owner meaning the landlord.  The owner is defined in the Public Health Acts as the person who is in receipt of the rack rent.  Under the present law, if a tenant does the work that he is ordered to do by this notice he may or he may not be entitled to be recouped by his landlord.  That depends on the contract of tenancy between them.  In most cases, if the sanitary work has to be done outside the house, it is quite probable that the landlord is liable as between himself and the tenant: that he would have to pay if the tenant does not; but where the work is to be done inside it is very often the tenant who would have to do it under the contract of tenancy.  If it is the landlord's job the tenant can recover if he does the work, so he does not want any other remedy.  But if it is the tenant's job, then he cannot recover under the present law, but there is a kind of sanitary work as to which that would be unfair to the tenant.  There is a kind of sanitary work which very often occurs where what is done is an improvement which will add to the letting value of the tenement, and for that kind of work, although the tenant is not entitled to recover from the landlord under the present law, it is quite clear that he should be entitled to recover.</P>
    <P>For that reason, that kind of sanitary work was attempted to be dealt with by the Bill as it came to this House.  It was dealt with in sub-section (5) of Section 16.  Sanitary work of this nature done by a tenant was so different from the improvements to which he would be entitled under the general provisions of the Bill that it had to be dealt with quite separately.  That is why it <Col N="2398" /> was dealt with by sub-section (5) of Section 16.  The way it was dealt with was this: that the improvement notice that the tenant had to serve on the landlord in the ordinary way in order to entitle him to recover compensation for improvements at the end of his tenancy was declared not to be necessary in the case of sanitary work.  That is how the matter was left and how it came to this House.  That was not fair to the landlord, because it deprived him of the right of what was called in the Bill an improvement undertaking. Under Section 12 of the Bill, where a tenant wants to get compensation for improvements at the end of his tenancy, he has as a condition to serve on the landlord, before he begins to make an improvement, what is called an improvement notice.  Having served that notice, the landlord then has two months within which to make up his mind whether he will do it himself or not.  If he makes up his mind within the two months to do it, he then serves on the tenant an improvement undertaking. If he does that the tenant has nothing more to do.  What he intended to do is done by the landlord and the thing is over.  As the Bill came to this House, in the case of sanitary work the landlord had no chance of saying &ldquo;I will do it myself.&rdquo;  He could not have the chance of saying it, because the sanitary notice always required the thing to be done in a limited few days &mdash;about three days, but never more than ten.</P>
    <P>Sub-section (1) of the new section that I am proposing requires the tenant, when he has been served by the sanitary authority with an order, to communicate to his landlord within three days the fact that he has been served with that notice and roughly what he is required to do.  With regard to the provisions laid down under sub-section (3) of the new section, the tenant gets off altogether, so far as the sanitary authority is concerned, if the landlord undertakes to do the work.</P>
    <P>Amendment 8 must be considered with this amendment.  It proposes to add at the end of the existing sub-section (5) the words: &ldquo;but a tenant shall not be entitled to compensation in respect of such work unless such <Col N="2399" /> tenant has served on his landlord a sanitary work notice in respect of such work and has become entitled under this Act to execute such work as an improvement.&rdquo;  That is to say, if he fails to carry out the conditions under the new Section 13 by serving notice on his landlord within three days, he cannot recover compensation for what he does as an improvement under this Act.  It may seem that that is a little hard on the tenant, but we must recollect that the tenant is acquiring an absolutely new right under this Act. This new section only applies to a case where only for this Bill the tenant could not recover any compensation at all.  It gives him a new right to recover compensation for the sanitary improvement which brings the landlord no chance of a larger rent.  The three days is, of course, short notice, but it cannot be helped.  The sanitary notice is so short that if the landlord is not to be deprived of his right, the same rights that he has under the rest of the Bill, of serving an undertaking to do the work himself, then it must be done within some short period like three days.  The landlord himself must make up his mind whether or not he is going to avail of this right within another three days.</P>
    <Speaker pid="CountessofDesart" hpid="Countess of Desart Countess of Desart">
      <NameTxt>Countess of Desart</NameTxt>
      <P>I second the amendment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelComynKC" hpid="Mr. Comyn Mr. Comyn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Comyn</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator Brown was right when he said that this amendment of his is rather hard on the tenant.  It is, and it is also hard on the public, who take an interest in sanitary work as great as that of the tenant and much greater than that of the landlord.  This is an amendment that requires very close consideration. I think it is one that ought to have been brought forward at the proper time&mdash;that is, on the Committee Stage of the Bill.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SamuelBrownKC" hpid="Mr. Brown Mr. Brown">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Brown</NameTxt>
      <P>I did bring forward one on the Committee Stage, to which this is an alternative.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelComynKC" hpid="Mr. Comyn Mr. Comyn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Comyn</NameTxt>
      <P>If Senator Brown says so I am sure it must be so.  All I can say is that anything that was suggested on the Committee Stage of the <Col N="2400" /> Bill did not make on my mind the impression which this amendment has made.  Certainly, whatever was brought forward on the Committee Stage was not urged by arguments such as the Senator has used on this occasion.  If it had been brought forward on the Committee Stage it would be very difficult even for persons acquainted with the very complicated system of Public Health law to understand the meaning of this amendment.  The House is now expected on the Report Stage to take up the consideration of this problem which has been very clearly and ably stated by Senator Brown from the point of view which he appears to advocate here.  The Senator himself has said that the amendment is going to be a little hard on the tenant.  I suggest that it is going to be very hard on the public.  I am opposing the amendment without knowing whether or not it is to be accepted by the Minister.  I oppose the amendment on principle.  Here is how the Bill stood as it passed through the Dáil. There is a general restriction in Section 16 of the right to compensation for improvements by the tenant. Notice must be served and matters of that kind attended to.  Sub-section (5) of the section provides:</P>
      <P>(5)  Neither of the two next foregoing sub-sections of this section shall apply in respect of an improvement which is a work executed in pursuance of an order of a sanitary authority under the Public Health Acts, 1878 to 1930, or the Housing of the Working Classes (Ireland) Acts, 1890 to 1921.</P>
      <P>The two foregoing sub-sections provide that:</P>
      <P>A tenant shall not be entitled to compensation for improvements in respect of an improvement made after the passing of this Act unless&mdash;</P>
      <P>(a)  an improvement notice was duly served in accordance with this Act in relation to such improvement, and</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>(b)  the tenant by whom such notice was so served became entitled under this Act to execute <Col N="2401" /> such improvement either on consent or by virtue of an improvement order, and</P>
    <P>(c)  such improvement was duly executed in accordance (as the case may be) with such improvement notice and this Act or with such improvement order.</P>
    <P>Senators can now see the reason why this clause was put in the original Bill in respect to improvements under the Public Health Acts.  The reason is that improvements under the Public Health Acts are matters of urgency in respect to which the public is concerned.  They are matters which must be done at once, and if they are not done the Public Health Authorities can prosecute. Moreover, any member of the public who is injured or whose child gets diphtheria or something of that kind has an action against the tenant who will not carry out an improvement under the Public Health Acts.  That is what is in the Bill.  The Bill in this matter was right as it left the Dáil. Senator Brown wants it varied by the Seanad on the Report Stage.  I am opposed to this amendment, which requires the tenant to serve a notice on the landlord authorising him within a certain time to do the improvement work.  Take a case where the landlord is unknown.  It has occurred that sanitary improvements have had to be made in the case of houses in this city where the landlord was unknown. Moreover, why should the landlord allow his premises to get into a state of dilapidation, requiring expenditure on his part to make them habitable and safe under the Public Health Acts?  If his house is in such a bad condition, what right has he to a notice?  That is one objection I have to the amendment. My second objection is, in the public interest.  Under the Public Health Acts, the person responsible is the occupier.  That is quite right.  The occupier must make the improvement. In the public interest, the improvements necessary under the Public Health Acts should be done at once. If a tenant is required to do them he ought certainly to get compensation if they add to the letting value of the holding, without being put to the necessity of finding his landlord and of serving him with notice.  My objection <Col N="2402" /> to the amendment is, first, in the interests of the tenant and, secondly, in the interests of the public.  Under paragraphs (a) and (b) of sub-section (3) of Senator Brown's proposed amendment, what is the liability that is transferred?  It is the liability under the notice; the liability to the public authority.  What about the liability to the third person who receives special damage and special injury by reason of the nonperformance of the sanitary work? These are only a few of the difficulties that seem to me to arise on this amendment. With regard to sub-section (4) of the proposed new section, why allow three days delay in respect of this public health work where a house has been allowed to get into such a condition that it becomes a public nuisance? Senator Brown is right in saying that this section gives a new right to the tenant, but the Senator seeks by his amendment to subject that new right to conditions which will certainly be injurious to the public.  I urge that, on this Stage of the Bill, a far-reaching clause of this character should not be introduced, and I hope the House will reject it.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JamesFitzgeraldKenne" hpid="Mr. Fitzgerald-Kenney Mr. Fitzgerald-Kenney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Fitzgerald-Kenney</NameTxt>
      <P>With a great deal of Senator Comyn's argument I was rather mystified.  I failed to follow a certain amount of it.  His argument was largely based on the assumption that always and in all circumstances under the Public Health Acts the liability is upon the occupier.  Unless my recollection of the Public Health Acts is completely wrong, notice can be served either on the owner or the occupier.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SamuelBrownKC" hpid="Mr. Brown Mr. Brown">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Brown</NameTxt>
      <P>It is directed to both.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesFitzgeraldKenne" hpid="Mr. Fitzgerald-Kenney Mr. Fitzgerald-Kenney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Fitzgerald-Kenney</NameTxt>
      <P>When the foundation upon which Senator Comyn built up his argument has to be abandoned I am afraid that a great deal of the superstructure, if not all of it, goes down too.  The proposed new section is an expansion of amendment 11 that came up on the Committee Stage.  I think it is an improvement on it.  The only difficulty I see is that possibly the term of three days is too short&mdash; not, as Senator Comyn thinks, that it is too long.  It appears to me that <Col N="2403" /> possibly it is too short, because the tenant may lose his rights if he neglects to act, so to speak, almost on the spur of the moment.  If he does not act within three days in serving the notice he may lose his rights.  That seems to me to be the only possible hardship on tenants that the section contains, but I frankly cannot see the answer to Senator Brown's argument. Since sanitary notices are always in their terms exceedingly short, the service of this notice by the tenant on the landlord, and the service back of the landlord's notice on the tenant, must be done at what I would almost call break-neck speed.  That seems to be a necessity considering the fact that sanitary notices are always for a very short period.  It occurred to me possibly that from the tenant's point of view some of this difficulty might be obviated if the sanitary authorities always served with the notice a slip of paper, or put on the back of the notice a statement drawing attention to the provisions of this section, or, perhaps, better than drawing attention to the provisions of this section, containing a précis of the section which would open the tenant's eyes and let him know immediately that he has to act if he wishes to get the benefit of carrying out the improvements. I have not had the opportunity yet of consulting with the Department of Local Government to see how far that can be made obligatory on sanitary authorities.  I fancy in that case sanitary authorities will be willing to do it, whether it is obligatory on them or not.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Apart from that difficulty, I cannot see any objection to this amendment, which really fits in with the entire scheme of work of the Bill, which enables landlords to carry out improvements upon their property.  Of course I see in a case like this a very strong reason why the landlord should, in a great number of instances, be the person to carry out the improvements, because notice might be served on half a dozen tenants occupying half a dozen adjoining houses, yet the improvement might be an improvement of a nature that will affect the whole lot of them. Each individual simply trying to carry <Col N="2404" /> out improvements might be tinkering at it while the landlord carrying out the improvements for the whole lot would not only get it done more cheaply but he would also carry them out more effectively, and, I believe, at a much quicker rate.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JosephConnolly" hpid="Mr. Connolly Mr. Connolly">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Connolly</NameTxt>
      <P>I must confess, as a layman, I am rather confused between two points of view from the lawyers on this amendment.  I would like to raise one or two points.  Senator Brown, in his reply, might deal with them.  I was always under the impression that in dealing with sanitary notices and questions of public health the responsibility was entirely on the landlord; the tenant might be notified, but it was really the landlord's work.  I cannot see how the tenant in those cases could be expected to carry out the necessary repairs to the property.</P>
      <P>There is only one objection that I can see to Senator Brown's amendment, and that is the question of &ldquo;a specified increase of rent or an increase of rent to be fixed by the court,&rdquo; because it seems to me that necessary sanitary improvements should be part of a landlord's duty, irrespective of any question of compensation. That is to say, if the public health laws are being administered it surely devolves on the landlord, as a matter of public responsibility, to keep his property in a proper sanitary condition.  I had always assumed, and it has been my experience in respect of any such property that I have ever had anything to do with, that the landlord was notified with regard to sanitary improvements to be carried out under the Public Health Acts.  I would like if Senator Brown could clarify that in his reply.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnKeaneBart" hpid="Sir John Keane Sir John Keane">
      <NameTxt>Sir John Keane</NameTxt>
      <P>Surely Senator Connolly has experience of the conditions that prevail in these small villages?  The cost on a landlord of providing sanitary arrangements might come to £20, while he receives 2s. a week rent.  Does he seriously suggest that the landlord ought to bear such a cost?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="2405" />
    <Speaker pid="JosephConnolly" hpid="Mr. Connolly Mr. Connolly">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Connolly</NameTxt>
      <P>My point is that people who can only afford to pay 2s. a week rent could not bear a cost of £20.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnKeaneBart" hpid="Sir John Keane Sir John Keane">
      <NameTxt>Sir John Keane</NameTxt>
      <P>I can speak from personal experience on this.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JosephConnolly" hpid="Mr. Connolly Mr. Connolly">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Connolly</NameTxt>
      <P>I am speaking of the tenant's capacity to do it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnKeaneBart" hpid="Sir John Keane Sir John Keane">
      <NameTxt>Sir John Keane</NameTxt>
      <P>I am speaking of the position of the landlord, and the suggestion that sanitary improvements can be done without an increase of rent.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. Johnson Mr. Johnson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Johnson</NameTxt>
      <P>I speak with great ignorance of this question.  The question will not arise unless premises are improved.  No question of improvement value arises unless the tenant does the job in response to the order that is served on him on behalf of the landlord.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JosephConnolly" hpid="Mr. Connolly Mr. Connolly">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Connolly</NameTxt>
      <P>On behalf of the public authority.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. Johnson Mr. Johnson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Johnson</NameTxt>
      <P>It is served on him to do the work.  The local authority ask that the work be done.  I take it the immediate responsibility lies on the occupier.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SamuelBrownKC" hpid="Mr. Brown Mr. Brown">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Brown</NameTxt>
      <P>There is equal responsibility on the landlord and tenant as far as the sanitary authority is concerned.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelComynKC" hpid="Mr. Comyn Mr. Comyn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Comyn</NameTxt>
      <P>But that responsibility cannot be enforced against the landlord except with great trouble and expense.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SamuelBrownKC" hpid="Mr. Brown Mr. Brown">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Brown</NameTxt>
      <P>I can easily be done.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. Johnson Mr. Johnson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Johnson</NameTxt>
      <P>I presume that one individual of the two is liable ultimately to the local authority for carrying out this work.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SamuelBrownKC" hpid="Mr. Brown Mr. Brown">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Brown</NameTxt>
      <P>Both.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. Johnson Mr. Johnson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Johnson</NameTxt>
      <P>If the tenant does it, and in the doing of it he adds to the letting value of the tenement, then it is provided in certain circumstances that the improvement value is credited to him.  If it is a case of five or six houses the liability immediately devolves upon the landlord.  The tenant is not going to do the job because it is not in respect of his particular tenancy alone.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="2406" />
    <Speaker pid="MichaelComynKC" hpid="Mr. Comyn Mr. Comyn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Comyn</NameTxt>
      <P>If it is a public sewer the public authority must do it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. Johnson Mr. Johnson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Johnson</NameTxt>
      <P>It may be other things. I find in the Bill, for instance, that the word &ldquo;improvement&rdquo; is defined and the definition includes &ldquo;the installation in the tenement of conduits for the supply of water, gas or electricity.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SamuelBrownKC" hpid="Mr. Brown Mr. Brown">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Brown</NameTxt>
      <P>That is an ordinary improvement.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. Johnson Mr. Johnson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Johnson</NameTxt>
      <P>Conduits for water might well be required to be carried out by the landlord or occupier, as the case may be.  If the occupier has to do it and it causes an improvement in the letting value, then something is due to the occupier.  The amendment seeks to ensure that the landlord will get a chance of doing the job in preference to the tenant, but the tenant, if he has to do it eventually, is not going to get anything credited to him in the way of improvement value unless he has succeeded in serving on the landlord this notice within three days. I can see the probability unless the landlord is a next-door neighbour or lives very close to him, that that notice will not be served within three days, and the chances are that the tenant will have no improvement credited to him even though he has improved the letting value of the property. That, of course, simply raises the question as to what period should be allowed in which to serve notice on the landlord.  If there were a sufficient period I could see some justice and decency in the amendment, but I think that in three days' notice you are practically depriving the tenant, or occupier, of the chance of getting an improvement value credited to him.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SamuelBrownKC" hpid="Mr. Brown Mr. Brown">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Brown</NameTxt>
      <P>With reference to what Senator Johnson has just said, you must recollect that this section only applies in cases in which the tenant has no right under the present law to throw the obligation on to his landlord.  If, under the existing law, the tenant has a right either to get the landlord to do it, or if he does it himself to recover from the landlord what he has spent on doing it, then this does not apply at all.  But then, as is the ordinary remedy at law, he can sue the landlord <Col N="2407" /> for what he has spent because this is a contract with the landlord, and in nine cases out of ten the sanitary work is done outside the house, and as a rule the landlord has to do repairs outside a house, and that sort of thing.  In nine cases out of ten the tenant will be entitled, if he does the work, whether he serves notice or not, to recover from his landlord.  It is only in cases where he has not that right, where it is not the tenant's job, and where he cannot recover from his landlord, that this amendment applies. They are both equally liable so far as the sanitary authorities are concerned. Senator Connolly assumed that the liability was on the landlord.  It is not. So far as the sanitary authority is concerned, it is on them both or either of them, and either of them can be made liable.</P>
      <P>I think that the suggestion that has been made by the Minister is an admirable one.  There is no reason why the sanitary order should not have an accompanying notice, not in any legal language at all, but in language such as any tenant can understand.  If the tenant neglects to serve the notice on the landlord of what he has been ordered to do he will lose his rights against him for compensation afterwards. It ought to be done, not by reference to any section or anything of that kind, but in language which an ordinary tenant will understand.  It is very seldom that a landlord is unknown to a tenant.  He pays his rent to somebody.  He is paying it to an agent if he is not paying it to the landlord. If the sanitary authority does not know who the owner is, in 99 cases out of a hundred the tenant does know who is his landlord, and there will be no difficulty about it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. Johnson Mr. Johnson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Johnson</NameTxt>
      <P>What happens if the landlord happens to be out of the country?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SamuelBrownKC" hpid="Mr. Brown Mr. Brown">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Brown</NameTxt>
      <P>Service on his agent would be sufficient.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. Johnson Mr. Johnson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Johnson</NameTxt>
      <P>If he is on holidays and has no agent?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesFitzgeraldKenne" hpid="Mr. Fitzgerald-Kenney Mr. Fitzgerald-Kenney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Fitzgerald-Kenney</NameTxt>
      <P>Notice might be left at his dwelling.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="2408" />
    <Speaker pid="JohnKeaneBart" hpid="Sir John Keane Sir John Keane">
      <NameTxt>Sir John Keane</NameTxt>
      <P>The tenant might be on holidays also.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JosephConnolly" hpid="Mr. Connolly Mr. Connolly">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Connolly</NameTxt>
      <P>Could the Minister suggest any means whereby it would be incumbent on the local authority to serve the landlord with notice at the same time as the tenant?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesFitzgeraldKenne" hpid="Mr. Fitzgerald-Kenney Mr. Fitzgerald-Kenney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Fitzgerald-Kenney</NameTxt>
      <P>They might not know the landlord; that is the difficulty. The sanitary authority is probably a doctor.  In most cases he sees that something has to be done to a house.  He knows who is living in the house, but he may not always know who is landlord of the house.  In many cases I daresay it would be very difficult to know who is the landlord.  I think the Senator will agree with me that it would not be at all desirable to have an amendment of the Public Health Acts in this Bill.  The Public Health Acts are a particular code, and they should be kept together as a code. It would be very difficult to have a little bit of public health legislation coming into the middle of this legislation. If there was to be anything of that kind it really would require a short separate Bill.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JanePower" hpid="Mrs. Wyse-Power Mrs. Wyse-Power">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Wyse-Power</NameTxt>
      <P>I think it would be necessary to amend the public bye-laws.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JosephConnolly" hpid="Mr. Connolly Mr. Connolly">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Connolly</NameTxt>
      <P>My suggestion only followed the Minister's suggestion that notice might be sent to the landlord. It might serve the purpose just as well if notice was served for the landlord on the tenant.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesFitzgeraldKenne" hpid="Mr. Fitzgerald-Kenney Mr. Fitzgerald-Kenney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Fitzgerald-Kenney</NameTxt>
      <P>I will approach the Department of Local Government and see if within the existing powers of the Department it would be possible to bring in such a regulation or such a bye-law.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Cathaoirleach Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>In the meantime this amendment will be dealt with.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDouglas" hpid="Mr. Douglas Mr. Douglas">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Douglas</NameTxt>
      <P>Would the Minister let us know to-morrow?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelComynKC" hpid="Mr. Comyn Mr. Comyn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Comyn</NameTxt>
      <P>Perhaps the Minister, in the meantime, would consider what should be deemed to be notice.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesFitzgeraldKenne" hpid="Mr. Fitzgerald-Kenney Mr. Fitzgerald-Kenney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Fitzgerald-Kenney</NameTxt>
      <P>I frankly think, even if it is impossible to compel <Col N="2409" /> the public health authority to serve such notice, that this amendment would have to be carried to carry out the full scheme.  You are imperilling tenants, possibly through their ignorance, but at the same time it seems to me that this is a valuable improvement in the Bill.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelComynKC" hpid="Mr. Comyn Mr. Comyn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Comyn</NameTxt>
      <P>Without specifying what the notice is?  You may have a case where a tenant could not possibly, within three days, serve notice on the landlord.</P>
      <P>Amendment put and declared carried.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Cathaoirleach Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Government amendment No. 7.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="2410" /> Section 16, sub-section (5).  To delete in line 52 the figures &ldquo;1930&rdquo; and to substitute therefor the figures &ldquo;1931.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="JamesFitzgeraldKenne" hpid="Mr. Fitzgerald-Kenney Mr. Fitzgerald-Kenney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Fitzgerald-Kenney</NameTxt>
      <P>It is owing to the fact that there has been a Public Health Act this year.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EileenCostello" hpid="Mrs. Costello Mrs. Costello">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Costello</NameTxt>
      <P>I second.</P>
      <P>Amendment put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>Debate adjourned.</P>
      <P>The Seanad adjourned at 7.20 p.m. until 3 p.m. on Thursday, 3rd December.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
</Debate>