<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE Debate SYSTEM "../Debate.dtd"[]>
<Debate DocTitle="Seanad Debate" Day="Thu" Date="10" Month="Dec" Year="1931" Vol="15" No="2" DateIrish="Déardaoin, 10 Nollaig 1931" DateEnglish="Thursday, 10 December 1931" House="S" CommitteeEng="" CommitteeIr="" SubNameEng="" cnum="43">
  <MainHeading Type="Prelude" LHead="" RHead="">
    <Title>
    </Title>
    <P>
      <Col N="43" /> Do chuaidh an Cathaoirleach i gceannas ar 3 p.m.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Election of a Leas-Chathaoirleach:" RHead="Fixing the Date">
    <Title>Election of a Leas-Chathaoirleach: Fixing the Date.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Cathaoirleach Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>The House will recollect that yesterday, pursuant to Standing Order 7, an order was made fixing the date for the election of the Leas-Chathaoirleach as the first Wednesday on which the Seanad shall meet in January, 1932.  I have since come to the conclusion that it is somewhat undesirable that the date should be fixed so far ahead.  The Leas-Chathaoirleach is <i>ex officio</i> Chairman of the Committee of Selection, and I do not see how that Committee can be properly appointed and function until a Leas-Chathaoirleach has been elected. Senators are aware that all committees are deemed to have been discharged at the end of a triennial period, and the duty of nominating the personnel of the new committees normally falls to the Committee of Selection.  For these reasons, and also because the House has been without a Leas-Chathaoirleach since the beginning of September last, I am inclined to regard any further delay as undesirable.  Hence, I would ask the House to discharge the Order made yesterday and to appoint next Thursday, the 17th instant, as the date for the election of a Leas-Chathaoirleach. If the House takes this course, motions nominating candidates must reach the Clerk not later than 4 p.m. on Saturday next.  I ask the House to consider the matter, and, if they agree with me, to make an order accordingly.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LaurenceONeill" hpid="Mr. O'Neill Mr. O'Neill">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Neill</NameTxt>
      <P>I think the statement the Cathaoirleach has just made is a very judicious one, and I beg to move that the order made yesterday fixing the date for the election of a Leas-Chathaoirleach be discharged and that the election take place on Thursday, 17th instant.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasFarren" hpid="Mr. Farren Mr. Farren">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Farren</NameTxt>
      <P>Yesterday we had a full House when a decision was come to <Col N="44" /> fixing the date for the election of a Leas-Chathaoirleach.  At the moment we have only half the members present. Therefore, I think it would hardly be fair to change the date of the election after a full House came to a particular decision on it yesterday.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardWilson" hpid="Mr. Wilson Mr. Wilson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Wilson</NameTxt>
      <P>There is this further point to be considered.  The Committee of Selection is only called together for the purpose of selecting members of this House to act on the joint committee to consider the Auctioneers Bill. As far as I know there is nothing very urgent about that Bill.  In view of the fact that a full House yesterday decided that the election of a Leas-Chathaoirleach should take place at the first meeting of the Seanad in the New Year, I do not see any reason why that Order should be changed.  This matter about the Selection Committee is not of such importance as to justify the House in changing the order.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDouglas" hpid="Mr. Douglas Mr. Douglas">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Douglas</NameTxt>
      <P>I think Senator Wilson is under a misapprehension with regard to the duties of the Selection Committee.  The committee in connection with the Auctioneers Bill will be chosen by the joint committee on Private Bill Standing Orders, which is quite a different committee to the one the Senator referred to.  It has been customary, after a triennial election, to choose most of the standing committees of the House.  They are nominated by our own Committee of Selection.  I have no personal views on the matter as to when the election of a Leas-Chathaoirleach should take place, but I think if there is any opposition it would be a mistake to rescind the decision come to yesterday.  If that view is held by the House, I would respectfully suggest that the difficulty with regard to the committees might be got over between now and January by a resolution of the House arranging that the present committees should continue until a Leas-Chathaoirleach is appointed.  If that were done, no real difficulty, I think, would arise, because on this occasion there has not been very much change in the personnel of the House and, therefore, it would be possible for the existing committees to carry on for another month or so.  I <Col N="45" /> have no personal views as to when the election is held, but as I have said if there is opposition I think it would be a mistake to rescind the decision come to yesterday.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Cathaoirleach Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I agree that it would be very undesirable to discharge the Order made yesterday if there is opposition.  It depends altogether on what the desire of the House is.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelComynKC" hpid="Mr. Comyn Mr. Comyn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Comyn</NameTxt>
      <P>If we change this evening the decision that was arrived at last evening it will be suggested that we are changing it for some special purpose.  Therefore, I think that we ought to adhere to the decision we came to yesterday.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. Johnson Mr. Johnson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Johnson</NameTxt>
      <P>Before we come to any decision on the matter, I think we should hear the views of the Senator who moved yesterday that the election should be deferred until January.  Presumably he had some reason for proposing that it should not take place next week.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMacEllin" hpid="Mr. MacEllin Mr. MacEllin">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEllin</NameTxt>
      <P>Personally, I do not see that there is any great need for hurry in making the appointment of a Leas-Chathaoirleach.  As the Cathaoirleach has pointed out, we have been without a Leas-Chathaoirleach since September last, and during that time I do not think the House has suffered any great inconvenience.  If the election were to take place, as suggested, on Thursday of next week, we would only have until Saturday next to hand in nominations.  It is quite possible that the members of this Party will be nominating a candidate, and I do not think it would be fair to expect us to have the nominations in between now and Saturday, particularly in view of the fact that the House came to a decision yesterday that the election would not take place until the first Wednesday in January.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Cathaoirleach Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>In view of the opinions that have been expressed, it is desirable, I think, that the Order made yesterday should stand.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EileenCostello" hpid="Mrs. Costello Mrs. Costello">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Costello</NameTxt>
      <P>Would it not be well to consider the suggestion made by Senator Douglas, that the existing committees should, by resolution of <Col N="46" /> the House, continue until such time as the appointment has been made?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Cathaoirleach Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>That is a matter that we can consider next week.  I take it that the opinion of the House is that the Order made yesterday fixing the date for the election of a Leas-Chathaoirleach should stand?</P>
      <P>Agreed.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Merchandise Marks Bill," RHead="1931&mdash;Second Stage (resumed)">
    <Title>Merchandise Marks Bill, 1931&mdash;Second Stage (resumed).</Title>
    <P>Question again proposed: &ldquo;That the Bill be now read a Second Time.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Cathaoirleach Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>The Second Reading debate on this Bill was opened yesterday by Senator Connolly and was then adjourned for the attendance of the Minister.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. Johnson Mr. Johnson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Johnson</NameTxt>
      <P>It would be well if the Minister made a statement explaining the purpose of the Bill.  It will be remembered that it was in order to accommodate Senator Connolly that the discussion was opened yesterday, but I think it was understood that the Minister would make a statement introducing the Bill to-day.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelComynKC" hpid="Mr. Comyn Mr. Comyn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Comyn</NameTxt>
      <P>We expect a statement from the Minister.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Minister for Industry and Commerce (Mr. McGilligan) Patrick McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Industry and Commerce (Mr. McGilligan)</NameTxt>
      <P>The principle of the Bill can be very briefly stated.  Its purpose is to amend the Principal Act of 1887 in which there have been found defects in at least three particulars. The first defect that occurred in the working of the 1887 Act arose on the question of enforcement and prosecution.  We are making certain extensions in this Bill.  We are giving better facilities for bringing offenders to book in this Amending Act.  The second point is that the 1887 Act was found to be useful only in regard to misdescription or false description of goods.  The part of it that has been found effective, if any part of the Act can be said to be effective, was in relation to misdescription as to the place or country in which goods had been manufactured. Under the Act of 1887 misdescription might relate to a great deal more than the country where the goods were produced. <Col N="47" /> Under that Act the expression &ldquo;trade description&rdquo; means &ldquo;any description, statement or other indication, direct or indirect (a) as to the number, quantity, measure, gauge or weight of any goods, or (b) as to the place or country in which any goods were made or produced or (c) as to the mode of manufacturing or producing any goods, or (d) as to the material of which any goods are composed, or (e) as to any goods being the subject of an existing patent, privilege or copyright.&rdquo;  Even though the scope of that is more extensive than most people imagine, it is entirely limited by this fact that there had to be misdescription.  There had to be what amounted to false description in relation to any of these particular goods which were not marked in any way and which did not give any description of themselves either in regard to the country of manufacture or the country of origin. We are seeking to amend that. Section 20 of the Bill covers the sale of imported goods bearing name or trademark of Saorstát Eireann manufacturer or trader or place or name in Saorstát Eireann.  Goods coming under this section must bear either on importation or on sale a description of the country of origin. With regard to all other goods, on an application being made to the Merchandise Marks Commission which we propose to establish under the Act an obligation may be put upon those who import or sell goods to affix to them a description saying that the goods are simply not manufactured here or specifically saying that they are manufactured in some named place.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The third point in which the old Act was found to be defective was that before it could be established that a false description applied it had to be by way of actual physical attachment to the goods.  An advertisement which was not connected with the goods did not count as a misdescription of a particular type of goods coming into the country.  We are taking false description or misrepresentation and extending the <Col N="48" /> representation so as to include representation, not merely physically aplied to the goods, but also if it is verbal or in writing or used in any advertisement.  Those who make false description in that way so long as it relates to the country of origin are brought within the scope of this Bill and render themselves liable to penalties. The Bill has reference not merely to false description of origin but it goes further and in certain cases requires a description of origin to be attached to certain goods on their entering into the country, and with regard to every other class of goods allows an application to be made to the Commission that certain goods shall not be allowed in or that no goods shall be allowed in unless a definite indication of origin is given. All that has to be done by the machinery to be provided.  We have enlarged the scope of the old Act by making it apply not merely to misdescription but in certain circumstances by imposing an obligation to mark the goods properly so as not to have goods coming in either on importation or when they are being sold without any description whatever.  In the case of the sale of imported goods bearing the name or trademark of Saorstát Eireann manufacturer or trader or place name in Saorstát Eireann these automatically without reference to the Merchandise Marks Commission cannot be brought in or sold unless accompanied at the same time by a particular mark indicating origin.</P>
    <P>In connection with the machinery of the Bill I would point out, although it has not yet been determined, that the Merchandise Marks Commission shall in personnel be the same as the Tariff Commission.  It will be our object to have the double functions carried out by the same body.  I think that the work that the Tariff Commission does fits it to take the rather rapid decisions arising under this Act.  There will be no necessity, I think, to duplicate that Commission.  We are leaving ourselves liberty to meet peculiar circumstances that may arise.  It may be that in the beginning when the Bill <Col N="49" /> passes into law there may be such a rush of applications that the Tariff Commission may not be able to deal speedily enough with them.  Under these circumstances it might be necessary for a short period of time to appoint somebody other than the Tariff Commission, but in the main the idea would be to occupy the Tariff Commission with the task that is outlined in this Bill.  We do not believe that there will be the same necessity for prolonged enquiry as to whether or not goods should be marked in a particular way.  If that is considered necessary expert evidence may have to be given as to the type of mark that ought to be affixed to special classes of goods, the way it ought to be affixed and so on.  The details will require more consideration, but I think the general principle of the Bill ought to be acceptable.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelComynKC" hpid="Mr. Comyn Mr. Comyn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Comyn</NameTxt>
      <P>A Bill of this character is long overdue.  The last Merchandise Marks Act of any consequence was passed in the year 1891.  The year 1891 represents an old world.  Trade has changed very considerably since then.  Countries are anxious to press forward and to sell their goods in other countries. They have resorted to various devices for the purpose of inducing the inhabitants of one country to buy the products of another country.  Some of these devices are fair, but some of them verge very closely on fraud.  I will give one example.  I believe it is a fact that foreign goods imported into this country have these two words on them, &ldquo;Madin Irelande.&rdquo; To the ordinary person that would convey &ldquo;Made in Ireland,&rdquo; but these words mean no such thing.  It is right that a matter of that kind should be stopped.  I welcome the Bill as showing that the Ministry have some information as to the course and the development of foreign commerce and foreign competition.  I hope they are alive to other features of that, including its financial features.  This Bill shows that the Ministry have been considering this question.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="50" /> My objection to the Bill is that it seeks to establish another board, another commission.  If a person objects to a foreign manufactured article coming in in competition with the article that he is making himself, he has first to organise his trade and then his trade has to go before a commission. The commission will then have to consider it just as if it were an application for a tariff, and after argument on one side and the other the decision may go against him.  It seems to me that a provision of that kind is not sufficiently vigorous to meet the situation existing at the present time.  I think all goods coming from foreign countries should have either on the article itself or on the package in which it is contained the country of origin.  I think that by a general rule of that character the Minister could get rid perhaps of his commission.  Perhaps he might not be able to get rid of this commission, but it seems to me that he could and that the simpler the regulations made the better.  The Minister is going to have a commission for trade marks and he is going to have a board for mines and minerals.</P>
    <P>I remember in former times, before the Minister came into public life, that we used to have a tremendous complaint about the number of boards that were being established.  I think that boards are like animals of low organism: they seem to have the faculty of multiplying rapidly.  The Minister has said that anything that is to be said on this Bill can best be said on Committee.  If I were in order on the Committee Stage I would move that the section relating to the commission should be deleted and that we should take a decision that no articles imported from foreign countries should be sold here unless they set forth the country of origin. Perhaps as a compromise in respect to some commodities we might be inclined to agree that they should be represented as foreign.  In any case I think this Bill will prevent the kind of fraud to which I have alluded, the fraud which suggests that articles of foreign manufacture are <Col N="51" /> made in Ireland.  I would not have given that example unless I had it on a most reliable authority.  I have confirmed the information that has been supplied to me.  It shows to Senators and ought to show the Ministry that international trade is in such a position now and competition is so severe that the utmost vigilance and promptness are necessary. In my opinion there is no necessity for the expense and the delay of having to make an application to a commission.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MauriceMoore" hpid="Colonel Moore Colonel Moore">
      <NameTxt>Colonel Moore</NameTxt>
      <P>I want to support the statement that has been made by Senator Comyn.  I believe it was always desirable and that it is now absolutely necessary that all goods coming into this country should be marked with the country of origin. There may be some few things, animals and the like, that it need not apply to. Speaking generally, I am strongly of the opinion that goods coming into this country for sale should be marked with the country of origin.  That has been done in other countries, and I do not see why it should not be done here.  It is being done in England.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>It is not done at all.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MauriceMoore" hpid="Colonel Moore Colonel Moore">
      <NameTxt>Colonel Moore</NameTxt>
      <P>It has been done in America.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelComynKC" hpid="Mr. Comyn Mr. Comyn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Comyn</NameTxt>
      <P>They are marked foreign.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>Not until they have appeared before a commission.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MauriceMoore" hpid="Colonel Moore Colonel Moore">
      <NameTxt>Colonel Moore</NameTxt>
      <P>Will the Minister accept &ldquo;foreign&rdquo;?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>Under the English conditions, yes.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MauriceMoore" hpid="Colonel Moore Colonel Moore">
      <NameTxt>Colonel Moore</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not know what they are.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>And the Senator introduces that without knowing.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MauriceMoore" hpid="Colonel Moore Colonel Moore">
      <NameTxt>Colonel Moore</NameTxt>
      <P>I will accept &ldquo;foreign&rdquo; temporarily if the Minister will not go any further. His Department and himself are reluctant to adopt anything except what is according to his own temperament and that of his officials. <Col N="52" /> Perhaps he is reluctant that English articles should be stamped.  I do not know, but that is my opinion, and I believe the opinion of practically every one in the Seanad.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelComynKC" hpid="Mr. Comyn Mr. Comyn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Comyn</NameTxt>
      <P>On a point of order, I hope the Minister will explain his interruption during Senator Colonel Moore's speech.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Cathaoirleach Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>That does not constitute a point of order.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasForan" hpid="Mr. Foran Mr. Foran">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Foran</NameTxt>
      <P>Are there any safeguards in the Bill to ensure that the brand will be allowed to remain on various articles?  After they are imported, articles are produced for sale in the shops.  I could instance a particular article which is heavily and severely branded when it is coming into the country, but when it is placed on the counter for sale the brand disappears and very often the article is represented as Irish produce.  I have heard great complaints about activities in this direction.  I would like to know if there is any power given by this measure to prevent that taking place.</P>
      <P>What steps, for instance, will be taken to ensure that Chinese bacon is not sold as Irish produce?  That sort of practice goes on to a very considerable extent, and if this Bill will do anything to prevent or limit that activity it is certainly well worth while.  I think it will be very difficult to prevent activities of that type.  Placing marks upon an article in order to show its country of origin is important enough in its way, but another important aspect of the question is that every purchaser should be entitled to get the home-produced article if he pays for it; in other words, foreign produce should not be passed over to the purchaser as Irish.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator Comyn desires to delete the sections in this Bill which relate to the establishment of a Commission.  The Senator can move to delete these sections if he thinks he can convince the Seanad that it is wise to do so; but by deleting the sections he does not change the system very much, because somebody has to decide.  If, for instance, the Senator substitutes my Department as the Department <Col N="53" /> which should decide whether a mark is to be put on, and, if so, how it is to be affixed and what type of mark it shall be, I would be put to the very same trouble as the Commission to gather together those expert in the matter, and the only people expert in such a matter are the traders concerned. I would have to have evidence from sundry people with regard to specific articles.  The mark that will be affixed to a piece of bacon might be slightly different to the mark on, say, a bag of nails.</P>
      <P>It is easy enough for Senators to say in a casual, haphazard way: &ldquo;Mark everything and let the trade take the consequences.&rdquo;  Even if you decide to mark everything there is an enormous amount of work still to be done requiring the attendance of expert witnesses, namely, the people interested in the trade, in order to find out even such small points of detail as what type the mark is to be, what is to be the degree that will be called conspicuous, and how is the mark to be attached to specific articles.</P>
      <P>With regard to the matter to which Senator Foran referred, we have importation restriction orders and orders relating to the restriction of sale.  We allow for both cases.  It may be that a restriction order with regard to importation without mark will be sufficient&mdash; in other words, it may be clearly seen that a mark put on during importation will have to be so indelibly attached that there will be no necessity to bother about it any further from the point of view of sale.  There may be other articles upon which the mark might be put in order to pass the Customs, and it could be easily removed before the point of sale.  That can be dealt with under this legislation by a special sale restriction order.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Senator Comyn, who spoke with a little knowledge on this matter, and Senator Colonel Moore, who spoke with none, have urged that we shall just mark the article.  Senator Comyn complains that this legislation is not vigorous enough.  It is not vigour we want; a little bit of sanity is welcome now and again.  In the case of the bull that is being led away from a china <Col N="54" /> shop after destroying all the beautiful china, it could not very well be complained that he was not vigorous enough.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MauriceMoore" hpid="Colonel Moore Colonel Moore">
      <NameTxt>Colonel Moore</NameTxt>
      <P>An effort should have been made to keep him out of it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>The effort in this instance should be directed to keeping the delicate china shop of trade out of the melée.  Just a little bit of order and sanity is required in attaching these restrictions on trade.  What is the good of attaching marks with regard to foreign origin on goods not produced here?  There is going to be no protective effect.  There is nothing to protect.  Someone has to pay for the cost incurred in putting on these things.  There is going to be a definite restriction on trade in some way.  The point of principle is quite simple; the point of detail is the difficult one.</P>
      <P>I have been asked by a Senator, who apparently does not understand what the English conditions are, if I would be prepared to accept the English conditions. I do not think they are so restricted as this.  They have the 1887 Act in England, and that Act was amended in 1926, and they established this system of a Commission to which application will be made.  Inquiries will then be instituted and a decision eventually given.</P>
      <P>Senator Comyn welcomes this Bill because he thinks it will enable us to meet such a case as he speaks of&mdash;an article coming in with the two words &ldquo;made in&rdquo; together, and then the word &ldquo;Ireland&rdquo; or some corruption of the word &ldquo;Ireland&rdquo; put after that. You do not require the present Bill to get after that.  The Senator says that he has reliable authority for saying that such articles come in.  I would like to have instances of such articles coming in.  It might involve a dereliction of duty on the part of the Customs authorities if there are such articles admitted.  I do not believe there are.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelComynKC" hpid="Mr. Comyn Mr. Comyn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Comyn</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not think the Minister ought to doubt my word.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>I am sure the Senator has made a very accurate statement regarding what has been said to <Col N="55" /> him; it is the representations made to the Senator that I would like some information about.  The Act of 1887 allows for the prevention of the importation of articles bearing a false trade description.  The practice of the Revenue Commissioners is that goods marked in the way the Senator describes would be forfeited on any attempt being made to bring them into the country.</P>
      <P>Question&mdash;&ldquo;That the Merchandise Marks Bill, 1931 be now read a Second Time&rdquo;&mdash;agreed to.  Committee Stage fixed for Wednesday, 16th December.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Senator's" RHead="Resignation">
    <Title>Senator's Resignation.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Cathaoirleach Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I greatly regret to announce to the House that Senator The Right Hon.  Alfred Byrne, Lord Mayor of Dublin, has written to me to-day resigning his seat in the Seanad. It will be necessary for the House to make an order directing the Clerk to send notice in writing of the vacancy to the Minister for Local Government and Public Health in order to cause such vacancy to be filled.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasForan" hpid="Mr. Foran Mr. Foran">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Foran</NameTxt>
      <P>Could we not postpone this matter until after the elections next January?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Cathaoirleach Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>We have no option but to send notice of the vacancy in writing to the Minister.</P>
      <P>Ordered accordingly.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Mines and Minerals Bill," RHead="1931&mdash;Committee Stage">
    <Title>Mines and Minerals Bill, 1931&mdash;Committee Stage.</Title>
    <P>(1)  In this Act&mdash;</P>
    <P>the expression &ldquo;the Minister&rdquo; means the Minister for Industry and Commerce;</P>
    <P>the expression &ldquo;exclusive mining right&rdquo; means the exclusive right of mining and taking minerals and digging and searching for minerals; the word &ldquo;rent&rdquo; includes any periodical payment in the nature of rent; the expression &ldquo;land purchase annuity&rdquo; means a land purchase annuity payable under the Land <Col N="56" /> Purchase Acts to the Irish Land Commission;</P>
    <P>the word &ldquo;inspector&rdquo; includes any person authorised in writing (either generally or for a special purpose) by the Minister to exercise all or any of the powers or perform any of the duties conferred or imposed on an inspector by this Act;</P>
    <P>the expression &ldquo;prescribed&rdquo; means prescribed by the Minister by regulations made under this Act.</P>
    <P>(2)  In Parts IV., V. and VIII. of this Act&mdash;</P>
    <P>the expression &ldquo;minerals&rdquo; includes all minerals and substances in or under land obtainable by underground or surface working.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MauriceMoore" hpid="Colonel Moore Colonel Moore">
      <NameTxt>Colonel Moore</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment 1:&mdash;</P>
      <P>Section 1, sub-section (1).  After the word &ldquo;Commerce&rdquo; in line 22 to insert the words &ldquo;the expression &lsquo;mineral&rsquo; means any material substance, not being animal or vegetable, which is a product of the bowels of the earth.&rdquo;</P>
      <P>Amendment 2 deals with the words &ldquo;and substances&rdquo; and, perhaps, I will be allowed to speak upon both amendments at the same time.  The second amendment has relation to sub-section (2).</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Cathaoirleach Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>The Senator may adopt that course.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MauriceMoore" hpid="Colonel Moore Colonel Moore">
      <NameTxt>Colonel Moore</NameTxt>
      <P>I am not in any way opposing this section.  I am only trying to get an explanation about certain words that are included in the Bill.  I know quite well that the definition of the word &ldquo;minerals&rdquo; has caused great anxiety to very many scientific people. I am aware that it is a difficult job to invent an explanation.  I adopted the expedient of going to the Oxford Dictionary, which is recognised as the best authority in connection with English words.  I took this word for word from the Oxford Dictionary, and I do not think I could do better than that.  I do not intend to try to do better than that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Cathaoirleach Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I am glad to know the source of the Senator's inspiration.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="57" />
    <Speaker pid="MauriceMoore" hpid="Colonel Moore Colonel Moore">
      <NameTxt>Colonel Moore</NameTxt>
      <P>The reason I want some definiteness in this matter is because there is a certain claim to interference with private rights and property.  I think this matter should be explained very definitely and clearly.  Speaking on this matter the other day, the Minister said that they adopted this wide expression because they did not wish anybody to make objection on any particular point.  I am not sure if that was the exact reason or whether it was they found it too difficult to get a better explanation of the word.  Later on I will come to the word &ldquo;substance.&rdquo;  I mentioned this matter in the House the other day, and I daresay there is no use in repeating the argument.  I looked up the dictionary also on that point and I repeated some of the explanations given in relation to the word &ldquo;substance.&rdquo;  The explanations cover practically everything that could be imagined, not only materials in the bowels of the earth, but things above the earth such as trees, grass, oats, turbary and hundreds of other things. Everything is included that lies on or under the ground.</P>
      <P>Surely the Minister does not want to claim all those things?  It seems to be unreasonable.  I am sure the President could not possibly have read this Bill. We all know how anxious he is to preserve property rights.  He is very particular about that, and I am sure he would not countenance a communistic measure of this nature.  I do not think the Soviet ever got quite so far as this Bill seeks to get.  I would like to have a good explanation of what &ldquo;minerals&rdquo; or &ldquo;substances&rdquo; means.  Water, for instance, could be described as a substance. The commonsense of Senators will suggest that any claim by the State to take over everything under and above the earth in the Free State area is a most unreasonable proposition. Such a proposal ought not to be permitted to go through, if it were only from the point of view of a defence of private property.  I have taken the best method I could to make a change, and I submit it to the favourable consideration of the Seanad.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="58" />
    <Speaker pid="MichaelComynKC" hpid="Mr. Comyn Mr. Comyn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Comyn</NameTxt>
      <P>I think Senator Moore's definition of the word &ldquo;minerals&rdquo; goes as near to the truth as anything I have ever seen.  I am sorry that the Senator's great rectitude compelled him to admit that it was taken from the Oxford Dictionary, because it was almost worthy of himself.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Minister for Industry and Commerce (Mr. McGilligan) Patrick McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Industry and Commerce (Mr. McGilligan)</NameTxt>
      <P>Very nearly.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardWilson" hpid="Mr. Wilson Mr. Wilson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Wilson</NameTxt>
      <P>What about coal?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelComynKC" hpid="Mr. Comyn Mr. Comyn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Comyn</NameTxt>
      <P>I would like the Seanad to understand that the Minister does not attempt to define &ldquo;minerals.&rdquo; Later on he says that minerals shall include such and such a thing.  It is almost impossible of definition.  Every substance in the bowels of the earth, with the exception of royal minerals, has been subject to decision at some time or other.  If the Minister will now accept a definite decision with regard to the meaning of minerals, I think Senator Colonel Moore has offered him the best form of words that could possibly be suggested.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SamuelBrownKC" hpid="Mr. Brown Mr. Brown">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Brown</NameTxt>
      <P>I am afraid that Senator Colonel Moore and his friend the Oxford Dictionary have gone too far, or perhaps I should say too deep, for the purposes of this Bill.  The definition which Senator Colonel Moore proposes would include far more than the Minister intends to include in the Bill.  It would include, for instance, granite boulders lying upon the surface of the earth.  Nothing comes more directly from the bowels of the earth than granite boulders.  They have been&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EileenCostello" hpid="Mrs. Costello Mrs. Costello">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Costello</NameTxt>
      <P>Irrupted.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SamuelBrownKC" hpid="Mr. Brown Mr. Brown">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Brown</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes, irrupted by volcanic action, and they certainly are not minerals within the meaning of the Bill.  We know they are on the surface of the earth and are used by the person in the occupation of the land where they lie for building his fences and so forth.  They are used in a great many parts of the country for making granite setts and kerbstones.  They are not minerals within the meaning of the Bill.  I agree with Senator Comyn that it is quite impossible to give a definition of minerals which will suit every case.  The meaning of the word &ldquo;minerals&rdquo; depends partly upon the <Col N="59" /> instrument in which it is used, whether it is an Act of Parliament, a lease or an agreement.  It may, too, depend upon the locality in relation to which it is used.  It may even depend upon local customs.  You cannot get any definition which will suit every instrument in every case.  I submit that the Minister has here a definition which absolutely suits the purpose of the Bill: &ldquo;the expression &lsquo;minerals&rsquo; includes all minerals and substances in or under land obtainable by underground or surface working.&rdquo;  I cannot imagine a definition more general and yet one which would exclude things not intended to be covered by the Bill.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MauriceMoore" hpid="Colonel Moore Colonel Moore">
      <NameTxt>Colonel Moore</NameTxt>
      <P>Does the Senator mean to say that the word &ldquo;substance&rdquo; does not include &ldquo;granite&rdquo;?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>There is something more stated.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SamuelBrownKC" hpid="Mr. Brown Mr. Brown">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Brown</NameTxt>
      <P>It must be obtainable by underground or surface working.  The word &ldquo;substance&rdquo; by itself would include almost anything.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasLinehan" hpid="Mr. Linehan Mr. Linehan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Linehan</NameTxt>
      <P>The occupiers of land in Ireland are very much affected by the definition that is given to the term &ldquo;minerals.&rdquo;  In this Bill two classes of minerals are referred to.  We have the minerals owned by the State and the minerals privately owned.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SamuelBrownKC" hpid="Mr. Brown Mr. Brown">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Brown</NameTxt>
      <P>They are the same minerals.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasLinehan" hpid="Mr. Linehan Mr. Linehan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Linehan</NameTxt>
      <P>In the case of minerals owned by the State and granted to them under the Land Acts of 1903 and 1923, the definition expressly excludes all stones, gravel, sand and clay.  By defining minerals now to include every substance, you take away from the occupiers of land their right to these four things: stone, sand, gravel, and clay.  If you take these things away what have you left?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>Do we take them away?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelComynKC" hpid="Mr. Comyn Mr. Comyn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Comyn</NameTxt>
      <P>No.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>We do not take them away.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="60" />
    <Speaker pid="ThomasLinehan" hpid="Mr. Linehan Mr. Linehan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Linehan</NameTxt>
      <P>This proposes to give the minerals to the State, and if you say that minerals include everything do you not take away stone, gravel, sand, and clay?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>No.  You give yourself the right to dispose of these if they are declared by a court decision to be minerals.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasLinehan" hpid="Mr. Linehan Mr. Linehan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Linehan</NameTxt>
      <P>I would be satisfied if it is made clear that these things are not interfered with, and that the occupiers of land still have the right, the same as they had before, to dispose of these four substances.  I could not agree to Senator Colonel Moore's amendment unless those substances are excepted from it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardWilson" hpid="Mr. Wilson Mr. Wilson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Wilson</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator Colonel Moore's amendment indicates that minerals mean any substance, not being animal or vegetable, which is the product of the bowels of the earth.  Coal must be regarded as a substance.  It is a mineral, and I think the Senator's definition would not be correct at all, because everybody understands that coal, while being regarded as a mineral, is a vegetable substance; it is the result of vegetation, and therefore the Senator's definition would be wrong.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JosephOConnor" hpid="Mr. O'Connor Mr. O'Connor">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Connor</NameTxt>
      <P>I wish to support Senator Linehan's contention as regards those four minerals.  I think it ought to be made very clear to the people in the country that these substances are simply and solely the property of the owner of the land.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>I think it is necessary, in discussing any of these amendments by way of definition, to take a glance at the whole lot of them.  I explained here on the Second Stage that the main purpose of the Bill was to provide the legislation which was looked to under Article 11 of the Constitution. Subsidiary to that we did bring forward certain matters which relate to mines and minerals in private ownership, but for specific purposes and nearly always for the purpose of allowing the owner of these mines and minerals better facilities for the working of the property which he owns.  We do depart from that principle with regard <Col N="61" /> to mines and minerals in private ownership in one sub-section of a particular section.</P>
      <P>One part of the Bill relates to mines and minerals governed by Article 11, gripped by the State, and the other part of the Bill refers to mines and minerals in private ownership.  There is no definition in the definition clause which relates to minerals in Part III; that is to say, the Part which talks of mines and minerals in the possession of the State.  The reason we do not define minerals is simply that we have to fill a certain gap.  Article 11 says:</P>
      <P>All the lands and waters, mines and minerals, within the territory of the Irish Free State ... shall, from and after the date of the coming into operation of this Constitution, belong to the Irish Free State...</P>
      <P>All mines and minerals, not defined, belong to the State excepting those in which there was a valid private right existing at the date of the passing of the Constitution.</P>
      <P>We submit to the Oireachtas regulations to enable somebody under the Constitution to dispose of whatever is hereafter found by the Court to be included in the term &ldquo;mines and minerals.&rdquo;  Consequently we do not define the term because by definition you might cut down your power of disposing of certain things.  It would not be an amendment of Article 11, because you cannot do that by a definition in an Act here, but you certainly might cut down the power I have referred to. Supposing we cut out coal.  Supposing we put in a definition section relating to Part III of the Bill and indicated that minerals there shall not include coal.  What would be the effect of that? You would not prevent Article 11 from gripping coal for the State, but you would prevent yourself from allowing anybody to work coal.  You put it into the dead hand of the State and you do not allow anybody to work it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>You must not have any definition in regard to mines and minerals in so far as mines and minerals are brought into State control by Article 11.  If Senators will look at Section 4 (1) (d) they will see: &ldquo;If for the purposes of this Act any question arises as to whether <Col N="62" /> any particular substance can be mined and taken under any particular such mining right...the Minister may refer such question to the Irish Land Commission, exclusive of the Judicial Commissioner, for their determination.&rdquo; That paragraph refers to whether or not mines and mineral rights have been reserved through any of the Land Purchase Acts.  We leave that for judicial determination.  If we delete any definition and simply use the same words as occur in Article 11, we leave it with whatever is given to us under Article 11.  We have power to dispose of it under this Bill.</P>
    <P>We define minerals in a very wide way over the other Parts of the Bill&mdash; IV, V and VIII.  We set out that the expression &ldquo;minerals&rdquo; includes all minerals and substances in or under land obtainable by underground or surface working.  It would be impossible to do as Senator Colonel Moore did, take out the word &ldquo;substances&rdquo; and then give some lore as to what the meaning of substances is.  It must be taken in relation to the words surrounding it: &ldquo;Substances in or under land obtainable by underground or surface working.&rdquo; The question of oats is definitely excluded from this.  We have a very wide definition of minerals for that section.  I think it is necessary. If Senators will look at the Part of the Bill which deals with minerals in private possession&mdash;Part IV&mdash;I think they will see that the full effect of Part IV is to enable people who own mineral substances, but who are prevented from working them because there is somebody who should join in the working and who is reluctant to do so, to work them.  We are coming to the aid of the owner of these minerals in pretty nearly every particular.  We go against him in one case.  Look at the restrictions that we have hedged around this.  The owner is to be helped, but only if it has become clear to the Minister that there is no other way to get the minerals worked.  Secondly, there has to be reference to the Board, and, thirdly, anybody who objects can make representations to the Board. The Board has to report, and the Minister has to consider the report and <Col N="63" /> to decide whether in the public interest the thing is required.  I think there is no necessity to be alarmed at that wide definition of the word &ldquo;minerals&rdquo; in Parts IV, V and VIII of the Bill, because it is mainly for the aid of a person who owns minerals.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MauriceMoore" hpid="Colonel Moore Colonel Moore">
      <NameTxt>Colonel Moore</NameTxt>
      <P>And substances.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>I am afraid I cannot get the bogey &ldquo;substances&rdquo; out of the Colonel's mind.  &ldquo;The expression &lsquo;minerals&rsquo; includes all minerals and substances in or under land obtainable by underground or surface working.&rdquo; That is my definition.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MauriceMoore" hpid="Colonel Moore Colonel Moore">
      <NameTxt>Colonel Moore</NameTxt>
      <P>&ldquo;Substances&rdquo; as given here has no definition.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>It is limited by the words which follow, &ldquo;in or under land obtainable by underground or surface working.&rdquo;  I think most of the amendments that have been put down have been put down because there was no complete analysis made by those who put them down of the purposes of the measure.  We must fill the gap that is left by Article 11.  We fill it by allowing ourselves full power to dispose of any matter hereafter found to be a mineral, but we do not decide what are minerals for the purpose of this.  We leave it for judicial determination hereafter.  We adopt a very wide definition, because we want it to apply in the widest possible fashion, so as to come to the aid of the person who owns a mineral.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MauriceMoore" hpid="Colonel Moore Colonel Moore">
      <NameTxt>Colonel Moore</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister always assumes that nobody has looked at the Bill except himself.  The reason I put in this definition of the word &ldquo;mineral&rdquo; was on account of the word &ldquo;substances,&rdquo; which was used in the next paragraph.  On account of that I made an attempt at a definition.  I do not understand what Senator Brown means by saying it would narrow it. However, the word &ldquo;substances&rdquo; here includes &ldquo;all minerals and substances in or under land obtainable by underground or surface working.&rdquo;&ldquo;In or under.&rdquo;  If there was &ldquo;under&rdquo; only we might suppose it dealt only with things that were under the ground.  If you said &ldquo;in&rdquo; only it might possibly <Col N="64" /> be understood in the same way and not on the surface.  When you add &ldquo;in&rdquo; and &ldquo;under&rdquo; together if &ldquo;in&rdquo; means anything it must mean &ldquo;over.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>And &ldquo;under&rdquo; would mean on.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MauriceMoore" hpid="Colonel Moore Colonel Moore">
      <NameTxt>Colonel Moore</NameTxt>
      <P>If you say &ldquo;in&rdquo; is &ldquo;under&rdquo;&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>It means on top of it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MauriceMoore" hpid="Colonel Moore Colonel Moore">
      <NameTxt>Colonel Moore</NameTxt>
      <P>Either &ldquo;in&rdquo; is useless in it or it means &ldquo;over.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>If &ldquo;in&rdquo; means on top what would &ldquo;under&rdquo; mean?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MauriceMoore" hpid="Colonel Moore Colonel Moore">
      <NameTxt>Colonel Moore</NameTxt>
      <P>If you have &ldquo;under the ground&rdquo; there is some sense in it, but if you have &ldquo;in&rdquo; and &ldquo;under&rdquo; there is no sense.  The word &ldquo;substance&rdquo; is the widest possible term that you can find.  It is an absurd word to use here.  The Minister says that will be for judicial interpretation.  How is a judge or anybody else to decide a word that nobody can define?  I maintain that the word &ldquo;substance&rdquo; is quite useless in that way.  It either means something or nothing.  He does not tell us what it is.  Let him leave it out.  Let him say only minerals and leave the judge to decide what is a mineral and what is not.  The Minister gets out of his difficulty by saying the judge decides.  Putting in these ridiculous words &ldquo;in and under&rdquo; and &ldquo;substances&rdquo; only embarrasses the whole situation.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>Where does a judge come in on my definition?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MauriceMoore" hpid="Colonel Moore Colonel Moore">
      <NameTxt>Colonel Moore</NameTxt>
      <P>A judge is no more a genius than anybody else.  He can only take the word you give him, and if you give him a word that has no sense how is he to define it?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>When will he be called on to define it?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MauriceMoore" hpid="Colonel Moore Colonel Moore">
      <NameTxt>Colonel Moore</NameTxt>
      <P>You said to leave it to the courts.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>We leave a particular thing but not that definition.  It does not apply to this Part of the Bill.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MauriceMoore" hpid="Colonel Moore Colonel Moore">
      <NameTxt>Colonel Moore</NameTxt>
      <P>A judge is not to decide this question at all?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="65" />
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>No.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MauriceMoore" hpid="Colonel Moore Colonel Moore">
      <NameTxt>Colonel Moore</NameTxt>
      <P>This is the first time you said that.  Anyway, a judge eventually has to decide these things when they come before him.  The fact is that these words were put in intentionally or unintentionally, and no one can understand them.  I will withdraw my first amendment, but I will have to have the question in regard to &ldquo;substances&rdquo; put.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>I want again to repeat that we do not define &ldquo;minerals&rdquo; for the purpose of Part III of this Bill.  That is deliberate, and no judge will hereafter, so far as Part III is concerned and so far as the State representatives are concerned, ever have to decide on the phrase &ldquo;and substances.&rdquo;  If the Senator will only look he will see that there is no definition which applies to Part III in the definition clause.  In the next amendment, the Senator intends to wipe out the words &ldquo;and substances.&rdquo;  That only applies to Parts IV, V and VIII.  Let us say it applies mainly to Part IV, and that applies to mines in private ownership and the intention is to help the owner of mines, including substances of a particular type, to get better facilities for the working of mines and the substances which he owns.  It is impossible, I think, to put in any definition in Part I.  If you put in a definition in Part I it is a definition that is going to run right through the whole legislation.</P>
      <P>Amendment 1 by leave withdrawn.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MauriceMoore" hpid="Colonel Moore Colonel Moore">
      <NameTxt>Colonel Moore</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment 2:&mdash;</P>
      <P>Section 1, sub-section (2).</P>
      <P>To delete in line 38 the words &ldquo;and substances.&rdquo;  I have said practically all I want to say about this matter. I maintain that the word &ldquo;substances&rdquo; there is perfectly useless and I would ask the Seanad to agree to have it taken out.</P>
      <P>Amendment put, and declared lost.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasLinehan" hpid="Mr. Linehan Mr. Linehan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Linehan</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment 3:</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Section 1, sub-section (2).  After the word &ldquo;substances&rdquo; in line 38 <Col N="66" /> to insert the words &ldquo;except any stone, gravel, sand or clay.</P>
    <P>This section states:</P>
    <P>(2) In Parts IV and V and VIII of this Act&mdash;the expression &ldquo;minerals&rdquo; includes all minerals and substances in or under land obtainable by underground or surface working.</P>
    <P>This section refers to privately-owned grounds.  It would apply to the cases of land purchased before the Act of 1903, where generally the landlords reserved the mineral rights of their lands before selling to the tenants. In those cases, it is the landlord who owns the mineral rights, generally speaking.  If by any definition in this Bill we decide that the term &ldquo;minerals&rdquo; includes other substances, there is a danger that the rights of the tenant and the occupiers would be in jeopardy and that they can legally be prevented from utilising the stone, sand, gravel and peat on their holdings.  I might say that those words in my amendment are taken from the Land Acts of 1903 and 1923.  I will quote for you Section 13 of the Land Act of 1903. The Act of 1923 contains a provision which is practically the same.  The section reads:&mdash;</P>
    <P>(3) On the sale under the Land Purchase Acts of any land by the Land Commission, or of any land comprised in an estate by the owner of the estate, there shall be reserved, in the prescribed manner, to the Commission the exclusive right of mining and taking minerals and digging and searching for minerals, on or under that land, and the said right shall be disposed of by the Commission in manner hereafter to be provided by Parliament:</P>
    <P>Provided that this sub-section shall not apply&mdash;</P>
    <P>(a)  to any demesne or other land resold in pursuance of Section 3 of this Act; or</P>
    <P>(b)  to any such right which constitutes a superior interest, or which is vested in the Crown; or</P>
    <P>(c)  to any stone, gravel, sand or clay.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="67" /> A contract has been made between the State and the tenant purchasers whereby the purchasers agree to pay a certain sum as annuity every year on the basis that the stone, gravel, sand and clay in their holdings are their property.  If the State by any means defines minerals to include all substances which of course would include these four substances I have mentioned, it will have the effect of putting the State in the position of breaking the contract with the tenants.  I trust that the Seanad will make it clear, in any legislation that they pass as regards minerals, that the bargain made with the tenants in 1903 and 1923 will be kept and that there will be no danger of any interference with their right to deal with these four substances.  I have quoted in my amendment the words exactly as they appear in the Land Acts.  I might have put in turf or peat but I wanted to keep to the words that were already in the Acts to which I have referred.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelComynKC" hpid="Mr. Comyn Mr. Comyn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Comyn</NameTxt>
      <P>I think it is much to be regretted that the Minister, in framing this very difficult measure, had not the assistance of Senator Linehan who knows so much about the question he is dealing with.  I said this is a difficult measure.  By Article 11 of the Constitution it is provided that all mines and minerals vested in any Public Department shall be the property of Saorstát Eireann and shall be administered as may be decided by Parliament.  Every word of that Article 11 of the Constitution is pregnant with meaning.  All mines and minerals vested in any Public Department!  What are mines and minerals?  It has been held that limestone is a mineral; it is carbonate of lime.  It has been held that <i>disjecta membra</i> of mammoth animals are not minerals.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardWilson" hpid="Mr. Wilson Mr. Wilson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Wilson</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelComynKC" hpid="Mr. Comyn Mr. Comyn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Comyn</NameTxt>
      <P>It has been held that they are not.  The point is what is a mineral?  If coal is a mineral, and undoubtedly it is, why should not turf be a substance of a mineral character such as Senator Moore has <Col N="68" /> indicated in his speech?  That shows you the difficulty of the subject in relation to what a mineral is, and the Minister was quite right in omitting to give any definition of a mineral. He only says &ldquo;in Parts IV, V and VIII of the Act the expression &lsquo;minerals&rsquo; includes all minerals and substances.&rdquo;  He defines minerals by using the very word minerals.  That shows the difficulty of the position.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I hope that Senators were able to give full attention to the speech which was made by Senator Linehan.  It was so concentrated that it was hard to follow it, unless you knew beforehand almost everything he was referring to.  What is the position in regard to minerals in the Free State? First of all, the owner-in-fee from the skin to the centre of the earth, is the tenant <i>in capite</i>, the head man&mdash; there were very few of these in Ireland.  In Thomond there was only one, and all the smaller gentry and landlords in Clare, Limerick and parts of Tipperary were only tenants of the House of O'Brien, and all the mines and minerals are reserved in the leases.  Therefore, when these landlords sold their estates the mines and minerals were reserved to the person who claimed to be the representative of the House of Thomond. They are not vested in the State and are in private ownership.  Again, in the case of land sold under the Ashbourne Act the sale was carried out by means of a conveyance to the tenant and the tenant has now in his possession the mines and minerals as well as the grass.  That state of things continued until the Act of 1903 was passed, the Act referred to by Senator Linehan.  On a sale under the Act of 1903 by a landlord the mines and minerals became vested in the Land Commission.  There were exceptions to that vesting.  The exceptions are set out in the Act of 1903.  One exception was that the minerals of any demesne did not go to the Land Commission, and the second exception is, that stone, gravel, sand or clay did not go to the Land Commission.  Now stone includes limestone, which is a mineral, and gravel might be limestone. I have often considered that <Col N="69" /> section, and I believe that clay there would not include china clay or potters' clay.  Nearly all the tenants in Ireland own the stone, gravel, sand and clay on their land, and nearly all the great lords in Ireland, especially in the South, still own the minerals on their land and they are not caught by Article 11 of the Constitution at all.  The Minister understood all that and of course he has to deal with that situation as it presents itself to him.  What does he do? He is quite right in saying that he does not attempt a definition.  He says the &ldquo;expression &lsquo;minerals&rsquo; includes all minerals and substances in or under land obtainable by underground or surface working.&rdquo;  That would be all right, I think, if the Minister could see his way to accept the amendment of Senator Linehan.</P>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. Johnson Mr. Johnson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Johnson</NameTxt>
      <P>That would kill all your argument.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelComynKC" hpid="Mr. Comyn Mr. Comyn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Comyn</NameTxt>
      <P>Not at all.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>Certainly.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelComynKC" hpid="Mr. Comyn Mr. Comyn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Comyn</NameTxt>
      <P>I have not argued, so far as I know, up to the present.  I have given a statement of the facts as a foundation for an argument. There is no use in making an interruption. This thing cannot be captured by a <i>tour de force.</i>  You cannot take away the rights of the farmers of Ireland without full consideration. Here is what Senator Linehan suggests and I think very wisely: &ldquo;Section 1, sub-section (2).  After the word &lsquo;substances&rsquo; in line 38 to insert the words &lsquo;except any stone, gravel, sand or clay.&rsquo;&rdquo;  It would read then and, as I think, rightly: &ldquo;In Parts IV, V and VIII of this Act&mdash; the expression &lsquo;minerals&rsquo; includes all minerals and substances except any stone, gravel, sand or clay in or under land obtainable by underground or surface working.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>In my opinion, and I say it with great deference to the experience of Senator Linehan in this matter, that is absolutely and entirely right and the Minister cannot meet that argument by simply saying it is a definition applicable to Part IV, because what does Part IV do?  Parts IV, V and <Col N="70" /> VIII of this Bill are the Parts that enable the State to come inside the boundary of a man's holding and dig up under his ground and allow another man to dig it up also.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>Where is that?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelComynKC" hpid="Mr. Comyn Mr. Comyn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Comyn</NameTxt>
      <P>I thought now that the Minister would be a little more patient.  Part IV of the Bill is the Part that provides for the grant of rights in non-State mines and minerals.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>Grant to whom?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelComynKC" hpid="Mr. Comyn Mr. Comyn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Comyn</NameTxt>
      <P>To exploiters.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>Look at it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelComynKC" hpid="Mr. Comyn Mr. Comyn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Comyn</NameTxt>
      <P>I have read it, and I have something to say about it.  I hope that Senators will consider it a little further.  It means if a man, in the opinion of the Minister or the opinion of his Board, acts the part of the dog in the manger they are going on to the land.  If you have a little bit of property and if some exploiter or prospector&mdash;mind you I have great respect for exploiters and for prospectors and I think we ought to have more of them, but at the same time I am conservative enough and I have experience enough to know that the last thing in the world to do is to go inside a man's boundary, especially if you have not good reason for doing it.  This allows the Minister to authorise his Board to go inside a man's boundary for the sake of taking stone, gravel, sand or clay.  That is what it means.  I hope I have stated it as clearly as I could possibly state it.  I want to state it clearly for the purpose of Part IV, that is, for the purpose of going in on a man's land. Minerals include stone, gravel, sand or clay.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnKeaneBart" hpid="Sir John Keane Sir John Keane">
      <NameTxt>Sir John Keane</NameTxt>
      <P>And turf.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelComynKC" hpid="Mr. Comyn Mr. Comyn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Comyn</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator Keane has mentioned turf.  That is in my own amendment, which comes on later.  I am now dealing with Senator Linehan's amendment, which does not include turf.  This empowers them to enter upon a man's land and to deprive him of the sacred right of property and the <Col N="71" /> sacred feeling of property.  Stone, gravel, sand and clay are minerals.  I hope I have made that clear.  That being so, I wish that Senators would recall another thing that Senator Linehan said.  Senator Linehan says that if you pass this Act and if you authorise any man for any purpose to go inside a man's farm to get a mineral which for this purpose includes &ldquo;stone, gravel, sand or clay,&rdquo; you tear up the agreement you made with him, because under his agreement of purchase and under his vesting order &ldquo;stone, gravel, sand or clay&rdquo; are his and you cannot touch them.  The Minister says &ldquo;I am not touching him, I am giving him compensation.&rdquo;  You have no right to touch him.  This Bill, by indirect means, is an invasion of the private rights of the small farmers of this country.  I do not want to say more on that.  I think it is a matter deserving of very mature consideration. I do not think it has received the consideration that it deserves.  Senator Linehan has great experience in matters of this kind.</P>
      <P>Now, I would not like that the Bill should in any way be injured by any of the amendments that I support, because I think this is a useful Bill and will be more useful after it escapes from the Seanad.  I use the word &ldquo;escape&rdquo; advisedly.  I do not want to be very critical, but I do think that the amendment of Senator Linehan, preserving the rights of farmers and the feeling of security in what they have bought, ought to be respected.  I have an amendment down myself, including &ldquo;peat.&rdquo;  I support Senator Linehan's amendment for the reasons I have given.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. Johnson Mr. Johnson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Johnson</NameTxt>
      <P>We have heard some surprising doctrines from the Senator who has just sat down, coming from the Senator particularly so.  Is the Seanad to understand that it is his considered view when dealing with mines and minerals and the rights of the occupying owner of any property that he has an absolute right over and above any superior right of the State? Are we to take it that the Senator is throwing over the doctrines that have <Col N="72" /> been preached by those whom, I think, he would consider to be his leaders; that, ultimately, if an individual's right contravenes the superior rights of the State, then the individual's rights have to give place to the superior rights of the State?  Apparently the Senator says the individual's rights are absolute and incontrovertible in any circumstances, and yet&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelComynKC" hpid="Mr. Comyn Mr. Comyn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Comyn</NameTxt>
      <P>On a point of explanation.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Cathaoirleach Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>You can speak later, Senator.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. Johnson Mr. Johnson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Johnson</NameTxt>
      <P>&mdash;&mdash;the Senator says this is a useful Bill.  He hopes that it will not be injured.  The Bill clearly sets out to provide machinery which, in certain circumstances, will affirm and make practicable the superior rights of the State where the State's greater interest is made manifest.  Now I test this amendment and the Senator's support of it by a reference to what he himself says.  The Senator says that stone includes limestone.  It might include china clay, but he is doubtful.  It would certainly include marble.  Let us read sub-section (4) of Section 18 in the light of the amendment which the Senator supports:&mdash;</P>
      <P>(4) Where, in the opinion of the Minister, minerals <i>except any stone</i>, <i>gravel</i>, <i>sand or clay</i> are not being worked or are not being worked efficiently and no satisfactory reason is shown by the person having an interest therein to the Minister for not working such minerals or for not working such minerals efficiently, the Minister may, subject to and in accordance with this Part of the Act, grant to any person who desires, either by himself or through his lessees, to work such minerals a right (in this Part of this Act referred to as a mining (unworked minerals) right) to work such minerals.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Further on in the same Part of the Bill&mdash;Part IV&mdash;there are very close precautions to ensure that there is going to be a very sound reason before any right will be granted over and above the right of the owner of the property, who may not be an occupying farmer&mdash;he may be a landlord.  Now <Col N="73" /> if it appears essential to the State that minerals sunk in the earth should be worked, that there must be some interference with some individual's rights to procure their working, the Senator would support that.  But if it appears that the working of china clay or limestone was essential for the wellbeing of the State, and that some individual possesses ownership rights and prevents their working, I ask the Senator would he say that the individual's rights must prevail?  If that is the case then the Senator has no right to support this Bill at all. The Bill goes by the board if the Senator's contentions are right or justifiable.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MauriceMoore" hpid="Colonel Moore Colonel Moore">
      <NameTxt>Colonel Moore</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not like to interrupt, but I think the Senator is not speaking to the amendment at all.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. Johnson Mr. Johnson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Johnson</NameTxt>
      <P>Perhaps the Senator is thinking of the amendments that have already been discussed.  I am speaking to Senator Linehan's amendment, which desires to &ldquo;except any stone, gravel, sand or clay&rdquo; in any reference to minerals in Part IV of the Bill.  If we &ldquo;except stone, gravel, sand or clay&rdquo; then sub-section (4) will have no effect in respect to these substances.  I ask Senators if that is their desire: that this sub-section should have no effect in respect to these minerals if it were found desirable that they should be worked, and if an individual owner was impeding their working.  So long as the reasonable rights of the owner are considered and protected as provided for in the later sections of that Part of the Bill, I think the Senator's own statement of facts makes it essential that the Seanad should oppose this amendment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>I want to get a distinction drawn between the determination of the rights of ownership over certain property and a certain interference which I hold is nine-tenths in aid of the owner and only a small fraction against him.  Senator Linehan talked about jeopardising the rights of the tenant owner in the case of the materials that he mentions: stone, sand, gravel, or clay.  Would the Senator point out to me any place in the Bill where, by a definition, we make a <Col N="74" /> determination prejudicially to the tenant owner in his rights of ownership in these things?  I suggest it will not be found in any part of the Bill.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelComynKC" hpid="Mr. Comyn Mr. Comyn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Comyn</NameTxt>
      <P>It will be found in Part IV.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>A determination of rights of ownership?  They are not interfered with.  His rights of ownership are already determined.  The Senator talked about jeopardising the rights of ownership.  He either means affecting adversely the tenant in the matter of working without taking away his rights of ownership and prejudicially affecting these rights because we allow somebody to work with him, or he may mean alternatively that you simply deny him his title of ownership.  I say you do not do the second thing at any rate. If anybody thinks that this Bill does that I want to have the section pointed out to me.  Section 4 provides: &ldquo;if for the purposes of this Act any question arises (a) as to whether an exclusive mining right has before the passing of this Act been reserved to the Irish Land Commission under Section 13 of the Irish Land Act, 1903, and, if so reserved, as to whether such right has been purchased or disposed of by the Irish Land Commission in accordance with law, and, if so disposed of, the nature and extent of such disposition.&rdquo;</P>
      <P>That brings in everything, the Land Commission rights <i>versus</i> the tenant's. If any question arises on these points the Minister may refer such question to the Irish Land Commission, exclusive of the Judicial Commissioner, for their determination.  Later there is the right of appeal to the Judicial Commissioner, and later still there is the right of appeal to the Supreme Court.  So far as rights are concerned in these four things, if any question arises with regard to any of the substances in Section 4, then they are going to be referred for judicial determination.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I want to know if the position as set out in the Bill is accepted.  Having either determined the rights of ownership, or, if they are not determined, having made provision for their future determination under Section 4 of the Bill, we then go on in Part IV of the Bill to say that where there is an owner <Col N="75" /> of minerals&mdash;Sub-section (1) of Section 18: &ldquo;Where minerals are comprised in or lying under land subject to a lease, exception, reservation, restriction, covenant or condition, or are otherwise incapable of being worked without the concurrence of two or more persons,&rdquo; then the Minister may, in accordance with this Part of the Act, &ldquo;grant to any person who has an interest in such minerals and who, either by himself or through his lessees, desires to work such minerals, a right ... to work such minerals.&rdquo; Senator Comyn said that was the section which granted mining rights.  I asked him to whom, and he carefully avoided giving an answer.  It is easy to conceive an area in which there are certain mineral substances and where for their proper working the concurrence of two or more persons is required, where one is recalcitrant and where the other is willing.  Power is given to grant to the willing man the right to work such minerals, but that right is subject to a considerable number of restrictions.</P>
    <P>I want to get this point clear.  Section 4 is the section which allows for determination by a judicial authority as to whether or not the tenant owns these things.  We make provision for the judicial determination of these things.  We do not refer to the rights of ownership in Part IV, but we do go on to say that once the rights have been determined, that where minerals are not being worked and where the concurrence of two or more persons is required, we may grant to one of the owners the right to work over the whole of the property.  In sub-section (4) of Section 18 we go outside of that and we say with regard to property of a mineral type that where the minerals &ldquo;are not being worked, or are not being worked efficiently, and no satisfactory reason is shown by the person having an interest therein to the Minister for not working such minerals, or for not working such minerals efficiently, the Minister may, subject to and in accordance with this Part of the Act, grant to any person who desires, either by himself or through his lessees, to work such minerals a right (in this Part of this Act referred to as a mining (unworked <Col N="76" /> minerals) right) to work such minerals.&rdquo; What is that section enveloped by?  By this, that the Minister may not even proceed to think of granting this right unless certain things that are referred to in Section 20 are evidenced to him: unless it is shown that it is not reasonably practical to obtain such right by private arrangement for any of the following reasons, and then the reasons are set out.  The reasons are evidenced when he receives an application. That application goes before the Mining Board.  Even if the report from the Mining Board on the application is in the affirmative, the Minister must, under Section 23, become satisfied that a case has been established entitling him to grant the right applied for, and that it is in the public interest that such right should be granted to the applicant.  It is only then that this right may be granted.</P>
    <P>I want to come back, for a moment, to sub-section (4) of section 18.  It is the only section which affects the granting away of a right to work a mineral.  It does not affect ownership at all.  If Senators want to except &ldquo;stone, gravel, sand or clay,&rdquo; then I suggest that they ought to go the whole way and cut out the whole section.  If they do I want them to remember this, that they are going counter to representations that have been made to me from a considerable number of places in which there are valuable minerals not being worked because there is somebody who owns the surface and will not allow the working to take place.  If we are going to allow interference with private property why not allow it in the rare cases of possible interference with &ldquo;stone, gravel, sand or clay&rdquo;?</P>
    <P>Senator Comyn wondered whether china clay would or would not come within the reservation.  Supposing you have at any rate clay surrounded by some silica and it has to be determined which predominates, then, under paragraph (d) of sub-section (1) of section 4, which speaks of &ldquo;whether any particular substance can be mined and taken under any particular mining right,&rdquo; that again goes forward for judicial determination.  In Part IV. of the Bill we do say, occasionally, in order to help owners that <Col N="77" /> we will not grant them extra facilities for working their own minerals where these minerals are enclosed in an area that requires the whole area to be worked before there can be efficient working of them.  The whole of Part IV, with the exception of sub-section (4) of section 18, is in aid of the owners of minerals.  It is nowhere adverse to them.  It may become adverse to them under sub-section (4) of section 18 in the case of these sacred substances, &ldquo;stone, gravel, sand or clay&rdquo; if you find cases where they are not being worked efficiently.  There ought to be power to grant a right to work these as there is to grant the right to work more valuable substances.  That is the only part of the clause that is adverse to the owner.  I think that there has been complete confusion on two points.  With the determination of the rights of the owner we do not interfere. We do not even pretend to define it for ourselves.  We leave it for judicial determination.  The other matter is in relation to the granting to an owner of an ancillary right to help him to get the minerals that he owns properly and efficiently worked.  In both cases there has to be a judicial determination.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelComynKC" hpid="Mr. Comyn Mr. Comyn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Comyn</NameTxt>
      <P>This debate has ranged over a rather wide field.  It seems to me that there is a fundamental difference in the points of view expressed by Senator Linehan and myself and the points of view expressed by Senator Johnson and the Minister.  There is a fundamental difference between us.  I would like to know whether the Minister has any particular case in mind in which he requires power to work &ldquo;any stone, gravel, sand or clay.&rdquo; Can he imagine a case in which&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SamuelBrownKC" hpid="Mr. Brown Mr. Brown">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Brown</NameTxt>
      <P>I can imagine lots of cases.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelComynKC" hpid="Mr. Comyn Mr. Comyn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Comyn</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator Brown says that he can imagine lots of cases.  The Senator has acquired the little habit of interrupting me.  It is disconcerting, but I will not be upset.  Does the Minister want to cover limestone?  There are hundreds of miles of limestone in Galway Bay which could be got without interfering with the private rights of anybody.  Does he want to cover <Col N="78" /> gravel?  There is no particular public service for which he wants &ldquo;stone, gravel, sand or clay,&rdquo; and yet he has, without any reason whatever, interfered, or rather asserted the claim to interfere, with property rights.  That is the claim that he has put forward.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasFarren" hpid="Mr. Farren Mr. Farren">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Farren</NameTxt>
      <P>After the payment of compensation.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelComynKC" hpid="Mr. Comyn Mr. Comyn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Comyn</NameTxt>
      <P>I can see from the Labour Benches that what I am saying is not accepted.  The Minister wants to familiarise you with the invasion of the private property of farmers.  That is what he wants to do. I think the members of the House have taken my meaning and that I need not elaborate it further.  What I will say to Senator Johnson and to the Minister &mdash;I have not mentioned it before and have not thought it necessary until now &mdash;is that this invasion of the private rights of farmers must stop, and stop quickly, when you come to a certain point.  In regard to what Senator Johnson said, certainly the State has the right to all the resources of the State, but the farmers of Ireland have a right to their holdings.  You must reconcile both rights, and you must not invade the right of the farmer without good and sufficient reason.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. Johnson Mr. Johnson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Johnson</NameTxt>
      <P>That is provided for.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelComynKC" hpid="Mr. Comyn Mr. Comyn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Comyn</NameTxt>
      <P>There is no reason for a demonstration on the part of Senator Farren.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasFarren" hpid="Mr. Farren Mr. Farren">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Farren</NameTxt>
      <P>With all respect, I was not demonstrating.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelComynKC" hpid="Mr. Comyn Mr. Comyn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Comyn</NameTxt>
      <P>The Senator was looking in a most provocative way.  I think the Minister ought to be careful.  I do not wish to be too severe, but in a matter of this kind I think there is no reason whatever why he should have interfered in the case of &ldquo;stone, gravel, sand or clay.&rdquo;  I think that wisdom lies in accepting the amendment proposed by Senator Linehan.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="KathleenBrowne" hpid="Miss Browne Miss Browne">
      <NameTxt>Miss Browne</NameTxt>
      <P>Is it not the case that at the present time the county councils can, without any authority, go into a quarry that a farmer owns and take away material out of it whether the farmer likes it or not?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="79" />
    <Speaker pid="MichaelComynKC" hpid="Mr. Comyn Mr. Comyn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Comyn</NameTxt>
      <P>There is a necessity for that, and there are quarrels about it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="KathleenBrowne" hpid="Miss Browne Miss Browne">
      <NameTxt>Miss Browne</NameTxt>
      <P>If that happened in my case I should resent it very much, while feeling at the same time that the rights of the greater number of people were greater than my private rights.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>I just want to refer to what Senator Comyn said last.  The Senator either objects to interference with the rights of private property or else he only objects when there is interference with certain named substances. I do not know which point he takes.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelComynKC" hpid="Mr. Comyn Mr. Comyn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Comyn</NameTxt>
      <P>Threatened interference without showing the necessity for it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>The Senator's last words, &ldquo;without showing the necessity for it,&rdquo; are important.  Suppose that a farmer was working and, therefore, was in possession of coal beneath his land?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelComynKC" hpid="Mr. Comyn Mr. Comyn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Comyn</NameTxt>
      <P>Coal is not one of the things referred to in the amendment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>Coal is dealt with in Part IV of the Bill.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelComynKC" hpid="Mr. Comyn Mr. Comyn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Comyn</NameTxt>
      <P>It is not &ldquo;stone, gravel, sand or clay.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>A farmer owns land which has coal beneath it.  He is working the coal.  It is in his possession. The Senator will allow me to interfere with a man's private rights if it is a valuable substance such as coal, but he will not allow me to interfere with the farmer in respect to the four named substances without, as he says, good and sufficient reason.  There have to be very good and sufficient reasons before there is any interference.  The number of cases in which there will be interference in these matters will be very rare indeed.  The Senator asked me if I had any cases.  In about thirty cases <Col N="80" /> representations have been made to my Department.  Cases have come before me where the substance looked for is clay.  In some of these cases the mineral is in different ownership.  I cannot understand the discrimination that is made.  Certainly in some cases interference is going to strengthen the hands of farmers in dealing with these four substances.  Is the position this: that there is a reluctance to interfere with farmers in their rights only in so far as these four named substances are concerned, and not in regard to anything else?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelComynKC" hpid="Mr. Comyn Mr. Comyn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Comyn</NameTxt>
      <P>Clay belongs to the farmer; minerals do not.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>A mineral may belong to a farmer.  If minerals do belong to the farmer, then the Senator is going to allow me to interfere, but he will not allow me to interfere in the case of the four named substances.  If you are not going to allow interference with private property, then the proper course to follow is to obliterate Part IV of the Bill altogether.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelComynKC" hpid="Mr. Comyn Mr. Comyn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Comyn</NameTxt>
      <P>Part IV is all right so far as it relates to minerals.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>And it is not all right if it allows me to grant a person having an interest in &ldquo;sand, stone, gravel, or clay&rdquo; better working facilities for these four things.  I am not to be allowed to strengthen the hands of an owner so far as these four substances are concerned.  If I am not to be allowed to do that, then it would be better obliterate the section altogether.  If you are going to leave the section in for one thing, then I think you are bound to leave it in for everything.</P>
      <P>Amendment put.</P>
      <P Just="Center">The Committee divided: Tá, 10; Níl, 21.</P>
      <P Just="Center">Tá.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <table pgwide="1">
      <tgroup cols="2">
        <colspec colname="1" colnum="1" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <colspec colname="2" colnum="2" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry rowsep="1">Michael Comyn, K.C.<br />James Dillon.<br />Thomas Linehan.<br />Seán E. MacEllin.<br />D.H. MacParland.</entry>
            <entry rowsep="1">Colonel Moore.<br />Joseph O'Connor.<br />William Quirke.<br />Séumas Robinson.<br />Séumas Ryan.</entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
    <P Just="Center">Níl.</P>
    <table pgwide="1">
      <tgroup cols="2">
        <colspec colname="1" colnum="1" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <colspec colname="2" colnum="2" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry rowsep="1">Samuel L. Brown, K.C.<br />Miss Kathleen Browne.
<Col N="81" />The Countess of Desart.<br />Michael Fanning.<br />Thomas Farren.<br />Thomas Foran.<br />Hugh Garahan.<br />Dr. O. St. J. Gogarty.<br />Sir John Purser Griffith.<br />Thomas Johnson.<br />Sir John Keane.</entry>
            <entry rowsep="1">Mrs. Costello.<br />John C. Counihan.
<Col N="82" />James Moran.<br />John T. O'Farrell.<br />M.F. O'Hanlon.<br />L. O'Neill.<br />Siobhán Bean an Phaoraigh.<br />Michael Staines.<br />Thomas Toal.<br />Richard Wilson.<br /></entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
    <P Just="Center">Tellers:&mdash;Tá: Senators Comyn and Linehan; Níl: Senators Farren and Toal.</P>
    <P>Amendment declared lost.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelComynKC" hpid="Mr. Comyn Mr. Comyn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Comyn</NameTxt>
      <P>I beg to move amendment 4:&mdash;</P>
      <P>Section 1, sub-section (2).  After the word &ldquo;substances&rdquo; in line 38 to insert the words &ldquo;other than peat, stone, gravel, sand or clay used for fuel, building or agricultural purposes.&rdquo;</P>
      <P>My object in moving this amendment is to see what attitude the Minister will adopt in regard to it.  I do not propose again to go over the ground which we travelled on the last occasion.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>It is practically the same thing.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelComynKC" hpid="Mr. Comyn Mr. Comyn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Comyn</NameTxt>
      <P>If the Minister will accept the amendment I need not say anything more about it.  I think that peat will be regarded as a mineral substance under the definitions contained in the Bill.  It seems to me turbary and peat are altogether outside the scope of a Bill of this character.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>I have exactly the same objection to this amendment as to the last.</P>
      <P>Amendment, by leave, withdrawn.</P>
      <P>Section 1 agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasFarren" hpid="Mr. Farren Mr. Farren">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Farren</NameTxt>
      <P>With regard to Section 2, so far as I understand it, it preserves certain rights and, in view of what Senator Comyn said some time ago about preserving certain rights of landlords who have sold their property, it appears to me that this section proposes to continue that system.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelComynKC" hpid="Mr. Comyn Mr. Comyn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Comyn</NameTxt>
      <P>It does.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasFarren" hpid="Mr. Farren Mr. Farren">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Farren</NameTxt>
      <P>Section 2 (2) says: &ldquo;shall continue to apply to any letting, lease, sale or demise of any such exclusive right.&rdquo;  That means that the old regulations made with regard to preserving the existing rights of landlords shall continue in force.  I ask the Minister to consider the deletion of these lines, because it is merely continuing a system about which there has been a lot of complaint.  The complaint centres round a man owning land, selling it to a tenant, but continuing to have in that land an interest in minerals and other rights.  I think that is wrong, and I ask the Minister to consider the question of deleting these words on the Report Stage.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOFarrell" hpid="Mr. O'Farrell Mr. O'Farrell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Farrell</NameTxt>
      <P>Perhaps the Minister will explain what is the nature of the rights that the last five or six lines of Section 2 preserve.  There was an old provision that the ex-landlord, although he had sold his interest in the estate, had a right to 25 per cent. of all royalties in respect of minerals.  Does this section propose to perpetuate that right for the future?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>That is precisely what is intended.  I am not pretending in this to speak with any special accuracy at the moment, and I do not intend to go into details.  Generally the situation was that where land passed and the mineral rights were reserved to the Land Commission, if, afterwards, the Land Commission made a letting of the minerals, a certain percentage, 25 per cent., of the royalties received by the Land Commission were reserved to the original landlord, whether or not he had worked the minerals.  That was the position up to the 1923 Act.  Under the 1923 Act, following out the provisions of the old Acts, a clause was inserted to say that where land passed under the 1923 Act and where, afterwards, a letting was made of mines or minerals, then the <Col N="83" /> percentage to be retained for the benefit of the original landlord would be such as would be hereafter determined.</P>
      <P>In the first draft of this Bill I included 25 per cent. in order to put the land passing under the 1923 Act on the same basis as under previous Land Purchase Acts.  The point was made in the Dáil that as these landlords had done nothing with regard to the development of the minerals, as they were old-time rights and as no provision reserving them had been made under the Act of 1923, it was inequitable to continue the provision.  I agreed with that, and I moved to leave it out.  This clause has been put in reserving the 25 per cent. in the very rare cases in which lettings of mines or minerals have been made by the Land Commission and where, in fact, some old landlords are in possession of 25 per cent. of the rents and royalties. We went the length of cutting it out where a rent or royalty was not, in fact, being derived.  We decided to keep it in where there is some interest passing to somebody.  The cases are rare; I do not suppose there will be half a dozen.  If the Seanad likes we can have that matter reconsidered.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OliverGogarty" hpid="Dr. Gogarty Dr. Gogarty">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Gogarty</NameTxt>
      <P>Are those rights to be determined, or are they to be in perpetuity? Can the landlords hand them on for ever?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>They will be in their possession, and they can be demised and all the rest of it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelComynKC" hpid="Mr. Comyn Mr. Comyn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Comyn</NameTxt>
      <P>I think the Minister has given a fair explanation of this rather complicated position.  In the case of a landlord whose interest has not been disposed of through the Land Commission, whatever that interest may be, his rights to mines and minerals, if he has any, are not interfered with by this Bill.  If a landlord sold his land under the 1903 Act and was at the date of the sale possessed of mines and minerals, then the percentage of the royalty to which he was entitled under the 1903 Act, or the indefinite proportion of the royalty to which he would be entitled under the 1923 Act, is gone now under <Col N="84" /> the amendment moved in the Dáil unless there has been an actual lease of the mines and minerals and a working under that lease.  That position is perfectly plain.</P>
      <P>I would like to bring another matter to the knowledge of the Minister.  It is suggested that the landlords have not worked the minerals satisfactorily.  I know one man, Lord Inchiquin, who during the last two or three years has spent £500 or £600 boring and searching for minerals.  If his rights are to be taken away he is, I think, entitled to some compensation.  I think that is a matter which the Minister ought to consider.  We must be fair to everybody.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OliverGogarty" hpid="Dr. Gogarty Dr. Gogarty">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Gogarty</NameTxt>
      <P>Are these residential or absentee English landlords?  If a royalty is to be enjoyed by absentees it is nearly as equitable as the allocation of the annuities to the English people without considering the Irish holders at all.  If you do not intend to pay annuities, why pay royalties?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelComynKC" hpid="Mr. Comyn Mr. Comyn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Comyn</NameTxt>
      <P>I am glad to see my friend is supporting our policy.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MauriceMoore" hpid="Colonel Moore Colonel Moore">
      <NameTxt>Colonel Moore</NameTxt>
      <P>They are all coming round, one after the other.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>Perhaps Senator Farren will put down an amendment dealing with this matter and we can discuss it on the Report Stage.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasFarren" hpid="Mr. Farren Mr. Farren">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Farren</NameTxt>
      <P>I will do so.</P>
      <P>Sections 2, 3 and 4 agreed to.</P>
      <P Just="Center">SECTION 5.</P>
      <P>(1)  In this Act the expression &ldquo;State mines and minerals&rdquo; means&mdash;</P>
      <P>(a)  in relation to any mines and minerals which at the date of the passing of this Act belong, by virtue of Article 11 of the Constitution or otherwise, to Saorstát Eireann, such mines and minerals;</P>
      <P>(b)  in relation to any mines and minerals which on or after the passing of this Act become, by any means, vested in Saorstát Eireann, such mines and minerals as on and from the date of such vesting.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="85" /> (3)  In sub-section (1) of this section the word &ldquo;minerals&rdquo; includes all minerals and substances in or under land obtainable by underground or surface working.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelComynKC" hpid="Mr. Comyn Mr. Comyn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Comyn</NameTxt>
      <P>I beg to move amendment 5:&mdash;</P>
      <P>Section 5, sub-section (1).  After the word &ldquo;Eireann&rdquo; in line 58 to insert the words &ldquo;including mines royal and minerals on or under the foreshores and seas surrounding Saorstát Eireann.&rdquo;</P>
      <P>The object of this amendment is to elicit from the Minister whether, in point of fact, he or the State is possessed of the mines royal and the minerals on or under the foreshores and seas surrounding the Free State. The amendment might be regarded as somewhat meticulous, but I think it is an amendment of very great substance. Mines royal, as Senators know, are gold, silver and quicksilver. There is gold in this country. If gold is blended with another minerals such as copper it is not a royal mine; it is an ordinary mine. If gold or silver is found alone, then it is a royal mine and it is vested in the King as such.</P>
      <P>I want to make special reference to foreshores.  It seems to me that in the development of our mineral resources the foreshores of the country will be more important in the immediate future than the dry land.  I was over recently in that part of Ireland which has the honour of being the birthplace of the ancestors of Senator Gogarty&mdash; the shores of Galway Bay.  I took up a fistful of top sand&mdash;it is a fad of mine to do these things&mdash;and, having made an analysis of the sand as best I could, I sent it to the School of Mines in Cornwall.  Here is the reply I got: &ldquo;I am in receipt of your letter enclosing a cheque&rdquo;&mdash;that is for the cost of assay &mdash;&ldquo;We have completed the assay of the sample of sand you sent us and we beg to report that it contains 6lbs. of tin metal per long ton of 2,240lbs.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OliverGogarty" hpid="Dr. Gogarty Dr. Gogarty">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Gogarty</NameTxt>
      <P>My grandfather's clock!</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelComynKC" hpid="Mr. Comyn Mr. Comyn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Comyn</NameTxt>
      <P>Observe how surprised my friend gets.  This is a most important <Col N="86" /> matter because the top sand, being the lightest sand, would, of course, contain the smallest percentage of the metal.  In my opinion the foreshore in that area could be made a most valuable asset for this country. I would like to say that similar samples of sand can be got 20 miles away from where I picked up that sand.  The foreshores of this country, especially on the Western seaboard, are, from the mining point of view, of great importance.</P>
      <P>I put down the amendment for the purpose of eliciting from the Minister whether he has control over foreshores and royal mines.  The foreshores hitherto have been a subject in regard to which lawyers differed as to ownership&mdash;whether the ownership was in the Crown itself or in any Department of the Crown.  The same doubt existed in regard to mines royal.  I know that for two or three years after the Free State came into existence it was a matter that engaged the attention of lawyers and, perhaps, the Ministry.  I would like to know from the Minister whether this question has been finally determined.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>This amendment affects nothing in the part of the Bill where it is proposed to insert it.  I think the Senator will agree with that. The section is merely a definition section, and it simply says: &ldquo;the expression &lsquo;State mines and minerals&rsquo; means in relation to any mines and minerals which at the date of the passing of this Act belong, by virtue of Article 11 of the Constitution or otherwise, to Saorstát Eireann, such mines and minerals.&rdquo;  There is not much use in putting in extra words if they are not covered by Article 11 of the Constitution.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelComynKC" hpid="Mr. Comyn Mr. Comyn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Comyn</NameTxt>
      <P>Has the Minister decided the question whether or not the foreshores belong to this country?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>We hold that mines royal belong to the State.  We also hold in the main that the foreshores belong to the State, but we recognise there have been private rights acquired in the foreshores in particular ways.  A definition, however, does not affect <Col N="87" /> that question.  It would be a matter for judicial settlement afterwards.</P>
      <P>Amendment, by leave, withdrawn.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasLinehan" hpid="Mr. Linehan Mr. Linehan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Linehan</NameTxt>
      <P>I beg to move amendment 6:&mdash;</P>
      <P>Section 5, sub-section (3).  After the word &ldquo;substances&rdquo; in line 6 to insert the words &ldquo;except any stone, gravel, sand or clay.&rdquo;</P>
      <P>This section is in Part I. of the Bill, and relates, I presume, to State-owned mines.  The particular sub-section with which I am concerned says: &ldquo;the word &lsquo;minerals&rsquo; includes all minerals and substances in or under land obtainable by underground or surface working.&rdquo; The Minister mentioned that the question as to what constitutes minerals will be referred to the Judicial Commissioner for decision.  No judge, however, can decide anything unless he refers to the law upon the subject.  If we pass legislation which enacts that every substance would be included under the term &ldquo;minerals,&rdquo; it is quite evident that the decision of the Judicial Commissioner in such a case would be to include everything.</P>
      <P>I would like to point out that under the Constitution the minerals that passed to this country were the minerals already in the possession of a Department of the State, either the Land Commission or some other Department. The Act which vested the minerals in the State expressly excluded the four substances I referred to to-day.  Unless it is intended to deprive land occupiers of the rights they acquired under different Land Acts I do not see why the Minister should object to making it clear that stone, sand, gravel and clay will be excluded under this Bill.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>This does not determine any rights.  The definition here indicates that when you see the phrase &ldquo;State mines and minerals&rdquo; in relation to Article 11 of the Constitution such mines and minerals will mean only such mines and minerals as Article 11 embraces.  It does not determine what these are.  The amendment would have this effect.  It would exclude anybody from having any dealings with these <Col N="88" /> substances if they were found to be rightly in the possession of the State. The Minister for Finance could not dispose of them under the State Lands Acts and I could not dispose of them as minerals.  They would be lying there, not in the possession of the tenant and indisposable by the State.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelComynKC" hpid="Mr. Comyn Mr. Comyn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Comyn</NameTxt>
      <P>I have not the slightest doubt that the Minister is perfectly <i>bona fide</i> in what he says, but it seems to me he has really misconstrued his own Bill.  If he has not done so he would not have treated Senator Linehan's amendment in the way he has treated it.  I would like the Minister carefully to consider the arguments in support of this particular amendment. Senators have not been inclined, I think to examine this Bill as carefully as they examine other Bills and I think the reason possibly is that we have very few mines or minerals in this country.  We may, however, in the future have them in the country and for that reason I believe it is desirable to have the foundations properly laid.</P>
      <P>I will make no apology for going into this section rather fully in support of Senator Linehan's amendment.  You see what is said in Section 5 &ldquo;In this Act&rdquo;&mdash;that is in the whole Act&mdash;&ldquo;the expression &lsquo;State mines and minerals&rsquo; means &ldquo;(a) in relation to any mines and minerals which at the date of the passing of this Act belong, by virtue of Article 11 of the Constitution or otherwise, to Saorstát Eireann, such mines and minerals.&rdquo;  You see in Article 11 of the Constitution &ldquo;or otherwise.&rdquo; They belong to Saorstát Eireann under the words &ldquo;or otherwise.&rdquo;  Perhaps by an indirect method the farmers of Ireland are deprived of the control of these four essential substances.  In sub-section (1) the word &ldquo;minerals&rdquo; includes &ldquo;all minerals and substances in or under land obtainable by underground or surface working.&rdquo;  These are State minerals.  That section, as it stands, is capable of this construction and I say, without any hesitation whatever, that it deprives the farmers who purchased under the Act of 1903 of the substances which they bought.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SamuelBrownKC" hpid="Mr. Brown Mr. Brown">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Brown</NameTxt>
      <P>It does not.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="89" />
    <Speaker pid="MichaelComynKC" hpid="Mr. Comyn Mr. Comyn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Comyn</NameTxt>
      <P>That is the position which has been put forward by Senator Linehan, a gentleman who is thoroughly acquainted with the land code, and I certainly, with all the force at my disposal, beg to support that amendment.  I think that the Minister between now and the time when this comes to Report Stage will really reconsider that section.</P>
      <P>Question put and declared lost.</P>
      <P>Section 5 put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>The following amendment stood in the name of Senator Comyn:&mdash;</P>
      <P>&ldquo;Section 6, sub-section (4).  To delete the sub-section.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelComynKC" hpid="Mr. Comyn Mr. Comyn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Comyn</NameTxt>
      <P>I wonder would it be possible to let this amendment stand over for the presence of the Minister, because the object of the amendment is to ascertain what kind of a board the Minister is going to set up.  Is it to be a permanent board or is it to be a board appointed <i>ad hoc</i> for each different occasion?</P>
      <P>Amendment ordered to stand over for Report.</P>
      <P>Sections 7 to 17, inclusive, put and agreed to.</P>
      <P Just="Center">SECTION 18.</P>
      <P>(1)  Where minerals are comprised in or lying under land subject to a lease, exception, reservation, restriction, covenant or condition or are otherwise incapable of being worked without the concurrence of two or more persons and by reason of the said matters the Minister is of opinion that there is a likelihood that such minerals will be left permanently unworked, the Minister may, subject to and in accordance with this Part of this Act, grant to any person who has an interest in such minerals and who, either by himself or through his lessees, desires to work such minerals, a right (in this Part of this Act referred to as a mining (proprietor's) right) to work such minerals.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelComynKC" hpid="Mr. Comyn Mr. Comyn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Comyn</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment 8:&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Section 18, sub-section (1).  After the word &ldquo;may&rdquo; in line 47 to insert <Col N="90" /> the words &ldquo;subject to the payment by the grantee of such yearly or other compensation as may be fixed by the Minister and&rdquo;.</P>
    <P>Section 18 is the section the Minister has already referred to.  It is in Part IV of the Bill, and provides for the case of a recalcitrant holder of land who will not agree with an adjoining owner in respect of the working of minerals.  What I want to put in is that the Minister &ldquo;may, subject to the payment by the grantee of such yearly or other compensation as may be fixed by the Minister and subject to and in accordance with this Part of this Act, grant to any person who has an interest in such minerals, and who either by himself or through his lessees, desires to work such minerals, a right (in this Part of this Act referred to as a mining (proprietor's) right) to work such minerals.&rdquo;  The Minister, by that section, can give to a grantee the right to work minerals in the holding of a person who does not wish to have them worked.  I think this amendment of mine would bring this Bill into line with all the other Acts of Parliament which authorise interference with a man's property or land.  I think it would be an improvement in the Bill as drafted.  The Minister may say that in a certain part of this Act he is providing for the payment of compensation.  That may be so, but in this section the Minister does not make the payment of compensation by the grantee a condition of entering upon the man's land.  I think the draftsman of this Bill must have been familiar with the clauses of the Treaty, because undoubtedly compensation is not given in the vital sections of this Bill.  Compensation is given by inference, by reason of the fact that there is machinery for assessing compensation in a later Part.</P>
    <Speaker pid="SamuelBrownKC" hpid="Mr. Brown Mr. Brown">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Brown</NameTxt>
      <P>There is in this Part.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelComynKC" hpid="Mr. Comyn Mr. Comyn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Comyn</NameTxt>
      <P>In a later Part of the Bill there is machinery for assessing compensation, but in the section that invades the private right there is not the statement that the invasion shall be subject to the payment of compensation. It is only by inference that you can arrive at a conclusion that <Col N="91" /> compensation is payable, just the same as in the Treaty it is only by inference that some people have convinced themselves that the Oath is binding, because it only says &ldquo;the Oath to be taken shall be.&rdquo;  I do not wish now to introduce burning political questions into a Bill of this kind which is really a business matter.  I do submit to the House that this amendment of mine ought to be accepted and for the reasons I have set out.  My amendment has another advantage, I think, over the Bill as drafted, because the Bill as drafted does not provide for the payment of compensation in periodical sums.  The Bill as drafted, so far as I can gather, provides for the payment of compensation wherever it has to be paid as a bulk sum.  My amendment would enable the Minister to settle an annual sum, subject to the payment by the grantee of such yearly or other compensation as may be fixed by the Minister.  That is not my own idea.  I got that from an old statute, a very well drawn statute, dealing with minerals.  The reason is this: it is better to have the compensation periodic because people will start to work mines and they may not have a large sum of money to pay compensation for all time.  The statute ought allow them to pay as they get the minerals and as they do damage.  I want to give the Minister and his advisers a suggestion as to how to fix the compensation&mdash;in a lump sum if it is thought proper, an annual sum if it is proper, or a month to month sum if it is thought right.  That would be an aid to the person who is working the mine.  He may not have very much money.  It would also be an aid to the person whose property was interfered with.  I think the Minister ought to follow the precedent that was set in the old Acts dealing with subjects of this kind.  I am sure the Minister does intend&mdash;if his own statute allows him&mdash;to act in that way. I do not think that Part of his own Bill dealing with compensation allows him to give compensation in the manner that I have suggested.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>The Senator has <Col N="92" /> apparently skipped part of this legislation. Because he does not find compensation mentioned here he assumes that there is no provision for it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelComynKC" hpid="Mr. Comyn Mr. Comyn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Comyn</NameTxt>
      <P>I know it is in Part VII.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>If the Senator would look at section 23, sub-section (5) he would see:</P>
      <P>&ldquo;Whenever the Minister grants to a person a right under this section, compensation (in this Act referred to as compensation under Part IV of this Act) in respect of such grant shall be paid in accordance with this Act by such person.&rdquo;</P>
      <P>Surely that is definite and clear?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelComynKC" hpid="Mr. Comyn Mr. Comyn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Comyn</NameTxt>
      <P>Does the Minister say that that authorises a periodical payment?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>That is a minor point.  The Senator thinks it is only by inference that you can discover that compensation is payable.  His analogy of the Treaty in that respect I am afraid was very unwise.  If the Senator's legal opinion on the Treaty is as weak as it is on this&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelComynKC" hpid="Mr. Comyn Mr. Comyn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Comyn</NameTxt>
      <P>I will leave that to a junior&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>The Senator might get a junior to advise him whether there is a compensation provision here. You cannot put everything into one section.  There is economy of effort in all these things.  You talk of the grant of mineral rights, the grant of ancillary rights, the restriction on grants of rights, the method by which they may be applied for, and when you get to the section which allows the grant you talk of compensation.  I think it is a most logical division.  Is there anything in Part VII which forbids a yearly payment? I see nothing.  A yearly payment could be made, but may I say frankly that I hope the Board when assessing will assess by way of a lump sum?</P>
      <P>Amendment, by leave, withdrawn.</P>
      <P>Section 18 put and agreed to.</P>
      <P Just="Center">SECTION 6.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelComynKC" hpid="Mr. Comyn Mr. Comyn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Comyn</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment 7:</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="93" />&ldquo;Section 6, sub-section (4).  To delete the sub-section.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>Here we have the establishment of a mining board.  So far as I can see that board has got power to do nothing more than a clerk in the office of the Land Commission formerly did.  There is this little matter about interfering with the private rights of a recalcitrant owner but except for that I do not see that this Board has any other power or authority. Then I ask myself what are the leases that were granted by the Land Commission before the passing of the Treaty.  Very few.  Of course, as the Minister has pointed out to you, they have granted no leases since the passing of the Treaty.  Is the volume of business sufficient to justify the establishment of a Board?</P>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Cathaoirleach Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>The amendment does not deal with the establishment of the Board.  It refers to a sub-section that makes provision for the payment of the Board after it has been established.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelComynKC" hpid="Mr. Comyn Mr. Comyn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Comyn</NameTxt>
      <P>If the Board are going to discharge their work without remuneration my amendment is of no consequence.  The meaning of my amendment is that there shall be no money paid for this public service in relation to a Board to look after the matter of mines and minerals.  I do not suppose the amendment will be carried.  I do not intend to press it to a division because if the amendment were carried the result would be that the whole Bill would go by the board. We would like to know from the Minister really whether we are going to have another Board.  This evening we have legislated for an additional Commission.</P>
      <P>We would like to know really if the Minister intends to go on with the mines in a vigorous way or is this whole Bill simply to legalise the rights which the Land Commission formerly had to grant leases where they were applied for?  That is what we would like to know.  We would like to know why we are to establish this Board.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Cathaoirleach Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>The Senator's amendment does not deal with the establishment of the Board; it deals with the payment of the Board.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="94" />
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>The Board will have nothing to do with my granting of a State lease for mines and minerals except on the small point of assessing compensation for the right to enter. The lease will be granted on whatever advice I get from the experts.  The Board do not come into that.  The main function of the Board is the assessment of compensation and the giving of advice when interference is sought with the right of private property.  I think that with the great defence we had from the Senator to-night with regard to private property, he should be the last to object to the right of private property passing to these people.  The Board will be appointed for such period as the Minister thinks fit.  Payment may be by fees or by remuneration for a period.  If there is a big volume of business it might be more economical to appoint for a period. Otherwise it may be more economical to pay fees for whatever work is done.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. Johnson Mr. Johnson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Johnson</NameTxt>
      <P>One member of the Board has to be a lawyer.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator Johnson reminds me that one member of the Board has to be a lawyer, and therefore Senators will see that there has to be some question of fees.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelComynKC" hpid="Mr. Comyn Mr. Comyn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Comyn</NameTxt>
      <P>We have not got out of the Minister yet whether he is going on with his scheme of developing the minerals of the country.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not develop minerals under this Bill.  I await applications and I grant leases.  I am not going to have a Board which is to make borings, to prospect, to furnish data to would-be prospectors, and afterwards to grant them leases to carry on work on the information they derived from us.  We can get certain information put before people through the Geological Survey, which is open to all and sundry.  The development, whether vigorous or not, will not depend on my Department.  It will depend on people with enterprise and courage to get certain information and then to develop themselves.  We might hamper development. I hope we are not going to do so, and certainly not through this Board.  The development the Senator <Col N="95" /> looks for will be mainly the development of State mines and minerals.  The Board has nothing to do except with the small point to which I referred.</P>
      <P>Amendment, by leave, withdrawn.</P>
      <P>Sections 6 to 18 agreed to.</P>
      <P>Amendment 9 not moved.</P>
      <P>Remaining sections and Title agreed to.  Bill ordered to be reported.</P>
      <P>The Seanad went out of Committee.</P>
      <P>Report Stage fixed for Wednesday, 16th December, 1931.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Finance (Customs Duties) (No. 3) Bill, 1931" RHead="(Certified Money Bill)&mdash;Third Stage">
    <Title>Finance (Customs Duties) (No. 3) Bill, 1931 (Certified Money Bill)&mdash;Third Stage.</Title>
    <P>Bill passed through Committee without amendment and ordered to be reported.</P>
    <P>Report Stage ordered for Friday, 11th December, 1931.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Unemployment Relief Bill, 1931 (Certified" RHead="Money Bill)&mdash;Third Stage">
    <Title>Unemployment Relief Bill, 1931 (Certified Money Bill)&mdash;Third Stage.</Title>
    <P>Bill passed through Committee without amendment and ordered to be reported.</P>
    <P>Report Stage ordered for Friday, 11th December, 1931.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Housing (Miscellaneous Provisions)" RHead="Bill, 1931&mdash;Third Stage">
    <Title>Housing (Miscellaneous Provisions) Bill, 1931&mdash;Third Stage.</Title>
    <P>The Seanad went into Committee.</P>
    <P>Section 1 agreed to.</P>
    <P Just="Center">SECTION 2 (1).</P>
    <P>the expression &ldquo;unhealthy area&rdquo; means an area the dwelling houses in which are by reason of disrepair or sanitary defects unfit for human habitation or are by reason of their bad arrangement or the narrowness or bad arrangement of the streets, dangerous or injurious to the health of the inhabitants of the area and in which the other buildings, if any, are for a like reason dangerous <Col N="96" /> or injurious to the health of such inhabitants;</P>
    <Speaker pid="OliverGogarty" hpid="Dr. Gogarty Dr. Gogarty">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Gogarty</NameTxt>
      <P>I move:</P>
      <P>Section 2, sub-section (1).  After the words &ldquo;an area&rdquo; in line 40 to insert the words &ldquo;the subsoil of which is unsuitable for the building of dwelling houses or.&rdquo;</P>
      <P>This matter affects everybody, and it will affect generations in the future if we do not now consider the definition of what is an insanitary area.  It is not houses that make an area insanitary.  It is very easy to see that no one would, except by the aid of an hospital sweep grant, build a tuberculosis sanatorium in Capel street when one remembers that Capel street is an unsuitable site apart altogether from the conditions of the houses there at present.  This city was founded in the ninth century in a haphazard manner by the Scandinavians who came up the river and could not go any further.  The river spread tidally to a much greater extent in those days than it does now. The cellars in a large area of the city are subject to tidal changes twice daily.  I have a letter from the City Engineer's department in which I asked to be given an idea of the area of Dublin under the high water level of the Liffey.  It says:</P>
      <P>&ldquo;the districts in which some of the roads are in many cases under high water are the North Lotts area extending from North Strand to East Wall road and the South Lotts area near Sir John Rogerson's Quay.  However, in other parts of the city, although I have not all the levels, I am sure that many of the basements are under high water, especially areas parallel to the River Liffey and on each side from Arran Quay and Merchants Quay eastwards.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>In other words for about 200 yards on each side of the Liffey the basements are flooded twice daily.  I think it is very ill-advised to build dwelling houses on these sites.  Remember that as the law at present exists it prevents people erecting houses on newly made lands.  We <Col N="97" /> cannot build houses at Fairview where sloblands have been taken in nor at Blackrock where land has also been made.  Twenty years is the minimum time in which houses could be built on such land.  Let me explain the reasons for that.  If you build houses on land made within the past twenty years all will be well until fires are lighted.  The moment the fires are lighted and the rooms warmed you turn that house into a suction opening into a syringe which brings the miasma even through a cement basement.  If that happens in ordinary dry land how much more harmful will it be when you are dealing with what has been an open sewer since 900?  The Corporation of Dublin in 1905 held up some of the effluvia in a large pipe which runs by the side of the river to Ringsend. The old brick drains were not removed when the Corporation sewers were built and now you get the second condition or factor which makes it inadvisable to erect dwelling-houses on that part of the city and on areas that can be cleared.  The water pipes and drains that run into the river quite freely when the Liffey is at low tide are momentarily subject to a backwash when the Liffey is at full tide and that backwash extends over a far greater area than the area I have mentioned.  It is influenced by the river apart altogether from the drainage area.  It extends to a greater area than the river itself and overflows at high tide.</P>
    <P>To give an idea of the conditions in the south side, the backwash of the Liffey extends to the Fusiliers' Monument at Stephen's Green.  There is an area of Dublin in which if it were built on, and if there were artificial means of getting it drained, the houses would be flooded each year. I refer to Trinity College Park, which is under the Liffey level.  The Trinity College Park is kept a grass park and not a snipe park by means of a large pump behind the medical school which had to be augmented by the fire brigade last year during the floods.  I ask the House to include in the definition of insanitary dwellings consideration of the soil on which it is <Col N="98" /> proposed to put people to live.  If houses are built in such places children will suffer from different forms of trouble, slight or otherwise, but which may end in greater troubles like rheumatics later.  Then we will have the perpetual vicious circle of continuing Dublin as the most hospital-ridden city in the world. We are supplying the hospitals with patients by ignoring the first principle of health.  The Local Government officials have to provide themselves with the diplomas of public health. It is not too much to ask the Local Government Department to put into action in that matter the knowledge that these diplomas confer and consequently to use common sense and not to build houses in a sewer area. I do not want to depreciate further the rateable value of this property, but I want to say that if you dig a hole and expose a sewer you will think that water is coming in from the river Liffey.  When you send for the plumber the water will have disappeared when he comes.  That is water from the Liffey.  If the rains come that will be much more increased if you are very near one of these water drains.</P>
    <P>There is a river I believe flowing under the Richmond Asylum on to the Liffey on the North side and on the South side you have another river flowing into the Liffey.  These rivers are subject to being choked up when the Liffey is at high tide and that is what I mean by the backwash which influences the health of houses within the Liffey bed.  I want the House to consider what I think is a prime factor in making a place insanitary and that is the subsoil.  If one is not allowed to build on made ground within a minimum period of 20 years how much more indefensible would it be to build on a percolated site like this?</P>
    <P>Citizens must have noticed that if one looks up Capel street no matter what the visibility one cannot see to the end of the street and that is not because of the curve but because there is a kind of bluish mist in the air.  That is not from a sewer, it is a miasma coming up from the percolated subsoil.  If it is a sunny <Col N="99" /> day you will notice that mist even much more.  It is to that we are going to condemn our children.  That is the air we are going to condemn them to breathe.  We are going to prejudice the health of three generations of people.  It is on land extending around that area that it is proposed to build new houses.  I hope you will not build on an ancient sewer.  That is why I think it is very important, under the circumstances, to know, before you make up your mind to build, the sort of place in which you are going to build.  On this matter surely nobody would think of saying &ldquo;we would like to see a tuberculosis hospital for little children erected in the middle of Capel street.&rdquo;  Anyone who would say that would be laughed to scorn. There is one at the North Wall but there is fresh air there.  This city is already rather remarkable for the amazing number of hospitals it has. No town of its size has an equal number of hospitals&mdash;nineteen hospitals. But if you are to build in the places I have indicated you will have to provide more hospitals.  You will continue the vicious circle.  As a result you will have cripples reared in that area.  I would ask the House to consider that matter very seriously.</P>
    <P>[<i>Senator Counihan took the Chair.</i>]</P>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelComynKC" hpid="Mr. Comyn Mr. Comyn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Comyn</NameTxt>
      <P>Anyone listening to the speech of Senator Gogarty would agree with the saying &ldquo;dread the man with one idea, above all, the specialist.&rdquo; Where are we to build houses in the City of Dublin?  We are told by the Senator that we must go to the Fusiliers' Monument at the top of Grafton Street before we get out of the ambit of the Liffey tide and the miasma of which he has spoken.  Is he going to build houses in Dame Street or Westmoreland Street?  What is wrong with Capel Street?  I never saw this blue Danish mist of which he has told us.  I think that Capel Street is above the sea level&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OliverGogarty" hpid="Dr. Gogarty Dr. Gogarty">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Gogarty</NameTxt>
      <P>You do not think&mdash;the City Engineer knows it and he has measured it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelComynKC" hpid="Mr. Comyn Mr. Comyn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Comyn</NameTxt>
      <P>I would be in favour of <Col N="100" /> the Senator's amendment if it would do any good and avoid undue expense. Is a man before he builds a house to have an investigation made as to the subsoil and who is to determine whether the subsoil is suitable&mdash;is there to be a special investigation with regard to the sub-soil?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OliverGogarty" hpid="Dr. Gogarty Dr. Gogarty">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Gogarty</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelComynKC" hpid="Mr. Comyn Mr. Comyn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Comyn</NameTxt>
      <P>Or are we to depend upon the Public Health Authorities who have already sufficient power to prevent the erection of houses on unsuitable places?  Does Senator Gogarty propose to clear the whole heart of the City, the North Lotts and the South Lotts, Dame Street and Capel Street?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OliverGogarty" hpid="Dr. Gogarty Dr. Gogarty">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Gogarty</NameTxt>
      <P>Certainly.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelComynKC" hpid="Mr. Comyn Mr. Comyn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Comyn</NameTxt>
      <P>When it is cleared I would like to buy some of the vacant spaces and then we could amend the subsection and Senator Gogarty could start building houses as his Danish forefathers did in the blue mists not in Fairview but in what the Senator calls the part of the City where he saw this blue mist.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasFarren" hpid="Mr. Farren Mr. Farren">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Farren</NameTxt>
      <P>I ask Senator Gogarty to withdraw this amendment.  I know that the area about which Senator Gogarty has spoken cannot be insanitary and it cannot be suffering from the dreadful things about which the Senator has told us.  As a matter of fact the Dublin Municipality did build a number of artisan dwellings within the immediate vicinity of the Liffey, in Church Street and in Mary's Lane, and we never heard the dreadful things about which the Senator has been telling us.  The people in the Church Street area are very happy. In that area there was a lot of dirty, miserable slums at one time.  Some of them fell and killed some of the inhabitants. They were all cleared away and the Municipality built there a lot of nice houses.  I am speaking of the Church Street area.  I suggest seriously to the Senator that he ought to withdraw his amendment.  This section of the Bill is not dealing with newly-made ground.  It is not dealing <Col N="101" /> with the Lotts area about which I know something, because the Corporation some years ago decided not to build on it.  I suggest that this amendment will not improve the Bill.  The municipality have surveyed the whole city on many occasions and they have taken into consideration the things the Senator has said, and I want to say this, that in the immediate vicinity of the Liffey it is an extraordinary thing that if the statistics as to the health of the City are looked up, it will be found that the people who live along the Liffey are the healthiest people in the city of Dublin.  I seriously suggest that the Senator ought to withdraw the amendment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. Johnson Mr. Johnson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Johnson</NameTxt>
      <P>There is a more serious defect in the amendment.  It purports to improve the definition of the words &ldquo;unhealthy area.&rdquo;  When you alter the definition of &ldquo;unhealthy area&rdquo; in the way the Senator wishes you are not effecting what he desires.  The definition clause has nothing whatever to do with where you are going to build the new houses.  If you declare that all these places within the centre of the city are unhealthy areas then you have got to demolish all the places in those areas.  I think the Senator would hardly desire to do that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OliverGogarty" hpid="Dr. Gogarty Dr. Gogarty">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Gogarty</NameTxt>
      <P>I was unable, by keeping too closely to the amendment, to make it more acceptable because I had in the back of my mind to make an appeal to the feelings of good citizenship of Senator Farren and my critics. At the present moment, when we are clearing the city, we ought not, without a spacious plan and a noble vision of a greater Dublin, to build on those cleared sites.  Otherwise, we will not be able to improve the city as European towns have been improved by the building of boulevards, etc. There is this shortcoming in the Bill, that it has not been made part and parcel of a town planning measure with which it really ought to run concurrently. If you do nothing except remove these old houses that have stood for hundreds of years and put perishable cement structures in their places, then you will simply be creating a horrible Hollywood of potential <Col N="102" /> slums.  There are hidden behind noble fronts houses that are hardly fit for habitation; these noble old houses are a fence to hide what is behind.</P>
      <P>I think, when we get a chance of clearing a city area, that it should not be immediately built upon until there is a definite scheme as to how the city is to be replanned.  It is really high time that the nation should at least be able in its charter of freedom to compete with the men of the 18th century whose high ideas made this noble city, the seventh city in Christen dom.  The great central avenue what is now O'Connell Street with the North and the South Circular Roads were beautifully planned.  The houses that have now become tenements were nobly proportioned.  They have stood for 200 years until now they have become tenements.  I wonder how long will the modern houses built out around Fairview last?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The limitation in my amendment is that I was not able to call on the spirit of citizens and to implore them not to build at all in the city until we have a co-ordinated plan before us to make a city worthy of the nation.  I saw a plan recently of Paris and its boulevards. It mentioned about seven great Parisians, but Dublin had at least seventy.  In Dublin you had the effects of fresh blood incoming for seven hundred years.  In Dublin you had the products of new and old races giving rise to a new native genius, and men like Hamilton and Burke, Dunlop and Griffith and others in their different spheres of life&mdash;these and modern men that we export like George Bernard Shaw.  I am merely asking in the amendment, in view of what might be done and ought to be done in the city, to withhold rebuilding on the cleared sites.  My idea of condemning certain sites is to make it easier for us to acquire them and to build a road sixty yards broad each side of the river from Butt Bridge to Parkgate Street on one side and Kingsbridge on the other. This would make the Four Courts stand out as its architect intended it, and also make Christ Church visible from O'Connell Bridge.  The Minister should give himself an opportunity of preparing the ground for a dignified Dublin. <Col N="103" /> I hope the Seanad will consider the amendment, as the effect of it will be to give a chance for considering this whole matter when there is a general town-planning scheme.</P>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General Mulcahy General Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>General Mulcahy</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not know whether the putting in of the words in the amendment would provide the Senator with machinery in the Bill for calling upon the spirit of citizens to do certain things.  There is, however, machinery in the Bill by which you can call on the City Corporation and on the Ministry to prevent building in an unsuitable way.  Under Section 9, when a clearance order has become effective, then no development of that area can take place except in accordance with such plans as will be approved of by the local authority in so far as building by the local authority is concerned. That is a matter, too, that will come under review by the Ministry.</P>
      <P>Amendment put and declared lost.</P>
      <P>Sections 2, 3 and 4 agreed to.</P>
      <P Just="Center">SECTION 5.</P>
      <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That Section 5 stand part of the Bill.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. Johnson Mr. Johnson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Johnson</NameTxt>
      <P>On the section I want to draw the Minister's attention to what seems to me to be a defect in the drafting of this in relation to section 14.  It is entirely a drafting matter, but I think it is not satisfactory as it stands.  It will be noticed that under sub-section (1) of Section 5 where the local authority are satisfied upon consideration of an official representation or other information in their possession that any area within their district is an unhealthy area, it shall cause the same area to be defined on a map, shall by resolution declare such an area so defined to be a clearance area and shall, in accordance with the provisions of the Act, proceed to secure the demolition of all buildings.  It is imperative on the local authority that they shall do these things, but under section 14 they are precluded from doing them until they have satisfied the Minister that they have provided alternative accommodation.  It seems to me that you cannot impose upon the local <Col N="104" /> authority an obligation to do these things, having been satisfied that the area is unhealthy, and then say that they must not decide upon doing that thing until the Minister is satisfied that they have done something else. Some proviso, I think, would have to be inserted in sub-section (1) of Section 5 to limit the order of the local authority until they have satisfied the Minister that certain things have been done.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General Mulcahy General Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>General Mulcahy</NameTxt>
      <P>In the first place we require the local authority, having examined a place, to mark on a map the area that they would propose to define by a resolution as a clearance area.  We require them before they pass the resolution to satisfy the Minister under Section 14.  The only thing from the drafting point of view that would be necessary there if it were necessary would be to say &ldquo;subject to satisfying the Minister under section 14 shall by resolution&rdquo; etc.  I would imagine that the presence of section 14 actually does operate between the compulsory making of the map and the passing of the resolution.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. Johnson Mr. Johnson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Johnson</NameTxt>
      <P>I would point out that it is not merely an obligation to cause a map to be made.  The section says that they shall by resolution declare such an area and shall proceed to demolish.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General Mulcahy General Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>General Mulcahy</NameTxt>
      <P>Section 14 says that the local authority shall before undertaking the business of a clearance do certain things.  When they come to the point at which the resolution has to be passed they are faced with the word &ldquo;shall&rdquo; enshrined in Section 14.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. Johnson Mr. Johnson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Johnson</NameTxt>
      <P>They cannot do what you order them to do because you refuse to allow them.</P>
      <P>Section put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>Sections 6 and 7 agreed to.</P>
      <P Just="Center">SECTION 8.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>(1) When a clearance order has become operative the owner or owners of any building to which the order applies shall demolish that building and clear and level the site <Col N="105" /> thereof before the expiration of six weeks from the date on which the building is required by the order to be vacated or, if it is not vacated until after that date, before the expiration of six weeks from the date on which it is vacated or, in either case, before the expiration of such longer period as in the circumstances the local authority may deem reasonable; and, if the building is not demolished before the expiration of that period, the local authority shall enter and demolish the building and clear and level the site thereof and sell the materials thereof.</P>
    <Speaker pid="RichardWilson" hpid="Mr. Wilson Mr. Wilson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Wilson</NameTxt>
      <P>On behalf of Senator Milroy I move amendment 2. Section 8, sub-section (1).  After the word &ldquo;thereof&rdquo; in line 56 to insert the words &ldquo;to the satisfaction of the local authority.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General Mulcahy General Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>General Mulcahy</NameTxt>
      <P>The purpose of the amendment is to establish the standard as to what exactly is required.  Without the amendment the person clearing an area might be prevented from stacking certain of the materials taken from the demolition on the area in the way in which the local authority would approve.  The amendment is to meet that.</P>
      <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardWilson" hpid="Mr. Wilson Mr. Wilson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Wilson</NameTxt>
      <P>On behalf of Senator Milroy I move amendment 3.  Section 8, sub-section (1).  After the word &ldquo;demolished&rdquo; in line 1 to insert the words &ldquo;and the site thereof so cleared and levelled.&rdquo;</P>
      <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
      <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That Section 8 stand part of the Bill.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnKeaneBart" hpid="Sir John Keane Sir John Keane">
      <NameTxt>Sir John Keane</NameTxt>
      <P>On the section I wish to ask for some information.  Has the Minister or somebody got the power to ensure that a clearance, if desired, is effected partially, because under schemes of re-housing I know that it has been found desirable to clear partially and to use some of the old buildings for temporary accommodation while the new buildings were being put up?  I do not know if that <Col N="106" /> power is there.  If there has to be a complete clearance for re-building, that may add to the difficulties with regard to temporary accommodation.</P>
      <P>There is another point I would like to put to the Minister as to the equity of recovering the cost of demolition from the owner.  It does not seem equitable that the owner should be out of pocket in the case of the demolition of buildings.  There are all sorts of ways in which an owner might get out of that.  He might be tempted to use some type of subterfuge, but is it desirable that there should be that temptation under those conditions?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General Mulcahy General Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>General Mulcahy</NameTxt>
      <P>So far as clearing the site is concerned, it must be cleared to the satisfaction of the local authority; but so far as the demolition of buildings is concerned, Section 5 contemplates that a clearance area will contain only houses that it is intended completely to demolish.  If there are houses in the unhealthy area, if there are houses contiguous to the unhealthy area, or if there is an island in it which the local authority considers need not be completely demolished because it does not come into the clearance area scheme, those places might be dealt with under the unhealthy housing portion of the Bill either at the time or afterwards.  The owner would be required to put the house or houses into a proper state of repair.</P>
      <P>So far as a clearance area is concerned, I can conceive no purpose that could be served by leaving a wall standing here, a chimney-stack standing there.  The purpose is complete demolition but only of an area where it has been decided that everything has to be demolished.  In so far as clearing an area under sub-section (1) of the First Schedule is concerned, that area can be cleared progressively.  The local authority can fix different periods at which different parts of the area can be cleared.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnKeaneBart" hpid="Sir John Keane Sir John Keane">
      <NameTxt>Sir John Keane</NameTxt>
      <P>Would the Minister care to touch upon the point of covering the owner with regard to the cost?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General Mulcahy General Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>General Mulcahy</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not quite catch the Senator's point.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="107" />
    <Speaker pid="JohnKeaneBart" hpid="Sir John Keane Sir John Keane">
      <NameTxt>Sir John Keane</NameTxt>
      <P>Under Section 8 the local authority have power to recover from the owner by summary jurisdiction the cost of demolition.  Can the Minister justify the equity of that?  Can he visualise the cases of owners who are likely to be out of pocket?  I am sure he is aware that, if they so desire, they can get out of their liabilities by methods that are not altogether desirable.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General Mulcahy General Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>General Mulcahy</NameTxt>
      <P>What particular sub-section is the Senator referring to?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnKeaneBart" hpid="Sir John Keane Sir John Keane">
      <NameTxt>Sir John Keane</NameTxt>
      <P>I am referring to the provision in the measure which enables a local authority, if the owner does not clear an area, to order its clearance and recover from the owner, by summary jurisdiction, the cost of the clearance.  I suggest that in some cases the owner would be out of pocket and I consider that that is not equitable.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General Mulcahy General Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>General Mulcahy</NameTxt>
      <P>I would like to hear the Senator arguing that the owner of an insanitary dwelling, dangerous to the health of the inhabitants in the neighbourhood, should be able to leave it standing there with impunity.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnKeaneBart" hpid="Sir John Keane Sir John Keane">
      <NameTxt>Sir John Keane</NameTxt>
      <P>I am quite prepared to argue that, seeing that the Minister and his officials alone can lay down the standard of sanitation.  I know that some of the officials are rather inclined to regard the question of sanitation from an unduly high theoretical and academical standpoint.  It does seem unjust that an owner of buildings should be left entirely in their power and should be out of pocket in clearing an area.  Let the local authority take over the place and compensate the site value.  I submit that an owner would be out of pocket over the cost of demolition.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JanePower" hpid="Mrs. Wyse Power Mrs. Wyse Power">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Wyse Power</NameTxt>
      <P>The demolition of the type of house we are discussing is absolutely necessary.  From our experience in public life we know that when houses are condemned and are allowed to stand poor people creep into them and live in them.  That is a most undesirable procedure.  I really think that declaring houses to be insanitary <Col N="108" /> and not demolishing them would be simply ridiculous, particularly when overcrowding and the need of houses form such a problem.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnKeaneBart" hpid="Sir John Keane Sir John Keane">
      <NameTxt>Sir John Keane</NameTxt>
      <P>I am not objecting to the local authority entering and demolishing.  I object to placing the responsibility of clearing on the owner and leaving him out of pocket.  He may be a poor man, and yet the local authority can recover by summary jurisdiction the cost of demolition.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General Mulcahy General Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>General Mulcahy</NameTxt>
      <P>It is not the person who is actually in control of the house; it is the owner of the house. The owner is any person who has an interest in it in any way, by way of ground rent or otherwise.  The court has power when fixing costs to distribute them over the various owners.  A person with a three years' interest is excluded under the definition of owner.</P>
      <P>Sections 8 and 9 agreed to.</P>
      <P Just="Center">SECTION 10.</P>
      <P>(1) A local authority who have under this part of this Act purchased any land comprised in, or surrounded by, or adjoining a clearance area shall, so soon as may be, cause every building thereon to be vacated and subject to compliance with any provision contained in a compulsory purchase order with respect to the carrying out of re-housing operations shall deal with that land in one or other of the following ways, or partly in one of these ways and partly in the other of them, that is to say:&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>(a)  they shall demolish every building thereon before the expiration of six weeks from the date on which it is vacated, or before the expiration of such longer period as in the circumstances they deem reasonable, and thereafter may, subject to the approval of the Minister, sell or let the land subject to such restrictions and conditions, if any, as they think fit, or may appropriate the land for any purpose for which they are authorised to acquire land subject to the like restrictions as are contained in section ninety-five of the Public Health Acts Amendment Act, 1907, with respect to the <Col N="109" /> appropriation of land by local authorities under that section; or</P>
    <P>(b)  they shall, subject to the approval of the Minister, so soon as may be, sell or let the land subject to a condition that the buildings thereon shall be demolished forthwith and subject to such restrictions and other conditions, if any, as they may think fit to impose.</P>
    <P>
    </P>
    <Speaker pid="RichardWilson" hpid="Mr. Wilson Mr. Wilson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Wilson</NameTxt>
      <P>On behalf of Senator Milroy, I beg to move amendment 4:&mdash;</P>
      <P>Section 10, sub-section (1).  To delete all after the word &ldquo;and&rdquo; in line 57 down to and including the word &ldquo;operations&rdquo; in line 59.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General Mulcahy General Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>General Mulcahy</NameTxt>
      <P>This amendment and the next amendment are consequential on the change introduced into the Third Schedule in the Dáil. Originally the difference in compensation as between a clearance area and a derelict site was that in the case of the derelict site that could be cleared at the site value as a cleared site, less the cost of the clearance.  As originally drafted the compensation to be paid where the local authority would be acquiring a clearance area, was the site value cleared of building.  An amendment was introduced and passed changing the amount of compensation to be given in a case like that to a site as a cleared site, less the cost of demolition. It was brought into the same position as regards compensation in relation to the derelict site.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Originally, when the amount of compensation to be paid was the site value cleared without any advertence being paid to the cost of demolition, the provisions of compensation included a provision that where a part of the cleared area was to be used for re-housing there would be a reduction as in previous Acts; the reduction factor would be introduced because of the fact that certain of the ground was going to be used for re-housing.  It would then be compulsory on the local authority to carry out their housing scheme, as a result of which they got a reduction in the price.  Now, when the compensation being paid is the site value, less the cost of demolition, there <Col N="110" /> is no reduction factor in respect of any re-housing that might take place. Therefore in the award there will be no requirement on the local authority to build houses.  We take out the words in amendment 4.  In order to allow the local authority to use the site in so far as they want it, for the purpose of housing, we propose to insert amendment 5 in the later part of the Section 10 (1).</P>
    <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
    <Speaker pid="RichardWilson" hpid="Mr. Wilson Mr. Wilson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Wilson</NameTxt>
      <P>On behalf of Senator Milroy I move amendment 5:&mdash;</P>
      <P>Section 10, sub-section (1).  After the word &ldquo;may&rdquo; in line 66 to insert the words &ldquo;use the land for the purposes of Part III of the Act of 1890 as amended by any subsequent enactment including this Act or may&rdquo;.</P>
      <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
      <P>Sections 10 to 19, inclusive, agreed to.</P>
      <P Just="Center">SECTION 20.</P>
      <P>(5) The local authority may by order declare any such expenses to be payable by weekly or other instalments within a period not exceeding thirty years with interest at such rate as the Minister may, with the approval of the Minister for Finance, from time to time by order fix, from the date of the service of the demand until the whole amount is paid, and any such instalments and interest, or any part thereof, may be recovered summarily as a civil debt from any owner or occupier of the dwelling-house, and, if recovered from an occupier, may be deducted by him from the rent of the house.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardWilson" hpid="Mr. Wilson Mr. Wilson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Wilson</NameTxt>
      <P>On behalf of Senator Milroy I move amendment 6:&mdash;</P>
      <P>Section 20, sub-section (5) To delete in line 23 the words &ldquo;any owner or occupier of the dwelling-house&rdquo; and to substitute therefor the words &ldquo;the person having control of the house or the occupier thereof.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="111" />
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General Mulcahy General Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>General Mulcahy</NameTxt>
      <P>The purpose of the amendment is to correct a mistake and to bring the person so liable under sub-section (5) into the same position as the person liable under sub-section (3) where any expenses incurred by the local authority can be recovered from the person having control of the house.  Sub-section (5) makes provision for the recovery of these expenses, and the person from whom they can be recovered is the person having control of the house.</P>
      <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnKeaneBart" hpid="Sir John Keane Sir John Keane">
      <NameTxt>Sir John Keane</NameTxt>
      <P>I wish to raise a point on Section 20 rather cognate to what I have already raised.  I can visualise the case of small owners who own, perhaps, one or two houses.  They invest their small savings in these houses.  I suppose the Minister is aware that ownership of these small houses in country villages is a thoroughly uneconomic proposition. One may take over possession of them and probably spend three or four years' rent in doing them up.  There is an idea prevalent in some minds that these owners are waxing fat on their rents.  That may be the case in cities, where you have rents of 8/- or 10/- a week, but in the country districts the rent is no more than 2/- or 3/- a week.  Sometimes you have the soft-hearted owner who may allow rents to slip by, and the thing in that light can be regarded almost as a charity.</P>
      <P>In most cases the owner cannot sell because the house will have very little market value.  Again, he cannot borrow because the bank will give him nothing on the house; there is nobody buying that sort of property.  Of course the officials will be somewhat theoretical in their outlook; they will be detached from the brass tacks of reality.  If one just glances back at the Claddagh controversy one will see the difference between the outlook of the occupier and the outlook of the theorist.  The officials will declare certain places insanitary and the owner has to carry out their dictates.  The whole thing is utterly uneconomic.  If the owner fails to do what he is ordered to do they will come along and recover the costs as a civil debt.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="112" /> Perhaps the Minister will consider some remedy between this and the Report Stage.  I ask him to consider how unjust the whole thing is.  I know that sentiment is very strongly against the owners and there is very little regard paid to the equities of the position. There is a distinct injustice in the case of these individuals.  In many cases the house owner cannot afford to do what is directed.  He may have only three or four houses and in order to meet the costs he may have to sell out and possibly he may become a bankrupt.  The rents do not justify him in doing these repairs that modern sanitation requires.  The case might be met by the appointment of a Receiver or the landlord might be allowed to surrender the property to the local authority.  I would be delighted to surrender some property that I have to the local authorities and let them work on it.  The rents are not worth the trouble of collecting and you cannot eject poor people.  I do not think that this House is at all in touch with the realities of the situation as regards those who own property.  We see the horror of the slum problem in Dublin.  I hope I have put the case clearly to the House and to the Minister, that there is a possibility of great injustice in this.  I do not know that it will not react on housing.  I know owners&mdash;I am one myself&mdash;who if they did not feel that they had a certain social duty would pull some of this property down and leave the land derelict because honestly it is not worth the trouble.  I do not think the Minister realises the position that faces a number of small owners in the country. If the Minister could see any possibilities of accommodation on that point I should be glad.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDouglas" hpid="Mr. Douglas Mr. Douglas">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Douglas</NameTxt>
      <P>I think the point made particularly in the last statement of Senator Sir John Keane requires attention. I find a difficulty, in reading the Bill, as to how exactly it will work out. It seems to me that if an owner is entitled to a valuable ground rent it is not unreasonable that he should have to pay the costs of demolition, but it does not seem reasonable that he should pay a cost above the value of the ground.  If the cost of demolition <Col N="113" /> is greater than the value of the ground I do not think it is unreasonable that he should be allowed to surrender the property to the local authority.  I do not own property myself and I am not personally interested.  I think there is a possibility that if people are put to expense over and above what they receive from the property that they might make it over on a pauper, leaving the position almost worse than it is.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General Mulcahy General Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>General Mulcahy</NameTxt>
      <P>I think it is stretching it to suggest that the purpose of this Bill is humanitarian.  The purpose of this Bill is to safeguard the lives of the people who are living in these houses and in the neighbourhood. In the first place, let me say that it is not officials&mdash;dictatorial, brutal and off the earth&mdash;who are going to deal with these matters.  It is the representatives of the local people, advised and guided by their officials, but completely controlling their own decision.  I think the Senator will realise that there are many houses of this particular kind that have been condemned by local authorities, twenty, twenty-five and thirty years ago, and the owners have been very leniently dealt with by the local authorities and even by the courts when the local authorities have taken some of these cases before the courts.  There is no very great past of ruthless action that need frighten us as to the way this Bill would be administered.  Sub-section (3) of Section 19 provides that a person shall not be ordered to repair an insanitary house except it is clear that it can be repaired at a reasonable cost, taking into consideration the value of the house when the works have been completed. A person so ordered can appeal to the court and have the protection of the court against any unjust action on the part of a local authority.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnKeaneBart" hpid="Sir John Keane Sir John Keane">
      <NameTxt>Sir John Keane</NameTxt>
      <P>Under which section?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General Mulcahy General Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>General Mulcahy</NameTxt>
      <P>Section 27 deals with appeals by a person aggrieved and he gets twenty-one days to deal with his grievance.  Then where a local authority comes in and carries out the work, there not having been an appeal <Col N="114" /> in the first place, sub-section (5) of Section 20 makes arrangements by which the cost can be collected over a period of thirty years if necessary, to avoid any considerable and immediate hardship falling on the person in control of the house.  In so far as Senator Sir John Keane would like a receiver to be put in, sub-section (6) practically gives power to have that done and to have the cost of carrying out the repairs dealt with in that particular way, by taking the rent or even by the sale of the lease of the place. I think we have made every possible arrangement here to make it easy for persons in control of houses to meet the liabilities that would fall on them in this matter.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnKeaneBart" hpid="Sir John Keane Sir John Keane">
      <NameTxt>Sir John Keane</NameTxt>
      <P>With all due respect, I am not a bit satisfied that what the Minister has said meets the point.  Going outside the assets of the property to recover any moneys that may be due in respect of repair is an injustice.  I cannot at all accept the view that the Minister takes of these officials, docile people, working entirely under the direction of the local authorities.  That might be so nominally, but I know that there is a hidden hand behind all these things.  I have seen it working myself.  The local authority are in many cases almost a cipher in these matters.  I wish the Minister would consider that point, limiting the liability to the rents received.</P>
      <P>Section 20, as amended, ordered to stand part of the Bill.</P>
      <P>Sections 21 to 25 put and agreed to.</P>
      <P Just="Center">SECTION 26.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>(1) When a demolition order under this Part of this Act has become operative, the owner or owners of the house to which it applies shall demolish that house and clear and level the site thereof within the time limited in that behalf by the order; and, if the house is not demolished and the site thereof cleared and levelled within that time, the local authority shall enter and demolish the house and clear and level the site thereof and sell the materials <Col N="115" /> thereof, and the provisions of subsections (2), (3), (4) and (5) of Section 8 of this Act shall apply in relation to any expenses incurred by the authority under this sub-section and to any surplus remaining in the hands of the local authority as they apply in relation to any expenses or surplus in a case where a building is demolished in pursuance of a clearance order.</P>
    <Speaker pid="RichardWilson" hpid="Mr. Wilson Mr. Wilson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Wilson</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment 7:&mdash;</P>
      <P>Section 26, sub-section (1).  After the word &ldquo;thereof&rdquo; in line 27 to insert the words &ldquo;to the satisfaction of the local authority.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General Mulcahy General Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>General Mulcahy</NameTxt>
      <P>This is a drafting amendment.</P>
      <P>Amendment put and agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardWilson" hpid="Mr. Wilson Mr. Wilson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Wilson</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment 8:</P>
      <P>Section 26, sub-section (1).  After the word &ldquo;thereof&rdquo; in line 28 to insert the word &ldquo;so.&rdquo;</P>
      <P>Amendment put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>Section 26, as amended, ordered to stand part of the Bill.</P>
      <P>Section 27 to 30 put and agreed to.</P>
      <P Just="Center">SECTION 31.</P>
      <P>(1) In any contract entered into after the passing of this Act for letting for habitation a dwelling-house at a rent not exceeding&mdash;</P>
      <P>(a)  in the case of a house situate in the County Borough of Dublin or the Borough of Dun Laoghaire, thirty pounds per annum;</P>
      <P>(b)  in the case of a house situate elsewhere, twenty-five pounds per annum;</P>
      <P>there shall, notwithstanding any stipulation to the contrary, be implied a condition that the house is at the commencement of the tenancy, and an undertaking that the house will be kept by the landlord during the tenancy, in all respects reasonably fit for human habitation.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardWilson" hpid="Mr. Wilson Mr. Wilson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Wilson</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment 9:</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Section 31, sub-section (1).  After the word &ldquo;habitation&rdquo; in line 52 to <Col N="116" /> insert the words &ldquo;but nothing in this section contained shall affect the liability of the tenant or occupier of any such house for any wilful act or default of such tenant or occupier whereby such house is rendered not reasonably fit for human habitation.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General Mulcahy General Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>General Mulcahy</NameTxt>
      <P>The introduction of this amendment is to allay certain fears that were expressed by house-owners, that the provision in this section might impose on them definite responsibility in a way that would give them no power to recover from a tenant damages that had been deliberately brought about by a tenant.</P>
      <P>Amendment put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>Section 31, as amended, ordered to stand part of the Bill.</P>
      <P>Section 32 put and agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardWilson" hpid="Mr. Wilson Mr. Wilson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Wilson</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment 10:</P>
      <P>Section 33, sub-section (2).  To delete the sub-section and to substitute the following new sub-section therefor:&mdash;</P>
      <P>&ldquo;(2) Any expenses incurred by a local authority under this section in obtaining possession of any building or of any part of a building may be recovered by them summarily before a court of summary jurisdiction from the owner of the building or, if there is more than one owner, from the owners thereof and the provisions of sub-sections (2), (4) and (5) of Section 8 of this Act shall apply in relation to any such expenses in like manner as those provisions apply in relation to expenses incurred by a local authority under that section.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General Mulcahy General Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>General Mulcahy</NameTxt>
      <P>This is to bring the section into harmony with Section 8 whereby the court has power to allocate over the various owners the cost incurred under that section.  As drafted, sub-section (2) might mean that one of the owners might be proceeded against for the cost under this section.</P>
      <P>Amendment put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>Sections 33 to 47 put and agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P Just="Center">
      <Col N="117" /> SECTION 48.</P>
    <Speaker pid="RichardWilson" hpid="Mr. Wilson Mr. Wilson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Wilson</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment 11.</P>
      <P>Section 48.  To delete the section and to substitute the following new section therefor:&mdash;</P>
      <P>&ldquo;48.&mdash;Unless the Minister shall in any particular case otherwise direct or agree, the costs payable by a local authority in respect of the acquisition of land for the purposes of the Housing of the Working Classes Acts shall be regulated by the General Order dated the 16th day of April, 1884, as amended by the General Order dated the 17th day of May, 1920, made in pursuance of the Solicitors' Remuneration Act, 1881, and the provisions of the said first-mentioned General Order as amended as aforesaid shall, with the exception of Clause 6 and Rule 11 in Part I of Schedule I of the said Order, apply accordingly.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General Mulcahy General Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>General Mulcahy</NameTxt>
      <P>Under an order of 1859, there was a certain scale of fees set out for the remuneration of solicitors. Subsequent to the passing of the Solicitors' Remuneration Act of 1881, another scale of fees was set out in an Order of 1884.  The original scheme was based on certain fees paid in respect of itemised details of work done.  The new scale, in so far as compensation was involved, bore definite relation to the amount of compensation awarded.  Under Clause 6 of the 1884 scheme, the solicitor had the option of telling his clients that he proposed to operate his fees on the old scale.  The new scale provided for fees that were reasonable compensation for the work done.  Under Rule 11, the scale did not apply to the Land Clauses Act nor did it apply where a local authority was buying land and the cost of the solicitor in connection with the acquisition had to be paid by the person concerned.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Local authorities are rather careful that their titles are perfect, and we naturally want to see that continued. Representations have been made by the city corporation that in connection with the purchase of land, where exhaustive inquiries have to be made and the amount of work involved in the <Col N="118" /> proving of title is considerable, the solicitor's fees on the old scale&mdash;the pre-1884 scale&mdash;reach very considerable proportions at times.  The original clause here proposed that solicitors in future would be paid on the new scale. Attention has been drawn to the fact that the compensation payable in certain cases may be very small, and that owners of property whose solicitors have gone to considerable expense in preparing elaborate titles, may find themselves getting a shilling or two as compensation.  That is not intended.  We provide under Section 50 that a simpler proof of title, such as is sometimes availed of in connection with the Labourers Acts, may be accepted by a local authority where the local authority are satisfied that it is sufficient.  We are bringing in the new Section 48 to enable the Minister where, under the post-1884 scale of costs, real hardship would be involved, to provide that the other scale or some other suitable scale shall be applied.</P>
    <Speaker pid="SamuelBrownKC" hpid="Mr. Brown Mr. Brown">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Brown</NameTxt>
      <P>Under Section 48 as it stands in the Bill, the solicitor for the person whose property is being taken, no matter what the amount of compensation or purchase money is involved, will be limited to a scale.  The scale is a percentage of the purchase money. In most cases, local authorities are not satisfied with a mere declaration of title.  They want to have what is known as a complete title&mdash;a forty years' title absolutely cleared up.  In a case where the purchase money or compensation is extremely small, the solicitor for the owner would only get a miserable sum&mdash;probably a few shillings&mdash;for doing this extremely difficult and responsible work.  The section which it is proposed to substitute for the present Section 48 gives the Minister, in a case like that, the right either to agree as to a sum for costs or to direct the solicitor to tax his costs in the ordinary way, item by item.  That is only just, because it would be a very great hardship on the owner and on his solicitor if Section 48, as it stands in the Bill, were allowed to remain.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelComynKC" hpid="Mr. Comyn Mr. Comyn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Comyn</NameTxt>
      <P>I wonder would the Minister be satisfied if this section <Col N="119" /> were slightly varied?  I agreed with Senator Brown that in some cases the cost of proving title is very great and the investigation of title very troublesome. But there is another side to the question.  If solicitors are to get from 40 to 60 guineas for investigating title to a house, the administration of this Bill will be very much impeded.  Under the Labourers Acts, the costs of the solicitor to the district council constitute a considerable item in the cost of the buildings.  If the Minister commits himself to allowing the scale costs on investigation of title in the case of every parcel of property taken up, he will find the legal expenses under the Bill to be enormous.  A case like this may also arise&mdash;a solicitor for an extensive landowner furnishes his abstract and proof of title in respect of one parcel of land.  He is allowed full costs in respect of each item.  That is quite fair in respect of the first parcel.  But six months, or a year, afterwards another parcel of land may be required from the same owner.  The solicitor has nothing to do but take the papers out of the pigeon hole and send them out again.  He will be paid his full bill of costs for the second time.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SamuelBrownKC" hpid="Mr. Brown Mr. Brown">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Brown</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister will not allow him to be paid that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelComynKC" hpid="Mr. Comyn Mr. Comyn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Comyn</NameTxt>
      <P>That is what the Senator says.  The amendment states: &ldquo;Unless the Minister shall in any particular case otherwise direct or agree...&rdquo; In order to prevent the solicitor getting full costs in respect of each edition of his papers, the Minister has to do a specific thing.  In the ordinary way, the solicitor gets full costs.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General Mulcahy General Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>General Mulcahy</NameTxt>
      <P>It is the other way round.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelComynKC" hpid="Mr. Comyn Mr. Comyn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Comyn</NameTxt>
      <P>&ldquo;Unless the Minister shall in any particular case otherwise direct or agree&mdash;&mdash;&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SamuelBrownKC" hpid="Mr. Brown Mr. Brown">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Brown</NameTxt>
      <P>The scale applies.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelComynKC" hpid="Mr. Comyn Mr. Comyn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Comyn</NameTxt>
      <P>Would it not be better to state that the Minister may in a particular case direct that the full scale of costs shall be allowed?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="120" />
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General Mulcahy General Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>General Mulcahy</NameTxt>
      <P>Is the Senator talking of the pre-1884 scale or the post-1884 scale?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelComynKC" hpid="Mr. Comyn Mr. Comyn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Comyn</NameTxt>
      <P>I am talking of the scales in existence at present, in respect of which we have practice from day to day, the scale on which solicitors to the district councils send in very big bills of costs from time to time. The Minister has considered this matter very carefully.  If he thinks that his form is better than the form I suggest, I have nothing more to say.  But I think that the form of this section ought to be seriously considered.  If a solicitor prepares an abstract of title in a particular case, he should be entitled to his full costs.  But he should not get full costs, as a general rule, if he sends forward the same abstract of title on a second or subsequent occasion.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SamuelBrownKC" hpid="Mr. Brown Mr. Brown">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Brown</NameTxt>
      <P>The effect of the proposed new section is that the solicitor for the owner or vendor will only get the scale fee&mdash;a percentage of the purchase money&mdash;which may be large or small.  In addition, in a case where hardship might be caused the Minister may direct that costs on a higher scale &mdash;item costs or some sum for costs&mdash; shall be paid in respect of the work done.  If the Seanad does as Senator Comyn suggests, it will take away the whole effect of this section&mdash;namely, that in the ordinary case solicitors are only to get the scale fee.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. Johnson Mr. Johnson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Johnson</NameTxt>
      <P>I look at this question from the other point of view.  Suppose the property acquired is very highly valued and that there is no trouble in proving title&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SamuelBrownKC" hpid="Mr. Brown Mr. Brown">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Brown</NameTxt>
      <P>There is generally less trouble in proving title in a case where the purchase money is large than there is in other cases.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. Johnson Mr. Johnson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Johnson</NameTxt>
      <P>What would be the remuneration of the solicitor then?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelComynKC" hpid="Mr. Comyn Mr. Comyn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Comyn</NameTxt>
      <P>His percentage.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. Johnson Mr. Johnson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Johnson</NameTxt>
      <P>It will not be a payment for work done; it will be a payment according to the value of the property. I should like to know whether the Dublin Corporation has been consulted in regard to this amendment <Col N="121" /> and whether they have any views upon the relative merits of the two forms. I can say nothing about the merits of the amendment, but I have information before me showing that the legal costs of the Dublin Corporation in acquiring and clearing a certain site amounted to £750.  It seems to me that one of the purposes of this Bill is to ensure that capital costs be kept down. Local authorities who may have to pay a heavy sum for property in respect of which there is no excessive trouble in proving title should have some protection in the case of highly-valued property as solicitors are to have protection in the case of lowly-valued property.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General Mulcahy General Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>General Mulcahy</NameTxt>
      <P>I think that the costs that Senator Johnson speaks about would naturally be fixed on the old scale we are trying to remedy at the very urgent insistence of the Dublin Corporation.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. Johnson Mr. Johnson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Johnson</NameTxt>
      <P>As to these two forms, which do they prefer?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General Mulcahy General Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>General Mulcahy</NameTxt>
      <P>What the Dublin <Col N="122" /> Corporation wants is 48 as against the old business.  We are here giving them in our amended Section 48 the newest scale.  That is what they want, but we are safeguarding the case in which wrong may occur by reason of introducing a scale of costs which is based on the percentage of compensation.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. Johnson Mr. Johnson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Johnson</NameTxt>
      <P>That meets my point.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelComynKC" hpid="Mr. Comyn Mr. Comyn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Comyn</NameTxt>
      <P>Is the Minister satisfied that he will not have to give more than a percentage?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General Mulcahy General Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>General Mulcahy</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelComynKC" hpid="Mr. Comyn Mr. Comyn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Comyn</NameTxt>
      <P>I am really surprised at the credulity of the Minister if that is so.</P>
      <P>Amendment put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>New Section 48 agreed to.</P>
      <P>The Seanad went out of Committee.</P>
      <P>Progress reported.</P>
      <P>The Seanad adjourned at 7.15 p.m. until 11.30 a.m., Friday, 11th December, 1931.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
</Debate>