<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE Debate SYSTEM "../Debate.dtd"[]>
<Debate DocTitle="Seanad Debate" Day="Fri" Date="11" Month="Dec" Year="1931" Vol="15" No="3" DateIrish="Dé hAoine, 11 Nollaig 1931" DateEnglish="Friday, 11 December 1931" House="S" CommitteeEng="" CommitteeIr="" SubNameEng="" cnum="123">
  <MainHeading Type="Prelude" LHead="" RHead="">
    <Title>
    </Title>
    <P>
      <Col N="123" /> Do chuaidh an Cathaoirleach i gceannas ar 11.30 a.m.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Housing (Gaeltacht) (Amendment) Bill, 1931" RHead="(Certified Money Bill)&mdash;Second Stage">
    <Title>Housing (Gaeltacht) (Amendment) Bill, 1931 (Certified Money Bill)&mdash;Second Stage.</Title>
    <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That the Bill be now read a Second Time.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="FionanLynch" hpid="Minister for Lands and Fisheries (Mr. Lynch) Fionán Lynch">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Lands and Fisheries (Mr. Lynch)</NameTxt>
      <P>This is a Bill to enlarge the provision of one quarter of a million pounds provided under the Principal Act.  Up to the present we have earmarked a sum of £230,000 in round figures out of that sum, and if we did not make further provision now sanctions would have to stop about the end of next month.  The fact that we have earmarked £230,000 does not mean that anything like that sum has been spent. In fact, only about £45,000 has so far been issued.  The time required to complete a house in very many cases is almost two years.  The person cannot give up the time that he would normally devote to his farm work to building. He therefore does the building when there is not very much doing in his ordinary farm work.  As well as that, there is only a limited number of handymen in the Gaeltacht and it frequently happens that a person cannot get a handyman when he wants one, such as a carpenter or a stone mason.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I am quite satisfied with the progress which has been made under the Act, and from the expressions of opinion I have heard from all sides in the Dáil I believe that the operation of the Act has given very general satisfaction. The inspectors engaged on this work were selected not only because of their competence in supervising work, but because of their sympathetic understanding of the people in the Gaeltacht. It is generally agreed that they have been very successful in their work and that the people met them in a friendly <Col N="124" /> spirit and looked upon them, not as they were rather accustomed to look on Government officials in the past, but as their friends.  That has been a very great advantage.  The officials themselves, because of their sympathy with the Gaeltacht, did their work with something more than what we might call the ordinary conscientious discharge of their duty.  I should like to take this opportunity of paying public tribute to the way they have done their work.</P>
    <P>In this matter there is a speed beyond which it is not wise to go.  As I said, the number of handymen is limited.  There is a large number of young men learning the different crafts connected with house building, but it would be unwise to allow them to take charge of the building of a house until they have become absolutely competent, because, as one can understand, the health of the people and the cost of repairs subsequently will largely depend on the efficiency with which the houses are built.  Something like 2,500 houses have been sanctioned up to date and this in itself will greatly relieve the urgency of the problem.  I assured the Oireachtas when the Principal Act was going through that I would deal first with what might be called the worst slum areas in the Gaeltacht.  In fact, the original Act provided that three-fifths of the total sum should be spent in the very congested areas in the fíor-Ghaeltacht. The principle adopted is that if the total valuation of an area, divided by the population, is one guinea or under, that area is one of the areas to which three-fifths of the money must be applied.  That does not mean that some of the other two-fifths might not also be applied there.  In fact, as we stand at present, out of the amount we have earmarked we have given something more than three-fifths to these particular areas.  Until these particular slum areas are relieved it would be unwise to deal with the places which are somewhat better off.</P>
    <P>Under Section 12 of the Principal Act the Department was empowered to assist people in the purchasing of materials.  We met with great success in a combined purchasing scheme in <Col N="125" /> this matter.  We found that the suppliers of materials met us in a very friendly spirit.  We dealt with home materials so far as possible and so far as was practical, but some foreign materials had to be procured and the makers of materials abroad even seemed quite anxious to help the Department in dealing with this problem and to help the people of the Gaeltacht.  The result was that we succeeded in lowering the cost of a four-roomed house as it would be built under ordinary circumstances by about £27 owing to this combined purchasing scheme.  That went, of course, to the advantage of the man who was building so that it was tantamount to an increase of £27 in the free grant.  I should like to say also, as it is a matter of considerable interest, that the entire working of this Act has been carried out in Irish.  The tender forms sent out and the correspondence from the Department were all in Irish and all the work done by the inspectors has been done entirely through the Irish language.  The work has not only not suffered in efficiency in that way, but everybody agrees that scarcely any Act has ever been so efficiently worked.</P>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMacEllin" hpid="Mr. MacEllin Mr. MacEllin">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEllin</NameTxt>
      <P>The original Gaeltacht Housing Act was very generally welcomed and, as the Minister has pointed out, the officials in the Gaeltacht areas have been welcomed on all sides.  I thoroughly agree with that, but from what I have seen there are not yet many signs of any great progress having been made under the Act.  The Minister has admitted that only £45,000 has been paid out so far under the Act although another £100,000 is made available under this Bill.  The great grievance of many people in the Gaeltacht is that they do not get replies to applications which they put in for grants and that those who do get replies hear nothing further about their applications.  I called at the office on one occasion and I found that they were in some difficulty there because there were not sufficient inspectors. Things may have improved since that time, but they have not improved to the extent that the areas scheduled under the Act are all getting the same <Col N="126" /> treatment.  It appeared to me that under the Act they were all to get the same treatment.  A Gaeltacht area is a Gaeltacht area, and when it is scheduled some effort should be made to allow the people in that area who have made applications for grants to make a start with the building of the houses.  At least they should be informed that there is a possibility that their application will be granted or that they come within the provisions of the Act.  People in the scheduled areas feel that they have a grievance in this matter and they are very annoyed about it.  I hope therefore that an effort will now be made to see that all areas scheduled under the Act will get the same treatment and that the benefits of the Act will be extended to them as quickly as possible.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. Johnson Mr. Johnson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Johnson</NameTxt>
      <P>This Bill has come upon us rather unexpectedly.  I take it there are other Senators in the same position as myself in not being quite prepared for the discussion of it today. The Minister's statement certainly was encouraging in more ways than one.  I had an idea when the original Bill was being carried through that it would give a good headline, if it succeeded, for tackling rehousing, in the rural areas not in the Gaeltacht.  From what the Minister said now I am convinced that that will be the lesson to be drawn and that similar methods of helping the rebuilding of houses in country areas will require to be followed to those undertaken in respect of the Gaeltacht housing.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Some of the figures the Minister read out suggest some queries.  I gathered that for the £230,000 earmarked 2,500 houses, approximately, have been arranged for.  That is equal to a subsidy of £92 per house.  That is rather a higher figure than I think we were led to believe when the original Bill was going through, but I cannot be too definite upon that point.  Perhaps the most important subject that the Minister mentioned was that through combined purchasing of materials they were able to provide a reduction of cost of materials amounting to £27 per house.  That confirms the contention that we from these benches have been <Col N="127" /> uttering for several years back that if in any general house building campaign there was some regulated and authoritative combination which would secure the combined purchasing of standardised materials, it would go further than any other single factor to reduce the cost of house building.  Even for so small a number of houses as 2,500, and I am not quite sure whether the combined purchasing of materials covered the 2,500 houses, the Minister has shown that combined purchasing of material has resulted in a reduction of cost per house of £27.  That, I hope, will be impressed upon the Minister for Local Government and Public Health. Perhaps we may take occasion to remind him of it when we are dealing with the next Bill on the Order Paper.</P>
    <Speaker pid="RichardWilson" hpid="Mr. Wilson Mr. Wilson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Wilson</NameTxt>
      <P>The only remarks I wish to make on this Bill are in reference to the cost of building.  The Minister indicated that these houses were built by what he described as handymen.  I was wondering has he any idea of the cost of building a four-roomed house in the Gaeltacht so that we could compare that cost with the cost of £450 in the city and with the £350 for the building of a three-roomed house.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickLynchKC" hpid="Mr. Lynch Mr. Lynch">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lynch</NameTxt>
      <P>It would not be quite easy to give that cost because the whole principle of the Act is that a man and his family supply their own labour.  Then handymen work in the Gaeltacht cheaper than ordinary tradesmen in Dublin and the eastern counties.  They are not as efficient as tradesmen.  The handyman is generally an all-round man, but, of course, in Dublin you have different men for different jobs, such as slaters, masons and carpenters. Generally the handyman is a type of person who is a jack of all trades. Such comparisons as the Senator suggested would not lead anywhere even if we were able to supply the figures.  Senator MacEllin must be speaking of areas in the Co. Mayo which are much better off than areas in the Gaeltacht for which this Act was primarily intended.  If he would have a run round Connemara he would see there visible signs of the <Col N="128" /> operations of the Act.  There are something like 500 houses put up, or partly put up, in Connemara and £76,000 out of the total £230,000 has been sanctioned there.  In the Senator's own county of Mayo £54,260 has been earmarked for Gaeltacht housing.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMacEllin" hpid="Mr. MacEllin Mr. MacEllin">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEllin</NameTxt>
      <P>But it has not been paid.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickLynchKC" hpid="Mr. Lynch Mr. Lynch">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lynch</NameTxt>
      <P>I am not suggesting it is paid.  An increase of inspectors is not going to hurry this.  As I pointed out there is a shortage of handymen and, also, the whole principle of the Act is that a man and his household help in putting up the houses and they will only do this when the farm work is not pressing.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMacEllin" hpid="Mr. MacEllin Mr. MacEllin">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEllin</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not agree.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickLynchKC" hpid="Mr. Lynch Mr. Lynch">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lynch</NameTxt>
      <P>We know it from our experience of the operation of the Act. I certainly would make no promise to depart from schemes I have set myself to work out from the worst places first. It was made clear when the Principal Act was going through both Houses that though there were 600 electoral areas affected by the Act many of them would never be touched by the quarter of a million of money to be spent under the Act, neither will all that number of them be touched by this further £100,000.  My particular job is to clear the slums in the fíor-Ghaeltacht and to work up from that to the breac-Ghaeltacht if and when money is available in the future.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>Committee Stage ordered for Wednesday, 16th December.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Housing (Miscellaneous Provisions)" RHead="Bill, 1931&mdash;Committee (resumed)">
    <Title>Housing (Miscellaneous Provisions) Bill, 1931&mdash;Committee (resumed).</Title>
    <P>Section 49 agreed to.</P>
    <P Just="Center">SECTION 50.</P>
    <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That Section 50 stand part of the Bill.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. Johnson Mr. Johnson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Johnson</NameTxt>
      <P>I want to call attention to this particular section and to ask for an explanation of its meaning. It might be thought by anybody reading <Col N="129" /> it that it was of extreme importance but as it is couched in language of reference to other Acts I would like the Minister to explain these Acts.  The Section reads:&mdash;</P>
      <P>Paragraphs (1) to (8) and paragraph (12) of section 11 of the Labourers (Ireland) Act, 1906, which amend the Lands Clauses Acts with respect to the payment of purchase money, the conveyance of land and other matters shall apply to the taking of land otherwise than by agreement under the Lands Clauses Acts as amended by the Housing of the Working Classes Acts by a local authority for the purposes of those Acts, in like manner as the said paragraphs apply to a district council so taking land for the purposes of the Labourers (Ireland) Acts, 1883 to 1930, with the modification that in paragraph (1) of the said section 11 of the Labourers (Ireland) Act, 1906, the words &ldquo;Land Clauses Acts&rdquo; shall be substituted for the words &ldquo;Land Purchase Acts.&rdquo;</P>
      <P>It will be evident to the Seanad that that is the kernel of the whole Bill. I have read it for the sake of the clarification of the meaning of this Bill.  It is so very clear and so easily understood by the most immature mind that it might seem unnecessary to ask the Minister to explain it.  For my part, I do not understand it and I would like the Minister to explain it and say whether he could not by some means give it a simpler meaning.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="Minister for Local Government and Public Health (General Mulcahy) Richard (General) Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Local Government and Public Health (General Mulcahy)</NameTxt>
      <P>It would be quite easy to give it a simple meaning, but from the point of view of getting the law clearly defined the section as it stands is in the simplest possible way for the technical person who has to deal with it.  The object of the section is to enable local authorities to accept a limited proof of title with a view to avoiding excessive expense in connection with the assessment of title to land where the compensation at present does exceed £60.  The local authorities are given power to pay compensation over to a person who gave <i>prima facie</i> evidence that he is the person entitled to sell <Col N="130" /> under the Lands Clauses Act and has been in receipt of rents and profits, and if there are mistakes made it provides for the rectification of those mistakes when shown.</P>
      <P>It is possible to accept a limited title in connection with the acquiring of land under the Labourers Acts.  In order to meet the position that we discussed on Section 48 yesterday, where the Dublin Corporation and others represented to us the great cost of proving titles which had to go back for a considerable period, it is considered desirable to allow urban authorities to take the same kind of simple proof of title that the rural authorities have had.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>Sections 51 to 62 agreed to.</P>
      <P Just="Center">SECTION 63.</P>
      <P>(1)  Notwithstanding anything contained in the Housing Acts, 1925 to 1930, as amended by this Act, the Minister may under section 3 of the Housing Act, 1929 (No. 12 of 1929), as modified by this section, continue to make grants to private persons erecting houses to which that Act as modified by this section applies.</P>
      <P>(2)  For the purposes of this section the aggregate amount of the grants made or to be made under the Housing Acts, 1925 to 1930, as amended by this Acts, shall be increased by the sum of twenty-five thousand pounds.</P>
      <P>(3)  The Housing Bill, 1929 (No. 12 of 1929) shall for the purposes of this section, have effect subject to the following modifications, that is to say:&mdash;</P>
      <P>(a)  Paragraph (a) of sub-section (1) of section 3 of the said Act shall have effect as if there were substituted therein &ldquo;£20&rdquo; for &ldquo;£45&rdquo;;</P>
      <P>(b)  Paragraphs (b), (c) and (d) of sub-section (1) and sub-section (3) of section 5 and subsections (1) and (2) of section 7 of the said Act shall not apply;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>(c)  No grant shall be made by the Minister under the said Act unless the local authority within whose functional area the house is erected make a grant in respect of the <Col N="131" /> house of an amount equivalent to that made by the Minister;</P>
    <P>(d)  For rules 2 and 4 of the First Schedule to the said Act there shall be substituted the following rules:&mdash;</P>
    <P>2.  The floor area of a house shall not be less than 500 square feet and not more than&mdash;</P>
    <P>(a)  950 square feet if such house is erected in a county borough, borough, urban district or town; or</P>
    <P>(b)  1,250 square feet if such house is erected elsewhere;</P>
    <P>4.  The erection of a house shall have been begun on or after the 1st day of January, 1932, and shall have been completed before the expiration of this section.</P>
    <P>(4)  This section shall continue in force until the 31st day of December, 1933, and shall then expire.</P>
    <P>The following amendment stood on the Order Paper in the name of Senator MacEllin:&mdash;</P>
    <P>Section 63, sub-section (1).  To delete in line 36 the words &ldquo;private persons&rdquo; and to substitute therefor the words &ldquo;Public Utility Societies.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Cathaoirleach Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I understand, Senator, you do not desire to move amendment 12 at this stage.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMacEllin" hpid="Mr. MacEllin Mr. MacEllin">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEllin</NameTxt>
      <P>No.  I am not moving it as there is a slight mistake in the wording.  I will move it on the Report Stage.</P>
      <P>Amendment not moved.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMacEllin" hpid="Mr. MacEllin Mr. MacEllin">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEllin</NameTxt>
      <P>Amendment 13 stands in the name of Senator Connolly:&mdash;</P>
      <P>Section 63, sub-section (1).  To add at the end of the sub-section the words &ldquo;or to private persons erecting such houses for their own occupation.&rdquo;</P>
      <P>As this amendment is more or less in keeping with the one that I will move on the Report Stage I would prefer if it were dealt with then, if that is satisfactory to the House.  If not I will go on with it now.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="132" />
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General Mulcahy General Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>General Mulcahy</NameTxt>
      <P>It is not clear what the meaning of it is.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Cathaoirleach Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Perhaps it would be more convenient to take the amendment on the Report Stage if the House is agreeable.</P>
      <P>Amendment not moved.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMacEllin" hpid="Mr. MacEllin Mr. MacEllin">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEllin</NameTxt>
      <P>I move: &ldquo;Section 63, sub-section (3), to delete paragraph (a).&rdquo;  I am not particularly enthusiastic about the amendment but would like to have it discussed.  It seems to me that the amendment would have the effect of leaving matters as they were under the original Act passed in 1929.  That Act stated that any person erecting one or more houses would get a grant not exceeding £45 in respect of each house.  That would be the most desirable state of affairs from the rural point of view.  This Bill would take away any advantage given to the rural areas in the previous Act.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General Mulcahy General Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>General Mulcahy</NameTxt>
      <P>I take it that there is some connection between this amendment and the next amendment &ldquo;To delete paragraph (c).&rdquo;  Under the 1929 Act a private person building a house in a rural or an urban area got £45, and a certain remission of rates on the lines of Senator Johnson's amendment.  The proposal in the Bill is that to a private person building a house there shall be made a State grant of £20 on condition that the local authority gives another £20.  There will be a two-thirds remission of rates in respect of the seven years provided for in the Bill.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMacEllin" hpid="Mr. MacEllin Mr. MacEllin">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEllin</NameTxt>
      <P>That point comes under the next amendment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General Mulcahy General Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>General Mulcahy</NameTxt>
      <P>I take it that in discussing whether we should take out this £20, and have it £45 from the State we want to take cognisance of the other idea as well.  At any rate I certainly have to oppose the making of a State grant of £45.  The general principle under which we are operating at the moment is that we have practically reached the time when grants to ordinary private persons building houses should cease.  We have come to the conclusion that the time <Col N="133" /> has practically arrived when it should cease.  We have been unwilling to take the grant away without giving some opening to persons in areas where the local authorities considered the housing position so important, and the general position in that area of such a nature, that private persons ought to continue for some time to get a grant from public funds towards building houses for themselves.  We require the local authorities to show us their conviction in that matter by undertaking to give a grant of £20.  If they give a grant of £20 the State will give a grant of £20, so that a person who, under the 1929 Act, got a grant of £45 will now be able to get within a limited amount, a grant of £40.  I think that is a reasonable step-down in the matter of giving grants to private persons building houses.  It is quite clear that the amount of money required to deal with the housing of the very poor, and to deal with insanitary housing, whether in the urban or in the rural areas, is so great that the subsidising of house building by private persons in the ordinary way must cease at the earliest possible moment.  We are simply giving this outlet to particular areas where the local authorities are convinced that grants ought to continue for some time.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. Johnson Mr. Johnson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Johnson</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister has enunciated a doctrine which, presumably, is going to determine Government policy in regard to housing in the future.  He indicated again that the time has been reached when public assistance to private persons building houses shall cease. The presumption, therefore, is that henceforth it will not be private persons will be building houses, but public authorities.  I do not know whether the Minister intends that, but that seems to me to be the logical conclusion. I can see no prospect, unless there is going to be an all-round advance in wages, of the average workman being able to pay the economic rent&mdash;a paying rent&mdash;for the house whose standard civilization has set.  The expectation the Minister holds out that private persons will build houses for profit for the working <Col N="134" /> classes suited to the wages of the working classes, is, I think, an expectation that will not be realised.  To contemplate that there shall be no public assistance given to private persons building houses means, that there will be no houses built for the working class unless the public authorities build them.  The conclusion, therefore, to be drawn from the Minister's statement is that the Government policy is, that no public assistance is to be given for the building of houses, and that houses for the working classes must come from the rates.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Cathaoirleach Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>We are going a little outside the section.  This is a question of a subsidy of £45 being given instead of £20 in regard to particular houses. It does not deal with the capacity of the poorer people to pay rents.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. Johnson Mr. Johnson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Johnson</NameTxt>
      <P>May I submit that it deals with the subvention of private persons building houses?  It is proposed to make the grant £45 instead of £20.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Cathaoirleach Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes, but you are making a far larger issue of it as regards the ability of poor persons to pay the rent of houses provided for them.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. Johnson Mr. Johnson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Johnson</NameTxt>
      <P>I would think that that is perfectly germane.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Cathaoirleach Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not think it is.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. Johnson Mr. Johnson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Johnson</NameTxt>
      <P>I submit to your ruling, sir.  I cannot pursue the argument.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General Mulcahy General Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>General Mulcahy</NameTxt>
      <P>Lest what the Senator has said would prejudice Senators in favour of the amendment, I would like to point out that in Section 64 (1) (e) we make arrangements by which public utility societies building houses are assisted by the State to the extent of 50 per cent. of the loan charges for 20 years, as well as the possibility of getting 75 per cent. of the capital moneys necessary. While reducing the amount of the grant to private persons in the Bill and putting in this condition, the Bill provides for the giving of the facilities of the Small Dwellings (Acquisition) Act to persons building houses in rural areas, so that they will be able to get through the local authorities, whatever percentage of <Col N="135" /> the capital cost of the houses that they require, up to the limit in the Act&mdash;90 per cent. of the cost.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMacEllin" hpid="Mr. MacEllin Mr. MacEllin">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEllin</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not agree with the Minister that Section 64 (1) (e) will cover any disadvantage as compared with the old Bill.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General Mulcahy General Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>General Mulcahy</NameTxt>
      <P>I was dealing with Senator Johnson's point.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMacEllin" hpid="Mr. MacEllin Mr. MacEllin">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEllin</NameTxt>
      <P>In connection with my amendment?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General Mulcahy General Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>General Mulcahy</NameTxt>
      <P>No.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Cathaoirleach Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>They are not the same.</P>
      <P>Amendment put and declared lost.</P>
      <P>Amendment 15, Section 63, sub-section (3).  To delete paragraph (c).&mdash; (Senator Johnson, Senator MacEllin.)</P>
      <P>Amendment 16.  Section 65, sub-section (1).  To delete the sub-section and to substitute therefor two new sub-sections as follows:&mdash;</P>
      <P>&ldquo;(1)  Each local authority having power to levy rates shall, in every of the first nineteen local financial years after the valuation for rating purposes of a dwelling-house to which this section applies remit a portion of the rates leviable in respect of that house in that year by the local authority.</P>
      <P>(2)  The amount of the rate leviable in each year as aforesaid which shall be remitted by a local authority under the foregoing sub-section shall be the proportion of such rate specified in the second column of the Fourth Schedule of this Act opposite the number of such year in the first column of the said Fourth Schedule.&rdquo;&mdash;(Senator Johnson.)</P>
      <P>Amendment 18.  New Schedule. Before the Fourth Schedule to insert a new Schedule as follows:&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P Just="Center">
      <Col N="136" />&ldquo;FOURTH SCHEDULE.</P>
    <P Just="Center">Proportion of Rates to be Remitted.</P>
    <table pgwide="1">
      <tgroup cols="2">
        <colspec colname="1" colnum="1" colwidth="15*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <colspec colname="2" colnum="2" colwidth="35*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <thead>
          <row>
            <entry rowsep="1">Number of year after valuation for rating purposes.</entry>
            <entry rowsep="1">Proportion of rates to be remitted.</entry>
          </row>
        </thead>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry>1st</entry>
            <entry>Nineteen-twentieths</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>2nd</entry>
            <entry>Eighteen-twentieths</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>3rd</entry>
            <entry>Seventeen-twentieths</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>4th</entry>
            <entry>Sixteen-twentieths</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>5th</entry>
            <entry>Fifteen-twentieths</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>6th</entry>
            <entry>Fourteen-twentieths</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>7th</entry>
            <entry>Thirteen-twentieths</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>8th</entry>
            <entry>Twelve-twentieths</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>9th</entry>
            <entry>Eleven-twentieths</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>10th</entry>
            <entry>Ten-twentieths</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>11th</entry>
            <entry>Nine-twentieths</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>12th</entry>
            <entry>Eight-twentieths</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>13th</entry>
            <entry>Seven-twentieths</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>14th</entry>
            <entry>Six-twentieths</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>15th</entry>
            <entry>Five-twentieths</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>16th</entry>
            <entry>Four-twentieths</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>17th</entry>
            <entry>Three-twentieths</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>18th</entry>
            <entry>Two-twentieths</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>19th</entry>
            <entry>One-twentieth.&rdquo;</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
            </entry>
            <entry>(Senator Johnson).</entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. Johnson Mr. Johnson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Johnson</NameTxt>
      <P>Amendment 15 is related directly to amendments 16 and 18.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Cathaoirleach Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Would you like to discuss them together?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. Johnson Mr. Johnson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Johnson</NameTxt>
      <P>I would.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Cathaoirleach Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I take it that the House will agree to that seeing that the amendments are related.</P>
      <P>Agreed to discuss amendments together.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. Johnson Mr. Johnson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Johnson</NameTxt>
      <P>I might say that I could probably have produced the same results if I had moved to delete lines in 49 and 50 the words &ldquo;and sub-sections (1) and (2) of Section 7.&rdquo; Perhaps.  That would not have been very clear, so I put down the amendments as they appear on the Order Paper.  Paragraph (c) which the amendment proposes to delete states:</P>
      <P>No grant shall be made by the Minister under the said Act unless the local authority within whose functional area the house is erected make a grant in respect of the house of an amount equivalent to that made by the Minister.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="137" /> The subsequent amendments are directed towards securing that private persons building houses, instead of receiving a grant from the local authority of £20 and a remission of two-thirds of the rates for seven years, will get no grant from the local authority but will get a grant of £20 from the Minister, the local authority remitting the rates in the manner in which they have been remitted during the past few years&mdash; that is to say, 19-20ths the first year, falling by twentieths to one-twentieth in the nineteenth year. Under this proposal, there will be practically no loss to the local authority. Assuming that the £20 proposed in the Bill as a subsidy were set aside for twenty years at 5 per cent. compound interest, it would, at the end of that period, amount to £53.  To put it the other way, the total amount of rates received under the plan of the Bill in twenty years would be £220.  If we deduct from that total, which the local authority will receive under the plan of the Bill, the amount which £20 set aside for twenty years at five per cent. compound interest will reach, we will get a sum of £167.  I am speaking now of a holding which pays £15 rates.  That same holding, under the proposal in my amendments, would give to the Corporation, instead of £167 in twenty years, £157 15s. in the same period, so that the financial effect on the local council would be very small. If there are any advantages at all to be got by the measure, the financial loss cannot be regarded as appreciable. That there are advantages to the corporation and to the community generally is the case that I think has to be made before the amendment will appeal to the House.</P>
    <P>I submit that the proposal in the Bill will deter builders and other private individuals from building houses.  The remission of two-thirds of the rates for the first seven years is going to add to the annual outlay of the occupant of the house for these first seven years as compared with the previous remission of rates by twentieths, and at the end of the seven years, there will be a sudden jump in the call upon his purse. In the case of the class of house that one thinks of in this connection, the <Col N="138" /> jump will practically amount to 5/- per week.  That will come at the end of the seven years, when there will be an annual demand for repairs and renovations, so that the effect of the Bill will be to deter prospective house-purchasers from building.  If the deterrent is such that no houses are built, then such income from rates as the corporation might expect during the twenty years will not be received.  Consequently, the corporation will be worse off under the Bill, if my anticipation is well-founded, than they would be under the scheme which has prevailed up to the present and which it is now sought to alter.</P>
    <P>The Minister has indicated that it is the view of his Department&mdash;I am speaking now of the Dublin area&mdash;that there should be some intermediate stage between the houses likely to be built by the corporation and the £800 to £1,000 houses which are being built.  He hopes to bring about the building of houses costing £600 or £650. I think that that hope is not well-founded. Under the proposal made by the Minister in the Bill, it seems to me that there is no prospect at all of a house valued by the corporation valuers at £600, the remission of rates being based on that valuation, being let at less than £1 a week or thereabouts for the first seven years, the rent increasing by about 3/- per week after that.  A man who can contemplate paying £1 a week as rent ought to have a better house than £600 will provide.  The experience of experts on this subject, I think, is that the person who can pay a rent of about £1 per week will look for a bigger house than £600 or £650 will provide.  There is not any great likelihood of this class of house being built by speculative builders or public utility societies under the proposals in the Bill.  I fear that there will be a considerable reduction in the number of houses built by private persons as a result of the new scheme as set out in the Bill.  I fear that the campaign of house-building which is hoped for through the clearance of sites and the provision of dwellings for the working classes will not be got under way within the next six months.  Therefore, we have to face <Col N="139" /> the prospect of a fall in the production of houses of the more expensive kind&mdash; costing from £800 to £1,000&mdash;without any concurrent production of houses of the cheaper kind.  During the next twelve months there will be, in my opinion, a slackening-off in house-building. That slackening might be mitigated if the plan of the recent Acts were revived&mdash;that is to say, if the inducement of remission of rates for twenty years were held out to private builders, speculators and public utility societies building on the lines on which they have been building up to the present.  That would be much more attractive to them than the scheme of the Bill.  As the proposal in the amendments will not have any adverse effect on either State finances or municipal finances&mdash;it will be actually beneficial to municipal finances&mdash;I think the case for the amendments is complete and I hope the House will support my proposal.</P>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMacEllin" hpid="Mr. MacEllin Mr. MacEllin">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEllin</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator Johnson and I have been thinking along the same lines with regard to the deletion of paragraph (c), but I view the matter somewhat differently from him.  My reason for moving the deletion of the paragraph is that I think it would be inoperative in the country.  Local authorities would not, I think, avail themselves of the opportunity of making grants, not because they are not anxious to assist in the building of houses but because these grants would involve an increase in the rates.  We have coming up here constantly Bills which involve an increase of some sort in the rates.  The innocent statement is made from time to time that such a Bill will only mean a penny in the £ additional on the rates, and that that will not be very much.  We may be told that a penny in the £ will implement the provisions of this Bill.  That does not look very much, but we must remember that during the past six months we have had half a dozen Bills in respect of which the same suggestion was made&mdash;that 1d. or 2d. in the £ on the rates would not matter very much. We have had the Vocational Education Bill, the Tourist Traffic Bill and the <Col N="140" /> Agriculture Bill, in respect of which there was the same underlying suggestion. That is why I object to this sort of legislation.  I feel that on account of this paragraph the Bill will not be made operative by the local authorities.  That will mean that no grants will go to the rural areas and that all assistance will be done away with.  We have had quite a number of Commissions appointed to take charge of local areas.  I have no doubt that the Commissioners will give effect to the Bill.  It will cost them nothing.</P>
      <P>These are the main reasons why I move the deletion of this particular paragraph.  I ask the House to give serious consideration to the two particular suggestions that are coming up here in this Bill.  I ask the House to turn down definitely this method of getting Bills passed, and I ask the House to refuse to implement Bills for the benefit of people other than for the benefit of people who are asked to pay more.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General Mulcahy General Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>General Mulcahy</NameTxt>
      <P>There is a tremendous readiness on the part of Senators and Deputies in general to embark on works that require money as long as the Minister for Finance is the person who has to go and find it.  But there is a reluctance on their part, as members of local bodies, to shoulder and carry out works where they themselves have to be the instruments for imposing the taxation.</P>
      <P>If there is on the part of local bodies a reluctance to raise money for housing, then, I think, there is being created by pressure of one kind or another on the members of the Executive Council something designed to create for them a false conscience in this matter.  If our housing conditions are such that they ought to be remedied by the application of public money to them, then those who are in charge of local government ought to be as sensitive to the necessity for that as those who sit elsewhere.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMacEllin" hpid="Mr. MacEllin Mr. MacEllin">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEllin</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister is not dealing with my point at all.  It is not dealt with in a parochial way down the country.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="141" />
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General Mulcahy General Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>General Mulcahy</NameTxt>
      <P>If we have not a parochial conscience then we cannot have a national conscience.  I do not believe we can have a national conscience, particularly in this question of housing, if that is the position.  It seems to me that the standard of housing that the people can afford is very closely allied to the whole of their economic life.  You cannot take an area, say, in Connacht and establish there a false standard of housing based upon a false conception of the amount of money that there is in Dublin to apply to housing.  I think we are working on very sound lines in passing from the position in which we can provide persons in particular circumstances with direct grants from the State.  In passing from that position we give local bodies an opportunity of seeing how much reality, from the point of view of their own particular circumstances, there is in this general demand for providing that persons building houses ought to be assisted from the public funds.  The whole policy of the Government would be to drop the grants for private persons right away if there was not evidence on the part of the local authorities from the facts that lay around them that they were prepared to stand for the idea, for some time to come at least, that private persons should be assisted from the public funds.  So much with respect to the cutting out of local authorities from these schemes.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>On the point raised by Senator Johnson that the old scheme of remission of rates should apply and that the State grant of £20 should be given, I want to say that the remission of rates proposed in the Bill is two-thirds remission for seven years.  This is two years in excess of the remission granted to ordinary building under the Local Government Act of 1927.  If you take a house in the City of Dublin with a valuation of £22, and assuming a rate of 16/- in the £, the capitalised value of the remission of rates in the Bill would amount to £68.  On the scheme of remission proposed by Senator Johnson the capital value of the remission would be £125.  If we pass over to the remission of rates on a sliding scale for <Col N="142" /> twenty years, for what purpose are we going to do that and how long are we going to continue?  It seems to me that we ought only do it on such a scale for the purpose of off-setting the high building costs.  If we are being driven by our general circumstances, financial and otherwise, here to the conclusion that we cannot go ahead with the present standard of housing at the present building costs, then we are only widening the hole in our pocket and we are going to be up against a serious financial situation as well as a serious social situation by encouraging people to expect, from a certain amount of effort, housing conditions of a kind that they cannot expect to continue.</P>
    <P>The sooner we clear the ground around the building costs and around the standard for building and the capacity of the ordinary people, I think the better it will be. When I speak of the capacity of the ordinary people I am not speaking of the poorer classes of the people and of the people who live in insanitary houses.  What we are proposing for them is that we will advance them loans if the parochial bits of the national conscience think that they ought to get a lump grant from the public funds.  If the local conscience thinks so they will get that grant.  But we are arranging as a kind of standard that persons of that kind, building houses, will get two-thirds remission of rates for seven years.</P>
    <P>In the Local Government Act of 1927 it was arranged as an amendment to a previous Act that ordinary new building would be entitled to two-thirds remission of rates for five years.  That Act was expiring in 1930 after three years.  I must say I was astounded when I found that that Act was being allowed to lapse without any person connected with any part of the building industry in this country drawing attention to the fact that it was lapsing and pointing out that they did not want it to lapse.  No approach good, bad or indifferent was made on behalf of the builders or on behalf of anyone dependent on the builders, protesting <Col N="143" /> that that Act was going to lapse, although it represented a two-third remission of rates for five years in respect of every class of building that was not getting it under the Housing Act.</P>
    <P>It seems to me that there must be a terrible amount of obscurity and of waste in building costs if those who are so vitally interested as the builders and others, can afford to ignore the possible dropping of an Act like that.  It was really in a most casual way that I extended the Act. I extended the Act because I thought it was reasonable that it should be extended.  It is reasonable that for such a small number of years in respect of new building that that remission of rates should be given.</P>
    <P>We propose in this Bill to give a remission of rates for seven years for that class of house.  I think it is better that that remission of rates should be given in a concentrated way over the seven years than that the total value of what would be given would be allowed to drag out in a scattered way.  I know if there were any rapid development of housing in any area it might very easily be a source of very great trouble to the local authority that these rates on a fairly large number of houses were not being paid up, and that at the time when we expect that local authorities will be called upon to bear fairly heavy burdens in connection with the provision of houses for the poorer classes and the removal and clearance of insanitary areas.  It will thus be seen how necessary it is that this remission period should not be too long drawn out.</P>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. Johnson Mr. Johnson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Johnson</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister has evidently not faced the probability that the house-building campaign would slow down, or perhaps he has faced it and looks upon it with unconcern.  If he thinks that the whole of the efforts of house builders should be concentrated on building houses for the clearance of and the re-housing of slum areas, and that that is going to be ensured, I have no fault to find with the proposals of the Bill, but I fear <Col N="144" /> that the present circumstances are such that that campaign of re-housing slum areas will not be undertaken with the avidity which everyone hopes because of the expectation of costs, the monetary difficulties and the inability to get down to the figure of £450 per flat that the Minister has set out.  If the local authorities had arrived at the conclusion&mdash;I am speaking now of the Dublin authority&mdash;that at all costs, even at the cost of an addition of another 5/- in the £ to the rates, that they would proceed with the re-housing of slum areas, then the chance of any subsidy from the local authority to assist or supplement the State subsidy of equal amount for private builders goes.  The chances of both those moneys being raised by the local authority are very small indeed. I wonder whether the Minister is in a position to give the House the assurances that within this next six months there will be a very wholehearted campaign for building houses for the re-housing of the slum dwellings in Dublin and whether the present prospects are such that we can look with confidence upon that being undertaken. The Minister asks for what purpose would this larger remission of rates be embodied in legislation.  The whole purpose is to ensure the building of houses.  It has been the Government's policy up to now, and I have supported it for one, that even though we are not building houses which do house the working classes, that every house which is built is easing the pressure and making it possible for a little less crowding to take place in the working class areas.  If that were well founded at all it would still continue if the houses of a better type are built, and so long as we are not asking the State to subsidise, to any greater degree than they are at present the building of that class of houses, so long as we are not asking the local authorities to pay any more money than the Bill contemplates, then I think the Minister's objection falls to the ground at once unless his policy is to prevent, so far as he can, the building of this better type of house.  Apparently there is no hope of the Minister accepting these amendments, and I suppose there is no strong opinion in the Seanad in <Col N="145" /> favour of them, but I shall be very agreeably surprised if we do not hear by next May that there has been a <Col N="146" /> great falling off in the house building campaign in and around Dublin.</P>
      <P>Amendment 15 put.</P>
      <P Just="Center">The Committee divided: Tá, 9; Níl, 17.</P>
      <P Just="Center">Tá.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <table pgwide="1">
      <tgroup cols="2">
        <colspec colname="1" colnum="1" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <colspec colname="2" colnum="2" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry rowsep="1">Caitlín Bean Uí Chléirigh.<br />Michael Comyn, K.C.<br />Michael Duffy.<br />Thomas Foran.<br />Thomas Johnson.</entry>
            <entry rowsep="1">Seán E. MacEllin.<br />Colonel Moore.<br />Séumas Robinson.<br />Séumas Ryan.<br /></entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
    <P Just="Center">Níl.</P>
    <table pgwide="1">
      <tgroup cols="2">
        <colspec colname="1" colnum="1" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <colspec colname="2" colnum="2" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry rowsep="1">Sir Edward Coey Bigger.<br />Samuel L. Brown, K.C.<br />Mrs. Costello.<br />John C. Counihan.<br />The Countess of Desart.<br />James G. Douglas.<br />Michael Fanning.<br />Dr. O. St. J. Gogarty.<br />Sir John Keane.</entry>
            <entry rowsep="1">James Moran.<br />Joseph O'Connor.<br />M. F. O'Hanlon.<br />L. O'Neill.<br />Bernard O'Rourke.<br />Siobhán Bean an Phaoraigh.<br />Michael Staines.<br />Richard Wilson.<br /></entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
    <P Just="Center">Tellers:&mdash; Tá: Senators Johnson and MacEllin; Níl: Senators Wilson and O'Hanlon.</P>
    <P>Amendment declared lost.</P>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Cathaoirleach Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>There is a new amendment which has not been circulated. It is to Section 63 (3).</P>
      <P Just="Center">SECTION 63.</P>
      <P>(3) The Minister shall not make any contribution under this section towards the expenses incurred by local authorities or public utility societies in the erection of any houses in respect of which grants have been or undertaken to be paid by him under the Housing Acts, 1925, to 1930.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardWilson" hpid="Mr. Wilson Mr. Wilson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Wilson</NameTxt>
      <P>I move:</P>
      <P>Section 63, sub-section (3).  To delete lines 3-6 inclusive of paragraph (d) and to substitute therefor the following:&mdash;</P>
      <P>4.  The erection of the house shall have been begun on or after the 1st day of October, 1931, and shall have been completed after the 29th day of February, 1932, but before the expiration of this section.</P>
      <P>It makes a change in the date.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General Mulcahy General Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>General Mulcahy</NameTxt>
      <P>Houses begun subsequent to 1929 and finished before 29th February, 1932, get a grant of £45. If a house were begun, say, in the month of November and not finished before the 29th day of February, 1932, with the date January in, that house could neither get a £45 grant nor the grant that would be available if the twenty plus twenty were made available in any particular area.  This sets back the date January to the 1st October, 1931.  It is impossible to set a date back so far that houses beyond the estimated number of houses would come in between the date which we fix here and the 29th February next.  I am told that it would be possible to begin a house, not now, but say on 1st December, for the purpose of completion under this Act to earn the £45.  It is not possible to extend the date back in my opinion, beyond the 1st day of October, but we are extending it so that if any houses escape they will be a small number of houses.  If they escape getting a grant they will escape it because of some radical difficulty in carrying out the work on the part of builders.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. Johnson Mr. Johnson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Johnson</NameTxt>
      <P>I think this is an amendment of which we should have notice, because it makes a considerable alteration so far as I can see.  As between the provisions of the Bill and this amendment there are twelve months in one case and there are four months in the other, ending on 29th February, 1932.  I cannot quite understand <Col N="147" /> the Minister's statement which was made while we were trying to read the amendment and collate it, and I am not satisfied that we should insert this amendment without notice.  I think it would be better to defer it until the Report Stage.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General Mulcahy General Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>General Mulcahy</NameTxt>
      <P>I put this net point.  At the present moment a house begun since 1929 and completed by the 29th February, 1932, will get the £45 grant.  We are providing in the section as it stands that a house which is begun on or after 1st January next and completed before 1933 will get a £20 grant, plus £20 from the local authority, if the local authority are giving it.  As the matter stands then, the house that was begun on 31st December, 1931, and was not completed before the end of February, 1932, could neither get the £45 grant nor the £20 grant, and the amendment is to change the date, 1st January, back to a more reasonable date, so that if a house was begun on 1st October or later than 1st October, and was not completed by 29th February, 1932, it would lose the £45 grant, but under the section would get the £20 plus £20 if the local authority were giving it.  That is the purpose of the amendment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. Johnson Mr. Johnson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Johnson</NameTxt>
      <P>If the Minister would agree to make the date 31st May instead of 29th February, to give a longer period, then I could understand the value of the amendment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelComynKC" hpid="Mr. Comyn Mr. Comyn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Comyn</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister's statement seems to be clear enough, but at the same time it does not show that there is any necessity why this amendment should be taken now.  We do not understand its terms except in so far as we have heard the Minister speak of them.  Of course, we accept every word he has said, but we do not fully understand all the bearings of the amendment. There is apparently no reason whatever why the amendment should be put to the House at this stage, and I think it would come in more conveniently on the Report Stage this day week.  I cannot see any possible objection to that.  I do not say that there is anything involved or hidden about the amendment as far as I can see.  The only thing that would make us believe <Col N="148" /> that there was something in it, which it was not desired we should know, is that the amendment should be put to a division now when there is no necessity for doing so seeing that it can be brought forward on the Report Stage.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General Mulcahy General Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>General Mulcahy</NameTxt>
      <P>In reply to Senator Johnson's point, the power of the local authority to give grants in respect of houses begun after 1st April ceased until it was included in this Bill.  We had to undertake to make provision by which houses begun after 1st April and completed by the end of February would get a grant equivalent to the grant available before, £45.  There has been full notice in respect of the terminal dates in respect of that. Really the normal terminal date was extended by four months, from October to 29th February.  What Senator Johnson would look for would be an extension of the date that would allow more houses to come under the £45 grant.  This amendment is simply shifting back the date in order that in the in-between period houses begun between 1st October and 1st January would not fail to get the new grants.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. Johnson Mr. Johnson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Johnson</NameTxt>
      <P>In that section, will houses started in September be covered?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General Mulcahy General Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>General Mulcahy</NameTxt>
      <P>They will not be covered at all because houses started in September would be expected to be completed before February.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. Johnson Mr. Johnson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Johnson</NameTxt>
      <P>That is one of the difficulties. A house is begun on 15th September and it is not covered, but if the building started on 1st October it will be covered.  The unfortunate man who happened to start a few men on the job in the middle of September, not knowing the date which was to be fixed, must lose this subsidy.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General Mulcahy General Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>General Mulcahy</NameTxt>
      <P>You must get a dividing date some time.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. Johnson Mr. Johnson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Johnson</NameTxt>
      <P>That is surely unfair?</P>
      <P>Amendment put and declared carried.</P>
      <P>Section 63, as amended, ordered to stand part of the Bill.</P>
      <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That Section 64 stand part of the Bill.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. Johnson Mr. Johnson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Johnson</NameTxt>
      <P>This section gives in detail the intentions of the Government regarding the financial provisions.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="149" /> I want to have set down fairly and clearly what the intentions of the Government are so that we will be enabled to see at some future time whether these intentions have in fact been carried out.  On the previous stage of the Bill the Minister told us that the £400 house built by a local authority&mdash; that is to say, a house which was not intended to replace those in the slum areas but an ordinary house built under the ordinary provisions of the Housing of the Working Classes Acts outside the slum area&mdash;could be rented at 9/- per week plus rates, the rates being from 20 to 25 per cent., a total charge of about 11/- or 11/3 per week.  Then the £350 single family house which it is intended shall be built to replace slum residences will be able to be rented at 5/10 plus rates, and the £450 flat, again for slum residents, will be able to be rented at 7/6 inclusive of rates.  I want these figures to be noted, because I cannot see the likelihood that the £400 house is going to be let at 9/- per week plus rates in view of the experience of artisans who have taken houses under previous schemes.  I have in my hand a copy of a tenant purchaser's account for a £400 house, and the purchase money, interest and capital repayment, amount to 9/6 per week, and the balance, things other than capital charges, comes to about 6/- per week.</P>
    <P>I do not know whether the period over which these tenant purchasers will have to pay and the price at which the corporation will be able to borrow money is going to make all the difference, but the cost to the purchaser of this particular house is 15s. 6d. a week.  The difference between 11s. and 15s. 6d. is so considerable that I very much doubt whether the probabilities of the Minister as to being able to let a £400 house at 11s. a week, or so, including rates, will be realised.  If they are realised, then I anticipate the occupants of Dublin Corporation houses will have something to say to the Corporation as to why they should have been placed in so disadvantageous a position compared with those who will be tenants of Corporation houses under the new scheme.  I hope the <Col N="150" /> Minister's expectations will be realised.</P>
    <P>Section agreed to.</P>
    <P>Amendment 16 not moved.</P>
    <P>Sections 65 and 66 agreed to.</P>
    <P>First Schedule agreed to.</P>
    <P Just="Center">SECOND SCHEDULE.</P>
    <Speaker pid="RichardWilson" hpid="Mr. Wilson Mr. Wilson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Wilson</NameTxt>
      <P>On behalf of Senator Milroy I move Amendment 17, Second Schedule. Part 1.  Paragraph 3.  To delete sub-paragraph (b).</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General Mulcahy General Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>General Mulcahy</NameTxt>
      <P>This amendment is consequential on the change that was made in the Dáil in respect to compensation for clearance areas.  It also gave rise to amendments that were inserted in the Seanad yesterday to Section 10.</P>
      <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
      <P>Second Schedule agreed to.</P>
      <P>Amendment 18 not moved.</P>
      <P>Third and Fourth Schedules agreed to.</P>
      <P>Title agreed to.</P>
      <P>Bill reported with amendments.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Suspension of" RHead="Standing Orders">
    <Title>Suspension of Standing Orders.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="LaurenceONeill" hpid="Mr. O'Neill Mr. O'Neill">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Neill</NameTxt>
      <P>I move:</P>
      <P>&ldquo;That, notwithstanding anything to the contrary contained in Standing Order 85, the Report Stage of the Housing (Miscellaneous Provisions) Bill, 1931, be taken to-day.&rdquo;</P>
      <P>This motion stood originally in the name of my friend Ald. Byrne, Lord Mayor of Dublin, who has resigned his membership of this House.  I am taking his place for the moment and proposing the motion.  I am not going to delve into this housing question. I consider it would be an insult to the intelligence of Senators to do so. Every member realises that housing is a pressing need, and that it is necessary to get on with the work. The purpose of the motion is to enable the Minister, in the words of a famous patriot, now dead, to get on with the work.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BrianORourke" hpid="Mr. O'Rourke Mr. O'Rourke">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Rourke</NameTxt>
      <P>I second the motion.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnKeaneBart" hpid="Sir John Keane Sir John Keane">
      <NameTxt>Sir John Keane</NameTxt>
      <P>I think it is presuming unduly on the docility of the Seanad to ask us to accept this motion. To hear Senator O'Neill speaking one <Col N="151" /> would think that some vital issue hung on the question of time.  I can imagine that for years this Bill has been incubating in Government offices, and now we are asked to say that the Bill cannot wait for a few days to enable Senators to consider whether, as a result of our discussions during the last two days, any amendments might usefully be framed for the Report Stage. Really, I think a motion of this kind is only making a travesty of legislation.</P>
      <P>No serious plea of urgency has been made.  Senator Johnson, only a few minutes ago, raised a matter which struck me as being one of importance, and one that certainly might be examined.  Our experience has shown that in the case of all measures of importance it has been exceedingly useful to allow a reasonable period of time, following Committee Stage discussion, with a view to amendments being prepared for Report Stage.  This Bill is one of great importance, and I protest very strongly against unseemly high haste of this kind.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasFarren" hpid="Mr. Farren Mr. Farren">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Farren</NameTxt>
      <P>In my opinion it would be very inadvisable for the House to pass this motion.  The Bill before us is one of a very comprehensive nature.  It raises very important issues relating to the whole question of housing.  The Bill has been before the House for a good part of two days.  During the Committee Stage a number of amendments were inserted, and surely Senators require a few days to look into the Bill again in its remodelled state? When Senators have an opportunity of doing that they may consider that further amendments on Report Stage are necessary, particularly in the interests of the body&mdash;the Dublin Corporation&mdash;that mainly will be concerned with the carrying out of the Bill when it becomes an Act.  I think it would be a great mistake to rush the Bill through to-day without giving Senators a further opportunity to examine the alterations made during Committee Stage.  Surely the Bill can afford to wait for a few days to enable Senators to do that?  The Report Stage could be fixed for Wednesday, and, if necessary, the Final Stage could also be taken that day.  In all the circumstances, <Col N="152" /> I think it would be a great mistake to rush the Bill through to-day,' particularly in the interests of those who will have to administer it later on.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelComynKC" hpid="Mr. Comyn Mr. Comyn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Comyn</NameTxt>
      <P>I am sorry that the last motion put on the Order Paper by the Lord Mayor of Dublin, who has ceased for the time being to be a member of this House, should be one tending to undermine the foundations of this Assembly.  Senator Sir John Keane spoke very gently when he said that to introduce a motion of this character is presuming very much on the docility of this House.  I would substitute for the word &ldquo;docility&rdquo; the word...</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OliverGogarty" hpid="Dr. Gogarty Dr. Gogarty">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Gogarty</NameTxt>
      <P>Servility.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelComynKC" hpid="Mr. Comyn Mr. Comyn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Comyn</NameTxt>
      <P>The word &ldquo;servility&rdquo; has been suggested to me by Senator Dr. Gogarty, who has such a command of appropriate language.  It is certainly a word that is appropriate to the present occasion.  It is our duty to resist motions of this kind which are altogether too frequent, motions which propose to supersede the rules of this House and to show a certain contempt for this Assembly.  Once or twice in a session a motion of this kind might be easily passed over, due to the necessities of legislation.  Sometimes we do abrogate our rules for the convenience of Ministers.  We are not unreasonable, and have never been unreasonable in this House.</P>
      <P>The Minister does not say that this motion is brought forward on the present occasion to suit his convenience. I will say this for the Minister, that we can rely upon any statements he makes here as being correct.  I will, however, say this also about the Minister, that he is the greatest offender in regard to his desire to abrogate the rules of this House in connection with various Bills from time to time.  I oppose this motion simply to show that we do not lightly consent to any breach of procedure.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>There is another reason.  A very important amendment has been brought forward here just now.  The Minister explained it fairly and frankly and, I believe, fully.  Still I do not understand all its implications.  It means money to some people.  It means the loss of money to a man <Col N="153" /> who started his house before 1st October and will not have it finished before 1st February.  It may cause serious injustice to an individual. There are other features of the Bill which, as Senator Farren said, ought to be considered calmly between this and next meeting.</P>
    <P>The Minister has not to go anywhere in particular.  He could be here next Wednesday.  Of course if he could not be here we might consider that as a reason, but so far as I know there is no reason why he cannot be here.  There is an amendment to Section 53, a very important amendment.  That could be moved next Wednesday.  For all these reasons this proposal ought not to be pressed.</P>
    <Speaker pid="OliverGogarty" hpid="Dr. Gogarty Dr. Gogarty">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Gogarty</NameTxt>
      <P>It is a new idea that a a Bill is passed here as a mark of favour to the Minister rather than in an attempt to relieve immediately the dreadful conditions that have existed in Dublin for so many years and that have been potential as a criticism of the Government because they have been allowed to exist.  If there were any hope that a few days' delay would produce any improvement in the Bill there might be some idea in leaving it over.  All that Senator Comyn has stated gives us to to understand that he desires to cogitate in a calm atmosphere upon a certain amendment until next Wednesday.</P>
      <P>If there were any hope that a new orientation would come out of a few days' contemplation, I would be prepared to resist this measure being hurried.  The suggestion we have listened to is not so much a presumption of the servility of the House as a criticism of the incapacity of the House to make up its mind immediately.  There is only one point at issue and that is the difference between September and October. Surely a talk between the Minister and Senator Johnson would put that right?  Surely one ought to be able to make up one's mind about a date in a few seconds?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. Johnson Mr. Johnson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Johnson</NameTxt>
      <P>The Senator might, but we are not all supermen.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OliverGogarty" hpid="Dr. Gogarty Dr. Gogarty">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Gogarty</NameTxt>
      <P>I am not even a sub-man. <Col N="154" /> Trying to turn the issue at stake into an insult on the House or endeavouring to take advantage of what Senator Comyn is so sensitive about, the presumed servility of the House, is not a fair way of dealing with this thing.  There is only one point at issue, but in the meantime the people of Dublin are waiting.  They have been waiting for years, and their patience is astonishing.  Let us get some credit for doing a very necessary thing quickly and slickly.  I suggest that the Report Stage should be taken immediately.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General Mulcahy General Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>General Mulcahy</NameTxt>
      <P>There is no desire to press the proposal if Senators do not wish it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Cathaoirleach Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister does not desire to go against the wishes of the House if Senators want this Stage postponed until next Wednesday.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General Mulcahy General Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>General Mulcahy</NameTxt>
      <P>I wanted to say that earlier.  I am sure Senator O'Neill does not wish to press this proposal after hearing the opinions expressed. This proposal was submitted by the Lord Mayor of Dublin after seeing the amendments that were actually down to the Bill.  There was an amendment introducing the question of grants for the improvement of rural housing submitted by Senator MacEllin and it did not appear from the amendments on the Committee Stage that that question was going to be further discussed. There did not appear to be anything radical in the original Committee Stage amendments that would necessitate waiting over until next week.</P>
      <P>In view of the fact that I thoroughly discussed all the various points at issue with the Dublin Corporation, and that I thoroughly discussed everything likely to be contentious with the Irish Landowners' Association, including the point Senator Sir John Keane dealt with yesterday, I did not expect that any major point on that side was going to arise.  I expected to be in the Dáil on Wednesday dealing with the Traffic Bill, and this motion was put down by Senator Byrne to convenience the work generally.  If the Seanad would arrange for the taking of the Report Stage of this Bill first thing on Wednesday, it would be a considerable convenience to me.  We can then get the amendments to the Dáil before the Dáil adjourns.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="155" />
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. Johnson Mr. Johnson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Johnson</NameTxt>
      <P>On the general question of this practice of putting down motions of this kind, I think it is quite excusable where there is a non-controversial Bill to which there were no amendments down for the Committee Stage.  Let us take the Unemployment Relief Bill.  That is a Certified Money Bill and it might well have been thought necessary to have it passed through all its stages yesterday.  There were no amendments possible, yet there was no urgent motion put down to carry the remaining stages of the Bill so as to enable the money to be spent before Christmas.  This motion was put down in face of the fact that there were ten or twelve amendments on the Paper.  Most of them were Government amendments and were likely to be passed, but they were altering the face of the Bill.  That the House should contemplate passing those amendments and taking the Report Stage without having an opportunity of finding out the effect of the amendments on the Bill would be an unwise procedure, and that ought not be a practice that we should allow to become generally operative. It is not by any means the truth, as Senator Gogarty suggested, that a delay of three of four days is going to affect by one second the carrying into effect of any housing scheme.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LaurenceONeill" hpid="Mr. O'Neill Mr. O'Neill">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Neill</NameTxt>
      <P>I am sorry that one of the last acts of the Lord Mayor in this Chamber should be designated by a member of the House as an attempt to turn the Seanad into a body of serfs. That was not his intention, I am sure. What prompted him to put down this motion was, I feel certain, his anxiety as Lord Mayor of Dublin to bring about an improvement at the earliest possible moment in the frightful condition of things that exists in the City. Those conditions have existed for upwards of a generation.  Living amongst such conditions as he does, knowing that fully 20,000 families, some of them consisting of three, four, five or ten people, are compelled to live in one-room apartments, the Lord Mayor is keenly desirous of having an improvement brought about in the immediate future.  He might, in his absence, have got some little credit, because I am sure that is exactly what <Col N="156" /> was in his mind when he put down this motion.  Owing to the kindly interest that the majority of the Senators seem to take in this Bill&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasFarren" hpid="Mr. Farren Mr. Farren">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Farren</NameTxt>
      <P>Not &ldquo;seem.&rdquo;  We always took an interest in it and did good work too.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LaurenceONeill" hpid="Mr. O'Neill Mr. O'Neill">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Neill</NameTxt>
      <P>Owing to the evident interest that the majority of the members of this Seanad take in this Bill&mdash; when we had a division on it to-day we had only twenty-six Senators present out of fifty-nine.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Cathaoirleach Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>You desire to withdraw your motion, Senator?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LaurenceONeill" hpid="Mr. O'Neill Mr. O'Neill">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Neill</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasForan" hpid="Mr. Foran Mr. Foran">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Foran</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not think the Senator ought to be allowed to withdraw it without some comment.  Seeing that one member of this House has almost made the supreme sacrifice and appealed to the House to pass the motion, we ought to consider that great, wonderful and heroic sacrifice made by this member and pass the motion as he suggested.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMacEllin" hpid="Mr. MacEllin Mr. MacEllin">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEllin</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister raised the point about my amendments in connection with the Report Stage.  I would like to know definitely now if they are in order for the next day or not.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General Mulcahy General Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>General Mulcahy</NameTxt>
      <P>That was not the point.  They were down for the Committee Stage.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Cathaoirleach Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>There was a great deal of talk about the practice of the House.  Senator Byrne was absolutely in order in putting down the motion and any criticism of his conduct is unjust.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. Johnson Mr. Johnson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Johnson</NameTxt>
      <P>In order, but very unwise.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Cathaoirleach Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>He was absolutely in order.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelComynKC" hpid="Mr. Comyn Mr. Comyn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Comyn</NameTxt>
      <P>We were in order in opposing it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Cathaoirleach Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Certainly.</P>
      <P>Motion, by leave, withdrawn.  Report Stage ordered for next Wednesday.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Finance (Customs Duties) (No. 3)" RHead="Bill, 1931&mdash;Final Stages">
    <Title>Finance (Customs Duties) (No. 3) Bill, 1931&mdash;Final Stages.</Title>
    <P>Motion&mdash;&ldquo;That the Bill be received for final consideration&rdquo;&mdash;put and agreed to.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="157" /> Motion&mdash;&ldquo;That the Bill do now pass&rdquo;&mdash;put and agreed to.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Unemployment Relief Bill," RHead="1931&mdash;Final Stages">
    <Title>Unemployment Relief Bill, 1931&mdash;Final Stages.</Title>
    <P>Motion&mdash;&ldquo;That the Bill be received for final consideration&rdquo;&mdash;put and agreed to.</P>
    <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That the Bill do now pass.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. Johnson Mr. Johnson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Johnson</NameTxt>
      <P>On the Final Stage, I am curious to know what the Minister would say to this point: that so far as it goes, £250,000 to be produced in the manner in which it is produced, is not very different from what is commonly called inflation.  So far as I understand it, this money is to be spent in anticipation of money to be received at some future time from the British Government.  In effect what is going to happen is this.  At some future time it is anticipated goods will be provided by the British people for this country's use without any payment in return, and in anticipation of that we are going to issue food tickets in the form of legal tender or consolidated bank notes to pay wages to people who are to make roads.  I would like if the Minister for Finance had been here to follow up this point, and find out from him whether that is any different from what is usually called inflation of credit, whereby goods for consumption might be produced within this country by the labour of people paid for by goods at present in the market.  As the Minister for Finance is not here, I suppose I had better defer pressing that point.  It is an academic consideration, but of very considerable importance, though the amount is only £250,000.  If it were £2,500,000, I think it would be readily judged to be an inflationary act, justifiable no doubt, the spending of money in advance of future production, in effect increasing the demand for commodities at present in the market without increasing the volume of commodities.  I have an idea that that is in germ in this Bill, and, perhaps, we might find a way of having a very much larger sum than £250,000 made available for the relief of unemployment and the promotion of production within the country.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="158" />
    <Speaker pid="MichaelComynKC" hpid="Mr. Comyn Mr. Comyn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Comyn</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator Johnson has just adverted to a point which he says is an academic point, the question of inflation.  To my mind it is the very nerve centre of politics both in Ireland and England at the present day. What I would like to know if the Minister for Finance was here is this: Whether inflation is not going on in England without any corresponding inflation here, and whether in point of fact we are not at the present moment receiving for our goods pieces of paper as pound notes.  I am glad Senator Johnson raised the matter because I intended, at the first opportunity, to raise it and to put those responsible on their guard in reference to this matter, because anybody doing business in Dublin at the present moment will find, from some reason or another, that he is getting in change Bank of England notes. How do they come here?  They come in exchange for goods.  When the Senator talks about its being an academic question, I think he uses the word &ldquo;academic&rdquo; in a peculiar sense. It is a living and a vital question.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Cathaoirleach Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>It is not very academic, but we are on the Unemployment Relief Bill.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelComynKC" hpid="Mr. Comyn Mr. Comyn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Comyn</NameTxt>
      <P>The Chair allowed Senator Johnson, and I presume the Chair will allow me, to say what I have been bursting to say for the last fortnight.  There is another matter which I think is relevant to the Bill, that is as regards the disposal of this £250,000.  I hope it will be scattered a little more than other relief grants were scattered.  In the county in which I am particularly interested, the County of Clare, we get very little from reliefs grants.  We are not in the habit of asking for relief, but we do not want to pay unless we get a share of the produce.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="Minister for Local Government and Public Health (General Mulcahy) Richard (General) Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Local Government and Public Health (General Mulcahy)</NameTxt>
      <P>There is so much nonsense talked about finance that I think it well to say that there is no more financial juggling involved in this proposal than this&mdash;the British owe us a sum of money.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMacEllin" hpid="Mr. MacEllin Mr. MacEllin">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEllin</NameTxt>
      <P>They owe us a good deal.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="159" />
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General Mulcahy General Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>General Mulcahy</NameTxt>
      <P>It is our money. We propose to make use of the borrowing power of the Road Fund to take £250,000 and spend it now, to be repaid out of moneys to be got from the British.</P>
      <P>Question put, and agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Public Charitable Hospitals (No." RHead="2) Bill, 1931&mdash;Committee">
    <Title>Public Charitable Hospitals (No. 2) Bill, 1931&mdash;Committee.</Title>
    <P>Section 1 agreed to.</P>
    <P Just="Center">SECTION 2.</P>
    <P>(2) Where the Minister for Local Government and Public Health pays under this section any money out of available surplus to a nursing organisation, he may require as a condition of such payment that such money shall be applied by such organisation only for or in relation to the promotion of its objects in particular areas specified by the said Minister.</P>
    <P>The following amendment was moved by Senator Wilson and agreed to:&mdash;</P>
    <P>Section 2, sub-section (2).  After the word &ldquo;of&rdquo; in line 32 to insert the word &ldquo;an.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>Section 2, as amended, agreed to.</P>
    <P Just="Center">SECTION 3.</P>
    <P>(1) This Act may be cited as the Public Charitable Hospitals (No. 2) Act, 1931.</P>
    <Speaker pid="RichardWilson" hpid="Mr. Wilson Mr. Wilson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Wilson</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment 2:</P>
      <P>Section 3, sub-section (1).  After the word &ldquo;Hospitals&rdquo; in line 38 to insert in brackets the word &ldquo;(Amendment).&rdquo;</P>
      <P>This amendment is designed to bring the title of the Bill into harmony with the title of the Public Charitable Hospitals (Amendment) Act, 1931, and with the title of the Public Charitable Hospitals (Amendment) (No. 3) Bill, 1931, now before the House.</P>
      <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
      <P>Section 3, as amended, agreed to.</P>
      <P>Title agreed to.</P>
      <P>Bill ordered to be reported with amendments.</P>
      <P>The Seanad went out of Committee.</P>
      <P>Report Stage ordered for Wednesday, 16th December.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Public Charitable Hospitals (Amendment)" RHead="(No. 3) Bill, 1931&mdash;Third Stage">
    <Title>Public Charitable Hospitals (Amendment) (No. 3) Bill, 1931&mdash;Third Stage.</Title>
    <P>
      <Col N="160" /> Bill passed through Committee without amendment.</P>
    <P>Report Stage ordered for Wednesday, 16th December.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Report of Joint Committee on" RHead="Private Bill Standing Orders">
    <Title>Report of Joint Committee on Private Bill Standing Orders.</Title>
    <P>Ordered to lie on the Table and to be printed.&mdash;(Senator Brown.)</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Order of" RHead="Business">
    <Title>Order of Business.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Cathaoirleach Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I should like to inform the Seanad that the probable course of business for Wednesday next will be further stages of the</P>
      <P>Housing (Gaeltacht) (Amendment) Bill, 1931.</P>
      <P>Public Charitable Hospitals (No. 2) Bill, 1931.</P>
      <P>Public Charitable Hospitals (Amendment) (No. 3) Bill, 1931.</P>
      <P>Defence Forces (Temporary Provisions) Bill, 1931: Second Stage.</P>
      <P>Railways (Valuation for Rating) Bill, 1931: Second Stage.</P>
      <P>Merchandise Marks Bill, 1931: Committee.</P>
      <P>Mines and Minerals Bill, 1931&mdash;Report.</P>
      <P>The Report Stage of the Housing (Miscellaneous Provisions) Bill will be the first business by agreement.</P>
      <P>In addition to the above, Senator Sir John Keane has given notice of the following motion to be moved on Wednesday next:</P>
      <P>That having regard to the Report and Accounts of the Electricity Supply Board, for the year ended 31st March, 1930, which was laid on the Table of this House on 9th December, 1931, the Seanad invites from the Minister for Industry and Commerce further information and explanation on the policy and prospects of national electrification.</P>
      <P>The Seanad adjourned at 1.45 p.m., to Wednesday, 16th December, at 3 p.m.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
</Debate>