<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE Debate SYSTEM "../Debate.dtd"[]>
<Debate DocTitle="Seanad Debate" Day="Wed" Date="1" Month="Mar" Year="1950" Vol="37" No="8" DateIrish="Dé Céadaoin, 1 Márta 1950" DateEnglish="Wednesday, 1 March 1950" House="S" CommitteeEng="" CommitteeIr="" SubNameEng="" cnum="553">
  <MainHeading Type="Prelude" LHead="" RHead="">
    <Title>
    </Title>
    <P>
      <Col N="553" /> Do chuaigh an Cathaoirleach i gceannas ar 3 p.m.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Deaths of Senators" RHead="Brennan and Campbell">
    <Title>Deaths of Senators Brennan and Campbell.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="TimothyJosephODonova" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>It is my painful duty to-day to bring to the notice of the Seanad the deaths within the Recess of two of our members.</P>
      <P>Both these members contributed much to the prestige of the Seanad and their passing away will be felt with deep regret by all their colleagues.</P>
      <P>They had both identified themselves with the building up of national institutions and have made their mark on public life.</P>
      <P>Senator Brennan, whose death was the earlier, was first elected at the September, 1938, Seanad General Election and sat until 1944.  He was re-elected at the April, 1948, Election.</P>
      <P>Senator Brennan was deeply interested in the work of the Seanad and was in constant attendance until, in recent months, his health deteriorated. He was a prominent figure in the commercial life of the country and was especially noted for his generous support of all cultural and artistic movements.</P>
      <P>Senator Campbell was elected to the Seanad in September, 1938; was nominated to the Seanad at the General Elections of the Seanad of 1943 and 1944, and in the General Election of 1948 he was again elected.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Senator Campbell entered wholeheartedly into all movements, whether national, social or philantropic, giving of his best and unsparingly.  At an early age he became a member of the Irish Volunteers.  He was associated with the Sinn Féin movement from its foundation.  His work for trade unionism, industrial development, social services and as a member of various commissions cannot be <Col N="554" /> chronicled in this brief statement. Every Senator is familiar with them. To the last, in spite of failing health and his almost complete loss of sight, he continued to take his place in the Seanad.</P>
    <P>To the widow and relatives of both these men, I shall convey, with your assent, your sympathy and appreciation. Solas Dé dá n-anam.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Messages from" RHead="the Dáil">
    <Title>Messages from the Dáil.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="TimothyJosephODonova" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>&mdash;</P>
      <P>Dáil Éireann has agreed to the amendments made by Seanad Éireann to the Irish News Agency Bill, 1949.</P>
      <P>Dáil Éireann has passed the Industrial and Commercial Property (Protection) (Amendment) Bill, 1949, without amendment.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Order of" RHead="Business">
    <Title>Order of Business.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Mr. M. Hayes Mr. M. Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Mr. M. Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>It is proposed to take business in the following order: Nos. 2 and 3 will be taken.  It is proposed not to take No. 4, to take No. 5, not to take No. 6, to take Nos. 7 and 8 and not to take No. 9.  The Minister for Agriculture will be available at 7 o'clock for motions Nos. 10 and 11 as they may be taken.  If there is time before 6 o'clock the Parliamentary Secretary to the Minister for Industry and Commerce will be in attendance and it might be possible to open the discussion on No. 12.  It will probably be necessary to sit to-morrow to conclude the debate on the motions.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Local Government Provisional Orders" RHead="Confirmation Bill, 1950&mdash;First Stage">
    <Title>Local Government Provisional Orders Confirmation Bill, 1950&mdash;First Stage.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>In accordance with Standing Order 117 of the Standing Orders of the Dáil and the Seanad relative to Private Business which places on the Leas-Chathaoirleach the duty of moving the various stages of a Provisional Order Confirmation Bill in the Seanad, I beg to move for leave to introduce the Local Government Provisional Orders Confirmation Bill, 1950.</P>
      <P>Leave granted.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>With regard to the Second Stage, I move in accordance <Col N="555" /> with Standing Order 64 of the Standing Orders of the Dáil and Seanad relative to Private Business that the Second Stage be taken this day fortnight or if the Seanad be not sitting on that day on the next following sitting day of the Seanad.</P>
      <P>Ordered accordingly.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Vacancy in" RHead="Seanad&mdash;Motion">
    <Title>Vacancy in Seanad&mdash;Motion.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOFarrell" hpid="Mr. J.T. O'Farrell Mr. J.T. O'Farrell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J.T. O'Farrell</NameTxt>
      <P>I move:&mdash;</P>
      <P>That the Clerk of the Seanad do send to the Minister for Local Government notice of a vacancy in the membership of Seanad Éireann occasioned by the resignation of Mr. Luke Joseph Duffy, a member elected to the Oireachtas Sub-Panel of the Industrial and Commercial Panel at the General Election for Seanad Éireann, April, 1948.</P>
      <P>This motion indicates the procedure by which an occasional vacancy shall be filled in the Parliamentary panel.</P>
      <P>Motion agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Customs (Temporary Provisions) Act, 1945 (Continuance)" RHead="Bill, 1950&mdash;Second and Subsequent Stages">
    <Title>Customs (Temporary Provisions) Act, 1945 (Continuance) Bill, 1950&mdash;Second and Subsequent Stages.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Mr. M. Hayes Mr. M. Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Mr. M. Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>I move that the Bill be now read a Second Time.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Minister for Finance (Mr. McGilligan) Patrick McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Finance (Mr. McGilligan)</NameTxt>
      <P>This is a Bill to provide for the continuance for five years of the Customs (Temporary Provisions) Act, 1945.  This Act took effect from the date of its passing, 24th April, 1945, but under Section 14 the Act was to continue to the 31st March, 1950, and shall then expire, so unless this continuing piece of legislation is accepted the Act of 1945 will lapse on 31st March of this year.  The Act of 1945 was passed to meet certain difficulties which had previously been found in the customs code in regard to goods which it was prohibited to export and of which illegal exports were taking place.  Many years before 1945 there was a series of Customs Acts and a consolidated Act dealing with the illegal importation of goods where import was prohibited.  It also dealt with goods that were restricted <Col N="556" /> in their importation by means of tariff or otherwise, but there was no code in existence with regard to export restrictions.  The Customs Consolidation Act of 1876 was brought into force with a few provisions regarding exports and the prohibition of the export of goods.  Export prohibitions came into operation from time to time and an attempt was made by patchwork legislation and later by Orders to amend the old time law to meet new requirements. The adaptations were very limited in scope.  Eventually the Scrap Iron (Control of Export) Act, 1938, was passed which contained detailed provisions with regard to exports on the lines of the Customs (Consolidation) Act of 1876 and they were applied in the case of this Act.  A number of other prohibitions came later and eventually all these prohibitions were operating under Orders made after the Emergency Powers Act, 1939, had passed.  The Orders again proceeded in a sort of adaptation and you had the absurd situation, that in regard to the export of dairy produce such as butter, offenders were all prosecuted under Prohibitions of the Scrap Iron (Control of Export) Act.  You had a good deal of amusement when the cases came to the courts when the Scrap Iron (Control of Export) Act was referred to as being the basis for the prohibition of the export of dairy produce.  The machinery was obviously awkward and the powers under its scope were definitely inadequate for the purposes for which they were required.  The Act of 1945 was accordingly drafted to provide a permanent measure dealing with export prohibitions, or the irregular export of goods in the same way as previous Customs Acts had dealt with irregular importations.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>A considerable amount of disagreement with the measure was voiced when it was brought in, in 1945, and, at a late stage of the discussion on it, the Minister in charge decided to accept an amendment making the piece of legislation operate for only five years.  If the Act is allowed to lapse on 31st March this year, the Revenue Commissioners will have no administrative powers over the wide range of exports that still remain on the prohibited list. <Col N="557" /> Many of these articles are on that list because of shortages which it is hoped are temporary, but certain others are of a type for which permanent control will be necessary, dictated by either economic or some type of social necessity. Articles of agricultural produce are to a great extent prohibited at the moment and dangerous drugs also suffer a prohibition.  We regard the latter as being one of social necessity. The Act was passed at the end of April, 1945, and since its enactment, there have been 649 prosecutions under it. Nearly all of these have been successful. That particular statistic takes no account of the tens of thousands of seizures which have never gone near the courts.</P>
    <P>The whole situation with regard to the Border has become very demoralised and has deteriorated very badly since the days of export prohibitions and more particularly since the scarcities occasioned by the Emergency of 1939 arose.  Smuggling is quite a valuable business to engage in in present conditions and very definite rackets developed around the Border under the circumstances.  Gangs were organised, with their own scouts, and people hired garages for the temporary receiption of certain articles which it was intended to smuggle.  The counter to that on the revenue side had to be that corresponding groups of officers had to be associated in an effort to prevent the smuggling.  Notwithstanding the difficulties put in the way and notwithstanding the very serious disadvantage under which the Revenue authorities operated, I think it can be claimed that, in the main, the serious smuggling across the Border has been suppressed. There were two types of smuggling which were much more serious than any others&mdash;one, the smuggling across the frontier of gold and the other, the smuggling of motor cars.  These were very serious and threatened to become still more serious, but owing to the patient and persistent detective and investigation work done, I think it can be claimed that these have been suppressed.</P>
    <P>This is not the type of legislation which any lawyer finds it easy to accept, but I have been coerced by circumstances <Col N="558" /> put before me by the Revenue Commissioners to accept responsibility for this particular continuing legislation.  I am advised that, without the Act, the successful prosecutions could not have been achieved and the successful prosecutions, as well as the seizures, have been the means of bringing what might have been quite serious breaches of the law to an end. I am also advised that, without these powers, the administration of the Revenue Commissioners would be made so difficult as to render their task almost impossible and that a free field would be left to those who engage in the modern racket of smuggling.  On these grounds, I recommend the Bill to the Seanad.</P>
    <Speaker pid="FrederickHawkins" hpid="Mr. Hawkins Mr. Hawkins">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hawkins</NameTxt>
      <P>While we regret the circumstances surrounding the introduction of this Bill&mdash;circumstances brought about not by any Act of an Irish Parliament but by an Act of a foreign Parliament&mdash;and while we regret that we should have customs barriers as between one section of our people and the other, we feel that we must give to the authorities every power they deem necessary to enforce whatever regulations are drawn in connection with measures of this kind.  We are therefore prepared to give the Minister all stages of this Bill to-day.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDouglas" hpid="Mr. Douglas Mr. Douglas">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Douglas</NameTxt>
      <P>I have a fairly clear recollection of the debate in this House when the previous measure, which it is proposed to continue, was being debated.  It was passed without any vote against it, but with a certain amount of reluctance.  All sides were prepared to give what they regarded as adequate powers to deal with smuggling and accepted the views which have just been expressed by Senator Hawkins, but one difficulty stuck in the minds of a number of Senators, and frankly I regard it as one of the flaws in this legislation as a permanent measure, that is, it provides that in certain cases the onus of proof is placed on the individual charged, which means that that individual is presumed to be guilty rather than innocent.  I quite agree, and I do not think anyone can dispute, that it was necessary to have an Act of this kind and that <Col N="559" /> portions of it should be permanent, but I should like to know from the Minister whether he is perfectly satisfied that those portions of the Act which place the onus of proof upon the individual are still regarded as an essential part and, if so, if it is really a good or a wise thing.</P>
      <P>I did not give the Minister notice of the question I am now about to ask and he may possibly be unable to answer it, but when the Bill was before the House, the then Minister for Finance, Mr. Ó Ceallaigh, in reply to, I think, Senator Sir John Keane who said that this principle had never been found in British legislation, said, in effect, that, in 1939, a British temporary Act was introduced which contained certain similar provisions but which also contained the objectionable provision that the onus of proof should be placed upon the individual, and I should very much like to know whether that 1939 Act, which was temporary in Britain, has become permanent and is being continued at present.</P>
      <P>I have no evidence and none has been brought to my notice to suggest that this Act has been used in any unfair way to harass people, as could easily be done, and I make no charge whatever of that nature, but I was rather amused on looking up the previous debate to find that, when I asked the then Minister for Finance how a shopkeeper could possibly know whether, when someone came into his shop and bought an article, that person intended to export it, the Minister said it ran through his mind that possibly if the person had a northern accent it might be suspicious.  I have an idea that the present Minister will not agree with his predecessor in that, though he appears to agree with him in the main.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I do not think there is anything to do but to allow this to become law, but I ask the Minister seriously to consider whether it is necessary to continue it for another five-year period, whether certain portions of it should not be regarded definitely as temporary and whether it would not have been better to have fixed on two years. I also found in the debate on the previous Bill that Senator Baxter, having <Col N="560" /> been assured by the then Minister that it was temporary, said he could not believe it would be for only five years.</P>
    <Speaker pid="LiamOBuachalla" hpid="Liam Ó Buachalla Liam Ó Buachalla">
      <NameTxt>Liam Ó Buachalla</NameTxt>
      <P>Ní dóigh liom gur gá don Aire aon leithscéal a glacadh leis an Seanad mar gheall ar an mBille a thabhairt isteach.  Is dóigh liom, is cuma cé acu a bheas ganntann ann sna blianta atá le theacht nó nach mbeidh, go mbeidh gá le cuid mhaith de na cumhachtaí atá sa mBille a bheith ann go seasmhach. Ní thaithníonn linn dlí a dhéanamh chor a bith.  Chomh luath agus smaoinimid ar dhlí a dhéanamh, tagann ar intinn againn go bhfuil muid le cur isteach ar dhuine éigin nó le cur as do dhuine éigin.  Is dóigh liom go mbeidh i gcónaí earraí áirithe ann a mba mhian linn nach gcuirfí as an tír iad, nó nach gcuirfí as an tír iad gan údarás speisialta.  Dá n-abródh an tAire go raibh faoi Acht buan a dhéanamh den Acht seo, ní chuirfeadh sé isteach ná amach orm agus déarfainn nach mbeadh aon locht agam air.</P>
      <P>Taithníonn liom an méid adúirt an tAire mar gheall ar an laghdú atá tagaithe ar chuid den gnó mídhlisteanach a bhí ar bun.  Ba mhaith liom a fháil amach uaidh, más féidir leis a innseacht dúinn, a bhfuil an laghdú ar an ngnó mídhlisteanach tagaithe mar gheall ar go bhfuil an gá a bhí leis an gnó mídhlisteanach san imithe uilig, cuid mhaith nó mar gheall ar go bhfuil na fórsaí atá ag cosaint na Tórann éirithe i bhfad níos éifeachtaí ná mar bhí.  B'fhéidir gurb é an chaoi nach bhfuil an oiread gá le trádáil mídhlisteanach is bhí, agus ag an am chéanna go bhfuil na fórsaí atá i bhfeighil cúrsaí custaim ar an Tórainn éirithe i bhfad níos cliste agus níos éifeachtaí ar an obair.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Dúirt an tAire gur tugadh suas le 650 cásanna os comhair na cúirte faoin Acht agus ba mhaith liom go bhféadfadh an tAire a innseacht dúinn céard a tharla sna cásanna seo.  Ar cuireadh príosúntacht ar na daoine nó príosúntacht agus fíneáil nó fíneáil amháin?  Ba mhaith liom go mbeadh tuairim agam ar cén chaoi a raibh an breithiúnas ar na cásanna roinnte. Rinne an tAire tagairt do na mílte &ldquo;seizures&rdquo; ach níor thug sé na <Col N="561" /> figiúirí dúinn, beag ná mór.  Bhfuil aon tuairm ag an Aire ar cé mhéid ab fhiú na hearraí a gabhadh faoin Acht?  Rud atá ar intinn agam, ba mhaith liom sórt léargas a bheith agam ar cé mhéid a chosain scéal seo na Tórann ar feadh réim an Achta.  Ba mhaith liom freisin&mdash;ní dóigh liom go mbeadh sé as bealach ar an mBille seo&mdash;a iarraidh ar an Aire a innseacht cén costas atá ar an Stát ó bhliain go bliain maidir leis na Seirbhísigh Chustaim fré chéile.  B'fhiú go mbeadh a fhios againn faoi sin.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Micheál Ó hAodha Micheál Ó hAodha">
      <NameTxt>Micheál Ó hAodha</NameTxt>
      <P>Ar an Tórainn?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LiamOBuachalla" hpid="Liam Ó Buachalla Liam Ó Buachalla">
      <NameTxt>Liam Ó Buachalla</NameTxt>
      <P>Ar an Tórainn amháin.  Bheadh sé oiriúnach ar an ócáid seo go bhfaigheadh muid léargas ar an méad costais atá an Tórainn a tharraingt.  Dúirt mo chara, an Seanadóir Ó hEachain go bhfuil an trioblóid seo ar fad ag teacht ar aghaidh mar gheall ar an Tórainn.  Is dóigh liom gur fíor é sin, ach níl aon neart air go fóill.  Ba mhaith liom go mbeadh a fhios ag an tír céard é an costas a bhaineas leis an Tórainn, idir príosúntacht, fíneála agus earraí, maraon le postanna do sheirbhísigh.</P>
      <P>Ní thaithníonn liom de ghnáth go mbeadh Bille os ár gcomhair a bheadh ag cur as do dhaoine eicínt.  Taithníonn liom an tuairim a nochtaigh an tAire, go bhfuil an gá atá leis an mBille imithe go mór i laghad.  Tá súil agam nach mbeidh gá leis chomh fada agus bhaineas sé leis an Tórainn agus ní miste liom go mbeadh an lá againn nuair nach mbeadh sé i bhfeidhm go seasta.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DenisBurke" hpid="Mr. D. Burke Mr. D. Burke">
      <NameTxt>Mr. D. Burke</NameTxt>
      <P>It has been brought to my attention that recently certain changes have been made in regulations particularly governing the import of machinery spare parts.  This was brought to my attention in the case of a firm requiring refrigerating spare parts for industrial type refrigerators. Heretofore, for a period of 25 years, these parts were imported free of duty. All that was required was that the customs forms should be sent to the port of entry and the goods would be passed through free of duty.  A new regulation has been made whereby it is necessary for a person to know what <Col N="562" /> part of the machinery is going to go wrong before it goes wrong, so that they may apply to the Revenue Commissioners for permission to import the spare parts free of duty.  Nothing so Gilbertian could possibly be envisaged by any person engaged in business.  I would like to ask the Minister for Finance to have that objection dealt with.</P>
      <P>I feel that when these rules and regulations are being framed they ought not be framed by some ingenious official as a sort of obstacle race for business people.  It does certainly appear to people engaged in business that the regulations are often made for no other apparent reason.  If it has been found desirable in a period of 25 years to allow into Ireland free of duty things that are not manufactured here and that there is no intention to manufacture here, it should be feasible to continue to allow them in in future.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>There is nothing about import in this.  It deals with export only.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DenisBurke" hpid="Mr. D. Burke Mr. D. Burke">
      <NameTxt>Mr. D. Burke</NameTxt>
      <P>I am sorry if I was not in order.  I was asked to mention about the export of cigarettes and to ask if the Minister could tighten the machinery adopted.  There are many complaints along the Border about this practice, and the people along this side of the Border find it difficult to procure cigarettes.  I was informed that this Bill dealt with imports and exports, so I apologise to the House for taking up the time of public business on the other matter.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator Douglas has put his finger on the matter to which most legal folk take exception, that is, the shifting of the onus where a person is charged with an offence. The shifting of onus is not so serious in this case as one would imagine from hearing that phrase from Senator Douglas.  Section 3 of the 1945 Act sets out seven different matters that constitute an offence.  It is really the same thing looked at <i>vis-a-vis</i> the different steps that would have to be taken to secure the desired result.  The first is that the person exports the goods in contravention of any enactment, the <Col N="563" /> second is any person who attempts to export, the third is anyone who brings or sends goods to any place for export, the fourth is ancillary, attempting to bring, the fifth is knowingly being concerned in dealing with goods the exportation of which is prohibited or restricted.  The second last is keeping goods at any place for the purpose of facilitating their exportation in contravention of any regulation or enactment. The last is the usual ancillary to any statute setting up an offence and includes aiding, abetting or assisting anyone to do these things.</P>
      <P>In respect of these things, there is certainly an onus shifted on to the accused person.  Take the first one&mdash;any person who exports.  If a person is charged with the offence and it is proved in the proceedings that the goods are goods the exportation of which is prohibited or restricted by such enactment or statutory instrument, and that the goods were on or about the said date exported, the person shall, until the contrary is proved, be presumed to have exported them.  Only on those three things being proved&mdash;the export having been achieved and that that was contrary to the regulations and that the person had them in his custody within a reasonable time prior to exportation&mdash;he has the onus.  It says that such person shall, until the contrary is proved, be presumed to have exported the goods in contravention of the enactment.  That, I suggest, is about the most serious onus put on the accused person.</P>
      <P>Take the next one&mdash;a person attempting on or about a particular date to export.  Then the onus shifts, but only in the circumstances that it is proved in the proceedings that the goods are goods the exportation of which is prohibited or restricted and that the person on or about the said date attempted to export.  There the onus is only that it is assumed that he attempted to export in contravention of the statute.  That is not a very serious assumption, if you prove in the proceedings that the goods come within the restrictions and that he attempted to export them.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The others go down in much the same <Col N="564" /> way.  I do not say that the matters I have given are applicable to all the various sub-sections, but I submit that the most serious onus is the one in subsection (3) in relation to the offence of exporting.</P>
    <P>In the Customs Act dealing with imports, the onus is shifting in exactly the same way.  Senators will no doubt accept that there is a difference between illegal import and illegal export. In the case of illegal import, the goods are here and can be taken or seized here and if they are goods the importation of which is restricted or prohibited and if they are in somebody's possession, there is a clear case. In the case of export, unless some onus of this type here is put on the accused person it would be almost impossible to have the case proved.  As long as the goods are inside the State, one cannot do anything, as a man may be hovering around the Border for weeks and you cannot do anything on suspicion. In those circumstances, the advantage is with the smuggler.  It is said that time can mean business, but maybe time is his business and the customs cannot be expected to keep check on him every hour of the day.</P>
    <P>It has to be remembered that this is not the first time there has been a shifting of onus, even in our own law. Sometimes the onus shifts over to the accused person, more often to the defendant in a civil action.  It is well known in regard to the law that deals with adulteration of food, where there are circumstances that are peculiarly within the knowledge of the person charged with the offence.  In civil actions, the onus often shifts to the defendant, where there are eight or nine ways of justifying what he has done and he has to say on which of these ways he is making his claim to have acted properly where the State claims he acted improperly.</P>
    <P>This happens also in other cases.  It is an offence under the criminal law for a person to be found with house-breaking implements, or instruments which could be used for house-breaking, in what is known as statutory night time, unless he discharges the onus in proving he had these &ldquo;house-breaking implements&rdquo; for an innocent purpose. Even in the case of a person found with <Col N="565" /> his face blackened during statutory night time, there is an onus on him to explain why he was going about in that fashion and it is assumed that the disguise or blackening at that time was for some illegal purpose, until the contrary is established.</P>
    <P>It is not so unusual to shift the onus. It is not so very serious here although it is objectionable.  If Senators look up the piece of legislation, they will find that the particular onus established in each of these sub-sections is not a very serious onus for him to discharge. There is the further point which has been mentioned, that in dealing with illegal export the situation is different from that of illegal import, as the circumstances are entirely in favour of the smuggler.</P>
    <P>Senator Ó Buachalla asked about smuggling being on the decrease.  I am afraid I cannot say that that represents an accretion of virtue in our people: it only means that the field for smuggling has been somewhat narrowed by the fact that certain restrictions have been removed and there is not so much chance now of breaking the law.  In addition, there is a stringent watch and the more efficient working which was made possible by this Act has made more difficult the task of many people who would like to smuggle and still have an opportunity; and to that extent we have brought it under control.</P>
    <P>In regard to the usual result of prosecution, I would say, speaking very generally, that it is a fine and sometimes imprisonment.  In cases where there are fines or imprisonment, there is nearly always an immediate appeal to the authorities who have a right of remission of penalties on the ground that the person was not acting for his own benefit but that his conduct was useful in the national interest.  For instance, a man who smuggled in motor car tyres at a time when there was great need for them claimed that he was doing good for the country.</P>
    <P>Regarding the cost of the customs service on the border, that is beyond my calculations at the moment.</P>
    <Speaker pid="LiamOBuachalla" hpid="Liam Ó Buachalla Liam Ó Buachalla">
      <NameTxt>Liam Ó Buachalla</NameTxt>
      <P>Even an approximation?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="566" />
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>I could get an approximation.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LiamOBuachalla" hpid="Liam Ó Buachalla Liam Ó Buachalla">
      <NameTxt>Liam Ó Buachalla</NameTxt>
      <P>The value of the goods seized?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>Is the Senator speaking of imports?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LiamOBuachalla" hpid="Liam Ó Buachalla Liam Ó Buachalla">
      <NameTxt>Liam Ó Buachalla</NameTxt>
      <P>No, exports; we are not dealing with imports.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>I am sure the statistics could be got approximately, but I could not give them at the moment. The serious ones were motor cars and gold.  I could get some general statement of value of articles under those two headings and then some miscellaneous group.  If the Senator thinks that would be of any advantage, I can have it calculated for him.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LiamOBuachalla" hpid="Liam Ó Buachalla Liam Ó Buachalla">
      <NameTxt>Liam Ó Buachalla</NameTxt>
      <P>In view of the question of the cost of the Border, such a figure would be of certain value.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>I would not like these two things brought too much into association.  Even though it might be a very expensive matter and far out of any ordinary relationship with the goods that were passing either way, a customs service would have to be maintained along the Border.  Otherwise there would be open trading and free trading between this and every country that would have access to the harbour of Belfast or any cross-Channel place.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>As far as cigarettes are concerned, attempts are being made to have that tightened up.  The chief reliance there has to be on the manufacturers of cigarettes here and I do know that they have a pretty good system whereby they pay special attention to complaints that come from those customers who rely upon traders in areas where there might be a temptation to send cigarettes across the Border.  I do know that the manufacturers call for statements on any occasion on which a complaint is made by any customer in any of the towns along the Border where it is thought that the deprivation of the home customer is due to the fact that the shopkeeper has sent cigarettes <Col N="567" /> across the Border.  In addition, the customs officers keep their usual watch.</P>
    <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
    <P>Agreed to take remaining stages to-day.</P>
    <P>Bill put through Committee and reported without amendment, received for final consideration and passed.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Order of" RHead="Business">
    <Title>Order of Business.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Mr. M. Hayes Mr. M. Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Mr. M. Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>Before we take No. 3, might I announce, with the agreement of the House, a change in the Order of Business?  The Minister for Finance is here.  It is not anticipated that No. 3 will take very long.  We intend to take No. 5, with the Parliamentary Secretary to the Minister for Industry and Commerce.  As the Minister for Finance is here, he is willing to take the discussion on No. 14, the motion in regard to the review of semi-State companies, in the names of Senators Orpen and George O'Brien.  If the House is willing, we would be prepared to take Nos. 3 and 5 and then go into discussion until 6 o'clock on No. 14.</P>
      <P>Agreed.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Irish Whiskey Bill," RHead="1950&mdash;Second Stage">
    <Title>Irish Whiskey Bill, 1950&mdash;Second Stage.</Title>
    <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That the Bill be now read a Second Time.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>The purpose of this Bill is quite simple and clear.  The method of arriving at the objective may seem a little bit roundabout.  The distillers had represented for some years back that a definition of Irish whiskey is required in order to safeguard the name of Irish whiskey at home and abroad.  Speaking in Dáil Éireann on the Financial Resolutions last year I indicated an intention to include a definition of Irish whiskey in the Finance Bill of 1949.  It was, however, then pointed out to me that by including any such definition I might bring about a result that certainly was not intended, that I would find my Finance Bill of last year was not a Money Bill, and that the Seanad would have more power over it than they were entitled to.  I decided then to <Col N="568" /> segregate this morsel and to leave this in itself to the Seanad for whatever it liked to do on it.</P>
      <P>The piece of legislation is contained in one clause.  It says that, for the purpose of a particular section of Section 105 of the Spirits Act, 1880, two things are to happen: that spirits described as Irish whiskey are not to be deemed to correspond to that description unless they have been obtained by distillation in the State from a mash of malt and cereals; and that spirits described as Irish pot-still whiskey shall not be deemed to correspond to that description unless they have been obtained by distillation solely in pot-stills in the State from a mash of cereal grains such as are ordinarily grown in the State, etc.  The effect of these two sub-sections is that if and when a permit or certificate having a description of spirits is sought, whatever may be the other requirements called for, these additional requirements are now imposed.  No certificate or permit can contain a description of spirits described as Irish whiskey unless it is clear that they have gone through either of these two processes. The Spirits Act of 1880 has a subsection&mdash;(9)&mdash;of Section 105, as follows:&mdash;</P>
      <P>&ldquo;If any question arises as to the accuracy of the description of spirits in a permit or certificate, the proof that the spirits correspond to the description shall lie on the owner or claimant of the spirits, who shall prove the same by the oaths of two credible witnesses, being skilful and experienced persons competent to decide by examination thereof.&rdquo;</P>
      <P>On that are imposed these extra requirements that spirits are not to be described as Irish whiskey unless they have been obtained by distillation in a particular way or, as Irish pot-still whiskey, unless they have been obtained by distillation in another way.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The permit or certificate that was given has nothing to do with export. Yet this description is required, according to the distillers, for the purpose of safeguarding Irish whiskey abroad. The way it will work is this: On the transfer of whiskey inside the State <Col N="569" /> from, say, one bonded place to another, a permit or certificate may be looked for.  Under the new conditions, that permit or certificate with the description of Irish whiskey will not be given unless it corresponds with what is in this new piece of legislation but, once the certificate is given hereafter, when that whiskey comes to be exported the people who get the whiskey on the export market will know that in its passage inside this country it has had to pass that test and that it has been so described and, therefore, that it has been obtained by distillation in either of these two ways.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelColgan" hpid="Mr. Colgan Mr. Colgan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Colgan</NameTxt>
      <P>Will that be borne out by the taste or some guarantee?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>That is a technical matter that I would not like to be too accurate upon.  We have been told by the whiskey distillers that this meets their requirements.  They fortify us in their contention by pointing out that years ago the Scotch distillers wanted Scotch whiskey defined and got a provision in an English Act corresponding to this, the necessary changes having been made.  We have consulted the Department of Industry and Commerce, who agree that this is all right and, finally, in the last resort, we did consult Ceimicí Teoranta, who agree that it will even pass their scrutiny.</P>
      <P>Apparently, we have all the technical people on our side in this matter.  I am not technical.  I do not know.  I put it forward on their advice.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrederickHawkins" hpid="Mr. Hawkins Mr. Hawkins">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hawkins</NameTxt>
      <P>One might sympathise with the Minister in bringing forward a Bill of this kind because some of us at least might feel that, in order to give a certificate of Irish whiskey to satisfy Senator Colgan, one would require a taste for it.  There are one or two points that I would like to ask the Minister to clarify.  Spirits described as Irish whiskey shall not be deemed to correspond to that description unless they have been obtained by distillation in the State from a mash of malt and cereals.  Is there any qualification as to what the mash of malt and cereals is to be?  We are all anxious, of course, that Irish whiskey, or any Irish product, particularly if it <Col N="570" /> is to be sold abroad, should be the genuine article.</P>
      <P>There is another point to which I should like to direct the Minister's attention. A system has grown up in this country of blending whiskies.  Have the authorities power to control the blending of whiskey at the present time?  I have been told that it is possible for blenders to purchase whiskey three years old and seven years old and to blend it and sell it as ten-year-old whiskey.  When we are taking measures to safeguard the export market, we should also take measures to safeguard the home market.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Captain Orpen Captain Orpen">
      <NameTxt>Captain Orpen</NameTxt>
      <P>I should like to ask the Minister, with reference to this short Bill, what is the real meaning in the definition of Irish pot-still whiskey where it says &ldquo;distillation solely in pot-stills in the State from a mash of cereal grains such as are ordinarily grown in the State&rdquo;.  It seems to me that in putting in that section there is, for some reason or other, an attempt to avoid saying what shall be put in or to define it specifically.  What grains are ordinarily grown in this State?  Can we claim that you might make a pot-still whiskey from corn? Can we say you can make it from rye? There is a small quantity of rye normally grown in this State.  Of course, most Irish whiskey contains a small percentage of rye but it is not a rye whiskey.  Would not it be safer and more advisable to state what is ordinarily grown in the State?</P>
      <P>This seems to be a rather roundabout way.  Reading between the lines, I conclude that it is to preclude a whiskey made from potatoes.  It says &ldquo;cereal grains&rdquo; but the phrase &ldquo;ordinarily grown in the State&rdquo; seems to me rather vague and it certainly, in my opinion, might allow one to produce a rye whiskey.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeamusOFarrell" hpid="Mr. S. O'Farrell Mr. S. O'Farrell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. S. O'Farrell</NameTxt>
      <P>In this we are amending an Act of 1880, that is, we are amending legislation passed 70 years ago and not passed by this Parliament. Is there anything in that Act of 1880 that imposed a penalty for a wrongful description, for a misdescription, for passing off something that is <Col N="571" /> not Irish whiskey as Irish whiskey? If there is no penalty for wrongful description, the mere tightening up of a definition of what is Irish whiskey will be of little use.  We cannot enforce it in America, where we are expecting to export whiskey.  Is there any way in which we can insist that nothing will be described in America as Irish whiskey except something that complies with this Bill?</P>
      <P>I know very little about whiskey.  I only get it when I have pneumonia and that, fortunately, is seldom.  We are defining Irish whiskey.  We are defining it in order that we may issue a certificate.  That does not prevent something that would not comply with this Bill being sold as Irish whiskey without being labelled as Irish whiskey, being substituted for Irish whiskey or just being sold as whiskey.  In an American paper recently I saw an advertisement. &ldquo;Irish Type Whiskey&rdquo; advertised for sale and the word &ldquo;type&rdquo; was in very small type.  If there is to be Irish whiskey which must comply with the definition I should like to ensure that anything which does not comply with that can be dealt with either here or in the export market.  I suppose that we can rely on our representatives abroad, if anything is put on the market which does not comply, that it will be immediately announced and denounced.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOFarrell" hpid="Mr. J.T. O'Farrell Mr. J.T. O'Farrell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J.T. O'Farrell</NameTxt>
      <P>I was only going to ask the Minister if there was any possibility that &ldquo;poitín&rdquo; whiskey would come within the definition in the Bill.  It is a very ancient Irish industry, as Irish as the ceanabhán, so is there any possibility that it could be claimed for export purposes to comply with the provisions in the Bill?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LiamOBuachalla" hpid="Liam Ó Buachalla Liam Ó Buachalla">
      <NameTxt>Liam Ó Buachalla</NameTxt>
      <P>Níl fúm cur síos ar scéal an uisce beatha ó thaobh na teicniciúlachta, ar phoitín, pot-still, patent nó rud ar bith eile, ach theastuigh uaim ceist nó dhó a chur ar an Aire mar gheall ar na sain-mhínithe atá anseo.  Faoín gcéad sain-mhíniú an bhféadfaí uisce beatha déanta de sheagal a dhéanamh i nÉirinn agus a dhíol mar uisce beatha Éireannach? <Col N="572" /> An bhféadfaí uisce beatha a dhéanamh ar an nós Albanach&mdash;is dóigh liom go dtugann daoine go coitianta &ldquo;patent whiskey&rdquo; air&mdash;agus a dhíol faoin téarma &ldquo;uisce beatha Éireannach?&rdquo; Mar adúirt an Seanadóir Ó Fearghail, an bhféadfaí poitín a dhéanamh agus a dhathú mar a dathuightear an t-uisce beatha eile agus a dhíol mar uisce beatha?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelColgan" hpid="Micheál Ó Colgáin Micheál Ó Colgáin">
      <NameTxt>Micheál Ó Colgáin</NameTxt>
      <P>Nach uisce beatha é?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LiamOBuachalla" hpid="Liam Ó Buachalla Liam Ó Buachalla">
      <NameTxt>Liam Ó Buachalla</NameTxt>
      <P>Seadh, is uisce beatha é cinnte, ach amháin nach ndéantar é faoi údarás.  Sin é an difir mór.  Ach dá bhfaigheadh daoine cead poitín a dhéanamh faoi údarás, an bhféadfaí é a dhíol mar uisce beatha Éireannach?  Más féidir, ba cheart an Bille a leasú agus iallach a chur ar dhaoine tuairisc chruinn a thabhairt ar an uisce beatha; más seagal an príomh-ábhar as a ndéantar é ba cheart go dtiúrfaí &ldquo;uisce beatha seagail Éireannach&rdquo; air.  Más &ldquo;patent whiskey&rdquo; é ba cheart go n-abrófaí &ldquo;Irish patent whiskey.&rdquo;</P>
      <P>Taobh amuigh dhe sin ba mhaíth liom go n-inseodh an tAire dúinn an bhfuil aon uisce beatha ar an margadh faoi láthair dhá dhíol mar uisce beatha Éireannach nach bhfuil do réir an sain-mhínithe i mír <i>(a).</i></P>
      <P>An dara ceist ba mhaith liom a chur ar an Aire; an eol dó go bhfuil aon deacracht ar an margadh taobh amuigh den tír do na déantóirí Éireannacha mar gheall ar thuairisc mhícheart a thabhairt ar uisce beatha?  An bhfuil uisce beatha dhá dhéanamh i dtíortha eile agus dá mheascadh beagán le huisce beatha Éireannach agus dhá dhíol mar uisce beatha ó Éirinn?  Má tá sé sin amhlaidh an eol dó aon slí nó seift a bhféadfaí teacht suas ar na daoine atá dhá dhéanamh agus an scéal a chur i gceart?</P>
      <P>Is léir go bhfuil riachtanas leis an sain-mhíniú.  Bhí an cheist ós ár gcómhair roimhe seo.  Is cuimhin liom an iar-Aire Tionscail agus Tráchtála ag cur na ceiste ceanann céanna os ár gcomhair sa Teach seo agus dúirt sé go rabh gá le sain-mhíniú don uisce beatha Éireannach le fada, go raibh tábhacht leis ó thaobh na trádála, go mór mhór i dtíortha coigríocha.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="573" />
    <Speaker pid="WilliamFearon" hpid="Professor Fearon Professor Fearon">
      <NameTxt>Professor Fearon</NameTxt>
      <P>Two points which are not too technical are puzzling me; why do the paragraphs differ so much? In paragraph (b) pot-still whiskey is described as being obtained by a distillation solely in pot still in the State from a mash of cereal grains such as are ordinarily grown in the State. That, I presume, is designed to exclude such other starchy sources as were referred to by Senator Orpen. Paragraph (a) is much shorter and I wonder does it give a loophole to a distiller who wishes to include some other source of sugar in the distillation. It would be necessary to say &ldquo;obtained by distillation in the State exclusively from a mash of malt and cereals.&rdquo;  The fact of having cereals knocks out other things although it does not prevent the use of cereals which are imported.  Why is it omitted in the first section and made more explicit in the second?  We should insert the word &ldquo;exclusively&rdquo; before &ldquo;a mash of malt and cereals.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator Séamus O'Farrell raised the point of penalties. There are any number of penalties under the Act of 1880.  It provides for a penalty of £500 where &ldquo;any person sends out, delivers, removes or receives any spirits...differing in...denomination...or strength from that expressed in the permit.&rdquo;  There is a penalty of £500 where &ldquo;any person who, having obtained a permit does not send out the spirits....&rdquo;  There is £500 penalty for a person who &ldquo;uses a permit for any purpose other than that of accompanying the removal and delivery of spirits therein described&rdquo;. In another section of the 1880 Act there are further penalties where &ldquo;any rectifier, dealer or retailer sends out, delivers or receives any spirits accompanied by an inaccurate certificate&rdquo;. I thought for one moment that the Senator had as his real quarry the publican who sells across the counter something which is not of the nature described.  That is not a matter for the 1880 Act but for the Food and Drugs Act.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeamusOFarrell" hpid="Mr. S. O'Farrell Mr. S. O'Farrell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. S. O'Farrell</NameTxt>
      <P>Not the scrap iron Act?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>No.  It makes it an <Col N="574" /> offence if a customer does not receive an article of the nature, quality or substance of the type requested by him.  According to the Act of 1879 &ldquo;in the case of a complaint regarding the quality of whiskey, a vendor shall be regarded as having met this obligation if it is established that the spirits sold were not of lesser strength than 25 degrees under proof.&rdquo;  It would probably be very hard to get a prosecution brought under the Food and Drugs Act where the complaint was that a person had asked for Irish whiskey and had not got Irish whiskey.</P>
      <P>I do not know whether some Senator raised a point regarding young whiskey being sent out of the country.  There is a special Act, the Immature Spirits (Restriction) Act, 1947, which prescribes the age for home consumption, but no restriction exists as regards exports.</P>
      <P>Regarding these two definitions, I answer questions put on them with a good deal of diffidence.  If I take paragraph (b) of Section 1 as first proposed, it confines the matter in this way: whiskey may only be described as Irish pot-still whiskey if the spirits are obtained by distillation solely in potstills in the State, and if they are from a mash of cereal grains such as are ordinarily grown in the State.  Those grains, as Senators know, are barley, wheat, rye and oats, and they are required to be fermented in a particular way.  As far as the definition of Irish whiskey itself is concerned, it is simpler than the definition of Irish pot-still whiskey because it is not intended to be so restrictive.  The main point in the first paragraph is that the spirits must be obtained by distillation in the State.  So far as the cereals are concerned, they may be imported cereals. The phrase in section (b) is left out and the section is not restricted to spirits obtained from a mash of malt and cereals grown inside the State.  I am advised that Irish whiskey could be a blend of Irish pot-still and Irish patent whiskey, but it could not be a blend of Irish pot-still and English or Scotch patent whiskey.  The blend is permissible only under the description of Irish whiskey and whatever is blended must correspond to the definition in section (a) &ldquo;distillation in the State&rdquo;.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="575" />
    <Speaker pid="LiamOBuachalla" hpid="Liam Ó Buachalla Liam Ó Buachalla">
      <NameTxt>Liam Ó Buachalla</NameTxt>
      <P>What about rye whiskey?  It could be produced here also.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>If the spirit could be produced from rye whiskey by distillation in the State it could pass as Irish pot-still whiskey.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LiamOBuachalla" hpid="Liam Ó Buachalla Liam Ó Buachalla">
      <NameTxt>Liam Ó Buachalla</NameTxt>
      <P>But if the grains are grown outside the State, could it be sold as Irish?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes, if it is distilled in the State.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LiamOBuachalla" hpid="Liam Ó Buachalla Liam Ó Buachalla">
      <NameTxt>Liam Ó Buachalla</NameTxt>
      <P>Would it not be a better phrase to have it described as Irish rye whiskey?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDouglas" hpid="Mr. Douglas Mr. Douglas">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Douglas</NameTxt>
      <P>Is rye whiskey a mash of malt and cereals?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>I am afraid I do not know what the Senator's brew is.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LiamOBuachalla" hpid="Liam Ó Buachalla Liam Ó Buachalla">
      <NameTxt>Liam Ó Buachalla</NameTxt>
      <P>There are whiskeys on the market some of which are described as Scotch and others described as rye, as there is a well-known Canadian rye whiskey.  I do not know, I am not an expert&mdash;but under the section as I see it, it will be possible to bring in rye here and make it to the formula of Canadian rye whiskey and sell it as Irish whiskey.  I was wondering if it could not have a better description, but I suppose if the distillers are satisfied with it, it is good enough, although it seems to me that it would be very much better if we faced the issue and described it as Irish rye whiskey, just as if whiskey is made after the Scottish formula, we would describe it as Scotch whiskey; or if it is patent whiskey, we would describe it as Irish patent whiskey and leave it at that.  It seems to me to be unsatisfactory that any whiskey may be described as Irish whiskey.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>These are all technical matters, which I am not prepared to go into at the moment.  What we have put in the Bill suits the distillers. It was at their request this measure was brought in.  They made the request many years ago, and I agreed that I would bring in a section in the Finance Bill corresponding to the views put before me.  If there are other points, we can easily leave it over and <Col N="576" /> have them looked into.  There is no doubt that what Senator Hawkins spoke of can happen.  The Scotch type may be made here and made from imported grains, but being made here of the patent type it will then properly pass under the description of Irish whiskey.  The distillers are content with that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LiamOBuachalla" hpid="Liam Ó Buachalla Liam Ó Buachalla">
      <NameTxt>Liam Ó Buachalla</NameTxt>
      <P>I think it could have serious consequences.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrederickHawkins" hpid="Mr. Hawkins Mr. Hawkins">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hawkins</NameTxt>
      <P>I should like to put a question.  When I referred to the blending of whiskey I referred to it as blending for home consumption, and I would like to have an assurance from the Minister that the suggestion I put forward was not possible&mdash;that is, that he can blend a three-year-old whiskey with a seven-year-old whiskey and sell it as ten-year-old whiskey.  I would like to be safeguarded against that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDouglas" hpid="Mr. Douglas Mr. Douglas">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Douglas</NameTxt>
      <P>I hope the Minister will adopt the suggestion that he should not force this too quickly.  I have been assured by a responsible distiller that this Bill is what they believe they want.  It does not always follow that what they think is a good draft is a good draft, and I would like to show them a report of this debate.</P>
      <P>I would like to have it read by some members of the trade so that they can study the points that have been made here.  It is only a matter of a couple of weeks.  If this measure were adjourned for a fortnight, we would have the report ready and I personally would like to show it to some members of the trade to see if there is anything in it from their point of view.  I am impressed by the suggestion that the word &ldquo;exclusively&rdquo; be put in it, but I do not know enough about it myself.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>There is no objection whatever to holding it over and if the Seanad desire it, I would not dare to make any objection.  The position is that we have consulted the distillers. As the Senator has said, they may have a different view when they see what has been said here.  As to the point raised by Senator Hawkins regarding three-year-old whiskey, I do not know where a publican could get three-year-old whiskey, and if the Senator knows one <Col N="577" /> or more, I would be glad if he would let me know who they are.  If they have three-year-old whiskey they are committing an offence.  A person may export three-year-old whiskey, but if he is using it here, he ought to be advertised immediately.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrederickHawkins" hpid="Mr. Hawkins Mr. Hawkins">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hawkins</NameTxt>
      <P>Seeing that the Minister assures us that it is not possible to get three-year-old whiskey, is it not possible to get five-year-old or seven-year-old whiskey blended with another seven-year-old whiskey and sell it as 15 or 20- year-old whiskey?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFrancisBaxter" hpid="Mr. Baxter Mr. Baxter">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Baxter</NameTxt>
      <P>What do the tasters say?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LiamOBuachalla" hpid="Liam Ó Buachalla Liam Ó Buachalla">
      <NameTxt>Liam Ó Buachalla</NameTxt>
      <P>I asked the Minister while I was speaking whether there is any whiskey on the market at the moment not coming within the definitions under (a) or (b)?  Is there a problem already there for the distillers?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>I am afraid my attention was distracted when that question was put.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LiamOBuachalla" hpid="Liam Ó Buachalla Liam Ó Buachalla">
      <NameTxt>Liam Ó Buachalla</NameTxt>
      <P>The question was whether there is on the market a whiskey which does not correspond with the definitions in the Bill.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Mr. M. Hayes Mr. M. Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Mr. M. Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>But is called Irish whiskey?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not know of any.  At all events, the request was made by the distillers that we should give them a description of Irish whiskey, when it was exported.  That was their main difficulty.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>Committee Stage ordered for Wednesday, 15th March.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Air Navigation and Transport" RHead="Bill, 1949&mdash;Second Stage">
    <Title>Air Navigation and Transport Bill, 1949&mdash;Second Stage.</Title>
    <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That the Bill be now read a Second Time.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="LiamCosgrave" hpid="Parliamentary Secretary to the Minister for Industry and Commerce (Mr. Cosgrave) Liam Cosgrave">
      <NameTxt>Parliamentary Secretary to the Minister for Industry and Commerce (Mr. Cosgrave)</NameTxt>
      <P>The Air Navigation and Transport Act, 1936 is the main statute governing civil aviation in this country. There were amending Acts in 1942 and 1946.  The main purpose of <Col N="578" /> this Bill is to provide for the continuance of the payment of subsidies to the air companies.  The remaining objects mainly deal with amendments and clarifications of the existing law which experience has shown to be necessary and which, while not involving any radical changes, have been shown to be of importance to civil aviation.</P>
      <P>The objects of this Bill are stated briefly in the Explanatory Memorandum circulated to Deputies and Senators with the text of the Bill on 27th January, 1950.  Section 79 of the Air Navigation and Transport Act, 1936, fixed at £500,000 the aggregate amount which might be paid to the air companies by way of subsidy during a period of five years from 14th August, 1936.  The period was extended for five years from 26th May, 1942, by the Air Navigation and Transport (Amendment) Act, 1942.  The sum of £500,000 was later increased to £750,000 by Section 19 of the Air Navigation and Transport Act, 1946, and the period in which payments might be made was extended for a further five years from 31st July, 1946.  The limit of £750,000 which might be paid by way of subsidy was reached in March, 1948.  It is necessary to make provision in the present Bill to continue the payment of subsidies to the air companies.</P>
      <P>The Bill enables the payment of subsidies to be continued for a further period of five years from the date of enactment.  Because of the difficulty of estimating what moneys would be required over a period of five years it is thought better that the Bill should not specify a limit on the amount to be paid during the period.  Any subsidy which has to be paid will be subject to the control of the Dáil in the usual way as provision will be made in the appropriate Vote each year.  Aer Lingus showed a loss of £162,000 for the year ended 31st March, 1949.  The original estimate for the current year was £125,000 and they expect to do considerably better than that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Section 3 of the Bill makes clear that the Minister has power to prosecute in respect of breaches of the Air Navigation and Transport Acts, 1936 to 1946, and of this Act.  Section 5 of the Bill brings the definition of &ldquo;State aircraft&rdquo; into accord with that contained <Col N="579" /> in the Chicago Convention of 1944.  The 1936 Act defines State aircraft as military aircraft and every aircraft used exclusively in State services including postal, customs and police services. This follows the definition in the Paris Convention of 1919, which was replaced by the Chicago Convention of 1944.  The definition of State aircraft in the Chicago Convention does not include aircraft used in postal services.  The intention of the 1939 Act was that the definition of State aircraft should apply to aircraft of all States but the wording of the definition was such that it might be interpreted as applying only to aircraft of this State.  As Ireland has ratified the Chicago Convention, it is desired to bring the definition of &ldquo;State aircraft&rdquo; into conformity with that convention and also to make clear that the term relates to State aircraft of States other than Ireland.</P>
    <P>Sections 6, 7 and 8 of the Bill clarify certain of the powers conferred on the Minister by the 1936 Act relating to the acquisition and disposal of land and the maintenance of water supply, sewage and other works ancillary to aerodromes.</P>
    <P>Section 6 of the Bill is intended to clarify the powers of the Minister in relation to the acquisition of land. Section 36 of the Principal Act defines the purposes for which land may be acquired either by agreement or compulsorily as including purposes relating directly to the safety of aircraft.  It was the intention of that Act to allow the acquisition of land for all requirements of an aerodrome but the manner in which Section 36 is framed might suggest that land could be acquired only for purposes relating directly to the safety of aircraft.  Section 6 of this Bill is intended to make it clear that the Minister may acquire land at or near an aerodrome by agreement or compulsorily for purposes such as the erection of radio beacons to assist the navigation of aircraft or the erection of ancillary buildings.</P>
    <P>Section 37 of the 1936 Act provides for the establishment and maintenance of aerodromes and the provision and maintenance in connection therewith of <Col N="580" /> roads, bridges, approaches, apparatus, equipment and buildings and other accommodation.  To remove any doubts it is desirable that specific powers should now be taken to provide and maintain water mains, sewers and sewage disposal works, electric lines, lights and signs.  This is done in Section 7.  The Minister is authorised by Section 8 of the Bill to enter before conveyance or ascertainment of compensation on any lands compulsorily acquired by him.  Where agreement cannot be reached on compensation arbitration proceedings tend to be slow. If the Minister wished to use land in order to comply with an international aviation requirement before a specified date, it might be essential to gain possession of the land without undue delay.  Up to the present the normal procedure has been followed and the additional powers now proposed would not be used unless in exceptional circumstances which would warrant entry on land before compensation had been fixed.</P>
    <P>Section 10 of the Bill deals with the vesting of lands at Dublin Airport in the Minister.  Some of these lands were acquired as long ago as 1918 by the British Government for use as a military aerodrome and are subject to the provisions of the State Lands Act, 1924. The Minister is hampered in making agreements and leases with airlines and others because the procedure laid down in that Act is not quite appropriate as a result of the developments which have taken place since the airport was built.  Section 10 is designed to remove these difficulties.  Other portions of the lands were acquired by the Minister for Defence and it is now proposed to vest these also in the Minister for Industry and Commerce for convenience of administration.</P>
    <P>Section 11 provides that these lands, as well as some other lands acquired at Shannon Airport under Emergency Powers Order, will be treated as if they had been acquired under the 1936 Act.  This is being done to ensure that the provisions of the 1936 Act relating to the development of aerodromes will apply to these lands.</P>
    <P>Section 42 of the 1936 Act empowers <Col N="581" /> the Minister to dispose of land no longer required by him for the performance of his duties or the exercise of his functions under that Act.  His right to lease sites, buildings, space or rooms at State aerodromes or to dispose of land other than land acquired by him under the 1936 Act is not expressly provided for.  Section 12 of the Bill puts the position beyond doubt.</P>
    <P>The presence of unlighted obstruction such as high buildings in the vicinity of aerodromes may be a hazard to aircraft. It is essential that such obstructions should be marked particularly where there are night operations.  It is important that the Minister should have powers where necessary to affix lights or signs to obstructions and that his officers should have access to these lights or signs for maintenance purposes. Section 13 of the Bill proposes to give the Minister such powers.  It also provides for the payment of compensation where any person proves that his estate or interest is injuriously affected in consequence of the exercise of these powers.</P>
    <P>Recommendations have been made by the International Civil Aviation Organisation, of which Ireland is a member, about controlling the height of obstructions in the vicinity of aerodromes particularly in the areas extending directly from the ends of runways.  Up to the present, the Minister has not had power to regulate the height of buildings or other structures in the vicinity of aerodromes, which would constitute a hazard to aircraft.  It is now proposed in Section 14 that the Minister will have power to regulate the height of buildings in the vicinity of aerodromes. The Minister may by Order declare a particular area to be a protected area and within that area no buildings may exceed a height fixed by the Minister.  Provision is made in Section 14 for the giving of notice to interested parties of the making of a protected area Order and for ensuring that any permit granted by the Minister in connection with a protected area Order shall not operate to release the holder from any restrictions imposed under the Town and Regional Planning Acts, 1934 and 1939.  Provision is made for the payment of compensation where <Col N="582" /> any person proves that his estate or interest is injuriously affected in consequence of the making of a protected area Order.</P>
    <P>Provision is made for the laying on the Table of each House of the Oireachtas, of every protected area Order as soon as it is made.  Either House may pass a resolution annulling such Order within the next subsequent 21 days after it sits.</P>
    <P>Section 16 of the Bill enables the Minister to make bye-laws for the maintenance of order and the control of traffic at State aerodromes and lays down penalties for the violation of the bye-laws.  The Bill also enables the Minister to make bye-laws for the custody and disposal of lost property found at State aerodromes.</P>
    <P>Officers authorised by the Minister will have power to prohibit and restrict the entry of, and to remove, persons, animals and vehicles; to control traffic and enforce speed limits and parking regulations; and to enforce the bye-laws.</P>
    <P>Section 22 of the Bill provides that a State aerodrome is a public place for the purpose of any enactment.  The provisions of the Road Traffic Act, 1933, and of the Licensing Act, 1872, refer to public places and the section is intended to make it clear that the provisions of these Acts apply to State aerodromes.  Part X of the Road Traffic Act, 1933, deals with the lighting of vehicles on roads and it is intended that that Act should apply to roads in a State aerodrome.</P>
    <P>Section 23 of the Bill provides that for the purpose of the management of Dublin Airport, Aer Rianta may act as agents of the Minister unless and until he otherwise directs.  Aer Rianta have been managing the airport since 1940 and no change is contemplated. It is desirable that there should be statutory recognition of this arrangement because of the increasing activity at the airport.</P>
    <P>Section 24 of the Bill modifies the Water Works Clauses Acts, 1847 and 1863 so that the Minister may, with the permission of the sanitary authority concerned, sell water to any person from the supply at a State aerodrome. I would be glad if the Seanad would <Col N="583" /> facilitate me in giving me all the stages of this Bill, as it has to become law before the 31st March, since it will be necessary to make certain provisions in regard to subsidies.</P>
    <Speaker pid="FrederickHawkins" hpid="Mr. Hawkins Mr. Hawkins">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hawkins</NameTxt>
      <P>We will afford every facility to the Parliamentary Secretary to give speedy passage to this Bill.  As he has pointed out, its provision is for a subsidy to our air companies.  He informed us that early in March of 1948 the limit of almost £1,000,000 provided in the Bill of 1946 was reached.  I would like some information in regard to what has happened in the intervening period.  If the 1946 Bill provided for a subsidy to be paid to a particular company operating a particular service, and if the limit of that subsidy was reached in March, 1948, what effect has that had on the finances of that company since then?  We must take it that if the limit was reached in March, 1948, provision should have been made before now for the introduction in the Dáil and here of a Bill to do what is proposed in the Bill before us now. Has this had a very serious effect on the finances of this company?  How was the money provided to keep the company going and to meet the deficiency in their outlay as between what they earned and what the subsidy should provide?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Any ordinary business man knows that if you have a loss in running the loss must be made good by curtailment of the business, by selling out some assets or by going to local finaciers. You must find the money to pay your way.  How did our air service continue up to the present time, when the subsidy provided by legislation was exhausted in March of 1948?  One could put it in a very jocose manner and say that if they have continued from March, 1948, without a State subsidy up to now they could continue on that basis without the introduction of this Bill, regardless of the fact that they have a loss on their income in the intervening period.  Of course, the answer is very easily found.  It is because of the campaign conducted before and during the last general election.  We are pleased that the Parliamentary Secretary comes along to make a case <Col N="584" /> for the Irish people to provide a sum and to ask this House and the Dáil, not for a particular sum of £500,000 or £750,000 but for a blank cheque for the next five years, to subsidise the air services for the people who, we were told during the last three or four years, should be in a position, if they wanted to travel by air, to pay at least their own air service fees.</P>
    <P>I am disappointed that the Parliamentary Secretary did not think fit to give this House or the Dáil, when introducing the Bill, an outline of Government policy on aviation.  For some years we have had quite an amount of criticism.  We had the cancellation of the transatlantic air service, we had that service made practically an election issue, and at least two Ministers have appeared before this House attempting to make the case for that cancellation.  We have the Parliamentary Secretary introducing, at this stage, a Bill that should have been introduced in 1948.  I suggest that the delay is due to that campaign previous to the election.  However, we have this Bill now.  We would have thought it would have been availed of by the Parliamentary Secretary to speak on policy.  I will say this, that despite the fact that many of the Ministers of the present Government criticised our air services, put forward the view that it was Irish money poured down the drain, he was the person chosen on every occasion to go to Cork and Limerick and to functions elsewhere, organised by those interested in the development of our air services, and to put forward a case for the development of such services.</P>
    <P>I believe that he himself is serious in this matter, since he knows that it is of national importance, that here at least is one particular opportunity in which we start off almost level with every other country of Europe.  If it were a question of starting a big shipping company, it could be contended that we are much behind the times, that other nations had something over and above us.  Here was something where we started on equal terms and something that we could develop.  The previous Government devoted a great deal of attention to this problem and were <Col N="585" /> anxious that we should avail of the opportunities that presented themselves for the development of that particular service.  I felt that the Parliamentary Secretary would avail of this opportunity to give us the Government's point of view and to tell us what the Government's policy is in relation to the development of our air services, if they have a policy.</P>
    <Speaker pid="LiamCosgrave" hpid="Mr. Cosgrave Mr. Cosgrave">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cosgrave</NameTxt>
      <P>Would the Senator mind if I left for a division in the Dáil?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrederickHawkins" hpid="Mr. Hawkins Mr. Hawkins">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hawkins</NameTxt>
      <P>I would not like to see the Government defeated because the Seanad meets.  We would have liked to get from the Parliamentary Secretary an indication of what the future policy is.  Why are we asked to pass a Bill giving the Government a blank cheque over a period of five years?  Why is the sum not mentioned? Why are we not told that this Bill is to make provision for £500,000, £750,000 or £1,000,000 subsidy to be paid over a number of years?  The answer that suggests itself to me is that, if the House were asked to make provision for a particular sum, the organisations operating this service would anticipate getting this particular sum from Government resources and, as a result, would not be as efficient as they would be if they knew there was nothing to rely on.  We are asked to issue a blank cheque over the next five years. Why?  Why do the Government ask us to do this?  Is air service a very important national service?  Is it a service that is availed of by the plain people of Ireland and that is of benefit to the plain people?  No.  It is a service that will be availed of by a particular section of the community and we are asked to subsidise it.  We are told that that is good national policy. Is it not strange that, when there was an organisation in existence that could be of great benefit to the country, that could have earned the dollars so essential for the nation, it was handed over to the Dutch and to the other nations of the world?  The service that we had built up was handed over and 300 personnel who had been trained at the expense of the Irish nation for the purpose of operating an Irish service were transferred.  When we talk about the <Col N="586" /> terrible atrocity of Partition, we always refer to the 40,000,000 Irish that are scattered throughout the world.  Here was an attempt to give those who would be in a position to avail of it&mdash; an Irish service between this country and America&mdash;a service that would earn the dollars that it has been indicated to us more than once are so essential.  I am sure that in 1952 we will feel the effects much more keenly than we do now of having scrapped that service.  That service has been scrapped.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFrancisBaxter" hpid="Mr. Baxter Mr. Baxter">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Baxter</NameTxt>
      <P>And a good job.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrederickHawkins" hpid="Mr. Hawkins Mr. Hawkins">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hawkins</NameTxt>
      <P>It is a good job, Senator Baxter says.  The people who fought for the right to establish an Irish Parliament did not do so for the sake of political freedom alone.  They did it in order that we could be in a position to develop our national resources, to build up every possible industry and to find employment for our people.  What happened to those 350 persons who were sent abroad to take charge of our transatlantic service?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFrancisBaxter" hpid="Mr. Baxter Mr. Baxter">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Baxter</NameTxt>
      <P>What happened the 250,000 who emigrated during the war?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrederickHawkins" hpid="Mr. Hawkins Mr. Hawkins">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hawkins</NameTxt>
      <P>They are now in the employment of Pakistan and other nations.  They were trained at the expense of the Irish people.  The Dutch and other nations are now earning dollars by carrying to Ireland the tourists that at one time some members of the present Government proposed should be taxed.  This Bill indicates a conversion, albeit, a small one.  This House is asked to pass this Bill, not for the purpose of bringing Senator Baxter's produce to the Dublin market or to bring the produce of rural Ireland to the Dublin market.  These are the slogans that were used against the development of aviation during the years 1945 to 1948.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>There is a more serious aspect.  There was another organisation developed which found employment for our people.  That organisation employed mechanics.  It was set up in Limerick. That is gone and cannot be brought back.  Despite the fact that Senator Baxter may be a member of the vocational organisation and the technical <Col N="587" /> organisation in his native county, and might be very interested in the development of those organisations, still those young people of ours who would have and have the ambition to be mechanics of one kind or another are deprived of the opportunity of employment in their own country due to the policy operated by the Government of which Senator Baxter is such an ardent supporter.  Some few months ago there was a conference in Dublin.  I regret that the Parliamentary Secretary was called away.  The present position is such that when an important measure of this kind is before the House, to save his Party from defeat he must vacate his seat and not be here as he should be to hear the views of the members of this House.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFrancisBaxter" hpid="Mr. Baxter Mr. Baxter">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Baxter</NameTxt>
      <P>We will tell him what the Senator says.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrederickHawkins" hpid="Mr. Hawkins Mr. Hawkins">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hawkins</NameTxt>
      <P>I always would rely on Senator Baxter to convey it in its true terms from what I know.  As a result of Government policy we had the closing of the Lockheed works, putting out of employment another 300 skilled workers, together with pilots and the people who would operate our transatlantic air services, and they have been forced to find employment in other lands.  Apart altogether from the importance of this small nation having a civil air service, a much more important factor is the defence factor.  I would like to have from the Parliamentary Secretary some information as to what is the personnel at the present time of our Army Air Corps.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOFarrell" hpid="Mr. J.T. O'Farrell Mr. J.T. O'Farrell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J.T. O'Farrell</NameTxt>
      <P>Is that in order?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>We are dealing with civil aviation at the moment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrederickHawkins" hpid="Mr. Hawkins Mr. Hawkins">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hawkins</NameTxt>
      <P>I will agree, but I put forward the theory that civil aviation is very much connected with our defence and that we should look at it in that light.  I propose to put forward some views in that connection. It is essential that we should review the present position in Europe.  We should get from the Government a very <Col N="588" /> straight and definite answer to the question: what is our future policy? What do they propose to do or have they any plan?  I say &ldquo;no&rdquo;.  If they say &ldquo;yes&rdquo;, then they should show us what the plans are.  The great nations of Europe to-day are preparing for another great set-to.  We know we are a small nation.  We know, and we are told by no less responsible a person than the Minister for Defence, that we must rely on our own resources.  What are they?  What is the personnel of our Army Air Corps at the present time? If we have not an Army Air Corps, where can we recruit the personnel for our civil air services?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFrancisBaxter" hpid="Mr. Baxter Mr. Baxter">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Baxter</NameTxt>
      <P>On a point of order.  Are we entitled to discuss defence?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrederickHawkins" hpid="Mr. Hawkins Mr. Hawkins">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hawkins</NameTxt>
      <P>Are you afraid to discuss it?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFrancisBaxter" hpid="Mr. Baxter Mr. Baxter">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Baxter</NameTxt>
      <P>Might we have a ruling?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>The Senator is apparently endeavouring to relate civil aviation to defence.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrederickHawkins" hpid="Mr. Hawkins Mr. Hawkins">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hawkins</NameTxt>
      <P>I can understand that Senator Baxter and the people associated with him are not prepared to discuss this vital matter, but it is one that will have to be debated and discussed in this and in the other House and in every corner of the country in the very near future.  It has a particular bearing on the subject under discussion here.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>It has not.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrederickHawkins" hpid="Mr. Hawkins Mr. Hawkins">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hawkins</NameTxt>
      <P>I will approach it from another angle.  I will ask the Parliamentary Secretary to give us tonight a definite statement as to how many of the personnel of our Irish air service were members of a foreign army air corps and in the event of that country being engaged in a conflict, how many of them would be called to its service and what would be the personnel of our civil air service as a result of that?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I am afraid that that has nothing to do with the Bill which is before the House.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrederickHawkins" hpid="Mr. Hawkins Mr. Hawkins">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hawkins</NameTxt>
      <P>While I am quite prepared to accept your ruling, I suggest that the Bill before us makes provision for a blank cheque to keep in operation <Col N="589" /> our air service and before I or any other member of the House is called upon to consent to the passing of this Bill, we must have the answer to the questions I put forward.  This to my mind is a question of national importance and the Parliamentary Secretary knows full well that it is such.  He knows full well that we have not at the present time sufficient personnel in our Army Air Corps to take the place of those people who pass out of our civil air services.  He knows that the majority of the people employed in our air service at the present time were formerly members of a foreign air service and that, in the event of that foreign country being engaged in a conflict, they are going to be called to it and our air services would be deprived of them.  If he can put forward facts and figures to prove that my statement is not correct, there will be no person as well pleased as I will be.</P>
      <P>Why has this Bill been introduced in such a manner?  Why have we not had some indication from the Government of the sum they are prepared to make available over a period of five years?  Why must we be called upon at this stage to issue a blank cheque to provide for air services when we were told that it was a fallacy to provide a transatlantic service to earn the dollars which are so much needed?  If it is wrong on the one hand it must be wrong on the other.  I would be prepared to consent to a Bill asking £100,000 or £500,000 or any definite sum, but when the Parliamentary Secretary comes before this House and asks us to give him and the Government authority to issue a blank cheque for such services, having regard to the approach this Government has had to the question of air services, then it is certainly too much to ask.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I, at this stage, suggest to the Parliamentary Secretary that he should take us more into his confidence, that he should admit to us if a mistake has been made and, if a new approach is about to be made to this whole question, he should give us an idea of what he thinks, and what the company thinks, will be the sum essential to carry on for the next five years.  If he is not prepared to do that, if he is not prepared to give us the information I <Col N="590" /> have asked for I would, at least, make this suggestion&mdash;it is again a national question&mdash;that if we are to have an air service we should make a serious attempt to, at least, go about organising that air service, and see that it is manned by people who will be at the service of the Irish nation in time of emergency, and who will not, because of their obligations be taken from the service of this nation into the service of another country.  If the Parliamentary Secretary is not in a position to give us that, well, we must take steps to ensure, as far as we can, that the matter is taken more seriously than it is at the present time.  I know full well that Senator Baxter is very anxious to get up to make a case.  I will be anxious to hear the case he will make.  I know full well, as I have already stated, it is not a case or it cannot be a case of taking the produce of the farmers of Cavan to the Dublin or the London market.  It must be a case of taking those people who are not small farmers, the same type of people who would be of much greater benefit to this nation and who were opposed by Senator Baxter and those who were associated with him.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDouglas" hpid="Mr. Douglas Mr. Douglas">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Douglas</NameTxt>
      <P>This is a Bill which is of a somewhat technical character.  It is obviously designed to make for the efficiency, not only of our own services, but of the airports provided for the safety of aeroplanes that land in this country, and for many other things which, I imagine, every member of this House wishes to see done, and wishes to see done efficiently.  The last speaker has varied from the County Cavan to the problems of Europe, and from 1852 to dollars, and I could hardly tell the number of things which he has introduced.  It seems to me that there are only two matters, directly relevant to this Bill, which he has dealt with. One is that he has a sense of grievance because there is no provision for a huge loss in this particular Bill, and that he is one of those who strongly believes, no matter what the loss, it was highly desirable this country should run a transatlantic air service.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>That is a matter on which there can be perfectly honest differences of <Col N="591" /> opinion, but whether you do that in the future or whether you do not, surely there is no room for two opinions as to whether our airports should be run efficiently, as to whether there should be safety precautions, or as to whether the matters in this Bill should not be made law and done as quickly as possible.  It seems to me there is no case whatever for introducing into the matter of air efficiency questions on which we may differ.  I completely differ from the point of view of the Senator with reference to the transatlantic service, but I recognise that there can be honest differences as to whether that was or was not in the national interest.  His other point was that he is strongly of the opinion that in dealing with the matter of air transport you should estimate your losses for five years ahead.  Personally, I think, that is just silly.  There is no case whatever for the statement that a blank cheque is being given.  The only difference is, that whereas the previous Bill put a statutory limit on what the Dáil could do without passing another measure, this one does not. There is no blank cheque.  There can be no money voted that is not passed or provided in an Estimate and, therefore, it would be an unfortunate thing if, as the result of the Senator's speech, it were to go abroad that there was a proposal for a blank cheque.  There is nothing of the kind.  I would like, when I am on my feet, to say that I am convinced and satisfied that whether we should or should not have an Atlantic service is relatively unimportant. What does matter is the fact that we have got a quite small, but very efficient service in Aer Lingus, one of which we can be proud, and one which has a good reputation abroad, not only by the good fortune that there has been no loss of life, but because it is well managed, and efficiently run. I have travelled a fair amount by air, and while I do not claim in any sense to be an expert, I do know that what I am saying now is shared by many people who are not Irishmen and, speaking generally, Aer Lingus has got an excellent reputation.  Now, nobody disagrees that that should be kept.  No one on any side of the House wants to <Col N="592" /> make that a Party issue.  Therefore I suggest that there is nothing of a Party nature in this Bill at all.  It is simply a Bill to provide for efficiency and it should be accepted by this House as such.</P>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasHonan" hpid="Mr. Honan Mr. Honan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Honan</NameTxt>
      <P>I had a difficulty in finding out what the purpose of the Bill was at all because, as far as I can see, most of the enactments proposed in the Bill have already been in force.  We have built roads and bridges and we have done all the necessary things of that kind that go to constitute an airport. Probably they wanted some clarifying and the Minister found it necessary to do so now.  Senator Hawkins has dealt with some of the points I wish to make, and has dealt with a lot I had no intention of making. There is one point, at least, that the people of Limerick and Clare are still rather perturbed about, and that is the negotiations that have been going on for a long time as to the possible transfer of business from Shannon Airport to Collinstown.  There is a general feeling that the Americans are trying to push that along, that they want to use it for their own purposes, and to use it for the purpose this year, in particular, of getting the Irish trade of taking our people across for the Holy Year.  Well, I think, Aer Lingus have such an excellent record, of which we are all proud, that if they have the ships and men they should see to it that this country, which is paying for the airports, should benefit as a result.  I am sure there will be a decision soon because that airport was built at a very poor time, a time of depression with very little employment in the country, very little indeed.  I knew workmen to cycle 15 to 18 miles to work at that airport in the earlier stage at a wage of 27/- a week.  That was increased gradually when it came to better times, but the sweat and blood of Clare and Limerick people were put into the construction of that airport and they hope and, I think, the country hopes that there will be no interference with it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>There is a small point that I wish to mention to the Parliamentary Secretary. In the early stages, after the <Col N="593" /> construction, the airport was a great novelty on Sundays, half-days and that sort of thing.  Nearly all the people of Munster came there, tinkers, tailors, soldiers and sailors, with the result that they had to be preyented going into the airport.  They had to pay a levy of 2/6 on a car and, I think, 6d. or 1/- a head for the passengers to go into the airport.</P>
    <P>It is very annoying and people who have travelled the world tell me it is the only airport where such a levy is imposed on visitors to the port.  It is a very poor method of making people air-minded to prevent them from entering the port and seeing what is going on and watching the ships arriving and departing.  I think that the big rush of people going to see the airport has subsided except for those who are coming to it on business, and it would be a nice thing if that admission fee were to be eliminated.</P>
    <P>As it is, even a passenger going in is expected to pay and, if he objects, he is told to see the man at the counter, but there are so many counters there that you do not know which one to go to, and usually the people are just annoyed and tell them to keep it.  Those travellers to whom I have spoken tell me it is the only airport at which there are charges made, and I am sure the Parliamentary Secretary could see his way to have them abolished.  I believe that some of the officials at the airport itself are feeling that way now, and saying that the time has come when charges should be wiped out.</P>
    <P>This Bill is such a comprehensive measure and there are so many ends and points to it that one could discuss it for a week, but I cannot let the occasion pass without remarking that most people thought that doing away with the Lockheed mechanical plant of 300 people, and with the proposed transatlantic air service, was nothing short of vandalism.  There were 300 people there earning from four to eight guineas a week each when they were just turned out and sent all over the world.  Perhaps the day will come when they or some of their kith and kin will come back there again.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOFarrell" hpid="Mr. J.T. O'Farrell Mr. J.T. O'Farrell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J.T. O'Farrell</NameTxt>
      <P>This question of air transport is usually associated with <Col N="594" /> a lot of sentimental talk divorced altogether from the business side of the problem.  Air travel is just another form of transport competing with existing forms of transport and it can only succeed to the extent to which it takes business from other forms of transport and communications.  Consequently, I think we devote too much time to talking about national prestige and the Irish across the sea&mdash;our great spiritual empire throughout the world &mdash;when we begin to talk of what is purely a business proposition.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Not only is every person who travels by air carried at less than the real cost, but the taxpayers have to pay the difference in order to subsidise it.  The more we increase the expenditure on air services at existing rates the greater will be the national deficit.  It was suggested actually that we were unfortunately misled in not widening the area of national loss by running a transatlantic service in competition with those huge American combines with hundreds of millions of dollars behind them&mdash;a perfectly crazy proposal&mdash; and that we should do that for national prestige reasons.  Already we see other developments we had not anticipated, like the desire of the big American companies to by-pass Shannon and throw men out of employment.  Surely we cannot blame the Government or any other Irish authority for that change, and greater changes than that will take place.  The day may come when Shannon will be by-passed altogether by American companies, because of the development of transport, and what they regard as the requirements of their trans-ocean passengers.  I do not know if there is any air company in the world actually making a profit to-day, but I would like the Parliamentary Secretary to say to what extent, if any, we are advancing towards solvency. For instance, is the subsidy decreasing year by year and, if so, to what extent?  In the natural order of things, I think we must work for the day when these services will have to pay for themselves.  We have already a tremendous commitment in the case of Córas Iompair Éireann and when it becomes a national undertaking this commitment will have to be paid until such time as the services <Col N="595" /> are able to pay their way.  Everybody would object to the perpetuation of a position in which rail and road transport would have to be subsidised. If that is so, why should we calmly and philosophically accept a position in which air transport, running largely in competition with these services, must be subsidised in perpetuity?  In the past, we rushed pell mell into air development and we are paying for that now.  You had the position where a most expensive hotel was erected down there at Foynes at a seaplane base which is now deserted.  The hotel had to be sold for a song.  That should be a lesson to the Government about entering into very heavy expenditure in regard to Shannon unless they are sure that it is going to be a permanent institution of an important kind.  I would like to know from the Minister if Aer Rianta observes the general commercial principle of making provision for depreciation and renewals so that they can say at the end of each year in the regular commercial accountancy sense of the word what is the extent of the loss.  Otherwise you will have no idea from a commercial point of view of the extent of the losses.</P>
    <P>Senator Honan was mistaken when he said it was the only airport in the world in which a charge is made for admission.  I remember seeing an advertisement in British newspapers some time ago announcing a scheme for the admission of visitors to British airports at weekends at definite fees of sixpence or a shilling a head and something additional for cars.  They looked on it as a form of entertainment that would bring revenue which the public would be willing to pay and they did make a charge.  I do not think you could make our airports open to all and sundry&mdash;that could create a position in which it would be impossible to carry on working.  The charge in that case is a reasonable one.  The rest of the Bill merely provides for regularising and bringing up to date the legislation governing air travel. Some of it seeks to remove doubts that previously existed, and other sections give powers, which the company had not got up to the present, to make air travel more efficient and safe.  To that <Col N="596" /> extent I do not think we need have any hesitation in passing the Bill.  The subsidy portion, as Senator Douglas pointed out, does not ask for a blank cheque as reference to Section 25 will show.  The moneys have to be provided by the Oireachtas in the ordinary way and any payments by the Minister for Finance may be annulled by either House in the ordinary way.  To that extent, the House retains control over the payment of subsidies.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelColgan" hpid="Mr. Colgan Mr. Colgan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Colgan</NameTxt>
      <P>There is one point arising out of the remarks of Senator Honan on this question of admission free or by charge to aerodromes.  I have nothing to say against the charging of an admission fee.  I believe that some limitation on the number of people going to these places is essential, because it is natural that in the case of the people of this country as well as those of any other country, if you give them a free show, they will tend to over-run the place, and it is probably judicious that some admission fee should be charged.</P>
      <P>There is, however, another matter about which I have heard much complaint, that is, the charge made by Córas Iompair Éireann for carrying passengers to and from Collinstown.  It is not very relevant, but I think I may take this opportunity to mention it.  I believe that visitors and others who have to travel to Collinstown are charged something like 1/3, where the normal fare would be 5d. or 6d.  It is the fact that this imposition is put upon them over and above their ordinary fare that they resent.  They do not resent paying the 1/3, but they do resent the principle of charging 1/3, and they feel that if they are to be flown from Dublin to some place in England, their fare from the centre of the city to the airport should be included in the fare they pay, and that there ought not to be this imposition on them.  I do not know if that is the case in other countries.  It has been alleged that it is peculiar to this country and it is a small matter which people who have to pay resent very much.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrederickSummerfield" hpid="Mr. Summerfield Mr. Summerfield">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Summerfield</NameTxt>
      <P>It is not my intention to go over many of the points <Col N="597" /> already covered in this rather interesting debate, but I want to suggest that we have in our air service something of which the whole country has every reason to be proud.  We have in it a service which, thank God, has been remarkably free from accidents and which has earned a reputation for efficiency, courtesy and general good management, which are matters that foreigners talk about.  Advertising itself costs money and I want to suggest that our air facilities are, in themselves, a remarkably good advertisement for the country, and if some loss has been incurred and may be incurred in future in running them, that loss is offset by the value we get in return in the form of the good opinions expressed about our services by people outside.</P>
      <P>Senator Hawkins raised one point which deserves the attention not merely of the Parliamentary Secretary, but of the Minister, that is, the personnel of our air service.  I think it is true that some proportion&mdash;I am not sufficiently well informed to say what proportion&mdash;of the flying personnel are non-nationals.  This is a time when we ought to be realists.  Their own country undoubtedly has first claim on these men for either civil or military service and I feel that it would not be asking too much of the Government if I asked that the authorities here would provide in our flying services an outlet for the brainy young men of our universities.</P>
      <P>If it was held out to them, to these young men with engineering qualifications and an adventurous bent, that, in our air services, there is an outlet for them, it would be an incentive to young fellows to take up flying as a career. I feel that it is a matter which is worthy of more attention than a mere passing reference in a debate.  We should ensure that our reservoir of trained men will be men whose first loyalty is to this country and not to another.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Anxiety has been expressed, and rightly expressed, about the future of Shannon.  I do not propose to go into that very controversial subject of whether or not we should have kept on the transatlantic service.  I could say a lot about it, but will not do so.  We <Col N="598" /> must, however, be concerned about the anxiety they have at Shannon as to the future of that airport, and I should like to know, no matter what may happen about the transatlantic services, so far as our own ownership of them is concerned, whether the Government is giving any thought to the possibility of erecting at Shannon a duty-free airport.  I feel that it is worth looking into, although, again, it is not something on which one can dogmatise.</P>
    <Speaker pid="LiamCosgrave" hpid="Mr. Cosgrave Mr. Cosgrave">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cosgrave</NameTxt>
      <P>It is there.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrederickSummerfield" hpid="Mr. Summerfield Mr. Summerfield">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Summerfield</NameTxt>
      <P>So much the better.  It is something which would ensure the future of Shannon if it were well developed.  It is well known that many of the most expensive articles in commerce to-day are articles of light bulk, and if inducements were held out to American exporters intending to sell their finished goods in Europe to use a portion of County Clare as a duty-free finishing-off place, the anxieties of Senator Honan and everybody in the country concerning the future of Shannon would be dissipated.</P>
      <P>This is a Bill which deserves the support of the House.  Anything that will increase the facilities and efficiency we have ought to commend itself not merely to the House but to the community as a whole.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesCrosbie" hpid="Mr. Crosbie Mr. Crosbie">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Crosbie</NameTxt>
      <P>I should like to associate myself with the measure of praise which has been given by many Senators to our air services.  Senator Hawkins raised a point with regard to non-nationals being employed by Aer Lingus and Aer Rianta, but the Senator, possibly without due deliberation, failed to point out that many of these non-nationals were brought in at a time when Aer Lingus was being expanded very rapidly, with such rapidity that we were unable at the time to provide the requisite number of trained personnel from amongst our own nationals.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I am in full agreement with him and Senator Summerfield that every inducement ought to be given to our young men to use our air transport company as a medium for employment. Unfortunately, in this country there is <Col N="599" /> no means whereby young men can be trained as pilots unless they join the Army Air Corps.  That, of necessity, is a limited force and it is not possible for everybody who wants to become a trained pilot to get into that corps, and, if they do get in, there is no guarantee that they will stay in it and not leave it to become a civilian air transport company pilot.  At a later stage, the Parliamentary Secretary ought to keep under his consideration the possibility of starting some form of school, if not for the training of pilots, for the training of young men in aeronautical engineering, by arrangement with the engineering faculties of the universities.</P>
    <P>One of the features which, I understand, is showing great promise in the development of the business side of Aer Lingus is the gradually increasing amount of freight which is being carried from year to year.  That is a feature which may hold very beneficial possibilities in the future.  I understand also that one of the most prosperous lines in that trade is the rapid transportation of lobsters, crayfish and other shell-fish from Shannon to the French markets.  There are possibilities that some fine day the Minister for Agriculture may require liquid milk to be exported from this country by air.  These, I think, are all possibilities the Minister and the Parliamentary Secretary ought to keep constantly under review.  It is quite clear that, like most other transport services, air transport is very unlikely to survive economically on passenger traffic alone.  Otherwise, there is nothing in this Bill that is not of a technical nature, giving the Minister the powers that are necessary for the safe handling of commercial aircraft under the various international agreements.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MartinODwyer" hpid="Mr. O'Dwyer Mr. O'Dwyer">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Dwyer</NameTxt>
      <P>On the question of the compulsory acquisition of land for airport purposes, we all know it is frequently necessary to acquire land compulsorily for building houses.  I know it is already provided for that there should be a price paid over and above the market value.  There should be compensation for disturbance.  It is not enough to pay market value in <Col N="600" /> a case like that, where a person is removed from the house he has held or where his family may have been for generations, or where the land has been specially prepared.  Some generous compensation should be paid, over and above market value.  It may be the case that that is being done but, if not, I hope the Minister will look into the point.</P>
      <P>I suggest that the Government do everything possible to insist on the retention of the traffic at Shannon as heretofore.  It means more than the actual maintenance of the port.  As we know, the tendency is for people to flood into Dublin and the east coast. One of the reasons for Dublin's overdevelopment is that all traffic and transport companies seem to turn towards the east coast and all our industries seem to follow that general trend of population towards the east. The result is that Connaught, Munster and the centre of Ireland are becoming more derelict and industry and population are fading out.  The only way to stop that is by the development of industries in the west and south.  One of the principal means would be the development of the ports, and Shannon Airport would be a great means of retaining the population there.  For that reason, if for nothing else, the Government should make an effort to retain the aircraft landings at Shannon.  In that respect, it was a great loss that our aircraft business was abandoned. I think the Government should again embark on that, if it is necessary.  In any case, it is of vital importance that those conditions be retained and that the development of Shannon Airport should continue.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamStanford" hpid="Professor Stanford Professor Stanford">
      <NameTxt>Professor Stanford</NameTxt>
      <P>I would like to say a word or two on one general aspect of this Bill and of some other Bills which have been before the Seanad recently.  I refer to State encroachment on the rights of the owners of land.  It is really deplorable that every third Bill or so, for some reason or another, entails the landowner losing his rights over his own land.  If his farm is damp, he is going to have people coming in and turning it round for drainage, whether he likes it or not.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="601" />
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFrancisBaxter" hpid="Mr. Baxter Mr. Baxter">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Baxter</NameTxt>
      <P>Oh, no.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamStanford" hpid="Professor Stanford Professor Stanford">
      <NameTxt>Professor Stanford</NameTxt>
      <P>If he is in a glen, a reservoir is poured over his farm and it will be engulfed and he will have to find some other place as a home.  If a main road is needed from Bray to Dublin, he finds his front door or back door cheerfully cut off from his house and obliterated, to enable faster speeding in cars.  Now we have aerodromes and if he lives in a flat place in the middle of the country he can look for trouble.  He cannot put up a high post, nor may he erect a tower.  If a church needs a spire, it may be a danger to aircraft, and the church spire comes under the Act.</P>
      <P>I know it is a general problem and it seems to be reactionary to speak on this point, but do we know where we are going in this matter generally?  We are steadily encroaching on the rights of people, in the interests of some big combine or of going faster in some direction.  Is that what we want?  Are we quite satisfied that a certain amount of money compensation, great or small, is enough justification for turning a man out of the home his family lived in for 100 or 500 years?  It is a general point and I suppose nothing can be done about it, in one sense.  I think we should keep our eyes open on this matter.  Every major Bill means another encroachment on these personal rights.  Let us see quite clearly what we are doing.  If we give these special powers, to stop one farmer putting up some high post for charging his electric batteries or something of the kind, or another farmer from building a tower over a certain height, or if we cause another to lose his front door or back door, is this what we want?  You may say that progress demands this.  Frankly, I believe we should think twice about the kind of progress we want in this country.  I appeal to the sensible members of the House to think of places like those farms which were in Bohernabreena, places which are not yet engulfed by progress, and to consider whether each of these Bills is not a nail in the coffin of Irish culture and civilisation.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LiamOBuachalla" hpid="Liam Ó Buachalla Liam Ó Buachalla">
      <NameTxt>Liam Ó Buachalla</NameTxt>
      <P>Is Bille é seo nach féidir linn morán lochtaí d'fháil air <Col N="602" /> mar Bhille.  Is léir uaidh go bhfuil na cumhachta atá á n-iarraidh ann ag teastáil, má tá cúrsaí aerloingseoireachta na tíre le bheith chomhhéifeachtach agus ba cheart iad a bheith. Tá mé ar aon intinn, cuid mhaith, leis an Seanadóir Stanford, nuair adeireann sé gur trua go bhfuil an oiread seo á dhéanamh againn in ainm dul ar aghaidh agus gurb é an deireadh a bheas air ar ball go millfear rudaí an-luachmhara.  I gcás aerloingseoireachta, do bheadh spéis agam fhéin ann ar dhá chúis&mdash;caithfidh Éire maireachtáil, agus caithfidh Éire seasamh i gcomórtas le náisiúin eile. Ní mór tráchtáil a bheith ann, ní mór caidreamh idir-náisiúnta a bheith ann, agus le haghaidh tráchtáil agus caidreamh idir-náisiúnta is léir go bhfuil aerloingseoireacht an-tábhachtach.  Ar an ábhar sin, ó tharla go bhfuil sé tábhachtach agus go bhfuil sé riachtanach, ba cheart dúinn gach dícheall a dhéanamh chun go mbeidh na seirbhísí aerloingseoireachta atá againn sa tír ar chuma chomh hard-éifeachtach agus is féidir.</P>
      <P>Is maith liom go mór an méid adúirt an Seanadóir Summerfield i dtaobh a fheabhas agus a stiúraíodh na Comhluchtaí Aerloingseoireachta sa tír go dtí seo.  Nuair a smaoiníonn duine ar an gcostas a bhí orainn iad a chur chun cinn agus an costas sin a chur i gcomórtas leis an méid a chaitheas tíortha eile le seirbhís aerloingseoireachta, sílim gur féidir linn a bheith sásta go ndearna Aer Lingus a chuid oibre go maith agus go sásúil.</P>
      <P>Ó thaobh timpiste, is dóigh go bhféadfaimis a rá go bhfuil seirbhísí na hÉireann ar na seirbhísí is lú ar an domhan ar bhain timpistí leo.  Is iontach an moladh é don lucht stiúrtha, do na píolótaí agus don phersonnel ar fad.  Sílim go mba cheart dúinn, ar an ócáid seo, a chur in iúl dóibh a mhéid agus atá meas againn orthu as ucht a fheabhas agus atá a gcuid oibre déanta acu.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>An darna cúis atá agam le spéis a bheith agam sa mBille seachas cúrsaí aerloingseoireachta i gcoitinne, sea chomh tábhachtach agus a bheadh aer-sheirbhísí dúinn ó thaobh slándála náisiúnta.  Dúirt an Seanadóir Summerfield go ndearnadh tagairt anseo don <Col N="603" /> tseirbhís transatlantic agus go bhféadfadh seisean a lán a rá ar an ábhar sin ach nár mhaith leis.  Is mór an trua é gur bhreathnaigh sé air mar sin.  Má tá tuairmí againn a bhaineas le aer-sheirbhísí, is cuma an mbaineann sé le seirbhísí Eoraipeacha nó seirbhísí go dtí na Stáit Aontaithe, ba cheart dúinn na tuairmí sin a nochtadh.  Is trua liom gur stopadh an tseirbhís a bhí beartaithe idir Éire agus na Stáit Aontaithe.  Is trua liom é ar dhá chúis. Is trua liom gur chailleamar cuid mhaith tráchtála.  Chailleamar cuid mhaith tráchtála an-luachmhar de bhrí gur cuireadh stop leis an tseirbhís sin.  Dúradh ó am go ham go raibh baol ann go mbeadh cailliúint mhór ar na seirbhísí sin.  B'fhéidir go mbeadh cailliúint ann ar feadh tamaill.  Níl a fhios agam aon ghnó ach amháin, b'fhéidir, &ldquo;black-marketing&rdquo; nach mbíonn cailliúint air ar feadh tamaill tar éis a bhunuithe agus, ar nós páipéar nuachta nó monarchan déantóra ar bith, ní chuirfeadh sé ionadh ná imní orm dá mbeadh cailliúint le tabhairt faoi ndeara ar imeachtaí na seirbhísí go dtí Aimeirice ar feadh tamaill de bhlianta.  Bhí an oiread muinín agam agus tá an oiread muinín agam fós, dá gcuirtí ar bun iad, dá stiúraítí iad chomh maith agus a stiúraítear na seirbhísí eile, nach mbeadh sé ró-fhada go dtí go mbeadh, in ionad cailliúint, tairbhe ann don tír.</P>
    <P>Bhí buaidh faoi leith acu, nach raibh ag a lán comhluchtaí eile, maidir leis an tseirbhís Atlantaigh.  Sé an buaidh é sin an &ldquo;goodwill&rdquo; a bhí againn thar mar a bhí ag tíortha eile, ar dhá chúis.  Aon chuís amháin chomh líonmhar agus atá ár muintir sna Stáit Aontaithe.  Is cinnte, dá mbeadh an rogha acu ar chóir taistil, gur túisce a thaistealóidís ar sheirbhís Éireannach ná ar sheirbhísí eile.  An darna údar&mdash;an cháil a bhí bainte amach ag na hEireannaigh, mar &ldquo;technicians,&rdquo; mar stiúrthóirí agus mar píolótaí, i gcúrsaí aerloingseoireachta.</P>
    <P>Léigh mé go cúramach an díospóireacht a bhí ar an mBille seo sa Dáil.  Níl a fhios agam céard adéarfas an Rúnaí Parlaiminte faoi ach déarfainn <Col N="604" /> féin gur ceann de na hóráidí ab fhearr a chuala mé ariamh an óráid a rinne an t-iarAire Tionscail agus Tráchtála agus é ag cur síos ar an mBille seo.  Ba mhaith liom a lán de na pointí a luaigh sé a lua anseo ach ní dóigh liom go mbeadh sé féaráilte don iarAire ná féaráilte don tSeanad.  Ba mhaith liom go ngéillfeadh an Rúnaí Parlaiminte don achainí a chuir an t-iarAire Tionscail agus Tráchtála air nuair d'iarr sé air léargas éigin cruinn a thabhairt dúinn faoi aigne an Rialtais i dtaobh na seirbhísí sin.  Ní leor dó a rá gurb é rún an Rialtais a ndícheall a dhéanamh le haer-sheirbhís a chur ar aghaidh do réir mar chítear dóibh gur cheart é sin a dhéanamh.  Ní leor é agus, ar ócáid mar é seo, is dóigh liom go mba cheart go mbeadh an Rúnaí Parlaiminte ullamh ar an léargas sin a thabhairt dúinn i dtaobh polasaí, i dtaobh aigne an Rialtais, maidir leis na seirbhísí seo, thar mar atá déanta aige sa Dáil.  B'fhéidir go bhfuil sé sin déanta aige anseo inniu.  Is dona liom nach raibh mé i ndon fanacht.  Bhí cruinniú le freastal agam air.  Munar thug, is dóigh liom go mba cheart dó géilleadh don achainí a cuireadh air agus níos mó eolais a thabhairt dúinn faoi céard atá beartaithe maidir leis an tseirbhís sin.</P>
    <P>An cailliúint de bharr na seirbhísí a chur ar ceal, is deacair é a mheas. Tá a fhios againn an réiteach a bhí déanta le píolótaí a thraenáil.  A lán den obair, bhí sé déanta.  Bhí ullmhúcháin déanta le go dtraenálfaí innealtóirí ar an obair speisialta a bhaineas le cúrsaí aerloingseoireachta. Bhí dóchas ann go mbeadh againn seirbhísí chomh hard agus ohomh héifeachtach agus ab fhéidir.  Ba dheacair aon luach a chur orthu do réir airgid.  Is cailliúint é sin, dar liom, atá go h-uafásach.</P>
    <P>Nuair a bhí an díospóireacht ar bun i dtaobh na seirbhísí sin do chur ar ceal, rinneadh a lán cainte ar an méid airgid a bhí caite ar traenáil lucht oibre, innealtóirí agus eile.  Ní cailliúint airgid é sin.  Oideachas, ar shlí, a bhí ann agus oideachas an-luachmhar.  Bheadh buntáiste ag <Col N="605" /> teacht don tír gur deacair é a luacháil i gceart.</P>
    <P>Má tharlann choíche sa saol mar a tharla cheana go mbeadh muid i sáinn agus cogadh thart, sin é an uair a d'aireodh muid an chailliúint a bheas ann de thoradh nach raibh sé de mhisneach agus de fhaid-bhreathnaitheacht ionainn dul ar aghaidh leis na seirbhísí seo.</P>
    <P>Rud a thugann sásamh dom i dtaobh an Bhille seo, go bhfuil sé socair ag an Rialtas dul ar aghaidh agus deolchairí, nó <i>subsidies</i>, a íoc más gá go ceann cúig bliana eile agus nach bhfuil aon teora leis an méid a íocfar i riocht deolchairí.  Bhéarfaidh sé sin deis don Rialtas, má athraíonn siad a n-aigne i dtaobh na seirbhísí aerloingseoireachta, polasaí maith a chur i gerích.  B'fhéidir nach dtuigim i gceart é, ach bheirim an méid sin sóláis dom feín, nach bhfuil an doras dúnta ar mhéadú nó leathnú na seirbhísí aerloingseoireachta, ní amháin ar fud na hEorpa, ach go dtí na Stáit Aontaithe le cúnamh Dé.</P>
    <P>Rinneadh tagairt do na strainséirí, na heachtrannaigh, a tugadh isteach i gcúrsaí na seirbhísí seo againne. Mar phrionsabal, níl mé i gcoinne eachtrannaigh a thabhairt isteach.  Sé an rud nádúrtha é, má theastaíonn oideachas nó eolaithe uait, go raghthá go dtí na daoine is fearr a bhfuil an t-eolas acu.  Más gá, i geás tionscail nó seirbhíse nua, dul i gcéin le haghaidh eolaithe d'fháil, níl aon locht agam air sin, ach ba cheart dúinn a bheith cúramach faoi cé mhéad acu a tabharfaí isteach agus faoi cén fhaid a bheadh siad sna postanna ceannais.  Mar adúradh, má éiríonn aon chlampar caithfidh siad a bheith dílis dá dtíortha féin agus caithfimíd a bheith cinnte ó thaobh na slándála náisiúnta de go mbeidh daoine againn leis an obair a dhéanamh sa mbealach ba cheart í a dhéanamh.</P>
    <P>Cloisim&mdash;níl fhios agam an fíor é&mdash; dá fheabhas na heiteallaín atá againn, nach bhfuil siad feiliúnach d'aistear trasna an Atlantaigh.  Feictear dhom go bhfuil sé sin go míllteach.  Deirtear nach n-airítear ganntanas uisce go dtéann an tobar i ndísc agus ba cheart dúinn fóghlaim ón éigeandáil atá caite&mdash;má tá sé caite&mdash;agus más gá <Col N="606" /> airgead a chaitheamh, nó a chailliúint mar adeir daoine áirithe, ar eitealláin le dul go dtí na Stáit, ní cailliúint a bheadh ann, sílim, ach buntáiste. Ba mhaith liom go dtabharfadh an Rúnaí Parlaiminte cuntas dúinn ar éifeacht na n-eiteallán atá againn. An mbeadh siad feiliúnach le haghaidh tráchtáil trasna an Atlantaigh dá mba ghá le linn éigeandála a leithéid a bheith againn?</P>
    <P>Ba mhaith liom a chloisteáil freisin an bhfuil aon bheartas ceapaithe amach maidir le haer-thaisteal intíre thar mar atá ann faoi láthair.  Ní hé go mbeinn ag súil go gcuirfí plean i bhfeidhm maidin amáireach, ach an bhfuil aon bheartas ceapaithe amach acu le haghaidh na haimsire atá le teacht? Bhí sé i gceist sa Dáil.  Céard a bheas ar intinn acu i dtaobh Chorcaigh, i dtaobh na Gaillimhe agus i dtaobh bailte móra eile ar fud na tíre?  An dóigh leis go mbeadh gá le seirbhís den tsórt sin?  Más dóigh leis go mbeadh, cén chaoia cuirfí ar fáil é?</P>
    <P>Tá pointe nó dhó eile agam nach mbaineann leis an mBille go díreach ach ba mhaith liom iad a mheabhrú don Rúnaí Pairliminte, féachaint an bhféadfadh sé aon rud a dhéanamh fúthu.  Tharla go raibh mé le goirid i nAerphort na Sionainne.  Tháinig an té a bhí le taisteal ó na Stáit agus bhí sé le dul ar aghaidh go dtí an Mór-roinn. B'éigin dóibh fanúint san Aerphort agus cuireadh £1 2s. 6d. costais orthu as leabaidh d'fháil, i gceann de na hoistéil atá san áit.  Níl fhios agam an bhfuil an figiúir sin as bealach le haghaidh cúpla uair a' chloig in oistéal, ní féidir liom ach an méid seo a rá: facthas do na daoine a bhí i gceist gur éileamh mí-réasúnta é agus gur fearr an margadh a gheobhadh siad da bhfanaidis i Luimneach nó i ninis.  Níl fhios agam an bhfuil sé as bealach, ach facthas do na daoine seo a bhfuil cuid mhaith taistil déanta acu go raibh.  Más é sin is dóigh le daoine, ní moladh duinn é, agus más féidir é a leigheas, ba cheart é a dhéanamh.</P>
    <P>Ba cheart na rialacha a dhéanamh i bhfad níos righne le haghaidh aerphoirt phríobháideacha.  Chonnaic mé sampla le goirid d'eiteallán ag teacht anuas beagnach ar an mbóthar.  Chonaic mé capall dá scanrú agus is beag nár <Col N="607" /> chaith sé a raibh sa charr amach as agus is furasta a thuiscint céard d'fhéadfadh titim amach.  Tharla go raibh daoine ag taisteal i ngluaisteán; stopadar agus bhí siad mí-shásta faoin dóigh a d'iompar na daoine san eiteallán iad féin.  Tá fhios agam go bhfuil rialacha ann agus gur deacair rialcha a chur i bhfeidhm, ach tá sé an-tábhachtach agus ba cheart féachaint chuige.  Más gá, ba cheart go mbeadh na haerphoirt i bhfad isteach ón mbóthar mór.  Bíonn muid ag iarraidh go mbeadh siad in aice an bhóthair mhóir, ach má tá, is deacair d'eitealláin tuirlint gan teacht i ngaireacht don bhóthar mór agus níl leigheas ann ach na haerphoirt a chur isteach ón bpríomh-bhóthar ionas go mbeidh deis acu coinneáil sách ard os cionn an bhóthair agus teacht anuas ar an aerphort.</P>
    <P>B'fhéidir go mbeadh pointe nó dhó eile ann ar a dteastódh tuilleadh eolais uainn, ach beidh sé luath go leor nuair a bheas an Bille os ár gcomhair arís.  Tá mé lán-tsásta an Bille a bheith ann, agus chomh fada is a bhaineas sé linne, gheobhaidh an tAire é chómh luath agus is féidir linn é a thabhairt dó.</P>
    <P>
      <i>Business suspended at 6 p.m. and resumed at 7 p.m.</i>
    </P>
    <Speaker pid="LiamCosgrave" hpid="Parliamentary Secretary to the Minister for Industry and Commerce (Mr. Cosgrave) Liam Cosgrave">
      <NameTxt>Parliamentary Secretary to the Minister for Industry and Commerce (Mr. Cosgrave)</NameTxt>
      <P>A number of matters were covered in the course of this debate, but I think the details can be more appropriately discussed on Committee. Some Senators asked why there was no limit on the subsidy provision and said, in effect, that we were giving Aer Lingus a blank cheque or, rather, giving the air companies a blank cheque.  That is not so.  As Senator Douglas pointed out, in the annual Vote which will come before the Dáil, full opportunity will be provided for a discussion on the amount which it is proposed to provide by way of subsidy. The proposal in the Bill, which specifies no figure, is deemed desirable because it may transpire that in the course of the next few years it will be difficult to estimate exactly what subsidy <Col N="608" /> will be required.  The aim is to provide ultimately for a time when no subsidy will be necessary.  I am glad to say that the figures show that in recent years the tendency has been in that direction.  In 1946-47 the total loss incurred by Aer Lingus was £139,476; in 1947-48 it was £612,432, and in 1948-49 it was down to £162,850. This year the original estimate anticipated a loss of £125,000, but I hope, and the company anticipates, that it will be possible to have a lower charge for subsidy.  I think it is reasonable that no figure should be mentioned, in view of the fact that the Dáil will have ample opportunity on the annual Vote to discuss the proposed figure which will have to be provided for each year in the Estimate.  Senator Hawkins also asked what had happened between the end of March, 1948, and the present time; how did the company exist, and what was its financial position.  He wondered how the company had survived without subsidy payment.  The explanation is quite simple.  The company had a number of aircraft, both Vikings and Constellations, which were disposed of and the money received was available for payment in respect of charges which the company was liable for.  There is now owed to the company in respect of subsidy something over £400,000, which has been provided for in the Estimate.</P>
      <P>Senator J.T. O'Farrell asked whether the company in its accounts provided for the ordinary depreciation and renewal charges which are customary in accounts.  The answer is &ldquo;yes&rdquo;. They provided fully for those, and all those charges are taken into consideration as well as a number of other items properly covered in the accounts on which the subsidy is estimated.  Two other matters engaged the attention of Senators, and I feel they are of importance and are more appropriate on the present Stage of the Bill than on the Committee Stage.  The first is the future position of Shannon and the second that of the transatlantic air service.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Shannon is, as Senators are aware, a modern fully-equipped airport.  The State has already expended large sums of money in providing there all services <Col N="609" /> which are necessary at such an airport, and in so far as the Government can ensure that traffic through Shannon, will continue at a high level, it is anxious to do so, but a number of Senators appear to have some misapprehension about the effect of the compulsory stop.  Under the agreement made in 1945, the United States has the right to ask for a revision of the terms of that agreement just as we felt we could also ask for a revision.  There is also a provision in the agreement which entitled either country, that is, the United States or Ireland, to denounce the agreement or to give notice that the agreement will terminate at the end of 12 months.</P>
    <P>Consequently, the United States' authorities, by virtue of the provisions of the agreement have, from time to time, put forward proposals for consideration which have been discussed on a number of occasions with a view to revising certain aspects of the agreement. I need hardly say that the Government is anxious to ensure that Shannon Airport should continue to get as large a share of traffic as possible, but in a matter of this kind the other party to the agreement has a right to ask for discussions with a view to revising the provisions of the agreement. Accordingly, when they asked for these discussions we were obliged to enter into discussions and I cannot, at this stage, say what the outcome will be, but it is only right that Senators should be aware that there is provision in the agreement for a revision and also provision for either party to terminate the agreement, provided they give a year's notice.</P>
    <P>The other matter about which there has been a great deal of discussion is the cessation of a transatlantic air service. I think there are few subjects on which there has been so much nonsense talked as the proposed transatlantic air service.  Senator J.T. O'Farrell said there was a great deal of sentiment about it.  That is perfectly true. He said it is a matter which should be considered as an economic or business arrangement, just as any other transport arrangement is considered.  I think that is equally true.  The proposed transatlantic air service had no <Col N="610" /> prospect in the foreseeable future of making money.  It may be that some people in the United States with Irish connections would have liked to travel on an Irish air service, but leaving that consideration out of it there is no evidence from any reliable source that it would have provided a dollar-earning potential of any dimensions, particularly when we realise that other transatlantic companies have so far failed to operate at a profit, and if conditions had so developed that these companies were operating at a profit or that they could not deal with the demand for accommodation across the Atlantic, then it would be reasonable to assume that an Irish transatlantic air service would make a profit, but in the absence of any such evidence&mdash;in fact, the evidence being all the other way &mdash;that all these companies are in receipt of heavy subsidies by means of air-mail contracts&mdash;the Government decided that the country could not afford the luxury of a transatlantic air service.</P>
    <P>That does not in any way take away from the present efficient air service provided by Aer Lingus, or lessen in any way the Government's high appreciation of the standard which that company has attained as well as the efficiency and safety record that it has secured, not merely a reputation in this country but a reputation among passengers who have come here from abroad.  I am glad to join with Senators in expressing my appreciation and the appreciation of the Government for the manner in which Aer Lingus services are carried on, but to compare the potentialities of the cross-Channel or the internal services with the proposed transatlantic service is to refuse to face realities.  In fact, up to the present, with the possible exception of one rather exceptional year, Aer Lingus has not operated at a profit and I think in a matter of this kind, where we have witnessed remarkable aeronautical developments in the last quarter of a century, or even since the outbreak of war in 1939, it is reasonable that a small country such as this should proceed with some caution as well as some regard for the responsibility which the Government and the Oireachtas owe to the taxpayers.  Consequently, <Col N="611" /> there is no proposal at present to start, and it is unlikely that in the future this Government will contemplate starting, a transatlantic air service.</P>
    <P>In connection with the personnel of Aer Lingus who may have had service in the past with the British Air Force, I think it only right to point out that Aer Lingus is partly an Irish and partly a British company.  The proportion of shares is 60/40, 60 per cent. being held by this country and 40 per cent. by Britain.  It is also true to say that we have had the benefit of a number of technical experts whose services at a particular time could not be done without, and to whose work I should like to pay tribute.  In a matter of this kind, we must appreciate that, while we have our rights and our interests, the other party has similar interests and responsibilities.  There is no danger that services will suffer in the event of hostilities and it is not correct to say that these people are non-nationals. There may be a few who are not nationals, but most of the personnel are nationals.  Some of them in the past served with the Royal Air Force, but in so far as it has been possible for the company, they have recruited personnel who were trained here in the Irish Air Corps; but, as Senators are aware, the strength of the Air Corps is such that it does not readily offer a reservoir from which we can draw personnel for the civil air services.  I should say with regard to the objections which Senator Hawkins and others mentioned concerning Aer Lingus personnel that the same objections might with equal validity have been made when the arrangement was made in 1947.  The company, under its present 60/40 Irish-British share-holding, was established in 1947 and I do not recollect that there was any criticism then of the fact that some of the personnel had in the past served with the Royal Air Force or that any objection was taken to it.</P>
    <P>A number of Senators, and Senator Stanford in particular, raised questions about the acquisition of land and suggested that it seemed nowadays that the State was taking more and more power to acquire property.  I suppose <Col N="612" /> it is partly true that various Government Departments from time to time acquire property and the Senator instanced the fact that local authorities acquire property for housing.  It is only right to point out, however, that it is in the interest of the community that local authorities should have such power to provide for cases in which they cannot secure land by agreement. Compensation is paid in these cases and it may be that the person whose land is acquired does not regard the compensation as adequate, but anyone who studies the history of this country will recollect that, in the past, instead of the State acquiring property, the landlords acquired it, and the compensation then, if any, was far less adequate than the compensation paid at present.</P>
    <P>There is rather stringent power in the Bill for the acquisition of land in certain circumstances, but, as I mentioned in my opening remarks, it is only where the provisions of some international agreement require immediate action that these powers would be used.  It is not the intention to abuse the power and it has not been abused in the past.  Land adjoining aerodromes may have to be acquired at short notice.  Acquisition proceedings take some time and delay occurs, and often not merely is it a matter of providing for efficiency but safety considerations enter into it and it is, therefore, deemed desirable to have these powers.  Some of the powers in this Bill are already contained in the earlier Acts, but in certain details amendment was necessary and it is only because some of the provisions of the earlier Acts require amendment that further powers are included in this measure.  As Senator Honan said, most of the matters dealt with were already provided for in the earlier Acts, but usage has shown that amendment was necessary.</P>
    <P>Senators also raised some minor matters which might perhaps be dealt with now rather than on Committee Stage.  One of these was the charge for the transport of passengers between O'Connell Street and Collinstown.  The 1/- charged for that journey is necessary, because Córas Iompair Éireann provides special buses, and, in fact, the <Col N="613" /> provision of the buses costs Aer Lingus more than 1/-.  Some airports in Europe make no charge, but it is not true to say that this is the only country in which a charge is made.  In America the charge from the city to an airport is usually a dollar, and in Britain some of the companies are anxious that a charge be made.  I suppose people object to it because it seems an addition to the fare.  I understood at one time that it was included in the fare paid by the passenger, but the losses of Córas Iompair Éireann are sufficiently high without asking them to bear the burden of carrying passengers between O'Connell Street and Collinstown.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOFarrell" hpid="Mr. J.T. O'Farrell Mr. J.T. O'Farrell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J.T. O'Farrell</NameTxt>
      <P>Add it on to the fare.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LiamCosgrave" hpid="Mr. Cosgrave Mr. Cosgrave">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cosgrave</NameTxt>
      <P>That is a suggestion worth examining.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelColgan" hpid="Mr. Colgan Mr. Colgan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Colgan</NameTxt>
      <P>You could add half-a-crown and get away with it, whereas you are only getting a shilling.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LiamCosgrave" hpid="Mr. Cosgrave Mr. Cosgrave">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cosgrave</NameTxt>
      <P>Another point relating to charges was raised by Senator Ó Buachalla in connection with the hostels at Shannon.  These hostels are made available so that accommodation can be provided for passengers who, for weather or other unexpected causes, are obliged to stay overnight, and, while the charge may seem excessive, staff have to be available whether the hostels are used or not and the same charge is payable by either Irish persons or persons who arrive there and who are detained because of the delays incidental to transatlantic air travel, due to weather conditions.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>Committee Stage ordered for Wednesday, March 15th.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Limerick Gas" RHead="Order&mdash;Motion">
    <Title>Limerick Gas Order&mdash;Motion.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Mr. M. Hayes Mr. M. Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Mr. M. Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>I move:&mdash;</P>
      <P>That the Limerick Gas Order, 1950, proposed to be made by the Minister for Industry and Commerce and laid in draft before Seanad Éireann on the 1st day of March, 1950, under subsection (4) of Section 10 of the Gas Regulation Act, 1920, be approved.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="614" />
    <Speaker pid="LiamCosgrave" hpid="Parliamentary Secretary to the Minister for Industry and Commerce (Mr. Cosgrave) Liam Cosgrave">
      <NameTxt>Parliamentary Secretary to the Minister for Industry and Commerce (Mr. Cosgrave)</NameTxt>
      <P>The Limerick Corporation have made an application to the Minister for Industry and Commerce under Section 10 of the Gas Regulation Act, 1920, and the Gas Regulation (Special Orders) Rules, 1940, for a Special Order to provide new plant and equipment as and when the need arises, with a view to the eventual replacement of the old works by a new installation on another site, and for this purpose to secure power to borrow a sum not exceeding £500,000; to extend the limits of supply of the undertaking from the present Borough of Limerick to the Borough of Limerick for the time being, together with such portions of the public health districts of Limerick and Clare not more than one mile from the city boundary; and for the modification of existing Acts and Orders.</P>
      <P>Borrowing powers will be exercised only with the consent of the Minister for Local Government and will be subject to the provisions of the Local Government (Sanitary Services) Acts, 1878 to 1948, in relation to borrowing by a sanitary authority.  The Minister for Local Government has already approved of the installation of auxiliary plant comprising 36 horizontal retorts, together with ancillary equipment and to the reconstruction of the existing ten vertical retorts.  These proposals are estimated to cost £75,750.  The work will commence shortly and when completed will result in an increase of gas output from 400,000 to over 1,000,000 cubic feet daily.  An increase in output of this magnitude will render increased gas storage space essential.  It is proposed, accordingly, to erect a new gas-holder of a minimum capacity of 1,250,000 cubic feet on the new site at Corkanree.  The holder will cost about £70,000.  The comprehensive plan which includes the new holder envisages the eventual erection on the Corkanree site of a new gasworks with a capacity of 2,000,000 cubic feet per day and the expenditure of a total of £500,000, which covers: general development; carbonising plant, including coal and coke handling plant, waste heat boilers etc.; ancillary plant; gas holders; gas mains, district governors, compressors, etc.; and consumers' meters and appliances.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="615" /> This expenditure will necessitate an extension of the existing borrowing powers of the corporation.  As these powers are subject to the consent of the Minister for Local Government, an inquiry was recently held, by Order of the Minister, in Limerick into the application for power to raise £500,000. The case for a development of this magnitude was made at the inquiry directed to be held by the Minister for Local Government.  It was emphasised by the Limerick City Manager that the proposed extensions would be gradual, and that each step would be preceded by a proved increase in demand; and it will be necessary for the corporation to obtain the specific approval of the Minister for Local Government to each work or installation included in the total figure of £500,000.</P>
    <P>The Order also provides that the revenues received from the gas undertaking shall be paid into the Municipal Fund, and that the expenses incurred by the corporation in production and management of the undertaking shall be defrayed from the Municipal Fund, subject to the condition that, as far as possible, the establishment charges in any year shall be defrayed out of revenue for that year.  For the purpose of meeting any deficiency in the income of the undertaking or any extraordinary claim or demand made on the undertaking, it is proposed to establish and maintain a reserve fund amounting to £100,000.</P>
    <P>The existing limit of supply is the present Borough of Limerick, and it is proposed to extend this limit of supply to the Borough of Limerick for the time being, together with those portions of the county health districts of Limerick and Clare for a mile from the boundary of Limerick for the time being.  Power is also sought to provide and maintain dwellings for persons employed in the undertaking, as well as offices, showrooms and similar accommodation.  The corporation also seek to secure power to refuse a supply of gas other than gas used for lighting or domestic use where, in the opinion of the corporation, the supply of such gas would interfere with a sufficiency of gas for lighting or domestic purposes. <Col N="616" /> Authority is also sought to purchase, take or lease land not exceeding 21 acres.</P>
    <P>The draft Order seeks to repeal Sections 22 and 23 of the Limerick Gas Act, 1878, and Section 40 of the same Act, as amended by Section 2 of the Limerick Gas Order, 1918.  Section 22 of the Limerick Gas Act, 1878, empowers the corporation to maintain the existing gasworks at that time, while Section 23 limited the storage and manufacture of gas to certain lands mentioned in the Schedule of that Act.  Section 40, as amended by the Limerick Gas Order, 1918, dealt with the revenues of the company and the establishment and maintenance of a reserve fund.</P>
    <P>The Gas Regulation Act, 1920, altered the old and cumbersome procedure whereby statutory gas undertakers were obliged to secure their powers by way of Private Act, or a provisional Order confirmed by a special Act of Parliament, and provided instead that powers or additional powers could be procured by a special Order approved by a resolution of both Houses.  The procedure, as laid down in the Gas Regulation (Special Orders) Rules, 1940, requires that the draft Order be prepared by the gas undertaking, and that full publicity of the intention to apply for the Order, and of the contents of the draft, be given by notices in <i>Iris Oifigiúil</i> and in local newspapers.  Notification must also be given to the State, and to private interests involved, one month being allowed for the lodging of objections. Subsequent stages are dealt with in accordance with the Gas Regulation Act, 1920.  If there are objections, an inquiry may be held, and after considering the report of the person who held the inquiry, the Minister may modify the draft before submission to the Oireachtas, or he may decline to submit the draft.  When the draft Order was published in accordance with the rules, no objections were made by interested parties, and under these circumstances, no inquiry by an officer of my Department was necessary.  The Minister for Local Government, as a result of the inquiry held by his officer relative to the proposed borrowing <Col N="617" /> powers, is prepared to give his consent to the proposed borrowing.</P>
    <P>The necessary resolution of approval has been passed by the Dáil, and I now submit the draft Order for the approval of the Seanad.</P>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamStanford" hpid="Professor Stanford Professor Stanford">
      <NameTxt>Professor Stanford</NameTxt>
      <P>May I ask the Parliamentary Secretary whether there is any power granted for the compulsory acquisition of lands or entry on to lands in this?  When I spoke earlier this evening on the rights of property owners, I was not thinking of the rich nobleman in his castle or the ancient planter in Tipperary or Fermanagh.  I was thinking of a small cottage in the Upper Liffey Valley, a cottage of decent people, a cottage which is now engulfed in a reservoir.  I was thinking of small suburban villas which have had their front or back gardens cut down to make way for roads.  The Parliamentary Secretary was mistaken in thinking I was representing simply the landlord class, when speaking earlier.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LiamOBuachalla" hpid="Liam Ó Buachalla Liam Ó Buachalla">
      <NameTxt>Liam Ó Buachalla</NameTxt>
      <P>Níor theastuigh uaim ach a rá go bhfuilimíd ar an taobh seo den tSeanaid lán tsásta an tOrdú seo a thabhairt don Rúnaí Parlaiminte. We agree that this issue be disposed of and we wish Limerick the best of luck in their venture.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LiamCosgrave" hpid="Mr. Cosgrave Mr. Cosgrave">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cosgrave</NameTxt>
      <P>I hope Senator Stanford did not misunderstand me.  I appreciated his interest in both big and small; but in the past, the difference was that people acquired land without paying any compensation, whereas now compensation is paid, whether it is adequate or not.  There is power taken in this to purchase, take or lease lands not exceeding 21 acres.</P>
      <P>Motion agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Mr. M. Hayes Mr. M. Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Mr. M. Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>I understand that it is proposed to take the motion in the name of Senator R.M. Burke, the amendment in the name of Senator Martin O'Dwyer, and the motion in the name of Senator Counihan together as they concern very much the same thing except that the word &ldquo;co-operative&rdquo; occurs in No. 10 and not in No. 11. I take it that that will be agreed. Senator Counihan agrees.</P>
      <P>Agreed.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Co-operative and Experimental" RHead="Farms&mdash;Motions">
    <Title>Co-operative and Experimental Farms&mdash;Motions.</Title>
    <Col N="618" />
    <Speaker pid="RobertBurke" hpid="Mr. R.M. Burke Mr. R.M. Burke">
      <NameTxt>Mr. R.M. Burke</NameTxt>
      <P>In the names of Senator Tunney, Senator McCrea and in my own name I move:&mdash;</P>
      <P>That in the opinion of Seanad Éireann the Government should encourage and facilitate the establishment of a small number of co-operative farms, or co-operative farm units as an experiment, with a view to the extension of either or both of these systems of farming if found to be satisfactory.</P>
      <P>I would like to make clear that I am not suggesting that there is only one system of agricultural co-operation.  I believe there are several systems of co-operative farming which could reasonably be varied according to the sizes and types of farms and in accordance with the wishes of the persons concerned, but I believe that there is a great deal to be said for some system of co-operation in agriculture.  Senators will notice that I mention, in particular, in addition to co-operative farms, the &ldquo;co-operative farm unit&rdquo; system. I should mention that this system was, I believe, first suggested in 1943 by Senator Orpen, who has spoken and written a good deal on this subject.  It is one system of co-operative farming. I do not intend to go into any detail in regard to that because Senator Orpen is here, and I will leave it to him, the originator of that system, to explain it in detail to the Seanad.</P>
      <P>It is desirable at the outset briefly to explain the reasons why I think it would be desirable for the Government to encourage this system.  One reason, which I mentioned in the motion, was that the system might be extended if found to be satisfactory.  There are two other very important reasons.  One is that some of these farms might be used for experimental and demonstration purposes, and the other is that they could be used for the improvement of agricultural methods in general.  Those two reasons are also mentioned, one by Senator Martin O'Dwyer and the other by Senator Counihan.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I would like to make clear that I am entirely in favour of Senator <Col N="619" /> Martin O'Dwyer's suggestion that some co-operative farms or co-operative farm units could be used for experimental and demonstration purposes, with a view to the improvement of agricultural methods in general.  I am also in agreement with Senator Counihan's suggestion that there should be more experimental farms in different parts of the country for the information and guidance of persons engaged in the farming industry, in addition to those already in existence.</P>
    <P>On all these points I think we are in agreement, but I believe, in addition, that there is a possibility that this system might be found so satisfactory that it could be extended considerably throughout the country for the welfare of farmers generally, in addition to being used for experimental and demonstration purposes.</P>
    <P>I am not suggesting for a moment that this proposal is the only important one, in regard to the improvement of agriculture.  Some time ago I proposed a motion which I regarded as more urgent with regard to long term loans for the improvement of land and buildings, and I am glad that some of the suggestions made in that motion are being implemented.</P>
    <P>I should now mention briefly some of the advantages which I think would accrue from this system.  I intend to refer to them under five main headings. The first is: I believe it would bring about an increased output of food per acre and greater efficiency, for several reasons.  First, many very small farms are so limited in acreage that it is very difficult for the farmers to pursue a correct rotation of crops.</P>
    <P>In County Galway, where I come from, it is continually urged, and rightly so, that farmers should grow more sugar beet.  There is a danger of the Tuam sugar factory being closed down unless more beet is grown. Yet, many farmers with very small holdings find it difficult to grow more sugar beet because it cannot be grown year after year on the same land.  If several small farms could be worked in co-operation there could be a greater variety of crops, greater rotation of crops, and more sugar beet, wheat and other crops could be grown.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="620" /> The second advantage is that it would bring about increased output per man-hour.  I think everybody is agreed that the output per man-hour from farms in this country is low, compared with farms in many other countries.  One of the reasons for that is that on these very small farms the farmers have not sufficient machinery, and more machinery could be obtained and could be more efficiently used if there was more co-operation.</P>
    <P>The third advantage is that if we had more co-operation and more people working together for the common good, it would be encouraging to all concerned.  When an individual small farmer is working absolutely on his own it may be an embarrassment to him when he is sick, and has to depend on the help of neighbours.  If a number were co-operating, the illness of one member of the group would not be so serious, because the others would automatically carry on the work.  Also, from a moral point of view, it is desirable that people should be encouraged to work together in co-operation, instead of being too individualistic.  It is in accordance with Christian principles that people should be encouraged to work together for the common good and to help each other.</P>
    <P>I should also emphasise that I am not suggesting for one moment that there should be compulsion, that people should be compelled or forced to co-operate, if they do not wish to do so.  Some persons would prefer a small individual farm.  Some persons, even if it meant a lower standard of living, even if it meant longer hours of work, would probably prefer to work on their own and, if they wish to do so, I am not suggesting that they should be compelled to do otherwise. But those who would like to work together in co-operation, should be helped and encouraged to do so.</P>
    <P>A fourth advantage is that any profits made could be shared between the cooperators so that they would all benefit by any improvements brought about. Conversely any unavoidable loss would be shared, and I think that is a very good thing, because no matter how careful people are, as we all know, <Col N="621" /> occasionally an animal may die even if it gets the best of attention.  If a small farmer loses a cow the loss to him is very heavy, but if this loss is divided between three, four, five or six the hardship per head or per family would not be so great.</P>
    <P>A fifth advantage of a co-operative farm, where the workers all work together for the common good over a farm owned by one man who merely employs men at a fixed rate of wages, is that there would be greater contentment amongst the workers, if they felt that the harder they worked the better off they would all be when the profits were shared, for in addition to a fixed minimum wage, they would look forward to some little extra at the end of the year, after the net profits had been calculated.</P>
    <P>I have mentioned the five advantages which, I believe, would accrue from this system, but some people might say: &ldquo;That is all very well in theory, but how would it work out in practice?&rdquo; I would like, therefore, to make clear that I am not speaking on this subject simply from theory.  One reason why I am convinced that there is a lot to be said for this system, is that I have had practical experience of it.  I have worked on a co-operative farm, and I think it is the only one in Ireland to be worked continuously on this system for almost 17 years.  We started this system almost 17 years ago in County Galway on a farm of about 250 statute acres, including some timber and bog, which gave full-time employment to seven men, and while we have had our ups and downs and our difficulties, I can say, after those 16½ years, that the system has worked quite well.  The workers all receive a fixed minimum wage and also a share of the profits in the form of a bonus half-yearly or yearly.  I found that since the system started the workers gradually took more and more interest in their work, because they felt that every one of them had a personal interest in it, and that it was up to each one of them to do his best.  The harder and the more efficiently they worked, the better the output, and the better it would be for themselves, and their fellow-workers. Under that system there is also a tendency for every man, not only to work <Col N="622" /> efficiently himself, but to encourage his fellow-workers to work efficiently also, for if his fellow-worker does not do his work right the whole group will suffer.</P>
    <P>Another advantage of the system is that it is a very democratic system. On the farm which we have worked under this system, everything is settled by majority vote, and the workers accept the majority ruling.  We have a full meeting once a month or oftener if necessary, to discuss all the working of the farm.  Subject to the amount of money which is available, it is left to the workers to decide the rate of wages, hours of work and conditions of employment.</P>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. Hayes Mr. Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>All by a free vote?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RobertBurke" hpid="Mr. R.M. Burke Mr. R.M. Burke">
      <NameTxt>Mr. R.M. Burke</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes.  All by a free vote.  The workers are sensible enough to realise that if they drew out too much in wages the concern would soon go bankrupt, so they always keep a reasonable amount in reserve.  On our farm we have paid a wage slightly above the Agricultural Wages Board minimum wage, and, in addition, we have been able to give out bonuses every year, which have varied from year to year.  They have improved considerably during the past two years, but there was a time when the bonuses were extremely small.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnCounihan" hpid="Mr. Counihan Mr. Counihan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Counihan</NameTxt>
      <P>How much was it last year?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RobertBurke" hpid="Mr. R.M. Burke Mr. R.M. Burke">
      <NameTxt>Mr. R.M. Burke</NameTxt>
      <P>After paying wages 4/- per week higher than the agricultural rate, it was £10 10s. 0d. per man for seven men.  The earnings of each man was, therefore, 8/- per week higher than the agricultural rate which, in County Galway, is about 1/2 an hour.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>With regard to hours, in mid-winter they work a 45-hour week, that is in December and January when the days are short, apart from Sunday work. For the remainder of the winter they work a 48-hour week, and in summer 49½ hours.  They decided of their own free will, by a majority vote, to work a six-day week in winter, and a five and a half-day week in summer, five days at nine hours a day and one at four and a half hours a day.  But <Col N="623" /> in hours the six days in winter are shorter than the five and a half in summer.  When we were debating the question of half holidays some time ago in the Seanad, some Senators mentioned the difficulties.  We recognise that a farm being different from an industry, cannot be closed down.  Somebody must do the necessary work, but so long as there is goodwill and co-operation the half-holiday system works satisfactorily.  Some take the half holiday on Saturday and some on Thursday, for obviously they cannot all take it on the same day, as men have to be there to milk the cows and other essential work.  Similarly, the work that has to be done on Sundays is taken in turn, and shared.</P>
    <P>I mentioned that when the animals were jointly owned one advantage was that if an animal died the loss was shared all round, and did not fall on one man, but I should like to emphasise that this does not mean that every animal must be jointly owned.  On our farm each man, in addition to having a share in the jointly-owned animals, has some animals of his own.  Each man has private ownership of his house and of some animals and a small amount of land which he works at his own discretion.  Some of the land is worked jointly and some is worked individually and I see nothing inconsistent in that.  With regard to individual owners working co-operatively in economic units, I think Senator Orpen will deal with that matter under his economic farm unit system.</P>
    <P>Another advantage of co-operative ownership of live stock is that some small farmers often hesitate to employ a veterinary surgeon because the fee might seem rather large to them, but when there is a co-operative group the fee of the veterinary surgeon, like everything else, is shared and does not fall heavily on one man.  On our farm we believe in utilising to the full the help that is given by the veterinary surgeon, and very often he can save the lives of animals.  We are also very glad to avail of the advice of the agricultural instructors of the Department.</P>
    <P>I would now like to suggest how such co-operative farms might be established. <Col N="624" /> I believe that one way in which it could be done, would be for the Land Commission, when they do take over some large estate or farm, to let it on reasonable terms to a group who would be enthusiastic about working it co-operatively.  I am informed that there was a group in Westmeath some years ago who wanted to do that, but who could not get the land to do it. I suggest that the Land Commission should purchase some estate when it comes on the market, or utilise some estate which they would be taking over, in any case, and, instead of dividing it up into a number of small holdings, that they should carry out the experiment of allowing an enthusiastic group work it on the co-operative system. Another experiment would be to try to find some farmers living near one another who would be willing to co-operate. I quite agree that that might be difficult, because while we may find a number scattered about the country who are willing to co-operate, we might not easily find two or three living next door to each other who would be very keen on co-operation.  If, however, a group was to take over a farm or estate, one of the things they would probably need would be capital to work it.  It is quite probable that men who would like to work on that system might not have sufficient capital.  I think, therefore, to make the scheme a success, a sufficient amount of capital should be advanced to them on reasonable terms.</P>
    <P>With regard to the economic farm unit system, I should mention, in addition to the fact that the idea was originated by Senator Orpen, that it is an idea that appeals to a good many people.  Just to mention one example, ex-Senator Professor Joseph Johnston is a believer in the system also, and read a paper to the Statistical and Social Inquiry Society of Ireland recently on that subject.  A number of people, in fact, are interested in this system, and I think it deserves serious consideration.  I think that all Parties in the House are unanimous that we should try to increase food production in this country, that we should try to increase agricultural output, and that we should try to get a better output per man-hour and, therefore, I think <Col N="625" /> we should leave no stone unturned to achieve that aim.  We ought to be willing to try any system which might bring about these desirable results.  I put this motion, therefore, before you, and I believe that to encourage and facilitate&mdash;I do not say to compel&mdash;to encourage and facilitate the establishment of a small number of co-operative farms and farm units would be a very desirable experiment.  The cost would not be great, and I am hopeful that the advantages which I have mentioned would far more than justify the initial outlay.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JamesTunney" hpid="Mr. Tunney Mr. Tunney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Tunney</NameTxt>
      <P>I wish formally to second the motion, and I reserve the right to speak afterwards.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MartinODwyer" hpid="Mr. O'Dwyer Mr. O'Dwyer">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Dwyer</NameTxt>
      <P>I move:&mdash;</P>
      <P>To delete all words after the word &ldquo;farms&rdquo; and substitute the following words: &ldquo;For experimental and demonstration purposes with a view to the improvement of agricultural methods in general.&rdquo;</P>
      <P>I listened very attentively to Senator Burke's statement.  I quite agree with his sincerity and I appreciate the interest he takes in agriculture, generally, and what is done in the locality, but the House will notice the words of the motion, that is:&mdash;</P>
      <P>&ldquo;That the Government should encourage and facilitate the establishment of a small number of co-operative farms or co-operative farm units as an experiment with a view to the extension of either or both of these systems of farming if found to be satisfactory.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>In the amendment I put down it should read: &ldquo;Establish these farms for experimental and demonstration purposes with a view to the improvement of agricultural methods in general&rdquo;. That is where the difference between the two arises, as the House will observe.  Senator Burke visualises a general extension of the co-operative method of farming in general, and that is where the objection comes in. Senator Burke has not explained how this method of co-operative farming can be extended to cover the small holdings, to include small holdings.  As <Col N="626" /> we know, the whole basis of agriculture in this country rests on private ownership, on peasant proprietorship as it was called.  In fact, only for that private ownership, the ownership of small farms, and the love of the land ingrained in the Irish people, it would have been impossible to retain the human element at all during the periods that have passed.  We must not forget that.  As regards co-operative farms, these co-operative farms, farms attached to co-operative societies are actually in operation in several places in the South.  Co-operative dairy societies have purchased farms with a view to experimenting on various phases of agriculture.  In one place they are experimenting on dairy cattle, in another place they are experimenting on milking machines to see if it would be possible to have them replace hand milking.  In other places they have experimented with pig feeding and various things for the benefit of their suppliers on the local farms without any intention of extending it beyond the actual farm.  It is suggested that this should be encouraged, but when I think over it, I do not see exactly what encouragement the Government can give, because these societies, if they have initiative enough to purchase these farms, will not require any Government assistance, and they have not asked for it.</P>
    <P>Therefore, I think, I would rather agree with Senator Counihan's amendment that the Government should set up a small number of farms under the guidance of the Department of Agriculture with a view to testing out in the locality the different problems associated with agriculture in that locality. I, therefore, withdraw my own amendment in favour of Senator Counihan's in that respect.  To come back to the principal motion, the objection that would be taken to it is that it seems to aim at the elimination of private ownership in land and, thereby, in these small holdings.  On that ground, I think we should take a firm stand against anything which would tend to eliminate private ownership in land.  It may be, that in time to come, owing to the development of machinery, to a decrease of population, and a change in <Col N="627" /> the way of living, farms may tend to become larger.  We cannot help that, but it is our duty to maintain the present system as long as ever it can possibly be maintained for the general good of the country.</P>
    <P>Senator Burke has pointed out the difficulty of working small farms on account of the small acreage, the difficulty of providing machinery, raising cattle and all that.  Well, as far as I can see, with a reasonable co-operative spirit the difficulty of these small farms can be overcome.  During the recent emergency co-operative creameries in the South got in machinery which tilled the land for all their farmers, and especially the farmers who had no machinery of their own.  They provided everything that the co-operative system could provide, and the small farmer was enabled to till his land as effectively as the man who had machinery of his own.</P>
    <P>I believe that system could be developed and that the provision of agricultural machinery would make it easier to work the land, particularly on small farms, than is at present the case.  It also enables production per acre to be increased.  It is quite possible, of course, that the Land Commission could set aside an area and work through a co-operative society such as Senator Burke describes.  No doubt, it would be a great thing to overcome the disadvantage which the small farmer suffers through not having machinery.  I do not think that the type of farm which is suggested in the motion would be suitable in this country.  It may come in the near future, but it is our duty now to keep it back as far as we possibly can.  In the meantime, by the development of co-operation, each farmer would be able to maintain his own way of life, and his ownership of his own land, the small farmers combining together, while retaining the system of private ownership with great benefit to the country.</P>
    <Speaker pid="TimothyJosephODonova" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator Counihan's motion is to come before you.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFirmullaghOReilly" hpid="Mr. Patrick O'Reilly Mr. Patrick O'Reilly">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Patrick O'Reilly</NameTxt>
      <P>Before the debate proceeds, I would like to ask a <Col N="628" /> question, if I might, of Senator Burke, for the information of the House.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TimothyJosephODonova" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>It is not a point of order.  You can put your question later.  I am calling on Senator Counihan.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnCounihan" hpid="Mr. Counihan Mr. Counihan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Counihan</NameTxt>
      <P>I move:&mdash;</P>
      <P>That in the opinion of Seanad Éireann the Government should set up and operate a small number of experimental farms in different parts of the country for the information and guidance of persons engaged in the farming industry.</P>
      <P>This motion was originally put down as an amendment to Senator Burke's motion, but it is now being moved as an independent motion.  My object in tabling is was to urge on the Government that if any money or facilities were given for experimental purposes, those experiments should be carried out by the Department of Agriculture under one of their experts, otherwise the experiment would be useless.  If my motion is adopted, I believe it would give a true picture of the position of agriculture in this country.  It would help to put a stop to the gross and misinformed statements about the enormous profits made by the farmers and about the miserable wages paid to the agricultural workers.</P>
      <P>I am sure the result will prove that 50 per cent. of the farmers of this country have a less return for their work than is paid to an agricultural worker for the same number of hours. Of course, it has been proved on many occasions that farmers are not getting the same remuneration for the amount of the work they do as is paid to an agricultural worker at present, but it has been proved by two experts in Roscommon and in parts of Cork and Limerick that the amount of profits which the farmers got was in no sense compensation for the amount of work they put into their farms and the number of hours they worked.  Of course, the Minister does not believe that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Minister for Agriculture (Mr. Dillon) James M. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Agriculture (Mr. Dillon)</NameTxt>
      <P>Tá an ceart agat!</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFrancisBaxter" hpid="Mr. Baxter Mr. Baxter">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Baxter</NameTxt>
      <P>That was before the Minister's time.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="629" />
    <Speaker pid="JohnCounihan" hpid="Mr. Counihan Mr. Counihan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Counihan</NameTxt>
      <P>There is no use in anyone trying to throw dust in the farmers' eyes.  I am sure that Senator Burke did not salt his accounts.  He has told us that after paying seven men and a managing director on a farm of 250 acres, the whole amount left over, after paying the agricultural wage, was £10 a man for the year, which amounted to 4/- a week each when it was divided between the eight farmers employed by Senator Burke.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOFarrell" hpid="Mr. J.T. O'Farrell Mr. J.T. O'Farrell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J.T. O'Farrell</NameTxt>
      <P>£10 more.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnCounihan" hpid="Mr. Counihan Mr. Counihan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Counihan</NameTxt>
      <P>That statement was made by the Senator here and it was made further.  It was repeated to an English Sunday paper and the same paper published his belief that it was a great record to pay a little over the agricultural wage and have £10 per man per year on a 250 acre farm.  If that is all the hope he is able to hold out for co-operation, I do not know what to say.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOFarrell" hpid="Mr. J.T. O'Farrell Mr. J.T. O'Farrell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J.T. O'Farrell</NameTxt>
      <P>He did not lose on it anyway.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnCounihan" hpid="Mr. Counihan Mr. Counihan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Counihan</NameTxt>
      <P>If he lost, it would be a very poor outlook for the agricultural worker and for the railway people whom the Senator sometimes prefers.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFrancisBaxter" hpid="Mr. Baxter Mr. Baxter">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Baxter</NameTxt>
      <P>They are different.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnCounihan" hpid="Mr. Counihan Mr. Counihan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Counihan</NameTxt>
      <P>There is another case which will probably shock the Minister and some of the Labour, perhaps I should say the Socialist representatives, in the House.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOFarrell" hpid="Mr. J.T. O'Farrell Mr. J.T. O'Farrell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J.T. O'Farrell</NameTxt>
      <P>Communists.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrederickHawkins" hpid="Mr. Hawkins Mr. Hawkins">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hawkins</NameTxt>
      <P>Be careful!</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnCounihan" hpid="Mr. Counihan Mr. Counihan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Counihan</NameTxt>
      <P>We believe there should be audited accounts of the Portrane Mental Hospital farm.  They employ about 60 agricultural workers there and get a certain amount of help free from some of the sane or semi-sane patients.  But even a gallon of milk on that farm was 3/-.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TimothyJosephODonova" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>It has nothing to do with the motion.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnCounihan" hpid="Mr. Counihan Mr. Counihan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Counihan</NameTxt>
      <P>Three shillings per gallon is the figure given in the audited accounts.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="630" />
    <Speaker pid="TimothyJosephODonova" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Portrane has nothing to do with the motion before the House.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnCounihan" hpid="Mr. Counihan Mr. Counihan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Counihan</NameTxt>
      <P>This is the motion I am discussing.  If the farms which I have proposed are set up, it will show the true picture of the position of agriculture in the country, and it will show that it is not in a very prosperous condition, much as the Minister and some of the other people talk about the high profits which we are making, and which is very disappointing, seeing that it is said that we do not pay our agricultural workers a reasonable wage.  I want to show that the farmers are paying agricultural workers as much as they can afford and more than they get themselves.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOFarrell" hpid="Mr. J.T. O'Farrell Mr. J.T. O'Farrell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J.T. O'Farrell</NameTxt>
      <P>Is this in order? I submit that it is entirely out of order. We are not discussing wages&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TimothyJosephODonova" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Or anything else. We are discussing experimental and co-operative farming, and everything else about farmers, but not wages or Portrane.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>May I respectfully submit that Senator Counihan's motion raises the issue of the merits of demonstration farms?  The Senator, in my respectful submission, is raising the question of how far demonstration farms demonstrate, and I will have to ask your indulgence to cover some of that ground when I am replying.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnCounihan" hpid="Mr. Counihan Mr. Counihan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Counihan</NameTxt>
      <P>Very well, if the Minister does not like it I will stop.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>On the contrary, Senator, I am defending you.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnCounihan" hpid="Mr. Counihan Mr. Counihan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Counihan</NameTxt>
      <P>Coming back to the motion, I think we are entitled to discuss these motions in a broad way.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TimothyJosephODonova" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnCounihan" hpid="Mr. Counihan Mr. Counihan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Counihan</NameTxt>
      <P>With regard to Senator M. O'Dwyer's amendment, there are a few people in this House who are co-operative mad and they jump at anything to which you apply the word &ldquo;co-operative&rdquo;.  I have a little experience, not very much, of co-operative activity and I can say that it is not <Col N="631" /> always successful.  In many cases, co-operative work is a very good thing but sometimes we can have too much of a good thing.  There is one case in that connection which the Minister will possibly know, the co-operative bacon factory in Castlebar.  That factory was being worked for the farmers and farmers' money was in it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TimothyJosephODonova" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>And not as a co-operative farm.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnCounihan" hpid="Mr. Counihan Mr. Counihan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Counihan</NameTxt>
      <P>It was worked on the co-operative system and it was worked until they lost every shilling, and they had to call in&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TimothyJosephODonova" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>It is not a farm, I must remind the Senator, and has nothing to do with collective farming. Perhaps the Senator will keep to the farms.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnCounihan" hpid="Mr. Counihan Mr. Counihan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Counihan</NameTxt>
      <P>I am blocked on every road.  I do not agree with Senator Burke's proposal with regard to co-operative farming, and one of the ideas I had in mind in putting down my motion was that it should be a counterblast to his motion, in which, in my view, there is neither sense nor meaning.  We have heard about the seven or eight men who were paid their £3 a week and about the £10 bonus, but how they can have a divide of a bonus on farming or know what it is going to pay until the year is up I cannot understand.  It cannot be done, because you do not know what return you will have from your crops or whether you will be able to reap them or save them at all.  In that job he says that Senator Orpen, his other farming expert, is going to wipe the floor with me for daring to oppose co-operative farming.  I have a great regard for Senator Burke.  He is a great idealist and one could almost put him down as a modern Abou Ben Adem.  I do not want to oppose his motion with any strong words and, as I am blocked in regard to the other matters, I propose to sit down.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeorgeCBennett" hpid="Mr. Bennett Mr. Bennett">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Bennett</NameTxt>
      <P>I formally second the motion, reserving the right to speak later.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="632" />
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Minister for Agriculture (Mr. Dillon) James M. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Agriculture (Mr. Dillon)</NameTxt>
      <P>I venture to trespass on the time of the Seanad at this stage of the debate because I think it is desirable to make quite clear the Government's view on the proposal enshrined in the motion proposed by Senator Burke and those associated with him.  Before dealing precisely with the terms of that motion, I beg leave to refer to motion No. 11 and, if I may, in affection, to its proposer, Senator Counihan.  It is the hallmark of a venerable Legislature to have among its legislators at least one revered figure who is regarded as the spokesman of two centuries ago. Whenever I hear my old and valued friend, Senator Counihan, speaking, I think of Colonel Saunderson of the British House of Commons and Viscount Chaplin of the British House of Lords.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Many years ago, these two old gentlemen slumbered in the smoke-room till they heard it whispered that a reference to Ireland had been made in either House of the British Parliament, whereupon they were to be seen at once steaming off at full speed in opposite directions, one to the Lords and the other to the Commons, to say that all Irish were cut-throats, that Ireland ought to be kept down and that were it not for the British occupation of Ireland, the Irish would have all killed one another long ago.  Whenever any question arises in this or the House below of raising agricultural wages, or in fact of making any movement forward, backwards, to the left or to the right in agriculture, I am always comforted by the spectacle of Senator Counihan moving into the fray to say that he greatly deplores that the workhouse on the road north from the City of Dublin has been closed because he seriously apprehends that every farmer in North County Dublin will shortly want a workhouse into which to retire. They are all dying of starvation, poverty and bankruptcy; they cannot pay anybody anything; and they do not make a profit on anything and never have, or, if they did, it was by mistake. But I am happy to note in that distinguished prop of Irish agriculture, Senator Counihan, than whom few men in this country have served agriculture <Col N="633" /> better, a prosperous, comfortable and richer man than most of us know.  Long may he remain so, because every penny he has he earned well, and, in earning it, I do not doubt, be stowed an ample share on those less industrious than he.</P>
    <P>I do not believe that Senator Counihan himself really believes in what his own motion advocates, but that, as he tells us, without much regard to what the motion meant, it was a general countermining operation against Senator Burke, with the aid of which he proposed to detonate a land mine under Senator Burke if that Senator got too frisky.  To suggest that we should establish experimental colleges and stations in this country, where we have Clonakilty, Athenry, Ballyhaise, Grange, Johnstown, the Albert Agricultural College, the Munster Institute and Brownsbarn&mdash;not to mention some others&mdash;is so frisky a piece of amnesia that I do not believe the Senator was really guilty of it.  He merely conveniently chose to ignore it.  If the Senator's motion is to be read as a request from him that the Department of Agriculture should set up demonstration farms operated by the inspectors of my Department, I can well imagine that, if ever I were betrayed into such a folly, the first farmer to come and lean over the gate and break his heart laughing at me would be Senator Counihan, and the first man to say with emphasis and effect that a demonstration farm run with the capital of the Treasury by a civil servant, in conditions which are not comparable with those obtaining in any commercial farm in Ireland, was perfectly useless, would be Senator Counihan.</P>
    <P>In so far as his demarche has discomfited Senator Burke and his colleagues, I am grateful to Senator Counihan for his countermining operations. I know he will excuse me from pursuing the content of his motion in its literal text any further, because I do not believe he meant a word of what the text said; and he can do his countermining quite effectively without any help from me.  That he has already demonstrated.</P>
    <P>Now, when I come to Senator Burke's proposal, let me say at once how stimulating <Col N="634" /> and good it is that we should have raised here or in the Dáil propositions of a new character for discussion, how grateful I am to Senator Burke for putting matters of this kind at issue, though I most profoundly and irreconcilably differ from him in the underlying philosophy and in the practical application of the idea which he has described.  A difference of opinion can be useful.  I want to differ as radically from Senator Burke as it is possible to differ from any man in regard to this proposal.  Most of us in this Oireachtas were reared in the atmosphere and tradition of the Land League.  The Land League was established in this country to ensure for our people the three F's&mdash;Fixity of Tenure, Freedom of Sale and Fair Rent.  In the course of the struggle to get these things, our people discovered that there could be no half measures, that you either owned your home or you did not own your home; and we made up our minds that our people would own their homes.</P>
    <P>As the Senator remembers quite as well as I do, our people found themselves confronted with what many people thought insuperable odds.  The odds were formidable, but not insuperable; and the only thing that gave our people the power to overcome the forces arraigned against them was not their wealth, not their armament, nothing but their resolution that, whatever the cost, they were going to own their homes.  I think they were right then; I think they are right now; and I would be sorely tempted to disown my son if he ever reneged on that principle. The right to own your own home is the foundation of the whole pattern of our rural life.  The idea of owning your own home on the tenant principle with a multitude of others, is, to me, utterly revolting I fully appreciate that Senator Burke does not envisage, and has not envisaged, the picture of eight separate families inhabiting one house.  He sees eight comfortable homes built all round the common farm.  But he will find very few people in Ireland who think of their homes as a house and no more. That is what so many people forget, when they compare what may be done <Col N="635" /> in a man's shop or in a man's factory or a man's workshop with what may be done upon his farm.  The difference is that every square inch of a farmer's farm is his home.  The manufacturer, the shopkeeper or the artisan keeps home as home and works in his place of business whence he comes home.</P>
    <P>For a farmer, his farm is the place whither he goes home.  It is nothing new, you know, this concept of communal farming.  Mr. Vandeleur tried it out in Clare 120 years ago and it worked for several years.  We will never know whether it would have gone on working or not, because it came to an end when Mr. Vandeleur, losing rather more money on the Derby than he ought to have, became insolvent and left the country and his estate was sold up.  It is being tried elsewhere as well.  I challenge any Senator to tell me of any place where it was tried and long survived, without the sanction of the prison or the gallows behind it.  Search the world for a single experiment of co-operative farming on the lines suggested by Senator Burke&mdash;and there have been many&mdash;which survived two generations without the shadow of a prison or a gallows to hold it together.  I know of none, and I do not think there ever will be one, because that kind of life, that kind of denial of individual responsibility, that implied rejection of a man's ultimate responsibility by his own efforts, unaided, to provide for the wife he has married and the family he has brought into the world, seems to me quite inconsistent with the natural law which ultimately controls the lives of us all.</P>
    <P>Senator Burke is so frank a man and so apparently honest a man that he has not hesitated to describe to us, with manifest veracity, his own precise experience in such an experiment in Galway.</P>
    <P>I heard the old familiar wolves giving tongue, thirsting for his blood.  It did not sound a great achievement&mdash; £3 a week, even perhaps £2 15s., plus a £10 annual bonus, from an area of land which would have given each of the men employed a 30-acre farm. Nobody within ten miles of the town <Col N="636" /> where I was born and raised has 30 acres of land.  Most of them have done pretty well on ten.  Those who have 30 come to Mass on Sundays in a rubber-tyred trap.  They will be coming in a baby Ford pretty soon.  Does the Senator think that £2 15s. a week plus an annual bonus of £10 is a distinguished economic achievement?</P>
    <Speaker pid="RobertBurke" hpid="Mr. R.M. Burke Mr. R.M. Burke">
      <NameTxt>Mr. R.M. Burke</NameTxt>
      <P>May I just say that the rate we pay is 5/- above the agricultural rate, plus £10 per annum, which would be 8/- a week above the agricultural rate?  May I mention that to make the matter clear?  I know it is not much.  A lot of the land is very poor.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>I want to say how genuinely indebted we are to the Senator for giving us the true facts.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOFarrell" hpid="Mr. J.T. O'Farrell Mr. J.T. O'Farrell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J.T. O'Farrell</NameTxt>
      <P>He is being turned down all round.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>As Senator O'Farrell interjects, little thanks he gets for doing it.  I think he gets the best thanks of all, that is, the respect of those who disagree with him.  He would not wish us to dissimulate assent to things from which we most vigorously dissent.  I do not think the Senator would wish us to forbear from adverse criticism of the result of his adventure, if we have adverse criticism to make.  I am putting it to him that, according to the criteria of the part of Ireland from which he and I come, if men have 30 acres of their own and a house, they would be disappointed, I think, with that return.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOFarrell" hpid="Mr. J.T. O'Farrell Mr. J.T. O'Farrell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J.T. O'Farrell</NameTxt>
      <P>Ask Senator Counihan.  They lose far more on it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>How valuable a testimonial for Senator O'Farrell is Senator Counihan.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOFarrell" hpid="Mr. J.T. O'Farrell Mr. J.T. O'Farrell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J.T. O'Farrell</NameTxt>
      <P>He represents the agricultural industry.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>Most nobly, but practical things are rarely noble.  The last thing anyone would say of Senator Counihan is that he is utilitarian and, in this context, he most emphatically is not. Senator Burke would justify co-operative <Col N="637" /> farms on several grounds.  The first is efficiency.  Why stop at co-operative farms?  If you have 200 acres with seven co-operators thereon, will not 1,000 acres with 35 co-operators be probably more efficient?  What is the point of maximum efficiency given the requisite mechanisation?  Does the Senator truly suggest that, from any point of view, it would be desirable to break up the land of Ireland into blocks designed only by the crude finger of efficiency?  It would make rural Ireland a pretty dreary place.  I think efficiency can be bought at too great a price.  If that is the price of efficiency, God grant that our people may be inefficient till the crack of doom.  I do not think it is the price of efficiency but, if it were, I would curse the day that we attained it.</P>
      <P>The second advantage he saw was the abolition of the inability to use farm machinery on a small holding.  Is he serious?  Does not the Senator agree with me that a modern tractor is usable on a field far smaller than any which was susceptible to cultivation with a horse and plough?  I have seen a Ferguson tractor plough and harrow a field up to the hedge, into which you could not have fitted the pair of horses and a plough tackled together, and make a very neat job of it.</P>
      <P>His third justification was that to work co-operatively for the common good is better than to work for one's own and that if one man be ill the other members of the co-operative will take up his share of the burden. Senator Burke must know as well as or better than I that neighbours in rural Ireland are not as distant from one another as that argument would imply. Has he ever known a small farmer's crop to go unsaved or a small farmer's beast to die for want of attention because the man of the house was ill? I do not think he has.  Certainly, in my part of the country, however poor, however hard pressed themselves, neighbours would never see a neighbour suffer for that reason, and I think, on reflection, Senator Burke will agree that that would be the rule in most parts of Ireland.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The next advantage he saw was the <Col N="638" /> sharing of profits and losses.  The sharing of profits, the Senator says, is a good thing, but think of the value of sharing the loss.  What am I supposed to do, a Chathaoirligh, when I am in full cry and there is a division in the Dáil?</P>
    <Speaker pid="LiamOBuachalla" hpid="Liam Ó Buachalla Liam Ó Buachalla">
      <NameTxt>Liam Ó Buachalla</NameTxt>
      <P>To facilitate the Minister, could we not allow him to go to his division and carry on the discussion in the meantime?</P>
      <P>Agreed.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeorgeCBennett" hpid="Mr. Bennett Mr. Bennett">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Bennett</NameTxt>
      <P>I am glad that the three Senators who have proposed the motions and the amendment have given us scope for a very interesting discussion. Candidly, I am opposed to all the motions, although I seconded Senator Counihan's motion for the purpose of putting him in order.  I was not quite clear as to what Senator Burke meant when he spoke to the motion in his name.  I could not really gather whether he meant that it was a co-operative farm or a profit-sharing farm.  He did not enunciate whether the farm was owned co-operatively or whether the farm just employed seven workers who were paid the ordinary wage and shared the profits afterwards. There is a difference between a co-operatively-owned and a profit-sharing farm.  While one might be opposed absolutely to a co-operatively-owned farm, there might be something to be said for profit sharing among workers.  I daresay that there are numerous employers in the country who pay their men an average wage and something more and at the end of the year, at Christmas perhaps, if they have had a good year, without any obligation whatsoever, they pass on bonuses and share the profits with their employees.  It is quite a common thing.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>With regard to experimental and demonstration purposes, I agree with the Minister that there are numerous farms in the country already under Government ægis where experiments are carried on and they are the proper place for experimentation.  It is after the experimental stage that the farmer becomes really interested.  If, by demonstration farm, it is meant that <Col N="639" /> the Minister should set up farms here and there all over the country to demonstrate some of the experiments which have been carried out and proved to the satisfaction of the Government, something might be said for it, but I am opposed to the idea of demonstration farms unless, with demonstration, you couple the word &ldquo;profit&rdquo;.  I believe that if it were possible to set up here and there, in every county, perhaps, a number of farms carried on by the Government&mdash;not as the Minister said by a civil servant, because I do not believe a civil servant is generally the proper man to run a farm, but one can easily envisage that it would be possible to get some Government nominee with actual knowledge of farming to run it on the lines the Department suggested &mdash; and if a balance sheet were issued at the end of the year's working showing a profit, then I daresay more farmers would follow the particular practice advocated by the Government through that means than through any other.  To arrange for experiments to be carried out and demonstrated afterwards on a farm run on extravagant lines without any regard to the cost will have no influence on intelligent farmers.  I am opposed to both propositions, but if one could have a farm set up to demonstrate new materials or experiments which were carried out, say, at Glasnevin, showing that such a farm could be worked at a profit, it would be all to the good.</P>
    <P>The question arises of individual ownership.  I agree with Senator O'Dwyer and the Minister that anything that purported to do away with individual ownership would be disastrous in this country.  The Irishman does not lend himself to co-operation when it becomes a question of sharing his home life.  I do not think you could compel any number of Irishmen to share their ownership of land with anybody.  It is something inherent in them and it will not ever be possible to have co-operation on those lines. The Minister said that he did not believe that co-operation proved a success anywhere.  I do not think it did.  In my long experience of farming I only knew one case where co-operative <Col N="640" /> farming was carried out to a large extent and it was among a Russian sect in Canada.  The Government gave them a tract of land and they worked it co-operatively.  There was no such thing as individual ownership of machinery.  There was no rent to pay in Canada and practically no rates and I daresay it showed a profit, but there was always a suspicion in the minds of these people, who were mostly uneducated people, that somebody was making something out of the particular experiment in co-operative ownership. I am referring to Saskatchewan 50 or at least 40 years ago.  In co-operation as in anything else, there has to be some head or manager.  You cannot run a co-operative business with everyone as boss.  In this place a man named Verigin was the manager.  Verigin became a rich man.  In fact, he became so rich that there was a town called after him and I suppose it is called after him still.  They all came to the conclusion that eventually you cannot beat private ownership and I do not think you could beat it in this country any more than in any other.  Having said so much, I do not want anybody to infer that the Irish farmer is not open to conviction, that his ways cannot be improved, or that he could not make much more profit and increase production.  The Government could help, and is helping in that direction.</P>
    <P>Senator O'Dwyer referred to co-operative farming among creameries, but it is not really co-operative farming. It is more or less co-operative individualism, if you could use the term. When the creameries buy a farm it is not co-operation.  It is run by one man; the manager, if he is an able man, runs it in the name of the creamery society. It is not at all tantamount to the idea advocated by Senator Burke of a co-operative farm and I could not find a better term than co-operative individualism. The creameries are a success because they are not hampered by a big number of owners.  I suppose essentially all creamery suppliers are really owners, but not one bothers his head about it.  They do not think twice of the matter.  They only know that a certain sum of their money is invested in a farm and that it is run generally at a profit.  Most of the ones I know <Col N="641" /> have made money and are useful in that way.</P>
    <P>The last point I want to make is that raised by Senator Counihan, the question of profit on a farm.  I do not say that farmers never made any profit.  If they never did, they would not be in existence now.  They existed all the time through bad and good years.  But for the Minister to say that every tenacre farmer in County Galway has a rubber-tyred trap and that soon every 20-acre farmer will have a rubber-tyred motor car is rather stretching things too much.  There is only one way of proving this and no Minister in this State has ever got down to it yet and I do not suppose that any Minister ever will because Ministers as a rule, and their advisers, do not take chances.  The farmers take chances. Having listened to all the solutions, I made my own suggestion that the only solution is a demonstration farm run on a profit basis.  If the Minister, as I said, will set up in every county, or in every second county, a farm run on modern scientific lines with all the suggestions made by the officials of the Department and proper accounts kept of that particular farm, and if at the end of the year or two years&mdash;I think the farmers would be glad to give him two years' start so that he would get used to it&mdash;just to work himself in&mdash;I think we would all be glad to give him two years of a chance, but after that, if every year a profit was shown on that farm worked scientifically with all modern developments, I would make bold to say there are not five farmers in this country who would not follow suit.  Until the Government and their advaisers take some such action it is idle for the Minister, his officials or anybody else to come into the Seanad or Dáil to tell me or any other farmer who knows his job that the farmers over the last 25 years have been making extravagant profits, because they have not.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFrancisBaxter" hpid="Mr. Baxter Mr. Baxter">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Baxter</NameTxt>
      <P>I think Senator Burke is to be congratulated on putting down this motion, and because of the sort of approach that is being made to it in certain quarters, I feel that it requires a great deal of hardihood on his part. I think it is very important, very <Col N="642" /> valuable, to have the sort of discussion on this problem that we have had from Senator Burke himself, and to have the facts presented to the House as they have been by him.  I may say that I am a whole-hearted co-operator.  I believe in the principle of co-operation in production, processing and marketing of agricultural produce.  I think it is possible to extend this principle within very narrow limits, but what I want to say about the motion is, that while Senator Burke refers to it as an experiment in co-operation, I think the truth is that it is an experiment with human nature.  That is the real problem.  In fact, that is the great problem.  Senator Burke has achieved a great deal himself on his own farm. He was an altruist.  He is prepared to organise his farm production policy on this co-operative basis and he was there himself to lead the way.  He introduced and cultivated the spirit of co-operation on his farm.  Now, that, I think, is the great factor that should make for success in any such venture, but I think our problem in regard to the handling of the land of this country has to be approached from the point of view of a land utilisation angle, the full utilisation of the land of the country.  When Senator Burke speaks of the establishment of a small number of co-operative farm units as an experiment, I am confronted with the difficulty of how you are to get these units.  If you take the existing farms, you have all the difficulties of differences in areas, the quality of the land and all that sort of thing.  I just cannot see how you are going to get into a co-operative group one farmer with 160 acres, a farmer with 20 acres, a farmer with 25 acres, one of the farms carrying a beast to the acre, and the other carrying three beasts to the acre. I just cannot visualise how we can organise a group of existing farmers on a co-operative basis where the difference in soil, in value of the soil, and in size of the farms was as great as that, and so it would seem that you can only approach this problem from the point of view of the land that still remains to be redistributed in the country.  The larger farms that are there, or a number of them will, possibly, <Col N="643" /> be taken over by the Land Commission in the next few years.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Now, when you come up to them, what do you find?  You find the policy of the Government, as far as it has been enunciated, to be the redistribution of this land on the basis of making economic holdings out of uneconomic farms as they exist at the moment.  You find the policy of men being transplanted from Mayo to Meath, from Cavan to Westmeath, and a man with a farm of 50 acres in one of these counties getting a 30 or 35 acre farm in Meath or Westmeath.  You find a number of people from different districts being grouped together as neighbours, people who have never known each other before, who have never met, with a different approach to the problem of farming, and a slightly different outlook on life.  I think you would have real difficulty in trying to hammer these people into a co-operative unit without the kind of spirit that exists on Senator Burke's farm.  These seem to be the practical difficulties that confront one in the acceptance or the making operative of the idea of Senator Burke's motion. I am not anything like as alarmed as the Minister appears to be, at the co-operativisation of agricultural production from the point of view of combining a number of farms or getting a number of farmers to work together in a unit. I think myself that it takes a much greater living example of the true Christian spirit to work together in the kind of way that people in Senator Burke's farm have to farm, than it does under the conditions where each of us will get our own way.  Naturally, where men and women, probably, too, are thrown very closely together, as they must be on this venture of Senator Burke's, there has to be a subordination of individual desires.  There has to be a toleration of the point of view of the other.  There has to be an effort to understand the point of view of the other and the spirit to combine together, sometimes in a project with which you may be slightly dissatisfied because you have not absolute confidence, and because you cannot absolutely believe in its success.  You have <Col N="644" /> to subordinate your private desires, and I must say, that I think it takes a very fine type of christian to do that sort of thing.  I commend what is being done by Senator Burke and his colleague.  I have not been down there, but I am quite sure it must be a good example of a spirit that we could have much more of, with advantage to agriculture, and to the country as a whole.</P>
    <P>It is stated that the earnings on Senator Burke's farm, despite the fact that it is on a co-operative basis, are not higher than the wage level that is enjoyed by the agricultural workers&mdash;I think the Minister pointed to the fact that farms of 30 acres in his own county would give a higher standard of living than this&mdash;but I just wonder how many farms in this country of 30 acres, where the owners will only work five and a half days a week, will give earnings that are being obtained in Senator Burke's farm.  Quite frankly in my judgement, and I have quite a lot of experience, the man who talks of having a five and a half-day working week, and hopes to enjoy a fair standard of living at that, is not facing up to the realities of the situation at all.  My experience is that it is a much longer day, and I would say that these people are actually working an eight-or nine-hour day.  I would like to ask Senator Burke if that is so.</P>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. Burke Mr. Burke">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Burke</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes, nine hours.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFrancisBaxter" hpid="Mr. Baxter Mr. Baxter">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Baxter</NameTxt>
      <P>Most of the people working on farms are not only working a seven-day week, but 12 or 14 hours a day instead of nine hours.  It is an important aspect of the case presented by Senator Burke, and in justice the House should be made conscious of it. I am not anything like as alarmed as the Minister appears to be at the dangers that would follow the denying of the right of the individual.  I do not regard it as a practicable proposition. We have to face the problem of how people are to combine to achieve the fullest utilisation of our land resources.  As the land is distributed to-day, it does not seem to me to be a practicable proposition to hammer the farmers, as they are, into co-operative units.  The great difficulty I see is that men are going to go on these <Col N="645" /> farms on the basis of what they have given up on the farms they owned before.  With regard to experimentation, either from the point of view of the amendment of Senator O'Dwyer or the motion of Senator Counihan, I have only this to say: In regard to Senator O'Dwyer's amendment, what is the point in our doing experimental demonstrations with a view to the improvement of agricultural methods on the basis of co-operation, unless we are going to spread, unless it is going to be the example of what the future is going to be?  I do not think that we are going to have these co-operative farms, and so demonstration on that basis would not be true to the possibilities of farming in the country.</P>
      <P>With regard to the motion of Senator Counihan and to what Senator Bennett has said, I think I agree with the Minister. I do not think it is worth a brass farthing to agriculture in this country to get the most efficient College of Science people, and put them on an experimental farm owned by the State. We see what is being done in various parts of the country, at Ballyhaise, Clonakilty and Athenry and elsewhere. What is the comment of all the farmers who go there or to the Albert College? They say, &ldquo;Oh, yes, the State owns that.  There is no shortage of capital. They can put in all the machines they like, get the stock breeds they like and all sorts of equipment and receive all the scientific knowledge that there is.&rdquo; If we are going to have demonstration farms of any value, the demonstrating must be done on an ordinary farm.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>Hear, hear.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFrancisBaxter" hpid="Mr. Baxter Mr. Baxter">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Baxter</NameTxt>
      <P>That is my conviction. Let the College of Science come to me, let them go to the ordinary farmer in the country and go in with all the equipment available to them for agriculture. Let them demonstrate on an ordinary farm, working the ordinary hours that have to be worked, that they can do better with scientific knowledge than with our present methods.  In my opinion, that is what we have to do, and I think that ought to be done, especially in view of the scheme which the Minister has inaugurated in the land rehabilitation project.  I believe there is scope in that.  There is no <Col N="646" /> doubt whatever in the minds of any of us who understand agriculture, that a great deal of the land of the country as it is to-day, is in a desolate condition, and no experimental farm would be a fair index of a reasonably high level of efficiency, because the land is sick and neglected and, in the condition in which it is, you could not do justice to any experiment.  You have now got an opportunity to put the land right under the land rehabilitation project, and when you have got health back to the land, we can start.  The land is like an animal or like a man.  There is no use in taking out a half-starved horse at the end of the winter and putting him to plough.  He will not be able to do a good day's work until you give him more oats and feed him up. By the time you have finished your ploughing, he will then be able to do a good day's work.  There are a great many of the horses of the country like that and it is the same with the land. The Minister is going to give health back to the land.  When he does, we can do experimental work on it&mdash;that is where it ought to be done.  I know that it is part of the Minister's policy to engage on that type of enterprise.</P>
      <P>I think that Senator Burke is to be congratulated on his courage in putting down this motion and especially to be congratulated on the spirit he has himself displayed in his venture in County Galway.  I think he will recognise&mdash; perhaps he is too good a Christian to associate with most of us&mdash;that his project does not mean experimenting with land; it is experimenting with human nature.  Unless you have a group of people with a right spirit to come together voluntarily and to abandon their liberty and pool their resources, and the conditions that are created by the pooling of those resources are acceptable to all and they pull together, it would be quite impossible. I frankly confess I do not rate human nature as highly as Senator Burke, and I am afraid there is too much selfishness and it would be too easy to stir up dissatisfaction and cause the group to break up again. What the result would be in the end I do not know.  I think that Senator Burke has done the House a very good service.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="647" />
    <Speaker pid="TimothyJosephODonova" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Does the Minister wish to conclude?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>If I might conclude now, I will not trespass long on the Seanad's time.  When I left I had touched on the last of the points raised by Senator Burke to recommend his system.  I agree with Senator Baxter that Senator Burke is to be congratulated in bringing this matter before the Seanad. Nevertheless, I warn him that unless my hand has lost its cunning, I discern, partly by tactile sense, that Senator Burke will hear the word &ldquo;Russia&rdquo; before this debate is over.  Nobody will call him a Bolshevik, but he will find himself in imminent danger of having that implied.  There are specious grounds&mdash;specious grounds&mdash;for drawing comparisons between his suggestion and the collective farms of the Communist system.  The danger is that Senator Burke dreams of a communal farm in the air of freedom.  The communal farm of the Soviet system is that which lingers under the shadow of the gaol and the scaffold. I think that the best test of the value of Senator Burke's motion is the admission of the feeling all of us have that it is not enough simply to say that his is a bad idea, and I think his idea is about as bad as an idea could be, without satisfying him and the Seanad that we have a better one.  I would be ashamed to dissent from the Senator as emphatically as I do were I not in a position to make a humble submission of a modest idea.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I think the proper alternative method of meeting the ideal the Senator desires to serve is the parish plan.  Far from desiring to see any individual farmer in any parish qualified in his ownership of his land, I have charged him to keep watch and ward beside his gate and to throw anybody out who tries to come in unbidden, including the Minister for Agriculture and all the officers of his Department.  I hope that, in each group of three parishes where a parish agent will function, he will have the benefit of the collaboration of a parish council representative of all the people in the parish, and, to me, one of the most distinguished and distinguishing marks of Muintir na Tíre, which has been responsible for organising most parish councils at present in existence, <Col N="648" /> is the virtual universal appearance on the platform and the executive of every parish council of all ministers of religion attached to the parish.</P>
    <P>It is something peculiarly welcome in our part of Ireland to see Christian men of every confession collaborating for the common good, without in any sense reneging on their own conviction as to the right way to do homage to God.  I think it is a good thing to associate with the pedestrian business of earning your living the spiritual centre of your life, the parish church, whether it is the Protestant Church, or, what is for me the true church, the Catholic Church, or the Presbyterian or Methodist place of meeting.  I conceive that to have a value exceeding any material advantage, though I can well understand a few of those who would say: &ldquo;What have spiritual values of this kind got to do with the political heads of public departments?&rdquo; I think that is a legitimate point of view.  It is not mine, because I think you cannot integrate life at all, if you do not recognise the various fractions of which the whole is composed.</P>
    <P>In addition to that, shall I say, numinous value of the parish plan, it has the practical advantage that it surmounts the difficulty which has confronted Senator Burke of making machinery and relatively expensive equipment available to the small individual farmer, because I would hope that the parish agents, working in collaboration with the parish councils, would help in developing parish or three parish units of suitable machinery which, through the parish council, could be made available in due rotation to the various small farmers who wish to avail of the service.  I know there will be cynics who will say at once: &ldquo;You could not do that in rural Ireland. Everyone would want the tractor and the plough on the same day.&rdquo;  To these people I reply: &ldquo;There is no use in saying you cannot do it.  I am going to do it right here and now.&rdquo;  That there will be difficulties, that there will be failures, that there will be complete breakdown, I know perfectly well, but if three out of every ten are attended with success from the date of their initiation, I will consider the achievement to have been most distinguished. <Col N="649" /> We have not waited to foresee every difficulty, to provide for every contingency, to think of every possible handicap and set back in order to make provision for all these things before we set forth on the campaign.  I would ask Senators not to be too critical of flaws in the initial stages of the land rehabilitation project, of the parish plan, of the domestic water supply schemes because there will be flaws, and there will be flaws not through any fault or lack of prescience on the part of officers of my Department.  There will be these faults because I would not wait for all these possibilities to be foreseen, because I knew that if I did, we would all be old men and women or in our graves before anything at all was done.  We know where we are going and we have not got the slightest doubt that, with the help of those of our people who are of good will, we will get over any of the initial difficulties.</P>
    <P>We dare to believe that in the parish scheme which we plan to operate we have at last the rural answer to the materialist dialectic, that we have the rural answer to the proposition that efficiency, maximum economic production, are the only criteria by which men should live, and that out of the parish plan we can demonstrate that there is such a generic name as happiness, which comprises modest prosperity, a decent sense of duty, the will to work honestly, a sense of responsibility and gratitude to God for the privilege of owning your own home and a realisation that no one is likely to grow rich in rural Ireland, and that, if it is riches they are after, the sooner they clear out to New York, to Manchester, to London or to Johannesburg, the quicker they will realise their ambition of being very unhappy men.  If they want to be happy, if they want to have the best life that any country in the world to-day can offer a good man, they will recognise themselves as members of a very select society, the parish, where they can never be insignificant again, where they can never feel again that it does not matter whether they do their best or their worst.  There they can never feel again, as people who live in great cities of the world feel, that if they were to vanish like <Col N="650" /> a puff of smoke in the air, no one would ever know that they had been born, no one would ever know that they had disappeared, the social unit to which they belong would never even falter for their disappearance.</P>
    <P>They will know that their presence or their absence in the social unit to which they belong makes a real difference, that if they do their best, they can make of their farm, as Senator Baxter has so aptly said, the real demonstration farm, a farm which will stop people on the road as they drive through, to envy the parish which has in it a man who can make so much of so little.  On the other hand, if they are lazy and feckless and worthless, they will become the subject of reproach by their neighbours, who will resent this blot upon the parish effort. But be it reproach or be it admiration, they will never know the infinite loneliness of utter indifference.  And it is those who wander in that wilderness who are the ready dupes of the materialist dialectic which offers them reintegration in a social unit where they are wanted, where there is work to do and where their failure or their success makes a difference to the Communist cell in which they are invited to participate.</P>
    <P>Have Senators ever asked themselves how many lonely people in the world are lonely because they feel they do not any longer belong anywhere? Did they ever ask themselves why people join societies, why there is that constant trend in human society to gather together in the Rechabites, in the Hibernians, in the Foresters or in the hundred and one benevolent or social societies, all of which indicate the desire of the lonely to escape from loneliness.  It is that knowledge that the dialectical materialist has so brilliantly capitalised in the assault on civilisation; and I think, perhaps, it is in the modest Irish rural parish that we can find the answer.  That is what I am looking for, in any case.</P>
    <P>I accept with enthusiasm Senator Baxter's definition of a demonstration farm.  There is no use demonstrating, as he says, the unlimited capital of the State, what can be done by a graduate in agriculture, with the implements <Col N="651" /> that all the money in the Treasury can command, on a 20-acre farm in County Mayo&mdash;because, rightly, the neighbours say: &ldquo;What has that got to do with me?&rdquo; But if the parish agent attains to the dignity of being the friend of those he serves and can demonstrate to neighbours that one of their number, accepting his advice, and putting into practice himself the knowledge which scientific research has revealed and which is now communicated to him by a technical expert, can make his farm twice as productive as it heretofore has been, there are very few farmers in Ireland who will not follow that example.  I have no hesitation in saying that as to 80 per cent. of the land of this country we can double its productivity. If we succeed, we shall increase our agricultural exports by 40 per cent.  That is the modest aim of the agricultural policy of this Government.</P>
    <P>Lastly, I want to say this.  I think it is foolish to shrug our shoulders and dismiss from our minds the possibility of bringing within the reach of a small farmer&mdash;I mean a 30-acre farmer&mdash;for his own use, modern appliances.  I can never reconcile myself to the belief that because men live on the land in Ireland they must submit permanently to the gross affront to the dignity of human nature that they shall be compelled to deny themselves two-thirds of the legitimate value of their labour, because the implements they use are inefficient.  In my submission, the implements of modernity enable an honest worker to-day to produce three times as much as he can produce with elementary equipment.  If a 30-acre farmer to-day could purchase for himself a 10-h.p. tractor, a single-furrow tractor plough, a harrow, and a power-driven mowing machine, would he not be fairly well equipped, according to existing standards?  If he could get it all for £350, with five years to pay, is it unthinkable that he should reach upon it?  Would it not be cheaper than keeping a pair of horses?  Do Senators consider that impossible?  They should not.  I hope I am going to see it some day soon.  Like many other of my hopes, they may be the fruit of excessive <Col N="652" /> optimism.  That is a politician's difficulty.  He is sometimes afraid to shoot at stars for fear that if he does no more than lasso the moon he will be derided as a failure.  I find that risk quite stimulating and, therefore, I have always delighted in keeping the Seanad informed.  I have always been a little alarmed by the manifest incredulity on the faces of the Senators on my right.  I have always been sustained by their enthusiastic rejoicing at my unexpected successes.  I look forward to their plaudits if this dream comes to realisation.  It is very like politics to speak thus but, then, I am a politician and very proud of that fact.  It affords one the opportunity of doing things that I have always wanted to do.</P>
    <P>I do not take the gloomy view about the small peasant proprietor.  My people were peasant proprietors.  My people were evicted.  My people put back every evicted tenant in East Mayo.  We do not regret it.  We do not want to undo it.  We treasure the right to our own holding more than anything else we have got and we are convinced that, given the opportunity, we can demonstrate that that system of land tenure will get from the land committed to our care a better living for us and our families than any other system of land tenure that can be imagined.  And we are convinced that happy men living in their own home in dignity and peace will produce more for the nation they belong to than the most efficient body of servants that the most excellent system of collective farming can ever provide.</P>
    <Speaker pid="LiamOBuachalla" hpid="Liam Ó Buachalla Liam Ó Buachalla">
      <NameTxt>Liam Ó Buachalla</NameTxt>
      <P>Níl fhios agam céard is ceart dom a dhéanamh i dtaobh na díospóireachta seo.  Tá sé beagnach a deich a chlog.  Is dóigh liom go dteastaíonn ó roinnt eile Seanadóirí labhairt ar na tairiscintí. Ar an ábhar sin, ní dóigh liom gur cheart moladh anois go gcuirfí deireadh leis an díospóireacht.  An bhfuil sé intuigthe go mbeidh cead ag Seanadóirí labhairt ar na tairiscintí amáireach?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Micheál Ó hAodha Micheál Ó hAodha">
      <NameTxt>Micheál Ó hAodha</NameTxt>
      <P>Beidh.  Tá díospóireacht ar siúl sa Dáil agus b'fhearr leis an Aire dul ann.  Más maith leis <Col N="653" /> an Seanadóir Ó Buachalla, féadfaidh sé labhairt amáireach.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LiamOBuachalla" hpid="Liam Ó Buachalla Liam Ó Buachalla">
      <NameTxt>Liam Ó Buachalla</NameTxt>
      <P>Is cuma liom. Tá mé lán tsásta más maith leis an Aire dul go dtí an Dáil.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Séamus Díolún Séamus Díolún">
      <NameTxt>Séamus Díolún</NameTxt>
      <P>Tá rún ar siúl sa Dáil mar gheall ar bhainne agus caithfidh mé imeacht.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LiamOBuachalla" hpid="Liam Ó Buachalla Liam Ó Buachalla">
      <NameTxt>Liam Ó Buachalla</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not think the Seanad will have very much difficulty in making up its mind as to what it ought to do with regard to these matters.  It is clear that we could not possibly accept the amendments because to accept them would simply be to admit that we know nothing of what has been happening in the country.  The Minister mentioned a number of experimental farms that are already in existence.  He did not give half the number.  He mentioned Clonakilty, Athenry, and Ballyhaise.  He did not refer to Pallaskenry, Warrenstown, Mountbellew, and so on.  What is asked for in these amendments is already provided.  Therefore, there seems to be very little point in discussing them.</P>
      <P>To come then to the motion.  Senator Baxter has declared that he is a co-operator. I, too, am a co-operator.  I like very much the theory of co-operation. I am not so happy that we have achieved all the results that we were led to believe should flow from putting these theories into practice.  I am in doubt as to the extent to which co-operation has been a success in the country.  Certain results have been achieved, but I am afraid the price has been too high.  This is not a new matter.  I have said more than once that I would like to see the whole question of co-operation in Ireland investigated because it seems to me that we have lost sight of the real aims of co-operation and are not operating the real methods of co-operation.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Senator O'Dwyer hit the nail on the head when he said that we ought to go all out in defence of the system of individual ownership which we have. Theoretically, at any rate, I think it would be possible to get greater output under a system of co-operation or collective farming but again I fear that the price would be too high.  There <Col N="654" /> may be difficulties; there may be losses; standards may not be as high, under the system of individual ownership. As I have said more than once in the Seanad, there are things that are higher than material gain.  I agree with that portion of the Minister's speech in which he dealt with the philosophy of life in rural Ireland.  I am glad that he devoted so much time to it.  It seems to me that there is no reason why we should ask the State to encourage and facilitate the establishment of a number of co-operative farms.  Why should we ask the State to do that?  There are two reasons why we should not, first there is a co-operative organisation in the State endowed to a considerable extent by the Government and endowed to some extent by private subscription and there is no earthly reason why that body, in view of its experience and wide knowledge of the country, of conditions and needs, should not undertake work of this kind if it thinks it should do so.</P>
    <P>The second reason why I think the State should not interfere at all is because Senator Burke has carried out an experiment and I think he has pretty well advertised what he has done and achieved.  He says that he has been at this for the past 16½ or 17 years.  I know farmers in County Galway, East and West, and I have great admiration for what these men have achieved.  I suppose that the finest farmers in the whole of Europe must be found in portions of North and East Galway and I think the finest farmers of all must be found amongst the rocks of Connemara.  Men who have lived, reared families and succeeded as the people in Connemara have succeeded, are certainly something to boast of and they are people of whom we should be proud.  It seems to me that there must be something radically wrong with Senator Burke's experiment if the farmers, looking at him and at what he believes to be a considerable measure of success, have not followed his example.  As a matter of fact, I am inclined to doubt whether Senator Burke's experiment is an experiment in co-operation at all.  The essence of co-operation would be, of course, co-operative ownership, and I wonder do these men working on these farms own <Col N="655" /> this farm.  If they do not, it seems to me that there is no use in talking of this as a co-operative experiment. He tells us of the wages he has paid, 5/- more than the standard wage.  I am personally acquainted with not a few farmers who pay more than the standard wage.  I cannot say how much more they pay, but I know from the workers and from the farmers themselves that they do pay more than the standard minimum wage.  That has been achieved outside this system which has been lauded so much by Senator Burke.  It is no more than an example of some kind of profit-sharing. He has not given us enough information to let us know whether it is really a co-operative scheme or not, but it seems to me from the information he has given that it is something in the nature of a mild form of profit-sharing. To what extent you could devise a scheme of that kind throughout the country I do not know, but I am aware that there are other farms in Ireland as big as, bigger indeed than, Senator Burke's, on which conditions of employment, pay and facilities are at least as good as those of Senator Burke, and they could not at all be described as co-operative farms.</P>
    <P>He mentions as one of the features of his system that the men may own a cow or stock on the farm.  It is a common thing in this country&mdash;and I hope it will be continued&mdash;where men are employed, that they get facilities for the rearing of stock on their employer's farm.  Not alone that but they get facilities for the raising of crops and so on, so I wonder to what extent Senator Burke's system differs from many examples of farming under individual ownership with which I am familiar throughtout the country.  The Minister referred to the prevalence of the co-operative spirit among the people and I am well aware of many cases where farm machinery is made available by those who are better off to those less well off.  We are all familiar with the happenings of autumn when the meitheal gather and everybody lends a hand in saving the neighbour's crops.  Some cases have occurred&mdash;and there were grave reasons for it&mdash;where a neighbour's <Col N="656" /> crops were allowed to rot, but, taking things by and large, there is a fine spirit of co-operation.  If aid is needed, men and women come out and do the work.</P>
    <P>The Minister made some references that ill-became him to those on his right being somewhat unhappy when he succeeds in doing certain things.  I think that is uncalled for.  When he achieves something that is good for the people he can rejoice and we will rejoice with him.  When something goes wrong and he was warned beforehand that it was likely to go wrong, then we have reason to feel angry with him.</P>
    <P>I am not going to go into things that have happened during the last few years but those who are interested will be able to recall examples of what I have in mind.  He talks about what he believes is the solution of this problem. In this House and on other platforms, I and those of my Party have consistently advocated that the solution of the difficulty in rural Ireland lies in the adoption of scientific methods of farming.  Much has been done long before the present Minister for Agriculture came into office to encourage a knowledge of science and its application to farming problems.  I do not want to go into what has been done in these colleges, in the extension of them, in the provision of silos and instruction as to how to handle silos and silage, in the provision of instructors and of demonstration plots up and down the country, but there is no use in trying to minimise the great value of that work or in saying that that work will not in due course have great results.  I am not at all pessimistic with regard to the future of Irish agriculture; I never was.  I felt that when the young men growing up who flock into our agricultural schools and to the rural science courses in our vocational schools got their turn to take over their parents' farms we would see a big change in the matter of agricultural production.  That change has gradually taken place.  The older hands are giving up to the new and the young men and women are approaching their problem with a much keener spirit, a much wider knowledge, a much greater determination to avail <Col N="657" /> of the knowledge provided by scientists than those who have gone before them. Therefore, I look forward, as the Minister looks forward, to a considerable advance in production, output and quality of agricultural produce in this country.  We are not at all pessimistic.</P>
    <P>I believe that the better way is, as Senator O'Dwyer says, to carry on and defend to the last ditch the system of individual ownership.  The Minister suggested that Senator Burke left himself open to a charge of Communism in the way this motion is worded.  It is very hard to avoid warning Senator Burke that the essence of Communism seems to be inherent in the motion in the wording about co-operative farming units.  I do not know of any means to have them other than collective farms. They may be good economy, but whether economic ends should be the main and sole ends of our people is another matter.  For my part I believe that there are things higher in life than material gains.  The motion goes on&mdash;</P>
    <P>&ldquo;with a view to the extension of either or both of these systems of farming.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>Who is going to carry out the extension if the neighbours of Senator Burke, <Col N="658" /> having seen the wonderful success of his system, have not adopted it?  In many cases the excellent results of the making of silage have not been followed up by farmers.  They have not adopted that particular system of providing fodder for their stock.  How are you going to get over it unless you compel them?  The whole idea of compulsion and collective farming seems inherent in the motion and so it seems to me that it is a motion which this House could not possibly accept.</P>
    <P>Senator Burke in winding up said that these farms would concern themselves with educational and experimental objectives.  I do not think Senator Burke knows really what the meaning of these two terms is, because inherent in them is speculation and I am afraid loss very often is a matter which is overlooked when we are trying to estimate the value of educational and experimental institutions like agricultural colleges and demonstration farms.</P>
    <Speaker pid="SeamusOFarrell" hpid="Mr. S. O'Farrell Mr. S. O'Farrell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. S. O'Farrell</NameTxt>
      <P>I move the adjournment of the debate.</P>
      <P>The Seanad adjourned at 10 p.m. until 3 p.m. on Thursday, 2nd March, 1950.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
</Debate>