<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE Debate SYSTEM "../Debate.dtd"[]>
<Debate DocTitle="Seanad Debate" Day="Wed" Date="11" Month="Apr" Year="1934" Vol="18" No="14" DateIrish="Dé Céadaoin, 11 Aibreán 1934" DateEnglish="Wednesday, 11 April 1934" House="S" CommitteeEng="" CommitteeIr="" SubNameEng="" cnum="913">
  <MainHeading Type="Prelude" LHead="" RHead="">
    <Title>
    </Title>
    <P>
      <Col N="913" /> Do chuaidh an Cathaoirleach i gceannas ar 3 p.m.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Death of the United" RHead="States Minister">
    <Title>Death of the United States Minister.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="JosephConnolly" hpid="Minister for Lands (Senator Connolly) Minister for Lands (Senator Connolly)">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Lands (Senator Connolly)</NameTxt>
      <P>I move:&mdash;</P>
      <P>That the Seanad extend its deep sympathy to the President and people of the United States of America on the death of their esteemed representative in Saorstát Eireann, the Hon.  William Wallace McDowell; and I ask you, Sir, to convey to Mr. McDowell's bereaved relatives the condolence of this House.</P>
      <P>I do not need to add much to the resolution.  I feel it expresses the sympathy of every Senator at the sad and tragic circumstances under which Mr. McDowell passed away.  It is worthy of note, perhaps, to point to the fact that at the time of his death Mr. McDowell was in the middle of a statement expressing his affection and his regard for the people of this country and his pleasure at being appointed here.  Every Senator, I am sure, will feel that our country has lost very much by the passing of Mr. McDowell, and I therefore commend the resolution to the sympathy of the House.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelComynKC" hpid="Mr. Comyn Mr. Comyn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Comyn</NameTxt>
      <P>I beg to second the resolution, and to say that Mr. McDowell, all through his life, was a sincere and an influential friend of Ireland.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Cathaoirleach Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I will put the resolution proposed in such a sympathetic manner by the Minister for Lands.  I will add nothing to it because I am sure every member of the House feels very deeply the circumstances of Mr. McDowell's tragic death.</P>
      <P>Resolution passed, all the members rising in their places.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Control of Imports Bill," RHead="1934&mdash;Message from the Dáil">
    <Title>Control of Imports Bill, 1934&mdash;Message from the Dáil.</Title>
    <Col N="914" />
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Cathaoirleach Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>The following Message has been received from the Dáil:&mdash;</P>
      <P>Dáil Eireann has agreed to the amendments made by Seanad Eireann to the Control of Imports Bill, 1934.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Sheepskin (Control of Export)" RHead="Bill, 1934&mdash;Second Stage">
    <Title>Sheepskin (Control of Export) Bill, 1934&mdash;Second Stage.</Title>
    <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That the Bill be now read a Second Time.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Minister for Industry and Commerce (Mr. Lemass) Minister for Industry and Commerce (Mr. Lemass)">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Industry and Commerce (Mr. Lemass)</NameTxt>
      <P>The scheme of this Bill is, I think, quite simple to understand. It provides for the regulation of the export of sheepskins.  It provides that no person can export sheepskins from the Saorstát except under a licence, to be issued in accordance with the provisions of the Bill, by the Minister for Industry and Commerce. The object of the introduction of the Bill is to secure the development, or the revival, of the fellmongering industry in the Saorstát.  The industry may not be of very great importance when compared to others, but it did provide in the past not inconsiderable employment for adult skilled workers in a number of towns in the Saorstát.  During the period of the Great War and in subsequent years, the industry dealt with all the sheepskins produced in the Saorstát but in latter years it has declined and, quite recently, its complete extinction appeared to be extremely likely. One of the reasons why the extinction of the industry appeared likely was that the sheepskin buyers from Great Britain were organising themselves to secure control of the supplies here, and to that end were paying for sheepskins prices which the Irish fellmongers could not afford to pay and which, in their opinion, were not justified by the state of the market, having regard to the prices to be realised for the pelts and the scoured wool.  It is proposed that the Bill will be operated so as to secure <Col N="915" /> an adequate supply of skins for the fellmongering yards here while at the same time checking any tendency that may appear on behalf of Irish fellmongers to take advantage of a closed market in order to depress prices unduly.  The prices at which sheepskins should be purchased can be easily determined, having regard to the prices secured for the pelts and the wool.  As long as that price is being paid there is no reason why any sheepskins which the Irish fellmongering yards are capable of dealing with should be exported.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>There was a number of firms engaged in the industry here some years ago.  At the present time only three are in operation, although I understand that certain firms that were, until recently, in operation and that are now inactive will commence operations again as soon as this Bill is passed into law.  While, in a sense, this is a minor measure, some apprehension was caused and was given expression to in the Dáil on the grounds that the fact of restricting people from exporting sheepskins might, in some way, affect the price of sheep.  I think it is clear that that cannot happen.  The price of sheep&mdash; we have an exportable surplus of these animals&mdash;will be determined by the export price, so that any reduction that might take place in the price of sheepskins would be a matter of concern only to those who are dealing in the butchering of sheep here and not to those engaged in the production of sheep.  It is not to be anticipated that any reduction in price will take place that might not otherwise occur.  Last year, of course, there was a substantial increase in the prices paid for skins.  That was due to certain causes, one being the alleged fact that British fellmongers were paying a price for skins that was not justified by the market in order to complete the efforts that they have been making in recent years to control the whole supply in this country. The British fellmongers, of course, are operating on a much larger scale than the fellmongers here.  The number of skins that they <Col N="916" /> purchase here represents only a very small proportion of their total purchases, and consequently a temporary inflation of prices here would be a matter of little concern to them, even though it might operate to put a number of Saorstát fellmongers out of existence altogether.  There is no reason to fear that any difficulty will arise in disposing of the products of the industry which have always been in demand.  In fact, at the present time the demand appears to be in excess of the supply.  The persons engaged in the industry have no apprehensions that they will not be able to dispose of all they can possibly produce.</P>
    <P>The aim of the Bill is to secure that all the sheepskins available here will be fellmongered in the country. At a later stage it may be possible to secure the establishment here of an industry for the tanning of the pelts but that industry is not one which can be easily brought into existence because it requires a very high degree of technical skill that is not yet available to us.  We trust, however, that the operation of this measure and the revival of the fellmongering industry will at least be a step forward towards the establishment of the other industry at a later stage.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JohnKeaneBart" hpid="Sir John Keane Sir John Keane">
      <NameTxt>Sir John Keane</NameTxt>
      <P>I would ask the Minister to justify the policy of establishing an industry such as fellmongering here.  He did not give us any particulars of the numbers likely to be employed.  Admittedly, as the Minister himself said, this is going to be done at the expense of the primary producer. He says that the whole object of the Bill is to give the home fellmonger the fells at a cheaper price than is now being paid for them.  He said that they cannot afford to pay the price that the extern buyer is prepared to pay; and that, therefore, they have to be protected.  Surely, that seems unreasonable.  This Bill seems to be part and parcel of the policy of dealing with the agricultural industry of this country in a piecemeal way.  Sheep, and the by-products of sheep, are part and parcel of our whole agricultural industry and should be considered in <Col N="917" /> relation to other branches of it.  It would also appear that the amount of employment to be given is very small. Although I do not clearly understand all that fellmongering involves, or the further processes of dealing with the hides, which the Minister admits cannot he done at home at present, I wish he would give us more particulars about this industry that is now going to be protected at the expense of the primary producer.  I am not convinced by the argument that there is going to be no reaction on farmers, because if there is a higher price given for the fells, that price, presumably, would be passed on to the farmers, so that in some way this will affect the price farmers will receive for sheep.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JosephOConnor" hpid="Mr. O'Connor Mr. O'Connor">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Connor</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not feel very anxious about this proposal, because the industry is hardly one about which one can form an opinion.  At present we know that the price of sheep is controlled very much by the imports from Australia of large quantities of frozen mutton.  As to the probability of this proposal helping the sheep industry, I have grave doubts of such a result. However, anything that would help to increase the price of sheep for the producers should be given every encouragement. From my experience the tanning of sheepskins is a very small business.  I doubt if it will be of very much value here.  I doubt if these proposals will materially increase the price paid to producers of sheep because wool is selling at a very low price.  The commercial value of plucked wool is not very great.  I hope the Bill will be a success, but I have grave doubts if it will be possible to work up an industry that will be a paying one.  This question should have been well thought out by people who have experience before I could give it very strong support.  It would be a mistake to have an industry started without having grounds for believing, from the previous history of the industry, that it would be a success. Instead of this proposal it would be better to have a committee of inquiry, who would go into the matter before asking the Seanad to support this Bill.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="918" />
    <Speaker pid="JohnBagwell" hpid="Mr. Bagwell Mr. Bagwell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Bagwell</NameTxt>
      <P>Whatever our opinions may be about this matter I do not see what we can do now.  At the same time, it would not be right at this stage for Senators, who think there is a considerable element of robbing Peter to pay Paul in this Bill, to abstain from saying so.  The Minister told us that there is a ring of English buyers of sheepskins, and the form that ring takes is not to cut down prices, but to give higher prices; prices which we have been given to understand are higher than the market justifies.  Well, these prices now go into some Irishmen's pockets, but in future smaller prices will go into the pockets of some Irishmen.  This is an attempt to resuscitate the industry of fellmongering, which we are told is moribund.  I suggest that the industry of the farmers who produce the sheep has an equal claim to be moribund, or certainly is running very close to it, looking at things as they are in this country at present.  What the gain will be, or, if there will be any net gain on the balance between the two, I cannot say.  It is quite clear that a great deal of whatever may be gained by the Bill will go to some people, while others, who are equally citizens, are not in a very good way.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnCounihan" hpid="Mr. Counihan Mr. Counihan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Counihan</NameTxt>
      <P>I am sorry I was not in time to hear the discussion that took place at the opening stage of the debate.  It was impossible for me to be here in time.  I am not opposing the Bill at this stage, but I want to say that I cannot support it in its present form.  If the Minister will accept an amendment, which I will try to frame for the Committee Stage, I think the Seanad would be, justified in passing the Bill.  In his speech in the Dáil the Minister made great play with a statement that has been made from time to time that where there is an export surplus of agricultural produce the value is regulated by the export price. I made that statement on many occasions and I stand by it.  The Minister went on to argue from that that as all sheepskins are bought on the sheep, there is export competition for sheep, and that consequently the farmers cannot lose.  However, many <Col N="919" /> statements, which are true in the main, have exceptions, and to understand the exception to the rule here, one should understand something about that particular class of trade.  The Minister will find that practically all of our most valuable sheep are not exported at all, that the very heavy wethers and nearly all the fat ewes are killed for the home trade.  The skins of these are much more valuable than the other skins and consequently there is no export competition for that class of sheep.  The Minister cannot hold to the rule that the export trade will regulate the prices for that class of sheep.  The majority of the sheep exported are lambs and small hoggets, and there I agree the skins will have to be bought against competition.  It is all nonsense for the Minister to say that the farmers will not lose anything.  Every butcher who buys sheep regulates the value of the offal in fixing the price and if, as the Minister admits, someone will have to lose, in the finish it is the producer who will lose.  The Minister may say that one or two shillings per skin, more or less, will not mean much, and that the butchers can afford it.  I can assure the Minister it is not the butchers who are going to lose.  Butchers could not afford to lose one or two shillings on sheep.  If the Minister thinks that trade is carried on in that way, and that one or two shillings per sheep does not matter, he is making a great mistake, because that amount may represent the whole profit of butchers on many occasions, and at some periods of the year.  In his speech in the Dáil the Minister stated that fellmongering is better managed by the English fellmongers than in Ireland and that as a result of the process the skins undergo they command a better price in England. If the English fellmongers are able to get better prices for the skins, the price of sheepskins in this country is going to be less than it would be if there was export competition.  As Senator Bagwell stated, I cannot see why one particular class of the community, the farmers, should lose in order to provide employment for a certain number of people here.  If the <Col N="920" /> Minister wants to create such employment, the nation as a whole should contribute&mdash;not the farmers alone.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelComynKC" hpid="Mr. Comyn Mr. Comyn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Comyn</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator Counihan said a good deal at the beginning of his speech with which I agree, that the price of fat ewes and big sheep is regulated by the home market, and that the price of lambs and hoggets is regulated by the international market. I am sorry the Senator was not here to listen to the statement made by the Minister, because that statement convinced me, notwithstanding all the arguments which have been so clearly put by Senator Counihan, that this Bill is desirable.  It appears that the fell is the skin with the wool on it, and that when the wool is removed and washed, then you have wool for sale and a pelt for sale.  In former times fellmongering was a considerable industry in this country, and fellmongers bought skins here and there and manufactured them in towns like Limerick, Athlone and other places.  Having taken the wool off the fell, washed it and made it marketable, they sold the pelt either to tanners in this country or to others who exported the pelt.  It appears now that what they will have to do, if fellmongering is established again, as I hope it will, is to remove the wool, wash it and make it fit for sale.  But they will, for the present, have to export the pelts, as the trade is centred amongst large combines.  It is easy for a combination of men so to arrange matters, by giving a high price for the fell in one place, where there is local competition, and a low price in another place, where there is no competition, to destroy altogether the fellmongering industry where it is trying to survive here.  That would be a great loss.  I shall endeavour to explain why.  We do hope to have tanneries in this country.  As the Minister has explained, the tanning industry is a highly specialised one and requires great skill.  As the foundation of that industry, you must have this other industry of fellmongering. If you have not a fellmongering industry, you cannot even begin with a tanning industry.  Many people are quite unaware of the <Col N="921" /> animal which produces the leather which they wear as boots, uppers, soles or even gloves.  Sheepskin is very useful in the manufacture of leather of high quality.  The tanneries do not prepare the pelt for tanning.  That is a separate and distinct trade.  In order to have a tanning industry, it is necessary to have a fellmongering industry in a fair way towards establishment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnCounihan" hpid="Mr. Counihan Mr. Counihan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Counihan</NameTxt>
      <P>Can you not tan the hides?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelComynKC" hpid="Mr. Comyn Mr. Comyn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Comyn</NameTxt>
      <P>You must have the pelt before you can tan it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnCounihan" hpid="Mr. Counihan Mr. Counihan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Counihan</NameTxt>
      <P>I am talking of hides.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelComynKC" hpid="Mr. Comyn Mr. Comyn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Comyn</NameTxt>
      <P>That is another day's work.  I am surprised that Senator Counihan should be so irrelevant. Why does he not confine himself to sheepskins?  I have some experience of tanneries and of fellmongers and fellmongering and I think that the Bill is wisely conceived, assuming that the Minister is going to do for this industry what he has endeavoured to do for other industries&mdash;that is, to build it up.  I think that this is the foundation of a plan for restoring to this country the tanning industry which we had even within the last 20 or 30 years.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardWilson" hpid="Mr. Wilson Mr. Wilson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Wilson</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator Comyn states that the Minister is going to build up this industry so as to enable the tanning industry to be revived.  I should like to ask the Senator at whose expense the Minister is going to build up this industry.  The explanation given by Senator Counihan regarding sheep used by the home market shows clearly that, in regard to ewes and the heavier class of wether, there is no competition for export at all and that the price of the sheepskin is part of the price which the farmer gets.  If that price be reduced by the stoppage of exports, naturally the producers of that particular class of sheep will lose.  I should like the Minister to explain why this industry is not able to stand up to the opposition offered it.  I hardly believe that any groups of <Col N="922" /> traders in England are going to give too much for our sheepskins.  That would be a peculiar explanation and one which would require substantial proof.  Perhaps the Minister would state what the cost of production in this fellmongering business is here as compared with the cost in Britain.  If it is greater, why is it greater?  Is it because the turnover is less?  The raw material is here at the doors of these fellmongering factories, while the sheepskins have to be sent across to Britain.  How can a higher price be given under these circumstances by the British manufacturers?  That requires explanation.  Even in regard to the milling trades, I was always of the opinion that there was no reason why the grinding should not be done as well in this country as in Britain. We could not make that possible and we had to put a block on imports by way of a tariff.  That has worked out very well in regard to milling, but I am sure that the cost of the milled products is greater than the extent of the tariff.  I should like the Minister to tell us how wage costs and working costs in the fellmongering industry here compare with those in Great Britain.  We are entitled to that information before we agree to the passing of this Bill.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeorgeCrosbie" hpid="Mr. Crosbie Mr. Crosbie">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Crosbie</NameTxt>
      <P>Every one of us would do everything we could to have tanneries established in this country. At one time, the tanning industry was one of the most important industries we had.  It is an industry for which the raw material can be got within the country, which is very exceptional in the case of those industries which enjoy the advantage of a tariff to-day. What I should like to know from the Minister is if the manufacturers of leather are to have the advantage of two tariffs.  Are they to have the advantage of cheaper raw material for their leather at the expense of the farming community than their competitors outside and, in addition, is the consumer to be charged more because of the tariff on the leather he uses?  I think that that would be unfair.  I agree that there should be a tariff on leather coming into the country, but I think it is unreasonable <Col N="923" /> to expect the very limited number of farmers who have to depend on this trade to be penalised.  Let the general consumer or user of boots pay for the leather but it is unfair that the farming community should be penalised and that they should be compelled to sell their goods at a lower price than they can get outside.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="KathleenBrowne" hpid="Miss Browne Miss Browne">
      <NameTxt>Miss Browne</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister stated very definitely that the farmer would not lose under this Bill.  I should like him to explain that statement.  In referring to criticisms of the Bill in the Dáil, he said he could prove that the farmer could not lose by this measure.  How can that be possible? This is only part of the general scheme to ruin the farmer in order to bolster up a few inadequate industries.  The farmer is of no account.  The great agricultural industry is being ruined on every hand.  Every time we come into this House we find that another blow has been prepared for the agricultural industry.  Senator Counihan and Senator Wilson put the matter very clearly and I should like the Minister to explain how the farmer is not going to pay in this case, as in every other case of the kind.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasForan" hpid="Mr. Foran Mr. Foran">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Foran</NameTxt>
      <P>I should like the Minister to answer a couple of questions when replying.  There has been some discussion about tanning. This Bill has nothing whatever to do with tanning.  All these skins and fells are exported, whether by the native fellmonger or the foreigner. So far as I can see, this Bill gives a monopoly to the local or native fellmonger and provides him with an opportunity to exploit the producer. That is the point I am concerned about.  I should like to know the number of fellmongers in the country and the amount of employment given by them.  Further, I should like to know whether the standard of employment will be a condition of the licence.  If this Bill brings us nearer to development of a tanning industry, I should like the Minister to explain how it does so.  I do not see how it will get us any nearer that development. <Col N="924" /> A sheep is killed to-day; to-morrow or six months hence the pelt or skin is not going to be used for tanning.  This Bill could be introduced six, eight or ten months, or even two years hence, just as well as to-day. So far as I can see, the Minister is giving a monopoly to certain people who will be able to exploit the producers unless very stringent conditions are imposed by the licence on these alleged native fellmongers.  I know some of them and they are anything but native or racy of the soil.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>It should be quite clear to Senators that the price which the fellmonger can pay for sheepskins is determined by the price which he can procure for the scoured wool and the pelts.  These goods are marketed in Great Britain and on the Continent. There is a fairly substantial market on the Continent to which Irish fellmongers export their products.  It is possible for one fellmonger in this country or a group of British fellmongers operating here to pay a price for sheepskins not justified by the market price of wool and pelts in order to put competitors out of business. That is a regular trade device not only in regard to this industry but in regard to other industries.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasForan" hpid="Mr. Foran Mr. Foran">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Foran</NameTxt>
      <P>Who gains?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>It may surprise some innocent Senators to learn that business men resort to tricks of that sort, but if they read the trade journals and examine other sources of information, they will find that it does happen.  It has happened in this industry.  The Senator asks who gains.  People do not do that sort of thing for the good of other people's health.  If I were a fellmonger and if I were determined to put other fellmongers out of business, I could devote a certain amount of capital to paying increased prices for the products I had to buy until I had achieved my end.  What I lost in that way I could get back by depressing prices when competitors were out of the way.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnCounihan" hpid="Mr. Counihan Mr. Counihan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Counihan</NameTxt>
      <P>But there will be a competitive market.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="925" />
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>Controlled by the British fellmongers who are operating here.  These people have, apparently, been operating a policy to that end. British fellmongers cannot, any more than Irish fellmongers, afford to pay an uneconomic price for sheepskins. The price they can afford to pay is regulated by the market price of their products.  That is an international price and is not within their control. It is affected by world conditions. They can, however, pay an uneconomic price for a limited time if it suits their trade policy.  They cannot do that indefinitely but they can do it for a time for some definite end.  In the long run, the economic price will prevail, whether the sheepskins are bought by Irish fellmongers or any other fellmongers.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardWilson" hpid="Mr. Wilson Mr. Wilson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Wilson</NameTxt>
      <P>Would the Minister quote figures proving that statement?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>What statement?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardWilson" hpid="Mr. Wilson Mr. Wilson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Wilson</NameTxt>
      <P>That the British are buying these sheepskins at a higher price than they obtain for the finished article in the shape of the wool and the pelt.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>No.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardWilson" hpid="Mr. Wilson Mr. Wilson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Wilson</NameTxt>
      <P>That is the statement the Minister made.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>The statement I made I repeat and assert though I cannot produce figures to support that statement because I have not got them.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardWilson" hpid="Mr. Wilson Mr. Wilson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Wilson</NameTxt>
      <P>It is an assertion then.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>I am directing attention to the fact that the price paid in the Saorstát in 1934 was practically double the price in 1932.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnCounihan" hpid="Mr. Counihan Mr. Counihan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Counihan</NameTxt>
      <P>That has nothing to do with it.  The prices will regulate themselves.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>Quite so: I am not denying that there was some justification for the rise in price.  The rise in prices was expected owing to the economic conditions and that shows up the ridiculousness of the statement <Col N="926" /> made by Senator Miss Browne, who said that this was another scheme to put the sheep farmers out of production. As a matter of fact the prices for sheep now are higher than in 1931 when the country was basking in the sunshine of Cumann na nGaedheal Government&mdash;I am disputing that ridiculous statement en passant.  It is not proposed to give anyone a monopoly under this Bill.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnCounihan" hpid="Mr. Counihan Mr. Counihan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Counihan</NameTxt>
      <P>Did the Minister state that the English fellmongers are obtaining more for their pelts?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>Not because of any superiority of manufacture or because they have a better process, or because they are producing a better article.  In this case, again, business morality comes into the matter.  There is a higher price paid for the pelts of sheep produced in certain parts of Great Britain and there is reason to believe that some of the skins exported to Britain from the Saorstát are sold as if produced in Britain.  Because of that the British pelt-mongers may be able to pay a higher price for the Saorstát pelts than the ordinary commercial price would justify.  However the difference in price is likely to be inconsiderable, if any difference arises at all, because the factors that will control the price of sheepskins in Great Britain will control the prices here although there is reason to assume that higher costs operate here.  Labour for one thing is paid higher wages here than in Great Britain so far as the information that I have at my disposal goes.  It is a factor affecting the price here and not one that I object to.  The only other argument of importance is that of Senator Counihan who contended there was no export market for the type of sheep most suitable for the purpose.  There is a market.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnCounihan" hpid="Mr. Counihan Mr. Counihan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Counihan</NameTxt>
      <P>There is no surplus of that sort.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>Any attempt to depress prices here will be corrected by exports so long as the export market is <Col N="927" /> open.  I think Senator O'Connor was right when, in reply to Senator Sir John Keane, he said the price of sheep was controlled by imports from Australia.</P>
      <P>I am not in a position to say definitely what increased employment will result from the development of the industry.  The total direct employment in addition to those already employed will be between 100 and 200 men.  The importance of the employment is that it is generally skilled and well paid employment.  It affords employment for adult men, and that employment, in the past, was given in the country towns of the Saorstát where it was of very great advantage.  I do not know what amendment Senator Counihan proposes to suggest.  I do not know that the Bill is open to amendment because it is a simple Bill and is only intended to give effect to one purpose but we will see what the nature of the amendment is when we come to the Committee Stage.  The main purpose of the Bill is to regulate exports.  It is not designed to prohibit exports until fellmongers are in a position to deal with a much larger number of skins than at present but they probably could not deal with all. Formerly there were ten such fellmongers. Now there are only three in operation.  We hope that some of those who went out of business will come back to it again, in the same towns that they were operating in previously.  That would be a gain and although in theory possibly a lower price would prevail the price in fact prevailing will be an economic price.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>Committee Stage ordered for Wednesday, 18th April.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Town and Regional Planning" RHead="Bill, 1933&mdash;Second Stage">
    <Title>Town and Regional Planning Bill, 1933&mdash;Second Stage</Title>
    <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That the Bill be now read a Second Time.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="SeanTOKelly" hpid="Minister for Local Government and Public Health (Mr. O'Kelly) Minister for Local Government and Public Health (Mr. O'Kelly)">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Local Government and Public Health (Mr. O'Kelly)</NameTxt>
      <P>The powers proposed to be conferred by <Col N="928" /> the Bill on local authorities are necessary for the proper and economic development of their areas.  It is generally accepted that their existing powers of control over development are insufficient The traffic problems in the larger cities to-day are largely due to the uncontrolled growth of these areas in the past.  It is not alone a question of guarding against a repetition of past errors but also one of controlling development that is injurious to the amenities of a district.  In most countries town and regional planning is regarded as amongst the most important of municipal functions.  A city or town whose growth is controlled by a properly formulated plan develops in a manner best suited to the public welfare, and the evils arising from unrestricted development are avoided.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>A plan is a framework of growth.  It determines the most appropriate housing sites and the density of residential development, the sites for industries and the areas best suited for commercial purposes.  The selection of the areas set aside for development should be intimately related to the provision made for sanitary services and to the traffic requirements of the area.  The need for proper planning is apparent on all sides.  The development of local government in recent years, due to changing conditions in the national life and to the demand for a higher standard of social services, has increased considerably the scope of the work of local authorities.  Public moneys are being applied to the carrying out of a large housing programme, the provision of sanitary services, the erection of hospitals, the construction and maintenance of roads and other public purposes.  In their own interests local authorities, therefore, would be well advised to have a plan of development of their areas prepared in advance of the execution of such works, when the provisions of this Bill become law.  Such a plan, in addition to giving control over private development works in their area would secure that the public works to be undertaken would be fully considered in relation to each other, and that in areas where houses are to be built they will be placed in the most <Col N="929" /> suitable position in relation to essential sanitary services, and the provision of schools and playgrounds.</P>
    <P>A planning scheme if intelligently availed of in this manner will reinforce the efforts which are being made to improve the standard of public health, and should also bring about economies in public expenditure on social services. The control over density of houses should go a long way to prevent the conditions associated with the present day slum problem, and the allocation of lands for the erection of buildings, properly grouped, will most likely result in reduced expenditure on roads, the laying of water mains, the provision of sewers and other public services.  It is also important in connection with the clearance of insanitary areas that the problem should be examined in relation to the industrial and traffic requirements of the district, and the need for the provision of children's playgrounds and recreation parks.</P>
    <P>Of the provisions of the Bill it is not necessary to speak in detail.  This House had under consideration some years ago a Town Planning and Rural Amenities Bill introduced by Senator Johnson, and supported by other Senators.  Although some of its provisions would now be regarded as out of date, still it had for its object the same purposes as the Bill now submitted to you, and I think a tribute is due to the Senator and his colleagues for their active interest in this question.</P>
    <P>The county, county borough and urban district councils will be the planning authorities for their respective areas.  Planning regions may be formed by two or more planning authorities, and a planning district of an urban authority may, in certain circumstances, be extended to include portion of the adjoining rural area. Special regions are formed in the Bill which may be planned by the municipal authorities for the cities of Dublin and Cork.  Once a planning authority has passed a resolution deciding to make a scheme, all constructive and other works come under control, and pending the final approval of the scheme the procedure laid down in Part <Col N="930" /> VII of the Bill will apply.  Development works will proceed in the usual way, subject to the power of the planning authority to prohibit the further proceeding with the construction, demolition or alteration of any particular structure in the area to be planned, which would be likely to contravene the provisions of the plan in course of preparation.</P>
    <P>Every planning scheme of a planning authority will require the approval of the Minister.  The Minister's Order approving of a scheme, together with the planning scheme, will be laid before each House of the Oireachtas with power to annul within three sitting weeks after the week in which the Order is laid before each House or the notice of publication of the making of the Order in <i>Iris Oifigiúil</i>, whichever is later.  The validity of a scheme or any provision contained in it may be questioned in the High Court on certain specified legal grounds.  Part VIII of the Bill contains provisions for the payment of compensation and payment for betterment.</P>
    <P>Under the Bill a planning system may be set up for this country which will give all the powers that are considered necessary for local authorities to secure the orderly and progressive development of their areas and for the preservation and improvement of amenities.  There will be present to the minds of members of this House many instances where it is eminently desirable to take action to preserve existing amenities and beauty spots throughout the country.  During the present week I received a petition from residents in the neighbourhood of the Sugar Loaf Mountains, Rocky Valley and district, regarding the disfigurement of the neighbourhood by the indiscriminate erection of buildings. The petition states that the glory of the Sugar Loaf Mountains and the beauty of the Rocky Valley, which afford such pleasure to both the people in the neighbourhood and to visitors, if once despoiled and defaced could never be restored.  I have not come to any official decision on the petition, but in cases of this kind the provisions of the Bill will enable a planning authority to obtain the statutory <Col N="931" /> powers to prevent the spoliation of the countryside, which in itself is a very important aspect of regional planning. I commend the provisions of the Bill to the House.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JohnBagwell" hpid="Mr. Bagwell Mr. Bagwell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Bagwell</NameTxt>
      <P>This is a very big Bill and it has been a long time on the stocks.  I am no authority on the subject but I have read the Bill very carefully and it seems to me a well-thought-out piece of legislation and one that is well designed to achieve the objects which are set out in the preamble.  If it is equally well administered, which is a much more difficult matter, it should have good results for the towns of the country, preventing bad development, congestion, disfigurement, and other matters which it is aimed at preventing.  Of course, the administration is the crux of the matter.  Perhaps it is too much to expect that the local authorities, who will have the working of the Bill, will make as good a job of that as the drafting of the Bill has been made. Very much depends on the Minister. He has great powers of control under the Bill and we can only hope that the Minister will exercise those powers in such a manner as to ensure that local authorities will work the Bill to the best advantage.  I think the Bill is quite a good one and I support the Second Reading.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. Johnson Mr. Johnson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Johnson</NameTxt>
      <P>I welcome this Bill, and I would say that it illustrates the difficulties that face any group of Senators or private persons, unversed in the Departmental problems, in trying to submit themselves a watertight measure capable of carrying out its purposes.  One reads this Bill knowing its intentions and purposes, and finds that the greater part of it is concerned with the technicalities of law-making rather than the purposes and the intentions sought to be attained.  I say that, because it is quite clear that no group of Senators, unversed in these technicalities, could produce a Bill of that magnitude in anything like that completeness.  The feature of the Bill to which I draw attention is that the producing of town plans or a planning scheme is to be left <Col N="932" /> at the option of the local authority, and there is not even latent in the Bill, as far as I can see, power for the Minister to call upon a local authority to produce a scheme.  That may be desirable in the present state of things, in view of the lack of experience in such matters, but as a consequence there are one or two things that seem to me to call for consideration at least. There are some of what I might call minor defects that should be remedied, minor matters that are crying out for remedy, such things as the removal of destroyed buildings, the elimination of unsightly advertisements and small things of that kind which anybody and everybody, taken individually, will denounce as an outrage, and yet there is no authority in the local council to remove those evils.  There is no power given in this Bill to a local authority to do these very desirable things until it has produced a plan.</P>
      <P>I can quite conceive of a position where many local authorities would like to do these desirable things, local authorities who are not prepared to go into the whole problem of planning their district or their region.  I do not know whether it would be possible, under the definition in Section 3, for a local authority to produce a plan which only dealt with these minor matters.  The definition in Section 3 refers to planning, and says that a planning scheme shall be taken to be a scheme made in accordance with this Act for the general purpose of securing the orderly and progressive development of a particular area whether urban or rural in the best interests of the community and of preserving, improving and extending the amenities of such areas.&rdquo;  So that a local authority under that definition would not be able to deal with these small matters of the removal of ugliness and items of disrepute from the aesthetic point of view.  Yet it is very desirable that local authorities should have this power.  I do not know whether it is possible to amend this Bill so as to bring within the scheme of things, whether by regulation or otherwise, that power be given to the local authority to carry out these desirable reforms.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="933" /> Before I leave Section 3, I would just query for a moment the desirability of putting in the phrase &ldquo;in the best interests of the community.&rdquo;  It seems to me that that would leave it open to any person to go into the courts and argue that a particular process was not in the best interests of the community. While it may be quite good and satisfactory as a journalistic sentence or phrase, it is hardly satisfactory, I think, in an Act of Parliament I had the same thought in regard to the word &ldquo;progressive,&rdquo; but on second thoughts, I read that word &ldquo;progressive&rdquo; in the literal sense of being progressive towards something although we are not sure what the &ldquo;something&rdquo; towards which we are to progress is.  However, that is less important than this other sentence, &ldquo;in the best interests of the community.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>In the main, the Bill as I say is highly technical and deals with fitting in its general purposes with the laws dealing with local government, and the authority given by Local Government Acts.  I would like to be assured that it will be possible to restrict or rather to control the uglification of towns by electric signs and advertisements&mdash;sky-writing has been talked about&mdash;and the exaggerated illuminated signs we hear of, promoted of course by the Electricity Supply Board.  I can see that the development of that process will make for anything but beauty, and there should be, I think, within the Bill power given to a local authority to control that kind of development.  I am not sure that it is contained in the Bill.  Perhaps I can be assured of that, and we can hear more of it at a later stage.  Speaking generally, I am sure the Bill will do something towards preventing more harm to the country than has already been occasioned, and will do something to make possible orderly development and to preserve, improve and extend the amenities of the countryside as well as of towns.</P>
    <Speaker pid="DavidRobinson" hpid="Mr. David L. Robinson Mr. David L. Robinson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. David L. Robinson</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister has pointed out that where there is a plan, it will be controlled by the local authorities.  What really matters is: who will control the local authorities? <Col N="934" /> Of course, the answer is the Minister, but I think it must be obvious to Senators that this legislation is as far ahead of public opinion as it is far behind similar legislation in other countries, in point of time.  I should like to call the attention of Senators to the existence of a magnificent organisation known as the Civics Institute of Ireland, and to read a portion of their annual report.  This states:&mdash;</P>
      <P>&ldquo;During the past year the main work of the Institute has been to assist in the formation of Public Utility Societies.  The model rules for such societies, published by the Garden Cities and Town Planning Association, are sold by the Institute and standard forms and all particulars about the formation, organisation and management of societies are obtainable only from the Institute which also undertakes the preliminaries in connection with registration.  The Housing Act of 1932 gives special facilities to Public Utility Societies, and in consequence a large number of inquiries are received, in some cases necessitating the Secretary visiting certain parts of the country in order to assist in their formation.  Seventy new societies were registered during the year and the number of houses built by them should make an appreciable difference to the housing problem... A Conference of societies already engaged in reconditioning houses in Dublin, and those proposing to undertake such work was called by the Institute to consider where there was a possibility of united action in this particular work.  Several meetings of representatives of these groups have been held but as yet no definite plan has resulted.  The work of the supervised Playcentre at Constitution Hill continues... The need for such Playcentres is very pressing and the Institute has been asked to consider the undertaking of two other such centres on the same lines.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I would suggest to Senators that, if they have not themselves any kind of local authority who will prepare plans, they would be very well advised <Col N="935" /> to get in touch with this organisation. I have not the smallest doubt that it will assist them very materially in forming a plan that is more likely to be acceptable to the Minister.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JohnKeaneBart" hpid="Sir John Keane Sir John Keane">
      <NameTxt>Sir John Keane</NameTxt>
      <P>There is one point arising out of the Bill about which I feel very concerned and I should like the Minister to say to what extent it will be protected by this measure. I feel that there is no tradition or no real beauty of outlook in these modern buildings round our towns.  There is no standard or style of domestic architecture and there is no attempt at the creation of any tradition of beauty. While of course it is easy enough to deplore that, it is very hard to suggest a remedy.  One obviously does not want to restrict individual choice but anybody who travels round and looks at many of these new buildings, sees the most terrible polyglot type of work that is revolting to all artistic sense.  When you think of the beauties of the past, you must think how dreadful it will be that this period should go down in history as a period that had no real artistic perception. Arising out of that, I would suggest that the matter can be, to a certain extent, met by a control of material. If you take most of these new schemes &mdash;they are not schemes actually, there are houses built on more or less general plans by individuals&mdash;what is so distasteful is the haphazard jumbling together of different types of material.  In the old days that was not possible.  People had not got the variety of material that is available nowadays.  There was, to a certain extent, a local tradition in each district and they were limited to the material of the district.  Take, for instance, the beautiful architecture of the Cotswolds which is well preserved yet.  There was local stone for the building of the structure and flat stone for the roofing.  You have there handed down through all the ages a material of great beauty which enormously enhanced even the economic value of the district.  People of taste very often connote people of wealth. They go there and make their residence there.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="936" /> I do hope that under this Bill it will be possible to take some steps in that direction.  While you cannot rigidly prescribe one type of material throughout the country, I think you should aim in schemes within localities at a uniform type of material within a given area.  Say, in one case you would have slates and bricks and in another case you would have tiles and roughcast, but you should not jumble these things together without thought or without any artistic sense of perception.  I do-not suggest that under a system of that kind you should have uniformity of design.  I would allow every type of design.  The more design the better, provided you aim at reasonable uniformity in the choice of materials&mdash; not uniformity everywhere, but uniformity in localities.  I hope, as far as it lies in the power of the local authorities, that they will bear that in mind and realise that they are guardians and the trustees not alone over the material wealth of the people to be housed, but over the art and traditional architecture of the country.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOFarrell" hpid="Mr. O'Farrell Mr. O'Farrell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Farrell</NameTxt>
      <P>I am sure everyone will welcome the introduction of this Bill after all the time that has been wasted, I think unnecessarily, by successive Governments in bringing forward such a measure.  The lack of anything in the nature of a town planning scheme is evident on every side. I fancy that Irish towns and villages, with few exceptions, are unsurpassed for ugliness in any country in Western Europe.  I think that will be generally admitted.  The few that are exceptions are small villages that, in the past, have been under the patronage of some estate owner who had a taste for art and beauty and who encouraged, and was able to control, the construction and building of these little villages. But, in the main, ugliness is the predominating feature: drabness, monotony and a general departure from everything that is beautiful and artistic.  In Dublin City, where the Oireachtas sits, we have evidence of chaos and ugliness on every side.  There is the classic example on the Rathmines road.  One may witness there an awful state of chaos; of everything that <Col N="937" /> is characteristic of ugliness in that one area alone.  Everybody that had a decent front garden in that area exploited it commercially by erecting a hideous little shop or a temporary structure in front, with the result that what was, I understand, a decent well-appointed residential district is now one of the most miserable semi-residential and semi-commercial areas that could be found in any city.</P>
      <P>Even some of the adjoining areas that have been built by the Dublin Corporation are little better than rabbit warrens&mdash;whole streets of houses without the slightest idea of a different variety between any two.  Then we have seen the desecration of beauty spots like Howth, the Vico Road, Dalkey, and seaside places like Donabate, where they are now building kiosks and bungalows just as if they were dropped from heaven.  You have the back of one facing the front of another.  You have all sorts of chaos at pretty seaside places which should be developed in an artistic and attractive way.  Another example of that kind of chaos is to be found around Portmarnock and Howth.</P>
      <P>The Bill does not make it compulsory on a local authority to prepare a town planning scheme and unfortunately, as Senator Robinson has said too truly, this Bill is miles in advance of the mentality of the average local authority. If the Minister has not the power to compel a local authority to prepare a scheme and put it into operation, then I am afraid the results to be expected from this Bill will be negligible over a great part of the country for quite a long time to come.  I would suggest that the power which the Minister wields through the making of grants for housing should be used in some way to require local authorities to prepare planning schemes.  He should see that vast sums of public money are not spent on the development of areas in a way that is foreign to everything that is pleasing to the eye.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I notice that the Dublin planning area shall include Meath, Kildare and Wicklow.  I would like to know if, <Col N="938" /> over that big area, it will be necessary before a scheme can be put into operation for each local authority to pass the necessary resolution.  Personally, I approve the idea that Dublin should have control of a widespread area so as to make its schemes comprehensive. I would like, however, that the body in Dublin would have power to override local petty prejudices and traditions of conservatism and reaction that might tend to hold up what otherwise would be a comprehensive scheme. The same consideration will arise in. Cork.  The Cork Corporation and the Lord Mayor are to be the town planning authority for Cork City and County.  We all know the jealousy of Cork men.  They are just as jealous of each other as they are of people from other counties.  I can imagine some Cork County men rebelling against the idea of a mere Cork City man conducting a town planning scheme for the whole of that great county.  I hope, if it is necessary, that the planning authority, whatever it is, will be given all the powers that are necessary so that it may carry out its plan over the area allotted to its jurisdiction.  I welcome the Bill.  I desire to express the hope that the Minister and his Department will see that, as far as it is possible on their part, this measure will be given full expression to, because I think there is no country in the world that requires the operation of a measure such as this more than this country does.</P>
    <Speaker pid="EileenCostello" hpid="Mrs. Costello Mrs. Costello">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Costello</NameTxt>
      <P>I welcome this Bill. According to Senator O'Farrell the situation is bad in Dublin, but I think it is very much worse in some country towns.  One constantly hears of certain things happening, but apparently nothing can be done to prevent certain types of buildings being put up all over the country.  On the public roads you see little bits of shops put up at a corner.  Apparently nobody has any power to stop that.  There is one point on which I would like to have some information from the Minister.  I heard yesterday that a housing scheme had been sanctioned for Tuam, and that the sites chosen are two fields: one at each side of the cemetery. <Col N="939" /> Would the Minister say if that is a fact?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="KathleenBrowne" hpid="Miss Browne Miss Browne">
      <NameTxt>Miss Browne</NameTxt>
      <P>I desire to join in the general chorus of approval at the introduction of this Bill.  At the outset, I want to say that I hope the use of certain classes of material will be prohibited in the erection of buildings for human beings.  I have principally in mind the use of corrugated iron. There is nothing more revolting, I think, than that.  It certainly is not suitable for roofs or even for the side walls of dwelling houses.  Take, for instance, the position in Rosslare, which I happen to live near.  At present anybody can come there and, without any control whatever, put up a little corrugated house, a hut or a bungalow.  The use of corrugated iron is all right for hay sheds or for farm buildings, but it is revolting to see it used for the housing of human beings. There are certain imitations, too, that ought to be cut out in house building.  It is a very common thing to see the wall of a house, which has been built of concrete, plastered and marked out in squares to imitate stone. That really shows execrable taste.  A rough dashing of the wall would be quite all right.  You sometimes see, too, horrible imitations of exquisite old Tudor houses, fine examples of which are so common in England.  The clapping of cheap boards on the end wall of a house, in imitation of these Tudor houses, is simply a monstrosity. I think there is nothing more beautiful than the sight of those old Tudor dwellings, but a cheap imitation of them is positively revolting to any person with an artistic sense.  There is no country in the world in which&mdash; if you exclude the manufacturing areas &mdash;beautiful old villages are so well preserved as they are in England.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Senator Sir John Keane referred to some of the districts where you see beautiful examples of old houses.  They are a beauty and a joy for ever.  In England too, you come across fine old thatched houses, centuries old, which are beautifully preserved.  Here thatched roofs are torn down and a corrugated iron roof put up instead. <Col N="940" /> To see what is going on makes one almost weep.  Instead of removing the thatch and putting up these corrugated iron roofs, it would be adding to the beauty of the countryside if the houses were re-thatched as they used to be years ago.  The people in the part of the County Wexford that I come from have an old traditional love for beautiful gardens.  Outside of certain parts of the North, the people there have a deeper appreciation of beautiful gardens than those in any other county I know.  It is sad to go through some counties and not see even a garden attached to a farmhouse.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JohnCounihan" hpid="Mr. Counihan Mr. Counihan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Counihan</NameTxt>
      <P>Nonsense.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="KathleenBrowne" hpid="Miss Browne Miss Browne">
      <NameTxt>Miss Browne</NameTxt>
      <P>It is quite true.  I know places where the plots attached to cottages are not cultivated, or a flower grown.  This country is terribly backward in all these respects.  I think that where houses are being built, it should be made compulsory on the occupiers to have a little garden cultivated.  On the whole this Bill is very badly needed.  Until they became almost completely dilapidated there was a great deal of beauty about the old Irish whitewashed house.  Most of those old houses were well kept and well preserved.  They were things of beauty, many of them.  Their preservation was a tradition in the country. Now you have a type of foreign architecture clapped down on the country, and I agree with other Senators who have spoken that it is a very bad thing indeed.  I hope the Department will be able to control local authorities in getting this measure administered as it should be, and that for the sake of the country, and for the sake of all of us who love this country, the operation of this Bill will be made a great success.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeorgeCrosbie" hpid="Mr. Crosbie Mr. Crosbie">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Crosbie</NameTxt>
      <P>I would like to emphasise the point that the great necessity in this country is the provision of dwelling houses.  I would object very strongly to anything that would make their erection more costly than it is at present.  Nobody, of course, wants houses with galvanised iron roofs, but there is the danger that <Col N="941" /> local bodies might make regulations that would add considerably to the cost of house building.  If that were to occur, it certainly would be very objectionable. Almost every Senator who has spoken has emphasised the desirability of beauty in the edifices which are to be erected.  I would urge the necessity of having useful, weatherproof and economic buildings put up.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EdwardBigger" hpid="Sir E. Coey-Bigger Sir E. Coey-Bigger">
      <NameTxt>Sir E. Coey-Bigger</NameTxt>
      <P>After all the commendation the Bill has received very little remains to be said.  I would like to join with the other Senators in saying what an excellent Bill this is. It is certainly very much overdue, as it is some years since a Committee was appointed to deal with town planning. This is the first Bill we have had dealing with the question.  One of the points that should be looked into in the administration of the Bill deals with the frontage line of houses.  We have had very many new road arteries constructed, at considerable cost to the ratepayers, where frontage lines have been straightened and streets widened. We should now look ahead for 20 or 30 years, so that every road approaching a city, a town or a village will be improved.  I hope the Committee Stage of this Bill will not be taken for a fortnight.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanTOKelly" hpid="Mr. O'Kelly Mr. O'Kelly">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Kelly</NameTxt>
      <P>I am grateful to Senators who spoke, and particularly grateful to those who have so generously praised this measure.  I do not think I can take any great part of the praise to myself.  That is rather for the Department and for the officials, for the work they have done in producing this important piece of legislation.  I did take an interest in the question from the time I became a Minister, as town planning was a subject in which I had been interested for a considerable time.  If my encouragement meant anything to the Department it was certainly given, so far as the production of the Bill was concerned.  Senator O'Farrell complained of the delay in producing the Bill.  There has been considerable delay but that was not altogether my fault.  In fact I do not think that the fault could be put on anyone's shoulders.  Since I became a <Col N="942" /> Minister I know that the Department were working at the Bill.  I believe I can say with truth that no time was lost so far as the Department was concerned. This is a new form of legislation and there were precedents to be got in America and in England and, as well as I remember old laws relating to the construction of buildings, rights of way, and matters of that kind, that were passed in the Napoleonic regime in France.  Wherever precedents could be got at all the laws and regulations were searched out and examined and used, so far as we could use them, in producing the Bill.  As Senator Johnson stated, it is a very technical kind of Bill.  In order to deal with this question adequately it had to be technical.  There are so many laws in existence giving powers to local authorities, and rights to private people, that local authorities or the Government would have to amend laws and regulations, when producing a Bill of this kind, and that that makes it very technical.  Senator Bagwell spoke of the administration of the Bill. A good deal will, of course, depend on administration.  Some Senator said that we were to a certain extent in advance of public opinion here on the question of town planning, but the discussions that took place in the Dáil and in this House, and the reports in the newspapers, will help to educate public opinion.  There has been considerable interest shown in the Press, if not so much by professional men and women who one would expect would be interested in this matter. Among architects and artists, there has not been as much interest shown as I would like.  A considerable amount of interest has been evinced in the Press and valuable suggestions made. The Department and the officials concerned are deeply interested in the subject and they have had to educate themselves for the production of the Bill.  As far as the administration by headquarters is concerned every encouragement is certain to be given to local authorities to produce plans. Once the plans have been adopted, and resolutions passed by local authorities, the Minister has very considerable powers under the Bill, so that what the <Col N="943" /> Minister and the Department regard as the proper thing will be done by local authorities.</P>
      <P>In principle the Bill is not mandatory. It is voluntary on local authorities to adopt it or not to adopt it, and to use the powers as they wish. Whatever we can do in the Department to encourage local authorities to use their power for town planning and improving their localities we will try to do.  We will instruct inspectors who travel around in connection with housing and other schemes to see the officials of local authorities and to try and get them interested in the subject, and to use all the powers conferred on them.  There are, unquestionably, defects in the Bill, many of which will not be discovered until it has been in operation for a few years. Naturally, the Dáil and the Seanad will use their best endeavours to find out any of the defects that exist.  I am sure there are some defects but we provided the best we could for the future.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelOHanlon" hpid="Mr. O'Hanlon Mr. O'Hanlon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Hanlon</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister said in a few years.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Cathaoirleach Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I think the Minister said &ldquo;now.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanTOKelly" hpid="Mr. O'Kelly Mr. O'Kelly">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Kelly</NameTxt>
      <P>I said I hoped the Seanad would point out the defects now.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelComynKC" hpid="Mr. Comyn Mr. Comyn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Comyn</NameTxt>
      <P>The interjection is not relevant.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. Kelly Mr. Kelly">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Kelly</NameTxt>
      <P>It is quite certain there are defects in the Bill that will only be discovered in the process of using the measure.  Senator Sir John Keane raised a point dealing with the regulation of buildings.  If he looks at Part II, Section 2, he will find it says:&mdash;</P>
      <P>Regulating and controlling or enabling the responsible authority to regulate and control the design, colour, and materials of buildings and other structures.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Town planning has to be adopted by the local authority, and when that is done and a resolution is passed, power is in the local authority primarily, and secondly in the hands of the <Col N="944" /> Department of Local Government, to see that the regulations suit the locality, and that houses built there are suitable from the aesthetic as well as from the economic point of view. I agree with Senator Crosbie when he talked about the provision of houses being the first consideration, even before the aesthetic side.  It is necessary to have the houses built.  We are driving ahead there, as far as we can, in order to get local authorities to agree to provide houses.  Many of them are doing so quite well; some not so well.  I think the Senator's own county is, unfortunately, one of the worst in that respect.  Cork City is doing remarkably well.  Generally speaking, while it is quite true to say that we are trying, as far as our powers go, to get local authorities to take into consideration the necessity for economy, we are also trying, where housing schemes are submitted, to improve the designs from the aesthetic point of view, within the limits of the money available.  Senator Mrs. Costello referred to certain types of shops that have been built at the corners of roads and to ugly structures that have been put up.  There are powers in the Local Government Act, 1925, dealing with the types of structures that can be put up within 25 or 30 yards of roads, and particularly dealing with shops, so that these can be regulated.  There is power to prevent the erection of ugly structures that would impede the view or obstruct the roads.  That power exists under the Act of 1925, but far too few local authorities adopted it.</P>
    <Speaker pid="EileenCostello" hpid="Mrs. Costello Mrs. Costello">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Costello</NameTxt>
      <P>Could the Minister explain the position with regard to the buildings I refer to?  I heard yesterday that the Department of Local Government had sanctioned building sites at each side of a cemetery.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanTOKelly" hpid="Mr. O'Kelly Mr. O'Kelly">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Kelly</NameTxt>
      <P>Where?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EileenCostello" hpid="Mrs. Costello Mrs. Costello">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Costello</NameTxt>
      <P>In Tuam.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanTOKelly" hpid="Mr. O'Kelly Mr. O'Kelly">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Kelly </NameTxt>
      <P>I do not know about it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EileenCostello" hpid="Mrs. Costello Mrs. Costello">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Costello</NameTxt>
      <P>I was told it was a fact.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanTOKelly" hpid="Mr. O'Kelly Mr. O'Kelly">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Kelly</NameTxt>
      <P>This Bill has been for a considerable time before the Dáil.  It <Col N="945" /> is not by any means a Party measure. We are anxious to get all the help we can to make it a valuable piece of legislation. It is a new type of legislation. There is not much help to be got from abroad.  Anything we could get that was of practical value we have included.  We are not in any sense anxious to rush it through the Oireachtas.  The Seanad will, I believe, take whatever time it thinks necessary for consideration of the Committee Stage.  Senator Sir Edward Bigger suggested a fortnight.  If three weeks or a month are required we will not object, although we are very anxious to get the Bill through, and to have the powers it contains put into operation immediately.  If extra time makes any difference, and if Senators would like that time to consider amendments, I would be quite happy to agree.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>Committee Stage fixed for April 25.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Local Services (Temporary Economies)" RHead="(No. 2) Bill, 1933&mdash;Second Stage">
    <Title>Local Services (Temporary Economies) (No. 2) Bill, 1933&mdash;Second Stage.</Title>
    <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That the Bill be now read a Second Time.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="SeanTOKelly" hpid="Minister for Local Government and Public Health (Mr. O'Kelly) Minister for Local Government and Public Health (Mr. O'Kelly)">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Local Government and Public Health (Mr. O'Kelly)</NameTxt>
      <P>The object of this Bill is to effect economies in the local services by the making of deductions from remuneration payable during the current local financial year to officers of local authorities.  The corresponding Bill which provided for economies in the public services was before the Oireachtas last summer, and passed into law in October last.  This Act&mdash;the Public Services (Temporary Economies) Act&mdash;contemplated the reduction of expenditure on salaries, not only in the public services, but also in salaries of local bodies where a proportion of such salaries was met by grants payable to local bodies.  Section 11 of that Act provided for deductions from such grants to such extent as would be determined having regard to the proportion of such grants ordinarily applied towards the payment of salaries. The section, however, goes on to provide that no deduction shall be made from grants to local bodies in <Col N="946" /> respect of services under the control of the Minister for Local Government and Public Health where such bodies have made approved deductions from the salaries of their officers.  The intention here was that the local body should make the deduction, and there would accrue a proportionate saving to the Exchequer in respect of all claims made by local bodies for recoupment of expenditure on salaries.</P>
      <P>As Senators are aware, a growing proportion of local expenditure is being met by way of grants from State funds and the present Bill is accordingly a necessary implementation of Government policy in connection with the securing of economies by deductions from salaries as set out in the Public Services (Temporary Economies) Act. The Act referred to passed into law, as I have said, in October last, but it was not found possible to complete the preparation of the Bill relating to local salaries until the present year, and accordingly the period of operation of the Bill will be the current local financial year instead of the last financial year to which the Act of 1933 related.</P>
      <P>The deductions to be made from salaries of local officers will be in accordance with the scales set out in the Schedule to the Bill.  Parts I and II of the Schedule contain different scales of deduction applicable to salaries carrying cost-of-living bonus and to fixed salaries respectively.  The salaries which have carried a bonus varying with the cost of living have been subject to regular reduction in recent years in accordance with the fall in the cost of living.  The fixed salaries which have not varied with the cost of living have, on the other hand, remained constant over a period of fall in prices.  It is, therefore, proposed to make the deductions applicable to the latter type of salaries on scales higher than the scales applicable to the salaries which have in fact been reduced from time to time owing to the gradual fall in the cost of living. Part III of the Schedule will mainly relate to professional men, not being whole-time officers of the local authority, employed at special rates of remuneration for particular works.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="947" /> In the case of dispensary doctors, a special provision is included in the Bill to the effect that £50 of their annual salary shall not be taken into account in the calculation of the deductions.</P>
    <P>Special provision is made for the preservation of pension rights.  No deductions made under this Act will affect the amount of salary by reference to which a pension or gratuity is to be computed.</P>
    <P>The Bill contains further provisions of an administrative nature as regards the returns to be furnished by officers to the chief executive officers of each local authority by whom they are employed and also as regards the duty of chief executive officers of local authorities who are required to furnish returns of the salaries of each officer in the employment of the local authority.</P>
    <Speaker pid="McGillycuddyReeks" hpid="The McGillycuddy of the Reeks The McGillycuddy of the Reeks">
      <NameTxt>The McGillycuddy of the Reeks</NameTxt>
      <P>I regret that the Minister has seen fit to introduce this Bill.  The present scale of remuneration of public servants of this State is, I think, a sensible scale.  Revolutionary movements such as we have had in this country generally carry with them some of the commitments of the parent body.  Some of these are good and some of them are not.  In this case, we have what I regard as a good one. I refer to the system of adequate payment of public servants which we have inherited from the British.  The British, who are extraordinarily good shopkeepers, invariably paid their public servants on what might be regarded as a liberal scale.  Why? Because they know that it has, in the end, paid them extremely well.  Other countries on the Continent of Europe and elsewhere have not always paid on the same scale and, in many cases, the penuriousness exercised had come back to roost.  That was particularly the case with German officials. During the war one remarkable and well-known case, due to want of proper remuneration of a German official, led to the whole of the German Admiralty code being given away to the British, thus enabling the British, throughout the whole of the war, to <Col N="948" /> read all the messages of the German ships at sea.  Some of these things are bound to happen when you lower the standard of living of your public servants.  I suppose that, with a peasant population such as ours, it is probably good politics to introduce a Bill of this kind, because the average peasant likes to see people getting a little bit less, particularly when he is getting less himself.  In the end, I think, the peasant will be the poorer man.  The public services must suffer by this type of cut because you will not have the best type of man trying to enter them.  The men engaged in these services spend a good deal on their education.  They start on a very much lower scale than the manager of a business undertaking with the same responsibilities.  Many thousands of pounds pass through the hands of some of them in a year and, on the medical side, they are charged with the care of very thickly populated districts.</P>
      <P>When they start, there is no definite basis of remuneration.  Their preliminary salary is, I admit, subject to the approval of the Minister for Local Government and Public Health, but it is dependent a good deal on the amount of influence that can be exercised when the appointment comes before the local body.  I have been a member of one of those local bodies and I have seen that happen very often.  In that way, you can have a variation in the initial salary and, very often, in the increments in the different counties.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The officers appointed settle down in these counties and make commitments. They marry and possibly buy houses, because they know that they are going to spend their lives in the district. They may be purchasing on the instalment system, they effect insurances, provide for the education of their children and then, suddenly, a cut of this kind comes along.  As regards the value of the service of these public officers, it is my personal experience that practically the whole conduct of the public business and the security of the ratepayers devolve on these public servants.  In addition, they have to be armed at every point to counter ill-considered suggestions made by <Col N="949" /> representatives of the people.  It is not the councillors who make these suggestions who have to face the music when the auditor comes around.  It is the officers who have to answer the questions and to try to prevent surcharges. Were it not for their personal pride in their work and the credit of the service to which they belong, the expense of local government would be colossal.  What else is there to prevent an officer seeing the proposals of all and sundry councillors in a rosy light and adding the cost to the annual bill for rates?  They will not suffer to any extent and, if there is any protest, they can shelter behind the orders given. I regret that the Minister, who I am certain knows much better, has asked us to consider a Bill of this nature at this time when other Dominions, such as South Africa, and Britain are restoring these cuts.  The London County Council has restored all the economy cuts made, with the exception of the cut in the teachers' salaries.  I believe that that will be restored very soon.</P>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasForan" hpid="Mr. Foran Mr. Foran">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Foran</NameTxt>
      <P>Was it the new county council that restored the cuts?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="McGillycuddyReeks" hpid="The McGillycuddy of the Reeks The McGillycuddy of the Reeks">
      <NameTxt>The McGillycuddy of the Reeks</NameTxt>
      <P>If the Minister could say that this £35,000 is an essential economy, he would have my unqualified support for this Bill as a temporary measure.  I presume, however, that this saving is going to be used to provide for losses which cannot be met by way of additional grants from the Government.  I fear that the Bill is going to do three things &mdash;lower the standard of the public service; inflict an injustice on individuals, because, although it is a flat cut according to salaries, the original basic rates are different; and react to the disadvantage of the ratepayers.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnBagwell" hpid="Mr. Bagwell Mr. Bagwell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Bagwell</NameTxt>
      <P>There can be only one reason for this Bill.  That is, the need for economy in local government. Since it will save but a small sum relatively, one is justified in inferring that the need for economy is very great.  If that is so, why begin with salaries of £300 a year?  Why not go below that figure and apply the same sort of scale to all people employed by local authorities? I can see no reason for the discrimination.  If that were done, there would be a real economy&mdash;<Col N="950" /> an economy of some volume.  Is this discrimination against people who are mostly technical men, with special qualifications, getting £300 a year and over, discrimination on merits or discrimination on votes?  It is common knowledge that, except in the case of the larger cities, the employees of local authorities are, broadly speaking, paid much better than similar workers employed by private individuals or companies who have to meet the wage bill out of their own earnings and are obliged to have regard to ordinary commercial considerations which, too frequently, are entirely ignored in the case of local authorities.  For these reasons, before dealing with so discriminatory a Bill as this, we ought to be certain of what we are doing. I think it would be very desirable that we should know of the general position and of the general need before we go in for saving this particularly segregrated and comparatively small sum. I suggest to the Minister that the debate on this Bill should not be resumed until after the discussion on the Budget.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOFarrell" hpid="Mr. O'Farrell Mr. O'Farrell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Farrell </NameTxt>
      <P>On a Bill of this kind, one would wish to think that what the Government wanted was money and that they were not going, merely as a gesture, to cut salaries for the mere sake of cutting.  If it is money they are looking for, the amount involved is negligible even in a country as small as this.  The Minister indicated, on the Second Reading of the measure in the other House, that the total saving would be about £35,000.  That is not the saving to the Exchequer alone but to the Exchequer and to the local authorities combined. It would probably be divided between them in about equal parts.  The Treasury will gain, therefore, about £16,000 or £17,000 as a result of the operation of this Bill.  That is an extraordinarily small economy to necessitate the introduction of a special Bill covering all the local authorities of this country.  So far as I can gather, the Bill is introduced to give effect to the principle that a certain amount of sacrifice must be made by certain sections.  The bulk of the sacrifice here would be on the part of the doctors.  Nobody who knows the <Col N="951" /> salaries paid to doctors and medical officers and all that has to be done in order to get the jobs would say that they are overpaid.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>It has been said, and I do not know with what amount of truth, that for every hundred doctors we train in this country, eighty have to find occupation outside, either in Great Britain or the Dominions.  We keep back one-fifth and this one-fifth we want to try and harrow and generally treat as if they were enemies rather than friends of the people.  We had a very eloquent, and at the same time deplorable example, of what can happen at the appointment of a medical officer of public health in the case recently in Monaghan.  Every class of individual, Senators, Deputies, professional men and gangsters were brought into play in connection with this appointment. In such instances one can imagine the amount of graft necessary in expenditure before a post of this kind can be obtained.  Another shocking business was that which occurred at Loughrea where a volunteer force had to be formed to protect a man, who took up a medical position, from physical violence.  That man has my sincere admiration for standing out against all this hooliganism and maintaining his position.  He has held on to his post although about two-thirds of his income which would come from private practice must be non-existent.  But you must have regard to all these circumstances before cutting salaries for the purpose of making this gesture.  A great number of the local authorities, in this country, are made up of people who unfortunately have few of the good things of life.  If they hear of a man earning £3 or £4 a week they look upon him as a semi-millionaire.  They are incapable of making allowance for all the money and all the effort that have been spent upon the training of that man in the school and the University. They look at the question on the basis of unskilled labour.  If a professional man has twice the wages of a labourer lie is regarded as well paid.  Unfortunately that tendency is encouraged and fostered by the present Government <Col N="952" /> cutting down the salaries of men who have qualified for professional positions.  It is inclined to drive out of the country the very best men.  I do not believe in cutting wages at all but I do not believe in the grading process&mdash;cutting down to the lowest possible level of the worst paid people in the country.  If there is one thing that we cannot dispense with it is the skill of the professional man.  Instead of driving them elsewhere where there is a better harvest we should encourage them in the manner in which we treat them.  This Bill is entirely futile except that it will possibly drive out of the country the best type of professional men.</P>
    <P>From 1920 upwards, when we first repudiated British local government, there has been a definite tendency to hit that type of official, such as secretaries of county councils and doctors and professional men, drawing salaries, as if they were part of the British garrison.  The tendency was to hit men with big salaries; they were considered fair game.  There were cases where salaries fixed seemed to be excessive having regard to the duties performed, but in most cases when vacancies occurred salaries were reduced to one-third of what they were recently.  Yet these men who got those positions at those reduced salaries are to be cut again now. Salaries recently offered for public appointments are on a scandalous grade; £250 is mentioned as the yearly salary of a skilled engineer after all his years of college and university training.  The average rate of increment has been scaled down from £10 to anything as low as £1, as I saw recently in the case of a particular appointment.  That is the mentality that influences those who are fixing these salaries.  The Minister here fixes a minimum, but he makes no maximum.  Local authorities can cut down as deeply as they like subject to his sanction, and judging by the outlook of the Minister and the Government there is nothing to prevent them doing this, so that instead of raising the lower towards the higher we are at present depressing the higher down to the lowest in the land. <Col N="953" /> That is an entirely retrograde principle and I most emphatically condemn the futility of it.  It is going to bring in no material gain to the Exchequer or the local authorities.  No ratepayer will benefit to the extent of a package of cigarettes whereas we are committing ourselves to the principle that purchasing power has to come down.</P>
    <Speaker pid="ErnestBlythe" hpid="Mr. Blythe Mr. Blythe">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Blythe</NameTxt>
      <P>This can only be regarded, I think, as a piece of cynical humbug on the part of the Government. If it was a piece of cynical humbug, and hit nobody, we need not say much about it, but it is a piece of political humbug that is going to produce undoubted hardships on a considerable number of people.  It is patent humbug because it cannot effect, and is not intended to effect, cuts in salaries to which it should be directed.  There is no reason to believe that as a result of the passage of this Bill there will be any relief to the ratepayers or the taxpayers, or that the burden that they have to pay to the State will be in any way reduced. If the Government were pursuing a policy of keeping rates and taxes as low as possible, there might be something to be said for the policy of the cuts, although the policy of the cuts should not be operated on the basis proposed in the Bill.  But when we see the general policy of this Administration we can understand that the few pounds that may be saved is going to be wasted on some entirely futile or fantastic product which is outlined already, or is sure to be forthcoming in a very short time from those who are driving the Government Party.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I would not myself suggest or recommend the Seanad to reject this Bill.  It is not a certified Money Bill, but its objects are finance, and it is in a sense, although not technically, a Money Bill. For that reason I would not suggest that the Seanad should take upon itself to reject the Bill, but I do think the Seanad ought to consider the details of the Bill on the Committee Stage.  I believe it is quite within the competence of this House, and quite within the constitutional province of this House to amend the Bill if they see that some of the hardships are as great as I believe some of them are. <Col N="954" /> While adopting that attitude, I do not believe that this House should be taken as accepting the view that there is nothing to be said for the principle of the Bill in the circumstances of the moment.  Possibly the Government expect to get some political advantage out of the Bill, in the hope that some individuals throughout the country may feel that this is some movement in the direction of economy, or in the nature of relief of the present burdens.  I believe that, in fact, they will get very little political kudos out of it.  The general situation is altogether too serious for people to be deceived now by measures of this sort that have the effect of disturbing and, perhaps, hurting and humiliating certain classes, and which at most can only give the Government a few pounds to waste upon some political or foolish project such as we have had too many of at the present time.</P>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasForan" hpid="Mr. Foran Mr. Foran">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Foran</NameTxt>
      <P>I only rise to say I cannot understand Senator Blythe's mentality. He talks about this measure as humbug, and injurious humbug.  He tells us it is not going to do any good to the ratepayers or to the taxpayers, but he is going to vote for it.  He went on to examine it from a political point of view, and thinks that the Government are looking to getting kudos out of it, and he does not think that they can get very much kudos out of it.  But Senator Blythe did not go into the merits or demerits of the Bill.  It will be interesting to see what attitude he takes when the Seanad is examining them.  At any rate it will be interesting to see what he will do when it comes to a question of a division on this Bill.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelComynKC" hpid="Mr. Comyn Mr. Comyn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Comyn</NameTxt>
      <P>I think if anybody should seek political kudos or votes at our prospective election, what he would be likely to say is that officers of public authorities should have good salaries and should have no cuts.  Why should the salaries of secretaries of county councils and other officers be reduced?  That is the popular thing to say, but the people charged with the administration of a country have responsibilities other than that.  It is desirable that in the circumstances in <Col N="955" /> which this country is placed, where some classes of the community are making very great sacrifices, that all classes should have an opportunity of contributing in some way to the sacrifices that are being made.  I think there are a great many local officials who will be proud to be able to say hereafter: &ldquo;Very well, the farmer has made his sacrifices, we will make our sacrifices.&rdquo;  I have heard no official of any local authority screaming at this. The only people who are screaming, like stuck pigs, are the people who are expecting to get political kudos out of the report of the speech they make against this Bill.  Senator O'Farrell, who always brings the most cogent arguments to the support of any position he takes up, has, I think, fixed upon one class of local officials that has upheld the best traditions of this country&mdash;the dispensary doctor.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>In the course of his speech I was looking through the Bill to discover what I had read already&mdash;that portion of the salary of a dispensary doctor to the extent of £50 is not subject to the percentage reduction.  It is a matter for consideration on the Committee Stage whether you should exempt a sum greater than £50.  As Senator Blythe has said, this is a financial measure and we should be very careful as to our treatment of it.  In fact, during Senator Blythe's speech we had an example of very sound sense when he said that the Seanad should not interfere to reject this measure.  We had an example of what he thought very good politics when he told us he was the champion of local officials. Of course they are distributed throughout the country.  They are influential men.  They have votes and they know where votes are to be got.  Their own vote is useful and their influence is more useful still.  So it is a very popular thing to support what he believes to be the wish of public officials or local officials.  But I do not think it is the wish of local officials. I think there are a great many local officials who will be proud that they, as well as the farmers who pay them, are making sacrifices in the times through which we are passing.  Of <Col N="956" /> course Senator The McGillycuddy who knows all about local officials smiles broadly and audibly at that suggestion but I know something about local officials as well as he.</P>
    <P>I think it is a courageous action on the part of the Ministry to come forward with a measure like this.  It does not mean very much&mdash;£36,500 a year&mdash;but why should they not try to economise to the extent of £36,000 a year?  In a fortnight's time we shall have men speaking eloquently as to the impossibility of meeting the charges of government and of the Budget increasing by leaps and bounds.  They will be very eloquent on that, but if the Budget is to be reduced it can only be reduced by economies here and there, small economies, and £36,500 is not such a small sum as people would be inclined to imagine.  If the Budget is increasing, the demands upon the public purse are naturally increasing in proportion, and the Minister by introducing this measure has shown that, although we have to meet charges that are increasing, we are endeavouring to curtail wherever we can and to economise wherever possible.  If this is a gesture, I think it is a very proper gesture.  The farmers are suffering considerably at the present time.  They have been suffering for the past two or three years very much and I think they will be glad to know that public servants, both servants of the central authority and servants of the local bodies, are making sacrifices too, sacrifices not by any means equal to the sacrifices which the farmers are making but that nevertheless they are bearing some share of the burden.</P>
    <P>It has been said, I think by Senator Blythe or Senator O'Farrell, that officers of local authorities have entered into commitments and have budgeted on the assumption that their salaries were to remain unaltered. Several people have budgeted on a similar assumption and have found that their annual income has decreased in the last two or three years.  The farmers have found that it is not now possible to educate their sons as it was two or three years ago.  You must always remember that this is a community mainly depending upon agriculture <Col N="957" /> and the farmers of this country at present&mdash;I hope only for a very temporary period&mdash;are suffering considerably. They are the people who are paying and I think they should be relieved wherever relief is possible. Even if it is not very substantial, a gesture should be made to show that others are willing to help them.  I think it is a courageous thing on the part of the Government to run the risk of the unpopularity which will result from this saving of £36,500. They knew very well that it was an unpopular thing to do and, of course, they must have anticipated that full advantage would be taken of it by their opponents who for the occasion, and for the occasion alone, are prepared to purport to defend officials of local bodies who have not asked them to speak on this subject at all.</P>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasFarren" hpid="Mr. Farren Mr. Farren">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Farren</NameTxt>
      <P>When I saw this Bill I was wondering what the justification was for the introduction of it.  The amount involved, when it is spread over all the local authorities in the country, will be a mere bagatelle as far as these authorities are concerned.  It will not affect in the slightest degree the amount of local or national taxation. It appears to me that the only justification for the introduction of the Bill is the fact that a Bill of a similar type was introduced and passed last year dealing with civil servants.  I was opposed to that Bill and I am more strongly opposed to this Bill.  An important fact that has got to be remembered in connection with this Bill is that it proposes that the employees of local authorities receiving over a certain remuneration shall be subjected to a graduated scale of reduction for a temporary period.  I suppose if we take the City of Dublin away, the amount involved for the other local authorities is not worth the expense and all the trouble necessitated by the Bill, the time taken up by the draftsmen, the cost of printing and the time spent by the Oireachtas in debating it.  Senator Comyn talks about the unpopularity of the Bill.  I do not agree with him.  I think from the point of view of the Government, it is a very popular Bill.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="958" />
    <Speaker pid="MichaelComynKC" hpid="Mr. Comyn Mr. Comyn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Comyn</NameTxt>
      <P>That is because it is felt to be necessary.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasFarren" hpid="Mr. Farren Mr. Farren">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Farren</NameTxt>
      <P>It is popular because of this fact, that we have arrived at the stage that people who have been unsuccessful in securing some of these posts are jealous of others who have more brains than they had, and who secured these posts in open competition. Senator Comyn talks about the farmers, but I venture to say that the majority of young men employed by local authorities are sons of farmers who have won their spurs in open competition. I know some little thing about local government, and I know that over a quarter of a century ago the Dublin Corporation, as the Minister is well aware because, I think, he took a leading part in bringing it into operation, even before the Government of the day thought of it, introduced a system of competitive examination for clerkships in the service.  I think the Minister will agree with me that that was the best thing ever done by the Dublin Corporation.  By that system of fair open competition, we got the best service of any city in the world.  It attracted the best brains in the country to the service, and it had the result of preventing the emigration of some of the best brains of the country, such as we have in the case of the medical profession and other professions.  Considering the type of person that was recruited to that employment, the remuneration was not more than it should be.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I have always believed that if we give a person responsibility and if we get a person who is fitted to accept that responsibility and to carry out the duties attached to it, we should pay him well.  I think it is true to say that the citizens of Dublin, through the system of open competitive examination got good, faithful and efficient service from the people recruited into their employment.  It is all very well to talk about gestures, but we must not forget another important fact, that owing to the amount of legislation dealing with social matters passed since the setting up of this State, a tremendous amount of extra work has been piled on to the officials of local <Col N="959" /> authorities in this country.  I do not think that will be denied.  The very Bill we had here to-day, when it becomes an Act, will throw an enormous amount of responsibility and extra work on local officials&mdash;engineers, architects and officials of that kind who will have to do with what was correctly described as a very intricate piece of legislation.</P>
    <P>We ought not to lose sight of the fact that employees of local authorities during recent years owing to the putting into operation of many items of social legislation have had a considerable amount of increased technical work thrown upon them.  We ought not to forget either that the majority of the employees of local authorities have been subject to the reductions in the cost-of-living bonus.  Some of them had salaries which were fixed apart from the cost-of-living bonus but I think the great majority of the salaries of employees of local authorities carry with them the cost-of-living bonus which has been fluctuating with the cost of living.  In consequence, these people already have suffered reductions in their salaries.  In addition, they have contributed a fair quota to any sacrifices that may be required.  It was only last year that the income tax was raised from 3/6 to 5/- in the £.  These people have had to pay their share of that.  In passing, I might say that employees of local authorities are not in the same position as other people because the tax-gatherer knows exactly the full amount of their remuneration as it appears in the public accounts.  They have to pay every penny that they are bound to pay in income tax.  They are not in the happy position of other people who are able to diddle the income tax authorities until they are caught.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelComynKC" hpid="Mr. Comyn Mr. Comyn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Comyn</NameTxt>
      <P>We cannot assume in this Seanad that the law is being disobeyed by diddlers.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasFarren" hpid="Mr. Farren Mr. Farren">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Farren</NameTxt>
      <P>For a lawyer Senator Comyn is terribly innocent.  I am really surprised at his innocence.  In fact, I am inclined to think he must be one of Mark Twain's Innocents.  As I <Col N="960" /> was saying these local officials have to pay every penny that they are legally liable for in income tax.  The amount involved in this Bill is not worth all the trouble that has been made about it, and therefore I think it is unfair for the Government to introduce it.  We have arrived at a stage here when we ought not to be curtailing the spending power of any section of the community. One hears of shopkeepers and others complaining of the lack of business. If the Government are going to curtail the spending power of people who do spend, and who have been in a position to spend, then I do not think they are going to derive a lot of benefit from this measure.  Under all the circumstances I think it is unwise for the Government to be going ahead with this Bill.  As I voted against the other Bill, I will be consistent and vote against this one.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasToal" hpid="Mr. Toal Mr. Toal">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Toal</NameTxt>
      <P>At the risk of doing the unpopular thing, I propose to vote for the &ldquo;cuts&rdquo; proposed in this Bill.  I realise that savings must be effected. Everybody connected with local government knows the position of the farmers in this country: that every possible saving, no matter how small, must be effected because the farmers have now no income that they can rely upon.  Their income has completely disappeared.  Public officials have an assured income, whether it be large or small.  I regret that the necessity has arisen for making cuts in their salaries. As a rule, the public boards of the country are served by very good officials.  It is certainly not an encouragement to them to have their salaries cut, but the necessities of the time compel us to assent to this.  I think it is only right that they should suffer as well as others.  Up to the present it is the farmers mostly who have had to do the suffering.  It is something to find here to-day that it is realised on all sides that the farmers are suffering.  I only wish that some Senators would take a journey through the country and see the actual sufferings of the farmers, and what their prospects are of being able to discharge their liabilities.  As I have said, it is not a popular thing to vote <Col N="961" /> for a measure of this kind, but at times necessity compels representative men to do things that are unpopular.</P>
      <P>Some remarks were made, I suppose in a joking way, about local government in the County Monaghan.  I stand for the purity of the local government administration in the County Monaghan&mdash;that its standard compares favourably with that of any other county.  A case has arisen in the county which I am very sorry occurred. The county council deeply deplores the fact that such a thing occurred. They were not responsible for it.  The Act of Parliament was changed which gave the right to the Appointments Commissioners to send down one name, and one only.  Therefore, that gave a chance for the sort of thing that has been referred to to be introduced by men inclined that way.  From my long experience of local government in the County Monaghan I can stand over the purity and honesty of its administration. I am proud to be a member of the Monaghan County Council, notwithstanding the view held that that particular case brought disgrace and dishonour on the county.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EdwardBigger" hpid="Sir E. Coey Bigger Sir E. Coey Bigger">
      <NameTxt>Sir E. Coey Bigger</NameTxt>
      <P>I regret very much the introduction of this Bill. Several Senators have expressed regret that the medical officers employed by local bodies should be included under it.  We all know that medical officers have been very badly hit.  Their private practice has almost completely disappeared.  To provide a mode of conveyance the Bill only allows a sum of £50.  That will not nearly cover the cost of it.  Therefore, the cuts proposed under this Bill will affect part of doctors' expenses.  A well-established principle is also being departed from in connection with this Bill, the principle that when an official was appointed at a particular salary it was not to be reduced.  It was the practice in many cases, to give increases, but never to reduce the salary originally fixed.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The introduction of such a principle in this Bill is a very serious matter, and one which I think this House should take notice of.  We all know that farmers are suffering a great deal at the present time, but <Col N="962" /> when times were good with the farmers there was never any suggestion that the medical officers' salaries should be increased.  Therefore, why should they be reduced now?  The other points that I wish to deal with can be deferred until we reach the Committee Stage, when I propose to move certain amendments.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDouglas" hpid="Mr. Douglas Mr. Douglas">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Douglas</NameTxt>
      <P>I think we have to regard this Bill from the point of view as to whether it is one which, however much we may dislike it, ought to be rejected by this House, and I think it is perfectly clear to most of us that we ought not to take that course.  It seems to me that most of the arguments I have listened to and that I have heard adduced against this Bill are really arguments against maintaining this Government in power.  Senator Farren, of course, will not agree.  He has to choose between two evils.  He will, no doubt, choose the least, which I think the bigger.  It seems to be rather ridiculous to argue in this House, since we have no power to alter the Government of the country, that it is unwise to reduce the spending power of anybody at the present time: that the net effect of that will be to reduce trade.  Personally, I agree absolutely with Senator Farren in that, but I think it is totally contrary to the policy which is being adopted as the State policy.  Therefore, to argue it in relation to one Bill alone is, to my mind, futile.  Personally, I doubt if, even in bad times, it is wise to single out officials appointed on a specific basis&mdash;officials not subject to increases and certainly not to substantial increases because of the prosperity of the times&mdash;and say that we are going to save £35,000 a year by a small reduction in their salaries.  I say that not because I have sympathy only with them.  Most people, outside of those holding official positions, would be delighted if the Government could give them a guarantee that their incomes are not going to be reduced by more than ten per cent.  Personally, I would be very glad to have such a guarantee, but I can see no hope of getting it.  It is not from the point of view of sympathy with officials <Col N="963" /> having to share that cut that I doubt the wisdom of this Bill, but because it seems to me that, as far as possible, we ought to eliminate officials appointed by local authorities or by the State from the vagaries of change due very largely to political or semipolitical conditions, and that it is only as a sheer absolute necessity, which makes it necessary to cut salaries, you can get proper political justification for doing so in the matter of officials.</P>
      <P>There might be a case for stopping increases over a period when there was a real necessity for it, but I have always doubted the wisdom of taking officials who, as I have said, have been appointed on a specific basis and deducting a rigid percentage of their remuneration.  However, although I doubt the wisdom of this Bill I do not believe, having regard to the circumstances and having regard to what we know to be the feeling in the country, that this House would be justified in rejecting the Bill.  Senator Comyn's argument was probably the best argument that could be adduced for the Bill: that because certain people are suffering, therefore we must make others suffer, and that as a gesture we should agree to this to show that we are fair to all.  I think that if I had to justify the Bill I should have to fall back on some other argument, but I do not think there is any better argument that can be adduced&mdash;the facts being as they are and knowing that it is the policy of the Government, perhaps rightly, to reduce the spending power of a very considerable portion of the population.  They may not intend to do it, but for the time being that is a necessary part of their policy, and they have got the support of a majority in the other House for doing it.  I do not believe that the Seanad would be justified in trying to hold up this Bill.  One may, of course, suggest possible amendments, but I think that to reject the Bill would be only folly.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Cathaoirleach Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister to conclude.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="964" />
    <Speaker pid="SeanTOKelly" hpid="Minister for Local Government and Public Health (Mr. O'Kelly) Minister for Local Government and Public Health (Mr. O'Kelly)">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Local Government and Public Health (Mr. O'Kelly)</NameTxt>
      <P>It is evident that this Bill is not received with the same enthusiasm as the last one that I had the pleasure of putting before the House for Second Reading to-day.  I agree with Senator Comyn and Senator Toal that this is not a popular measure in the country.  I think that any Government that would expect that every measure it introduced would be a popular measure would be a Government that would not last long and would not be worthy of its position.  I believe that economies are necessary at the present time.  It is not due to the present Government that there has been such a calamitous fall in the value of agricultural produce. It has been falling and falling rapidly all over the world, in the last seven or eight years, and nowhere more than in the wealthiest country in the world, which is probably the United States.  The farmers there are in a far worse position than the farmers here.  I think I can use the phrase without exaggeration that farmers in Western America whom I knew, personally, some years ago to be rolling in wealth are to-day ready to be thrown out on the roadside.  That is true of the United States.  Bad as the situation may be here it is not nearly as bad as it is in the United States and in other parts of the world. Farmers certainly have lost.  Prices have continued to fall in the last year or two, but for some classes of agricultural produce the prices that our farmers are getting are certainly better than they were two years ago. Certainly I do not regard it as a popular measure for a Minister for Local Government to bring in a Bill cutting the salaries of those throughout the country on whom he has to rely to carry out local government. But it is a necessary Bill in present circumstances, and as some Senators are probably aware, local officials have come to me, and in the name of some of their organisations asked me to introduce a measure into the Oireachtas cutting salaries, rather than leaving the cuts to be carried out by the local authorities.  That has happened. Some local authorities have already <Col N="965" /> passed resolutions cutting salaries by 15 and 20 per cent.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasToal" hpid="Mr. Toal Mr. Toal">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Toal</NameTxt>
      <P>Hear, hear.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanTOKelly" hpid="Mr. O'Kelly Mr. O'Kelly">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Kelly</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator Toal approves of that.  It is true that they have done so.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasToal" hpid="Mr. Toal Mr. Toal">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Toal</NameTxt>
      <P>What I meant was that local authorities had passed resolutions to that effect.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnKeaneBart" hpid="Sir John Keane Sir John Keane">
      <NameTxt>Sir John Keane</NameTxt>
      <P>Can the Minister say if these cuts have been allowed to operate?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanTOKelly" hpid="Mr. O'Kelly Mr. O'Kelly">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Kelly</NameTxt>
      <P>Where the Minister thought that the cuts were out of proportion or inconsiderate, they were not allowed to operate.  Senator The McGillycuddy rather suggested in his speech that the cuts would tend to have the effect of making officials of local authorities unfaithful to their trust.  I do not believe that is so.  I do not believe there is a single official of a local authority who is going to be induced by a cut of 5 or 10 per cent. to be unfaithful to his trust.  I do not believe that is true at all.  It is entirely improbable.  I will say this, if there is any official of a local authority, whose mentality is likely to be unfaithful, because of a 10 or a 15 per cent. cut, an increased salary would not make that man a faithful servant, and no attempt to purchase an official of that kind by an increased salary would make him a better official of any local authority.  That kind of mentality may rule in officials of local and governmental authorities in other countries. I do not believe it rules here.  As Senator Toal reminded us, there are a few public men here and there in this country who are not fit to occupy honourable positions in public life; who were unfit to be elected.  I say that without any reference to politics or party.  There are such individuals, and I wish I could get evidence against them&mdash;whatever side they are on&mdash;and I would make them feel the consequences. I believe there are a few in different parts of the country.  I do not believe that is true of officials.  That is my experience.  There were occasions in the last two years, since <Col N="966" /> I became a Minister, when officials failed in their trust.  There were small peculations here and there, due to bad habits, drinking, gambling or something of that kind, but, as long as people are human, these things will happen.  Generally breaches of trust in a large way are foreign to our public servants.</P>
      <P>Senator Bagwell talked about the limit of £300 that has been inserted in the Bill.  There is a point, and there has been a very important difference of opinion about when that point is reached, below which a man cannot live and rear and educate a family. People are bound to differ on what that point is.  After a good deal of argument pro and con in connection with cuts in the salaries of public officials, £300 was fixed for an ordinary citizen, rearing a family.  That is why that figure was put there, to prevent the cut operating on any salary below that amount.</P>
      <P>Senator O'Farrell and Senator Sir Edward Bigger referred to the case of the doctors.  If there is any profession amongst any section of the officials of local authorities whose salaries it is unpopular to cut, I believe it is medical men and the dispensary medical officers.  I do not enjoy the privilege of doing it any more than anyone else. I believe it is true that in perhaps from 60 to 75 per cent. of the cases of medical men connected with local authorities they will not be affected at all.  When the Bill was under discussion in the Dáil a doctor from one county stated that he had examined the Bill with the County Medical Association, and it was found that 75 per cent. of the doctors there would not come under the Bill at all, so that there will be very few of them affected, to any extent.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOFarrell" hpid="Mr. O'Farrell Mr. O'Farrell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Farrell</NameTxt>
      <P>That means that they have less than £210 yearly.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanTOKelly" hpid="Mr. O'Kelly Mr. O'Kelly">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Kelly</NameTxt>
      <P>£260.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOFarrell" hpid="Mr. O'Farrell Mr. O'Farrell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Farrell</NameTxt>
      <P>£210, plus £10 for travelling.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EdwardBigger" hpid="Sir E. Bigger Sir E. Bigger">
      <NameTxt>Sir E. Bigger</NameTxt>
      <P>As the Minister states that 75 per cent. of the doctors will not be affected, is it worth while cutting the other 25 per cent?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="967" />
    <Speaker pid="SeanTOKelly" hpid="Mr. O'Kelly Mr. O'Kelly">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Kelly</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not want to mislead the Seanad.  I have not had a mathematical examination made, but that was the statement made by one doctor, that he thought in one county 75 per cent. of the doctors would not be affected.  There is a figure of between 60 per cent. and 75 per cent. who will not be affected because of the low salaries paid to medical men.  They start in some counties with £250, in other counties with £275, and in no place do the salaries go beyond £350. These are the basic salaries of the medical officers of health.  I do not know whether it is worth while replying to the political speech of Senator Blythe.  I do not think anyone will have any doubt that it was meant to play at politics and nothing else, when he referred to the Bill as &ldquo;cynical humbug.&rdquo;  That came badly from the Senator, because during his time as Minister for Finance, if cynical humbug was played at by anybody, it was played at by Senator Blythe and played to the full.  Certainly no man played it with greater effect to attack the standard of public servants.  I think he cut the salaries of public servants much more severely than is proposed now.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LaurenceONeill" hpid="Mr. O'Neill Mr. O'Neill">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Neill</NameTxt>
      <P>The old age pensioners.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanTOKelly" hpid="Mr. O'Kelly Mr. O'Kelly">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Kelly</NameTxt>
      <P>The Senator did not stop at such cuts, but he cut the poorest of the people, the old age pensioners, on the grounds of economy. Surely to God, having cut the old age pensioners who got a maximum of 10/- a week, a man must have a face of brass to talk about cynical humbug when cutting salaries.  It might come well from someone else in the House, but when it comes from Senator Blythe it is a bit thick.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnMacLoughlin" hpid="Mr. MacLoughlin Mr. MacLoughlin">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacLoughlin</NameTxt>
      <P>It is surely cynical to talk of saving £40,000 out of £36,000,000.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanTOKelly" hpid="Mr. O'Kelly Mr. O'Kelly">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Kelly</NameTxt>
      <P>The Senator is another good example.  We know what &ldquo;cynical humbug&rdquo; it has been to hear Senator Blythe talking, but you could not get two better champions of it than the Senators.  They do it well and get away with it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="968" />
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Cathaoirleach Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not think we should have political arguments now.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanTOKelly" hpid="Mr. O'Kelly Mr. O'Kelly">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Kelly</NameTxt>
      <P>That is so.  I think the speech of Senator Blythe was a political speech.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Cathaoirleach Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister is perfectly justified in replying to what was said, but not to argue it further.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanTOKelly" hpid="Mr. O'Kelly Mr. O'Kelly">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Kelly</NameTxt>
      <P>The Senator said the money was wasted on futile and fantastic projects.  If building more houses in two years than were built in the previous ten years is a futile and fantastic project, I make the Senator a present of it.  In that period we have housed more poor people, and we have given more employment in building and in the ancillary work of providing houses.  We have also done more to abolish slums.  This money will go for that purpose.  I do not see how anyone who is truthful could say that the provision of decent homes is futile and fantastic, and that is how the money will be applied.  There is not much political kudos in this measure for anybody. I know that, as I have a good deal of experience of local authorities. While I am not as long connected with local authorities as Senator Toal, I know the influence that officials of local authorities can exercise on the public, or when elections are coming on.  This measure will get no support for the present Government from the officials of local authorities.  That is undeniable.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDouglas" hpid="Mr. Douglas Mr. Douglas">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Douglas</NameTxt>
      <P>I thought some of them asked to have salary cuts made.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanTOKelly" hpid="Mr. O'Kelly Mr. O'Kelly">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Kelly</NameTxt>
      <P>They asked not for cuts but that the Minister should make the cuts in preference to local authorities.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDouglas" hpid="Mr. Douglas Mr. Douglas">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Douglas</NameTxt>
      <P>I thought they would support these proposals in preference.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanTOKelly" hpid="Mr. O'Kelly Mr. O'Kelly">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Kelly</NameTxt>
      <P>It does not make it any more popular if they lose a ten pound note.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasFarren" hpid="Mr. Farren Mr. Farren">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Farren</NameTxt>
      <P>I understood the Minister to say, in reply to Senator Toal, that where local authorities had asked for a cut to be made in the salaries of their employees, in certain circumstances he granted their request.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="969" />
    <Speaker pid="SeanTOKelly" hpid="Mr. O'Kelly Mr. O'Kelly">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Kelly</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator Toal did not ask any questions of that kind.  I think the Bill is necessary in present <Col N="970" /> circumstances and I recommend it to the House.</P>
      <P>Question put.</P>
      <P Just="Center">The Seanad divided: Tá, 16; Níl, 9.</P>
      <P Just="Center">Tá</P>
    </Speaker>
    <table pgwide="1">
      <tgroup cols="2">
        <colspec colname="1" colnum="1" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <colspec colname="2" colnum="2" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry rowsep="1">Chléirigh, Caitlín Bean Uí.<br />Comyn, K.C., Michael.<br />Connolly, Joseph.<br />Douglas, James G.<br />Keane, Sir John.<br />Keyes, Raphael P.<br />Linehan, Thomas.<br />MacEllin, Seán E.</entry>
            <entry rowsep="1">McGillycuddy of the Reeks, The.<br />Moore, Colonel.<br />O'Neill, L.<br />O'Rourke, Brian.<br />Phaoraigh, Siobhán Bean an.<br />Quirke, William.<br />Robinson, Séumas.<br />Toal, Thomas.</entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
    <P Just="Center">Níl</P>
    <table pgwide="1">
      <tgroup cols="2">
        <colspec colname="1" colnum="1" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <colspec colname="2" colnum="2" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry rowsep="1">Costello, Mrs.<br />Duffy, Michael.<br />Farren, Thomas.<br />Foran, Thomas.<br />Johnson, Thomas.</entry>
            <entry rowsep="1">MacLoughlin, John.<br />Milroy, Seán.<br />O'Connor, Joseph.<br />O'Farrell, John T.<br /></entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
    <P Just="Center">Tellers:&mdash;Tá: Senators S. Robinson and Quirke; Níl; Senators Farren and O'Farrell.</P>
    <P>Question declared carried.</P>
    <P>Committee Stage fixed for Wednesday, 18th April, 1934.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Children Bill," RHead="1934&mdash;Second Stage">
    <Title>Children Bill, 1934&mdash;Second Stage.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Cathaoirleach Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I give permission for the Parliamentary Secretary to the Minister for Local Government and Public Health to attend and be heard in regard to this Bill and in regard to the two remaining Bills on the Order Paper, of which he is in charge.</P>
      <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That the Bill be read a Second Time.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DrFCWard" hpid="Parliamentary Secretary to the Minister for Local Government and Public Health (Dr. Ward) Francis Constantine (Dr.) Ward">
      <NameTxt>Parliamentary Secretary to the Minister for Local Government and Public Health (Dr. Ward)</NameTxt>
      <P>Briefly, the purpose of the Bill is to strengthen the law relating to children to whom Part I of the Children Act, 1908, applies.  Part I of that Act was intended for the protection of children who were nursed and maintained for reward by persons other than their parents.  It is administered in this country by the local poor law authorities and the experience of its working has revealed many defects which it is desirable to remedy.</P>
      <P>The provisions of the Bill could be classified under different headings, namely, those relating respectively to (a) the protection of the child; (b) the powers of the local authority, and (c) the functions of the Minister.</P>
      <P>Generally speaking, all the provisions of the Bill are intended for the protection of the child, but there is one to which it might be well to make particular reference.  Where the nursing and maintenance of a child is accepted for reward, apart from its parents or having no parents, Part I of the Act of 1908 gives the local authority certain powers in relation to the child until it reaches the age of seven years.  After that age the child is not protected by Part I.  This appears to be a rather tender age to release the child from the protective provisions of the Act, and the Bill proposes to raise the age to nine years.</P>
      <P>It will be observed that one of the first provisions of the Bill is that which requires a person who undertakes the nursing and maintenance of an infant to whom the Act applies to give to the local authority at least 48 hours' previous notice of the proposed reception. This will enable the visitors of the local authority to visit and inspect the proposed home before the child is actually received in it.  Hitherto the notice was required to be given within 48 hours of the reception of the infant.  The child was actually placed in the home before the local authority became aware of the fact.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="971" /> Another important provision of the Bill from the point of view of the local authority is that relating to the institution of legal proceedings for failure to give the requisite notice to the local authority.  The Bill provides that this offence shall be deemed to continue so long as the infant remains in the care of the person by whom the notice should have been given and has not been given.  Some years ago a court of law decided that the offence of failing to give notice took place at the expiration of 48 hours from the time at which the child was accepted for reward by the foster parent, and that the time for taking legal proceedings expired at the end of a period of six months from the commission of the offence.  This decision created a new difficulty for local authorities who might be unable to institute proceedings within the six months, or who did not become aware of the commission of the offence within that period. The proposed amendment will enable the local authority to take proceedings at any time while the offence continues and within a period of six months after the end of the period during which the offence continued.</P>
    <P>In connection with legal proceedings, another provision of the Bill worth noting is that contained in Clause 3 (9), which provides that an illegitimate child shall be deemed to have been accepted for reward until the contrary is proved.  This is intended to meet the difficulty which is sometimes experienced in proving to the satisfaction of a court that a child has been received for reward.  In the case of an illegitimate child the onus of proving that it was not received for reward will now rest with the foster parent.</P>
    <P>New powers conferred by the Bill on the local authority, and to which it might be well to call attention, are those which empower them (a) with the approval of the Minister to terminate the employment of infant protection visitors, and persons authorised to discharge the duties of visitors; (b) to withdraw with the approval of the Minister an exemption from visitation granted by them in the case of any premises to which the Act applies; <Col N="972" /> (c) when they fix the number of children to be kept in any dwelling to impose any conditions which they think proper in relation to those infants.</P>
    <P>The Bill proposes to bring the local authorities under the general regulation and control of the Minister in the administratiton of Part I of the Act of 1908.  Hitherto the Minister had no functions in the matter and no power to direct or control the local authorities.</P>
    <P>The Minister is also given specified powers in relation to the appointment of infant protection visitors and their removal from office, the authorisation of persons to act as visitors and the withdrawal of any such authorisation, and the exemption from visitation of premises to which the Act applies.  All these matters are to be subject to the approval of the Minister.</P>
    <P>The Minister is to be given power (a) to remove infant protection visitors from office; (b) to withdraw the authorisation in the case of persons authorised to perform the functions of visitors; (c) to withdraw exemptions from visitation granted by the local authority in the case of any premises to which Part I of the Act of 1908 applies, and (d) to authorise any of his officers to exercise the powers of infant protection visitors.</P>
    <P>It might be well also to refer to the new power proposed to be conferred by Clause 7 (2) on District Justices to make an order for the removal of a child from unsuitable premises or from the care of an unsuitable foster parent. Section 5 of the Principal Act empowered an infant protection visitor to apply to a justice or to the local authority for an order for the removal of a child kept in certain classes of premises or by certain classes of persons specified in the section.  Formerly Part I of the Act was administered by the boards of guardians. Those boards, as a rule, met once a week and there was not much delay between one meeting and another. Most of the new poor law authorities meet only once a month and there is room for much delay between the meetings.  It is considered desirable to give power to the District Justice to make an order for removal at any time or place in view of the possible <Col N="973" /> danger of delay in waiting for the next court day or for the next meeting of the local authority.</P>
    <P>Another important proposal is that contained in Clause 12, which prohibits the publication of advertisement indicating that any person will undertake or arrange for the nursing and maintenance of an infant under the age of nine years, unless the name and residence of that person are correctly stated in the advertisement.  This provision is intended to prevent the practice of disposing of infants through anonymous agents.  It is understood that this practice does not always operate in the best interests of the children.</P>
    <P>I might mention that the reforms contemplated by the Bill have been strongly advocated by social welfare societies and by local authorities, particularly those functioning in the neighbourhood of Dublin.  The Commission on the Relief of the Sick and Destitute Poor also recommended the amendment of the law for the protection of nurse children, particularly illegitimate children, amongst whom the death rate was appallingly high.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JanePower" hpid="Mrs. Wyse Power Mrs. Wyse Power">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Wyse Power</NameTxt>
      <P>I support the Second Reading of this Bill.  It is only people closely in touch with the problems contained in the Bill that know the urgency of the amendments proposed.  This Bill deals with boarded-out children, not by public bodies but by parents or relatives.  I think if an analysis of the statistics were made it would be found that the class of children affected in the majority of cases would be the unwanted child.  The mother comes to Dublin, and her great desire is to get rid of the child on payment of a certain sum.  There has been little inspection of the place in which these children were boarded in the past.  A good deal of that was due to the fact that registration was not necessary before the child was given out to nurse.  Under this Bill notice of registration must be given 48 hours before the child is placed in the house of the nurse.  That will give time for inspection of the house, and as to the qualification of the person who undertakes <Col N="974" /> the care of the child.  The Bill, although it deals with children up to nine years of age, gives attention to babies, a number of whom at four or five years of age are often shipped off to industrial schools.  The Bill amends several sections of the Children Act formerly passed, and which it has been found necessary to amend.  In large cities like Dublin I expect the necessity for this Bill is much greater than in the country. The majority of the children come from the country.  The mother goes back, and the child is left to a person who is paid to take care of it.  We know the results of many inquests that have been held with their verdicts of death from malnutrition and so on.  That is the reason why this Bill has been introduced. Its provisions will have to be faithfully carried out by those who take charge of the child.  They will be very strictly looked after.  I think, in the main, this Bill will do a great deal in the interests of the unfortunate children and I hope it will go through all its stages quickly and become law.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EdwardBigger" hpid="Sir. E. Coey Bigger Sir. E. Coey Bigger">
      <NameTxt>Sir. E. Coey Bigger</NameTxt>
      <P>This Bill should greatly strengthen legislation in regard to the protection of infants and children. To my mind the whole success of the administration of this Bill when it becomes an Act will depend on the Prevention officer.  If the Prevention officer is properly selected not only to look after the physical welfare of the child that is boarded out, but to look after its comforts, its food and its housing, it will lead to the avoidance of very great cruelty.  A great deal will depend, as I say, upon the selection of the Prevention officer.  I am glad to see that the Bill strengthens the hands of the Minister in the supervision of the Prevention officer.  The Bill extends the age from seven to nine years; that is also a move in the right direction.  I think the Bill may reduce very materially the death rate of illegitimate children. These children are not wanted; they are boarded out, and if they die so much the better.  I think from every point of view the Bill is a good one and I have great pleasure in supporting it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="975" />
    <Speaker pid="MichaelComynKC" hpid="Mr. Comyn Mr. Comyn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Comyn</NameTxt>
      <P>I also have great pleasure in supporting this measure, which, I think, is an extremely useful one.  Its aim is to provide against some defects contained in the original Act and I think it ought to be passed as quickly as possible.  It seems to me it will not be necessary to make any great amendments on this Bill after it becomes an Act because it appears to have taken note of imper-sections generally and contains very many useful provisions.  The requirement of the service of notice is very essential and will be found, I am sure, very useful.  It is, of course, perfectly right that non-compliance with that requirement should be regarded as a continuing offence.  Also it is very desirable that control should be exercised in regard, not merely to the premises in which the child is kept, but after the child is allowed to go there, and that that control should be continuing.  Consequently, I think the power that is given to order the removal of children from unsuitable premises is very desirable.  On the whole, looking through this Bill, I think it has been drafted with great care and great knowledge and with proper feeling for the poor children mostly, as Senator Mrs. Wyse Power has stated, illegitimate children who will come under its operations.  In this and in all matters relating to the welfare of children we have always found that Senators Mrs. Wyse Power and Sir E. Coey Bigger have taken the keenest and most intelligent interest.  I hope this Bill will be passed as quickly as possible.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamQuirke" hpid="Mr. Quirke Mr. Quirke">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Quirke</NameTxt>
      <P>I wish to support the motion for the Second Reading of this Bill.  I believe it will do something which should have been done years ago.  I think it is time that we concentrated more upon human beings than on dumb animals.  While supporting this measure I hope I shall be excused for drawing attention to the fact that while we have the Opposition Benches crowded when it is a question of cruelty to animals, their benches are empty when it is a question of preventing cruelty to human beings.  It is also strange to find that people who are so <Col N="976" /> enthusiastic about the League of Youth, and so terribly interested in human beings, when they can be brought to the aid of their political organisation, have no interest whatever in human beings when they are at a stage that they are not able to look after themselves and have nobody to look after them.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDouglas" hpid="Mr. Douglas Mr. Douglas">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Douglas</NameTxt>
      <P>I did not intend to speak and possibly would not have done so but for the speech we have just heard.  The only excuse for that speech is the fact that the Senator is not long in this House and, therefore, a child so far as experience is concerned. If the Senator were here for any length of time he would realise that there is one thing which is never a Party issue and never will be, and that is the question of dealing with children.  Members in all Parties, ever since this House commenced, at every opportunity that has arisen, have given their time to the question of the welfare of the children.  The Senator has spoken as he has because of a small grievance he has about the Prevention of Cruelty to Animals Bill, passed here a short time ago.  That is no reason why he should make a general attack upon a subject which has never been a Party question.  If he was really getting in what he thought was a cheap jibe at absent Senators I have no objection to his political views.  But if his object was to cause the impression outside that matters such as this Bill have been the subject of Party politics, I wish to assure him that they never have been such.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamQuirke" hpid="Mr. Quirke Mr. Quirke">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Quirke</NameTxt>
      <P>It is because the members of the Senator's Party could not make any political capital out of these debates that they are absent.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDouglas" hpid="Mr. Douglas Mr. Douglas">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Douglas</NameTxt>
      <P>If the Senator is happier after that remark, I leave him to his happiness, though I believe it does not do him any great credit. There is only one possible criticism that I would offer on this Bill.  I hope that some day we will get a Government that, when they present legislation by reference, will not go back beyond 1922, and that when they wish to make amendments of British <Col N="977" /> Acts it will be done in detail.  While this is not an attack upon this Bill, I think the suggestion I have made would lead to greater efficiency.  Unless one can afford, as I cannot, to get a full supply of British Statutes, one would have to come up here and look them up to find the meaning of references contained in this Bill.  Where a reference goes back only as far as the date I mentioned, it is not very difficult for any person who keeps a file to look it up; but few people can find the time to come up here, especially Senators from the country, to look up these references, and find out exactly what the Bill is all about.  And although you know generally and approve of what the Bill contains you cannot make any really intelligent criticism unless you look up all these details.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EdwardBigger" hpid="Sir E. Coey Bigger Sir E. Coey Bigger">
      <NameTxt>Sir E. Coey Bigger</NameTxt>
      <P>The original Children Bill was passed in 1908.  It is in existence ever since, not only here but in England and Scotland, up to 1932.  An amending English Act was then passed and this Bill is practically a copy of the English Act.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDouglas" hpid="Mr. Douglas Mr. Douglas">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Douglas</NameTxt>
      <P>That does not quite meet my point.  When you go back prior to 1922 the complete sections should be put in.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="KathleenBrowne" hpid="Miss Browne Miss Browne">
      <NameTxt>Miss Browne</NameTxt>
      <P>I would like to express my approval of this Bill.  I acted for a number of years on a committee for the prevention of cruelty to children, and I also acted as secretary for some time on a ladies' committee dealing with boarded-out children, so I think I have some knowledge of the necessity for amending the present law in regard to these matters.  These committees of ladies in the country, of course, dealt with children boarded-out by public authorities.  That is a different matter.  But at any rate I have worked on these committees and spent a considerable amount of time visiting homes where these children were kept and nursed, so that I know something about this matter.  I have had the opinion of many people in the country to the effect that I should give my approval to this Bill.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="978" />
    <Speaker pid="DrFCWard" hpid="Dr. Ward Dr. Ward">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ward</NameTxt>
      <P>There is not much criticism to be met.  The only criticism was not of the Bill but of the method of presenting our proposals as legislation by reference.  Personally I am not keen on legislation by reference. I can well understand how confusing it is to anybody who tries to acquaint himself with the actual meaning of such a Bill.  But, on the other hand, most of the amendments introduced in this Bill are matters of urgency.  If we were to present the House with the Principal Act and the amendments of it embodied, and open up all the sections to discussion, we could not get the points we are so anxious to get legislation upon through in such a short period.  Legislation by reference is objectionable from many points of view.  As soon as we get the time in the Local Government Department we hope to codify a whole lot of our legislation, including legislation in reference to children.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelComynKC" hpid="Mr. Comyn Mr. Comyn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Comyn</NameTxt>
      <P>That is a very valuable statement.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>Committee Stage ordered for Wednesday, 18th April.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Registration of Maternity Homes" RHead="Bill, 1934&mdash;Second Stage">
    <Title>Registration of Maternity Homes Bill, 1934&mdash;Second Stage.</Title>
    <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That the Bill be now read a Second Time.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="DrFCWard" hpid="Parliamentary Secretary to the Minister for Local Government and Public Health (Dr. Ward) Francis Constantine (Dr.) Ward">
      <NameTxt>Parliamentary Secretary to the Minister for Local Government and Public Health (Dr. Ward)</NameTxt>
      <P>The purpose of this Bill is to make provision for the registration and inspection of maternity homes. Hitherto there has been no official control over maternity homes.  It was quite open to any person to carry on a maternity home, and there was no machinery in existence to ensure that it was efficiently managed or that the premises in which it was carried on were suitable or in a good sanitary condition.  Local authorities had power under Section 17 of the Midwives (Ireland) Act, 1918, to enter maternity homes, but that section related merely to the supervision of midwives and not to the home itself or to the persons other than midwives <Col N="979" /> employed therein.  It may be contended that there is no more necessity to supervise maternity homes than there is in the case of the voluntary hospitals that are very successfully conducted in different parts of the country. Doubtless there are maternity homes under suitable control and efficient management, but against that it is a well-known fact that in some of our large cities there are maternity homes of a very poor class which are availed of largely by unmarried mothers.  We are not at all satisfied that those homes are properly managed.  As a matter of fact, we have information to the contrary in the report published in 1927 on the relief of the sick and destitute poor.  The Commission drew attention to different evils which they traced to the poor-class maternity homes, or to the not too scrupulous management of those homes, particularly the connivance of the management at the secret disposal of children to unsuitable foster parents, and the consequent high death rate amongst the children.</P>
      <P>In the Bill we propose to take steps as far as we can, to remedy those evils. The scope of the Bill is extended as widely as possible.  Its provisions will apply to any premises wholly or partly used or intended to be used for the reception of pregnant women or of women immediately after childbirth. The administration of this measure will be entrusted locally to the local authorities who now exercise supervision under the Midwives (Ireland) Act, 1918.  These are the county borough councils in the county boroughs and elsewhere the boards of health for the joint county districts. Each local authority will be bound under clause 3 of the Bill to keep a register of the maternity homes in its administrative area.  Any person who proposes to carry on a maternity home in the functional area of the local authority may apply to have the home registered in the register kept by the local authority.  The local authority will have power to refuse registration but if they do not refuse registration, they must enter the prescribed particulars of the home in the register.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The local authority may refuse <Col N="980" /> registration if satisfied that the applicant is not a fit and proper person to carry on the home, or that the premises are unsuitable, or, in the case of a home which did not exist before the passing of the Act, the superintendent nurse is not a qualified nurse or a certified midwife.  The local authority may also cancel registration for similar reasons or if the person registered has been convicted of an offence under the Act. There will be provision for an appeal to the Minister against the decision of the local authority refusing to register a maternity home or cancelling registration.  The Minister may, as he thinks proper, uphold or reverse the decision of the local authority. The Minister may, if he so thinks fit, grant exemption from registration to any hospital or institution which is a maternity home but is not carried on for private profit.  Any such exemption may, at any time, be withdrawn by the Minister.  I might also draw attention to the provision made for the records to be kept in the maternity homes.  These records will show particulars of receptions, discharges, confinements, miscarriages, births, deaths, the removal of children and the addresses to which they are removed.  The records should contain full details of the work done in the home.</P>
    <P>The Bill provides for the inspection of maternity homes and the records kept therein by the Minister's inspectors and by authorised officials of the local authority.  When this Bill comes into force it shall not be lawful for any person to carry on a maternity home either registered by the local authority or exempted from registration by the Minister and the penalty for failure to observe this requirement may be a very salutary one, namely, a fine not exceeding £50 and, in case of a continuing offence, a fine not exceeding £10 for every day during which the offence is continued.  In the interests of both mothers and children the Minister considers that the provisions proposed by this Bill are essential and he hopes that he may soon be in a position to bring the measure into operation.</P>
    <Col N="981" />
    <Speaker pid="JanePower" hpid="Mrs. Wyse Power Mrs. Wyse Power">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Wyse Power</NameTxt>
      <P>I shall only say that this Bill has been spoken of for many years.  The problem was considered so urgent during the sitting of the Poor Law Commission in 1927 that the Commission recommended that all private maternity homes should be licensed annually by the local authority and that no licence should be granted unless the home was properly and suitably equipped for the purpose and that it was in charge of a respectable person trained in maternity care and nursing.  I think that backs the Bill better than any speech of mine could.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelComynKC" hpid="Mr. Comyn Mr. Comyn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Comyn</NameTxt>
      <P>I am glad that Senator Mrs. Wyse Power has spoken on this measure but I think probably there is a point or two in the Bill which is open to discussion.  I quite agree that it is desirable that wherever children are born, especially children of unmarried mothers, the place should be registered and that registration should be granted only in the case of a person who is qualified and to premises which are suitable.  I think the Parliamentary Secretary is wise in giving relief from these restrictions in cases where maternity homes are already in existence but where I would, I think, differ from the Minister is here.  In Section 4 he makes provision for cases of disobedience to his orders.  Here is the provision he makes:</P>
      <P>If any person acts in contravention of this section (that is, in relation to carrying on a maternity home in the case of a person who is unsuitable or of premises that are not suitable), such person shall be guilty of an offence under this section and shall be liable on summary conviction thereof to a fine not exceeding £50 and in the case of a continuing offence under this section to a further fine not exceeding £10 for every day during which the offence is committed.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I am sure the Parliamentary Secretary knows much more than I do about matters of this kind, which are medical matters, but it seems to me, as an ordinary man, that that penalty is not sufficient because the maternity home that would be likely to come under the lash of an Act like this would be a <Col N="982" /> maternity home that would not be well conducted and that would probably be in the hands of a person to whom a fine of £10 would be the same as a fine of £1,000,000 or a fine of 6d.  Therefore, subject to what the Seanad may consider wise, I think that this case can only be met in the last resort by having a penalty which is not a monetary penalty but a penalty of imprisonment. No doubt the Minister has considered that.</P>
    <P>The next matter in the Bill to which I would like to draw attention is this. There is provision here for exemption. There is exemption in the case of an institution which is a maternity home that is not carried on for private profit.  Why should there be any exemption?  If an hospital or maternity home is carried on on any such extensive and efficient scale, why should they not go to the trouble of registering, so that we may have all maternity homes registered and so that they may set a good example to others?  I admit that the main object of the measure is to prevent the possibility of children of unmarried mothers and others from being born in places that are not suitable and cared for by people who are not qualified. In that respect I think it is a most useful measure and I am greatly surprised that this matter has not been legislated for long ago.  I think it is a most useful measure and urgently needed, but I do think that all homes should be registered where children are born and that for failure to register or for carrying on a maternity home in contravention of the statute, the ultimate penalty should be imprisonment.</P>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasFarren" hpid="Mr. Farren Mr. Farren">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Farren</NameTxt>
      <P>I think that the Bill, as introduced by the Parliamentary Secretary, is quite sufficient to deal with the problem with which the Minister wants to deal.  It is, unfortunately, true that there is a problem that requires urgently to be dealt with and the Minister has introduced the Bill to deal with that problem.  There is no use in talking about the semipublic maternity homes that are not run for profit and that everybody knows are carried on quite correctly. Unfortunately there are certain homes <Col N="983" /> carried on for profit, where a trade almost is done in children.  It is regrettable to have to say these things but, unfortunately, it is true.  There are deals made by people who carry on these alleged homes with regard to how much they will take to get people to take charge of the children.  That is the problem that has to be dealt with.  Of course there are other maternity homes that might require supervision, but I think on the whole the Minister is dealing very adequately with the problem.  I think we ought to pass the Bill as speedily as possible to allow him to get on with the work of registration of these homes.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DrFCWard" hpid="Dr. Ward Dr. Ward">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ward</NameTxt>
      <P>In regard to the point raised by Senator Comyn and Senator Farren, the definition of maternity homes sets out:&mdash;</P>
      <P>The expression &ldquo;maternity home&rdquo; means any premises which are wholly or partly used or intended to be used for the reception of pregnant women or of women immediately after childbirth.</P>
      <P>All such institutions come under the scope of the Bill, but then under Section 7 the Minister has power to exempt.  That means that there must be positive exemption before any institution can get outside the scope of the Bill.  All these institutions will come under review.  It is very desirable to leave that discretionary power with the Minister, having in mind mainly the charitable institutions that the Minister might consider could be very well left out of the scope of the Bill.  I think that is the only point.  On the question as to whether imprisonment is a better deterrent than a fine. I will look into that.  I think, if all that we hear about the economic conditions be true, there are people who would prefer to go to gaol for a considerable period rather than pay a fine of £50.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>Committee Stage ordered for Wednesday, 18th April.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Public Assistance (Acquisition of Land)" RHead="Bill, 1934&mdash;Second Stage">
    <Title>Public Assistance (Acquisition of Land) Bill, 1934&mdash;Second Stage.</Title>
    <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That the Bill be now read a Second Time.&rdquo;</P>
    <Col N="984" />
    <Speaker pid="DrFCWard" hpid="Parliamentary Secretary to the Minister for Local Government and Public Health (Dr. Ward) Francis Constantine (Dr.) Ward">
      <NameTxt>Parliamentary Secretary to the Minister for Local Government and Public Health (Dr. Ward)</NameTxt>
      <P>The object of this Bill is to empower local public assistance authorities or poor law authorities to acquire land for the purposes of their powers and duties.  The provisions of the Bill will apply to the purchase of land either by agreement or compulsorily.</P>
      <P>Hitherto the authorities concerned did not possess compulsory powers. If they required land they could only purchase by agreement, and the results were not always satisfactory.  The local authority had to confine their selection to any land that might be offered for sale and very often the land offered for sale was not the most suitable for the purposes of the local authority.  Neither was there any machinery to fix a suitable price and the local authority had to rely on bargaining methods which rarely secured the land at a reasonable figure. Invariably when it became known that land was required by a local authority in any particular locality the value of the land in the neighbourhood went up, and the local authority if they desired to proceed with their project were compelled to purchase at an inflated price.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>In the ordinary course of their administration the purchase of the land by a public assistance authority is not a very frequent occurrence, and it might not be a matter that would call for special provisions.  At the present time, however, all those bodies are engaged in the provision of improved hospital accommodation, and their hospital schemes often necessitate the purchase of new sites.  Where the expenditure of large sums of money is involved it is highly desirable that the authorities concerned should be afforded every facility to work out their schemes successfully.  If the poor law authorities are to be expected to negotiate the purchase of suitable sites for their hospitals it will be necessary to equip them with much more extended powers than they at present possess.  There can scarcely be any great objection to endowing the public assistance authorities with powers to acquire land compulsorily. Public health authorities already <Col N="985" /> possess such powers for the purposes of housing, water supply and sanitary schemes.  Where any local authority are under an obligation to acquire land for the purposes of their powers and duties, the power to acquire compulsorily is essential to the successful performance of those duties.</P>
    <P>The scheme of the Bill for the compulsory acquisition of land contains nothing new.  It is similar to that provided in some of the Housing Acts. When a public assistance authority desire to acquire any particular land compulsorily, they may make a compulsory acquisition order.  They must give the usual publicity by advertisement and by notice to owners, reputed owners, lessees, reputed lessees and occupiers.</P>
    <P>Any person aggrieved by the compulsory acquisition order may make objection to the Minister.  If no objection is received by the Minister he may as he thinks proper either refuse to confirm the order or confirm the order with or without modification. The Minister may also if he thinks fit cause a public local inquiry to be held before dealing with the order.</P>
    <P>Where an objection (other than an objection which in the opinion of the Minister relates only to compensation) is made to the compulsory acquisition order and not withdrawn the Minister must cause a public local inquiry to be held in respect to the order, and after consideration of the report of the person holding the inquiry and of the objection or objections which occasioned the inquiry the Minister may as he shall think proper either refuse to confirm the compulsory acquisition order or confirm the order with or without modification.</P>
    <P>Any person who is affected or whose property is affected by a compulsory acquisition order may apply to the High Court for the complete or partial annulment of the order.  The High Court may as it shall think proper annual the whole of the order or part of the order if satisfied that the order or any part of the order was made in excess of or was otherwise not authorised by the powers conferred <Col N="986" /> by the Act, or that the person making the application or any other person has been substantially prejudiced by any failure to comply in relation to such order with the provisions of the Act.</P>
    <P>Other minor provisions of the Bill are those which will enable a public assistance authority, with the consent of the Minister and subject to any conditions which he may impose, to appropriate and use for the purpose of any of their powers and duties, land vested in them for any purpose and not required for that purpose, and also to sell land acquired under the Act which appears to be no longer required for the purpose for which it was acquired.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelComynKC" hpid="Mr. Comyn Mr. Comyn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Comyn</NameTxt>
      <P>In regard to this measure, which I think will be a very useful one and seems to cover the ground pretty closely, I do not see any clause as to the measure of compensation. Paragraph (a) of Section 7 provides: &ldquo;If no objection (other than an objection which, in the opinion of the Minister, relates only to compensation) to such compulsory acquisition order has been duly made to the Minister,&rdquo; then there shall be a public inquiry. I do not suppose, having regard perhaps to other legislation, that it was necessary to put into this measure any special provision relating to the measure of compensation.  I mention the matter because I think the Parliamentary Secretary is now dealing with a class of case which, in some respects, is not similar to the case of acquiring land for building.  Under this measure it seems to me that premises adjoining hospitals or premises on ground which will be regarded as suitable for hospitals are to be acquired.  There will be a certain goodwill attaching to premises of that kind.  It is different from the case of acquiring land upon which no buildings have been erected, and in respect of which there is no goodwill.  No doubt the Parliamentary Secretary has considered that, and I am sure he has very good reasons for not including in the Bill specific provisions dealing with the assessment of compensation.  If by any chance, which is very unlikely, he has omitted <Col N="987" /> to consider that matter I am sure it can be disposed of on the Committee Stage.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DrFCWard" hpid="Dr. Ward Dr. Ward">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ward</NameTxt>
      <P>The measure of compensation which Senator Comyn refers to will, of course, be arrived at by the arbitrator following the sworn inquiry. I presume the Senator has read Section 4 and, of course, a man of his legal eminence will understand it even better than I do.  I think that the usual machinery for arbitrating and for arriving at adequate and proper compensation is set out in Section 4. All such questions as have been mentioned by the Senator would, of course, be taken into consideration by the arbitrator in arriving at his figure. However, if the House is convinced <Col N="988" /> that any further amendment is necessary on that it can be considered at a later stage, but I think the Senator will find, when he examines it more closely, that what he had in mind is already adequately safeguarded.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelComynKC" hpid="Mr. Comyn Mr. Comyn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Comyn</NameTxt>
      <P>I was only thinking of the question of goodwill attaching to premises, and no doubt it is adequately safeguarded.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>Committee Stage ordered for Wednesday, 18th April.</P>
      <P>The Seanad adjourned at 6.55 p.m. until Wednesday, 18th April, 1934, at 3 p.m.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
</Debate>