<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE Debate SYSTEM "../Debate.dtd"[]>
<Debate DocTitle="Seanad Debate" Day="Wed" Date="23" Month="Feb" Year="2000" Vol="162" No="9" DateIrish="Dé Céadaoin, 23 Feabhra 2000" DateEnglish="Wednesday, 23 February 2000" House="S" CommitteeEng="" CommitteeIr="" SubNameEng="" cnum="0">
  <MainHeading Type="Prelude" LHead="" RHead="">
    <Title>
    </Title>
    <P Just="Center">
      <Col N="541" /> Chuaigh an Cathaoirleach i gceannas ar 2.30 p.m.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Business" RHead="of Seanad">
    <Title>Business of Seanad.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="BrianMullooly" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I have notice from Senator Tom Hayes that, on the motion for the Adjournment of the House today, he proposes to raise the following matter:</P>
      <P>The need for the Minister for Education and Science to sanction a secretary for Scoil Aonghusa special school, Cashel, County Tipperary, as it caters for 150 pupils who have mild to multiple learning difficulties.</P>
      <P>I have also received notice from Senator Norris of the following matter:</P>
      <P>The need for the Minister for the Environment and Local Government to intervene in order to prevent damage by road development to the historic gardens at Mount Congreve, County Waterford.</P>
      <P>I regard the matter raised by Senator Tom Hayes as suitable for discussion on the Adjournment and it will be taken at the conclusion of business. I regret that I have had to rule Senator Norris's matter out of order as the Minister for the Environment and Local Government has no official responsibility in this matter.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Order of" RHead="Business">
    <Title>Order of Business.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="DonnieCassidyFF" hpid="Mr. Cassidy Mr. Cassidy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cassidy</NameTxt>
      <P>Today's Order of Business is No. 1, Second Stage of the Equal Status Bill, 1999, and No. 20, motion 13, with contributions of spokespersons on No. 1 not to exceed 20 minutes and those of other Senators not to exceed 15 minutes. No. 20, motion 13, will be taken from 6 p.m. to 8 p.m., with business to be resumed thereafter, if not previously concluded.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MauriceManning" hpid="Mr. Manning Mr. Manning">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Manning</NameTxt>
      <P>I am a little concerned about the provision that business is to be resumed thereafter if not previously concluded. It would help Members involved with the Equal Status Bill if a <Col N="542" /> time were set for the conclusion of the day's business. I will be at the match.</P>
      <P>Will the Leader make Government time available for Committee Stage of the Shannon River Council Bill? This Bill has the approval of all parties in the House. Will he make time available for Committee Stage next week, while there is enthusiasm for it in his party and elsewhere? The Opposition would be very grateful if he did so.</P>
      <P>Can No. 16 on the Order Paper, the motion on the Grand Canal docks area, be taken with debate? Many Members want to offer their views on some of the current developments in the docklands area. Although a public inquiry is taking place, many people are shocked by the density and intensity of some of the proposed developments. It would be appreciated if the Leader made time available in the next couple of weeks to debate this new order.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeOToole" hpid="Mr. O'Toole Mr. O'Toole">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Toole</NameTxt>
      <P>I support Senator Manning in regard to the finishing of the day's business. The Government made an announcement this week about the need for family friendly policies and a balance between work and family life. It is important for the staff of the House to know when their day's work will be complete. I also await the Leader's answer in regard to Committee Stage of the Shannon River Council Bill.</P>
      <P>No. 8, the Telecommunications (Infrastructure) Bill, 1999, has been on the Order Paper for months, which is astonishing. We have no idea why it is not being moved forward or what the Government intends doing with it. Is this because of objections about telecommunications masts or other difficulties? What is the problem? We need to know what is happening. This is particularly ironic in a week when Eircom announced it is starting a huge initiative in Northern Ireland to expand its infrastructure and broadband network there, while we are wondering what to do in our jurisdiction. It is hugely important that we know what is happening in this regard. Many landowners and communities are watching this Bill with great interest. I ask the Leader to get an absolute position from Government on this or else remove it from the Order Paper so that we know where we stand. There is a certain nervousness about this.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeCostelloLAB" hpid="Mr. Costello Mr. Costello">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Costello</NameTxt>
      <P>I agree entirely with Senator O'Toole on No. 8, the Telecommunications (Infrastructure) Bill, which has been languishing on the Order Paper for a very considerable period. It relates to the very important issue of the infrastructure for the establishment of telecommunications, rights of access and sharing of facilities. If we are to progress the telecommunications industry, it is extremely important to get the infrastructure and legislation in place.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Will the Leader facilitate a debate on asbestos in buildings? The five year survey which has been <Col N="543" /> commenced by the Office of Public Works is showing some very revealing and alarming figures. The survey, which deals with 1,800 public buildings, has revealed that one third of the school buildings in the State built before the mid-1970s contain asbestos. It also revealed that for Farmleigh House, which cost the State £23 million, another £8 million will be needed for the removal of asbestos. There are other public buildings which this initial survey by the Office of Public Works does not cover. What about private buildings such as offices, churches and stands in football stadia? Will the Leader of the House provide us with an opportunity to debate the issue so we can offer some guidance on a way forward?</P>
    <P>I wish to raise No. 20, motion 10, on the Order Paper, the proposal to make St. Brigid's day a national holiday. In the run up to St. Patrick's Day, when Ministers will travel to every corner of the globe to honour our great male saint, it would do no harm to honour St. Brigid, our great female saint, with a national holiday. Many women's organisation see International Women's Day, 8 March, as an ideal day, but that would be difficult because it is very close to St. Patrick's Day.</P>
    <Speaker pid="BrianMullooly" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>We cannot debate the motion now.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeCostelloLAB" hpid="Mr. Costello Mr. Costello">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Costello</NameTxt>
      <P>Will we have an opportunity to debate the issue before International Women's Day and St. Patrick's Day?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MairinQuill" hpid="Miss Quill Miss Quill">
      <NameTxt>Miss Quill</NameTxt>
      <P>On recent happenings in the Arts Council, the Minister for Arts, Heritage, Gaeltacht and the Islands indicated that part of the problem stems from the fact that the Arts Council has to operate under legislation which is out of date.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BrianMullooly" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>No. 20, motion 14, on the Order Paper deals with that matter and I would not like to pre-empt it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidNorris" hpid="Mr. Norris Mr. Norris">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norris</NameTxt>
      <P>I am very grateful to Senator Quill for raising my motion. She is always most helpful.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MairinQuill" hpid="Miss Quill Miss Quill">
      <NameTxt>Miss Quill</NameTxt>
      <P>The motion escaped my notice. I apologise to Senator Norris. Kevin Myers apologised to him today so I will follow the fashion.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidNorris" hpid="Mr. Norris Mr. Norris">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norris</NameTxt>
      <P>Not at all.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryHenry" hpid="Dr. Henry Dr. Henry">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Henry</NameTxt>
      <P>Last year the scientific community was delighted when £560 million was allocated to scientific research. There is concern now about how that money will be spent. It appears that much of it will go into bricks and mortar to build two large institutes which may not be of as much value as giving the money directly to research. <Col N="544" /> Will the Leader of the House alter tomorrow's business to allow us debate this with the Minister of State with responsibility for science and technology so the views of those who are concerned that this money may not be spent in the best possible manner are aired? It is an urgent matter because the Government will make a final decision on the matter next week.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TonyKett" hpid="Mr. Kett Mr. Kett">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Kett</NameTxt>
      <P>Last week Senator Finneran informed the House of a wheelchair user having to be accommodated in the guard's van of a train from the west. As we discuss the Equal Status Bill today, it shows how far we must go to grant equal rights to people with disabilities. Ireland is one of the countries in breach of the European Commission provision for mandatory access for people with disabilities on class one buses. Will the Leader ask the Minister for Public Enterprise why this is the case?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryJackman" hpid="Mrs. Jackman Mrs. Jackman">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Jackman</NameTxt>
      <P>There has not been an increase in subventions to nursing homes since the early 1990s, the maximum subvention being £120. With an elderly population there is an increasing demand for nursing home spaces. It is creating great difficulties for families. I hope the Minister will address these issues in the House and that he will prioritise them at the outset of his term of office.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidNorris" hpid="Mr. Norris Mr. Norris">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norris</NameTxt>
      <P>I am grateful to Senator Quill for raising the matter of the Arts Council. I hope time will be given to a debate on the issue because it seems extraordinary that so many people should have resigned at the same time. I do not wish to be critical of the Minister&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BrianMullooly" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>We should not pre-empt the debate on the matter.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidNorris" hpid="Mr. Norris Mr. Norris">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norris</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not propose to be critical of the Minister &ndash; she is a good Minister. However we ought to have a debate so that we can look at what lies behind this situation.</P>
      <P>I am also grateful to my colleague, Senator Costello, for raising St. Brigid's day. I understand the Leader gave an undertaking &ndash; I am sure he will correct me if I am wrong &ndash; that he would provide time to debate this matter. Since 8 March is International Women's Day and there will be international recognition of this at 11 o'clock and since the House will sit on that day, I suggest that a debate be taken for even half an hour at that time so that we can coincide with the rest of the world.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I recognise your ruling, Sir, about Mount Congreve and I will not challenge it. In the light of that ruling and given the seriousness of the situation, will the Leader arrange a debate on this and related issues? Significant damage has been done to the ancient oak wood at the Glen of the Downs, there has been the history of Coolattin <Col N="545" /> Estate and now Mount Congreve is threatened. It is extraordinary that a gift to the nation should be treated in this utterly cavalier fashion. Given that the Cathaoirleach has found that it is not possible to raise this matter in a narrow fashion on the Adjournment, we should take the opportunity to open up this issue for full debate in the House.</P>
    <P>In view of continued posturing about ethics in Government and so on, could we examine the decentralisation policies? There are coincidences in the series of resignations in the Arts Council, but there are even greater coincidences in the fact that every Department that has been decentralised just happens to have been decentralised to the Minister's constituency. I am sure there are good grounds for this, but perhaps we could hold a wide ranging debate in the House so that we could know the criteria by which these estimable decisions are arrived at.</P>
    <Speaker pid="LabhrasOMurchu" hpid="Labhrás Ó Murchú Labhrás Ó Murchú">
      <NameTxt>Labhrás Ó Murchú</NameTxt>
      <P>In recent weeks the Northern Ireland solicitor, the late Rosemary Nelson, has been honoured for her work for peace. She was murdered because of that work and there are many questions to be answered regarding the circumstances of this brutal murder and the possibility of the collusion of the security forces. The legal profession has thrown its weight internationally behind the call for an independent and full inquiry. Will the Leader raise this matter with the Minister for Foreign Affairs because it is vital that such a murder is investigated and the full facts made known?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThereseRidge" hpid="Mrs. Ridge Mrs. Ridge">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Ridge</NameTxt>
      <P>I join with Senator Kett in seeking information on low floor buses. I hope he has more success than I when I asked the Minister the same questions. In his list of promises to deal with our requests for debate, the Leader should be aware that we did not receive a response last week on the wheelchair issue and we are still awaiting a response on the buses.</P>
      <P>On another transport issue, in the last week there have been a number of very lucky escapes in accidents involving young people. What are the safety checks on the multiple carriers that transport new cars around the country? These are enormous vehicles and people may not be so lucky if there is another accident.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PaulCoghlan" hpid="Mr. Coghlan Mr. Coghlan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Coghlan</NameTxt>
      <P>Last Thursday I asked the Leader if he would update the House on the Government's position on the much spoken of single regulatory authority for financial institutions. I am sure he did not intend to tell me an untruth or to mislead the House, but he erroneously responded that the matter had been referred to the Joint Committee on Finance and Public Service for consideration. I have since been informed that this is not so. I believe the Leader owes it to the House to clarify the matter and I would be grateful if he did so today.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="546" />
    <Speaker pid="FergusODowdFG" hpid="Mr. O'Dowd Mr. O'Dowd">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Dowd</NameTxt>
      <P>I ask the Leader to arrange for an urgent debate on Sellafield, given that safety records there have been falsified for a number of years and that there are grave concerns over safety in the industry. This is an urgent matter of great importance.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TomHayes" hpid="Mr. T. Hayes Mr. T. Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Mr. T. Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>I ask the Leader to arrange an urgent debate on the recently published CSO figures relating to the wealth of people in various regions, with particular emphasis on why the south eastern region fared so badly. It backs up the often made argument that the influence of the Celtic tiger has not been felt in the regions.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FintanACoogan" hpid="Mr. Coogan Mr. Coogan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Coogan</NameTxt>
      <P>I support the request made a few weeks ago by Senator Finneran and reiterated today by Senators Kett and Ridge for a debate in response to the public demand that we pay attention to those less able than ourselves. This issue will not go away and the call for a debate is not prompted by media attention.</P>
      <P>I also wish to raise the issue of radon gas. The Leader has promised me time and again a debate on this issue. Recently a Member on the Government side made a similar demand and supported my request, but that demand was a result of media attention, as if the dangers of radon gas only occur when the media pay attention to the problem. That danger exists all the time and the matter is worthy of debate in the House. Will the Leader give a guaranteed commitment and a timeframe for this debate?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnDardis" hpid="Mr. Dardis Mr. Dardis">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dardis</NameTxt>
      <P>It is important to clarify the matter of the single regulatory authority and the role of the Joint Committee on Finance and the Public Service. The committee, of which I am a member &ndash; I think Senator Finneran is also a member &ndash; has given detailed consideration to the matter. The Governor of the Central Bank, the Director of Consumer Affairs and senior civil servants from the Departments of Finance and Enterprise, Trade and Employment have addressed the committee on this issue. The Senator may be technically correct in saying the matter has not been referred to the committee, but it certainly has been debated at length by it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PaulCoghlan" hpid="Mr. Coghlan Mr. Coghlan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Coghlan</NameTxt>
      <P>With respect, that is not what was said on the record last week.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnDardis" hpid="Mr. Dardis Mr. Dardis">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dardis</NameTxt>
      <P>I would like to reassure Senator Costello and Senator Norris that the people of Kildare never have any difficulty and never need an excuse to celebrate the feast of Saint Brigid.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidNorris" hpid="Mr. Norris Mr. Norris">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norris</NameTxt>
      <P>Hear, hear.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnDardis" hpid="Mr. Dardis Mr. Dardis">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dardis</NameTxt>
      <P>We shall continue to do so for many years to come. It is worth reminding the House that one of the first and most successful breweries was brought here by the selfsame saint.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="547" />
    <Speaker pid="DonnieCassidyFF" hpid="Mr. Cassidy Mr. Cassidy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cassidy</NameTxt>
      <P>Regarding the issue raised by Senator Manning, I understood that the phrase &ldquo;business to resume thereafter if not previously concluded&rdquo; was a favourite line when the Senator was Leader of the House.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MauriceManning" hpid="Mr. Manning Mr. Manning">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Manning</NameTxt>
      <P>Only after consultation and agreement.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DonnieCassidyFF" hpid="Mr. Cassidy Mr. Cassidy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cassidy</NameTxt>
      <P>I was just following my predecessor. Of course, we can review progress later in the afternoon.</P>
      <P>Senator Manning also raised No. 16 regarding the docklands. As the Senator is aware, orders are not normally debated in the House, but if he requires a debate I will certainly allow the necessary time.</P>
      <P>Senators O'Toole, Manning and Costello raised the Shannon River Council Bill, Second Stage of which was completed in the House last week. I have left time during the next number of weeks for the Finance Bill, the Social Welfare Bill and some very important legislation on which there is a time limit. I will possibly review the timeframe around Easter.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MauriceManning" hpid="Mr. Manning Mr. Manning">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Manning</NameTxt>
      <P>It will not go away, you know.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DonnieCassidyFF" hpid="Mr. Cassidy Mr. Cassidy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cassidy</NameTxt>
      <P>It is a Fianna Fáil Bill and we will make sure it will not go away.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeOToole" hpid="Mr. O'Toole Mr. O'Toole">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Toole</NameTxt>
      <P>On a point of order, is it a Fianna Fáil Bill?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DonnieCassidyFF" hpid="Mr. Cassidy Mr. Cassidy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cassidy</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeOToole" hpid="Mr. O'Toole Mr. O'Toole">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Toole</NameTxt>
      <P>We were not made aware of this, but we are glad to hear it. It was reprinted in the names of the Senators, but word for word and line for line it is the same as former Senator Daly's excellent legislation.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MauriceManning" hpid="Mr. Manning Mr. Manning">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Manning</NameTxt>
      <P>Of what is the Leader afraid?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeOToole" hpid="Mr. O'Toole Mr. O'Toole">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Toole</NameTxt>
      <P>Is the Leader putting his name to it?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BrianMullooly" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>The Leader, without interruption, please.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DonnieCassidyFF" hpid="Mr. Cassidy Mr. Cassidy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cassidy</NameTxt>
      <P>It is still afloat. Senator Costello referred to the Telecommunications (Infrastructure) Bill, 1999. As I have stated on many occasions, I will bring it before the House when ordered to do so by Government.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Senator Norris, supported by Senators Costello and Dardis, requested a debate between 11 a.m. and 11.30 a.m. on Wednesday, 8 March, which is International Women's Day. Nollaig na mBan is <Col N="548" /> 6 January, which is a very suitable time to plan a national ladies day.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JoeOToole" hpid="Mr. O'Toole Mr. O'Toole">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Toole</NameTxt>
      <P>Obviously, ladies day is more important than the Shannon River Council Bill, 1998.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MauriceManning" hpid="Mr. Manning Mr. Manning">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Manning</NameTxt>
      <P>Why does the Leader not call it girls day?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BrianMullooly" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>The Leader, without interruption, please.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DonnieCassidyFF" hpid="Mr. Cassidy Mr. Cassidy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cassidy</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator O'Toole seems to be floating all the time. Not all Members have a boat. Senator Costello called for a debate on asbestos and I will make time available for that. Senators Quill and Norris called for a debate on the Arts Council. It will take place on Thursday afternoon of next week. It is time to debate it at length in the House and I look forward to many Senators making worthwhile contributions. I have my own opinion on the Arts Council and the enormous sums of money that could do a great deal of good, but which are not evenly distributed. That is my view, not that of the leader of my party.</P>
      <P>I will ascertain whether I can meet Senator Henry's request. Senators Coogan, Kett and Ridge expressed their concerns regarding wheelchair users, and everyone totally supports their request. That matter can be raised during the debate on the Equal Status Bill, 1999. I will pass on the views of Senators Jackman and Norris to the Minister. I will also convey Senator Ó Murchú's concerns regarding Rosemary Nelson to the Minister for Foreign Affairs. I join with him in calling for a full independent inquiry into this case. The Minister for Foreign Affairs will be in the House tomorrow between 1.30 p.m. and 3.30 p.m. and the Senator can avail of that opportunity to raise the issue.</P>
      <P>I will pass on Senator Ridge's views on car transporters to the Minister for Public Enterprise. Senator Dardis clarified Senator Coghlan's query. I will facilitate Senator O'Dowd's call for a debate on Sellafield the week after next. Senator Tom Hayes again had some difficulty with statistics. I will pass on his views to the Minister for Finance. He hails from a prosperous part of Ireland and the rest of the country is just catching up.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TomHayes" hpid="Mr. T. Hayes Mr. T. Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Mr. T. Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>It is not that black and white.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DonnieCassidyFF" hpid="Mr. Cassidy Mr. Cassidy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cassidy</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator Coogan called for a debate on radon gas and I assure the House that it will take place. Perhaps the Sellafield and radon gas issues could be discussed together the week after next if the Senator is agreeable.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="549" /> Order of Business agreed to.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Equal Status Bill, 1999:" RHead="Second Stage">
    <Title>Equal Status Bill, 1999: Second Stage.</Title>
    <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That the Bill be now read a Second Time.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="JohnODonoghue" hpid="Mr. O'Donoghue Mr. O'Donoghue">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Justice, Equality and Law Reform (Mr. O'Donoghue)</NameTxt>
      <P>I am pleased to bring before the Seanad this important measure which is a key element of the Government's equality agenda.</P>
      <P>The Equal Status Bill will, for the first time, provide protection against discrimination outside the field of employment. It deals with discrimination on the grounds of gender, marital status, family status, sexual orientation, religion, age, disability, race and membership of the Traveller community and gives those who are discriminated against a statutory means of redress. It has a broad-ranging scope covering provision of goods and services, disposal of premises and accommodation, education, and registered clubs. The Bill applies to goods and services which are available to the public, whether on payment or not, and irrespective of whether provided by the public or private sector. This measure complements the Employment Equality Act, 1998, which prohibits discrimination on similar grounds in the workplace.</P>
      <P>Senators will no doubt recall the fate of the previous Equal Status Bill. That Bill, which was initiated in 1997 by the then Minister for Equality and Law Reform, Mr. Mervyn Taylor, passed all Stages in both Houses of the Oireachtas. The entire Bill was then referred by the President to the Supreme Court under Article 26 of the Constitution. The Employment Equality Bill of 1996 had already been referred to the Supreme Court and on 15 May 1997 the court found that Bill to be unconstitutional in three respects. As two technical provisions found unconstitutional in the Employment Equality Bill were also contained in the Equal Status Bill, it then became inevitable that the Supreme Court would also find the Equal Status Bill unconstitutional. The court gave its judgment on the Equal Status Bill on 19 June 1997. As expected, the court held those two aspects of the Bill &ndash; vicarious liability of employers for criminal acts of employees and use of a certificate in a criminal trial &ndash; to be repugnant to the Constitution. The Supreme Court declined to consider the Bill further.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Preparation of the revised Equal Status Bill was necessarily a more complicated matter than was the development of the revised employment equality legislation. The Employment Equality Bill had been thoroughly examined by the Supreme Court, particularly as regards a range of key and controversial provisions, and was found constitutionally sound except for three aspects. It was possible, therefore, to revise that Bill relatively quickly and to bring forward a redrafted measure in the latter part of 1997, resulting in the enactment of the Employment Equality Act, 1998, in June 1998. In the case of the Equal Status <Col N="550" /> Bill, however, the Supreme Court did not examine the Bill as a whole and did not give its imprimatur to any aspect of it. It was, therefore, necessary to obtain extensive legal advice before developing the revised Equal Status Bill. As this is a wide-ranging and complex measure, it was necessary to proceed thoroughly and carefully to ensure that the revised measure would pass constitutional muster.</P>
    <P>Following on the Employment Equality Act, 1998, which is now fully in operation, this Bill is a further step forward in the area of equality legislation. The Bill is based on the principle that everyone has an equal right to participate in our society. People should not be denied access to services, facilities or amenities just because of their skin colour, disability or membership of the Traveller community. Everyone, male or female, white or black, old or young, with or without disability should be seen as of equal worth and entitlement. Each person should be treated on his or her own merits and not on the basis of a prejudice or stereotype.</P>
    <P>At present there is an absence of legal redress for a woman who cannot become a member of a local golf club simply because she is a woman, the person who is refused entry to a pub because he or she uses a wheelchair or the black person who is not given a flat simply because of his or her skin colour. Such people want more than mere sympathy, they want the protection of the law. Groups representing persons who have experienced discrimination have been pressing successive Governments for legislation along these lines for a considerable time and are anxious to see this measure in place.</P>
    <P>Until this legislation is in place, Ireland cannot ratify the UN Convention on the Elimination of All Forms of Racial Discrimination. This convention dates from the 1960s and Ireland signed it in 1968. In the intervening years, the convention has been ratified by more than 150 countries, including all our EU partners. The UN monitoring bodies have on a number of occasions called for action by Ireland to ratify the convention and I can confirm that we will take steps to do so after the passage of this legislation. Similarly, the enactment of the Equal Status Bill is necessary to enable us to lift a reservation on the UN Convention on the Elimination of All Forms of Discrimination against Women.</P>
    <P>Senators will agree that there is across the board acceptance of the principle of equal status legislation and, thus, the enactment of an Equal Status Bill has been a fundamental element of the programmes of successive parties in Government. Equal status legislation is among the commitments in the Good Friday Agreement. Equal status legislation has been endorsed by the social partners who participated in the Programme for Competitiveness and Work, Partnership 2000 and the recently agreed Programme for Prosperity and Fairness. Recommendations relating to anti-discrimination legislation were set forth in the reports of the Second Commission on the Status <Col N="551" /> of Women, the task force on the Travelling community and the Commission on the Status of People with Disabilities.</P>
    <P>At EU level the fight against discrimination has moved beyond the traditional field of gender discrimination in the workplace. The Amsterdam Treaty, which came into force last May, empowers the Union to take action on discrimination in a way not conceived of when the treaties founding the Union were agreed. Article 13 of that treaty gives the Union a basis to combat discrimination, both in employment and non-workplace areas, on grounds of sex, race or ethnic origin, religion, disability, age and sexual orientation. In November 1999 the Commission released details of its package of measures under Article 13, consisting of two draft anti-discrimination directives and an action programme. This package is being discussed by the member states.</P>
    <P>The essential thrust of the current Bill is the same as that of the 1997 Bill. Changes have been made to rectify faults identified by the Supreme Court consequential on the court's finding on the Employment Equality Bill, in response to faults identified in legal advice, to correct technical points or remove anomalies arising from representations and comments on the Bill since it was published last April and in response to points made when the measure was debated in the other House.</P>
    <P>I will now set out the main changes. The 1997 Bill required service providers to make reasonable accommodation, including the provision of special treatment or facilities, for people with disabilities unless such reasonable accommodation would give rise to undue difficulty. As Senators will be aware, the Supreme Court found the comparable requirement in the Employment Equality Bill, 1996, to be unconstitutional. The implications of this judgment were carefully examined before the revised Equal Status Bill was developed. The redrafted version follows the approach taken in the Employment Equality Act, 1998, that is, the obligation to make reasonable accommodation is subject to a nominal cost threshold. This approach has been taken following extensive legal advice on the matter. As required by the Supreme Court judgment, vicarious liability of employers for acts of employees now applies only in respect of civil proceedings. The subsection which allowed for the use of a certificate as evidence of an offence has been deleted.</P>
    <P>The 1997 Bill provided for the establishment of the Equality Authority with a remit in both employment equality and equal status matters. As the Employment Equality Act, 1998, now includes provision for the establishment of the authority and for its functions in the employment equality area, the Bill simply extends the functions of the authority to equal status matters. There are a number of changes in the education area, including the deletion of the provision which allowed schools catering for persons of a particular nationality or national origin to restrict <Col N="552" /> access in certain circumstances. This provision presented constitutional difficulties and, on further consideration, was deemed to be unnecessary. Provisions dealing with discrimination by firms, including partnerships, against members or partners have been deleted. These provisions were anomalous <i>vis-à-vis</i> the provisions of the Employment Equality Act, 1998, and were not required by the EU directive on self-employed activity.</P>
    <P>Registered clubs which are found to be discriminatory will forfeit their certificate of registration but, following legal advice, this is now the sole sanction against such clubs. Procedures for referral of claims have been modified to give greater flexibility in exceptional circumstances. Provision is now made for the Equality Authority to carry out equality reviews and action plans in non-employment matters. Senators will doubtless observe other changes in the 1999 Bill as against the 1997 Bill, but I do not propose to go into details of these at this stage. I will now deal with the specific provisions of the Bill.</P>
    <P>The Bill is divided into five parts as follows: Part I contains definitions and sets out what is meant by discrimination, Part II deals with discrimination in particular areas, Part III provides means of redress and compensation for persons who may have suffered discrimination, Part IV, together with the Schedule, extends the functions of the Equality Authority to equal status matters, and Part V contains general and technical provisions.</P>
    <P>Part I defines terms used in the Bill. Senators may wish to note the broad definition of disability in section 2. There is also a comprehensive definition of &ldquo;services&rdquo;, which includes services and facilities of any nature including access to and use of any place, banking or insurance services, facilities for entertainment, recreation or refreshment, cultural activities, transport or travel and professional or trade services. The definition of &ldquo;Traveller community&rdquo;, which is now included is modelled on the Race Relations Order (Northern Ireland), 1996, and such a definition was sought by Traveller interests.</P>
    <P>Section 3 sets out what is meant by discrimination. Discrimination occurs where, on discriminatory grounds that existed, exist, are believed to exist or are considered likely to come into existence, a person is treated less favourably than another person is, has been, or would be treated. It also occurs where a person is treated less favourably because of his or her association with someone in one of the protected categories. A further form of discrimination occurs where a requirement to comply with a condition has a disproportionately adverse effect on a particular category of person and this requirement cannot be justified as being reasonable in all the circumstances of the case. This form of discrimination is commonly known as indirect discrimination, although the term does not appear in the Bill. The discriminatory grounds are gender, marital status, family status, sexual orientation, religion, <Col N="553" /> age, disability, race, including colour, nationality or national or ethnic origin, and membership of the Traveller community. Victimisation of a person because of his or her involvement in proceedings under the Bill is also treated as a discriminatory ground.</P>
    <P>Section 4 contains provisions related to persons with disabilities. I have already referred to the Supreme Court's findings that the reasonable accommodation provisions of the Employment Equality Bill were unconstitutional and the consequent insertion in the Employment Equality Act, 1998, of a nominal cost threshold for reasonable accommodation. This approach has been followed in the Bill.</P>
    <P>Part II deals with discrimination in particular areas. Section 5 prohibits discrimination in the provision of goods and services. There are a number of exceptions for differences of treatment in certain circumstances in particular areas, such as insurance, sporting events and entertainment. Among these exclusions are reasonable differences of treatment in the area of insurance and finance which are based on actuarial or similar data. Examples of this would be the different treatment of persons under 25 in motor insurance and the different treatment of persons on age grounds in life assurance. Differences of treatment of persons on the grounds of gender, age, disability, nationality or national origin are permissible in relation to sporting facilities and events. Thus, for example, the Bill recognises and allows for different events, such as women's or men's football teams, under 21 football teams or games for people with a disability. As these examples show, the various exceptions reflect what most people would regard as acceptable and necessary differences of treatment.</P>
    <P>Discrimination in disposing of premises and provision of accommodation is also prohibited, subject again to a number of exclusions. Among the exemptions are disposals by will or gift, small premises where the accommodation provider continues to live on the premises, accommodation intended for use by persons of one gender and refuges and nursing homes.</P>
    <P>Educational establishments may not discriminate against students in matters such as admission or access to courses. There are a number of exemptions in the education area. For example, single gender schools are permissible. Denominational schools may refuse to admit non-religionists in certain circumstances. Educational establishments may make reasonably necessary distinctions based on gender, age or disability in relation to sport. Differences of treatment are also warranted if the admission of a student with a disability would make impossible or be seriously detrimental to the education of other students.</P>
    <P>Sections 8 to 10 deal with discrimination by registered clubs. The approach taken in relation to such clubs differs from that taken in other areas. The Bill does not prohibit discrimination by clubs against members or potential members. <Col N="554" /> Instead, it seeks to discourage such discrimination by allowing a complainant to apply for a determination from the District Court that a registered club, that is, one which can sell intoxicating liquor, is a discriminating club. If the club is determined by the District Court to be a discriminating club, it will not be entitled to renew its certificate of registration until it has rectified the situation.</P>
    <P>A number of exemptions are provided in section 10 in relation to registered clubs. Clubs are not regarded as discriminating just because they cater for persons of a particular religion, age, nationality or ethnic origin. A club may provide separate but equivalent facilities for particular age groups or different sexes in certain circumstances. Relevant and reasonably necessary differences of treatment in relation to sporting facilities or events based on gender, age, disability, nationality or national origin are permissible. Certain positive action measures designed to promote greater equality are also exempted.</P>
    <P>In section 11 sexual harassment or harassment based on any of the discriminatory grounds is prohibited in the areas covered by the Bill. A person in authority in an educational establishment, a person providing services or accommodation or disposing of goods or premises may not sexually harass or harass a student, customer etc. Furthermore, a person who is responsible for the operation of an educational establishment or a place at which goods, services or accommodation facilities are offered to the public may not allow a student, customer etc. to suffer sexual harassment or harassment there. It will, however, be a defence for the person responsible to show that he or she took reasonably practicable steps to prevent such harassment. Section 12 prohibits any form of advertising which indicates an intention to discriminate, to sexually harass or to harass.</P>
    <P>I have already referred to some of the specific exemptions which apply to particular areas. There are also some general exemptions in sections 14 and 16. For example, actions which are required to be done by or under statute, court order, EU law or international obligations are exempt, as are bona fide positive action measures. A reasonable preferential charge for persons together with their children, married couples, persons in a specific age group or persons with a disability is permissible. Different treatment is also acceptable where it arises in the exercise of clinical judgment or because the person concerned is incapable of entering an enforceable contract or of giving informed consent.</P>
    <P>Section 15 deals with safeguards. It makes it clear that a service provider or similar person is not required to serve a customer if the service provider has reasonable grounds, other than discriminatory grounds, for the belief that provision of the service would create a substantial risk of criminal or disorderly conduct or behaviour or cause damage to property. It also provides that action taken in good faith for the sole purpose of <Col N="555" /> complying with the Licensing Acts is not discrimination.</P>
    <P>Sections 17 to 19 make special provision for the needs of persons with a disability in the area of transport accessibility and convenience in using public streets and pavements. They provide for regulations requiring that buses and trains, and bus and train stations, be readily accessible to persons with disabilities. In addition, road authorities must provide kerb ramps or similar features when constructing or altering public paths.</P>
    <P>I now turn to the enforcement provisions under Part III of the Bill. Senators will be aware that both the Equality Authority and the Office of the Director of Equality Investigations stand established under the provisions of the Employment Equality Act, 1998, and that both entities commenced operations in relation to employment matters in October last. The functions of the authority and the director will be broadened to include equal status matters once the present measure is brought into operation.</P>
    <P>Claims of discrimination or harassment may be referred to the Director of Equality Investigations who will provide a simple, inexpensive and speedy means of redress for victims of discrimination. As I have said, the decision on whether a club is a discriminating club is a matter for the District Court and I would emphasise that the Director of Equality Investigations will have no function in the matter of discriminating clubs.</P>
    <P>The procedures outlined in sections 20 to 38 which deal with cases referred to the director correspond, subject to certain modifications and exceptions, to those applicable to cases referred to the director under the Employment Equality Act, 1998. I will mention some features of the redress procedures. A claim referred to the director under this Bill must be preceded by an initial notification to the respondent within two months of the alleged discrimination or of its most recent occurrence. Should exceptional circumstances have prevented the complainant from doing so within two months the director may, if he or she is satisfied that it is just and equitable to do so, give an extension to four months for the notification to be given to the respondent. The giving of a notification is intended to put the respondent on notice, afford him or her the opportunity to take remedial action and, if the respondent wishes, to give the respondent's side of the story. There is a six month limit for referral of claims to the director, which may be extended in exceptional circumstances to 12 months.</P>
    <P>The director may at any time dismiss a claim which is made in bad faith or is trivial, vexatious or frivolous. The director may investigate a claim or, alternatively, seek to resolve the matter by mediation. Having investigated a claim, the director may award compensation and/or require that a particular course of action be taken. Compen<Col N="556" /> sation is limited to the maximum that could be awarded in a civil case in contract, currently £5,000.</P>
    <P>The director will have strong investigative powers to enter premises, to obtain relevant information, through interview or otherwise, and to ensure the imposition of sanctions in the event of failure or refusal by persons to co-operate with an investigation. Decisions of the director may be appealed to the Circuit Court within 42 days.</P>
    <P>The Equality Authority will have the power under section 23 to refer certain cases to the director. Such cases could involve discrimination against a group of persons or a situation where the person concerned is not in a position to bring a case themselves. The authority may also refer cases involving prohibited advertising and non-compliance with the regulations on transport accessibility. It will also have the power to seek injunctions.</P>
    <P>Part IV together with the Schedule, extends the functions of the Equality Authority, as set out in the Employment Equality Act, 1998, to include equal status matters. Part V deals with various general matters, including expenses, regulations, vicarious liability, offences and commencement.</P>
    <P>This legislation will have a profound impact on Irish society. Its provisions, together with the Employment Equality Act, 1998, will put in place a comprehensive and advanced anti-discrimination code. I look forward to a constructive and wide-ranging debate on this important legislation.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JohnConnor" hpid="Mr. Connor Mr. Connor">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Connor</NameTxt>
      <P>The reintroduction of this Bill in this House is welcome. It is now a little short of three years since the Equal Status Bill, 1997, was debated here. Unfortunately, although it was willingly passed by this and the other House, with the Employment Equality Bill, 1996, it did not bear up to the constitutional test heard in the Supreme Court. We must always respect the Constitution in any Supreme Court test of any laws made in these Houses under the Constitution. Nevertheless, taking into account the Supreme Court decision, this Bill and the Employment Equality Act are less good as legislation.</P>
      <P>The quality and effectiveness of these items of legislation are particularly important because they are designed to protect the interests and opportunities of some of the most vulnerable people in the population. It is regrettable that the Constitution &ndash; by common consent a very good document but rooted in the thinking of the 1930s &ndash; can do something to diminish this important legislation. I hope the committee dealing with constitutional review might take note of this.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>There are nine grounds under which discrimination is outlawed under this legislation. Generally, the provisions of the Bill are comprehensive and proactive in promoting equality and the principle of equal status under all the headings. This long-delayed addition to our anti-discrimination <Col N="557" /> law is needed. We pride ourselves on our advanced society and we feel that we are in the forefront in the world evolving and applying best practice in human rights law. Yet there is much evidence that there is a worrying degree of nascent racism not far below the surface. The attitude we see towards asylum seekers and refugees &ndash; often the institutional attitude &ndash; is instructive. Recent court cases involving the renewal of pub licences and members of the Travelling community are also very instructive.</P>
    <P>Ireland is not unique in this regard. However socially advanced or enlightened a country seems to be, one always finds nascent racism or a willingness to practice or express discrimination and social exclusion. Recent political events in Austria are a warning of what can happen when jingoism and barely concealed racism are dressed up in populist language and rhetoric, and how significant sectors of the population, from all social backgrounds in what is regarded as a socially advanced society, can embrace this corrosive, backward, uninformed and simplistic propaganda and vote for it.</P>
    <P>The most disappointing feature of the Bill is the non-inclusion of the statutory sector or the public bodies within the scope of the Bill. The National Consultative Committee on Racism and Interculturalism, a body under the aegis of the Minister's Department, made an interesting submission to the Joint Committee on Justice, Equality, Defence and Women's Rights on this Bill after it was published. One of the points made was that the activities of public bodies do not fall within the scope of this Bill, under the provisions of section 5(2)(<i>a</i>), dealing with the provision of services and disposal of goods because these activities do not take place in the course of a business or trade. Thus, policing activities, immigration control, operation of prisons and implementation of tax, social welfare and planning codes are not governed by this Bill.</P>
    <P>Even if section 5(2)(<i>a</i>) were dropped, the definition of service in section 2 would also exclude many public service activities. Look also at section 14 which excludes the taking of any action required under statute from the scope of the Bill. Moreover, there is no duty imposed on the public bodies to work for the elimination of discrimination and to promote equality of opportunity. One might make comparisons here with section 71 of the UK Race Relations Act, 1976. This is a serious and interesting point made by a body set up under the aegis of the Department in commenting on this Bill.</P>
    <P>It is noteworthy that the new UK Race Relations Bill, published recently by the Home Secretary, Mr. Jack Straw, places a very direct and specific responsibility on public bodies such as the police, immigration officers, officers dealing with tax and social welfare and the prisons that they perform their official duties not alone <Col N="558" /> in a way that gives no hint or impression of racism or discrimination, but to proactively exclude all forms of unequal treatment.</P>
    <P>Under the Government's strategic management initiative for the public service, the various Departments are obliged to produce a customer action plan which must show how they intend to interface with their customers, including responding to the needs of minority groups. Why is this laudable innovation in the delivery of Government service, which has been in operation for some time, not reflected in the Bill? Has the Minister not taken note of the reported comments of Mr. Peter Finlay, who recently resigned as chairperson of the Refugee Appeals Authority, which clearly indicate his unhappiness with the manner in which the Department of Justice, Equality and Law Reform deals with the applications of asylum seekers and refugees? As I speak, Mr. Finlay is appearing before the Joint Committee on Justice, Equality, Defence and Women's Rights to explain his position and the reasons surrounding his resignation. I greatly regret that I cannot be present at that meeting to hear his comments.</P>
    <P>I referred earlier to the new race relations Bill under discussion in the United Kingdom and the fact that we could learn from it in respect of the inclusion of the public service within the scope of our legislation. In that context I wish to refer to another item of Westminster legislation, the Northern Ireland Act, 1998, which was enacted to fulfil part of the provisions of the Good Friday Agreement. Section 75 of the Act places a statutory obligation to produce an equality scheme within all areas of administration in Northern Ireland and demands that a practical approach be taken to show that, as far as possible, all administrative activity displays a non-discriminatory and complete fairness bias.</P>
    <P>An inquiry was held in the United Kingdom into police activity following the death of Stephen Lawrence, a black British citizen. The findings of that inquiry were, to say the least, damning. However, there is no doubt that this case had an influence on the new race relations legislation in the United Kingdom and the inclusion within its scope of the British public service.</P>
    <P>In this country we have had the resignation of Mr. Peter Finlay which has seriously damaged the public credibility of our asylum and refugee procedures. Does this not make the case, in the most eloquent terms, for the inclusion under the terms of the Bill of at least part of that public service which interfaces with accused persons, asylum seekers, migrants, refugees and Travellers?</P>
    <P>I referred earlier to submissions made to the Joint Committee on Justice, Equality, Defence and Women's Rights in respect of the Bill. The committee was addressed by representatives from, among others, the Irish Council for Civil Liberties, Pavee Point and the National Consulta<Col N="559" /> tive Committee on Racism and Interculturalism, and a number of interesting points were made. For example, the National Consultative Committee on Racism and Interculturalism stated:</P>
    <P>The defence to a claim of discrimination arising out of the provision of a service or accommodation contained in section 15 of the Bill may be over-broad in that it may, in effect, protect discriminatory behaviour and attitudes. This provision allows a person providing personal property, services, or accommodation to discriminate &ldquo;in circumstances which would lead a reasonable individual having the responsibility, knowledge and experience of the person to the belief, on grounds other than discriminatory grounds, that the provision of the property or services, etc., to the customer would produce a substantial risk of criminal or disorderly conduct or behaviour or damage to property at or in the vicinity of the place in which the property or services are sought or the accommodation or land is located. The problem here is that the defence is not limited to cases in which the person discriminated against is responsible for the criminal or disorderly conduct or behaviour or damage to property. Thus, if a publican [or restaurateur or barber] could show that the presence of a traveller in the pub would lead to disorderly conduct by other customers, that publican could refuse to serve the traveller.</P>
    <P>The representatives further stated, &ldquo;The Equal Status Bill should not provide protections to discriminatory behaviour and should be amended to reflect the concerns raised above.&rdquo;  I would like the Minister to comment on that matter when replying to Second Stage.</P>
    <P>The representatives of Pavee Point raised an interesting point in respect of positive action in relation to the Traveller community. They said:</P>
    <P>The provision on positive action in section 14 of the new Bill could be strengthened to permit positive action in support of an interest, as opposed to a need, of ethnic groups and also so as to permit the provision of particular medical services to particular ethnic groups. (Section 16(2) of the new Bill protects different medical treatment of individuals but not groups.)</P>
    <P>It is not clear whether the terms of section 14(b) of the new Bill permitting certain types of positive action extend to the protection of cultural or other activities restricted to travellers.</P>
    <P>The legislation does not permit travellers to register a club limited to travellers under the Registration of Clubs Acts, 1904 to 1995.</P>
    <P>They also commented, &ldquo;Positive Action should be strengthened to permit action in support of an interest; positive action should be extended to the <Col N="560" /> protection of cultural or other activities restricted to travellers and travellers should be permitted to register a club limited to travellers.&rdquo;  Will the Minister comment on that in his reply?</P>
    <P>We on this side of the House urge speedy passage of the Bill and we hope the Minister will accept our reasonable amendments on Committee Stage. It is an important step in adding to the corpus of law that has been placed on the Statute Book on both sides of the Border to combat racism and discrimination on the nine fundamental grounds laid down in the Bill.</P>
    <P>It would be pointless fooling ourselves by believing that racism is not a factor in Irish society. We need only look at the racism experienced by refugees and asylum seekers entering this country in recent years and, unfortunately, official attitudes in that area have not helped. There is also the racism experienced by members of the Traveller community. All Travellers will testify that, in one way or other, they have experienced racism and discrimination. There are at least 22,000 members of the Traveller community in the Republic and there are approximately 3,000 Travellers in Northern Ireland. Travellers are by far the largest minority group on this island and all too often their distinct culture and nomadic identity is not recognised by many in the broader settled community.</P>
    <P>Minority ethnic groups experience racism in this country on the basis of their skin colour and ethnicity regardless of their legal or citizenship status, and racism of the sort experienced by women from minority ethnic groups can be very specific.</P>
    <P>Globalisation is not just concerned with the globalisation of business, it has meant the mass movement of people from one country to another. In 20 years the ethnic make-up of this country will be entirely different from that which exists today, with probably more than 25% of the population not what could be called &ldquo;ethnic Irish&rdquo;. I welcome this diversity and I believe we must lay the groundwork for the demographic changes to which I refer. People must realise that we are experiencing, to a lesser extent, what has already been experienced in most other parts of the world.</P>
    <P>We can only imagine what it must be like in a reasonably stable African country such as Tanzania which has on its borders a country or countries where stability is not known, where civil strife is always present and where law and order has broken down. This leads to the mass movement of hundreds of thousands of people &ndash; in one instance the figure came close to one million &ndash; from their homes to become refugees in other countries. That is the experience of many countries in Africa and southern Asia. A large number of recipient countries, which have low levels of economic development, are generous enough to <Col N="561" /> find a place to accommodate people in flight from another country.</P>
    <P>The history of cultural diversity in this country has been quite different from that of any other European country. As an island nation, we were cut off from transnational movements of people. Travellers, who are an indigenous Irish community, are Ireland's largest minority ethnic group and they have a distinct culture and history based on nomadism.</P>
    <P>In contrast to our neighbours, there has never been large scale immigration into Ireland for the reasons I stated. In Europe there were huge movements of people across national boundaries after the two world wars. The integration was so successful that many people nowadays hardly know it happened. This island, North and South, was always characterised by mass emigration caused by unemployment. That peaked in the 1950s and was a major feature here in the 1970s and from the mid-1980s to the early 1990s.</P>
    <P>These factors, combined with restrictive immigration laws &ndash; which we practise with great enthusiasm &ndash; and the conflict in Northern Ireland, ensured there was no substantial immigration into this country in the past 30 years. We have been insulated, by and large, from the mass transnational movement of people which has been a feature in most other parts of the world. That has contributed greatly towards developing our attitudes. The great pity is that the attitude permeates into the way the Administration expresses itself, which should not happen.</P>
    <P>I am delighted to welcome this Bill. It is a pity it took so long to come to this House and that parts of the original Bill were struck down by the Supreme Court. However, we are not permitted to discuss that matter. We will be tabling some common sense amendments, to which I hope the Minister will have an open-minded approach.</P>
    <Speaker pid="DennisODonovan" hpid="Mr. O'Donovan Mr. O'Donovan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Donovan</NameTxt>
      <P>The Bill is well overdue, given that it was first initiated in 1997. However, for the reasons outlined by Senator Connor, some matters, which were also in the Employment Equality Bill, 1996, were referred to the Supreme Court. The court held that certain aspects of that Bill were unconstitutional, particularly the notion that an employer could be vicariously responsible for the criminal acts of employees. This had a knock-on effect on the Equal Status Bill, 1997.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>As a consequence of the Supreme Court decision, the incoming Government in 1997 had to give great consideration to the new legislation. Although the Supreme Court decided on certain aspects of the Employment Equality Bill, it did not consider the whole Equal Status Bill, 1997. Consequently, the Minister had to seek legal advice on the matter and had to move cautiously to ensure the Bill would stand when it was passed by the Houses. The important feature of this Bill is that it deals with discrimination in the work<Col N="562" /> place or the provision of services outside the employment situation, which is dealt with by the Employment Equality Act, 1998.</P>
    <P>Senator Connor mentioned the resignation of Mr. Finlay and its knock-on effect on the debate on refugees and asylum seekers. I am not competent to comment on the reasons for his resignation. However, two senior colleagues of his differed on major issues relating to the grounds for his retirement. Furthermore, from the facts that have emerged, Mr. Finlay, in his role as appeals commissioner, had the highest rate of refusals on appeal &ndash; in the region of 75%, which is phenomenally high. I am somewhat concerned about this and I do not know the reason for his resignation. This matter is part of an ongoing debate.</P>
    <P>As public representatives and members of local authorities, we have been lobbied by the Vintners' Association about its fears in regard to dealing with the Traveller community. It is accepted there has been discrimination against certain members of the Traveller community in the past. The Bill proposes to address that and to provide penalties for those who disobey the law and continue to discriminate.</P>
    <P>Senator Connor made the interesting point that there are about 22,000 members of the Traveller community in Ireland. I was not aware of that figure. It says it is the largest minority group on this island. If the current trend of in excess of 1,000 refugees and asylum seekers arriving in Ireland per month were to continue for three years, they would overtake Travellers as the largest minority group, which is an interesting scenario. Senator Connor referred to that in his learned contribution.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JohnConnor" hpid="Mr. Connor Mr. Connor">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Connor</NameTxt>
      <P>It is one for our learned friends.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DennisODonovan" hpid="Mr. O'Donovan Mr. O'Donovan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Donovan</NameTxt>
      <P>The Bill deals with discrimination. There is a very broad definition of discrimination on the ground of disability in section 4. The Bill defines &ldquo;disability&rdquo; as including physical disability and &ldquo;the presence in the body of organisms causing, or likely to cause, chronic disease or illness&rdquo;, which could include AIDS. It also includes people with physical defects, learning difficulties such as dyslexia, emotional stress, mental illness, etc. The definition of disability is far-reaching and takes in a very wide scope.</P>
      <P>The Bill provides that it will be discriminatory and contrary to the Bill's theme to discriminate in the disposal of goods and services. For example, people will not be able to refuse to deal with travellers or those with certain skin pigmentation and golf clubs will not be able to refuse to deal with women. That will be outlawed except in regard to wills and gifts in a family context.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The Bill also covers discrimination in educational establishments. There are very valid exceptions to this rule. It is not wrong to decide which school a person can go to, but educational <Col N="563" /> establishments cannot discriminate by saying they will take X, Y and Z but not A, B and C. This Bill prevents educational establishments from doing that.</P>
    <P>Hoteliers and publicans were afraid that if this legislation was enacted there would be widespread trouble from sections of the Traveller community. The Bill does not go to the extremes that those in the Vintners' Federation of Ireland had feared. If a person goes into a bar, no matter what his background, and is likely to cause trouble or is interfering with customers, the hotelier or bar owner can warn the person that he will have to leave unless he behaves. If an asylum seeker, a member of the Traveller community or a person with a disability goes into a bar, it is wrong to refuse that person a drink solely because of his background. If trouble is caused or is likely to be caused, however, the publican can give the person a valid reason for not serving him.</P>
    <P>The Minister has been criticised because there is a perception that there is widespread discrimination against Travellers. There may be in some areas but in my area Travellers are fairly treated. There have been instances at large gatherings with excess alcohol when they are inclined to be over-robust and unruly and in those circumstances publicans must protect their premises. There must be fair play on both sides. It is wrong to refuse food or a drink to a Traveller or a person of a different colour who walks into a hotel or pub unless there is a reason for doing so. If a licensee fails to comply with that provision there is a mechanism in this legislation where the person affected can object to renewal of the licence. In recent times such objections were treated seriously by the courts. This must be sensibly resolved, otherwise every annual licensing court will be tied in knots with objections. The proposals set out by the Minister deal with the matter fairly.</P>
    <P>Cork County Council will soon debate a motion concerning possible discrimination against couples who cohabit or same sex couples who want to acquire local authority housing. This legislation will prevent local authorities from discriminating against such couples.</P>
    <P>The debate about discrimination in golf clubs is relevant to this legislation. Women feel they have been discriminated against down the years and that is true in some golf clubs. I do not know much about golf, but such discrimination is wrong and the sanctions to deal with it in the Bill are strong. Any person offended as a result of discrimination in a golf or other club has the right to object to renewal of the licence. All these licences must be renewed annually and it is not expensive for an offended party to go before the licensing authority to object to renewal of the licence on the grounds of discrimination because of gender.</P>
    <P>The Bill is far-reaching and covers discrimi<Col N="564" /> nation in many areas &ndash; gender, marital status, family status, sexual orientation, religion, age, disability, race and membership of the Traveller community. It gives those who are discriminated against statutory redress. As the Minister said in the Dáil, this is a ground breaking approach to equal status legislation and compliments the Employment Equality Act. The greatest challenge to the Bill is the readiness of society to accept change. Local authorities now provide the necessary access for those with physical disabilities. Most local authority buildings cater for those with physical disabilities. Co-action has several branches in west Cork and there are integrated development groups which monitor discrimination against certain sections of society. Almost ten years ago most employers were asked to employ wheelchair personnel on a temporary basis to give them training and work experience and it has worked well.</P>
    <P>Senator Connor referred to widespread discrimination against refugees and people of different religions and races, be they black, Africans or east European. This legislation will make a full impact only when society accepts change and becomes more broad minded and tolerant in its approach to other religions and races, including Travellers. If society does not accept this there will be a struggle because, regardless of what the law says, enforcement will be difficult. That is the biggest challenge we face. A parallel can be drawn with speed limits. People in towns and villages may erect speed limit signs and ramps, but if the attitude of society does not change no amount of legislation or community effort will prevent speeding because it would be impossible to place Garda officers at every corner and junction.</P>
    <P>Society must come to terms with change. I was my party spokesman on justice when the then Minister, Máire Geoghegan-Quinn, introduced legislation to decriminalise homosexual acts between consenting adults. That legislation was a huge step forward. While disheartening remarks were made on it from some parts of the House, it has been broadly accepted. Similarly, if society accepts there are problems in the areas covered by this legislation and we move with the times, then its provisions will be successfully implemented.</P>
    <P>The Employment Equality Act provides for the appointment of employment equality officers. This Bill contains measures to penalise those who fail to comply with its provisions. While legislation can be placed on the Statute Book, we must also educate our young people and encourage society to think beyond the narrow parameters of the past.</P>
    <P>This is an important Bill and I am sure it will be broadly supported by all sides of the House. I welcome its provisions. It is such a ground breaking measure that it will take a considerable time to debate it fully. I thank the Minister for introducing it and I wish it success. I am sure there will <Col N="565" /> be broad contributions by many Members and that amendments will be proposed on the later Stages. The legislation has already been tested before the Supreme Court, which imposed some restrictions, and it returns to the House in amended form. It is a welcome step forward. I compliment the Minister and his officials and I also compliment those involved in preparing the original 1997 Bill.</P>
    <P>The legislation brings into force provisions that have been enacted in other EU countries. We are the last to act in this regard. I wish the Bill a speedy passage through the House.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelFinneranFF" hpid="Mr. Finneran Mr. Finneran">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman (Mr. Finneran)</NameTxt>
      <P>I call Senator Norris. I understand Senator Norris and Senator Henry wish to share time. Is that agreed? Agreed.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidNorris" hpid="Mr. Norris Mr. Norris">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norris</NameTxt>
      <P>I welcome the Bill. When I entered this House in 1987 such a Bill would have been unthinkable. That shows how much we have moved since then. Much has been said about the earlier Bill, which has now been cured of its constitutional defects, and I do not intend to rehearse too much of that. The Bill is welcome, but Senator O'Donovan has wisely said that while one may legislate, legislation merely forms a headline. People's attitudes and frames of mind need to be looked at and attacked.</P>
      <P>With regard to the question of disability, it is regrettable that when the Bill was before the other House CIE commissioned 150 buses that were not wheelchair accessible. For a public agency to do something like that sends a very poor signal. However, as that moment has passed there is not much point in going back over it. Nevertheless, we must ensure that it never happens again because it is such a slap in the face for the Oireachtas.</P>
      <P>I am disappointed that the definition of &ldquo;disability&rdquo; has not been changed, although strong reservations were expressed about it, especially with regard to the use of words such as &ldquo;malfunction&rdquo;, &ldquo;malformation&rdquo; and so on, so that we are left with a medical definition of &ldquo;disability&rdquo; which appears to place people, even linguistically, at a certain disadvantage. Perhaps the Minister will look at that again.</P>
      <P>Section 15 provides that a proprietor of a public house has the right to discriminate if he or she feels that other customers will be offended. That is a dangerous road to go down because it goes close to the idea of guilt by attainder. There need not be sufficient cause for offence. The proprietor may act on an instinct that his customers may not like, say, people with red hair and so will not allow any to enter the premises. That is wrong.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I am not against discrimination. It is foolish for people of a liberal persuasion like me to say we are against discrimination. We are not. We discriminate every day and for very good reason. When I ran a discotheque geared to raising money for a political cause in which I believe, we did not discriminate on any other basis except behaviour. We did not discriminate on appear<Col N="566" /> ance, class, race, sex or even sexuality. We were so broad minded that we let heterosexuals in to dance. I though that was wonderful. However, we ruthlessly discriminated on the basis of behaviour if we felt that behaviour was anti-social, dangerous, threatening or placing our customers at a disadvantage. I make no apology for that &ndash; it is always reasonable.</P>
    <P>However, I do not like the idea of discrimination at second remove. It is wrong to refuse to admit somebody to a premises on that basis. I speak with authority here because I suffered from that. I was in a pub in South Anne Street 25 years ago with a friend, a lovely person and fairly flamboyant. The barman refused me a drink. I asked why and was told it was because I was with this person. I said I did not allow barmen to choose my friends for me. I presented my card and said I would return at 11 o'clock the next morning and told the person concerned to have the owner present. When I returned I told the owner I would object to his licence or he could give me an apology and a drink. He did so and I told him it was the last drink I would have in his pub. I have not been in it to this day.</P>
    <P>My point is that I have the right to object. We are not giving anybody a great benefit when we provide that if people in golf clubs are discriminated against they have the right to object to the licence. Of course they have. Everybody has that right. We are not giving anybody anything new in that. Any member of the public can object to a licence. Golf clubs and other clubs should be put on notice that they are not permitted by law to discriminate in this fashion.</P>
    <P>I do not suffer from the affliction known as golf and I give thanks to God every morning that I am not a golfer, but there are people who suffer from it and I pity them. Some of them are married to each other &ndash; that is even worse. Take the case of a women married to a golf addict who does not like the treatment she is getting and decides to object. Can one imagine the marital harmony that will create in the home? Clubs should not be allowed to discriminate at all.</P>
    <P>I have raised the thorny issue of marriage. I am very grateful to Senator O'Donovan for being so sensitive to the issue of sexuality and sexual orientation. It is refreshing that these phrases are inserted naturally in legislation without the blinking of an eye, given the battles we had in the past to have them included. There is no facility for gay people to marry or to have their relationships recognised. Therefore, they are at a disadvantage. In his speech in the Dáil &ndash; he repeated it in this House &ndash; the Minister said that the comprehensive definition of disability services in section 2 includes services and facilities of any nature, including access to and use of any place, banking or insurance services, facilities for entertainment, recreation or refreshment, cultural activities, transport or travel and professional trades services, and does not include services provided under contract of service, services not generally available to the public, services generally covered <Col N="567" /> by the Employment Equality Act etc. I assume this could be construed as saying that the provision of a marriage licence through a registry office is a service under the terms of the Bill. If that is so, the Bill permits people to seek a marriage licence from a registry office, and the registry office would be breaking the law if it did not provide one. One could argue that marriage is a facility for entertainment, recreation or refreshment and that it would be illegal to discriminate against gay people who apply for a marriage licence. I am glad to see my colleagues smiling, but there is a serious point.</P>
    <P>I am glad Senator O'Donovan raised the issue of housing. Gay people are treated as single and because of that are at the bottom of the pile in terms of housing and cannot get local authority housing whatever their financial situation. This is a great pity.</P>
    <P>I would like to know whether the issues I raise are contemplated in the Bill. If not, is the Minister serious &ndash; I think he is &ndash; when he says discrimination occurs when a person is treated less favourably than another person is, has been or would be treated, or where a person is treated less favourably because of his or her association with the person to whom the discrimination grounds apply, or where a requirement to comply with a condition has a disproportionately adverse effect on a particular category of persons and this requirement cannot be justified as being reasonable in all circumstances? I think we are making a very good case for recognition of gay relationships. I believe it may be a case of what is called in the Roman Catholic Church &ldquo;indirect cause&rdquo; or &ldquo;multiple effect&rdquo;, namely, that it provides for something not explicitly stated. It would be lovely if this Roman Catholic theological notion sanctioned the recognition of relationships. That day will have to come. Recently it came in France, and recognition already exists in Holland, Denmark and many other countries. It is not an extravagant or absurd demand, it is simply at the core of the Bill, that is, the requirement to be treated as ordinary and equal citizens.</P>
    <P>I well remember the day Senator O'Donovan spoke about when Máire Geoghegan-Quinn, a member of the Government party and a splendid Minister, introduced legislation decriminalising homosexuality. I remember there were some mean-minded attempts to create a discriminatory age of consent. I was so heartened when she said she would need good and cogent reasons in order to discriminate against a citizen of the State and that no such reasons had been provided by the other side of the House. This is a very good approach. The treatment of gay relationships, with very clear and practical consequences, is highly discriminatory and has to do with the perceived status of gay people and their capacity to form relationships.</P>
    <P>I have already mentioned buses, and I know that some taxis have been specially adapted, with licences given at a reduced cost. Some taximen <Col N="568" /> very honourably use the licences while others do not, which is very regrettable. I thought it was absurd and rather offensive for a public official to complain about the hygiene of taximen. In defence of taximen, recently I saw a taximan on O'Connell Street, in an old taxi which was not adapted, assisting a disabled person into his taxi, carefully folding the wheelchair and trying to put it into the boot of quite an old car. I stopped my car and said, &ldquo;Well done, I am proud of you as a citizen of Dublin for doing so&rdquo;.</P>
    <Speaker pid="HelenKeogh" hpid="Ms Keogh Ms Keogh">
      <NameTxt>Ms Keogh</NameTxt>
      <P>That is unique.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidNorris" hpid="Mr. Norris Mr. Norris">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norris</NameTxt>
      <P>It is not entirely unique. It was an awkward thing for the taximan to do given the ancient car he had.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryHenry" hpid="Dr. Henry Dr. Henry">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Henry</NameTxt>
      <P>From the way the Senator spoke we thought he put the old woman in the boot.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidNorris" hpid="Mr. Norris Mr. Norris">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norris</NameTxt>
      <P>No, it was not Dr. Henry &ndash; the Senator is the old woman in the shoe.</P>
      <P>It is excellent that there is provision for an equality authority and I am glad there is provision for funding. However, from the beginning there should be clearly defined lines of contact with all the specific organisations concerned, including women's organisations, organisations for the disabled and those representing gay people and Travellers. It is only with that kind of liaison that we will learn what is happening at the cutting edge and that the agency will fulfil its proper function.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryHenry" hpid="Dr. Henry Dr. Henry">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Henry</NameTxt>
      <P>I welcome the Bill, although I have some reservations about parts of it. I had the great satisfaction of seeing the last Bill struck down by the Supreme Court. Senator O'Toole and I were quite convinced that it would be declared unconstitutional. It was not declared unconstitutional on the grounds we suggested, but I am sure if the Supreme Court had looked more closely at the provisions to which we objected, it would have thought the same.</P>
      <P>I take on board the points made by Senator Connor about racism. It is unfortunate the Bill is so urgently needed in this context. When we had no foreigners here we were extremely non-racist, but now that we have a considerable number of people of other races in the country we get reports almost on a daily basis of people being harassed or in other ways discriminated against, which is most regrettable. Some people have come here as refugees or asylum seekers, and one must admit that despite the best efforts of many people in the health boards, they are getting the fuzzy end of the lollipop in many cases as they have difficulty in securing accommodation and are harassed in the street and life in general is not very easy for them.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Recently I heard a women on the radio whom I thought was very honest when she said that a few years ago if she met a black man on the street she thought he was a doctor, but now she thinks <Col N="569" /> he is a refugee and her attitude towards him is totally different. Of course the person could be a refugee doctor, and I assure the House there are some in the city.</P>
    <P>To my sorrow I have met some children of programme refugees who have told me they feel very much discriminated against. It is very sad that we brought them here, offered them a home and yet our behaviour towards them is apparently not as welcoming as it should be. A surprising number of these people in their 20s are not employed and they feel it is because of their race.</P>
    <P>A third group which should be paid special attention are children from South America, the Far East and Africa adopted by Irish couples. We must be aware that these children could easily be the victims of racism. Recently I had an extraordinary experience when speaking at a school celebration. The school's headmaster made an excellent speech in which he referred to young people growing up with integrity and treating people properly. I continued in this vein and spoke about treating people in a decent manner. I thought it had gone down well but at tea afterwards a man approached me and said that it was all very well to say that people should be treated equally and that they are all the same, but that I should have said that Romanians were not the same and did not have a work ethic. I cannot imagine anyone in their right mind expecting somebody to announce at a school, which could have adopted Romanian children on its roll, that all people are equal but one group should be singled out. I was absolutely stunned that anybody could even think like that. We are not doing enough to try to combat racism in Ireland and more could be done in schools.</P>
    <P>The Bill could encourage a more proactive approach to defeating discrimination. Many of its provisions require complaints to be made and it would be nice if a provision to promote equal treatment were included. Senator Connor referred to the non-inclusion of statutory bodies. That is unfortunate and I wish planning authorities were included. I live in Dublin's south inner city and already there is segregation in some areas. For example, Romanian people mainly reside on certain streets while Nigerians predominate on others. Planning authorities could quite easily get a notion that it is best to keep people segregated. Segregation was used successfully in many other countries to discriminate against certain people and I am concerned about that. Differences could develop in schools and all of us are aware of the horrible developments in other countries as a result of segregation.</P>
    <P>With the best will in the world, immigration officials are the same as us and if we are inclined to be racist I cannot say whether they might not be. A young woman of my acquaintance has a child who is not quite as fair as her and when the child was returning from a visit to its father in London, it had a very difficult time at immigration. Such small incidents makes one realise <Col N="570" /> that we have a long way to go to be as tolerant as we should be.</P>
    <P>I will conclude by referring to sexual harassment and golf clubs. I am glad section 11(5) has been included because it can be difficult sometimes to definitively say certain behaviour is sexual as opposed to being physical abuse. This seems to be covered in the legislation and it can be discussed further on Committee Stage. Section 11(5) states: &ldquo;Harassment takes place where a person subjects another person (&ldquo;the victim&ldquo;) to any unwelcome act, request or conduct, including spoken words, gestures or the production, display or circulation of written words, pictures or other material, which in respect of the victim is based on any discriminatory ground and which could reasonably be regarded as offensive, humiliating or intimidating to him or her.&rdquo;  It is good that such a strong subsection is included because referring only to sexual abuse and not physical ill-treatment sometimes ignores an area which is extremely distressing to the victim, but it may be difficult to prove if only sexual abuse is covered. The Minister will be aware of our efforts to have physical ill-treatment included in another Bill.</P>
    <P>Golf clubs are extraordinarily foolish to discriminate in the manner that they do. I had the good fortune to be one of the first two women members of the University and Kildare Street Club. The late Ms Grace Carroll and I behaved so well that within a year or two the club desperately sought other women members. I was constantly asked whether I could find more women members because we behaved well and paid our bills. Golf clubs would be well advised to think of their pockets and consider how useful it would be to have well behaved women members who pay their bills. It is such a pity as many organisations have realised that people can be admitted as members on an equal basis.</P>
    <P>Like Senator Norris, I have the good fortune not to play golf as I believe in the old adage that it spoils a good walk. I have great sympathy for women who work all week and are good golfers but cannot play at weekends. It is a pity that people are excluded on such a childish basis. I hope the boards of golf clubs will come to their senses. Senator O'Donovan stated that laws can be changed but not people's attitudes. If the Fitzwilliam Lawn Tennis Club can change its attitude, any club can.</P>
    <Speaker pid="HelenKeogh" hpid="Ms Keogh Ms Keogh">
      <NameTxt>Ms Keogh</NameTxt>
      <P>I participated in a debate on the original Bill in the Dáil on 27 February 1997. At the time, while I welcomed the Bill and all of us recognised its necessity, I was pessimistic and said that it had been rushed because the then Minister, who had done a good job, wanted to get it through the Houses of the Oireachtas before the pending general election and, therefore, there were flaws. I stated:</P>
      <P>. . . we are allowing some elements to fall between the cracks. It would appear that some of their implications have not been given sufficient thought.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="571" /> I questioned some provisions which might have been unconstitutional, but I did not realise that I was prophetic. However, the then Minister accepted amendments which improved the legislation. The Minister has accepted amendments to the current Bill in the Dáil but it has been proved that if legislation is rushed, it is often flawed. Despite the fact that there has been a long delay, this legislation was worth waiting for.</P>
    <P>It was also quite extraordinary that in 1997 the emphasis was very much on the Travellers versus vintners issue and it was perceived that undue emphasis was placed on that in the consultations and subsequent debate on the legislation. Fortunately, the emphasis has moved from that issue to discrimination against people with disabilities, which was my main focus. It has been recognised that Ireland must fulfil its international obligations and issues must be addressed, including human rights, under the terms of the Good Friday Agreement.</P>
    <P>However, because of the change in our society we are even more conscious of the discrimination against our immigrant population. The Equal Status Bill, 1997, was introduced shortly after a book had been published by Fr. McGréil entitled <i>Prejudice in Ireland Revisited. </i>It illustrated the degree of prejudice that existed in society. If he were to rewrite that book now the emphasis would be different. We do not want or need intolerance and discrimination in our society. This legislation, in tandem with the Employment Equality Bill, 1999, must be a mainstay in ensuring that intolerance is eliminated.</P>
    <P>I agree with colleagues who stated the legislation is fine but attitudes are the problem. I frequently hark back to the fact that the enactment of much of the legislation relating to women's rights would have taken much longer were it not for Ireland's membership of the EU. Some of it might never have been introduced. There is a big gap between introducing and enforcing legislation and changing attitudes, which is a major challenge.</P>
    <P>I regret that some of the provisions of the Bill were not acceptable to the Supreme Court. The Minister mentioned the main changes that were made. The 1997 Bill required service providers to make reasonable accommodation, including the provision of special treatment or facilities for people with disabilities, unless such reasonable accommodation would give rise to undue difficulty. Unfortunately, that was found to be unconstitutional and now the obligation to make reasonable accommodation is subject to a nominal cost threshold. I regret that.</P>
    <P>I would like to focus on the issue of people with a disability, although other colleagues mentioned areas such as transport and so on. I am delighted to hear that Senator Norris saw one incident of a taxi driver helping a person with a disability. I have experience of this issue because my mother was and my father is confined to a wheelchair or, as people with a disability prefer to say, he is a <Col N="572" /> wheelchair user. Trying to get my father anywhere is a nightmare if we cannot transport him in our own car. Despite the many licences that are available, it is very difficult to get a suitable taxi for a person with a disability. I have personal experience of ringing six companies to get a taxi that would take a wheelchair. The whole process, which was extremely frustrating, took most of the day and was very demeaning for my father. It totally disrupted our family life for that day and that is grossly unfair.</P>
    <P>There is an excellent Cheshire Home facility in Monkstown, in my Dún Laoghaire constituency. I have seen active discrimination against its residents, who are very independent people. They have been discriminated against in pubs and shops and I am aware of the huge difficulties they face in terms of mobility. The problem of wheelchair access to restaurants, pubs and so on must be addressed, and it is so easy to get around these issues.</P>
    <P>This is real &ldquo;mother-in-law research&rdquo; but these are the issues that affect people with a disability. A friend of mine who is confined to a wheelchair wanted to go out for an evening's entertainment with the family. They eventually found a restaurant that had wheelchair accessibility only to discover that the toilets were two floors up. That is utterly ludicrous. How could somebody in a wheelchair possibly manage such nonsense? That is something that should be outlawed because it is utterly disgraceful.</P>
    <P>On the issue of access to transport, quite apart from taxis, the buses have been mentioned already, and I do not want to rehearse the issue. A person with a disability finds the use of public transport virtually impossible &ndash; that goes for trains, buses, taxis, etc. I hope that when the Bill is enacted, it will be enforced. I accept Senator Henry's point about the individual having to make a complaint. I would prefer if we were more proactive, to use that appalling word, in ensuring that facilities are available for people with a disability.</P>
    <P>In 1997 I referred to the development plans for county councils and the reason it should be essential that all the elements that would make life easier for people with a disability should be contained in them. The 1992 building regulations allow for this but they are not enforced. We may enact laws but if we do not enforce them we are insulting people with a disability. This legislation was not enacted because it was rejected by the Supreme Court, but everybody knows the difficulties that have to be addressed. Nevertheless, there has not been the preparation that should have been made over the past three years. That is disgraceful and I blame local authorities in that they are not sufficiently aware of these difficulties. I am not convinced that all local authorities live up to their obligations in that regard, despite opinion to the contrary.</P>
    <P>In 1997, I said that this was colloquially known as the Travellers versus the vintners Bill. We have moved on from that but we continue to see a <Col N="573" /> great deal of discrimination against travelling people. I am glad that they have evolved groups within their own ranks such as Pavee Point and they are now aware of their rights and their responsibilities. Unfortunately, there has been bad publicity surrounding rows at weddings, etc., but we must not generalise in that regard. We must be aware of the rights of travellers as well as other groups to the provision of services as stated in the Bill.</P>
    <P>I want to touch on the issue of golf clubs. I would prefer to see some penalty other than a licence not being renewed, although that hits clubs where it hurts &ndash; in their pockets. We have come a long way on this issue. When I was a member of the women's rights committee in 1991, we wrote to all the golf clubs. A considerable proportion of them did not even bother to reply, after all, we were only the women's rights committee of the Oireachtas. Times have changed since then and clubs now realise that a sanction can be imposed and their attitude will be different. As Senator Norris pointed out, however, one could always challenge the renewal of a licence. I am sorry that a more draconian sanction cannot be imposed. Perhaps that is because I felt so annoyed at the golf clubs ignoring an official committee of the Oireachtas.</P>
    <P>The stories of discrimination against women in golf clubs are legion. I have had only a brief flirtation with golf but I am aware of incidents of discrimination from friends of mine, particularly those who live in the country. A friend of mine who was out at work all day discovered that the local golf club did not allow women to play golf after 5 o'clock in the evening during the summer because the men would be coming home from work and would want to play. I think that rule has changed in that particular golf club and, I hope, in every golf club, but it was a long time coming. For many clubs, it was the threat of legislation such as this and the availability of sanctions that made them act. Unfortunately, unless there is a threat of sanction under legislation, it is difficult to change actions, never mind attitudes. I hope we will not see many clubs having their licences revoked as a result of discrimination.</P>
    <P>I am not 100% sure about the provisions in the Bill in relation to sexual harassment. I had reservations about them in 1997 and they have been changed slightly. However, I still have difficulty with the concept of the reasonable person and the definition of sexual harassment and harassment generally. I am open to correction on this and I hope the Minister will refer to it when he replies to the debate.</P>
    <P>There was a reference earlier to accommodation. Senator O'Donovan mentioned the motion being brought before Cork County Council next Monday in relation to couples who do not fall within a neat category for local authority housing purposes. I am proud that my party colleague is putting the motion forward. It will be <Col N="574" /> interesting to see the reaction to it. The fact that there is a great openness to accepting the motion indicates that there is a great deal more openness than previously. However, it will be interesting to see if there is a backlash against it. The jury is out on it at present.</P>
    <P>There is a sense of <i>déjà vu</i> about the provisions of the Bill, which I support. I wish some elements were a little stronger but I am aware of the constraints which have been put upon the Minister, particularly in the context of the Supreme Court's findings. My wish is that society would have attitudes that are ahead of legislation and that legislation would try to catch up with them rather than the other way around. I hope society will develop a tolerance for all elements within it and an openness to change in the future.</P>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. Ryan Mr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>Ar dtús báire cuirim fáilte roimh an Aire. Tá a lán ama caite agam féin agus aigesean le chéile le déanaí agus tá sé in ndán dó rud éigin eile a dhéanamh agus ansin a éalú as an Teach seo chomh tapaidh agus ab'fhéidir leis. Caithfidh mé fáilte a chur roimh atá sa Bhille, áfach. Mar a dúirt an Seanadóir Keogh, b'fhéidir go mbeadh duine ag súil le níos mó ann ach tá fáilte roimh an mhéid atá ann.  One cannot but welcome this legislation. I do not mean to cavil but to sound a wake up call to everybody in the political system by pointing out that conventions such as the UN Convention on the Elimination of All Forms of Racial Discrimination, which dates from 1968, should not have to wait so long to be ratified by the State. It would be interesting to get a list of the international conventions we have signed, the dates we signed them and when it is proposed to ratify them. We appear to be a little slow in this regard although a few Bills have come before the House.</P>
      <P>It would be equivalent to the priest at Mass denouncing to the congregation those who do not go to mass for me to criticise this Minister for the fact that other conventions have not been ratified when he is doing the job in this legislation. However, there is a problem in legislative structures when a convention is left unratified for 32 years and a reservation is entered with regard to another convention on the rights of women. This does not speak well for us. Neither House of the Oireachtas was so busy in the past that it could not have ratified them and it is well past time that it was done.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>In an ideal world, legislation such as this would not be required. In a world full of tolerance and with the values advocated and articulated by the speakers in this debate, people would not discriminate against other people on spurious grounds which have nothing to do with any objective reality either threatening, offensive or to do with something about which people deserve to be made feel lesser members of society. The truth is, however, that every ground listed in the legis<Col N="575" /> lation is a ground on which, in some way great or small, more often great than small, citizens of Ireland have been discriminated against in the provision of various services and in access to those services.</P>
    <P>All sorts of agencies and, to some extent until recently, the State were far from being models of tolerance &ndash; that must be said. I was not a Member of the Seanad when a previous Minister for Justice, Máire Geoghegan-Quinn, courageously ploughed a furrow on the issue of homosexual law reform. That moved Ireland from being perceived as extremely illiberal to being to the forefront of sensible, practical, liberal common sense. I have no patience with excesses of liberalism any more than with any other type of excess. However, what was done in that case and the subsequent succession of legislative measures, which have copperfastened various minority groups' rights not to have people incited to hate them, are building blocks in the recognition that we are a diverse society.</P>
    <P>We are obviously diverse in terms of gender and we are now diverse in terms of unorthodox family structures. Many of us might find many of the unorthodox family structures a little regrettable and we might wonder about the well-being of children living in them. However, they exist and society must recognise them. We have to live with the society we have. Many of the changes in our society are the negative consequences of many of the good things that happened in that society.</P>
    <P>This country has a better record with regard to discrimination against people on the ground of religion than many cardinals of liberal Ireland would have us believe. It was not a country in which it was impossible to grow up as a member of a minority religion. One would sometimes have the impression that until about 1964 this country was the European equivalent of Saudi Arabia or Iran or somewhere similar. It is not and never was.</P>
    <P>It was a country which, in the profoundly illiberal 1930s, put in place a Constitution which vigorously asserted freedom of speech, freedom of religion and freedom of conscience. It was qualified to a degree but not to a degree to which anybody could object. We should not in this context, therefore, flagellate ourselves too much. Given our relatively new independent status and what that entailed, and given the climate in Europe in the 1930s, the 1937 Constitution is a remarkably liberal document. I would be less than enthusiastic about a new one which would emanate from existing State organisations. I would not be as convinced as many others that a new Constitution would contain within it the capacity the old Constitution contained for the citizen to defend himself or herself against the State.</P>
    <P>That is why it is regrettable that an otherwise <Col N="576" /> progressive, forward-looking and liberal document was peculiarly interpreted &ndash; I use the word advisedly &ndash; by their lordships in the Supreme Court. The use of the right to property as a justification for striking down progressive, sensible legislation, which was essentially the grounds used, was a profound mistake on the part of the Supreme Court. We must pass this legislation to ratify certain international conventions, but as I have said on previous occasions, the remedy in the longer term is to restore a proper balance which defines the common good in such a way that it includes the good of those who are disabled and so that the rights of property may be constrained. I would be concerned that the requirement for taxi drivers in Dublin, however reluctant they appear to be to provide the service, to purchase wheelchair accessible taxis would result in some smart alec pursuing the matter to the Supreme Court on these constitutional grounds and their lordships, who fortunately are a much changed bunch now and on balance for the better, are coming to the same conclusion.</P>
    <P>I am also concerned about planning regulations and the planning process. The Simon Community, an organisation with which I am involved, went through the planning process and came into conflict with people developing a hotel on a neighbouring site. Objections to planning permission were raised on the grounds that the provision of services for the homeless next door to a hotel would undermine the capacity of the hotel to do its business. If the logic of how this legislation's predecessor was found to be unconstitutional and how the employment equality legislation was similarly struck down were to be extended a fraction of a millimetre further, one could enter extremely difficult territory concerning the location of services for any group, such as Travellers or a social club for gay men or women, because of the argument that the provision of those services and the insistence of the State in allowing them to be provided in a certain place would arguably cause a collapse or a fall in the value of surrounding property. The solution to copperfasten against that is a constitutional amendment to make it clear that the common good provision of our Constitution extends to the protection and assertion of the rights of people who are disabled. I invite the Minister to consider that in the medium term.</P>
    <P>Much of what I wanted to say has already been said and I do not want to repeat myself excessively. While Senator Keogh is perhaps correct about the wording of the sections on harassment, people in charge, especially of educational and other establishments, would want to be alerted to the scale of their responsibilities under the Bill and that it is their obligation to ensure that all reasonable steps are taken to avoid sexual harassment occurring. This would especially be the case for anyone working in third level education. Any<Col N="577" /> one working in second level education who becomes involved in what would be classified as sexual harassment is involved in something much more offensive &ndash; sexual assault on children who are mostly underage. In third level education, where the students are adults, the issue of sexual harassment is a matter of genuine concern. In some areas, especially the areas of science and technology with which I am familiar, women are relatively new participants and many working in those areas could do with significant education and guidance from their employers and management about the new realities of the correct way.</P>
    <P>The phrase &ldquo;politically correct&rdquo; has been devalued but there is a logic to it. There is a correct way to talk about and treat people. One of the things which has grown from this understanding of correctness, even political correctness, is the unacceptability of what used to be regarded, in male circles especially, as a reasonable bit of fun. A great deal of what is now clearly classified as sexual harassment was treated by many men, some considerably younger than me as well as most of those who would have been older, as harmless fun. What would have been treated as such by an employer <i>vis-à-vis</i> a female employee is now to be made illegal. That is correct and we owe it to employers to remind them not only what they must not do but also that they must take reasonable steps to ensure that their employees do not do it either. That is something which would need to be hammered out in great detail.</P>
    <P>I am glad discriminatory clubs will suffer some penalties. I have never understood this peculiar attitude and the logic or rationale behind it is beyond me. I have this vision of men almost in a state of refugee status seeking refuge from half the human race and claiming some type of constitutional or legal right to do so in conditions of their own choosing.</P>
    <P>While I welcome the Bill, I have a few questions which the Minister might address. We discussed one of these during the debate on the Employment Equality Act and I am still not entirely persuaded. It is: &ldquo;As between . . . . . two persons, the discriminatory grounds . . . . . are . . . . . that they are of different sexual orientation&rdquo;. As my holy mother, the Church, would say, there is a difference between having a sexual orientation and being sexually active as a homosexual. There is nothing in the Bill or in the Employment Equality Act which would copperfasten the right of a homosexual couple to live together and have a sexual relationship. We are simply saying that the orientation cannot be discriminated against. It is perfectly reasonable to argue that what is being said is that, as long as a person is celibate, they cannot be discriminated against. I do not believe that is the intention, nor that it would fulfil our obligations under various international conventions, but that is what the wording means. <Col N="578" /> I cannot be discriminated against on the grounds of my marital or family status, but a gay person cannot be discriminated against on the grounds of orientation. Nowhere does it say that they cannot be discriminated against on the grounds of their activity.</P>
    <P>I am not talking about a high camp Quentin Crisp lookalike providing entertainment but about the late couple who provided this country with such wonderful theatrical entertainment at a time when most people would not pronounce the word homosexual, let alone admit that we were turning into national heroes two men who were openly and actively gay. I am not persuaded that this legislation will protect such a couple from discrimination because it is based on their orientation, not their activity. The orientation, as the Catholic Church will say, is not objectionable. It is to the physical expression of that orientation that most Christian churches, particularly the Catholic Church, object. We do not protect people from discrimination in this legislation if that discrimination is based on the physical expression of their homosexual orientation. I have been concerned about that since the Employment Equality Act was passed in this House.</P>
    <P>I am not sure what section 3(3) means. It states: &ldquo;Treating a person who has not attained the age of 18 years less favourably or more favourably than another, whatever that other person's age, shall not be regarded as discrimination on the age ground.&rdquo;  You have to read it a few times to figure out what it means. I am sure the Minister has read it many times and knows what it means. Perhaps he could give us examples of what it is meant to protect us from because obviously there is a reason for it. Sometimes it would be wrong to discriminate between people who are under 18 years of age and those who are over 18. However, the phraseology is wider than that. It appears that one could discriminate between two 17 year olds or between an 18 year old and a 17 year old.</P>
    <P>Section 5(2)(<i>g</i>) refers to &ldquo;differences in the treatment of persons on the gender ground where embarrassment or infringement of privacy can reasonably be expected to result from the presence of a person of another gender&rdquo;. One can understand this in places such as public toilets, swimming pools or dressing rooms. However, the language could be more precise. Section 5(2)(<i>i</i>) refers to &ldquo;differences in the treatment of persons on the gender, age or disability ground or on the ground of race, reasonably required for reasons of authenticity, aesthetics, tradition or custom in connection with a dramatic performance or other entertainment&rdquo;. I know what is intended but it should be made more explicit that this applies to people participating in the performance, not to people attending the performance.</P>
    <P>Perhaps the Minister could clarify the position where an employee is directed to discriminate. What is the employee's legal obligation? Should he refuse to carry out that instruction or should <Col N="579" /> he carry it out and let the employer take the blame? Will the employee be protected? </P>
    <P>Since sections of this Bill enable us to ratify a convention which is 32 years old, why is it not possible to indicate that it will be ratified within a short period of its enactment? Section 48 states that this Act shall come into operation on such day as may be fixed by order made by the Minister, and different days may be so fixed for different provisions and for different purposes. We should have included a reference in the Bill that the convention will be ratified within a short period of its enactment.</P>
    <Speaker pid="TonyKett" hpid="Mr. Kett Mr. Kett">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Kett</NameTxt>
      <P>I thank the Minister for bringing forward this legislation. I recall the legislation first introduced in 1997 which was found to be unconstitutional. I applaud the Minister for his efforts in bringing this Bill to the stage we are at today because it would have been easy to set it aside. The Bill seeks to prevent discrimination under a wide range of headings outside the employment area. I will concentrate my remarks on the area of disability.</P>
      <P>Legislation is only as good as our ability to implement and monitor it, particularly when people may choose to ignore it. Many Governments made promises and commitments to remove discrimination from our society. However, many of them fell short of what is reasonable and acceptable in a civilised society. People with disabilities have recently complained to us about the lack of commitment they feel we have shown in this regard. They feel we have failed to effect the necessary changes to ensure accessibility at all levels and proper integration to society. We are all aware of the protests by disabled people at the gates of Leinster House. They have found their voice and they will not go away.</P>
      <P>It is important that we use language which reflects the rights of people with disabilities so they are treated as full citizens and included in all aspects of society. In order to achieve this, we must include them in the decision-making process. I applaud the Minister for setting up the disability authority. For the first time people with disabilities will be able to speak for themselves at a body which is sponsored by the Government. I am sure that people with disabilities are delighted to be able to express themselves at this forum.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Access is the gateway to full participation for people with disabilities. This does not only mean access to buildings, parks and beaches but to the right to travel freely, to education and housing and to live independently if someone so wishes. The frustration and anger felt by people with disabilities as a result of inaccessible buildings was evident from the submissions made to the Commission on the Status of People with Disabilities in 1997. The introduction in 1991 of the building regulations with a section on access for people with disabilities, which referred to new buildings and significant changes to old buildings, raised the hopes and expectations of people with dis<Col N="580" /> abilities. Unfortunately, those hopes gave way to a weary resignation when they did not materialise.</P>
    <P>Despite strong pressure, the pace of change has been extremely slow but this is not the fault of a particular Government. It is a matter of changing attitudes and opinions on how we should go about it and how swiftly we should move on. The approach was not aimed at establishing an enabling environment. It was done in a piecemeal fashion and we made special provision for special cases. The words &ldquo;reasonable provision&rdquo; were used and could have been interpreted to suggest that it was reasonable to deny access rather than allow or give access. The wording was too ambiguous and it left too much room for the building regulators and designers to place their own limits on a situation as they saw fit.</P>
    <P>The Minister mentioned transport. Providing transport that would be more accessible is not of interest only to people with disabilities. It is of interest to a number of people, particularly the elderly and women shopping with children and trying to get on or off buses with prams. Ireland falls well behind our European counterparts in terms of accessible transport. I will not labour the point that was raised by Senator Norris and others in relation to the 150 buses. I did that on the Order of Business some time ago. Nor will I labour the point made by Senator Finneran last week on the Order of Business about the disabled person travelling by train in the guard's van. That is degrading and unacceptable. The more speed we introduce into this issue the better.</P>
    <P>Transport is a key issue to people with disabilities because they want to integrate into society. Without transport, accessibility to education and all the other elements we have talked about cannot be achieved. In the past we have heard the argument about the cost of adapting rolling-stock but that is no longer a reasonable argument. I know this is not the Minister's bailiwick. It reflects on all Departments that have a commitment to financing the various areas that need to be financed to address this matter. If we stand back from the issue on the basis that we cannot afford it &ndash; and I know it is a costly thing to put right &ndash; we will never get it done.</P>
    <P>Section 4(2) frightens me somewhat. The Minister referred to it in his speech where he stated that he is constitutionally bound on it. It states: </P>
    <P>A refusal or failure to provide the special treatment or facilities to which <i>subsection (1)</i> refers shall not be deemed reasonable unless such provision would give rise to a cost, other than a nominal cost, . . . .   </P>
    <P>Is &ldquo;nominal cost&rdquo; defined or can people use their own definition of it?</P>
    <P>The Commission on the Status of People with Disabilities made recommendations on transportation. It referred to purchases of new and older public transport vehicles, including those ordered by private operators, and suggested that they should be accessible as and from 1 January 1997. <Col N="581" /> Three years later that has not become a reality. I am not sure that transport providers are aware that their licences could be revoked if they do not adhere to that recommendation. I do not believe the law is there to be invoked.</P>
    <P>The number of people with disabilities in education is estimated to be 5% of the school going population. That figure is open to question because the information available may not be accurate. It is the policy of the Department of Education and Science to educate as many children with disabilities as possible in mainstream schools. That is a welcome development in recent years. In bringing about that kind of integration we must have the resources to go with it. I know the position and it has improved. I know of a young girl who was allowed into a secondary school a few years ago but the resources to facilitate her did not exist. She had to rely on the good nature of her friends to do something as personal as toileting her. That is not acceptable and I know that facilities have greatly improved.</P>
    <P>Independence is an important aspiration for all of us but it is more important for people with disabilities. It could be defined as dignified self-determination, with or without the help of others. Technology and telecommunications can play a major role in helping people with disabilities to secure equal status. We should be able to assist in that regard. We can assist people with hearing impairments to communicate. We can help people with visual problems to read and use computers. We can also help people who are physically impaired to live independently if we have commitment, resources and goodwill.</P>
    <P>Technology is available now but the problem is to get the resources to bring it to people in the community. We have achieved that in some respects because we have relied on European schemes. Unfortunately, they are set over two or three years and then a vacuum develops. Something that has been created and is of benefit to people with disabilities falls down because the resources are not there at domestic level.</P>
    <P>We should continue to do all in our power to highlight the needs of the disabled. The Minister has endeavoured to bring about a better quality of life for people with disabilities. We only have to look at the legislation that he has brought through this House in the past two years to be convinced of that. I look forward to the passage of this Bill through the Seanad and to continuing improvements for people with disabilities and the marginalised in our society.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JohnCreganFF" hpid="Mr. J. Cregan Mr. J. Cregan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J. Cregan</NameTxt>
      <P>Like previous speakers, I welcome the Minister to the House. I am glad to have the opportunity to comment on this complex legislation. Members have said that the Bill is long overdue. However, due to its complexity everyone wanted to ensure that it was right. I compliment the Department of Justice, Equality and Law Reform on its input. Not long ago it was accused of not being a friend of the public but in response the Minister cited several pieces of <Col N="582" /> legislation that had been introduced. This Bill is another typical example of the Department and the Minister coming up trumps.</P>
      <P>I support the provisions of this far reaching measure which has the potential to affect many areas of Irish life. It replaces the Equal Status Bill, 1997, which the Supreme Court found unconstitutional. The thrust of this measure is the same as the 1997 Bill but it has been appropriately amended to meet the requirements of the Supreme Court.</P>
      <P>The Bill represents a commitment to the implementation of the Good Friday Agreement. It is necessary to enable Ireland to ratify the UN convention on the elimination of all forms of racial discrimination and to lift our reserve on the UN convention on the elimination on all forms of discrimination against women. The Bill provides for the promotion of equality and the prohibition of discrimination, harassment and irate behaviour in non-employment areas and for remedies and enforcement measures. It complements the Employment Equality Act, 1998, which outlaws discrimination in all areas relevant to employment. The specific grounds on which it prohibits discrimination are gender, marital and family status, sexual orientation, religion, age, disability and race, including colour, nationality, ethnic and national origin and membership of the Traveller community. The Bill outlaws direct and indirect discrimination on these grounds regarding the provision of goods and services, accommodation, disposal of premises and education. All services generally available to the public are covered, including facilities for refreshments and entertainment, credit facilities and transport services.</P>
      <P>Complaints of discrimination, other than discrimination by registered clubs, may be referred to the Office of the Director of Equality Investigations, established under the Employment Equality Act, 1998. The director, having investigated the case, can award compensation of up to £5,000 and/or require the taking of a specific course of action. Decisions of the director on equal status cases may be appealed to the Circuit Court. Cases involving registered clubs will be heard by the District Court, with an appeal to the Circuit Court. Under the Bill, the remit of the Equality Authority will also include equal status matters.</P>
      <P>Section 3 defines discrimination for the purpose of the Bill. Discrimination shall be taken to occur where on any of the grounds that exists at present or previously existed but no longer exists or which may exist in the future, or which is imputed to the person concerned, a person is treated less favourably than another person is, has been or would be treated. Discrimination also takes place where the requirement to comply with a condition has a substantially more adverse effect on a category of persons than on others and the obligation to comply with that condition cannot be justified as being reasonable in all the circumstances of the case.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Section 5 prohibits discrimination in the dispos<Col N="583" /> ing of goods or the provision of a service. It is irrelevant whether the goods or service are provided for payment or only to a section of the public. There are exemptions for the disposal of goods by will or gift and for differences of treatment in certain circumstances in particular areas, such as insurance, adopting, fostering, sporting events and entertainment and where privacy is a factor.</P>
    <P>Section 6 prohibits discrimination in land dispositions, provision of accommodation and services and amenities related to accommodation.</P>
    <P>Section 7 prohibits discrimination by educational establishments against students in relation to admission, access to courses and facilities. Primary and post-primary schools will not be regarded as being discriminatory simply because they are single gender and a seminary may restrict admission to students of only one gender or religious belief. Differences of treatment by third level institutions as between EU nationals and students from third countries are exempt. An educational establishment may limit the access of a student with a disability if the student's disability is such that it would make impossible or be seriously detrimental to the education of other students.</P>
    <P>Section 8 outlines the criteria and process by which a club is determined to be a discriminating club. A club is considered to be a discriminating club if it discriminates against a member or applicant for membership. Any person, including the Equality Authority, may seek a determination of the District Court that a club is a discriminating club. Such an application may be dismissed by the District Court if it is brought in bad faith or is frivolous, vexatious or trivial. The determination may be appealed to the Circuit Court within 42 days.</P>
    <P>Section 9 provides that in certain circumstances a club is not considered to be a discriminating club. A club whose principal purpose is to cater for persons of a particular religion, age, nationality or ethnic or national origin and which refuses membership to a person who does not belong to the relevant category is not considered discriminating. A club is not considered discriminating if it confines access to a membership benefit or privilege to persons of a particular gender or age group, provided that it would not be practicable to do otherwise and provided that the same or equivalent benefits are provided separately to those excluded.</P>
    <P>I broadly agree with the provisions of section 10, which provides that a certificate of registration under the Registration of Clubs Acts, 1904 to 1995, which would permit the sale of intoxicating liquor will not be granted to or renewed for a discriminating club. Common sense would have to prevail in this area. Recently in my county the proprietors of licensed premises have had extreme difficulty in having their licences renewed owing to lack of common sense and their refusal to serve certain persons. The condition on <Col N="584" /> any publican's licence states that he is obliged to keep maintain a good house at all times. That is one law and we cannot have another law that will directly contradict it. If a publican honestly believes that a client, whether from the settled community or the Traveller community, is likely to misbehave, cause disturbance or cause financial loss, it should be in his own hands and he should be entitled to refuse and give such a reason for it. Some of the recent decisions taken in the court did not acknowledge the common sense that should prevail.</P>
    <P>The Minister referred to this issue on Second Stage in the Dáil and stated:</P>
    <P>In the past there were some misconceptions about the effect of the Bill on commercial interests. This Bill will prohibit discrimination on specified grounds only. It will not require traders to admit all-comers nor will it prevent business people from refusing service to someone because of bad behaviour or lack of hygiene. It will not give any protection whatsoever to trouble-makers or anti-social elements.</P>
    <P>This is very important and I welcome it because it has allayed many of the fears of publicans and confirmed that the common sense approach should prevail. I would not criticise any decision taken by the courts but that approach will have to prevail if people are to be allowed to run their businesses properly.</P>
    <P>Sexual harassment is covered by section 11. A person in authority in an educational establishment, a person providing services or accommodation or disposing of goods or premises is prohibited from sexually harassing or harassing a student or customer, as the case may be. Sexual harassment is defined as an unwelcome act of physical intimacy and unwelcome requests for sexual favours or an unwelcome act or conduct with sexual connotations.</P>
    <P>Section 12 makes it an offence to publish or display an advertisement which indicates an intention to engage in prohibited conduct. Section 16 specifies that certain actions are non-discriminatory.</P>
    <P>A reasonable part of the Bill deals with enforcement. The Employment Equality Act, 1998, provides for the establishment of the Equality Authority and the Office of the Director of Equality Investigations and for their respective functions in employment equality.</P>
    <P>Under section 21, a person who claims that prohibited conduct under the Bill has been directed against any person may refer the case to the director. No claim will be investigated unless the complainant gives the respondent an initial notification in writing within two months of the alleged act of discrimination and the respondent fails to reply to the satisfaction of the complainant. That is very fair and gives both sides an equal opportunity and equal status. The director may dismiss the claim if the complainant does not have sufficient interest in the claim or the claim has been made in bad faith, is frivolous, vexatious <Col N="585" /> or trivial. There are claims made in many walks of life which are in bad faith, frivolous, vexatious or trivial but there are also genuine ones.</P>
    <P>Sections 26 to 31 deal with the investigation by the director. The types of redress which the director may order are one or both of the following: an order for compensation or an order that persons as specified in the order should take a specific course of action. The director may go to the Circuit Court to seek information to take a specific course of action. Part IV of the Bill outlines the initial functions conferred on the Equality Authority.</P>
    <P>I fully support the legislation which is enshrined in the Good Friday Agreement and the principles of common sense. We want to build a society that respects the differences of others. Discrimination must be eliminated. The Amsterdam Treaty gives the European Union greater powers in combating discrimination in society. The European Union should take the necessary measures to achieve these important policy objectives.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JohnODonoghue" hpid="Mr. O'Donoghue Mr. O'Donoghue">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Justice, Equality and Law Reform (Mr. O'Donoghue)</NameTxt>
      <P>I thank all those who contributed to this interesting debate including Senators Connor, O'Donovan, Norris, Henry, Keogh, Ryan, Kett and Cregan. Senator Connor referred to the question of whether this legislation would apply to the State. This has exercised my mind and the minds of our officials. We are advised that following the 1993 Supreme Court judgment in the case of Howard<i> v.</i> the Commissioners for Public Works it is no longer either necessary or desirable to state in legislation that the State is bound by it. Apparently the doctrine of crown prerogative, whereby the State would not be bound by any statute which does not include it expressly or by implication, did not actually survive the Constitution of 1937. There was uncertainty about that until the Howard <i>v.</i> the Commissioners for Public Works case, but in that landmark decision it was established that whether a statute expressly or by implication bound the State or not, the State was still bound. That is why in that case, the Senator will recall, it was held that the State was obliged to apply for planning permission to build the famous interpretative centre at Mullaghmore. It is no longer necessary to state explicitly in legislation that the State is bound by that legislation. It never was necessary to do so but there was a great deal of uncertainty about the actual position. I appreciate Senator Connor's wish to raise this matter.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Senator Connor also inquired whether the legislation will apply to the public service. Service is defined in section 2 as &ldquo;a service or facility of any nature which is available to the public generally or a section of the public&rdquo;. This wide definition of service applies to public services as well as those provided by the private sector. The application of the legislation to public services is unquestionable. That is reinforced by section 5(1) which provides that it is irrelevant whether the <Col N="586" /> services are provided for &ldquo;consideration or otherwise&rdquo;. The reference to the State in section 14(<i>a</i>)(iii) also underlines that point.</P>
    <P>It is clear that the Equal Status Bill applies to services provided by the State. This matter which was raised by Senator Connor has exercised my mind and those of my officials and it was raised with us by interested groups on a number of occasions. However, there is no question that the State and the services it provides are bound by the legislation.</P>
    <P>The scope of the equal status legislation is not confined to those public services which are analogous to those provided in the private sector. For example, social welfare services have no counterpart in the marketplace but they come within the scope of the Equal Status Bill. I am aware that United Kingdom case law restricted the application of anti-discrimination legislation to public services which actually have a parallel in the marketplace. However, I am strongly advised that a similar limitation would not apply in this jurisdiction. The UK judgments were delivered against an entirely different legal and constitutional background. In addition, the United Kingdom legislation does not define a service but merely offers examples thereof, whereas the Equal Status Bill defines a service as &ldquo;a service or facility of any nature&rdquo;.</P>
    <P>Under section 14, actions which are required to be done by or under statute are exempt from the legislation. Distinctions in the tax code based on marital status or in social welfare legislation based on age &ndash; for example, pensions &ndash; will not be regarded as discrimination under the Equal Status Bill. I stress that this exemption applies only to actions which are mandatory under the relevant statute and not to the discretionary actions of statutory bodies or public officials.</P>
    <P>Lest there be doubt, even where a particular matter is exempt under section 14 the obligation not to discriminate will apply to the interaction between officials and the public in the delivery of the relevant statutory function. For example, the fact that the requirements of the tax code are exempt does not allow Revenue officials to discriminate in granting access to buildings and information or in providing advice or other forms of assistance.</P>
    <P>Senators Connor and O'Donovan referred to immigration. Not all actions of the State <i>vis-à-vis</i> members of the public can be regarded as services. There is a distinction between controlling the duties exercised by the State and the services it provides. I am advised that immigration and citizenship matters are not services within the meaning of the Equal Status Bill but rather an expression of the State's duty as a sovereign power to control who it admits to the country. Controlling duties in the area of policing, defence and prisons would, likewise, not be regarded as services. The service aspects of policing, immigration, defence and prisons will, however, come within the scope of the legislation. For example, while a decision to grant a visa would not be <Col N="587" /> covered by the Equal Status Bill, the interaction between officials and the visa applicant and collateral services and facilities such as access to buildings and information would come within the scope of the legislation.</P>
    <P>In the area of policing where, for example, riot control or apprehending a criminal gang could not be regarded as services, information and assistance provided by gardaí, including responding to reported crimes, would be regarded as a service within the scope of the equal status legislation. Furthermore, the fact that the controlling duty of the State does not come within the scope of the equal status legislation does not give <i>carte blanche</i> to officials to discriminate in the exercise of such duties. Discrimination or irrationality in the exercise of controlling duties can be challenged in a High Court constitutional action or in judicial review proceedings.</P>
    <P>Senators Connor and O'Donovan also referred to section 15, which was intended to reassure vintners and other commercial interests that the Bill would not oblige them to admit troublemakers or prevent the normal operation of their businesses. The safeguards in section 15 do not actually interfere with the Bill's central thrust which is to outlaw discrimination. Section 15(1) can be invoked only in limited circumstances. There must be a substantial risk of criminal or disorderly behaviour. A key feature of section 15 is that any difference of treatment must be on grounds other than discriminatory grounds. For example, someone cannot refuse to serve a Traveller because he or she happens to believe that Travellers are inclined to cause trouble. Such behaviour will not be allowed.</P>
    <P>Section 15 is not intended as some form of escape hatch to allow people who want to discriminate to do so. I assure Members that is not the intention. Section 15 is a necessary safeguard to meet the concerns of vintners and other commercial interests, which it does successfully. However, I stress that it will not be an escape hatch for people who want to discriminate.</P>
    <P>Senator Norris referred to the definition of disability, which was extensively discussed during the debate on and the passage of the Employment Equality Bill in 1996 and 1998. The definition in the Equal Status Bill is the same as that which appears in the Employment Equality Act, 1998. That, in turn, is modelled on Australian legislation and is intended to be as wide as possible and to protect as many people as is practicable from discrimination on the grounds of disability. Other definitions of disability are used for different and other purposes &ndash; for example, for eligibility for adapting a car. We have tried to define disability as best we could. Any change would have the effect of limiting the provisions and the protections provided for in the legislation.</P>
    <P>Senator Henry queried the role of the Equality Authority and referred to a need to promote equality. The latter is one of the key functions of <Col N="588" /> the Equality Authority under section 39 of the Employment Equality Act, 1998.</P>
    <P>Senator Connor referred to the work of the National Consultative Committee on Racism and Interculturalism which was originally established during the European Year against Racism. I share his concern that a small minority of people can exhibit racist tendencies in our society. In that context, given the fact that asylum seekers are entering the country, I felt it important that the National Consultative Committee on Racism and Interculturalism should not cease its work when the European Year against Racism ended. I continued the work of the committee and provided extra funding for it. I am concerned it should continue with its excellent work.</P>
    <P>Senator Keogh expressed concern about the issue of women golfers and offered several examples of discrimination. There is no doubt there has been discrimination against women golfers. A few clubs do not allow women to be members, which is hard to believe in 2000. Other clubs allow women to be associate members only. That means they have limited playing time and usually cannot play at weekends. They cannot vote and, therefore, cannot have a real say in decisions affecting members such as fees, playing times and so on. These rules appear to assume women do not work and should play midweek rather than at weekends. This patriarchal view of women is entirely unacceptable.</P>
    <P>This legislation will eliminate discrimination on grounds of gender in regard to the delivery of services. We can take it, therefore, that the gender issue will be resolved. However, there are other issues attendant upon the changes which must be addressed, not least of which is the issue of voting rights. As I said, we are giving deep consideration to that matter. Everyone will accept that, irrespective of one's gender, one should have the option of deciding whether to be a full member. Voting rights should then be dealt with logically in terms of associate members, members for certain lengths of time and so on, always remembering that what is sauce for the goose is sauce for the gander. In other words, we must ensure there is equality of opportunity and services for all concerned. As I said in the Dáil, we have been discussing some of these matters with the Attorney General. I hope to reach my final conclusions soon, certainly before this Bill is passed by the House.</P>
    <P>Senator Ryan expressed concern about the meaning of section 3(3). It means that someone under 18 years cannot claim discrimination on the ground of age. Equally, someone over 18 years cannot claim discrimination on age grounds based on a comparison with someone under 18 years. For example, a person over 18 years will not be entitled to demand to be charged the same bus fare as someone under 18 years. That is reasonable. Otherwise, we would reach the stage where we would meet ourselves coming back. The Bill provides that children under 18 years can claim discrimination on all other grounds, such as race <Col N="589" /> and disability. In other words, the Bill protects children in regard to all the other grounds.</P>
    <P>Senator Ryan mentioned the UN convention of 1966 and wondered if it could operate immediately. Ratification of that convention will not be possible until this Bill is fully in operation and people can avail of their rights under it. Therefore, an early operation date solely stating that ratification can take place would serve no purpose. I would have to reject any such amendment.</P>
    <P>Senator Kett, whose contribution dealt mainly with disabilities, wondered about the issue of nominal cost and was concerned it is not defined in the Bill or the Employment Equality Act. I accept he has a point. The only logical answer is that the issue of nominal costs may vary, according to the nature of the service and the circumstances of the service provider. In other words, what might be regarded as a nominal cost for a service provider with a large turnover might not be a nominal cost for a small business. For example, a person with a very large turnover and a person with a small business both giving £10 to charity are not in an equivalent position. The amount is the same but the effect on income is different. The director of equality investigations will decide whether a cost is nominal.</P>
    <P>I trust I have dealt with all the concerns raised. Senator Cregan, who was the last speaker, raised the issue of the right of vintners and other service providers to refuse service. I have dealt with section 15. I hope I have dealt comprehensively with Senators' queries. I thank them for their informative and interesting contributions. I look forward to Committee Stage, when we will have an opportunity to discuss Senators' amendments.</P>
    <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>When is it proposed to take Committee Stage?</P>
      <P>
      </P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DennisODonovan" hpid="Mr. O'Donovan Mr. O'Donovan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Donovan</NameTxt>
      <P>It is proposed to take Committee Stage on Wednesday, 8 March 2000.</P>
      <P>Committee Stage ordered for Wednesday, 8 March 2000.</P>
      <P>
        <i>Sitting suspended at 5.48 p.m. and resumed at 6 p.m.</i>
      </P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="National Development Strategy:" RHead="Motion">
    <Title>National Development Strategy: Motion.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="EndaBonner" hpid="Mr. Bonner Mr. Bonner">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Bonner</NameTxt>
      <P>I move:</P>
      <P>That Seanad Éireann calls on the Minister for the Marine and Natural Resources to implement a comprehensive national development strategy to maximise the growth and employment potential of the marine and natural resources sectors.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I welcome the Minister, Deputy Fahey, to the Seanad. This is his first occasion in the House as a Minister and I congratulate him on his appoint<Col N="590" /> ment as Minister for the Marine and Natural Resources. I thank him for the efficient and quick manner in which he has visited the coastal ports to meet those involved in the marine and fisheries industries. I am amazed at his grasp of the portfolio after only a few short weeks. The Minister is aware that there are many problems in the fishing industry.</P>
    <P>The way forward for our marine and natural resources is charted in the national development plan. The proposed Government expenditure of £938 million in the period 2000-06 underpins its commitment to our most natural indigenous asset and, with further investment of £317 million, total expenditure on this sector will reach £1.2 billion.</P>
    <P>The development of these sectors is vital for many coastal and rural communities which have nothing other than farming and tourism to sustain them. Given the disastrous situation in farming over the last two years, there is now nothing but tourism to sustain many areas along the west coast. I hope, therefore, the Government's huge investment in this sector will help to redress the deficiencies that have developed over the years and provide an alternative source of revenue for many coastal communities.</P>
    <P>The investment will ensure the benefits of economic prosperity in all regions. The programme provides funding for infrastructural development, value added, marketing and research. A wide range of resources are included, such as sea angling, aquaculture, fishery harbours, seaports, angling, marine tourism and leisure and forestry.</P>
    <P>The development of our vast natural resource is one of our greatest challenges. The marine and natural resources elements of the national development plan are designed to deliver sustainable growth, competitiveness and jobs, regional, rural and coastal development and environmental and economic infrastructure. The Programme for Prosperity and Fairness also sets down many objectives in this area and outlines how they can be achieved.</P>
    <P>The main objective in which I am interested is concerned with balancing the objectives and parameters of the EU Common Fisheries Policy with the potential to develop the sector in coastal regions where there are few alternative work opportunities. I hope the targets for the fishing industry will be achieved in the review of the CFP in 2002, in which we will seek to maximise the long-standing case for a significant increase in Ireland's quota share and more effective fishery management systems within the CFP framework through an effective strategic negotiating position informed by the research and conclusions of the national common fisheries policy review group and the recommendations of the NESC on fisheries policy. This is the first time I have seen recognition of the difficulties facing our fishing indus<Col N="591" /> try which have arisen since the previous CFP and I am glad the Government is to address this.</P>
    <P>The review group chaired by Padraic White has produced its first report on the sustainable future for European fisheries through technical conservation measures which will protect young sea fish. We are all agreed that there should be management and conservation of sea fish, but many Irish fishermen and processors, especially those involved in the pelagic industry, believe they alone are involved in most of these activities.</P>
    <P>The PPF also sets out to maximise the value added potential of our fishery resource throughout the supply and demand chain by developing a first class national fish and shellfish health monitoring and research facility. It also acknowledges the significant potential of aquaculture production. In many coastal areas aquaculture has taken over completely from fishing and fish processing. With the passage of licensing legislation just over a year ago much progress has been made in this area.</P>
    <P>Unfortunately, there are still many areas where difficulties arise with coastal zone management and the quality of the water due to the lack of sewage treatment plants in town adjacent to many bays. I have raised this issue here on many previous occasions. Many licences in my town of Dunloe have been refused because of the water quality.</P>
    <P>The PPF also acknowledges the importance of the fish processing sector and sets out to improve and strengthen it. It proposes that it be supported to create a competitive value added capability of scale at national and international level through the development of new products, technology and scale, including building effective networks among the small and medium sized enterprises in the processing sector. It also proposes that investment support strategies for the medium to long-term be informed by a comprehensive review of the processing sector to be carried out this year.</P>
    <P>The PPF also sets out to ensure that the inclusive management, conservation and development of our inland fisheries resource is brought to the highest standard and to realise its potential in terms of social and economic benefits to the regions, farmers and local communities. This will be done by negotiation between all stakeholders, including farmers and the regional fisheries boards. The programme also addresses the need to develop forestry to a scale and in a manner which maximises its contribution to national economic and social well being on a sustainable basis and which is compatible with the protection of the environment and the support of climate change commitments.</P>
    <P>I welcome the investment of £171 million to support a sustainable, competitive and quality driven seafood industry. This is broken down between £76 million for the productive sector, £10 <Col N="592" /> million to provide training and £85 million to support aquaculture and fishery harbours. The development of seafood processing to create a competitive value added product is the main aim of the national development plan. Its purpose is to ensure that we can compete with other countries with the highest quality of fish produce. This sector employs 16,000 people throughout the country, with 1,500 directly employed in the industry in my constituency of Donegal South-West. When one takes account of the service industry and the other back-ups, in excess of 25,000 people are employed in the sector. Up to 3,000 people on the west coast of County Donegal are totally reliant on the fishing industry.</P>
    <P>The EU Common Fisheries Policy negotiations in 1983 failed the west of County Donegal. The Minister heard most of the problems and complaints when he visited the area last week. When I grew up Killybegs was not as large a port as it is now and Burtonport was approximately the same size. The main fishing at that time was for herring, salmon and white fish. For a variety of reasons these species have collapsed over the years and we are now reliant on the pelagic industry. Boats and factories have been developed in line with the development of this industry and in recent years we have became totally reliant on mackerel and horse mackerel. However, the jobs and livelihoods of the large numbers employed in the industry must be protected, otherwise County Donegal will face a crisis far greater than that caused by the problems at Fruit of the Loom.</P>
    <P>I appreciate that exports are of low valued added, but over the years the industry has had no other option but to proceed on this basis because a lead was not given and the industry had to develop itself. In doing so it unfortunately had to rely totally on mackerel. The pelagic fleet was built up without any grant assistance and the innovative fishermen acquired bigger boats. Regrettably we are now almost totally reliant on pelagic fisheries.</P>
    <P>We are now told we must develop other species. We tried to do this recently with blue whiting, but unfortunately when the quota system was introduced we were sold short again. Nevertheless, I compliment the former Minister, Deputy Woods, on securing an increase in the quota for blue whiting.</P>
    <P>Four years ago we had a quota of 90,000 tonnes of mackerel. Last year it was reduced to 60,000 tonnes, but thankfully it has been increased to 70,000 tonnes this year. Up to two years ago there was no quota in respect of horse mackerel, but now there is a quota of approximately 70,000 tonnes. When the Minister visited Killybegs it was pointed out that most of the mackerel are spawning off the west coast and that all we seek is an adequate supply of our own natural resource. This is not a national issue, it affects the western <Col N="593" /> area of one county because of the numbers who are totally reliant on the industry.</P>
    <P>We all acknowledge that the value added element is not what it should be. In order to have more value added products factories will need to re-equip. The last equipment grant available to the industry under a previous EU directive was to improve hygiene. We now need the maximum grants available under Objective One status to enable factories diversify, change direction and produce high quality fish products.</P>
    <P>We heard about EU controls and the discarding of fish at sea. The industry feels it is operating the controls properly and that tightening will be needed. From the Minister's comments in Killybegs I know he will do everything in his power to achieve this.</P>
    <P>Factories will probably close from February to September, a terrible situation, particularly for ordinary employees, due to the CFP. Our national quota is owned by us all. It saddens me that some of our boats land some of our quota in other countries and by doing so put jobs at risk.</P>
    <P>The national development plan sets out to enhance the safety, quality and efficiency of our fleet. The white fish renewal scheme, introduced by Deputy Woods when Minister, has improved the situation immensely, with many fishermen investing in new fishing boats. After years without investment we now have new boats entering the fleet. The Minister launched one of these, <i>Naomh Eoin,</i> last Friday in Burtonport for Mr. Hannigan. We were totally reliant on the pelagic fleet, but hopefully the former Minister's initiative will change the situation. I also congratulate him on introducing safety grants.</P>
    <P>The national plan also identifies the necessity to continue programmes to underpin safety standards in employment, expand the skills base and attract new entrants right across the seafood sector, providing £10 million in this context. Apart from low value added product, poor marketing strategy is also a major shortcoming in our seafood sector. Most companies in Killybegs are marketing separately on the Continent and using different agents. The national development plan will provide £6 million to enhance seafood market development strategies to capitalise on international markets.</P>
    <P>I could refer to many other items in relation to the development plan and the strategies being put forward by the Government. However, I will conclude by referring to the large gas find off the Mayo coast. I ask the Minister to take note of what has been said about the harbour development in Killybegs. There is an airport in Carrickfinn and Enterprise Oil will be returning in April to use both facilities. Hopefully there will be a large oil find which will help the people in Mayo, many of whom have gone to England over the years to work in the gas and oil business. Other <Col N="594" /> counties in the west are hoping they will get a share of the cake.</P>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Before calling Senator Tom Fitzgerald I wish to welcome the new Minister for the Marine and Natural Resources to the House. I congratulate him and wish him every success.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TomFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. T. Fitzgerald Mr. T. Fitzgerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. T. Fitzgerald</NameTxt>
      <P>Ba mhaith liom ar dtús fáilte a chuir roimh an tAire ar ais chuig an Seanad, an uair seo le caipín nua mar Aire na Mara agus Acmhainní Nádúrtha. It makes people like myself very proud to see these young people returning to the Seanad having trained them well. I wish the Minister every success in his new Department and I compliment the former Minister, Deputy Woods, on the fine job he did.</P>
      <P>I will probably be critical in some of the things I say, but this is not meant to be offensive in any form. I see things we can do which would make a huge difference to the fishing industry. The Department of the Marine and Natural Resources is understaffed and under resourced. A plan cannot be implemented without having the necessary people and resources. The Department has great people in various sections whom I have known over the years, and I feel they are getting frustrated as some of them are undoubtedly overworked. I do not think it is our fault that there is insufficient staff. Rather it is because there are better jobs available.</P>
      <P>Many of us have spent many years involved in the fishing industry and its development. However, there is no joint Oireachtas committee to which the Minister is answerable. We have a Committee on Agriculture, Food and the Marine and while there are at least a few on that committee who have a great interest in fishing, they may not have the same interest in the related activities. It is very strange that such a committee exists, which can bring people from the industry before it to find out what is happening on the ground, but that we, who know about fishing, are not involved. I ask the Minister to examine the establishment of a proper committee which would facilitate appropriate consultation with the fishing industry.</P>
      <P>Every other day farmers are meeting the Minister for Agriculture, Food and Rural Development and advising him. He calls them in and asks them to accompany him to Brussels. This should also be happening in the fishing industry. I am not saying that such people are the be all and end all, but it is their business and they should be advising the Minister, or more accurately telling him what is happening in the industry. I would like to see much more consultation.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The Minister is new to the job and, rather than waiting for somebody to ask him to go to Brussels to discuss the fishing industry, he should immediately seek a meeting with Franz Fischler to out<Col N="595" /> line the difficulties and the hardship which the EU has imposed on us. The Minister is from the west and does not have to look too far to see the difficulties in the fishing industry over the years. It is amazing that the 200 mile zone to the west is shared with all of Europe. The original concept of a united Europe involved sharing all our natural resources. However, no other country in the EU is sharing its natural resources with us. We are the only country which is sharing our fishing grounds, and we are getting the least from it.</P>
    <P>Those fishing our waters are mainly Spaniards, and I have a list of boats and their activities. A Spanish boat, <i>Gonzalez Covello,</i> was detained in Castletownbere having been fishing for two years without a licence, with none of its catch recorded. The Minister will be arguing with such people in Brussels. I do not know whether the Department has the list of other boats. The UK/Spanish ship, <i>Mount Eden,</i> exceeded its monthly quota twice in five days. It had 4,390 kilogrammes of monkfish on board even though the quota was 200 kilogrammes &ndash; 23 times the quota. This is one of a number of court cases which have taken place in Ireland and they can be examined to ascertain readily what is happening.</P>
    <P>It is estimated that the EU benefits to the tune of £2 billion annually from Irish fish stocks. EU officials are quick to point out, including one who appeared on &ldquo;Euronews&rdquo; recently, that Ireland is doing well financially because of the EU. However, if the EU has taken £2 billion worth of fish out of our waters annually since the introduction of the fisheries policy in 1983, it is a massive amount of money for which Ireland has received nothing in return. The EU is destroying the livelihoods of people in the Minister's constituency and along the west coast. Can anyone name any other worker who has not been compensated after his rights were taken from him?</P>
    <P>I have no problem with the introduction of laws which protect fish stocks. Tuna fishing was a lucrative business in the west. There was no quota for such fishing and our fishermen used drift nets. French fishermen were the only others to use drift nets. Last year, like a thunderbolt out of the blue, the EU decided that drift netting would not be allowed any more and that Irish fishermen should adopt long line fishing, similar to the Spanish and Portuguese. It was unfair of the EU to do that without first informing fishermen about the change. Such a change would cost a fisherman approximately £200,000, yet it took place over a few months. Members will recall the trouble in Brussels when the fishermen went there to protest because they were terribly annoyed about was done to them. Advance warning should have been given. Senator Bonner outlined other examples, such as blue whiting and horse mackerel.</P>
    <P>Foreign boats should land in Ireland because <Col N="596" /> the local economy would benefit from their presence. Every large fishing boat which docks in our ports generates approximately £10,000 for the local economy. The Spaniards are now sending out &ldquo;mother ships&rdquo; which means that their boats will not even have to come into port because their catch and supplies will be transferred to and from such ships at sea. I do not know whether the Department is aware of this practice but the Minister should resist it. How can the Spanish fleet stay at sea 365 days per year when our fleet can only fish for four months because of quotas? I want the Minister to dig his heels in and tell the EU that enough is enough. I will outline the arguments for him.</P>
    <P>It is difficult to draw up a positive plan. I dwelt on the problems in the fishing industry and I hope other Members will deal with other elements of the Minister's brief, such as inland fishing and natural resources. I wish him well in his new portfolio.</P>
    <Speaker pid="ErnieCaffrey" hpid="Mr. Caffrey Mr. Caffrey">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Caffrey</NameTxt>
      <P>I welcome the Minister and wish him every success in his new post. It is gratifying that a politician west of the Shannon has been given the marine portfolio. The Minister will devote his energy and imagination to it. I regret that Galway and Mayo are not in the same constituency because one factor that seems to determine the Government's decentralisation policy is where the Ministers are from. Nevertheless, I am delighted that the Minister is transferring the Marine Institute to Galway. We, in Mayo, would have been delighted if it had been decentralised to Mayo because its director, Dr. Peter Heffernan, is from Ballina. The realities of political life dictate that it will be moved to Galway and it will be a major boost for the region.</P>
      <P>Ireland's territorial waters total 900,000 square kilometres. This is a tremendous resource which is not being utilised. Recently, Enterprise Oil discovered gas 35 miles from Achill Island, which will have major implications for the country. I hope that the new appraisal well which is being drilled will be a positive development and that the company will announce in the near future that it is viable. County Mayo should be the primary benefactor from this major natural resource. However, it is one of many resources which are underwater.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>At the rate the construction industry is expanding, sand and gravel will be in short supply in the near future. There are unlimited quantities of sand and gravel on the sea bed and many countries have the technology to extract these minerals without causing great damage to the coastline. Ireland is doing nothing about this. Ireland is also running low on electric power. It is estimated that if consumption continues to increase at present levels there will be a shortage of power in a year or two. We have wave energy as a resource. Many countries are tapping into this <Col N="597" /> energy source in terms of research and development but we are not doing much in that regard. We have our fishing industry and I will be parochial by referring to Mayo in particular. No other county in Ireland has the same length of coastline as we have in Mayo, yet we have a deficiency of ports and harbours. We cannot cater for a fishing fleet of a significant size. They have to go to Killybegs, Rossaveel or elsewhere. We have no facilities in Mayo. The recent announcement for ports and harbours in the county was totally inadequate. As I said at the recent county council meeting at which it was announced, these are minor developments that will merely maintain the<i> status quo</i> in the county.</P>
    <P>In a county with the resources we have and our natural coastline, we should examine the possibility of major infrastructural development. The fact that 90% of our imports are carried into the country by sea gives us some idea of the vast potential to develop along the west coast. Four million people come into this country by ferry every year. Those statistics are amazing and Government policy, especially in our region, is to just maintain the current position and not look at the bigger vision. The bigger vision is a major seaport along the west coast. I know the Minister has commissioned a feasibility study for Rossaveel which is due to be completed within three or four months. It will be interesting to see what is recommended for the Killala Bay region where, over the past ten years, two feasibility studies have been done on the possibility of a deep sea port in the region.</P>
    <Speaker pid="FrankFahey" hpid="Mr. Fahey Mr. Fahey">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Fahey</NameTxt>
      <P>In Killala?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ErnieCaffrey" hpid="Mr. Caffrey Mr. Caffrey">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Caffrey</NameTxt>
      <P>Killala Bay, yes. McCarthy and Partners have already produced two substantial reports on it. An international firm of marine experts which came here last year said that the natural resources existed but that we needed capital investment and a policy. I hope the Minister will cast his eyes far down the coastline and examine the potential in this region.</P>
      <P>We also have an abundance of seaweed along the west coast. Arramara Teoranta has a factory in Newport. There was always a seaweed production factory in Newport but that industry has been phased down over recent years. However, there is great potential in the seaweed industry. In the 1950s and 1960s, the seaweed industry in Westport employed up to 100 local people and during the seasonal period that figure rose to 200. There is new emphasis on the production and manufacture of seaweed and it is something the Minister and the Department should examine.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>On the question of policy for resources, a blueprint, Towards a Marine Policy for Ireland, was published in 1991 by the Marine Institute. That was a most comprehensive document with every aspect of our marine infrastructure covered and <Col N="598" /> which included the gem of many good ideas. It would be worthwhile resurrecting that document and examining it to see the various recommendations that were put forward at the time as a basis for a dynamic marine strategy for the whole of Ireland. I am disappointed this document has not formed the basis of Government policy over the years in pursuing a total marine strategy for our country. We have the ideas, the technology, the natural and financial resources and people who are interested in pursuing this ideal, and it is something the Minister should take on board.</P>
    <P>I am delighted a man from west of the Shannon is in charge of this portfolio which offers tremendous opportunities. No other portfolio in the entire Government structure has such possibilities as this one. I am sure the Minister, being the intelligent man that he is, fully realises its potential. I hope he will work on that over the coming years.</P>
    <Speaker pid="DennisODonovan" hpid="Mr. O'Donovan Mr. O'Donovan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Donovan</NameTxt>
      <P>I welcome the Minister to the House and wish him every success in his new brief. I have no doubt he is well capable of handling the new challenge before him.</P>
      <P>Before the last election, Fianna Fáil was one of two parties &ndash; Fine Gael being the other &ndash; which brought forward a programme for Government that had reference to marine strategies, plans for fisheries etc. in the future. Some of the other parties did not look beyond Dublin and have little interest in fishing or farming.</P>
      <P>I pay a sincere tribute to the Minister's predecessor, Deputy Woods, who did trojan work with limited resources, particularly in my area. Ten years ago, in the tiny hamlet called Union Hall, which the former Minister, Deputy Woods, visited, one would have to reverse a juggernaut for half a mile to get to the pier where the fishermen landed their fish. Thankfully, since then a major pier and onshore parking facilities have been developed. Union Hall obtained funding towards that development because its catch increased from £500,000 or £600,000 to in excess of £8 million or £10 million in four or five years. The fishermen went out in relatively small fishing vessels and caught non-quota fish. Currently there are more than 200 people working on shore either in Skibbereen or elsewhere as a result of the initiative of the fishermen.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>We all can be critical of Ministers and Departments, but there has been a lot of success in the Department of the Marine and Natural Resources. I have no doubt that with the proper strategy and plans, we can succeed in creating onshore jobs, one of my main interests. Much work has been done in Castletownbere also. Thanks to the initiative of the former Minister, Deputy Woods, a number of state of the art whitefish vessels have been built. Two of them have been delivered already to the west Cork region and six more are awaited. This is an indica<Col N="599" /> tion of the Government's commitment to fishing despite our problems with Europe, lack of quotas and so forth.</P>
    <P>The Department has a greater remit than fishing. It is also responsible for natural resources and oil and gas exploration which, no doubt, will be of major importance in the future. My colleague, Senator Bonner, spoke about a strategic plan for the proper harnessing and development of offshore resources.</P>
    <P>When we joined the then EEC in 1973 the fishing industry, probably due to lack of interest and commitment on the part of successive Governments, was a fledgling weak industry. It was a substratum of the then Department of Agriculture. Despite the fact that Ireland had almost 25% of EU waters, it ended up with approximately 4% of the fishing catch. We can thrash out this issue <i>ad infinitum</i> but I must urge the new Minister to get tough with Brussels. We must put our foot down and take no nonsense. If the need arises, the Minister should take the extreme step of using his veto to ensure we do not lose jobs in the fishing industry.</P>
    <P>We have put up with nonsense for long enough. The fisheries on the south-west coast, in particular, have been ridden bareback by Spanish fishing vessels which are far larger and better equipped than Irish vessels. They are marauding the Irish waters and raping them of valuable stocks. Apart from getting tough with Europe, trying to hold our own and perhaps gain extra quotas, the biggest issue facing fishermen in the next ten years is conservation. The big concern for fishermen who own trawlers, and I meet them daily, is what will be in the sea in ten or 20 years. If the rape of our waters by foreign vessels continues without restriction, the future appears bleak.</P>
    <P>As a result of research carried out by the Department of the Marine and Natural Resources, a number of new species of fish have been identified off our coasts. These fish, so far, are not subject to quotas. If a quota regime is introduced, we must be first in line to guarantee we receive a quota for those species. For too long we have played second fiddle to our European counterparts.</P>
    <P>When we joined the European Community, the fishermen did not have their catch properly logged, apart from in a few prominent ports such as Killybegs and Castletownbere. As a result, we ended up with an extremely poor quota. To a great extent, the fishermen were to blame. The normal practice in my area was for fishermen to be paid cash for their catch. Records were never kept so when the fateful day arrived to produce the records, the fishermen, unlike the farmers, had great difficulty producing evidence of their catch.</P>
    <P>The traditional fisherman in Cork, Kerry and probably along the entire west coast generally <Col N="600" /> had a small boat which he would use to fish for lobster and crayfish. In the winter he might turn his hand to mackerel or herring fishing. That tradition has gone by the board. One of the finest natural spawning grounds for herring, recognised as such by the Dutch and the Germans, was a place called Gearhies in Bantry Bay. Alas, that is gone now and the herring market has collapsed. The sale of roe to Japan has virtually evaporated. In 1976, when I was herring fishing, we were getting £16 per box for herring. Now, 25 years later, one would not get even £10. There is something radically wrong.</P>
    <P>That type of traditional fishing is gone and the small fisherman has disappeared. There were little hamlets around west Cork where people fished for herring, mackerel and horse mackerel from September to March. Hundreds of small farmers got their income from working the poor land, in so far as they could, in the spring and summer and from fishing in the winter. That practice has evaporated. On a positive note, it has been replaced by successful mariculture or aquaculture development.</P>
    <P>The aquaculture industry in places such as west Cork and south west Kerry has created between 300 and 400 jobs onshore. That is something we must protect and develop. In fairness to the Department and to BIM, this has been a success story. On 8 January 1979 on Whiddy Island there was a massive explosion in which 50 lives were lost. The biggest asset of the bay at that time, which created much employment, was more or less closed down. By trial and error, many of the men who were formerly fishermen or were from fishing families started fish farming.</P>
    <P>They generally started with mussel rafts, but due to lack of knowledge or expertise, the rafts sank. One of the reasons they sank was that mussel growth in the Gulf stream along our coasts was only nine or ten months for a market-ready product whereas the fish farmers' knowledge came from Scandinavian books which said the period required was double that. Since then, BIM and the Department have pumped a great deal of money into the industry. There are two state of the art factories in the Bantry area. One was recently completed and is not yet opened. I hope the Minister will open this massive factory for processing mussels in the not too distant future. It cost almost £7 million and it is hoped it will create and sustain approximately 200 onshore jobs.</P>
    <P>This is the way to go. For too long about 70% of the fish landed in Castletownbere was carried by juggernauts over desperately bad roads across Europe to Spain or Italy. This is a sad statistic. The Minister will be aware of the difficult terrain for a huge, heavily loaded truck which has to drive from Castletownbere across Great Britain, through France and into Spain. It is regrettable <Col N="601" /> that this percentage of the fish is being exported in its raw state.</P>
    <P>I have always advocated that onshore processing should take place for added value and the creation of jobs. In the last ten years, despite the restrictions imposed by Europe and the shackles and chains which have held the industry down, the Department of the Marine and Natural Resources has done exceptionally well in that regard. When Dr. Woods was moved from the Department, the Irish South and West Fishermen's Organisation issued a frank and positive statement which thanked him for his years of effort. He was long associated with trying to promote the fishing industry in the south-west, although I cannot speak for the west or Donegal. Ports such as Union Hall stand as a monument to this Government's policy for positive development.</P>
    <P>Recently there was a huge welcome in Union Hall when one of the newly built boats was officially launched by the new Minister, Deputy Fahey. Twelve years ago this was a sleepy village which had only a few small punts and a couple of clapped out trawlers. Now it is a vibrant port with many onshore jobs. It is easy to be negative but I urge people to be positive. Much has been done and a great deal of work is currently being done on the improvement of harbours and piers. Money is available and we should continue the infrastructural development in peripheral areas, be they Bantry or Baltimore in west Cork or Killybegs or Killala. That is the direction in which we should go.</P>
    <P>While I wish the Minister luck in the difficult task of dealing with Europe, he should take off the kid gloves and not leave any stone unturned. We have lost out badly and this island nation which depends on fishing and the natural resource of the sea cannot afford to lose jobs around its coastline. I urge the Minister to be prepared to go all the way and use the veto. For too long, especially in the 1970s and 1980s, successive Ministers under different Governments, including those of my party, returned from Europe with empty promises and small quotas which meant we were rowing backwards for many years. Matters have improved in the past ten years and I am glad the industry is in a healthy state. The Minister has an arduous task ahead of him but we will be singing his praises in a few years if he can succeed in the Common Fisheries Policy.</P>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. Ryan Mr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>It is good to debate a motion such as this but I would have preferred had it been more precise in its prescriptions. I listen with great interest to Senator Bonner every time he speaks. He knows far more about the fishing industry than I do. I suspect he has forgotten far more about the industry than I will ever know. There is a ring of truth in the point he has consistently made that, perhaps in terms of the areas of <Col N="602" /> the country which are most underdeveloped, which by and large are along the west coast, the greatest single policy error was made in the negotiation of our accession to the Common Agricultural Policy. I have never been entirely clear why we did so but we seemed to assume that agricultural production and prices would increase indefinitely and entirely independent of market conditions. We in this country have had a considerable education in the ups and downs of the marketplace with our various economic crises, and we are all a little more hard-headed and perhaps a little more realistic in our beliefs about what the State can do and our understanding about the way markets operate than we were 25, 27 or 28 years ago when we discussed membership of the EU. Nonetheless, one does not have to be an economic genius, not that there are many of them, to accept that one cannot continue producing forever. The tragedy was that we were so swept up in the joys of the Common Agricultural Policy and many people failed to confront the ongoing tragedy of that policy.</P>
      <P>A major study in economic history remains to be conducted to examine the failure of the country to develop a competitive fishing industry before we joined the EU. At a time when other countries in less favourable locations, such as Iceland or Norway, developed internationally recognised fishing industries, we were piddling around in little boats on the margins of our coastline talking about 12 miles as the upper limit of our ambitions in terms of what we would ever use as our fishing resource. I have never understood why Irish private enterprise did not do something about that. I do not say this in any ideological sense. It is a fascinating example of a lack of self-belief that this country never managed to make for itself an industry out of a resource which was freely available and which was ours to sell into a market which, even 40 years ago, was sophisticated. We did not seem to know that there was a whole European Continent which, by the 1950s, was prosperous and growing economically at a rate at which no other collection of countries had grown and with a huge taste for marine produce. We seemed to believe that the problem was that our people would not eat fish except on Fridays and even then only reluctantly.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>We never managed to lift our horizons, but the great thing the EU has done is enable us to do so. Far more than economic benefits or transfers, it enabled us to discover all these little countries all over Europe which were spectacularly richer according to the index we always used to measure ourselves, which was the neighbouring country, and which obscured in more ways than one and more psychologically than physically our vision of what the rest of the world was like. However, since we joined the EU, we have had one hand, if not one and a half, tied behind our backs in terms of what we can do for the cheapest natural resource we have. As Senator Caffrey said, 90% of what should be the national territory is sea, and that represents a greater proportion of the <Col N="603" /> European Union's fishery resource than our land area represents of the EU land area or that our population represents of its population.</P>
    <P>We are reaching a stage where many of the things we did well and large parts of the bargain we struck when we joined the EU are beginning to be questioned. We have already seen, for better or worse, the abolition of duty free sales, an Irish invention begun in Shannon Airport and copied throughout the world. We have seen that taken from us to a considerable extent. We now see our judicious use of tax policy to encourage development beginning to be questioned. The great success of the 1980s was the International Financial Services Centre, a greater success than people like to acknowledge because of what it did to develop skills in and improve understanding of international technology and communications and where it dragged us in terms of communication. People are beginning to say now that the preferential tax rates for such developments must be abolished. The beginnings of an attack on our generalised low levels of taxation for the corporate sector are already on the horizon and will grow as our prosperity does. I am not necessarily committed to a 12.5% rate as are many others in the Oireachtas or in my party. Nonetheless, I see a gradual reshaping of the bargain. Perhaps it is inevitable. It is most evident in agriculture.</P>
    <P>There is a wrong attitude in this country to the EU. The single greatest benefit for us has been the cultural shift where we went from seeing ourselves as small and poor next to someone who was rich and powerful to being an equal partner in all levels of decision-making and where those who had patronised us, at the very least, for many hundreds of years had to treat us as equal. However, much of the rest of the bargain has been taken from us. As that has changed, vast quantities of a natural resource have been taken away gratis by other countries.</P>
    <P>There is considerable concern about the renationalisation of support for agriculture and by consumers throughout Europe who have developed a stubborn preference for local produce because of fears about food safety. There is a case for renationalising fisheries, although I do not mean that in the classic left wing sense. This is a vast resource which we are giving away. A colleague in the other House asked the previous Minister for the Marine and Natural Resources a question about the scale of fish catches in terms of price in our zone of economic interest by non-national fleets. The figure for our 27 years of membership of the EU is between £12 billion and £20 billion worth of fish. That makes all the transfer payments look small.</P>
    <P>Another reason we should renationalise fisheries is that fishery resources are being depleted throughout the world. I want to register a note of dissent from a general type of national adulation. I am not overly impressed that we have built the largest fishing vessel in the world to fish off the west coast of Africa because we are now doing <Col N="604" /> there what we are angry that other people are doing off our coast. I do not feel comfortable with the idea that enough fish to feed 14 million people could be in one ship off the coast of a starving continent, although I do not criticise the individuals involved.</P>
    <P>We are the only people who will have sufficient interest and commitment to look after our fisheries resources. If we leave it to a collectivity, such as the EU, collective decisions will be taken but there will also be collective enforcement and that will not be sufficient. Iceland does not participate in those collective operations. It has succeeded, nevertheless, in protecting its fishery resources and it fought a cod war against the United Kingdom, although it was a farce, to insist on its right to conserve its resources.</P>
    <P>The fundamental issue is that any review of the Common Fisheries Policy must ascertain whether it has worked in delivering prosperity to the countries where the resource exists and in providing a sustainable basis for future fisheries development.</P>
    <Speaker pid="FrankChambers" hpid="Mr. Chambers Mr. Chambers">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Chambers</NameTxt>
      <P>I congratulate Deputy Fahey on his appointment as Minister for the Marine and Natural Resources. He has already visited a number of counties involved in the fishing industry.</P>
      <P>The challenge is to sustain the development of our waters to maintain a certain level of fish. I remember spending eight or nine hours on a fishing boat in Cyprus some years ago and I did not see one fish in the water. We must protect our natural resource. The Minister must avail of opportunities in the review of the Common Fisheries Policy and in the management of our natural resource.</P>
      <P>I welcome the positive decision by the Minister to move the Marine Institute to the Galway area. This will help in the management of our seas, rivers, inlets and coastline. We must also manage our catchment areas, set out principles and balance the development of mariculture, whether it is shellfish or salmon farming. We have the institutes to do that on a trial basis. There is a great opportunity to set up ranches along the western seaboard where fish could be released and a measurement system could be put in place to build up our fish stocks.</P>
      <P>I welcome the recent launch of new ships in the fishing industry which will help its development. Inshore fishermen must benefit from existing resources to sustain their families. This is a time of economic boom but a time will come when we will need our natural resources to sustain families and young people. We must invest and encourage people to become involved in the shellfish industry and in the management of our lobster and crayfish stocks which are under threat and for which there is a market. We must create jobs, sustain families and retain a resource that is important to our people.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>A challenge facing the Minister is the development of the seaweed industry which we have <Col N="605" /> failed to develop over many years. It is a changing market. It can play a greater part in sustaining families in correlation with the development of our marine resources. If it is properly managed, investment is found to help it expand and terms of reference are laid down, it will provide opportunities for people, particularly along the western seaboard.</P>
    <P>The shellfish industry has developed strongly along the western seaboard and throughout the country. Our waters are of good quality so they are a good resource for rearing fish. The shellfish industry creates employment and it gives a good return and it should be developed further.</P>
    <P>The Minister should look at areas along the west coast in which management plans can be developed and he should consider developing and investing in our tributaries and small rivers. This has been tried in Iceland and it has been extremely successful in retaining stocks. Perhaps this might be included in a future national plan.</P>
    <Speaker pid="FrankFahey" hpid="Mr. Fahey Mr. Fahey">
      <NameTxt>Minister for the Marine and Natural Resources (Mr. Fahey)</NameTxt>
      <P>I thank the Senators for their good wishes on my appointment. It is nice to back in the Seanad as a member of the Cabinet. I spent some of my happiest times here and I learned a lot from being a Senator. It is a pleasure for me to come back as Minister for the Marine and Natural Resources.</P>
      <P>One of the greatest challenges facing Ireland is the development of its natural resources. While the Senators have concentrated on marine matters, there are a number of other important areas that I want to mention in terms of my responsibilities and my portfolio, not least natural resources involving the mining industry, the offshore search for oil and gas and the forestry sector which is a major contributor to our economy in rural Ireland. The forestry sector has potential for development and is one of the areas that I am keen to develop. The forestry investment programme in the national plan will have an impact on this economy and on people throughout rural Ireland. We must make difficult decisions in respect of our forestry developments and the future of Coillte. I hope to be able to make those difficult decisions and move on the development of this important natural resource.</P>
      <P>With regard to offshore developments, an important appraisal well will be drilled by Enterprise Oil in April which will determine the commerciality of the Corrib field. We must be careful not to be over confident about the possibilities of a commercial gas find until we have the results of the exploration exercise. If it is successful it will be of great significance, not least for the west.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>With regard to the marine sector, most people do not realise that 90% of Ireland's territory is under water. It is a significant resource. We can all agree with the point made by Senator Ryan that we did not do as well in the EU negotiations with regard to the resource off our coast as we <Col N="606" /> did in other areas. As a result we have the major disadvantage of a tight quota position.</P>
    <P>During my term in office one of my highest priorities will be the renegotiation of the Common Fisheries Policy. A high level review group is examining this policy and preparing a case with me that will be presented in Brussels. I can assure the House, especially Senators who mentioned that we need to fight, that we will put up a solid case and a strong fight to try to improve our position. It will not be easy. If we get an increase in our quota we will have to take it from someone else. No one is naive enough to believe that getting favours from our European partners will be easy. I can assure the House that we will leave no stone unturned, we will be well prepared and we will use the best scientific evidence available to us, in addition to the strong case that this is our resource. As Senators have said, our waters are being heavily fished by other nations who have bigger capacity than we have and I am concerned about that. Notwithstanding that, there is potential to develop this industry.</P>
    <P>I will concentrate on the major area of marketing, processing and the additional added value of the fishing sector. There is no doubt that we have a fine product and that we do not market, process or add value to it as much as we should. During my term of office one of my main priorities will be to work with BIM, the Marine Institute, my Department and with the industry in bringing forward a vigorous marketing campaign and developing an effective processing sector. We will talk to Enterprise Ireland and An Bord Bia with a view to getting a comprehensive programme in place as quickly as possible so that fishermen can benefit to a greater extent from their fine product.</P>
    <P>Aquaculture is a huge resource which has developed well over the years but there is room for further development. The salmon sector was mentioned earlier. We produce only 18,000 tonnes of farmed salmon whereas Scotland produces 100,000 tonnes, Norway 400,000 and the Faroe Islands, which only got into the business recently, produces 35,000 tonnes. Therefore, farmed salmon has potential.</P>
    <P>There have been difficulties about getting the balance right between aquaculture, the environment and the traditional fishing sector. I have talked with the research people in the Marine Institute and I am satisfied that we can get the balance right and prove scientifically that both sectors can live and progress together. I will try to get that message across. Scientific evidence will prove to everyone that we can develop aquaculture without detrimental effects on the environment or the traditional fishing sector.</P>
    <P>The whitefish fleet has been a huge success. There are not many projects we can claim to have successfully brought to fruition in 18 months, whether in industry, agriculture or the public sector. It is remarkable that in the past 18 months, from the first day a document was put together, the whitefish fleet has developed to the point <Col N="607" /> where on the first day of my tenure as Minister we launched the first two boats which cost £1.5 million each. They were launched under the stewardship of two young west Cork skippers and there are about 30 more boats to follow. That is a great credit to the young men and women around the coasts who have the courage to proceed with such an investment. The whitefish fleet sector has a bright future. We will have difficulties but we can overcome them.</P>
    <P>The pelagic sector also faces difficulties. As Senator Bonner said, I was in Killybegs to meet people from the fishing and processing industries. We have tight quotas and we have well equipped fishermen in Donegal who can catch more fish than they are allowed. Clearly, we have a major difficulty in terms of the controls we must implement and with the European Commission to ensure that we adhere to the rules.</P>
    <P>I believe there are new ways to go forward and new markets. I also believe that there is new terrain to be fished outside of the immediate control areas. There are new processing and marketing opportunities which will bring this industry back to the better days it once enjoyed. I am happy to work with the industry and to move forward with these new initiatives.</P>
    <P>Under the national plan £171 million has been allocated for investment. We can upgrade our processing facilities, our ability to reach new markets and our ability to fish for new species.</P>
    <P>We have the ability to marry some of the smaller operators involved in the sector through the inshore fishing fleet with aquaculture developments. The development of our inshore fleet will be one of my priorities over the coming months. There will be a new emphasis on investment and modernising that fleet, replacing some of the older vessels, which are, on average, up to 30 years old. I intend that people involved in the inshore fishing business be also involved in aquaculture. There is no reason why the two cannot go hand in hand. I know of some examples, not least in west Cork, where recent developments mean that inshore workers are now involved in various aquaculture exercises, which are proving very beneficial.</P>
    <P>We can add the marine tourism sector to that, a sector with significant potential for which a sum of £20 million was provided in the national plan and which is almost totally undeveloped. Senator Tom Fitzgerald tells me that during summer, many tourists from France and other places, whose presence would enhance the already great reputation of Dingle, are being turned away. It is ridiculous that the facilities are not available to take these high-spending tourists who want to enter some of our ports and marinas. A new division has just been started to put forward a series of developments in marine tourism. There is much potential across the spectrum and many developments are under way. I acknowledge the work done by my predecessor and the Department to date, in making great progress.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="608" /> One area of concern is that my Department has not been good in the past on customer relations. I am taking immediate steps to try to improve that. It is not due to any lack of effort on behalf of the Department officials, but rather to some of the old-fashioned structures and systems within which they operate. One of my priorities will be to streamline those systems and to devolve some of the work, such as the marine surveying work, licensing work and some of the other engineering works which cause frustration and delay and which hold up progress. While we will not allow reductions in the standards that must be imposed, in terms of safety and quality of work and so on, we can improve our ability to make decisions faster and to allow people to proceed with their work. Already progress is being made on that and I hope much further progress will be made over the next 12 months.</P>
    <P>I will put every ounce of energy into improving and increasing the work already being done. I will be happy to consult Members of the Seanad in any way I can. Some of the Senators raised the question of a joint Oireachtas committee. In principle, I have no difficulty with a joint Oireachtas committee on fisheries. Our Department is currently very stretched and has to resort to fire brigade action because of a lack of staff, as some Senators said. As we are not able to respond as effectively as we should, I ask the Members to give us a chance to deal with some of the issues before we set up yet another committee. However, I am happy to consult Members of the House in any informal or formal setting to deal with some of the issues of concern to them. As we progress, we intend to set up a formal committee to deal with some of these issues more appropriately.</P>
    <P>We want to introduce some items of legislation and I am taking initiatives to bring forward that legislation more quickly than has been the case to date. I am happy to communicate with the House on those matters again in the future.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelFinneranFF" hpid="Mr. Finneran Mr. Finneran">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Finneran</NameTxt>
      <P>I welcome the Minister to the House and congratulate him on his elevation to a portfolio of such importance. A more fitting man could not have been picked for this position. It is a great honour for him and his family to be elevated to the position of Cabinet Minister but it is also a great honour for the west of Ireland, Connacht in particular, to have a young, enthusiastic Member at the Cabinet table. I wish him every success. He is well up to the task and will show innovation and set down a great foundation of development in the Department, which offers much opportunity. While he may be constrained somewhat by negotiations which took place many years ago regarding EU quotas, there are, as he said, other opportunities, including his ability to negotiate under the Common Fisheries Policy generally.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The seas around Ireland are a wonderful resource. The inland lakes and rivers are also of importance, as are other natural resources, <Col N="609" /> including natural oil, gas and forestry. People from coastal counties have a far better understanding of the fisheries industry than I, although I have gained some experience through a recent investigation in this regard under the strategic management initiative by an Oireachtas committee. It is a vast industry and our investigation opened my eyes to many windows of opportunity, which I had previously not seen, concerning the potential in the industry. The Minister is correct on that matter.</P>
    <P>The potential in inland fisheries is far greater than that currently being experienced. Recently, I undertook some research into inland fisheries in Northern Ireland. I was flabbergasted to find out the level of activity taking place in Lough Neagh, for example, in the eel industry alone. This is an area with much opportunity for employment and exports. It is a useful export industry and our take from the Shannon, for whatever reason, is negligible compared with that in Northern Ireland. The potential is there and also in the inland fisheries.</P>
    <P>I recently applied for afforestation permission and was turned down on the basis that the land was not considered up to standard. The same lands for which I applied were adjacent to those passed and put under forestry by Coillte, namely sections of the Derryfadda Bog. If that is to be the approach of forestry officials, then we are losing out. Cutaway bog and lands which are not good for farming and are not involved in the Special Areas of Conservation, are ideal for forestry and should be promoted for it. We should invest for the future and bring the level of afforestation up to a level that would compare favourably with the rest of Europe.</P>
    <P>Nothing is confirmed yet on the possibility of a major gas find off the west coast and the possibility of that find being transported through the country. It is vitally important that there should be links between the cities of Galway and Dublin.</P>
    <P>The potential using a combination of gas and peat to produce energy in the west should be considered when new proposals are being put forward. I know that this does not come under the Minister's remit but it is time such a combination was considered. In that context, the resources contained in 25,000 acres of peat land in the Suck and Shannon basin and in County Galway remain untapped.</P>
    <P>I reiterate my congratulations to the Minister on his elevation to Cabinet. I look forward to working with him. There is already great enthusiasm in the industry, particularly among people on the west coast, about his appointment. Everyone in the west wishes the Minister the best of luck with his portfolio.</P>
    <Speaker pid="LiamTCosgrave" hpid="Mr. Cosgrave Mr. Cosgrave">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cosgrave</NameTxt>
      <P>I wish the Minister well in his new role. He succeeds his immediate predecessors, Deputy Woods, who is present in the House, and my constituency colleague, Deputy Barrett.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="610" /> I wish to raise a number of points which I hope the Minister will take on board. First, I want to discuss the need to maintain vigorous standards in respect of preventing pollution. Certain beaches in Dún Laoghaire and Killiney have been awarded blue flags but beaches in many other areas require maintenance. If we are not vigilant it will be easy to allow standards to slide, particularly in terms of leakages from trawlers and the pumping of sewage directly into our ports. The Minister must give careful consideration to this matter.</P>
    <P>I welcome the Minister's comments on marine safety. Unfortunately, there have been a number of tragic accidents in recent years and I recall a particular incident which occurred off the coast of Donegal. Monitoring mechanisms must be put in place in this area. A system has been put in place to inspect eight year old cars and there are many trawlers which could benefit from similar inspections because some of them do not have the necessary safety equipment on board. Trawler owners should be obliged to maintain basic life-saving equipment, emergency flares and radio equipment.</P>
    <P>People should not take chances by putting to sea in rough weather, they should adopt a common sense approach. The same applies to those who engage in marine leisure activities. Too many tragedies have been caused by people taking to the water without life jackets etc. Perhaps the Minister will ensure that the various checks and inspections are carried out. If trawlers do not have the necessary equipment, they should be confined to port.</P>
    <P>The final issue I wish to raise involves the National Maritime Museum in Dún Laoghaire. Discussions are currently taking place with the Dublin Docklands Development Authority and others regarding moving the museum. Most people would like to see the museum remain in Dún Laoghaire, given that it has been situated there for many years. I accept that other ports throughout the country might have claims to house such a museum, but the museum has been situated in Dún Laoghaire for a long period. The port there is growing and the marina is being developed.</P>
    <P>I ask the Minister to consult with his colleague, the Minister for Arts, Heritage, Gaeltacht and the Islands, Deputy de Valera, on this matter to ensure that the museum is retained in Dún Laoghaire and upgraded. The problem with museums is that some of them do not operate on a self-financing basis. People would like to see some of the millions of pounds raised through the national lottery etc. used to finance the National Maritime Museum, the National Museum and other museums in order that our heritage is preserved. We are making great advances for the future, but there is no harm in people remembering their past.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="611" /> I ask the Minister to consider this matter in conjunction with the Minister for Arts, Heritage, Gaeltacht and the Islands to ensure that the National Maritime Museum is retained in Dún Laoghaire. I accept that the location may have to change and that the aspect of funding must be examined. However, I hope the Minister will take my comments on board and consider the case on its merits.</P>
    <Speaker pid="EndaBonner" hpid="Mr. Bonner Mr. Bonner">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Bonner</NameTxt>
      <P>This has been an informative debate. While many Members concentrated on the fishing industry, a number of colleagues, including the Minister, referred to issues involving natural resources. I acknowledge the presence of his predecessor in the House and I referred to many of the initiatives for which Deputy Woods was responsible during his time in the Department. I refer here to his actions in respect of the whitefish fleet and the national plan on the marine and natural resources, which was developed during his stewardship of the Department.</P>
      <P>I compliment the new Minister on his knowledge of the industry. I note that he rarely referred to his script and he displayed a great knowledge of the industry and of matters relating to natural resources. It is encouraging to note that, according to the Minister, certain changes will take place.</P>
      <P>The Minister referred to customer relations within the Department. Since I entered the House two and a half years ago I have always been treated with great courtesy by the staff of the Department of the Marine and Natural Resources. I have always found them helpful, particularly on a one-to-one basis. Unfortunately, as the Minister stated, the structures in place do not allow certain things to happen. Perhaps we can look forward to changes in that regard.</P>
      <P>I was encouraged by the Minister's comments in respect of a number of other areas. He stated that he intends to make immediate moves to develop the inshore fleet and inland fisheries. The Minister said that £20 million or £24 million in funding for tourism and leisure has been made available over the period of the national plan.</P>
      <P>Other speakers referred to forestry. I note £80 million is available under the national plan for excess harvesting and other matters such as public relations. In many heavily afforested areas a great deal of damage is being done to public roads and access roads. The Department should ensure that harvesters and Coillte, in particular, are held responsible for the damage they cause to the infrastructure.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>We have made a number of changes in the draft development plan for Donegal in relation to afforestation. It baffles me that people with less than a certain acreage who are not looking for a grant do not need planning permission, but those looking for grants always have planning per<Col N="612" /> mission difficulties with the local authority. I would like the Department to look at that.</P>
    <P>Up to now the Department has been extremely slow in developing ports. The former Minister, Deputy Woods, made certain changes when he was in the Department. I am talking here, however, about the small harbours around the coast. The Minister's constituency colleague, the Minister of State, Deputy Ó Cuív, has, through his Department, provided much of the funding for the development of many harbours in my county that had fallen by the wayside.</P>
    <P>Senator Caffrey referred to the lack of harbour development along the Mayo coast. The difficulty is that all the Mayo fishermen have moved to Killybegs. Senator Ryan referred to the largest fishing boat in the world, which is owned by a Mayoman who has lived in Killybegs for many years. Quite a few Mayo people are involved in the industry and have been very successful.</P>
    <P>Reference was made to the Marine Institute moving to Galway. I suppose that decision was made long before the Minister was appointed. However, it is only right that it should move to Galway. When I was studying in UCG almost 30 years ago Professor Ó Céidigh was involved in marine research long before anyone else took a serious interest in it.</P>
    <P>The biggest issue, and the one on which most speakers concentrated, is the question of quotas. I raised a number of matters with the previous Minister, Deputy Woods. I congratulated him when he secured the extra 5,000 tonnes for small boats. However, many boats had not applied for and did not get onto that scheme. I am talking here about traditional fishermen whose families have been in the fishing industry for many years. Some of them are only looking for one or two tonnes. I ask the Minister to see if any of the special tonnage is left to help a number of these people.</P>
    <P>The Minister of State, Deputy Ó Cuív, has also raised with the Department of the Marine and Natural Resources the issue of a small tonnage being put aside for people on the offshore islands who want to get back into fishing, and I support him in that regard. When I was growing up, Burtonport was a very successful salmon port. Many of the half-decker boats that operated out of Burtonport were based on Aranmore Island. I think there are only two boats on Aranmore Island now. A special case could be made in that regard.</P>
    <P>The Minister heard what everybody said about the tonnage and quota system. I was not too hard on him when I referred to it earlier. However, it is the single biggest issue facing fishermen. Senator Ryan raised the issue of how we were sold out in the earlier negotiations. This is our last chance. I know from listening to the Minister and the knowledge he is gaining that he will do his best.</P>
    <P>We have been trying for years to get proper access for Killybegs. Under the National Roads <Col N="613" /> Authority and the Department of the Environment and Local Government, up to £50 million will be spent on improving the road structure. It would be a great disaster if we had the road infrastructure but no fish for the factories. We can do everything else in Killybegs, but if we do not have the supply of fish, we cannot improve efficiency, added value and other matters.</P>
    <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>When is it proposed to sit again?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TomFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. T. Fitzgerald Mr. T. Fitzgerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. T. Fitzgerald</NameTxt>
      <P>At 10.30 a.m. tomorrow.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Adjournment Matters." RHead="- School Staffing">
    <Title>Adjournment Matters. - School Staffing.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="TomHayes" hpid="Mr. T. Hayes Mr. T. Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Mr. T. Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>I thank the Minister for coming to the House. I am aware he has been waiting for 15 or 20 minutes and I will try to be as brief as possible.</P>
      <P>The kernel of the problem in relation to Scoil Aonghusa special school in Cashel, County Tipperary, is its need for clerical assistance. There seems to be an unwillingness in the Department in this regard. The board of management has expressed great concern at the historical twinning of Scoil Aonghusa and Scoil Cormac in Cashel. Scoil Cormac is now a huge school with up to 150 pupils with mild and multiple learning disabilities and it has special need for a full-time secretary. Scoil Aonghusa has great need for, but no access to, a secretary. Both schools are located on the same site in Cashel.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The board of management has pointed out to the Department many reasons for its need for a full-time secretary. The first reason is to free the principal for operational duties. The role of the principal of such a school is very onerous and time consuming. A secretary is also needed to liaise with the principal on a daily basis on administrative matters. There is a huge amount of administrative difficulties in running such a school. A secretary is needed to serve the families of 36 children with moderate to exceptional needs, which is a huge number. A secretary is also needed to provide services to the 14 full-time and ten part-time staff members and the ten FÁS trainees. The experience gained by FÁS trainees in that school has prepared them well to work in that field. Many of them have proved themselves by training in nursing and education for the handicapped. A secretary is needed to provide services for the eight therapists in the school. A secretary is also needed to provide a link with the wider community. The people in the broader catchment area of Cashel do a great deal of fundraising to support this school for which they need <Col N="614" /> secretarial assistance. The list of reasons for needing a secretary goes on and on.</P>
    <P>At a time when we hear daily about the Celtic tiger and that the economy is buoyant with cash, I implore the Minister to consider this. I do not know what he will say to me but I am not certain I will be leaving with the promise of a secretary. If that is the case, I ask him to reconsider that decision. This is very important for these people and for mental handicap education, not only in Cashel but in the wider county area. The Tipperary association for the mentally handicapped is a voluntary body which is one of the greatest examples in this country of community based help and support for the handicapped. I implore the Minister to give me a decent answer.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelJWoods" hpid="Dr. Woods Dr. Woods">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Education and Science (Dr. Woods)</NameTxt>
      <P>Currently my Department provides funding towards the cost of secretarial assistance in primary schools under two separate schemes.</P>
      <P>The first of these schemes &ndash; the provision of clerk-typists in national schools &ndash; was introduced in 1978 as a job creation measure. The scheme's purpose is to meet the costs of salaries and employer's PRSI for secretarial staff employed in the larger primary schools. Under this scheme a number of primary schools qualified for a shared secretary and Scoil Aonghusa special school is currently involved in a sharing arrangement with another special school in the same area. Grants covering the cost of salaries and employer's PRSI are paid to the school authorities. The board of management of the special school with which Scoil Aonghusa has the sharing arrangement is the employer in this case.</P>
      <P>The scheme introduced in 1978 is being phased out as posts become vacant. There is currently no provision for the appointment of full-time secretaries in posts which are being shared. The second scheme for the provision of secretarial and caretaking services in primary schools was introduced in 1992 as part of the Programme for Economic and Social Progress, PESP. Under the programme's terms, a phased programme of financial assistance by way of a supplementary capitation grant for the provision of secretarial and caretaker services came into effect on 1 September 1992. Primary schools eligible for grant assistance under this scheme receive £30 per pupil per annum, subject to a maximum of £15,000, in respect of secretarial and caretaking services if they do not have such services already under the Department's existing schemes for the employment of secretaries and caretakers. Where a school already has either a secretarial or caretaking service under the Department's existing schemes, it is only entitled to receive £15 per pupil, subject to a maximum of £7,500. Boards of management are responsible for making the necessary arrangements for the provision of secretarial and caretaking services appropriate to the needs of the school.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="615" /> With effect from January 2000, all primary schools with 100 or more pupils which do not have a service already are eligible for a grant of £30 per pupil. Therefore, as Scoil Aonghusa has a shared secretary arrangement under the 1978 scheme, it also currently receives £15 per pupil towards the cost of caretaking services under the PESP scheme.</P>
    <P>The Senator will be aware that an additional £9 million was provided for in the recent budget for the next two years which will enable me to extend and improve the supports available to all primary schools. Details of the implementation of this will be worked out in the near future following con<Col N="616" /> sultations and will, when taken together with the earlier move, make a major contribution to assisting schools. The issue of providing further assistance to schools involved in a sharing arrangement is a matter that is being examined in my Department in the context of the working out of the details of the improvements in the scheme which I have outlined.</P>
    <P>I have noted the Senator's comments about this school and the onus on the principal. In the consultations taking place now, I will consider the points raised.</P>
    <P>The Seanad adjourned at 8.10 p.m. until 10.30 a.m. on Thursday, 24 February 2000.</P>
  </MainHeading>
</Debate>