<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE Debate SYSTEM "../Debate.dtd"[]>
<Debate DocTitle="Seanad Debate" Day="Wed" Date="16" Month="Feb" Year="2000" Vol="162" No="7" DateIrish="Dé Céadaoin, 16 Feabhra 2000" DateEnglish="Wednesday, 16 February 2000" House="S" CommitteeEng="" CommitteeIr="" SubNameEng="" cnum="0">
  <MainHeading Type="Prelude" LHead="" RHead="">
    <Title>
    </Title>
    <P Just="Center">
      <Col N="433" /> Chuaigh an Cathaoirleach i gceannas ar 2.30 p.m.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Business" RHead="of Seanad">
    <Title>Business of Seanad.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="BrianMullooly" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I have notice from Senator Caffrey that, on the motion for the Adjournment of the House today, he proposes to raise the following matter:</P>
      <P>The need for the Minister for Finance to expedite the proposal for a new Garda station in Ballina, County Mayo, having regard to the totally unsuitable and inadequate conditions under which the Garda in Ballina have to operate.</P>
      <P>I regard the matter raised by the Senator as suitable for discussion on the Adjournment and it will be taken at the conclusion of business.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Order of" RHead="Business">
    <Title>Order of Business.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="DonnieCassidyFF" hpid="Mr. Cassidy Mr. Cassidy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cassidy</NameTxt>
      <P>Today's Order of Business is No. 1 and No. 20, motion 13. On No. 1, the Comhairle Bill, 1999, Second Stage shall be taken today, with contributions of spokespersons not to exceed 20 minutes and of all other Senators not to exceed 15 minutes. No. 20, motion 13 shall be taken from 6 p.m. to 8 p.m. and business shall resume thereafter, if not previously concluded.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MauriceManning" hpid="Mr. Manning Mr. Manning">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Manning</NameTxt>
      <P>Will the Leader of the House arrange, at the earliest convenient time, a debate on the events in Northern Ireland? There have been debates here in the past when there was good news about Northern Ireland and we were happy to share in and support those happy or helpful events. Now there is bad news from Northern Ireland and many Members of this House would like to discuss the matter. Our debates have always been helpful and constructive. This is the right time to have a debate and this is the appropriate place to have it. I ask for a debate as soon as possible.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I raise a question on No. 2 on the Order Paper, the Shannon River Council Bill, to which I would like an answer, maybe not today but tomorrow, and which the Leader may want to consider. Last week, the Minister of State at the Department of <Col N="434" /> the Environment and Local Government said that the Government proposed to ask that this Bill be referred to the Joint Committee on Public Enterprise and Transport. That came as a bolt from the blue for Members. There are a number of questions arising which the Leader should answer before we take the business tomorrow.</P>
    <P>First, why refer the matter to the Joint Committee on Public Enterprise and Transport? Surely a committee which deals with the Office of Public Works or the Department of the Environment and Local Government would be the appropriate committee. Second, is the Minister asking to have Committee Stage taken at that committee? If so, the committee would then become a select committee of the Dáil and Senators would be excluded from debating Committee Stage of a Seanad Bill. That clearly would not be suitable. Alternatively, is the Minister suggesting that the Bill be parked in that committee where it can be delayed further? Is this a delaying tactic? This would be unacceptable to all sides of the House. I ask the Leader to find out if this is the case. All Members wish the Bill to proceed to Committee Stage in this House and whatever flaws are in the Bill can be sorted out there. It is a Seanad Bill.</P>
    <Speaker pid="DavidNorris" hpid="Mr. Norris Mr. Norris">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norris</NameTxt>
      <P>Hear, Hear.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MairinQuill" hpid="Miss Quill Miss Quill">
      <NameTxt>Miss Quill</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MauriceManning" hpid="Mr. Manning Mr. Manning">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Manning</NameTxt>
      <P>I hope, in the interests of the House and in its protection, the Leader will resist any attempt by the bureaucracy to have this Bill sidetracked.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeOToole" hpid="Mr. O'Toole Mr. O'Toole">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Toole</NameTxt>
      <P>I support Senator Manning on this matter. We should stand behind the Leader on this and not let him be thrown around by Government types.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PaulCoghlan" hpid="Mr. Coghlan Mr. Coghlan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Coghlan</NameTxt>
      <P>Heavyweights.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeOToole" hpid="Mr. O'Toole Mr. O'Toole">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Toole</NameTxt>
      <P>It is time for the Leader of the House to do the bidding of the House and respond to the views of the House. The fine speeches made by his side of the House last week made a deep impression all round. There is no precedent for sending this matter to a committee of this type which does not seem to have jurisdiction over the area of the Shannon. That is not appropriate. Neither is there a precedent for dealing with Committee Stage of a Seanad Bill in a committee. These issues relate to the business of the House and must be dealt with on that basis. The Government should do as was promised last week. It should examine this Bill, make the necessary changes and bring it back to this House for Committee Stage debate.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Will the Leader tell the House when the debate on the Programme for Prosperity and Fairness will be resumed? Positive things were said about the programme last week and it is important that the views of Members on both sides of the House be heard. The programme was negotiated partly <Col N="435" /> by the incoming general secretary of the Labour Party and I am sure we can look forward to that party's support for the programme. The debate will ensure that Members of the House influence public debate on this issue.</P>
    <P>Last week the Leader indicated his willingness to invite the Minister for Public Enterprise, Deputy O'Rourke, to the House to outline her proposals for Aer Lingus. She has indicated to me privately that she would be happy to do that. This should be done, although I agree with Senator Manning that a debate on Northern Ireland is more urgent and should be held first.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JoeCostelloLAB" hpid="Mr. Costello Mr. Costello">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Costello</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator O'Toole has referred to the debate on the national agreement. Will the Leader tell the House when the debate will be resumed? Although the incoming general secretary of the Labour Party was involved in the discussions on the Programme for Prosperity and Fairness, his involvement related to the community and voluntary pillar. That sector is well catered for at present.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeOToole" hpid="Mr. O'Toole Mr. O'Toole">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Toole</NameTxt>
      <P>Has there been a split even before he begins the job?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeCostelloLAB" hpid="Mr. Costello Mr. Costello">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Costello</NameTxt>
      <P>Our concerns are with the content of the programme, which has perhaps been negotiated by other negotiators, not with the process. Members would like to have a say on that matter. When will the debate be resumed?</P>
      <P>I support Senator Manning in asking for a debate on Northern Ireland. I have called for such a debate over the last weeks. This House has been particularly sensitive to the question of the timing of such a debate and we have agreed to delay it for some time. However, we seem to be the only people who show such sensitivity. The question merits a debate at this time of increased recrimination and the disastrous decision of the IRA to disengage from the de Chastelain commission places the matter back in crisis. I wish the Taoiseach and the Prime Minister well in their discussions today. A debate on Northern Ireland would be merited next week.</P>
      <P>I echo Senator Quinn's call for a debate on inflation. He has been proved correct and inflation is rapidly increasing. Some of the taxation measures of the last budget which favour those already well off will fuel inflation. This matter is of considerable concern.</P>
      <P>Will the Leader ask the Minister for Public Enterprise to come to the House and make a statement on public transport? Dublin ground to a halt yesterday.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeOToole" hpid="Mr. O'Toole Mr. O'Toole">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Toole</NameTxt>
      <P>I thought the opposite was the case.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MairinQuill" hpid="Miss Quill Miss Quill">
      <NameTxt>Miss Quill</NameTxt>
      <P>It was never more free-flowing.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeCostelloLAB" hpid="Mr. Costello Mr. Costello">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Costello</NameTxt>
      <P>We experience transport chaos every day in Dublin. The total absence of bus transport yesterday added to the difficulties <Col N="436" /> which are frequently raised in this House, such as those relating to taxis and hackneys, quality bus corridors, Luas&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BrianMullooly" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>These are matters which can be raised in the course of the debate which the Senator is seeking.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeCostelloLAB" hpid="Mr. Costello Mr. Costello">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Costello</NameTxt>
      <P>I was merely justifying my call for a debate.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelFinneranFF" hpid="Mr. Finneran Mr. Finneran">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Finneran</NameTxt>
      <P>I wish to raise a matter with the Leader regarding wheelchair users on Iarnród Éireann trains. While I appreciate the investment the Government has made and continues to make in the rail network, I must take serious issue with Iarnród Éireann regarding their lack of facilities for wheelchair users, particularly on trains travelling from the west. This matter was brought home to me at the Irish Wheelchair Association's annual general meeting in my county last week.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeCostelloLAB" hpid="Mr. Costello Mr. Costello">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Costello</NameTxt>
      <P>Another reason for a plan.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelFinneranFF" hpid="Mr. Finneran Mr. Finneran">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Finneran</NameTxt>
      <P>It is inappropriate that wheelchair users can only be accommodated in the dining car or in the passages between carriages. I ask the Leader to bring this matter to the attention of the Minister for Public Enterprise. I ask that an instruction be given to Iarnród Éireann to provide facilities for wheelchair users on all its trains and I call on the Minister to insist on this.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidNorris" hpid="Mr. Norris Mr. Norris">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norris</NameTxt>
      <P>For those of us who live in the city rather than in the outer suburbs of Sean McDermott Street, the streets seemed to be much freer yesterday. It makes a good argument for getting as many buses as possible off the streets.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DonLydon" hpid="Mr. Lydon Mr. Lydon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lydon</NameTxt>
      <P>Hear, hear.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidNorris" hpid="Mr. Norris Mr. Norris">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norris</NameTxt>
      <P>Nothing could have demonstrated better how correct the Minister is to put the Luas under ground on the north-south axis. It is about time we did it on the east-west axis as well and I look forward to her doing that. That would clear the streets better than anything I can think of.</P>
      <P>I join Senator Manning in calling for a debate on the North. It is time we had our say. There are things that need to be said and perhaps this is the only House in which they will be said. If we look at the difference between Sinn Féin/IRA and the loyalists, the latter apologised to people for the carnage they created, they appointed somebody to the de Chastelain Commission in February 1997, they have surrendered token arms. That is very important. The others have done nothing of this. They have played a poker game. We heard from Gerry Adams they were going to jump together &ndash; Trimble jumped and Adams is sitting on the fence laughing at him.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BrianMullooly" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>These points can be made in the debate which has been sought.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="437" />
    <Speaker pid="DavidNorris" hpid="ÜfcMr. Norris ÜfcMr. Norris">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norris</NameTxt>
      <P>I stand reproved. I also join Senator Manning regarding another matter. I am so innocent that I did not see what might be afoot with regard to the referring of the Shannon River Council Bill. It has raised a very important point that the Leader should look into, that is, the way in which Members of this House are disbarred from sitting on select committees. It is outrageous. There is also an Oireachtas Select Committee on Foreign Affairs. I see no reason Members of this House should be excluded from it.</P>
      <P>I am sure the House would wish to congratulate the people of Zimbabwe on the resounding answer they gave to the appalling dictator Mugabe, who was openly described by a member of his own parliament as a trickster.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LabhrasOMurchu" hpid="Labhrás Ó Murchú Labhrás Ó Murchú">
      <NameTxt>Labhrás Ó Murchú</NameTxt>
      <P>I too support the call for a debate on the North. This is a particularly sensitive time for the peace process and nothing will be served by recriminations. They will only make a bad situation worse. If we had a debate it would give us an opportunity to remind ourselves of what has been achieved to date and the risks we now face. It would also be important for us to give responsible leadership for the common good and to ensure that we do not follow the same road as people who may be trying to score political points.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PaddyBurke" hpid="Mr. Burke Mr. Burke">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Burke</NameTxt>
      <P>I call on the Leader to ask the Taoiseach to come here to discuss the Government's decentralisation programme. The Government is committed to decentralisation but it does not seem to have a proper plan in place. It seems to be taking place willy nilly. Perhaps the Taoiseach could come here and state what Departments will be decentralised and how it will be done. This is an important issue for the rest of the country.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DrMauriceHayes" hpid="Dr. M. Hayes Dr. M. Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Dr. M. Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>I too support the call for a debate on the North. There is never an optimum time for having it. It was proper for us to show some restraint while discussions were going on <i>in camera, </i>but they have now moved into the open and there is a danger that the agenda will be set by people outside the political process. There is a broad public opinion which I support and which my fellow Senators are well placed to reflect.</P>
      <P>Will the Leader of the House ask the Minister for Agriculture, Food and Rural Development when he intends to amend the regulations relating to the importation of domestic animals and pets to bring them into line with those applying throughout the European Union and, in particular, with the changes made in the United Kingdom to allow tourists bring their pets with them on holiday? It would be ridiculous if a different arrangement were to apply here from that in Northern Ireland.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="KathleenOMeara" hpid="Ms O'Meara Ms O'Meara">
      <NameTxt>Ms O'Meara</NameTxt>
      <P>The comments of Senator Hayes reflect the genuine desire of Members to have a debate on Northern Ireland. Restraint can be <Col N="438" /> exercised but it is important that we are given an opportunity to express our views and genuine concerns. By having a debate we can show the value of diversity of opinion by highlighting the strongly held views of our constituents. I, therefore, support the call for a debate on the matter.</P>
      <P>Concern has been expressed about the way the Shannon River Council Bill has been handled. As one of its promoters, it was my clear understanding last week that the principle of the Bill was being accepted by all sides. This issue has been debated in the past. The Government's response, however, was considered to be very cynical; it kicked for touch by referring the Bill to a committee at which Members will not have an opportunity to respond. I believe the Leader of the House would not support such a move and I expect him to act to ensure it does not happen.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WillieFarrell" hpid="Mr. Farrell Mr. Farrell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Farrell</NameTxt>
      <P>I support the call for a debate on Northern Ireland. I sometimes think it was a pity Mo Mowlam was withdrawn at such an important time. I pay tribute to Mr. David Ervine for being so honest on &ldquo;Morning Ireland&rdquo;. His comments were very fair. In doing so he took the high ground.</P>
      <P>Can we have a debate on the serious issue of coastal erosion? In my area a good golf course which I walked recently is being lost to the sea. I play a lot of golf and golf courses throughout the country are in danger of losing a lot of land through erosion. I cannot understand that the environmentalists are not talking about this matter on which we should have a debate to see if anything can be done about it.</P>
      <P>According to a recent report we have become too hygiene conscious. The heading was, &ldquo;Dirt prevents disease.&rdquo;  The incidence of asthma and other diseases has increased enormously and the reason is that we are so clinically clean that we have no resistance to bugs to which previous generations were immune. Perhaps we have gone over the top and it is time we took the middle ground by cutting out some of the farcical nonsense of over-cleanliness.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FergalQuinn" hpid="Mr. Quinn Mr. Quinn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Quinn</NameTxt>
      <P>I wish to refer to three matters, two of which I have mentioned before. The reason I ask the Leader of the House to consider them is that the Seanad could have a special role as a watchdog in this area. One of these matters is the intergovernmental conference starting on Monday. Let us remind ourselves of what happened in the past. This will probably end up with a treaty and referendum here and, as in the past with referenda, we will discover that nobody knows what we are talking about. We have not taken the appropriate steps and the public is lost. There is a role for the Seanad in this area. If we debate what is happening in the intergovernmental conference we can see what is happening and keep abreast of matters so that they do not come as a surprise later.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The second matter is inflation, to which Senator Costello referred. A monthly watch <Col N="439" /> should be kept on this and the Seanad should be the watchdog in this regard. This is necessary. I have asked for it before and the Leader said we can find the opportunity to debate it. However, the situation has now become very serious. Yesterday's figure of 4% was described by <i>The Irish Times</i> as a little frightening, but it is not a little frightening, since it is by far the highest in the EU, it is scary. It is in danger of threatening our whole success story and the Seanad should look at this on a monthly basis.</P>
    <P>I recently referred to the hackers' attack on the Internet and asked the Leader to ask the Minister concerned whether our law agencies have the legal framework to handle this matter. Yesterday President Clinton called the chief executives of Internet and e-mail companies to the White House to see what could be done to protect the United States. We have set a target for ourselves of becoming leaders in this area in Europe. Let us make sure we do not fall foul by being unprepared for this. Has the Leader heard anything from the Minister regarding my question as to whether we have the legal framework to handle this?</P>
    <Speaker pid="TomHayes" hpid="Mr. T. Hayes Mr. T. Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Mr. T. Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>I seek a debate on rural development with particular emphasis on the future of the Leader groups. These groups are concerned as there is no direction as to their future and people are concerned that jobs may be lost. We talk about rural development and there is a huge number of projects on line, but it is important to discuss this matter thoroughly. I appreciate the Government's commitment of £55 million to rural development, but this debate is urgently needed and I ask the Leader to arrange it as soon as possible.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DermotFitzpatrickFF" hpid="Dr. Fitzpatrick Dr. Fitzpatrick">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Fitzpatrick</NameTxt>
      <P>I echo the views of other speakers who have called for a debate on Northern Ireland. It is about time we debated it and brought the facts into the open. As Senator Maurice Hayes said, we should not let the debate into the backrooms, where ordinary people may be disenfranchised. We are the voice of the people in many respects.</P>
      <P>I ask the Leader to speak to the Minister for Public Enterprise about what happened in Dublin yesterday. It was unforgivable. The people of Dublin were held to ransom on the coldest and wettest day of the year by two groups arguing arcane ideological points. Let us start knocking heads together to solve this problem.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThereseRidge" hpid="Mrs. Ridge Mrs. Ridge">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Ridge</NameTxt>
      <P>Will the Leader ask the Minister for Justice, Equality and Law Reform for a progress report on the review of the censorship laws? It was promised last April and, given the debate in <i>The Irish Times</i> letters column, I would like to know how the Minister intends to proceed.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I join with my Leader and other speakers in calling for a debate on Northern Ireland. Perhaps <Col N="440" /> if there were more women in the Assembly there, things would not be the way they are.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JoeOToole" hpid="Mr. O'Toole Mr. O'Toole">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Toole</NameTxt>
      <P>That is the kind of sexist comment we could do without. It is beginning to become a bit of a joke around here.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThereseRidge" hpid="Mrs. Ridge Mrs. Ridge">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Ridge</NameTxt>
      <P>I have never interrupted Senator O'Toole, though I notice he frequently interrupts&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidNorris" hpid="Mr. Norris Mr. Norris">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norris</NameTxt>
      <P>I interrupt him all the time.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BrianMullooly" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Order, please, the time for the Order of Business is very limited.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThereseRidge" hpid="Mrs. Ridge Mrs. Ridge">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Ridge</NameTxt>
      <P>They are very bold and should be given 100 lines. I am sorry I have been interrupted.</P>
      <P>I support Senator Finneran's comments on the provision of wheelchairs on trains. However, I am surprised he is asking the Leader to consult the Minister on this issue when he lives in the next county to her and is a member of the same party.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PaulCoghlan" hpid="Mr. Coghlan Mr. Coghlan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Coghlan</NameTxt>
      <P>I support the call by Senator Manning and others for a debate on Northern Ireland. Sadly, things have taken a very difficult turn there and we wish all sides well in their efforts to get back on track as soon as possible.</P>
      <P>I also support Senator Manning's remarks on the Shannon River Council Bill and urge the Leader to take his views on board in the best interests of this House. When can we expect a further announcement, a clear-cut and definitive policy statement from the Government on Aer Rianta and the Great Southern Hotels Group? </P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DonLydon" hpid="Mr. Lydon Mr. Lydon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lydon</NameTxt>
      <P>I support the call for a debate on Northern Ireland. Will the Leader consider holding a debate on the United Nations and affiliated bodies such as the World Health Organisation? It may not be widely known but doctors in Taiwan, a country with a population of 23 million people and the twelfth largest economy in the world, are not allowed to attend meetings of the WHO or contribute their knowledge to it in any way. We were not afraid to discuss East Timor and should not be afraid to discuss this issue either.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FergusODowdFG" hpid="Mr. O'Dowd Mr. O'Dowd">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Dowd</NameTxt>
      <P>Will the Leader arrange for a debate as soon as possible on disability services and their delivery? In particular, will he arrange for us to discuss with the Minister for the Environment and Local Government the necessity for each local authority to appoint an officer to deal and work with people with disabilities in their communities? This would have a significant effect on the quality of life of people with disabilities.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="AnnLeonard" hpid="Ms Leonard Ms Leonard">
      <NameTxt>Ms Leonard</NameTxt>
      <P>I support the call for a debate on Northern Ireland. We owe it to people North and South of the Border to hold such a debate. Will the Leader impress upon the Minister for Health and Children the need for a public awareness <Col N="441" /> campaign in regard to the childhood immunisation programme? We are currently aiming for a 95% level of uptake but the actual level is only 75%. These vaccinations are available free from general practitioners. Whereas we had hoped to eradicate diseases such as measles, mumps and rubella, they are currently reaching epidemic proportions. This is a matter of urgency in view of the risk of a major health scare occurring.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnCreganFF" hpid="Mr. J. Cregan Mr. J. Cregan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J. Cregan</NameTxt>
      <P>There have been very positive reports in recent days in regard to the plans of the Minister for Health and Children to make our society smoke free. Even though I am a smoker, I welcome those plans. On a related issue, I read a disturbing headline on the passing on of seized contraband cigarettes to psychiatric institutions such as the Central Mental Hospital in Dundrum and others throughout the country for the benefit of psychiatric patients. I was disturbed to hear this practice had stopped. I ask that psychiatric patients would be considered in the context of whatever regulations are introduced through new legislation on the tobacco industry. In many cases, cigarettes are their only comfort or pleasure. They are not a very strong lobby group and we should not forget them. We should try to be as humane as possible. When we passed health board regulations recently, we excluded psychiatric hospitals and psychiatric wards in acute hospitals. I urge the Leader to ask the Ministers for Health and Children and Finance to reconsider this issue.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EndaBonner" hpid="Mr. Bonner Mr. Bonner">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Bonner</NameTxt>
      <P>I also call for a debate on Northern Ireland. While I still hold Mr. David Trimble in high regard, it was very easy for him to jump when he had a safety net provided by Peter Mandelson. We all realise now why Mo Mowlam was moved on. The British Government acted too hastily last Friday&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BrianMullooly" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>These points can be made during the debate which the Senator is seeking.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EndaBonner" hpid="Mr. Bonner Mr. Bonner">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Bonner</NameTxt>
      <P>The institutions should be reconvened immediately. I agree with Senator Hayes on the Leader groups. While £55 million in funding is available, there is anxiety among the groups, including the four in my county. They employ many people and have difficulty retaining them without knowing the financial outcome. I would like the Minister of State, Deputy Davern, to come to the House to inform us of his proposals.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="CamillusGlynn" hpid="Mr. Glynn Mr. Glynn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Glynn</NameTxt>
      <P>I support Senator John Cregan's comments on cigarettes and psychiatric patients. In my experience, cigarettes are significant to most psychiatric patients and they have a role, although this may be frowned upon by other sections of the community. Will the Leader arrange statements on the Irish language? Perhaps Members could suggest ways of using the teanga dúchais more positively in the House.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="442" />
    <Speaker pid="BrianMullooly" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Many of the matters raised on the Order of Business would have been more appropriate to the Adjournment or Private Members' time.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DonnieCassidyFF" hpid="Mr. Cassidy Mr. Cassidy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cassidy</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator Manning and many others called for a debate on Northern Ireland. I will inform the House of the time of that debate on tomorrow's Order of Business. It will be early next week and I will allow as much time as the House requires to enable Senators to make contributions. I would like to join with the Taoiseach, the British Prime Minister and everyone concerned in trying to return to the stability of last week. The events which took place are regrettable. However, we now have an opportunity to prevent a return to where we started. I welcome the clarification in the media, although I do not know whether it has been confirmed, that the IRA's objective is peace and that it wants the country to revert to its position of last week.</P>
      <P>Senators Manning, O'Toole and many others expressed their concerns about the Shannon River Council Bill. I have allocated Government time tomorrow morning for the Bill. We are all in favour of the progression of this Bill. Senator O'Meara may have misled the less senior Senators in the House &ndash; all Governments fudged the serious decline and flooding of the Shannon. It is one of the great national resources and touches 13 counties. This Bill was introduced by the former Senator, Deputy Daly, who held eight portfolios and the former Commissioner and Minister, Deputy O'Kennedy. It is about time everyone concerned, including the six Departments, 30 local authorities and Opposition Senators who have re-introduced it for our consideration, does everything in their power to bring it to&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeOToole" hpid="Mr. O'Toole Mr. O'Toole">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Toole</NameTxt>
      <P>Committee Stage?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MauriceManning" hpid="Mr. Manning Mr. Manning">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Manning</NameTxt>
      <P>The Statute Book.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DonnieCassidyFF" hpid="Mr. Cassidy Mr. Cassidy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cassidy</NameTxt>
      <P>I am doing my best to bring it to a successful conclusion.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MauriceManning" hpid="Mr. Manning Mr. Manning">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Manning</NameTxt>
      <P>The Leader has our full support.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DonnieCassidyFF" hpid="Mr. Cassidy Mr. Cassidy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cassidy</NameTxt>
      <P>I thank the Opposition for its support but I do not want anyone to go on a crusade or a solo run because if they do, I will have to go on record, in the House or the media, and say how all Governments have ignored the great advantages of the Shannon.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidNorris" hpid="Mr. Norris Mr. Norris">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norris</NameTxt>
      <P>The Leader is holding himself back and not saying it today.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DonnieCassidyFF" hpid="Mr. Cassidy Mr. Cassidy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cassidy</NameTxt>
      <P>I did not hear that squeak.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BrianMullooly" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>The Leader of the House, without interruption.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DonnieCassidyFF" hpid="Mr. Cassidy Mr. Cassidy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cassidy</NameTxt>
      <P>Senators O'Toole and Costello asked for a continuation of statements on the <Col N="443" /> Programme for Prosperity and Fairness. I propose to resume the statements from 1.30 p.m. to 4 p.m. tomorrow. Senators Costello and Quinn asked for a debate on inflation and I will make time available for a debate on the issue. I said last week in this House that the issue could be discussed from time to time. Perhaps it could be included in the statements tomorrow on the new national agreement.</P>
      <P>Senators Costello, Norris and Fitzpatrick expressed their views about the one day bus strike which took place yesterday. I hope this will not continue because it caused great disruption to people trying to get to and from their workplace and for employers who had to provide taxis throughout the day to ferry people to and from work. One would not see a strike on a Saturday or Sunday. These people made their point yesterday and I ask them, in the interests of all concerned, to give an opportunity to those who, at the end of the day, will have to sit around the table and negotiate a settlement. When travelling to the House yesterday, I noticed there was very little traffic on the streets. I take Senator Norris's point that the Minister for Public Enterprise was probably pleased she made the decision to go underground with Luas because what took place yesterday was a great example of what can happen when traffic is taken off the streets and how pleasant it is to come to the capital city and avail of all the services.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidNorris" hpid="Mr. Norris Mr. Norris">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norris</NameTxt>
      <P>Hear, hear. It took her to do it as well.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DonnieCassidyFF" hpid="Mr. Cassidy Mr. Cassidy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cassidy</NameTxt>
      <P>I will pass on the views of Senators Finneran and Ridge to the Minister regarding wheelchair accessible vehicles, particularly in relation to Iarnród Éireann. Senator Burke called on the Taoiseach to come to the House to make a statement on decentralisation. I am in agreement with this because Mullingar, the capital town of the midlands, has been ignored in this regard by all Governments.</P>
      <P>I will pass on the views of Senator Tom Hayes to the Minister for Agriculture, Food and Rural Development. Senator Farrell called for a debate on coastal erosion. It is approximately eight years since there was a debate on this issue and, therefore, I will make time available for such a debate.</P>
      <P>I will make time available for a debate on the Intergovernmental Conference as requested by Senator Quinn. The Senator also asked for a debate on the important topic of attacks on the Internet. I will pass on his views to the Minister and I do not have a problem making time available for a debate on the issue.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Senators Tom Hayes and Bonner called for a debate on rural development. I take Senator Tom Hayes's point welcoming the £55 million which the Government has made available for this scheme. I am sure he is proud of his fellow countyman the Minister of State, Deputy Davern, who is performing excellently in his portfolio. His £55 <Col N="444" /> million announcement to the House was well informed. I will make time available on a Thursday afternoon in the coming weeks for this debate.</P>
    <P>Senator Ridge inquired about the progress of the review group on censorship laws. I will pass on her inquiry to the Minister for Justice, Equality and Law Reform. Senator Coghlan called for a debate on Aer Rianta. I do not have a difficulty with that request. Senator Lydon called for a debate on the United Nations. This is a worthwhile request and I will make time available for such a debate.</P>
    <P>Senator O'Dowd asked for a debate on disability services. He has gone next door to County Meath and made a request to the Minister for the Environment and Local Government.</P>
    <Speaker pid="FergusODowdFG" hpid="Mr. O'Dowd Mr. O'Dowd">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Dowd</NameTxt>
      <P>The attention to Meath is heartening.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DonnieCassidyFF" hpid="Mr. Cassidy Mr. Cassidy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cassidy</NameTxt>
      <P>I will be pleased to ask his next door neighbour, the Minister, to come to the House for a debate on the matter.</P>
      <P>Senator Leonard called for a debate on health and children and I will pass on her views on this serious issue to the Minister for Health and Children.</P>
      <P>Senator John Cregan and Senator Glynn called for a debate with the Minister for Health and Children on smoking and the pending legislation in that regard. The fire regulations governing public places, such as pubs and hotels, where people smoke should ensure that proper ventilation systems are in place. This matter should be addressed as a matter of urgency. I will make time available for a debate on it in the coming weeks.</P>
      <P>As the national holiday on St. Patrick's Day approaches, Senator Glynn called for a debate on the Irish language. I will be pleased to make time available for such a discussion.</P>
      <P>Order of Business agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Comhairle Bill, 1999:" RHead="Second Stage">
    <Title>Comhairle Bill, 1999: Second Stage.</Title>
    <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That the Bill be now read a Second Time.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="DermotAhern" hpid="Mr. D. Ahern Mr. D. Ahern">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Social, Community and Family Affairs (Mr. D. Ahern)</NameTxt>
      <P>I am pleased to present the Comhairle Bill to the House. The Bill provides for the establishment of a new organisation, Comhairle, to combine the National Social Services Board with certain disability support functions of the National Rehabilitation Board. The proposal is one of a series of measures being undertaken by the Government to mainstream the provision of services for people with disabilities.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The Government's Action Plan for the Millennium recognises disability as one of the most important social challenges facing us today. It includes as stated priorities implementation of <Col N="445" /> the commission's report and achieving greater equality for people with disabilities. My colleague, the Minister of State at the Department of Justice, Equality and Law Reform, has specific responsibility for disability issues and is co-ordinating the Government's programme in implementing the commission's report across a range of Departments.</P>
    <P>Since taking office the Government has taken a number of significant steps in promoting equal opportunities for people with disabilities. The establishment of the National Disability Authority on a statutory basis through the National Disability Authority Act and the setting up of an interim board represent a significant step forward. The Bill to establish Comhairle is a further significant measure in the mainstreaming process.</P>
    <P>Comhairle will be the mainstream support agency for information services for all people, including those with disabilities. It is part of the overall Government programme aimed at ensuring that people with disabilities are treated equally by all service providers. The primary responsibility for this rests with the service providers themselves but the NDA will have a key role in developing standards, monitoring progress and promoting awareness at all levels. Comhairle's complementary role will relate specifically to information services as it seeks to ensure that all individuals, including those with disabilities, have access to information, advice and advocacy of a high standard.</P>
    <P>I wish to review some of the more important initiatives in relation to people with disabilities. With regard to legislation, important advances have been made on two fronts. Last June, the Employment Equality Act, 1998, was enacted. This legislation outlaws discrimination on grounds of disability in gaining access to employment and advancing in employment. It also gives protection to employees in the public and private sectors as well as to applicants for employment and training.</P>
    <P>The Equal Status Bill, 1999, which is currently going through its final stages in the Dáil, prohibits discrimination on a number of grounds, including disability, and deals with discrimination outside the employment area, including education, provision of goods and services, accommodation and disposal of property.</P>
    <P>In addition, the Government has provided substantial funding during the past two years in developing services for those suffering from a mental or physical disability. In the review of the programme for Government, it is recognised that these services must now be developed at a faster rate and the Government has given a firm commitment to provide substantial additional funding to address this shortfall in services. Key priorities will include the development of services for people with physical and sensory disabilities and a comprehensive disability strategy.</P>
    <P>The establishment of Comhairle follows from recommendations made by an establishment group set up by the Minister for Justice, Equality <Col N="446" /> and Law Reform in November 1997 and asked by Government to develop detailed proposals for a new infrastructure for disability issues and to consider the most appropriate future location of departmental responsibility for the functions of the National Rehabilitation Board. The group reported to Government in June last year. The Government adopted its report, Building a Future Together, and gave approval for the implementation of its recommendations.</P>
    <P>People with disabilities wish to be treated the same as their fellow citizens by having services delivered to them by the mainstream agencies, that is to say, the same agency that provides the particular service to the rest of the community. This represents a significant change of approach. In the past the State addressed disability issues primarily from a medical perspective. Responsibility for services to people with disabilities was placed, therefore, with the Department of Health and Children which provided many of the services through the NRB. The mainstreaming approach now proposed is not intended to replace such measures but to operate in parallel with them. In line with this principle, the group also recommended a number of administrative measures which involves the relocation of the functions currently performed by the NRB.</P>
    <P>One of the key elements in the proposed arrangements recommended by the establishment group was the setting up of the National Disability Authority. The authority will be the central focus of the Government's approach to the provision of services to people with disabilities. Its main function will be to develop standards in services provided to people with disabilities and to conduct independent monitoring of such services. It will not be a service providing agency but will work in close co-operation with service providers in the voluntary and statutory sectors. An interim board has been established and it is planned to have the new authority up and running within the next few months.</P>
    <P>In line with this mainstreaming approach, the Government has decided that vocational training and employment services for people with disabilities will be provided by FÁS operating under the Department of Enterprise, Trade and Employment. This will represent a major step in integrating people with disabilities into the workforce and enabling them to achieve independence and choice. Similarly, the information services for those with disabilities currently provided by the NRB will, under the provisions of this Bill, be provided through Comhairle. A number of services will be attached to other Departments, such as the audiology service, which will be provided by the Department of Health and Children through the health boards.</P>
    <P>The establishment group is continuing its work towards implementing the new administrative and institutional arrangements for the NDA and the mainstreaming of services. It is working closely with management and staff of the NRB and the relevant Departments and agencies. A <Col N="447" /> target date of the end of March next is now envisaged for full implementation of this series of measures which also involves a transfer of current NRB resources to the various Departments and agencies, including Comhairle.</P>
    <P>The main purpose of the Bill is the setting up of the new organisation, Comhairle, to ensure that individuals have access to accurate, comprehensive and clear information, advice and advocacy services on the full range of social services. The provision of information is an essential element of the relationship between social service providers and the people who use their services. This particular aspect of the service may not have been given the attention it deserved in the past. However, I am pleased to say that administrators are now much more aware of the needs of their customers in this regard.</P>
    <P>The development and delivery of social services is a complex task at the best of times. Schemes and supports are designed to meet the needs of people, individuals and families in a wide variety of circumstances and it is, therefore, necessary to ensure that the supports are broadly based and flexible enough to address their needs. The downside is that they can often be difficult to understand and perhaps even more difficult to access, particularly where the benefits required are administered by more than one Department or agency. In these circumstances, the challenge is to ensure that people have access to information and advice, at local level, which is clear, accurate and comprehensive. There is, of course, an onus on Departments to provide information and advice directly on their services and an expectation that this would be broad enough to guide people towards related services provided by other agencies. Senators will agree that we have seen significant improvements in this regard in recent times.</P>
    <P>However, the ownership of information is not vested in the statutory services alone, nor should it ever be. Independent sources of information can invariably offer a far more flexible and comprehensive service than any single arm of Government. It is extremely important that people have a choice in this regard and it is clear that, in many cases, they prefer to deal with an independent organisation either as an alternative to the statutory services or in preparation for claiming their rights and entitlements.</P>
    <P>For many years, the NSSB has provided resources to the independent information and advice giving sector as well as to the statutory sector. The NSSB transferred from the Department of Health and Children to my Department a few years ago. This was seen as a first step towards strengthening and developing the independent information sector. Since then the NSSB has embarked on a strategy of significantly upgrading the support it provides for independent and statutory information providers' centres. For example, it currently registers and supports a network of 85 independent Citizens Information Centres <Col N="448" /> throughout the country which provide a free, confidential and impartial information service to members of the public. This involves 35 key full-time centres which are supplemented by 50 part-time and outreach centres.</P>
    <P>The NSSB has also developed a computerised database, citizens information database, which is a comprehensive, user-friendly source of information on social services. It has become one of the mainstays of many information giving organisations throughout the country. Many Senators will be familiar with the monthly information bulletin, <i>Relate,</i> which provides current information from a variety of sources in an easily readable form. In addition, the board has over the years, provided a wide range of services to the voluntary social service sector. Its strategy in this area includes the development of a range of services to support this sector in the areas of information, training management and organisational supports.</P>
    <P>The National Rehabilitation Board currently operates 18 centres which provide, as part of their remit, information, advice and advocacy services to people with disabilities. These centres are located in the larger towns throughout the country and distribute a range of information on services in a variety of formats to people with disabilities. Some of the larger centres have a display range of technical aids for those with disabilities.</P>
    <P>The Bill is divided into three parts. Part 1, comprising sections 1 to 5, contains standard and technical provisions. Part 2 provides for the functions of the new organisation and requirements relating to the members of the board, its chief executive and staff. Part 3 includes provisions arising from the dissolution of the National Social Services Board. I will explain some of the more important provisions.</P>
    <P>Section 7 provides for the functions of Comhairle. The principal function will be to ensure that individuals have access to accurate, comprehensive and clear information, advice and advocacy on the full range of social services and are referred to such services. To date this function has been discharged by the NSSB and the NRB in a variety of ways. The first priority for Comhairle will be to ensure that there will be no disruption of services. An important responsibility for it will be to assist and support people, including those with disabilities, to understand their needs of the broad range of social services and to help them identify the most suitable options available to them. It will assist them in securing their entitlement to services by referring them to the appropriate agency or service provider.</P>
    <P>In this context, I should mention that Comhairle will have responsibility for continuing the provision of information and advice on assistive technology for people with disabilities. This latter service is currently provided by the NRB through some of its main centres. This involves information and advice on technical aids and options for people with disabilities and providing up to <Col N="449" /> date information on new technological developments. Comhairle will also continue to perform a number of functions which are currently discharged by the NSSB. These include promoting access to information by working with other organisations in the voluntary and statutory sectors, contributing to the development of social policy through feedback from the users and providers of information and supporting voluntary organisations which deliver social services by providing a range of services on information, training and organisational development support.</P>
    <P>The NSSB currently operates an effective training and development service which delivers a general training programme to the whole range of organisations in the social services sector, including community information centres and organisations dealing with people with disabilities. These include courses on basic information and interpersonal skills required for the delivery of a quality information service. In 1998 alone, 1,500 people working in the area of social services received training from the NSSB. I have no doubt this service will be further developed by the board of Comhairle.</P>
    <P>Section 8 requires Comhairle to prepare and submit to the Minister strategic plans relating to its objectives and strategies. The first three year strategic plan will be completed within six months of establishment day and will lay the foundations for the medium-term development of the organisation and its services. The full integration of the various functions and operations of the NSSB and the NRB components of the organisation will be its initial goal. I will be asking the board to give particular attention in its initial stage to the issue of accessibility of its services and premises and the development of appropriate training for all staff and service providers in addressing the information needs of people with disabilities.</P>
    <P>In the recent budget I provided an extra £750,000 towards the new organisation to allow it develop. Since I became Minister the NSSB budget has been dramatically increased in recognition of the fact that it would be taking on these additional responsibilities.</P>
    <P>Section 9 provides for the membership of the board which will comprise 20 members including a chairperson. The board will include five members representative of people with disabilities nominated by the Minister for Justice, Equality and Law Reform, an elected member of staff and a representative from my Department.</P>
    <P>Last November, I appointed a new board to the NSSB. In anticipation of the establishment of the new organisation I extended the membership of that board from 15 to 20 members and included five members representative of people with disabilities who were nominated by my colleague the Minister for Justice, Equality and Law Reform. This board is acting as the interim board of Comhairle and is currently working closely with the establishment group and my Department on the practical arrangements involved in the pro<Col N="450" /> posed merger of both agencies. On establishment day, the board will become the first board of Comhairle. The section also deals with the terms of office of the members of the board who shall be appointed for a maximum period of three years.</P>
    <P>Section 13 provides for the appointment of a chief executive of Comhairle who shall be appointed by the board. The main functions of the chief executive will be to administer the affairs of Comhairle. Section 14 provides for the appointment of staff of Comhairle.</P>
    <P>Sections 20 to 23 are standard provisions covering grants and the accounts and audit of the new organisation. Comhairle will be funded mainly by the Exchequer through an annual grant from my Department's Vote. The necessary resources will be drawn from those currently available to the NSSB and a transfer of funds from the Vote of the Department of Health and Children to my Department in relation to the current NRB services. The issue of additional resources will be examined in the context of the board's three year strategic plan to be prepared immediately following its establishment.</P>
    <P>Section 24 provides for the submission by the board of an annual report to the Minister and for the laying of each such report before each House of the Oireachtas.</P>
    <P>Sections 27 to 32 deal with the dissolution of the National Social Services Board and the transfer of the staff, assets and liabilities of the board to Comhairle.</P>
    <P>The Government is committed to achieving greater equality for people with disabilities. Under its new mainstreaming approach to service provision the Government aims to ensure that people with disabilities are treated equally, have access to all services, including employment and training, and to comprehensive and clear information on their entitlements on the same basis as provided to the rest of society.</P>
    <P>I express my gratitude to the NSSB for the work it has carried out since 1984 in developing an independent information sector and to the NRB for its work over the last 30 years in providing a dedicated service to people with disabilities. I am confident that the staff from both organisations, who will transfer to Comhairle, will continue to provide excellent standards of service for all people, including those with disabilities.</P>
    <P>While I commend the Bill to the House I look forward to Senators' comments. A good debate took place in the Dáil and I have no doubt Senators will add to it.</P>
    <Speaker pid="ThereseRidge" hpid="Mrs. Ridge Mrs. Ridge">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Ridge</NameTxt>
      <P>I read the Dáil debate with great interest and noted its contents. I will approach this Bill in a positive manner and I hope the Minister will take my comments on board. In acknowledging the proposed new authority, which arises from the merger of the National Social Services Board and the transfer of certain functions of the National Rehabilitation Board, I pay tribute to the invaluable contributions of the two bodies. I <Col N="451" /> have no doubt the proud record of the staff of the NSSB and the NRB will be continued in the new authority which proposes to mainstream services for people with disability. I love the word &ldquo;mainstreaming&rdquo;&ndash; it conveys many positive ideas but I often wonder how it works.</P>
      <P>The main service provided for the clients of Comhairle will be &ldquo;to empower and enable people with disabilities to achieve and exercise their economic, social, political and civil rights&rdquo;. These are noble proposals and excellent goals. One could not be opposed to them. Is this authority's remit broad enough to achieve equality and enhanced quality of life for our citizens who deserve the best but who, year after year, come out on the wrong side of the equation? In saying that I am conscious of the failure of us all until now to take on board our duty in a much more comprehensive manner.</P>
      <P>In noting the advocacy and advice services for the disabled I suggest there should be a strong component of advice and information for the general public whose lack of knowledge about and, in some cases, total lack of interest in their disabled fellow citizens is all too obvious. I give as an example my experience as a former teacher in the service of the disabled. My duties were the same as those of any other teacher. I had special responsibility for the social education of teenage students with a mild to moderate learning disability, living at home and well able to access their place of work, training or learning. Our efforts to enhance their social skills and widen their experiences were difficult to achieve because of the attitude of the public. I enrolled the students in the local public library because their literacy levels were sufficient to enable them avail of the books in the library. We did supermarket shopping, clothing shopping, used public transport and went to the theatre and cinema. The rudeness and ignorance of a large number of the public was astounding. It is assumed that because people look different, they are different. They were stared at and commented upon.</P>
      <P>One of Comhairle's objectives should be to educate the public to have respect for the difference, physical and mental, of the disabled and to realise how negative and frustrating their attitudes can be in these sensitive areas. Some walls have come down but the mental wall is still in place, particularly with some employers.</P>
      <P>I have not had time to absorb the Minister's contribution today but I read his contribution in the other House. I am still anxious about the volunteer staff who previously manned the Citizens Information Centres. Will there be an ongoing role for them? Given that 10% of the population have some form of disability what is the position with regard to the accessibility of the buildings? I presume that before the service comes into operation all buildings used will be accessible.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I wish to inquire about telephone and Internet services. I appreciate the Minister referred to information technology training. However, what <Col N="452" /> I am concerned about &ndash; I am sure the Minister is sick of hearing this &ndash; is the intricacies of the social welfare system for those who do not have learning difficulties or are not disabled. One would need a PhD to work it out. I acknowledge there are experts in the social welfare field who are not very expert in other regards but who know their way around the system. Will people using the Comhairle services be given information by telephone? Will it be readily accessible? Will it be available on the Internet? How will rural people who cannot access a centre or use the telephone get the information? Information must be available within a reasonably short period after a written or telephone inquiry is made.</P>
    <P>The service should advertise on radio and television because many people do not read leaflets that come through their door. In Dublin it is not uncommon to receive four advertising leaflets a day. Leaflets sent out in a mailshot could get lost. Radio advertising of Comhairle's services would be desirable, especially for the visually disabled. I presume there will be a Braille section for the visually impaired. The Minister can tell me about that in his response.</P>
    <P>I also presume there will be one-stop-shops which will have the information required by the caller readily available, either immediately or within a reasonably short period, unlike the old system under which it sometimes took a month to get an answer via about ten Departments. I acknowledge the great improvement in the Minister's Department where there is now much greater ease of access at every level. However, I want the disabled to have perfect access, if possible.</P>
    <P>Given that 60% of the disabled are employed, will suitably qualified disabled people be eligible to work in the new service? The Minister stated in the Dáil on 18 November 1999 that &ldquo;for too long our fellow citizens with disabilities have had to suffer grave and outrageous inequalities&rdquo;. It would be a grave and outrageous inequality if employment were not provided in this service for people with particular disabilities who would be suitably qualified and able to work.</P>
    <P>While recognising the positive aspects of the Bill, I ask the Minister to reconsider worker participation on the board. There should be a representative on the board from the voluntary sector, which has worked so willingly for so many years with the NSSB and the citizens information centres. I would like the voluntary sector, which is such an invaluable resource to any community, to be retained. I presume those people can be retrained, if necessary, and their expertise and local knowledge used to the advantage of the new service. Ireland has had a very long and successful history of co-operation between the statutory and voluntary sectors. There is a workable interdependence between State and voluntary agencies and it is desirable that that should continue.</P>
    <P>I hope Comhairle will work. The function of Comhairle will be to provide advice, information <Col N="453" /> and advocacy. I am very confused about the advocacy aspect in that it is not envisaged in the Bill that the service will include the provision of an advocate for a disabled person in a court case. Perhaps the Minister might clarify the advocacy remit.</P>
    <P>I wish to refer to some aspects which this service will not provide. We still do not have proper wheelchair facilities on trains. I saw the Minister in the Distinguished Visitors' Gallery when that was mentioned on the Order of Business today. Only a very small number of buses have low floors. I welcome that 150 of these buses are on order, which I gather will all be allocated to Dublin. I cannot believe that in February 2000 the visually impaired must still travel in the dark on suburban DART trains and buses with no voice-over facilities.</P>
    <P>The provision of advocacy, information and advice is most commendable. However, without action and funding, this new body could be in danger of just paying lip service. The full integration of the disabled is not just desirable, it is their right. I want to be extremely positive and welcome the Bill. I look forward to the first annual progress report of Comhairle. I look forward equally to what I hope will be the Minister's open-mindedness in taking on board amendments proposed because they will not be tabled to score points but to approach this in the best possible way from my experience.</P>
    <P>How long have I spoken for?</P>
    <Speaker pid="PaschalMooney" hpid="Mr. Mooney Mr. Mooney">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman (Mr. Mooney)</NameTxt>
      <P>The Senator has adequate time left to expound her philosophy.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThereseRidge" hpid="Mrs. Ridge Mrs. Ridge">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Ridge</NameTxt>
      <P>I will willingly give the remainder of my time to my esteemed colleagues because I have nothing further to say.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MairinQuill" hpid="Miss Quill Miss Quill">
      <NameTxt>Miss Quill</NameTxt>
      <P>That is a very honest statement. We would have lovely short speeches if everyone did that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Acting Chairman Acting Chairman">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman</NameTxt>
      <P>As I am sure the Senator is aware, Senators do not have to fill the amount of time they are allocated.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThereseRidge" hpid="Mrs. Ridge Mrs. Ridge">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Ridge</NameTxt>
      <P>It is the quality, not the quantity, that is important.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Acting Chairman Acting Chairman">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman</NameTxt>
      <P>Absolutely. That is the tradition in this House. The Senator is following in a very proud tradition.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="AnnLeonard" hpid="Ms Leonard Ms Leonard">
      <NameTxt>Ms Leonard</NameTxt>
      <P>I welcome the Minister to the debate on another important Bill, which is part of the Government's legislative programme to mainstream the services for people with disabilities. This Bill will set up the new statutory authority through the combination of the National Social Services Board and certain aspects of the National Rehabilitation Board. As the Minister said, this is another step in a series of measures by the Government to, first, mainstream the pro<Col N="454" /> vision of services for people with disabilities and, second, make these services more user friendly and accessible. I pay tribute to the staff of the National Social Services Board and the National Rehabilitation Board who have provided an excellent service within their remit over the past 30 years.</P>
      <P>It is important to outline the steps taken by the Government to improve the lot of people with disabilities. As the Minister said, the Government has already introduced legislation in this area. The Employment Equality Act, 1998, aims to eliminate discrimination against disabled people in terms of employment. The Equal Status Bill, which has already passed through this House and is now in the Dáil, aims to eliminate discrimination in all other aspects of life. One of the most important pieces of legislation was that setting up the National Disability Authority which will, through time, develop and monitor standards in the services provided to people with disabilities.</P>
      <P>This Bill will act as a foundation stone upon which the rest of the equality legislation will be built. Legislation to protect people with disabilities has been long awaited. As the Minister said, the ultimate aim is to mainstream services for people with disabilities because unfortunately they have been dealt with in various different categories, including health, and generally along the margins of society. This brings them all together.</P>
      <P>The recent National Disability Authority Act, 1999 states that a person with a disability has the right to achieve and to exercise their economic, social, political and civil rights. However, if people with disabilities do not have access to information on their entitlements and the services available, then we are immediately disabling them further and preventing them from achieving their full potential in society. This Bill aims to deal with accessibility of information. I listened to the Second Stage debate in the other House where a number of Deputies spoke about the lack of vision of the Bill. The Bill sets up a board, the vision and functions of which are clearly outlined. One establishes what can be achieved in the short term and develops vision through time. The functions of the board are very clearly outlined in the Bill as being to directly provide independent information, advice and advocacy services so as to ensure that individuals have access to accurate, comprehensive and clear information relating to social services and are referred to the relevant services. That speaks for itself.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Unfortunately, many people, including those with disabilities, are unaware or unsure of their entitlements. They try one avenue to access information and if they are unsuccessful they very often give up their search. This Bill states that it shall be one of the functions of the board to support individuals, in particular those with disabilities, in identifying and understanding their needs and options and in accessing their entitlements to social services. For an able-bodied individual, to be sent from one agency to another in search of advice or basic information can be a very frustrat<Col N="455" /> ing and demeaning experience. People with disabilities also have their pride. To a disabled person who is sent from one agency to another in search of basic information, any obstacle which would be a molehill to an able-bodied person seems like a mountain. To have to go from one office to another in trying to access the various services may involve financial cost or physical inconvenience.</P>
    <P>I am delighted to see regulations stating that all public buildings now being built are to be wheelchair accessible. If the NSSB and the NRB amalgamate and existing citizen information centres are to be used as part of their personalised one-to-one assistance service, action should be taken very quickly to make these offices more user friendly and more wheelchair accessible. Some of our citizens' information centres are not the most accommodating places, particularly for an individual who is disabled.</P>
    <P>The amalgamation of any agencies generates a certain amount of uncertainty for those involved. There is some uncertainty among those involved in the citizens' information centres as to their role following the amalgamation of the NSSB and the NRB. On Committee Stage, there may be an opportunity to discuss their role following this amalgamation.</P>
    <P>A number of these citizens' information centres depend largely on volunteers. To provide the information and advice services envisaged in this Bill, it will be necessary not only to recruit more volunteers but to provide special training facilities for them so that they can deal adequately with the needs of people with disabilities. Anyone who has ever dealt with people who are disabled knows it is important to be focused on their needs.</P>
    <P>This Bill also states that one of the functions of the board is to promote public awareness of the social services. I agree with Senator Ridge that not only public awareness of the social services is needed but public awareness of people with disabilities. Unfortunately through the years, people with a disability have been, as Senator Ridge said, stared at or looked down upon. We have all witnessed someone talking over the head of someone in a wheelchair to whomever is accompanying them. Increasing public awareness, whether through literature or the national media, would contribute to changing the mindset of able-bodied people. When talking about disability, ignorance disables the thinking of those who are able-bodied.</P>
    <P>I referred to the volunteers in the citizens' information centres. Centres in rural areas, in particular, are dependent on volunteers who are already giving out information required by people with disabilities. In line with this Bill, the volunteers must be kept fully informed on any changes and any entitlements which may become available from the Department. Information must be easy to read and understand.</P>
    <P>I thank the Minister for his input to developing <Col N="456" /> the customer-friendly service provided by the Department of Social, Community and Family Affairs. In the few years I have been a Member of the House, I have found it one of the most accommodating Departments in imparting information, returning calls and giving prompt replies. I acknowledge the customer-friendly service provided by the staff of the Department of Social, Community and Family Affairs, who have been at all times extremely helpful and informative.</P>
    <P>Five members representative of people with disabilities will be nominated to the board by the Minister. The individuals selected should represent different types of disability. The obstacles faced by an individual with, for example, impaired hearing do not compare with those faced by an individual who is wheelchair-bound. It is important that representatives of people with various disabilities should be included on this board. Very often those who are visually impaired, to whom Senator Ridge referred, or those with impaired hearing can feel much more isolated than an individual who is otherwise physically disabled. The knowledge and the expertise gained by these individuals over the years can have a huge influence on the development of social policy, which is one of the functions of this board.</P>
    <P>I recently attended a seminar on equal employment opportunities for people with disabilities. I listened to one contributor who had impaired hearing. He had worked for the same company for 11 years but had hardly spoken to a colleague, not to mention his employers, during that time. Through an initiative funded by the EU, he was asked to join a project team and it was only then that he made contact with fellow-workers. It is amazing that something as simple as sign language can open a new world to a person with a disability. We tend to think of highly technological ways of tackling disability but very often something as simple as a rudimentary knowledge of sign language or even good manners can make a great difference to an individual's life.</P>
    <P>I hope links between the board and the voluntary agencies will strengthen. The board can only be effective if it is aware and conscious of the experiences of people who are involved with disability. It is essential that the new body works in co-operation with the voluntary bodies and that there is a two-way line of communication. Not only should the board impart clear, concise and accurate information but the problems and difficulties of people with disabilities and anomalies in the system must be relayed to the board and the concerns of people using the services highlighted.</P>
    <P>It is important that we refer to the report of the Commission on the Status of People with Disabilities. This report dealt with a wide range of topics and has been a catalyst for many changes. One of its recommendations was that a single network be set up to give information, advice and support. Information is the key to equality and <Col N="457" /> independence. It must be available to all people and co-ordinated so that it can be used by all.</P>
    <P>The aim of the Bill is to mainstream the services for people with disabilities. We have moved a long way from the time when disability was seen as a health problem. Perhaps we must move further and change our mindset with regard to people with disabilities. Many people with disabilities still feel disadvantaged when trying to access information and their entitlements to social services. This Bill will empower those who feel powerless. It will ensure equality of access to information and we all know that the best way to empower people is to provide information which is accurate, comprehensive and easily accessible. This Bill will ensure that service providers are empowered with this knowledge so that they, in turn, can empower those who use the services.</P>
    <P>I thank the Minister for bringing forward so much legislation. It will take some time to put all the wheels in motion but given time, this legislation will make a great difference to the lives of people with disabilities. Many people with disabilities have said that the Minster of State with special responsibility for people with disabilities, Deputy Mary Wallace, has worked extremely hard to highlight the issues associated with disability. It would be remiss not to acknowledge that fact.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MaryHenry" hpid="Dr. Henry Dr. Henry">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Henry</NameTxt>
      <P>I welcome the Minister to the House and I welcome the Bill, which is a splendid initiative. We have spoken of changing our mindset. I would be very grateful if Comhairle would begin by changing the mindset of the Department of Finance. I have had the gravest difficulty during the past few years regarding tax concessions for disabled drivers and passengers. If any people deserve advocates, they certainly do. I hope Comhairle will try to get something done about the serious difficulties they experience.</P>
      <P>We are inclined to think of people in wheelchairs as the only people with disabilities. A large number of people have other sorts of disabilities and many are doing the best they can to get on with their lives and not have to use a wheelchair. The Minister has stressed the need to integrate people into vocational training and employment services, but it is essential that people are able to get to training centres and to take advantage of employment opportunities. Senator Leonard was quite right in stressing the difficulties of rural people. Some of the most tragic cases where tax concessions have been refused have involved rural people.</P>
      <P>With any luck blind people do not have to use wheelchairs but they find it impossible to get tax concessions regarding transport, and lack of mobility keeps them from taking advantage of training schemes. The medical criteria for tax concessions are long out of date. They were established 30 years ago when disability was described on the basis of medical condition rather than on the degree of a person's mobility.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Probably because I am a doctor many people <Col N="458" /> have written to me about this topic. I had one of the most embarrassing experiences of my life when my medical colleagues on the National Rehabilitation Appeals Board asked some of the people making appeals if they would allow me to sit in on some of the cases which were being heard. Every one of them said they would be delighted for me to do so. I saw one after another severely disabled person being refused tax concessions for mobility because they did not fulfil the very narrow criteria. The Minister is well aware of these criteria. There are about six different categories, one of which is for people who have lost two legs and one arm. Would it not be a miracle for a person with such a disability to get out from under the blankets in the morning and try to tackle life at all, not to mention apply for a tax concession? What really distressed me was the presence of so many young people who were desperate to get training or access to jobs.</P>
    <P>Let me give some examples. A man in his thirties, an engineer, had a stroke and the firm he worked for was prepared to continue to employ him because his was a desk job. However, it was not very well paid and he was not in a position to get tax concessions, which are extremely good, so that he could continue with his job. He was, therefore, forced to stay at home. A farmer who was about 60 years of age applied for a tax concession so that his wife could drive him. He was largely a stock farmer and he felt that if his wife could drive him he could continue farming and his son would not have to cut short his course at agricultural college and come home. A young woman with very severe rheumatoid arthritis was not in a position to get a tax concession. She was severely disabled, having arthritis in her hands, feet and spine, yet she wanted to continue working. The work was not highly paid enough for her to provide transport from where she lived and her only hope was to get a special car and good tax concessions to go with it. I could go on. I know of a couple who have a severely handicapped child who also has drop epilepsy. Their child did not need to be in a wheelchair but she had to wear a helmet to prevent her injuring her head when she would fall. She was not a suitable person to take on the DART or the bus. Even though the couple could not afford a car they were refused a tax concession. The general practitioner who was on the appeals board at that time told me that he did not know if he could continue because he found it distressing to refuse people like that. I hope that Comhairle would be in a position to see, if there is no money in the large kitty on Merrion Road, that we could have at least a graded allowance.</P>
    <P>At long last parking permits are given more generously. Not all the disabled parking slots are taken up because permits are given more generously. People are responsible about using them and only do so when it is necessary. I live near one of the Departments on Mespil Road and every morning I see two people avail of designated car spaces and go into work within the <Col N="459" /> Department. Would they be able to continue with their lives if we did not have a scheme like that? No, they would not. It is not just the financial status this scheme gives them but the tremendous sense of social inclusion, which is what the Minister wants in this Bill. I hope the first letter Comhairle receives will be from me stating that I expect it to have done something about this matter as rapidly as possible. If the largesse does not extend to increasing the number of tax concessions it can give, surely it can have graded concessions. This would ensure that people in a serious position who want to continue their studies or at work could have someone to ask the Department of Finance to alter the position. The narrow medical criteria have been in existence for over 30 years but now there has been a total change in our views on mobility. It could ask for some leeway to be allowed so that people can go about their lives in the way in which I suggest this Bill wants and requires.</P>
    <P>Blind people have no hope of qualifying and surely they are some of the most important people. However much we may think it at times when we are out on the roads, blind people are not supposed to drive. As the Minister's speech has suggested, the whole thrust of the new Comhairle should be to try to integrate the disabled into society. This is one of the most practical propositions and a way it could start.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MairinQuill" hpid="Miss Quill Miss Quill">
      <NameTxt>Miss Quill</NameTxt>
      <P>I welcome the Minister to the House. I also welcome this Bill, which gives all of us good grounds for optimism. It is another milestone on the road to creating equal opportunities and fair play for people with disabilities. In recent times a good deal of progress has been made, much of it by the Minister, through his Department, and by the Minister of State, Deputy Mary Wallace. That is widely acknowledged and it is only fair that credit be given.</P>
      <P>This Bill is another piece in the jigsaw that will help to enable people who were in the past classified as disabled. A corpus of legislation is being put in place which will give disabled persons acknowledgement before the law. That is to be welcomed and is as it ought to be. However, those of us who work on the ground know from experience that having equal status in law is not enough. All sorts of provisions must be made to enable that equal status to be exercised in full. The setting up of Comhairle with the functions that are being assigned to it in the context of this Bill will be a major advance in helping people with disabilities to reach their full potential and to enjoy as much equality as they can in every facet of life. That is critically important and is the way it should be in any civilised Christian country.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>While I wish the members of the incoming Comhairle good luck, I also acknowledge the work carried out by NRB members for 30 years and their advocacy at times when our thinking on disability was not as developed as it now is. Their <Col N="460" /> good work must be acknowledged. I also pay tribute to the work carried out by the National Social Services Board. Its work has not gone unnoticed.</P>
    <P>The work we are doing here is critically important for a number of reasons. It brings a new kind of coherence into the delivery and development of the services. That is important because for far too long fragmentation has had a negative effect in the identification of initiatives that ought to be taken and in the development and delivery of services. Anything that reduces fragmentation and bureaucracy is welcome and can only bring a new energy and sense of direction in the provision and delivery of services. I welcome the bringing together, mainstreaming and coherence that will accrue from the establishment of Comhairle with its brief as set out in this Bill.</P>
    <P>I am particularly impressed with and optimistic about the idea of making information fully available through an independent source no matter where the person seeking it lives, whether it is in urban or rural Ireland. There is no doubt knowledge is power. Knowledge on its own is an enabling factor. Making information available quickly and in accordance with the most up to date technology is a minimum provision. It is one that will be made in this Bill.</P>
    <P>A good deal of emphasis has been placed on the provision of transport and the removal of obstacles to access, whether it is access to education, work or the health services. It ought to be our aim to adopt a uniform approach to public transport and the provision of parking permits and cars suitable for use by disabled drivers. We should be working to develop and to increase these provisions. One of the Minister's colleagues drew attention to the fact of someone in a wheelchair not being able to get access to a railway carriage other than the dining carriage. If that is crowded by hungry commuters where does that leave someone in a wheelchair? That is a minimum provision. It is unthinkable when new rolling stock is being ordered or when buses or other public service vehicles are being designed that comprehensive provision is not made for people who use wheelchairs or crutches or people with lesser forms of mobility. It is unthinkable that proper provision would not be made because that is the key to enabling many other things to happen.</P>
    <P>I am glad reference has been made to the role that FÁS can play in skilling and upskilling people with disabilities. The fact that people have disabilities does not mean they do not have a range of intelligence and capacities which if properly nurtured could enable them to become part of the workforce. That is the ultimate form of independence. It has been said many times that the greatest weapon against poverty and disability is a job, the ability to earn a living and have a bob in one's pocket. With proper training and the provision of transport there are large numbers of people who could go out to work.</P>
    <P>There is strong emphasis nowadays on the need <Col N="461" /> to conduct manpower surveys. In different areas there are manpower shortages. We should look to the disabled with their undeveloped capacities to become full and productive members of the economy. I think in particular of those who are deaf but who can communicate fully with one another through sign language. There is a need to put in place a cohort of interpreters to enable those who are deaf to communicate with the rest of us, to gain greater access to education and employment. This would make a difference and open doors by enabling them to perform to their full capacity at interviews and, if the need arises, to plead their case in court.</P>
    <P>Education is the key. It is painful to read that in this the first year of the new millennium about 10% of children leave primary school every year without having mastered literacy skills. Although not classed as such, this is a form of disability in the context of the challenges that confront them. It is appalling and, although it does not fall directly within the ambit of the Bill, I cannot resist mentioning it. There are others who lack numeracy skills, who cannot read their bank statements or the small print on their insurance policies. They, too, are disabled in what is now a very complex world. These matters require urgent attention.</P>
    <P>Education is the key to independent living and employment in particular. The required investment has to be made. I compliment the COPE Foundation in my home city on the extraordinary work it has done during the years, initially with limited funding although it is now well funded. The work that organisations under the umbrella of the National Rehabilitation Institute do for the disabled is extraordinarily valuable and ought to be valued, but there is scope for expansion. If the disabilities of younger people are identified early &ndash; we have enough knowledge to intervene early &ndash; they can be assisted to attain their full potential but, as Senator Henry said, there are many older people who have been involved in a car accident or who have suffered a stroke and for whom little is done. Comhairle, in which advocacy powers are being vested, should lobby to ensure they are not left out, particularly those living in small groups in rural areas. Better provision should be made for them and it is very important that they have access to education and employment.</P>
    <P>Senator Henry made an excellent point which I had intended to make. The fox had only one trick but because he knew it so well he always managed to save his bacon. I had one key point to make but I was outfoxed by Senator Henry. It relates to the criteria for establishing entitlement. She made the point very effectively and gave a number of good examples. I endorse what she said and appeal to the Minister to bring the system kicking and screaming into the 21st century. The criteria being applied are notoriously out of date. They are Dickensian and seem to be designed to exclude at a time when we preach the philosophy of inclusion. If we are serious about <Col N="462" /> enabling people to attain their full potential we must get rid of this mindset and mentality. We must not erect roadblocks but open doors as a matter of urgency. The criteria must be brought into line with current thinking and the spirit, intent and objectives of the Bill.</P>
    <P>Under the arts plan there should be greater access to the arts, not just as spectators but as participants. There is no doubt that exposure to the arts at every level is a powerful stimulant to exercise the imagination and emotions. The fact that one has a broken leg does not mean that one does not have good imagination. Those involved in the Arts Council and those who promote the arts at local authority level should be conscious of the need to open all the avenues it is possible to open for the disabled.</P>
    <P>I am glad that Comhairle will issue an annual report which will give us an opportunity to establish if the aims and objectives of this fine legislation are being realised. By having an annual debate we can maintain the energy behind the realisation of its aims and objectives. This would be of great benefit to all concerned.</P>
    <P>I commend the Minister on introducing the Bill. Its aims and objectives are highly commendable and give one good grounds for optimism. I hope all those aims and objectives will be fully realised.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JoeOToole" hpid="Mr. O'Toole Mr. O'Toole">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Toole</NameTxt>
      <P>I welcome this legislation. It is very much in line with discussions in other places, with the Government's programme as outlined in the national plan, the programme for the millennium and the demands of many groups in society, including the social and voluntary community pillars as well as those of the Irish Congress of Trade Unions during recent discussions on the Programme for Prosperity and Fairness. This fits into that milieu and advances demands in this area that little bit further. It does not bring in huge resources, but it does a lot to try to change and mould attitudes and in that sense it is very welcome. The Minister referred to the Equal Status Bill. I have some problems with that Bill, but they are very minor problems and are confined to a number of the Bill's sections. In the main it is a welcome and important Bill and I will not go into my problems with it, as this is not the place to do so.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>What I like about this Bill is that it sets about making a statement as a democracy. It sets about saying that this is how it should be and is better than all the talk about inclusion. It puts in place a structure to create a sense of inclusion, which is badly needed. It also deals with how to get people suffering from a handicap or disability &ndash; whichever is the politically correct term of the day &ndash; to access all the opportunities and experiences of life which are available to the rest of the community. More importantly, it supports those groups which are trying to ensure not only access but full participation, as access without participation is only half the journey. It aims to give full <Col N="463" /> life experience to people who would not otherwise have that opportunity.</P>
    <P>One aspect of Government policy which has been ignored in the past few years is the policy requirement of the last few Governments that a certain percentage of those employed in the public service come from a background of disability. That policy should be pushed. In my area, teaching, there are many people coming through the special education system who could well develop into good teachers if certain obstacles were taken out of their way and encouragement given to them. We should have that as an objective, but it will not happen on its own. We need some positive discrimination. That positive discrimination should be available at all levels of education, but we must set our sights high. We must ensure that those who come through the special educational service, people from a background of disability, can make their contributions in a full, affirmed and recognised way. Teaching is one area in which they could do so.</P>
    <P>In order to achieve this, certain obstacles must be removed. One crucial matter is access to and use of public transport, to which several speakers have referred. It is no longer acceptable to us as a society, particularly in the context of this Bill, to have a situation where access to the train service is restricted, confined or unavailable to less able persons. We have demanded access of taxis and buses and we should demand the same of trains, though not in a way where people must remain in their wheelchairs in the spaces between corridors, which is grossly uncomfortable. This reflects badly on us as a society. I do not want to sound pious about this &ndash; there are good reasons that this is the case, such as that we inherited it from less enlightened days &ndash; but it is important to set about the objective of sorting this out. Nothing is ever completely good enough, but at least if we were moving in the right direction and making sure that access to our trains is available to those suffering from disabilities, particularly those with mobility problems, that would be very welcome.</P>
    <P>I was very taken with the representations made to me by the blind car owners association. One might argue against their points, but they made them logically. Obviously they can never be drivers, but nonetheless they may need cars and might purchase a car which someone else can drive. Under current legislation they are not entitled to the tax refund scheme available to others and this could be solved by including the blind in that scheme. One can see that when this was first considered in 1994 people did not think of blind people owning cars. However, it is perfectly logical that if a blind person lives in a remote area, needs car transport and can afford a car, that should be supported. It is a minor matter which costs pennies in terms of the national budget and should be put forward strongly at Cabinet. I presume it is a matter for the Minister for Finance, but it should have the enthusiastic <Col N="464" /> and energetic support of the Minister for Social, Community and Family Affairs.</P>
    <P>One of the most important developments in computerisation has been that, extraordinarily, it can compensate for certain people's disabilities. We have all heard of the Christopher Nolans who could hardly communicate but suddenly found they could write books. I do not want to talk about those who emerged as geniuses &ndash; that is not what the Bill is about. I refer to ordinary people who have difficulties communicating, whether it is a matter of speech difficulty or problems with limb control. By adapting computers and electronic equipment these people can communicate successfully just like anyone else. Anybody who has ever had the extraordinarily enriching experience of watching someone in adulthood communicate for the first time or for the first time in years after an accident will recognise that it is priceless and something upon which one could not put a value. There are many examples from those in the medical profession of people in a coma for three or four years, but someone believed they could communicate, even if it was only by moving their pupils or eyelids. This in turn could be translated into electronic communication, thus allowing them to speak. This issue is hugely important and I want more research and support for it, particularly in rehabilitation centres.</P>
    <P>In the primary education sector, the policy of this and previous Governments has been to have a more inclusive, integrated approach to the primary education system for children with various disabilities. Nobody could argue against that as a proper objective, but it only works if the resources are in the school to ensure the child gets the support he or she requires. That means the State must be prepared to say: &ldquo;There is a child with a disability. What do we need to allow that person to have full access to the education system?&rdquo;  Maybe it is something as simple as widening the door jambs in the school building and changing the toilets so the child can bring a wheelchair to school. It could be that simple or something far more complicated. Either way, we should seek to ensure that this type of access is provided. This legislation will provide support to those trying to achieve these objectives. It gives recognition and affirmation to voluntary bodies which provide social services to people with disabilities, among others.</P>
    <P>The importance of the provision of independent information, advice and advocacy cannot be overstated. This is a very heartening aspect of the Bill. It is wonderful that the State is seeking to ensure independent information and representation will be available to people and that they will receive the support to which they are entitled. That is an enlightened, 21st century approach which will be welcomed by all those working on behalf of people with disabilities.</P>
    <P>Some of us will recall when Brian Crowley, MEP, was elected to this House some years ago. His election required immediate changes to be <Col N="465" /> made in the House. It was great in one way and sad in another that we waited to make those changes until one of our own Members required such facilities. It reminded me of a story told about one of the founders of the Irish Wheelchair Association who died ten years ago. He was a thorn in the side of architects and others in regard to the provision of adequate access to houses. The man, who was married, bought a new house into which he installed a ramp for his own use. He was only a few months in the house when he developed a disease and died shortly thereafter. The couple's elderly neighbours, who were lovely, helpful people, visited the house to offer their condolences to his wife and when they were leaving, one of them said, &ldquo;I suppose you'll be taking the ramp out now&rdquo;. That comment probably reflects a great deal about Irish life. Instead of providing access on the possibility that it might be required, we provide it only when it is required. We have all made changes in our offices and elsewhere. We cannot provide access all the time; there are some places in which it is not feasible to do so. We do not have to run ahead of politically correct people but we must do our best. That sometimes necessitates actions which may not be architecturally attractive. Ramps may not look particularly attractive but it is very important that they are provided.</P>
    <P>This legislation, the new national programme and the new development plan reflect a change of attitude in the direction of a more inclusive society which will provide for full access, participation and life experience for people who suffer from a disability. This is modern, caring, inclusive and necessary legislation which I welcome and support.</P>
    <Speaker pid="CamillusGlynn" hpid="Mr. Glynn Mr. Glynn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Glynn</NameTxt>
      <P>Cuirim fáilte roimh an tAire. This is very important and practical legislation which seeks to rationalise the provision of services by agencies such as the National Social Services Board and the National Rehabilitation Board. We do not want to see duplication of services and this Bill will ensure that does not occur.</P>
      <P>I pay tribute to the NSSB and NRB staff who have provided excellent services over the years to people with disabilities. The NSSB was established in 1984. Its strategy to ensure citizens had access to the highest quality information, advice and advocacy on social services was to provide a large range of resources for the support and development of the independent information and statutory sectors. Its core resource is a citizens' information database which provides information on a range of social services such as social welfare, health, income tax, etc. The database is used by more than 400 organisations which provide information services. The NSSB also developed a network of independent information centres. It registers and supports a network of 85 citizens' information centres throughout the country which provide a free, confidential and impartial service.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The Commission on the Status of People with <Col N="466" /> Disabilities recommended the establishment of a disability support service which would operate one-stop-shops for information, advice and advocacy and which would assist people with disabilities to understand and identify their needs and help negotiate appropriate provision to meet those needs.</P>
    <P>There are currently 18 disability resource centres operating under the aegis of the National Rehabilitation Board. In considering how a disability support service, as envisaged by the commission, might be provided, the establishment group adopted the following guiding principles: the disability support service should be mainstreamed as a matter of principle with no diminution in the level of services; there should not be any unnecessary duplication of services; the services should be visible and available on the high street &ndash; that is one of the most welcome provisions of this Bill; and the cost effectiveness of the support service should remain an essential prerequisite. The group, therefore, concluded that the most appropriate structure would be a new agency which would combine existing services while at the same time adequately meeting the needs of people with disabilities. In examining existing services, the establishment group considered the most appropriate merger could occur between the NRB network of information centres and the NSSB.</P>
    <P>In 1998, the Government approved the establishment of a new organisation, Comhairle, under the aegis of the Minister for Social, Community and Family Affairs which would comprise a merger between the NSSB and the NRB disability support service as proposed in the report of the establishment group. The Government also approved the appointment by the Minister for Social, Community and Family Affairs of an interim board of Comhairle and the dissolution of the NRB.</P>
    <P>It is important to point out Government commitments in this area. The Government's Action Programme for the Millennium prioritises the implementation of the recommendations of the report of the Commission on the Status of People with Disabilities and the achievement of greater equality for people with disabilities. The Government has also made significant steps through the establishment of the National Disability Authority, the setting up of an interim board of Comhairle, the Employment Equality Act, 1998, and the equal status legislation. Substantial funding has been provided by the NSSB over recent years. The figure has increased from under £3 million in 1997 to more than £5 million this year. This is a clear indication of the Government's commitment to ensuring citizens have access to the highest quality of information on a range of social services.</P>
    <P>The Minister has provided some £750,000 this year to the NSSB and towards the establishment of Comhairle. The Department provides a comprehensive information service directly to its customers in the form of leaflets and application <Col N="467" /> forms through its countrywide network of offices, public libraries and centres operating under the aegis of ICTU and the Irish National Organisation for the Unemployed. A special information booklet was distributed last October to old age pensioners and widowed pensioners outlining their full range of entitlements to social services.</P>
    <P>The benefits of Comhairle for people with disabilities will be that they will be treated the same way as their fellow citizens by having services delivered to them through mainstream agencies. They will now have access to a nationwide network of 85 citizen information centres, 11 NRB offices and over 300 other independent and voluntary information providers.</P>
    <P>I wish to refer to an issue which has been mentioned by other Senators, including Senator Leonard &ndash; the thoughtless practice of motorists who park in disabled driver spaces. This has been raised at Westmeath County Council and I am sure in many other fora. It is time we stopped talking about it. Any able-bodied person who parks in a disabled driver space should be banned from driving and have their car impounded. It is the meanest and lowest activity among motorists.</P>
    <P>As Senator O'Toole said, there are many public and health care bodies which do not have adequate facilities for disabled persons. It is also interesting to note that, as Senator Henry mentioned, people think a disabled person is someone with a white cane, in a wheelchair or on crutches. There are many forms of disability, all of which must be catered for adequately.</P>
    <P>I have a great deal to say on this Bill. However, at this stage everything has been covered very well and repetition would be a waste of time. I am enthusiastic about this Bill because it will merge services which were provided by various agencies. The one-stop-shop concept will provide the optimum service to people with disabilities. The high street facility is a shining beacon of this Bill, which I welcome. I commend it to the House.</P>
    <Speaker pid="DermotAhern" hpid="Mr. D. Ahern Mr. D. Ahern">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Social, Community and Family Affairs (Mr. D. Ahern)</NameTxt>
      <P>I thank Senators for their excellent contributions, which I will take on board. Many Senators raised the issue of disabled drivers, which is not my direct responsibility. However, I share their frustration as I have experienced similar cases. There was a good discussion on the issue at a recent parliamentary party meeting. The Minister for Finance has set up a review of the criteria. It is surprising that they are so restrictive. They were changed a number of years ago to make it easier to qualify, or so we thought. However, it now seems to be harder to qualify. The issue is on the agenda of the Minister for Finance who has to take many factors into consideration as it is not simple.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I will deal with a number of issues raised by Senators. The monitoring of quality of service and promotion of awareness is the responsibility of the NDA which has overall responsibility in this area, although the primary responsibility <Col N="468" /> rests with the service providers. The NDA will monitor the issue. As regards my commitment to ensuring that the transition to the new body is as seamless as possible, all I can do is ensure the structures are in place and that the new board knows exactly what is required, as I am sure is the case, knowing the members. It is also my responsibility to provide adequate funding. In 1997, the funding for the NSSB was £2.97 million. In 2000, it will be £5.2 million, which represents a significant increase of almost 100%.</P>
    <P>Senator Quill referred to making equality a reality, not just a legal provision. This is a responsibility not only of Comhairle but of all Departments and agencies. As I said, the NDA will monitor this. Senators Ridge and Quill referred to telecommunications and access to the Internet. A pilot freephone information service was launched in Cork last December. Depending on how that progresses, we hope to expand it nationwide. We will also endeavour to ensure that the new organisation will provide access to computerised information through the Internet in the not too distant future. One of the main reasons for the increase in funding is to expand the new computer information network throughout citizens' information centres. I assure Senators we will be using every form of technology to allow Comhairle achieve this.</P>
    <P>Advocacy was also raised in the other House. It will not include legal representation, nor should it. A free legal aid service is available if there is a difficulty. I have some knowledge of CICs as I gave free legal advice to its forerunner in my area, which was the initiative of a number of newly qualified solicitors. At that time there were no free legal advice centres. If the CICs gave free legal advice and then provided advocacy in court, it would dilute their capacity to carry out general work. They will provide advice and advocacy as regards dealing with Government Departments, agencies and other providers of service but they will not give legal representation which is, in effect, the responsibility of the Legal Aid Board.</P>
    <P>One of the main aims of the board's new strategic plan, when implemented, is to make physical access to buildings as easy as possible. We will be taking on 11 of the NRB offices which are accessible, more or less, to disabled people. Many of the 35 main CICs are accessible, although not many of the 50 others are at this stage. Obviously, this is one of the future tasks for the board. Physical access and access by telephone and technology is being looked at. The board and the Department are aware of their importance.</P>
    <P>There is a large voluntary and community sector representation on the board. It is estimated that approximately eight people are involved in other areas of the voluntary sector. The whole idea of CICs has been based on voluntary input and obviously this will continue.</P>
    <P>On Senator Ridge's point about worker representation on the board, I empathise with the request I received from the Senator and in the other House that there should be more worker <Col N="469" /> representatives. It is normal to have worker representatives on commercial bodies. In some instances there are no worker representatives on non-commercial bodies but I have written into the legislation that one of the board members should represent the various workers. If I were to go further and include two, three or four worker representatives, this would either require me to increase the number on the board, which stands at 20, or alternatively leave people off the board. Given that one must ensure there is gender balancing, which is well catered for in the Bill, geographic balancing, disability balancing and so on, it is difficult to keep all the various interests happy. In the end, the balance must come down in favour of retaining one worker representative.</P>
    <P>Senator O'Toole welcomed independent and free advice. This has always been the case with the NSSB and NRB and will continue to be supported by the Government and no doubt future Governments.</P>
    <P>Many Senators thanked and complimented the staff of the NSSB and NRB. I wish to echo those words and say that it is an exciting time for the people involved in this area. I appreciate this is a leap into the dark for many people. However, I assure Members that as far as my Department and I are concerned, we will do all in our power to ensure the transition is as smooth as possible so that the people who use the service will not notice any diminution but will in the future notice a betterment of the service. I thank Senators for their remarks.</P>
    <Speaker pid="ThereseRidge" hpid="Mrs. Ridge Mrs. Ridge">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Ridge</NameTxt>
      <P>I thank the Minister for his response. On a point of clarification, the Minister did not refer to the possibility of educating the wider public. Perhaps the Minister would consider this issue to which Senator Leonard and I referred.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DennisODonovan" hpid="Mr. O'Donovan Mr. O'Donovan">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman (Mr. O'Donovan)</NameTxt>
      <P>I suggest to the Senator that this question is more appropriate to Committee Stage.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Acting Chairman Acting Chairman">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman</NameTxt>
      <P>When is it proposed to take Committee Stage?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="AnnLeonard" hpid="Ms Leonard Ms Leonard">
      <NameTxt>Ms Leonard</NameTxt>
      <P>It is proposed to take Committee Stage on Thursday, 24 February 1999.</P>
      <P>Committee Stage ordered for Thursday, 24 February 1999.</P>
      <P>
        <i>Sitting suspended at 5.05 p.m. and resumed at 6 p.m.</i>
      </P>
      <P>
        <i>
        </i>
      </P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Overseas Development Aid:" RHead="Motion">
    <Title>Overseas Development Aid: Motion.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="MaryHenry" hpid="Dr. Henry Dr. Henry">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Henry</NameTxt>
      <P>I move:</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>That Seanad Éireann recommends that the Government increase immediately the financial assistance given to Third World development <Col N="470" /> aid from 0.31% of GNP to the recommended UN level of 0.7%; and calls on the Government to give further support to the efforts of Irish Aid in sub-Saharan Africa.</P>
    <P>I welcome the Minister of State. I am delighted he is present to respond to the motion. The involvement of Irish people with medical and educational institutions in developing countries in the Third World has a long and illustrious history. I am delighted that Dr. Oliver Murphy is present in the Visitors Gallery. He has had a long involvement in numerous African countries in this respect and, in common with others in those countries, he is not praised enough.</P>
    <P>Religious and lay Irish people have made an enormous contribution to improving the lives of those in need in Africa in particular. It was with delight that I read about the report from the Department of Foreign Affairs in which it was announced that the funding of Ireland Aid projects would be increased this year by £1 million. The money will be spent by Ireland Aid on the fight against HIV-AIDS in 2000. The total sum available stands at £2.5 million.</P>
    <P>The public is incredibly generous in its response to foreign disasters and it is good that the Government realises we expect as good a response from the public purse. The United Nations target of 0.7% of gross national product for development aid has never been achieved by Ireland &ndash; the latest figure I have seen is 0.31%. In view of Ireland's increasing prosperity, it is good that an increasing sum is being given. During the debate on last year's Finance Bill, there was some bargaining between the Minister for Finance and the Minister of State, Deputy O'Donnell. I presume the extra £1 million arose from those discussions.</P>
    <P>I do not have the political power of the Minister of State, Deputy O'Donnell, but there is no harm in trying to get some money. My argument is that we should give more money not because we are so rich, but because I have had a first hand opportunity of seeing how well our money is spent. Ireland is giving an increased share of development money to the International Monetary Fund and the World Bank and this must be the case. If we do not put a large amount of money into the basket from which developing countries can borrow, the governments there will never be able to set up projects of their own. They must be able to do this if they are ever to achieve proper independence after decades, and sometimes centuries, of colonial rule.</P>
    <P>The rest of the money is spent by Ireland Aid on what could be called our pet projects, and I praise these projects. It is important to become involved in the programmes in each country, but it is also important to try to keep our projects going for the time being and support them. When the Taoiseach returned from his visit to South Africa and Lesotho last month, he said he would press the European Union to tackle the AIDS crisis in Africa. This is good, but we can do more.</P>
    <P>Last month, with Mrs. Mary Banotti, MEP, <Col N="471" /> and the Minister of State, Deputy Eoin Ryan, I visited Uganda and Zambia. This study trip was organised by the International Planned Parenthood Federation and I thank them for the opportunity to see first hand the truly dreadful situation there. The Taoiseach said after his trip, &ldquo;Africa's biggest problem is the AIDS problem, they are crying out for help.&rdquo;  There is an excellent report in the Department of Foreign Affairs and all we need to do is implement its recommendations. The people who wrote the report should be praised, but there are also talented people who are well able to implement the recommendations.</P>
    <P>In Uganda and Zambia I saw Irish projects which are making a practical, tactful input to the serious problems arising from AIDS. Maternity clinics run by local staff are funded by us. With some supervisory input from Ireland Aid employees, women are given good maternity care. HIV and syphilis testing is carried out and treatment given where possible. Research carried out in Kampala in Mugola Hospital has shown that the anti retro-viral drug, Zidovudine, given in tablet form to a woman as she goes into labour and in syrup form to the newborn baby, can cut the transmission rate from mother to baby by 50%. This is a cheap drug and perhaps our maternity clinics could include this treatment in their preventative medical programmes. We could buy huge supplies of the drug and even set up more clinics. With this treatment and the establishment of extra clinics, we could be sure that babies are safely born disease free.</P>
    <P>Maternal and infant mortality rates in Africa are soaring. It must be soul destroying for those working in these areas to accept that the figures were better 20 years ago than they are now. AIDS is a major component of this huge increase. However, it is not all despair. The Irish Aid clinics in Lusaka have a maternal mortality rate of 331 per 100,000 births whereas the national average for the same year &ndash; 1996 &ndash; was 649, almost double. Who cannot say that these clinics, which are almost entirely run by local people, are not doing a tremendous job? The loss of a mother to children under five in the developing world is almost fatal. How many children have also been saved? Our maternal mortality rate is in single figures &ndash; a rate of five in any one year would be quite dreadful. From that perspective, the work being done in these clinics is incredible. I do not know whether an Irish architect designed them but I have rarely seen such well designed buildings as these purpose-built clinics which are almost indestructible and inexpensive.</P>
    <P>Many children are left orphaned by AIDS. The programmes run by Ireland Aid were the best I saw for many reasons. For example, the children remain in the community with grandparents or other relatives and do not lose contact with their extended families. This is very important. Building large orphanages in Africa is not the answer. Once children lose contact with their extended <Col N="472" /> families they are in a very isolated position. The children come every day to the centres for high calorific and high protein food prepared by local women and paid for by us. They also receive medical care at the centres. I was very interested to note, though it sounds very esoteric, that the Planned Parenthood of Zambia Association runs a roundworm deworming programme alongside its family planning programme. That is very practical. The children also receive some schooling at the centres.</P>
    <P>Ireland Aid feeds 11,000 orphans each day in the Copper Belt in Kitwe. Those children were among the best nourished I saw and were, I think, the only ones wearing shoes. Another important point is that these children were dressed like any other child in the area. I was a little depressed when I visited another centre, not run by Ireland Aid, to see children wearing T-shirts proclaiming them &ldquo;International Orphans&rdquo;. I thought those days had gone. I was glad to see that when children left the Irish feeding centres no one knew where they had been, they were not labelled. Why can we not extend these schemes? Many more children are in need of such care. Young adults are dying, leaving elderly relatives to mind these children.</P>
    <P>Much of the emphasis on HIV and AIDS in sub-Saharan Africa has been on the provision of drugs which, although very expensive, have managed to make HIV infection into a chronic rather than a fatal condition in the western world. While I fully support the TRIPs Agreement whereby compulsory licences could be given to Third World countries with the capacity to produce essential drugs, it will be a long time before the infrastructure is available to allow such drugs to be used in large parts of the developing world. People on such drugs require careful monitoring. The medical centres which I visited do not even have the capacity to measure electrolyte levels in blood, never mind the more complicated tests which would be needed. We could, however, provide more money for research to develop suitable vaccines.</P>
    <P>Ultimately we have to recognise that the spread of HIV infection in these countries is mostly by heterosexual activity. While I understand the motivation of those who promote the use of condoms, cultural change can only be brought about by those who live there and who understand their traditional cultural practices. As one tribal elder said, &ldquo;If traditional cultural practices are dangerous, traditional cultural practices must change&rdquo;. We cannot even stop the cultural practice of smoking in Ireland. All we can do is help these people to identify those practices which are dangerous and hope they will initiate change themselves. For instance, any female genital mutilation or the practice of dry sex which will cause bleeding at intercourse are a terrible cause for the spread of the disease. It was depressing to find that teenage girls were six times as likely as teenage boys to be HIV positive because of older men using them as safe sexual partners. Perhaps <Col N="473" /> we could send out some anthropologists and sociologists to explain the dangers of casual sex.</P>
    <P>I applaud what the Government has done. I hope we continue to do more in the areas in which we are making an excellent contribution at a practical level. We are helping to deal with serious problems which are destroying the economic and social structure of these countries.</P>
    <Speaker pid="FergalQuinn" hpid="Mr. Quinn Mr. Quinn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Quinn</NameTxt>
      <P>I welcome the Minister to the House and welcome the opportunity to speak on this debate. It is traditional when one stands up to second a motion to say one is happy to do so. However, I am not happy to second this motion; I am ashamed to do so. I am ashamed of our performance in terms of development aid. I am ashamed that the Government insists on playing Scrooge in the case of the poor countries in the world. Playing that role in the costume of the Celtic tiger is incongruous. At one time we could put on the poor mouth with full justification. We did so when we sought money from Brussels which was of enormous benefit to us and have done so when dealing with the disadvantaged in our own country while promising to do the devil and all when resources permitted. We did the same when it came to supporting development aid, stating we would do what we could when resources permitted. The poor mouth days are, we hope, gone forever but the poor mouth attitude remains. As a result poor mouth behaviour remains with us. We are behaving out of proportion to our means. We are mean when it comes to development aid. There is no excuse for this and that is why I am ashamed.</P>
      <P>I have a mental picture of one of the mandarins in Merrion Street coming down to breakfast one morning in a very bad state and his wife looks at him and says, &ldquo;What's wrong, love?&rdquo;  He tells her he had a dreadful nightmare and the wife says, &ldquo;Tell me about it&rdquo;. He goes on to say it was really bad, thinks for a few minutes and says, &ldquo;I had this outrageous dream that resources did permit&rdquo;. He could not live with that because he was so used to its being the other way. Is there something at work about which we are not aware?</P>
      <P>Senator Henry pointed out that as individuals the Irish people are remarkable in their generosity and have been for years. When asked to support a good cause, we do &ndash; sometimes quite spectacularly. We do not seem to be deficient on an individual level but something happens when that individual level becomes a national one. For some reason we, as a State, find it impossible to behave with the generosity that characterises our citizens. How can that be? What is the Irish State but the collective will of its people? How can the State be a Scrooge while individual citizens are generous almost to a fault? This has only recently become a conundrum because until recently we were strapped for cash and the resources argument could always be used to fill that gap. We used it. The resources argument is no longer available, the gap is yawning at us, demanding to be explained.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="474" /> Please do not get me wrong, I am not suggesting that even today we have money to do everything we want. No matter how large the budget surplus, any Minister for Finance could easily find ways to spend all that money several times over. There is a sense in which we will never have enough money to do everything we want, not immediately at least. What is different now is that for the first time in the history of the State we do have the money to do the important things, perhaps not all the important things but certainly the vast majority of them. That is the revolutionary change that is happening to our finances. The scope of that change is apparently too vast for some people to grasp. We do not have the money for everything but we have it for most of the important things. What happens? We find we are not doing some of the important things, or not doing enough of them. Meanwhile we are throwing money around like snuff at a wake, as they used to say in the country, on imperial follies such as national stadia that I am not sure we want. Everyone seems to be jealous of the other one.</P>
    <P>In Ireland we are not doing enough about the disadvantaged, although we are pouring money in that direction. It seems a great deal only in terms of what we used to spend, but in relation to the size of the problem and the difficulty in solving it, it is not a lot and, more crucially, it is not enough.</P>
    <P>Let us not think we have heard the last of disadvantage as a problem. Outside Ireland we are as mean as ever. By juggling the figures we can claim to be doing more. It is interesting to note that the amendment today draws our attention to the fact that we are doing better than in the past. The unforgiving benchmark is the percentage of national wealth we devote to development aid. On that United Nations benchmark we are a nation of rich meanies.</P>
    <P>I wish to dwell on the irony of this from my particular viewpoint. I have been concerned for some time about the danger of the economy overheating. That is a real danger about which I spoke here earlier today. The EU and the OECD are aware of it but at official level we pretend to think it is not a real issue. One of the budgetary problems is that the State has money coming out its ears. If it simply puts that money back into the national economy it will add to the overheating just like throwing oil on a fire.</P>
    <P>We should look at productive and deserving ways of spending money in a manner that will not contribute to that future overheating; spending more money on development aid is exactly one of those ways. In addition to the overwhelming moral argument for being more generous, there is also an actual self-interested economic argument for doing so. We have all the reasons in the world to be generous in our development aid yet we persist in being incredibly mean. I suggest incredible is the right word. I find it difficult to believe that as a country Ireland could be so mean when, for the first time in the history of the <Col N="475" /> State, we have the actual means to meet and to surpass the not very demanding EU target set for us. Senator Henry mentioned the target of 0.7% but we are not even half way there. We can reach it and for the first time we are able to do it.</P>
    <P>I second the motion but almost with a sense of shame because of our failure to achieve what is in our grasp. I hope the Minister will bring us good news. His heart is in the right place and I hope we will learn that we are grasping hold of this and giving ourselves the opportunity to do something about it.</P>
    <Speaker pid="BrianMullooly" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I have been informed that the amendment which has been circulated is not being moved.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RobertMolloy" hpid="Mr. Molloy Mr. Molloy">
      <NameTxt>Minister of State at the Department of the Environment and Local Government (Mr. Molloy)</NameTxt>
      <P>Today in the Dáil there were eight questions on ODA budget levels. On the Dáil's Order Paper there is a motion on the issue to be debated soon. Here in the Seanad we are addressing the same topic.</P>
      <P>I warmly welcome this interest in development aid. It is a heartening reflection of the public support for a strong and growing Irish programme. This was attested to recently in a nationwide survey. The political consensus in support of a substantial and effective aid programme, which is implicit in this interest, is important. I echo the point made by the Taoiseach recently that there is no Member of either House who opposes the idea of a strong programme or of growing allocations for it. For my part, I am pleased to have this opportunity to address the Seanad on this topic on behalf of my colleague the Minister of State, Deputy O'Donnell, whose energy and commitment have been the key driving force behind our development co-operation policy in recent years.</P>
      <P>At the heart of the motion is the issue of budget allocations for the development aid programme. Although the matter has been addressed a number of times in both Houses, I reiterate that the total development aid budget for 1999 is likely to total £178 million and we estimate an outturn of £190 million for the current year. This is the highest level ever attained and is the result of an unprecedented level of growth in recent years. The extent of that growth will be clear if Members recall that in 1992 the total aid provision was a mere £40 million. In the last three years alone, it was increased by £12 million, £15 million and £38 million, respectively. It is important, in commenting on allocations, that these facts are kept in mind. The Government has shown real commitment to substantial increases in our contribution to the developing world and is determined to continue that commitment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>There has been lively debate on the issue of our progress to the UN target of 0.7% of GNP. This is desirable and legitimate. The Government and its predecessors have pledged themselves to <Col N="476" /> steady progress to meet that target. That pledge has been honoured as demonstrated by the record of substantial annual increases, at a rate which outpaces that of most member states of the OECD.</P>
    <P>We have to accept, however, that because of a unique combination of circumstances, it has been difficult to make progress according to the benchmark of growth as a percentage of our gross national product. The first of those circumstances is the unprecedented annual growth in the Irish economy which we have been experiencing in the last five years.</P>
    <P>We have been criticised as complaining about that level of growth and as using it as an excuse for lack of progress in the aid budget. Nothing could be further from the truth. The Government and all our citizens cannot but be delighted at the turnaround in the economy. Its current healthy state &ndash; the result of years of wise policies &ndash; allows us address a wide range of domestic issues, from infrastructure to hospital queues, which it has not been possible to tackle until now. It permits us to make generous provision for our overseas assistance and to commit ourselves to continue doing so into the future.</P>
    <P>The second circumstance is that we have introduced a new method of calculating GNP in accordance with EU rules. This has had the effect of depressing the percentage figure for the ODA budget. It should not, however, be allowed to mask the reality which is that our aid budget is one of the fastest growing in the world.</P>
    <P>Members should not take the view that the Government has abandoned the goal of reaching 0.7% of GNP. On the contrary, at a time when we have joined the ranks of wealthy nations, we are more than ever concerned to ensure that the aid programme should not stall or diminish as a proportion of our national wealth. To address this issue, a fundamental series of reviews has been carried out in the Department of Foreign Affairs. A set of proposals has been prepared for Cabinet consideration. The Minister and the Minister of State at the Department of Foreign Affairs will be working on these in the coming weeks. They would hope to have decisions shortly.</P>
    <P>Underpinning these proposals and the thrust of the whole programme is the determination to ensure that the aid budget is used to achieve enduring, sustainable development. That issue of quality aid is vital. Any current or former aid worker will tell you that Africa is pitted with the flaking rust of failed aid projects, the relics of western ideas imposed on developing countries without reference to local consideration or need.</P>
    <P>The Irish programme is focused on quality. Last year the programme was reviewed by its peer donors in the OECD. That review found that Ireland sets high standards for aid; we have demonstrated that aid can work; we have an undeviating focus on poverty reduction; and we are a strong performer in putting partnerships into practice.</P>
    <P>This quality aid, which is at the heart of the <Col N="477" /> Irish programme and to which the OECD peer review is a handsome testament, took years of patient work to build. A real working partnership with a developing country begins with building an understanding of its people's reality, with getting beneath the skin of the daily challenges and with, as Abraham Lincoln put it, &ldquo;shuffling a while in another man's shoes&rdquo;. It is slow, patient work to get beyond the barriers, common in any environment of poverty, of low self-esteem. We must also get beyond the assumption that outside know-how is better and we must reach a common understanding of needs. An authoritative international aid expert, addressing a forum in Dublin a few months ago, summed up his caution regarding quick aid with the tongue-in-cheek quip, &ldquo;Don't just do something, stand there&rdquo;.</P>
    <P>Ireland makes no grandiose claims to have cracked the code on quality aid. The peer review was a welcome plaudit for past hard work. However, maintaining that reputation of quality requires more of the same patient, hard work and more of the slow build-up to the common understanding on which the partnership process is built. What is more, we must continue to build up our own management capacities to ensure continuing quality, effectiveness and accountability.</P>
    <P>What all of this points to, in the context of growing allocations, is that a balance must be struck between the requirements of quality and chasing what is, in reality, a moving target. Quality aid requires planned, prudent growth in aid involvement and management capacity, both among donors and partner governments. These are the important issues which will have lasting beneficial impact on the lives and livelihoods of poor people in developing countries. We must not allow an exclusive focus on targets to divert our attention from these priorities. That is the thrust of our review and the basis on which we hope to secure agreement on a path to the UN target.</P>
    <P>A related issue which has been raised recently is that of putting allocations on a statutory footing. There is some merit in this on the face of it, but I would question it. My main question is whether there is a need for it. The purpose of such a move is to increase allocations. However, if they are going to increase, as I hope, in a measured way, that purpose is achieved. Second, if one can conceive of aid being put on such a basis, then why not other deserving causes? Seen thus, putting ODA allocations on a statutory footing is potentially an unnecessary complication.</P>
    <P>I will take the opportunity of this motion to give a short overview of where the programme is going and its priorities. I will begin with the bilateral programme.</P>
    <P>The focus of Ireland Aid is on the least developed countries, and that of the bilateral programme is on six such countries in Africa &ndash; Lesotho, Zambia, Tanzania, Uganda, Ethiopia and Mozambique. All these countries rank low in terms of human development indicators, includ<Col N="478" /> ing the percentage living in absolute poverty, life expectancy, adult literacy, infant mortality, access to safe water, sanitation and health services.</P>
    <P>In these six priority countries, the thrust of the programme is on basic needs, including rural development, education and health, and on a framework of democracy and good governance. In the health sector, we work with governments and local authorities to provide primary health care. In education, we focus together on primary and informal education, teacher training and adult literacy. In rural development, we fund programmes for food security, rural roads, provision of clean water and sanitation, and micro-credit, especially for women. In all these, we work with our partners to ensure that women's and men's needs are met appropriately and that there is respect for the environment.</P>
    <P>Most aid in the priority countries is delivered in the form of integrated programmes at regional or local level. These are selected in consultation and partnership with governments in the priority countries. More recently, we have been working with governments and other donor countries on sectoral investment programmes. In these cases, aid is provided in the form of general budgetary support to sectors such as health and education. The aim here is to reduce the burden on under-resourced administrations of dealing with a plethora of donors and to help build the internal capacity of the governments concerned to push forward their own development.</P>
    <P>The guiding principles that inform the bilateral involvement are summed up as the three Ps &ndash; poverty, participation and partnership. The universal strategy is poverty reduction. Participation refers not simply to local involvement but to real ownership by the partner government in accordance with its own national priorities of development programmes. Partnership involves the use of local administrative structures and building wider understanding and enduring trust.</P>
    <P>There are many challenges in our programmes in Africa. One of the greatest is the HIV/AIDS epidemic. As at least one Member of this House &ndash; Senator Henry, whom we have heard speak &ndash; can testify from a recent visit, this disease is a major public health problem in all our priority countries. Its spread has huge economic and social effects and has set back development progress in many areas by years.</P>
    <P>Ireland Aid, together with partner governments and other donors, has been responding to these challenges in the past 15 years. The lessons from this experience have been drawn together in a new strategy which we recently launched. At the same time, the Taoiseach has written to EU Commission President Prodi, stressing the need for the EU and its member states to explore urgently the level of resources devoted to the fight against HIV/AIDS and the need for greater international co-operation. The Taoiseach also called for consideration of how best to procure affordable treatment for AIDS for poor countries <Col N="479" /> and the EU's role in supporting the search for a vaccine.</P>
    <P>Many of the poorest countries in the world are burdened by levels of external debt which make it almost impossible for them to develop. A situation in which flows of overseas development assistance to a country are exceeded by its debt repayments is clearly not viable.</P>
    <P>The issue of debt has attracted huge international attention. The Jubilee 2000 campaign, calling for debt cancellation, has received wide support and has been influential in securing major improvements in existing international arrangements for the provision of debt relief. In 1999 we witnessed a new international resolve to ease the heavy burden of debt in many developing countries. The G7 agreed important modifications to the Heavily Indebted Poor Countries Initiative, which were subsequently agreed by the World Bank and the IMF.</P>
    <P>The enhanced HIPCI should result in broader, deeper and more generous debt relief to the countries most heavily burdened. The qualification criteria have been relaxed and there is now a clear connection established between debt relief and poverty reduction. It is expected that over 20 heavily indebted poor countries will have qualified for debt relief by the end of this year.</P>
    <P>The enhanced HIPCI will require funding of up to $27 billion to write off debt. There have been considerable difficulties in raising this money. In December the EU agreed a debt relief contribution of e1 billion, with e700 million going to multilateral debt relief. Ireland strongly supported this important EU contribution. Our share of the EU contribution will be over e6 million.</P>
    <P>It was our deep concern about the effects of debt on developing countries which lay behind the comprehensive and forward-looking debt relief package approved by the Government in September 1998. Although Ireland is not a creditor state, we have allocated over £31 million for debt relief. We have also made tackling the debt issue an integral part of Ireland's overall overseas development co-operation strategy.</P>
    <P>In addition to providing bilateral debt relief of almost £10 million to two of the priority countries for Irish Aid, Mozambique and Tanzania, £15 million has been committed to the joint World Bank-IMF Heavily Indebted Poor Countries Initiative, HIPCI, while £7 million has been allocated to the IMF's Enhanced Structural Adjustment Facility, ESAF.</P>
    <P>Ireland also contributes substantially to the aid programmes of the European Union, which is now the fifth largest donor in the world. If one includes the individual aid programmes of the member states, the EU is, in fact, by far the largest provider of development aid in the world. The programmes of the EU, while global in reach, are concentrated in Africa.</P>
    <P>In this regard, the long-running series of Lomé agreements, which have governed trade and development relations between the European <Col N="480" /> Union and countries of Africa, the Caribbean and the Pacific since the 1970s, is an example of what can be achieved. The agreements are regarded as the most ambitious and sophisticated ever negotiated.</P>
    <P>The current Lomé Convention expires on 29 February 2000. Negotiations on its successor have been successfully concluded. The new convention should be signed in Fiji on 31 May 2000 and will run for 20 years. It is based on a partnership between the EU and the ACP states and is focused on poverty eradication.</P>
    <P>The new convention brings the relationship between the EU and its 71 African, Caribbean and Pacific partners into the 21st century. It will revolutionise the trading relationship between the EU and its ACP partners by providing for the creation of free trade agreements between the EU and ACP regions. The agreement recognises the importance of globalisation for development and will facilitate the integration of developing countries into the world market.</P>
    <P>Throughout the negotiations Ireland placed great emphasis on the need to deal with the marginalisation from world trade of the least developed countries. We strongly support the EU's commitment to introduce duty and quota free access to the EU market for essentially all products from LDCs by 2005. This commitment should be taken on by the other major trading powers such as the US and Japan.</P>
    <P>The new convention will allocate e13.5 billion to the ACP states over the next seven years. Ireland's share of this, which will come from our ODA budget, will be e89 million.</P>
    <P>The need to integrate developing countries, particularly the least developed, into the global economy is now a key issue of development. While globalisation has brought huge benefits to many countries, including Ireland, others are falling further behind. The total GNP of the least developed countries with their 600 million people is less than the collective assets of the world's three richest people. The income gap between rich and poor countries is widening as the poorest countries are not in a position to meet the challenges of globalisation. The outcome of the WTO ministerial meeting in Seattle in December 1999 clearly indicated that development issues are now central to future global trade negotiations. Issues such as implementation, market access and the transparency of the WTO's working methods are high on the agenda of the developing countries.</P>
    <P>Ireland Aid is placing greater emphasis on the need to assist developing countries to integrate into the global economy. At Seattle, together with several other like-minded donors, we, in co-operation with the Tánaiste's Department, co-founded the Advisory Centre on WTO Law. This is a new independent body, based in Geneva, which will advise and assist developing countries, particularly the least developed, in taking legal cases at the WTO under the dispute settlement mechanism. If the world trade system is to provide benefits for all, it is essential that developing <Col N="481" /> countries be in a position to avail of their rights at the WTO. The new body, to which Ireland will contribute $2.5 million over five years, will play a key role in achieving this.</P>
    <P>Ireland Aid remains a strong supporter of the UN's role in development. We are also committed to increasing our contributions to the main UN funds and programmes such as the UN Development Programme, the UN Children's Fund and the UN Population Fund. All of these bodies are suffering from sharp falls in donor contributions and are having to cut back programmes in the poorest countries. At the same time they have introduced major management reforms designed to streamline their operations and to maximise their impact.</P>
    <P>The aid programme includes measures to support democracy and human rights. In each of our priority country programmes, as I mentioned before, there is a strong emphasis on building and reinforcing democratic structures and on good governance. We also actively encourage measures to reinforce democratic reforms through our human rights and democratisation funding programmes in many countries worldwide. For example, in Albania and Macedonia we supported women's participation in democratic processes and in Bosnia Herzegovina we have assisted the establishment of a human rights commission. In China, we funded training of Chinese judges in human rights. We have supported human rights defenders from many different countries and human rights training programmes worldwide. We have been assisting the peace talks in Burundi and supported election monitoring in a number of countries. These are but a few examples of the many diverse projects in this area supported by Ireland Aid.</P>
    <P>The protection of human rights is the first responsibility of all governments, yet in Europe we have seen some of the worst human rights abuses in the last decade. The former Yugoslavia has seen atrocities and barbaric acts of depravity and cruelty. This is the only area of Europe, since the end of the Second World War, for which it has been necessary to establish a UN tribunal to prosecute and punish those guilty of war crimes. The events in recent years in the former Yugoslavia are a stark reminder that after 50 years of human rights rhetoric there is much unfinished business.</P>
    <P>Events in Kosovo in 1999, when ethnic Albanians were forced to flee their homes, is a case in point. While neighbouring countries, like Macedonia, responded most generously and gave refuge to hundreds of thousands, they were sorely pressed in trying to cope with the tide of distressed people crossing their borders. Third countries were asked by the UN High Commissioner for Refugees to help. Under a humanitarian evacuation programme, co-ordinated by the UNHCR, a total of 1,031 ethnic Albanian refugees were given temporary protection in Ireland. Some 200 have since returned to Kosovo. The generosity of the Irish people, both in their wel<Col N="482" /> come for the refugees and in their response to the Kosovo emergency, was tremendous. During the Kosovo crisis, Irish aid agencies received around £7 million in voluntary contributions. For every pound contributed by the Irish people, the Government matched it three times over in direct assistance to Irish and international aid agencies in the region and in our contribution to the humanitarian evacuation programme of Kosovar refugees to Ireland. Our commitment to the Balkan region also involves helping to rebuild Kosovo through the EU and UN budget programmes for the region.</P>
    <P>The Refugee Agency, which has responsibility for co-ordinating the reception and resettlement of refugees admitted to Ireland from crisis situations, is funded by the Department of Foreign Affairs. In addition to its ongoing responsibility for the resettlement of Bosnian and Vietnamese refugees and their families in Ireland, the agency played a central role in the co-ordination, reception, accommodation and care of the Kosovar refugees in Ireland. I appreciate also the role played by other Government Departments, health boards and local authorities in the implementation of the Kosovar programme.</P>
    <P>Ireland Aid continues to respond quickly and as effectively as possible to humanitarian emergencies, whether of sudden onset or protracted. Last year, 1999, was a particularly difficult year, which saw the aftermath of Hurricane Mitch, the crisis in the Balkans, the devastating earthquake in Turkey and the terrible events in East Timor.</P>
    <P>However, we must not forget that there are many other humanitarian crises worldwide which are not on the nightly news, which are &ldquo;out of sight and out of mind&rdquo; and which also need a generous response. Many countries in Africa faced severe food shortages last year and are looking at a similar vista this year. Ireland has not forgotten these most vulnerable of people and is responding to appeals for assistance in countries such as Angola, Sudan, Somalia and Burundi. Ireland Aid is committed to implementing the highest standards of humanitarian practice. We are working with the UN agencies and the NGOs, who receive the bulk of funding, to ensure that taxpayers' money is spent efficiently and effectively and, most importantly of all, reaches those most in need.</P>
    <P>A rehabilitation budget line enables Ireland Aid to assist the most vulnerable people in post-crisis situations to re-establish their lives and livelihoods. In many such situations it is also necessary to help Governments and/or the UN to rebuild institutions and develop human resource capacity with the aim of assisting in the creation of conditions that can lead to peaceful, just, stable and inclusive societies. East Timor and Kosovo are priorities for this type of assistance this year. Other countries which continue to receive rehabilitation support include Bosnia, Rwanda, Somalia and Honduras. The majority of funding <Col N="483" /> is channelled through Irish and international NGOs and through UN agencies.</P>
    <P>Ireland Aid continues to build on the strong relationship fostered over the years with Irish NGOs. There is a fruitful funding partnership and work relationship which allows us to draw on their valuable experience for the benefit of developing countries. They in turn receive significant and growing support from Ireland Aid and APSO for their emergency, human rights and development projects in many countries worldwide from Africa to Asia to Central and Southern America. I welcome this opportunity to express admiration for their work, often under difficult and physically hazardous conditions, and a commitment to further strengthening our relations.</P>
    <P>The Government would like to see a greater public awareness and ownership of Ireland Aid by all Irish citizens, not just the major stakeholders. The elimination of extreme poverty is a responsibility of our common humanity at a time when we are inundated with images of cruelty and mass inhumanity. All sectors have a role to play &ndash; business, trade unions, Government, the media, the churches, schools and voluntary organisations. Ireland Aid, through the National Committee for Development Education, provides support for activities, in both the formal and informal sectors, designed to raise awareness of development issues. Ireland Aid itself is also active in promoting awareness of Government action, on behalf of the Irish people, on these issues. We hope in this way that more people will come to have a deeper appreciation, and hence a greater sense of ownership, of the Ireland Aid programme and the part which Ireland is playing in international development efforts.</P>
    <P>In the 26 years of the life of the Irish programme of development assistance to poorer countries there have been improvements in life expectancy and infant mortality rates in the regions of sub-Saharan Africa. More people have access to clean water and sanitation and more children are going to school. However, these achievements have been slight compared to what could be achieved and what has been achieved in other regions. The gap between rich and poor has widened. <i>Per capita</i> income in some sub-Saharan African countries is lower than it was 20 years ago.</P>
    <P>We can be proud of what we have achieved so far and glad of the validation of that work received from our donor peers, but there is no gainsaying the scale of the problems in the developing world, the depth of poverty to be reduced and eradicated, the moral obligation we, as a wealthy nation, owe to those whose greatest challenge is survival from day to day.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MadeleineTaylorQuinn" hpid="Mrs. Taylor-Quinn Mrs. Taylor-Quinn">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Taylor-Quinn</NameTxt>
      <P>I support the motion and am delighted the Government parties have chosen not to move an amendment but to accept the motion as it stands. The proposal that we increase our overseas development aid funding to <Col N="484" /> the UN recommended rate of 0.7% of GNP is highly commendable. Given our current economic success, it is more than commendable and I hope we will proceed rapidly to achieve that target and to make effective use of our aid budget.</P>
      <P>Recently I had the privilege of visiting Lesotho and Tanzania, two countries which are given priority for Irish overseas aid. I compliment the Irish communities in Lesotho and Tanzania on the tremendous work they are doing. Any Irish person visiting either country would be proud to be Irish. The staff at the Irish consulate in Lesotho were very familiar with aid programmes in that country, they knew everyone working on the ground extremely well and were in direct consultation with people working on the various projects. It was the level of consultation with those working in the field which impressed me most because while the people were getting support they also had a vital input into decisions regarding what was to be done. Irish officials support and monitor projects very closely, and we cannot commend them highly enough. In Lesotho our consul general, Tom Wright, and his staff were extremely impressive and in Tanzania, our <i>chargé d'affaires , </i>Isolde Moylan-McNally, and her staff were also impressive. In a much larger country they had excellent contact with those involved in projects and there was again a high level of consultation.</P>
      <P>It was a privilege to go to a Third World country. I do not wonder that we speak of the Third World because, although we live on the same planet, such countries are in a very different world. There is an enormous difference between our consumer society and the totally non-consumer society in Third World countries. One could never give enough assistance to communities in these countries. The benefit from that assistance is extraordinary. In Lesotho the bringing of water schemes to some of the most isolated mountain villages has a positive effect on the health of the community, particularly the children. This was wonderful to see. Support is being given for the building of schools and to assist educational projects in very isolated areas. These areas have one of the harshest climates in the world with extremes of temperature and it is extremely difficult to produce any sort of cash crop. Nevertheless, these hardy people are surviving and Irish Aid is of great assistance in agriculture and education. A footbridge scheme sponsored by the Government in conjunction with the Government of Lesotho is improving accessibility for communities across the valleys, especially in times of flooding.</P>
      <P>If the Minister will listen for a moment&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TomKitt" hpid="Mr. T. Kitt Mr. T. Kitt">
      <NameTxt>Mr. T. Kitt</NameTxt>
      <P>I am listening.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MadeleineTaylorQuinn" hpid="Mrs. Taylor-Quinn Mrs. Taylor-Quinn">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Taylor-Quinn</NameTxt>
      <P>&mdash;he will hear that when Senator Lanigan, the clerk of the Joint Committee on Foreign Affairs and I met the foreign affairs Minister in Lesotho we raised the matter of the murder of Mr. Ken Hickey, the Irish engin<Col N="485" /> eer who had responsibility for the construction of the footbridges in that country. The Minister gave us a commitment that everything possible would be done to apprehend the culprit, who is known. He is the son of a senior retired politician in Lesotho who appears to be free to travel between Lesotho and South Africa. There is an onus on us to ensure that this man is apprehended and that justice is seen to be done. This issue is of extreme concern to the Irish community in Lesotho. I hope the Department of Foreign Affairs will pursue this matter with the foreign affairs Minister and see that his commitment is met. He is in a position to apprehend this man and if this does not happen it will be because of lethargy on the part of the Government there. I urge the Department to pursue this matter quickly and vociferously.</P>
      <P>Tanzania is a much bigger country than Lesotho and is very productive agriculturally. A great amount of development work needs to be done there and much assistance is required. Our <i>chargé d'affaires, </i>Isolde Moylan-McCann, must be highly commended for the manner in which she involves herself in all Irish aid projects. Her level of knowledge, consultation and input is far beyond the normal call of duty. She deserves to be complimented.</P>
      <P>Despite the advances in eradicating traditional diseases, AIDS has spread in both countries. In some areas one person in three is infected. In one village in the bush in Tanzania which one would not think AIDS could have reached, we were told that one person in three is HIV positive. There is a need for an educational programme among the communities. Senator Henry has spoken of the medical aspect of this problem. In both countries there are traditional male-dominated, patriarchal societies. While this continues, it will be very difficult to overcome this problem. There is a real need for a health education programme for men and women. As we travelled back from one village in the bush I spoke to the chairman of the local council who told me that a high percentage of children in the village die before they are five years old. When I asked him what he was doing to change this he told me that there are ante-natal classes for women. I asked about education for men and he said the women are expected to go home and teach the men. I told him that it is unrealistic, in a patriarchal, male-dominated society, to expect men to listen to what women told them. An education programme is required to bring about cultural change. I commend the Department of Foreign Affairs staff, the NGOs and all the Irish community who worked in a private or an official capacity. We can be proud of them.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DonLydon" hpid="Mr. Lydon Mr. Lydon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lydon</NameTxt>
      <P>I am glad to have an opportunity to discuss this important topic. I was pleased to hear the Minister of State's contribution, particularly to learn that a comprehensive package of initiatives is under way with a view to strengthening our development co-operation policy pro<Col N="486" /> gramme. In the past there may have been a feeling that a token contribution for development aid would be enough in Ireland's case. In the early 1980s Ireland's income per head was closer to developing country levels than to the north European average but this is no longer the case. Today, Ireland is one of the fastest growing economies in the western world and its responsibilities have grown commensurably. A number of Members referred to this fact and Senator Quinn said that we must dip a little deeper into our pockets.</P>
      <P>The allocation for development aid has grown from £40 million in 1992 to £178 million in 1999. By any measure that is a substantial rate of increase. However, we must acknowledge that GNP has grown so rapidly in recent years and our ODA budget relative to GNP has not increased. There will be strong public support, as well as from all parties in this House, for measures to ensure that our official development assistance allocation should increase in financial terms and as a proportion of GNP. That is the sense of the motion.</P>
      <P>The motion acknowledges the progress made to date in terms of increasing the aid budget and urges further steps to increase the aid allocation, not only in absolute terms but also as a proportion of GNP. It also urges us to take all the necessary steps to ensure the effective implementation of the programme.</P>
      <P>The Minister of State assured us that a new development co-operation strategy will be unveiled soon which will address the quantity and quality of our aid programmes. He said a set of proposals are being prepared for Cabinet consideration and that the Minister for Foreign Affairs and the Minister of State at the Department will be working on them in coming weeks. They hope to have a decision shortly. I am sure they will and I look forward to that. I assure the Minister that the new strategy will be awaited with interest as there is a real sense across the political divide, on the part of all parties and public opinion, that now is the time to put our development co-operation policy on a solid footing once and for all.</P>
      <P>A strategy should address a number of issues. There must be firm multi-annual commitments of funding. Building on a foundation of predictability of funding an effective approach to programme planning and implementation should flow. In other words, a policy of quantity and quality. Endorsement of the reduction of poverty in poor countries should be the overarching goal of any new strategy. There should be an unambiguous commitment to deploying aid to promote real lasting development in poor countries without there being any question of other objectives that could dilute that aim.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>There must exist a relationship with partner countries that fully respects their dignity and sovereignty. There must be a determination to achieve the highest standards of efficiency and effectiveness with regard to the programme and <Col N="487" /> its implementation. There must also be an innovative approach to promoting ownership of the programme on the part of the Irish public. As has been said, the public has always responded generously when approached for support for a needy project. If the programme is explained to them they will rise to the occasion again and encourage the Government to give more than it is giving at present.</P>
    <P>I welcome that the Minister of State's comments are in the same vein as the points I have made. As always, what matters most is if they are followed through. In this regard I commend the Minister of State at the Department of Foreign Affairs, Deputy O'Donnell, who, unfortunately, is unwell at the moment and I wish her a speedy recovery. She has always spoken strongly on development aid and she will follow through on it. I am sure the new Minister for Foreign Affairs will do the same.</P>
    <P>It would be helpful if the House could come back to this question when the Minister's strategy has been completed and made available to the public. Further consideration of the topic would be more than a mere formality because many Members would have much to say when the strategy is available concerning the most effective methods of its implementation.</P>
    <P>I approve of all but one item in the Minister of State's speech, that is the support for the United Nation's population fund. I do not approve of it because part of its strategy is the promotion of direct abortion. The cause of world poverty is not the amount of people in the world but the inequitable distribution of wealth. The Minister of State said, &ldquo;The total GNP of the least developed countries with their 600 million people is less than the collective assets of the world's three richest people&rdquo;. That is a terrible position in one sense. It is sad to see rich countries waste so much of their wealth, natural resources, food and production but not help countries that do not have the means to help themselves.</P>
    <P>We are moving in the right direction. I welcome this motion and I commend Senator Henry for tabling it. We should return to the matter as soon as the strategy referred to by the Minister of State is in place. I commend the motion for the approval of the House. The Government will find that it is pushing an open door if and when it brings forward a strategy to address the key questions of aid quantity and quality.</P>
    <Speaker pid="DavidNorris" hpid="Mr. Norris Mr. Norris">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norris</NameTxt>
      <P>I am grateful to Senator Jackman for allowing me to speak because I must chair a meeting elsewhere.</P>
      <P>I welcome the Minister of State, Deputy Kitt, to the House. His presence is appropriate because I know he has strong feelings on this matter and I have worked with him in related areas over many years. It is a pity he is not directly involved in this area of responsibility because he would be very good and he would be in accord with the feelings expressed by Members from all sides.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="488" /> I am grateful to the Government for not tabling an amendment. It would have been a pity to make this a matter of confrontation. I commend Senator Henry for tabling a motion that is direct without being abrasive or antagonistic to the Government so that it could accept the motion.</P>
    <P>I would like to address the issue of AIDS in sub-Saharan Africa which was addressed so eloquently by Senator Henry. It is important that we know what is going on there. Unfortunately, many people in Ireland do not know what is going on there. Paddy O'Gorman, who presents &ldquo;Queuing for a Living&rdquo; on RTÉ Radio, wrote an appalling article in which he said that the heterosexual transmission of AIDS was a myth, that it did not exist anywhere. It does. It is the overwhelming mechanism of transmission outside Europe, particularly in Africa and other countries. It is a tragic distortion of reality if we do not accept the fact. Some of the governments in these countries also refuse to acknowledge it. For example, Zimbabwe is ruled by Robert Mugabe, an appalling tyrant who uses his position to oppress his people if they are gay and seek their rights. That is highly dangerous, even though in Zimbabwe the huge infection rate predominantly from heterosexual relations.</P>
    <P>The case is similar in India where a tragic situation also exists. I note that one of the Minister's advisers is a distinguished Irishwoman who was the Irish ambassador in India when I attended an IPU conference in Delhi. She invited us for a meal and asked if she could be of any help. I asked her about the current position of organisations working in the area of AIDS. The next morning she gave me a list of about 70 organisations, but only one of them dealt with homosexual men and this method of transmission, which was highly dangerous. When I raised it I discovered that homosexual men and female prostitutes had attempted to attend a conference in the same hotel exactly a year previously and had been expelled by the police. They were not allowed to speak. There is a need for accurate information and it must be produced in such a way that it can educate. I do not mean this in a patronising way but tragically there are men in African countries who believe, because of the cultural context, that they can cure themselves of AIDS by having unprotected sex with virgins. This has the cataclysmic impact of setting up a whole new generation of infection in these unfortunate innocent victims.</P>
    <P>On the economic situation, the drug companies have found a goldmine in AIDS. There could not be anything better for them, particularly now with the triple drug therapy which has turned a fatal illness into a chronic illness. People will be continuously on their products, which are highly priced. As this is a very weak country, for strength the Government should join other countries against the multinational drug companies to ensure they permit the production of non-proprietary brand products at a cheap level for African countries. What benefit is it to these <Col N="489" /> pharmaceutical combines to deny the products of scientific ingenuity to the most vulnerable of people? There is unfortunately a two-tier system in this as in every other area. There is the patenting of life forms, bio-patenting and the patenting of seeds that belong to indigenous peoples and which are being sold back to them at inflated prices.</P>
    <P>The Minister of State referred to the question of world debt cancellation. I take a slighty sceptical view of pop stars who become involved in political campaigning but I give every credit to Bob Geldof and Bono in particular for the very shrewd way in which they appealed in newspaper advertisements to the French people, over the heads of the French Government, to involve themselves in debt cancellation. They have had a very creditable measure of success.</P>
    <P>On the question of ODA as expressed as a percentage of GNP, we have had this argument time and again since I was elected to the Seanad. It has tended to increase, particularly when expressed arithmetically. Government after Government has used this excuse but it has staggered slightly. It almost reached 0.35% at one stage before falling back again to 0.31%. It is an appropriate and useful target but it must be monitored and expressed as a percentage of GNP. It is not enough to say that it is more apparent than last year, it has to increase in percentage terms. It looks as if it will remain stuck at this level, even though the Government has stated that it will reach its target by 2002. It is very difficult to see how it will achieve this in its two remaining budgets. I honestly do not see how we will reach the target we have set for ourselves of 0.45% by 2002.</P>
    <P>The Minister of State said:</P>
    <P>A related issue which has been raised recently is that of putting allocations on a statutory footing. On the face of it there is some merit in this but I would question it. My main question is whether there is a need.</P>
    <P>That is a fairly weak question to ask. If there really was a problem with it the Minister of State would have asked a more incisive question. Justin Kilcullen of Trocaire said:</P>
    <P>We will propose that ODA is taken out of the budget entirely and instead is provided for in legislation. This now appears to be the only way by which we can ensure that Ireland's aid budget reaches the Government's own target and ultimately reaches the United Nations' recommendation.</P>
    <P>For God's sake let us keep monitoring the situation in East Timor. I know the Taoiseach is going out there. I also know that two of our friends from East Timor who were educated for seven years in Ireland and housed by Tom Hyland went back at Christmas. They telephoned in tears to say that they wanted to come home because they could not bear the conditions in East Timor. It has not been solved and we must continue to look at it. They are not getting enough food and they <Col N="490" /> are not getting communications. The situation is a disaster. The position is the same in Tibet. How can we be happy just to educate Chinese? For God's sake what are we going to do? The previous Government was afraid to entertain the Dalai Lama and we have not asked the questions about the Panchen Lama.</P>
    <P>I commend my colleagues for tabling the motion. I wish we had more time because we could stir up so many issues which need to be stirred up and looked at as uncompromisingly as my two Independent colleagues have done.</P>
    <Speaker pid="HelenKeogh" hpid="Ms Keogh Ms Keogh">
      <NameTxt>Ms Keogh</NameTxt>
      <P>It is important to underline the need to concentrate on this issue from time to time. This House has a very proud record in stressing the need for ODA and keeping its eye on the ball. I congratulate Senator Henry in particular on tabling the motion and I was more than pleased when it was agreed with the Minister of State, Deputy Molloy, that no amendment should be tabled. It would not have been appropriate to do so. We should all be on the same side on this issue. The Minister of State underlined the scope of our ODA and the necessity to increase it. This should be welcomed. This is something on which we should all agree and not engage in partisan politics. There is consensus across the political spectrum that development co-operation should be strengthened. That is the purpose of this debate. It will in turn strengthen the hand of the Minister for Foreign Affairs and the Minister of State at that Department, Deputy O'Donnell, who everyone agrees has played a sterling role on this issue. We should support her efforts as much as possible and judging from its generosity to date there is widespread public support. We must ensure the issue is moved along.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The Minister of State, Deputy Molloy, indicated that ODA has grown significantly in absolute terms but when measured as a percentage of GNP &ndash; the conventional way of measuring a country's aid effort &ndash; we have failed to make progress in recent years. There is a need to ensure a steady pattern of growth. The mechanisms by which this can be done have to be addressed. We used to rely on the annual Estimates process but as that did not provide the certainty required it was agreed &ndash; a battle won by the Minister of State, Deputy O'Donnell &ndash; that there would be multi-annual budgeting. That is very important. We want to ensure we reach the targets we have set. Although we know the UN target of 0.7% of GNP has only been achieved by a small number of countries, we want to say that our place is with the leaders. We are more and more conscious of the fact that ours is a relatively wealthy country, despite the fact that we are coming from a long way behind. The strength of our economy dictates that we should be generous in this matter and we must not let go of that very important principle. We should be planning for a substantial future period and multi-annual budgeting would deal with the difficulties faced by NGOs in annual budgeting, where there is no certainty about allo<Col N="491" /> cations. That is a dreadful situation for any organisation to operate in and I know from many years in voluntary groups that the worst thing of all when receiving a Government contribution, no matter how niggardly, is uncertainty about what is coming. It is impossible to plan on that basis and it is essential to have certainty on budgeting. When we do so it is very important that we, as Senators, have an opportunity to contribute to decisions on strategy.</P>
    <P>Members referred to the quality of aid and the fact that it is easy to lose sight of partnership in aid. The example given to me is the way Ireland used EU Structural Funds. The emphasis there is that we know what we need and we must get away from the paternalistic approach to overseas aid wherein we make decisions. I do not have the depth of experience of many Members in observing overseas projects, but I have travelled in Africa and I had the honour of monitoring elections in South Africa and Mozambique. The latter was completely and utterly devastated. There was no wildlife left in the country, never mind chickens or pigs. In the middle of nowhere a beautiful road had been built, but the local people did not want or need this road. They were concerned about aid being given to them in this paternalistic way, with outsiders deciding matters, when they only had two stand pipes for fresh water. The majority of people in the town I was in had to travel some distance to the river to get fresh water. It was ludicrous. We must be conscious that the needs of the people, as dictated by the people, must be addressed.</P>
    <P>I totally support the points made by Senators Henry and Norris on AIDS programmes. The disinformation put out about AIDS is nothing short of criminal and I echo the praise given to Irish support for AIDS programmes in Africa. We should be particularly mindful of the devastation that is wreaking on so much of Africa. We should support efforts to provide necessary medicines and to fund vaccine research.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MaryJackman" hpid="Mrs. Jackman Mrs. Jackman">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Jackman</NameTxt>
      <P>I am delighted to support Senator Henry's motion and I am glad the Government is not moving its amendment. I start with a quote from <i>The Reality of Aid 2000</i> by Elin Inge:</P>
      <P>The fact that more than a billion people are living and dying in poverty is not a tragic twist of fate but a deliberate turning of heads. The goal of absolute poverty elimination remains affordable and within reach. Most Governments have committed themselves to this goal. If it is to become reality there is an urgent need for a concerted and imaginative approach to replacing the old donor-driven model of aid.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>It is a pity we do not have time to look at different structures, as obviously what is being done is not enough. This book, from the Reality of Aid <Col N="492" /> project, is compulsory reading if we are to make inroads into the problem. The statistics are frightening. More than four million children born this year will die before they turn five. We can gloss over statistics quickly, but that is appalling. Approximately 1.3 billion people live on less than a dollar a day, but that number is likely to have risen to 1.5 billion given that these statistics are from the end of 1999.</P>
    <P>The question raised by this book is, what are the world's richest countries doing to change this? The answer is that they are not doing what is necessary or possible or what they promised they would do. In that context I am critical of what the Minister of State, Deputy Molloy, said. We are talking about £190 million with an overrun for the current year, but it is short of 0.7% of GNP, which is our target. I and Fine Gael support the Labour Party in seeking legislation to have this enacted rather than leave ODA as part of the budget. This was referred to briefly by the Minister of State who questioned the recommendation of putting allocations on a statutory footing, then he dismissed it and moved on to other points. A debate like this would have been an opportunity for us to see if we can move away from the budget and examine using legislation.</P>
    <P>The NGOs are saying that the Government must stop relying on them to meet its obligations and must restructure development aid under the auspices of a semi-State body. This should have been discussed. They also want VAT on charities repealed, which would free millions of pounds to fund NGOs. Those are specific requests and there may be reasons they cannot be carried out, but I would like them debated. Elin Inge's book looks at where we are in relation to other EU countries and there is a reference to slowness which states: &ldquo;Aid grows but progress to the 0.7% is slow . . .  given the growth in the economy and the resultant high rates of growth in Government revenues . . . &rdquo;. The point is whether we have the structures in place to deal with funds to overseas aid.</P>
    <P>We should know the importance of overseas development, as part and parcel of our economic growth stems from receiving development assistance from the EU. If we have been able to do this in such a short time, there is no reason structures should not be put in place for the sub-Saharan countries. The absence of such structures is not an excuse. We should be able to put them in place. We have been working on ODA for the past 30 years and the people would welcome our commitment to put those structures in place. A percentage of our funds goes to the EU, a percentage goes to the UN and a rather small percentage goes to NGOs, which have the support of the people of Ireland. Irish people give generously to collections for Concern, Trócaire or GOAL.</P>
    <P>Where is our aid spent? I welcome the fact that our aid is targeted at the poorest countries, with <Col N="493" /> more than 80% going to sub-Saharan Africa. Some 20% of our aid is bilateral aid and 15% is multilateral. We do not have tied aid.</P>
    <P>I spent some time in Africa and two things which really struck me were the lack of materials for school children and the importance of water. Generally speaking, we take water for granted and complain when we are asked to pay for it. Water really is life in a Third World context.</P>
    <P>We are not doing as well as we should. In 1998, our contribution was the equivalent of 7p in the pound. That is not a huge commitment. Irish aid levels have remained constant in regard to other EU countries but are not moving upwards as quickly as they should. Ireland ranks 19th out of 21 donor countries for its volume of aid. Those statistics may not always give a true picture and I can understand that ranking in so far as Ireland is a small country. We move up the league in terms of generosity, ranking tenth out of the 21 countries.</P>
    <P>Irish aid is spent on the provision of basic health and education facilities. Education is the key to success in Third World countries. On the issue of how Irish aid is spent, I am aware that the NGOs are monitored but I am concerned about aid which goes through a bureaucratic layer, particularly in countries which have poor human rights records and which are perceived as being corrupt. I would like a future Private Members' debate to focus on the evaluation of the manner in which Irish aid, whether voluntary or State aid, is spent and the quality of its impact.</P>
    <P>Millions of Third World children will not reach five years of age this year. I have not had an opportunity to address the AIDS programme. I have attended AIDS conferences and we must also address this issue which requires tremendous support from Ireland and other EU countries.</P>
    <Speaker pid="WillieFarrell" hpid="Mr. Farrell Mr. Farrell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Farrell</NameTxt>
      <P>I congratulate Senator Henry for tabling this motion. I spent three weeks in Mozambique where I witnessed real poverty at first hand. The conditions in which people live are unbelievable and there are serious health issues which must be addressed. Towards the end of our visit, we were involved in monitoring elections in Mozambique. When we arrived at one centre, we were informed that a lady there was seriously ill and asked if we could offer any assistance. We had a four wheel drive vehicle and I suggested that we bring the woman to the small country hospital 20 miles down the road. I held the woman in my arms in the back of the jeep. She was in agony and I thought she would die before we reached the hospital. When we reached the hospital, we were told to bring the woman down to what we would describe as an out-patient department. It consisted of a little shed which would not house a donkey. Inside the shed was a small stretcher on which there was an old brown mattress with a narrow strip of white sheet across <Col N="494" /> the centre. We left the woman in the care of the doctor and nurse and returned to the election centre.</P>
      <P>The people working in the booths travelled up to 12 miles to work in the centre and slept in the open at night. We returned to the hospital at 12 o'clock that night with the woman's belongings and were informed that she was ready to go home. Our driver could speak the language and we drove the woman some 20 miles down the road. I had a spare flash lamp which I gave her. I can still see that little beam of light going through the bush as the woman, who had a miscarriage, made her way to her little cabin. That was real poverty.</P>
      <P>One of the schools we saw did not have a roof as it was blown off in the civil war. Children sat on the floor and the teacher wrote on a black wall with a piece of stone. The children did not even have books. A local chapel was built from bamboo leaves. The poverty I witnessed would draw tears from a stone.</P>
      <P>Up to 2,000 people attended the polling booths to vote. Of the hundreds of babies there, I never heard one of them cry. The mothers carried their children in shawls on their backs and when the children whimpered, they just fed them.</P>
      <P>We could not leave the track because if we had veered off it, we could have been blown up by land mines. When we went astray and had to turn around, we had to comb the ground with a length of bamboo to ascertain the presence of land mines. There was no life to be seen in the fields, only the carcases of cattle blown up by land mines. I never witnessed that kind of poverty anywhere else.</P>
      <P>When I returned home, Sligo County Council was debating the location of a traveller site. I voted for the proposal immediately and told my colleagues that if they had witnessed the poverty I had in Mozambique, they would not object to travellers having a place to park their caravans and get some water.</P>
      <P>We stayed in a top hotel in Mozambique in a town as big as Leixlip. When we went upstairs, there were three old beds in the room and a half filled bucket of dirty, brown-coloured water in the corner of the room. Local women had carried that water for up to five miles in containers on their heads.</P>
      <P>The area in which we stayed was on the border where there was a danger of being caught in the cross-fire between the two opposing parties. We went to a hardware shop in the local town and bought its only tin of paint and its only paintbrush in order that we could mark the bushes and find our way out in the event of trouble.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I congratulate the Government on its actions in this area but we must do a great deal more to eradicate poverty. I spoke to a priest in Mozambique who told me that they did not even have coffins in which to bury people. They wrapped <Col N="495" /> them in cowskin and buried them. That is poverty. If we could run excursions to the Third World people would see what poverty is. They would return and thank God they live in a country of plenty. We do not know what poverty is. There are terrible problems with AIDS and HIV in the Third World. I congratulate the Taoiseach on raising this issue with the EU in order to provide services to combat AIDS, the biggest problem in the Third World.</P>
    <P>We are discussing Third World aid but no one is talking about how we can help Chechnya. Many homes there have been razed to the ground by Russian bombs and corpses are left lying on the street. There would be an epidemic if it were not for the cold weather and the frost and snow. The people there have no roofs over their heads. No one is talking about Chechnya. Why are we doing nothing for them? They have suffered one of the most severe wars of recent times. It is time that we were fair minded. I appeal to someone to see what can be done to assist the people of Chechnya and to perform one of the most important corporal works of mercy &ndash; the burying of the dead. We have seen the unburied dead on television. We should help the Chechens and give them food, clothes and shelter. Chechnya has been ravaged by war and is now a Third World country. I appeal for someone to take up the cause of the Chechen people. They are suffering terribly and need assistance.</P>
    <P>Mozambique was a wealthy country and had fine hotels. A few are left but there is no one in them. Five of us went to a big hotel there and it was an effort to find anyone to serve us. One of us had fish and chips, which was all the food that was left. We bought ten glasses of beer, two bottles of Coca-Cola and the bar was drained.</P>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. Ryan Mr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>I propose to share my time with Senator Costello.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JosephDoyle" hpid="Mr. J. Doyle Mr. J. Doyle">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman (Mr. J. Doyle)</NameTxt>
      <P>Is that agreed? Agreed.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. Ryan Mr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>I wish to clarify that the United Nations' target is 0.7p per pound of our gross national product &ndash; that is what 0.7% of 1% is. I wish to put the figures on the record. I am grateful to the Minister because he gave me enough figures to work it out. In 1992, ODA was £40 million. In 2000, it will be, according to the Minister, £190 million. Between 1992 and 1997, when the last Government was in power, ODA increased almost fourfold. It increased from £40 million per year in 1992 to £148 million in 1997, the last year in which the previous Government had budgetary control. In the three years since it has increased by barely one third &ndash; at a time when the economy is growing faster than ever. It is a spurious argument to suggest the problem is we are growing too fast.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>For years we could not fund ODA because we were too poor. Now, without a blush, the Govern<Col N="496" /> ment tells us we cannot fund ODA because we are too rich. The fundamental reason we will not fund ODA is that the worst Minister for Finance in the history of the State will not make the money available. It may be possible to argue about the capacity to immediately handle the huge increases. However, the solution to that is to create a separate fund to spend the money, not to say we will not make it available. We could make it available in the future, directly or indirectly. The real issue is the allocation of that proportion of our national resources. There is only one reason we are not doing that &ndash; because we choose not to.</P>
    <P>Attitudes to affluence and poverty are at issue here. The civilised countries of northern Europe enjoy being affluent but have overcome the idea of looking down their noses at those who are poorer than they and blaming them for their poverty. Unfortunately, the United States, upon whom this Government wishes to model itself, has a different view &ndash; that the poor are lazy and it is their own fault. Hence the US reluctance, either in terms of private donations or government aid, to significantly help world development. We are making a choice in ways we do not even notice &ndash; apart from the obvious one regarding money. It is so trite that I will not discuss it. It is almost an insult to one's intelligence to have a Minister of the capability of Deputy Molloy say the reason we cannot increase ODA is we are too rich. We do not want to hear that anymore and it should not be presented to us. There are capacity and many other problems. However, there is a network of Irish volunteers and religious working around the world who have a billion different ideas of what they could do with money. The only reason they cannot spend the money is we will not give it to them.</P>
    <P>Bigger issues will confront us in the future. I am probably the only person in the country who has reservations about the enormous fishing vessel launched in Norway last week. We are told this will have space for enough fish to feed 14 million people for a day. Where will the fish be caught? Off the starving continent in Africa. They will be taken out of the sea there and brought back to the already affluent Europe. Is there something peculiar in our taking a natural resource, which is the property of the people of Africa, according to international law &ndash; because it is only under international agreements that we can do it &ndash; and bringing it back to indulge the tastes of the Spanish, French, Irish and British?</P>
    <P>The issue of trading emission permits to surmount our carbon dioxide problem and the breach of Kyoto limits has also floated to the top of the Government agenda. From whom will we buy those permits? From the poor countries of the world. This means they will be selling us the possibility of affluence in order to live today &ndash; so we can continue to indulge ourselves in excess expenditure of energy which we could just as well do without. That is the agenda we are setting ourselves. The symptom of that agenda is the <Col N="497" /> scrounging and miserliness about ODA. The reality is that public policy has set its face against any fundamental restructuring of the world in the direction of justice.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JoeCostelloLAB" hpid="Mr. Costello Mr. Costello">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Costello</NameTxt>
      <P>I compliment the Independent Senators on tabling this motion. They often table motions of merit and this is one. I wish to take up where my colleague, Senator Ryan, finished. Progress was made by previous Governments &ndash; including the Labour-Fianna Fáil Government in which the Minister of State, Deputy Tom Kitt, was involved in a ministerial capacity &ndash; from 1992 to 1997. We have allowed that progress to slip since 1997. It was unbelievable to hear the Minister of State, Deputy Molloy, say the Government will try to meet its targets but we have to accept that, because of a unique combination of circumstances, it has been difficult to make progress according to the benchmark of growth as a percentage of our gross national product. He said the first of the circumstances causing difficulty is the unprecedented annual growth in the Irish economy which we have been experiencing for the last five years. We cannot have it every way, difficult when the economy is going badly and virtually impossible when the economy is booming.</P>
      <P>The three Nordic countries are the only countries in Europe to have reached the benchmark. Given our booming economy, it is high time we sought to rival that progress. The benchmark for us as a civilised society is how to use our new found money. Will we use it in a civilised and suitable manner domestically and will we take our international responsibilities seriously? We are now in a position to progress the percentage increase to the level at which the economy is growing. Why is a specific target not included in the Programme for Prosperity and Fairness? Why is there just a bland statement that we will build on the substantial progress of recent years in providing overseas development assistance in future years? Why was there not a specific commitment for a three year period, followed by a specific commitment for another three year period, with a view to reaching a specific target within at least six years? We could then try to progress matters further. There are no such commitments and unless the Government is prepared to change its mind or there is a new Minister for Finance, there will not be the slightest hope of an improvement in relation to overseas development aid.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryHenry" hpid="Dr. Henry Dr. Henry">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Henry</NameTxt>
      <P>I thank the Government for withdrawing the amendment. I phrased the motion carefully because I felt it could be accepted by the Government. As Members will be aware, there is consensus on all sides of the House on this issue. I am pleased the Minister of State is present for the debate because he has been very involved in Third World issues. Like other Members, I wish the Minister of State, Deputy O'Donnell, a speedy return to health. She has shown a great commitment to this issue.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="498" /> Senator Ryan was probably very wise to remind us how our increased affluence has a serious effect on others. The reaction of the general public to issues such as the Finance Bill and the recent partnership debate shows that there is concern for people who are not doing so well. This should be borne in mind and we should not worry about the fact that we have so much money we do not know what to do with it. Many people working in Irish Aid could give pointers on what to do with the money. Senator Jackman mentioned accountability, which is important. I was very impressed by the fact that many people working with aid organisations were trying to ensure that the taxpayers' money was being put to good use.</P>
    <P>Some of the concluding remarks in the Minister's speech worry me slightly. Senator Norris stressed that we need accurate information. I was horrified that a newspaper article stated that heterosexual activity is not involved in the spread of HIV. How on earth do they think women are becoming infected and dying? They are not all drug addicts in India or Africa. The maternal and infant mortality rate has increased dramatically. The life expectancy in many central African countries has decreased. In countries such as Zambia, Uganda and so on, life expectancy was climbing up well into the late forties. However, the recent figures I received for both men and women indicate that it has decreased to 40 or 41 years, which is dreadful.</P>
    <P>I was very pleased to hear the OECD report which stated that we did so well in relation to our aid projects. They would have saved themselves a lot of money if they had just sent me out, because I said exactly the same. It was worthwhile pointing out the three Ps &ndash; poverty, participation and partnership. However, we need to stress another aspect, that is, politics. Perhaps in our civil rights programmes we should try to do a bit more with the politicians in some of these countries. I must single out Uganda as being much more positive under President Museveni in trying to tackle its problems. I regret to say that some of the politicians in Zambia appeared to think it was a bit of a joke and were not taking seriously enough the fact that we would have a stick approach as well as a carrot in relation to the various aid programmes.</P>
    <P>The United Nations needs to co-ordinate its efforts because there are problems in some cases with overlapping. I would say to Senator Lydon that I never heard abortion mentioned or promoted by the United Nations population fund. Both countries have different abortion policies. Uganda has a very limited legal abortion policy and Zambia has a broader legal abortion policy. I heard of an appalling level of illegal abortions in both countries and a terribly high death rate, particularly among teenagers. First, we do not wish to see teenagers becoming pregnant and, second, we do not wish them to have abortions. The illegal abortion rate and lack of treatment is quite horrific and is not being addressed at all; <Col N="499" /> they just pretend it is not happening. This problem is not being spoken about and it is a major contributing factor to maternal mortality figures. I was extremely alarmed by this.</P>
    <P>I must mention many excellent projects such as the hospice movement which is being set up in Uganda and supported by Irish people. We are supporting the education of health care workers, which is very worthwhile because they can then go out into the community after three years and give a great deal of help and advice. I saw buildings being erected at the rate of knots to train laboratory technicians who are in very short supply. Countries such as Chechnya and so on are also desperately in need of aid.</P>
    <P>I was pleased to learn that we were co-founders of the Advisory Centre on World Trade Organisation Law because information is so important in all these areas. No matter from what side it comes, it is of the greatest value to countries where it is extremely difficult to obtain information.</P>
    <Speaker pid="BrianMullooly" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I wish to point out to the Minister of State that Senator Henry has replied and the debate has concluded. It is not usual procedure to have two ministerial contributions. However, if he wishes to make a brief intervention, I am sure Members of the House will hear him.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TomKitt" hpid="Mr. T. Kitt Mr. T. Kitt">
      <NameTxt>Minister of State at the Department of Enterprise, Trade and Employment (Mr. T. Kitt)</NameTxt>
      <P>I appreciate it is unusual and I thank the House for the opportunity to contribute. I wish to make a few brief comments out of respect for the Seanad and because in a previous Government I was Minister with responsibility for overseas development.</P>
      <P>I am pleased the Government supports the motion. I listened carefully to the debate and this is why I am anxious to acknowledge the role of many Members of the House in visiting the developing world. I visited this area with many Members present and that personal experience means much to all of us. It has added a huge personal dimension to the debate and I thank Members for this. I could list a number of projects in Zambia and Tanzania such as the pre-natal and post-natal maternity clinic in Lusaka, water projects in northern Zambia, the work with AIDS victims by our missionaries, who are an important element of the Irish diaspora, and the NGOs working in Sudan, Somalia and Rwanda. We all have many personal experiences which add to the strength of Ireland's position in relation to development aid. This is why I am pleased the Government supports the motion and we must press on with progress in this area.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Senator Henry mentioned the WTO. I moved from a development to a trade ministry and it is of fundamental importance that we recognise the linkage between global trade policies and development. Everybody agrees our aid projects <Col N="500" /> are well focused and I pay tribute to our staff at home and abroad. I work with dedicated people but the individuals in the Department of Foreign Affairs who work on these projects at home and abroad are hugely committed.</P>
    <P>However, there is a bigger picture in that global policies on trade must be linked to development. In Seattle, I was proud that the Government agreed to provide US$1 million to the legal advisory service for the least developed countries to help them with the huge and complex problems they encounter in dealing with trade issues. I am also pleased the Government supported the approach of providing duty free access to the European Union and global markets for goods from the developing world. They are important trade issues which will affect the lives of individuals in countries where the people truly are the poorest of the poor. As a Minister of State with responsibility for trade, I am pleased I can pursue these policies.</P>
    <P>I was glad to go to Seattle, although I heard Senator Ryan complaining that a Minister of State was going. However, he did not understand that development was a major issue in Seattle. I was proud to be able to put the Irish development agenda firmly on the global agenda of the Seattle meeting. There is also a need at global level for co-ordination between the UN, the WTO, the IMF, the World Bank and the ILO. They are tremendous organisations but some of them need to be rationalised and reorganised. As we start a new millennium, there is a need for these organisations to work together.</P>
    <P>I thank the Cathaoirleach for allowing me to speak. Some of the issues raised, such as Chechnya, could be addressed and perhaps Senators could follow them up with me. I will be glad to answer their queries on behalf of the Government. I thank Senators for their contributions because this area is close to my heart. I am pleased and proud that I was part of a previous Government, as Senator Costello noted, which increased the aid budget. As a member of this Government, I want to work with the Senators to ensure that we continue to make progress.</P>
    <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
    <Speaker pid="BrianMullooly" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>When is it proposed to sit again?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WillieFarrell" hpid="Mr. Farrell Mr. Farrell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Farrell</NameTxt>
      <P>Tomorrow at 10.30 a.m.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Adjournment Matter." RHead="- Garda Stations">
    <Title>Adjournment Matter. - Garda Stations.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="ErnieCaffrey" hpid="Mr. Caffrey Mr. Caffrey">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Caffrey</NameTxt>
      <P>I welcome the Minister of State. This is an important matter for Ballina and the surrounding area. I am sure the Minister of State is aware of the position from her briefing in the Department but it is over ten years since the campaign first started in Ballina for a new Garda <Col N="501" /> station in the town. The current station is housed in an old, practically antediluvian building. It has been altered and improved and whatever could be done with its limited facilities has been done.</P>
      <P>The people of the town and the Garda Síochána are concerned because the station is located in a cul-de-sac and there is only one way out. Given the imagination of criminals nowadays, it is not difficult to visualise what could happen in circumstances where the Garda station is located in a cul-de-sac and only has one entrance. In addition, there are houses on both sides of the station. For this and many other reasons, a new Garda station is needed in Ballina.</P>
      <P>In provincial towns two types of building reflect the prosperity and activity in the area and people's attitudes in terms of the tidy towns competition and other aspects of a town's environment. These are the municipal buildings and the Garda station. They are a barometer of a town's prosperity and reflect the ambience of an area. This is another reason Ballina should get a new Garda station.</P>
      <P>Ironically, tomorrow night Ballina Urban District Council is due to discuss, among other matters, the development of a new municipal building for the town. The current building is over 20 years old and it is not in the same condition as the Garda station. However, given the level of development in the town, councillors believe it needs a new municipal building. Thankfully, this is within the remit of county and urban district councillors and the Department has also provided a grant for such a building. Fortunately, it is not necessary to involve the Office of Public Works. It has been looking at sites and options for a Garda station for the past ten years, but nothing has happened.</P>
      <P>Ballina has progressed in many respects over the past ten years. It has grown out of all proportion. There has been a big increase in population with a concurrent increase in crime levels. Every time the population increases, the crime level also increases. Despite zero tolerance, the level of petty crime, particularly in provincial towns, is increasing. Drugs are also becoming a problem in provincial towns. Heretofore, they were only evident in major cities and centres of population but many provincial towns now have the associated crime. This is another reason that Ballina needs a new, state of the art Garda station with modern technology.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>At present, the station has 24 or 25 gardaí and four or five sergeants. This is a considerable number of people who have to work in unsuitable conditions. Given that we are at the start of a new millennium, I ask the Minister of State to consider, in conjunction with the Office of Public Works, what can be done to expedite this matter. This problem has been ongoing for too long &ndash; ten years is a long time to toy with an idea. We are told small developments have taken place but at the end of each year, nothing has really changed. Progress should be made now given the availability of Exchequer funds and the Govern<Col N="502" /> ment's emphasis on crime prevention and control, zero tolerance and crime related issues.</P>
    <P>There has been no increase in the incidence of crime in many areas as a result of the way the Garda is tackling crime. It is one step ahead of the criminal on many occasions and that is how it should be. There must be a physical infrastructure in place if one is to operate an efficient Garda force. We do not have such an infrastructure in Ballina.</P>
    <P>Largescale industrial development is currently taking place in Ballina, with one of the biggest industrial complexes in the world, Coca-Cola, due to open there shortly. When the Taoiseach visited the premises last week he was extremely impressed with the scale of the operation and the contribution it will make to the local and national economy. Two thirds of the world's requirement for Coca-Cola will be produced in Ballina. That is a major boost for the town. Our infrastructure must reflect our status. Part of the required infrastructure is a new Garda station, previous appeals for which have fallen on deaf ears. I am sure the Minister can provide some light at the end of the tunnel.</P>
    <P>I have tried to present an overview of the situation. I am sure the Minister of State is not familiar with the current physical structure in Ballina. If she visited Ballina she would see the inadequacy of the current building to cater for a modern police force.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MaryWallace" hpid="Miss M. Wallace Miss M. Wallace">
      <NameTxt>Minister of State at the Department of Justice, Equality and Law Reform (Miss M. Wallace)</NameTxt>
      <P>I thank Senator Caffrey for raising this issue and for the very strong case he has made for a new Garda station in Ballina. The Minister of State at the Department of Finance, Deputy Cullen, could not be here this evening but asked me to inform the Senator of the current position.</P>
      <P>Every effort to acquire a suitable site is being accorded top priority by the commissioners property management services and the Commissioners of Public Works are aware of the need for a new Garda station in Ballina. Location of the site is a critical factor to enable the gardaí to discharge their operational responsibilities. The need for a reasonably central location limits to some extent the number of suitable sites for consideration. Nevertheless, the Commissioners of Public Works recently identified a number of suitable sites. They were unsuccessful in securing a site which they tendered for last year, despite the fact that they tendered at what they believed was the upper limit of the value of the site to the State. Towards the end of last year the commissioners sought to purchase a potentially suitable site, this time at auction, but again they were outbid. They are currently in negotiations to acquire a suitable site. It is too early to say if these discussions will be successful but I am advised they are hopeful of a positive outcome.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The commissioners have a definite preference to purchase a site and build a Garda station in Ballina. However, they have had indications that <Col N="503" /> some developers may be willing to deal with them on the basis of providing a site and designing and building a Garda station on it. They have not ruled out this option and if the current negotiations fail they will actively explore this and other options.</P>
    <P>The Minister of State, Deputy Cullen, has <Col N="504" /> asked me to assure Senator Caffrey and the House that the Commissioners of Public Works will leave no avenue unexplored in their effort to secure a suitable site for a Garda station in Ballina at an early date.</P>
    <P>The Seanad adjourned at 8.16 p.m. until 10.30 a.m. on Thursday, 17 February 2000.</P>
  </MainHeading>
</Debate>