<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE Debate SYSTEM "../Debate.dtd"[]>
<Debate DocTitle="Seanad Debate" Day="Fri" Date="16" Month="May" Year="1997" Vol="151" No="13" DateIrish="Dé hAoine, 16 Bealtaine 1997" DateEnglish="Friday, 16 May 1997" House="S" CommitteeEng="" CommitteeIr="" SubNameEng="" cnum="0">
  <MainHeading Type="Prelude" LHead="" RHead="">
    <Title>
    </Title>
    <P>
      <Col N="1061" /> Chuaigh an Cathaoirleach i gceannas ar 10.30 a.m.</P>
    <P Just="Center">
      <i>Paidir.</i>
    </P>
    <P Just="Center">
      <i>Prayer.</i>
    </P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Order of" RHead="Business">
    <Title>Order of Business.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFallon" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Before calling the Leader, I wish to make some comments as this is probably the last sitting day of the present Seanad.  I have no doubt that some Members may be going on to higher things in the Lower House and I thank all Members for their co-operation.  I cannot but recall my two predecessors and Senator Gordon Wilson, whom we lost during the lifetime of this Seanad.  I also thank Members for their co-operation not only in recent months but when I was Government Whip and before that, Opposition Whip.  I thank the Clerk of the Seanad, the Clerk Assistant, the stenographers, ushers and all staff of the House.  After the events elsewhere yesterday, many Senators will be participating in the first of the summer festivals on 6 June, and they have my good wishes.  The Seanad elections come later.</P>
      <P>I also thank those Senators who have been temporary Chairmen and particularly the Leas-Chathaoirleach, Senator Mullooly.  I also thank Members who at times co-operated fully on the Order of Business.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MauriceManning" hpid="Mr. Manning Mr. Manning">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Manning</NameTxt>
      <P>Today's business is items 1 and 2.  Item 2 is not to commence before 12.15 p.m. if that is agreeable and I thank the Opposition for their co-operation on these matters.</P>
      <P>This is the end of the Seanad as it is presently constituted and it has been the second longest Seanad in the history of the State.  The 27th Dáil has just ended but this is the 18th Seanad in its present form.  The only Seanad that lasted longer was the Seanad of 1938 to 1943 so this one has almost run its full term.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>This has been a unique Seanad in that there has been a change of Government during its lifetime and it has seen Senators cross the floor to different positions in an orderly way.  We have even had a colleague cross the floor and move back again.  The smooth transition speaks volumes for the level of co-operation and the civilised relationships in the House, and the change was effected with the minimum disruption.  I wish <Col N="1062" /> to record my grateful thanks to the Opposition and particularly Senators Wright, Fitzgerald and O'Toole for their co-operation in making the work of the House possible in unusual circumstances.</P>
    <P>The quality of debate and input to legislation during the lifetime of the Seanad has been extremely high.  A number of important Bills bear the imprint of this House which improved them greatly.  We had a number of important initiatives during the lifetime of the House.  It will be a time of change during the next Seanad, whoever is in Government, but we have shown we are ready for and capable of change and we are not afraid to face the challenges which may lie ahead.</P>
    <P>I join with the Cathaoirleach in remembering three wonderful people who died during the lifetime of the Seanad.  All three deaths were sudden and unexpected.  We all have warm and happy memories of our colleagues, Gordon Wilson, Seán Fallon and Liam Naughten, three of nature's gentlemen.</P>
    <P>Like the Cathaoirleach, I thank the staff of the House.  I also thank the media for the good and honest coverage of the proceedings of this House. We all feel the coverage should be more extensive but at least the coverage during this session, especially on &ldquo;Oireachtas Report&rdquo; and in <i>The Irish Times,</i> has been fair and accurate.  We cannot ask for more than that.</P>
    <P>I wish all colleagues well.  I wish every success, God speed and good luck to those who aspire to go to a lower place by standing for election to the other House.  I also send my heartfelt good luck to those who seek the honour of serving in this House again.  I thank colleagues for their co-operation.</P>
    <Speaker pid="GVWright" hpid="Mr. Wright Mr. Wright">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Wright</NameTxt>
      <P>I thank the Leader for his kind remarks at the close of this Seanad, which should be seen as a successful one.  As the Leader pointed out, there have been many changes during its lifetime, including the unique handover of power.  Legislation benefited from the numbers in the House and the kind response of Ministers. The legislation is better as a result of the many amendments made here.</P>
      <P>I will remember this Seanad for the deaths of three distinguished colleagues, Gordon Wilson and two Cathaoirligh, Liam Naughten and Seán Fallon, who were personal friends to us all.</P>
      <P>I thank the Leader and all those who helped me during my term as Leader of the House and in Opposition.  I pay special tribute to two of my colleagues, Senator Mullooly, who was Chief Whip during my time as Leader, and Senator Fitzgerald, who is Chief Whip in Opposition. Anyone who has played that role realises its importance and the time given by those who accept it.  I also thank you, a Chathaoirligh, the Clerk, Clerk Assistant, the staff and press.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I wish all my colleagues who are standing for the Dáil or Seanad the best of good luck.  I thank all those I have had the chance to work with for <Col N="1063" /> their support and I look forward to seeing everyone again in the next couple of months.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JoeOToole" hpid="Mr. O'Toole Mr. O'Toole">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Toole</NameTxt>
      <P>The Order of Business is agreed. We, on the Independent benches, would like to be associated with the votes of thanks to the Clerk, Clerk Assistant and the other members of staff who have been extraordinarily helpful and overworked during the past few years.  We are not the employers of the staff of the House but we should recognise the effort it takes to deal with 200 amendments to a Bill between 10 p.m. and 2 in the morning.  That might be a slight exaggeration but the work they do is extraordinary, in terms of volume and the focus required to get it right.  I appreciate it and, as an Independent Member of the House, I also appreciate the evenhanded advice of staff which has always been available to all sides of the House.  They are very fair and, although I am probably one of the more awkward people with which they must deal, I appreciate their effort.</P>
      <P>I remember with sadness the events which brought the Cathaoirleach into office, and also remember his two predecessors and Senator Gordon Wilson.  It has been a sad time but they will always be in our memories and we have paid due tribute to them.</P>
      <P>I support the points made by both Senator Wright and the Leader.  I thank them both and those who support them, especially the Whips.  I also thank my parish colleague, Senator Fitzgerald for the co-operation shown to us over the term of this Seanad and my colleague Senator Ross who not only changed sides twice but also moved up and down twice on this side and who at all times kept teachers in focus with that great and unwavering love for them which he has always shown.</P>
      <P>This has been an extraordinarily useful Seanad. When the history of Seanad Éireann is written, the impact this one has made on legislation will be seen to have been tremendous.  I felt a great sense of relief yesterday when the Supreme Court rejected the Employment Equality Bill, as it no doubt will the Equal Status Bill.  Despite the protestations of the Minister for Equality and Law Reform that it was rejected for the wrong reason, I do not care whether I win by a goal or a point so long as teachers are protected from that abominable legislation which I hope will not be repeated.</P>
      <P>This has been a very good Seanad.  It is the first time in my ten years as a Member that Ministers, because of the numbers in the House, had to listen to arguments and to show flexibility and reasonableness.  Ministers were able to tell their advisers that certain decisions were political and outline the way they wanted things done.  This has been good for Ministers as it has allowed them to &ldquo;find their oats&rdquo;, as it would be said in another business.  It has brought the best from many of them and has been very helpful and progressive.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="1064" /> Coverage of the House by the press has been very good and we should compliment RTÉ and <i>The Irish Times</i> which continuously cover the Seanad.  I again appeal to <i>The Examiner</i> and the <i>Irish Independent</i> to reconsider their coverage.</P>
    <P>I start my election campaign by asking all graduates of NUI colleges to consider me as their highest option when they receive their ballot papers.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MauriceManning" hpid="Mr. Manning Mr. Manning">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Manning</NameTxt>
      <P>Likewise.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeOToole" hpid="Mr. O'Toole Mr. O'Toole">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Toole</NameTxt>
      <P>More importantly, we have discussed the issues of constitutional reform and I hope the people of this House who stand for election, either to the Dáil, Seanad or other places, carry themselves with dignity and I wish them well.  I hope the undemocratic nature of Seanad representation in elections will be addressed between now and the next election so that colleagues of ours in third level, who are disenfranchised because they are from different universities, will be included to create an extended franchise.</P>
      <P>I thank the Cathaoirleach for his courtesy at all times and my colleague, Senator Mullooly, the Leas-Chathaoirleach, and I wish him well.  I thank people on all sides and the staff of the House for their support.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SamMcAughtry" hpid="Mr. McAughtry Mr. McAughtry">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McAughtry</NameTxt>
      <P>I am glad of the opportunity to say a few words about my experience here.  I have had a good many experiences in my lifetime. I have been lucky and unlucky.  I have experienced many lows and highs.  My experience here would certainly go down as one of the highest points of my life because of the hunger I have, coming from the North, for democracy and all its aspects and benefits.  This is what I have experienced here in the past 15 months.</P>
      <P>I am full of admiration for those who nominated me for this post but I wonder if they knew anything about me.  I do not have a reputation for respecting the man in charge.  I was like a fish out of water in the Northern Ireland Civil Service with all its hierarchical ranks and the lickspittling that goes on in that sort of organisation in order to get on in life.  I came here full of admiration that anyone would take a chance with me not knowing what I was liable to say in the House.  I spent the first six months watching, listening and lapping it up.</P>
      <P>We had a Unionist Government in Northern Ireland which was discredited for a number of reasons.  However, the one good thing one could say about it was that its Ministers were accessible. This was a wonderful benefit.  Ministers and those in the Oireachtas who hold the reins of power are accessible.  This is true democracy.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Three quarters of a century have elapsed since independence.  The South has grown apart from the North.  However, I have witnessed a bridge in terms of Border colleagues who speak with the same voice as me.  I have been able to sit and reflect on history and on what the future holds.  I <Col N="1065" /> hope the future will hold good in Northern Ireland under the British Government and this enlightened country.</P>
    <P>Despite comments I have made in support of my political views, I have enormous admiration for the way both sides in this House co-operate. I hope we will achieve full democracy in Northern Ireland similar to this State and I hope the apparatus of law and order will be supported by all the people.  I have enjoyed my stay in this House and thank Senators for the courtesy shown to me and the true and warm friendship I have experienced.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MickLanigan" hpid="Mr. Lanigan Mr. Lanigan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lanigan</NameTxt>
      <P>A Chathaoirligh, thank you for the courtesy you have shown to all Members during your time in office.  We have never abused you or departed from the rules of the Order of Business.  I hope you will be back in the Chair again and that all Senators will be back in this House if they do not aspire to the other House.</P>
      <P>Senator McAughtry has been a Member of the House for 15 months.  I do not agree with his politics but I agree with much of what he says.  He has addressed this House in a reasonable manner and I hope his time here has given him a better understanding of those of us who hold an opposing political view.</P>
      <P>I thank Senators and the staff of the House for their courtesy.  We should not hold up the Minister for too long.  Anyone with sense will ensure that the Prompt Payments Bill will pass in ten seconds.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ShaneRoss" hpid="Mr. Ross Mr. Ross">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Ross</NameTxt>
      <P>I hope that was not Senator McAughtry's farewell speech.  Let us hope he is back under whatever type of Government is elected on 5 June.  When Senator O'Toole puts on his trade union hat he normally does not speak for all the Independent Senators.  However, on this occasion I agree with his comments about the staff of the House.  We are unanimous on that. Their help is not only appreciated but vital.  If the truth be known they do far more work on the drafting and amendments to Bills than Senators. We are very grateful for that.</P>
      <P>I will raise one serious issue with the Leader. Before the Taoiseach gets completely and utterly consumed in the election campaign, will he address a problem in his own constituency of Meath?  Five miles north-west of Navan the most appalling vandalism has taken place in the last few days.  An ancient historic site has been destroyed by bulldozers.  The site is 2,500 years old and the Tailteann games were held there.  It is a matter of extraordinary concern that a national monument such as this was bulldozed, apparently to the ignorance of the county council and with no interference from the relevant Department. We have a Heritage Council and many quangos whose tasks include preserving historic sites. However, it seems nothing was done to prevent the destruction of this site.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Nevertheless, there is hope.  It is not too late to rescue the site.  A small amount of the mound remains and it can be rescued and restored.  The <Col N="1066" /> least the State should do is acquire the site immediately.  Its destruction appears to have been the result of a series of ill informed mistakes.  A remedy is possible and I ask the Leader to tell the Minister for Arts, Culture and the Gaeltacht and the Taoiseach that the Seanad regards this as a matter of urgency which could be remedied before the general election.</P>
    <Speaker pid="WillieFarrell" hpid="Mr. Farrell Mr. Farrell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Farrell</NameTxt>
      <P>I endorse the praise that has been expressed for the Leader of the House, the Cathaoirleach and the Leader of the Opposition. The House has worked smoothly and efficiently as a result of their combined efforts.  I also thank the staff of the House, particularly the ushers who do a great job looking after the visitors we invite to the House.  They are also most helpful when people call and they go to trouble beyond the call of duty to ensure the relevant Members are contacted.</P>
      <P>I wish to pay a special tribute to the Northern Ireland Senators who were Members of the House over the past ten years.  They offered us great insight into Northern Ireland and our debates on that subject were the better for it.  I have no doubt that we helped to contribute a small measure of peace to the North, regardless of what others might say.  The northern and southern views have been represented in the Seanad and they have informed discussions about the problem in a clear and forthright manner.</P>
      <P>I wish candidates for the Dáil every success in the election.  However, I make a special appeal to teachers and university lecturers to encourage the youth to vote.  There appears to be an awful cynicism about politics on the part of the youth and it is encouraged by the media.  Members who went to Mozambique and other countries to monitor their elections realise how much the native populations appreciated their right to vote, often for the first time.  Ireland is a democracy but people often do not exercise their vote.  It is up to every political leader to encourage people to vote, regardless of who benefits from it.</P>
      <P>I wish a safe journey to each Member of the House who will be on the circuit of Ireland hoping to secure re-election to the Seanad.  It is a hazardous business.  Drive carefully and le cúnamh Dé, beimíd go léir ar ais arís.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PaschalMooney" hpid="Mr. Mooney Mr. Mooney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Mooney</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator Farrell sounded a little like me on the radio when I say goodnight at the end of a programme.  Perhaps he has a future in broadcasting should he decide to choose an alternative profession.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I concur with the comments of my colleagues. However, I wish to raise a matter with the Leader of the House, despite this being the final day of this Seanad.  I was extremely disturbed by a report in the <i>Sunday Observer</i> which stated that the association of frozen food manufacturers intends to add large quantities of water to processed fish without including that information on the label.  Sadly, a substantial amount of frozen fish is imported into this country even though <Col N="1067" /> there are excellent Irish products.  Since fish fingers are part of the stable diet of many school children, if this initiative is allowed to proceed unchecked it could have serious implications for the national diet.  This may appear to be a frivolous issue but I have reflected on it in recent days and this is my final opportunity to raise it in a national forum.  I ask the Leader to convey my concern to the Minister for Health.  Many people would share my concern if they were aware of this initiative which emanated from the United Kingdom.  Permission is being sought to add large quantities of water to frozen fish, particularly fish fingers, without stating that fact on the package.</P>
    <P>As a Border Senator, irrespective of what Government is returned after the election, I hope it will ensure that both sides of the divide and the two traditions in Northern Ireland continue to be represented in the House.  My friend and colleague, Senator Lanigan, said he did not agree with Senator McAughtry's politics but he admired much of what he said.  The only difference between Senator McAughtry, Senator Lanigan, me and others is that we are Irish Nationalists and he is an Irish Unionist.  However, although that is a fundamental division, more unites us than divides us.</P>
    <P>My colleagues and I did not vote for Senator McAughtry but we have come to admire his fearless stand on many issues.  He has said unpopular things but he has also made points which needed to be made to inform and educate a Southern Nationalist electorate which has not always appreciated the genuine fears and concerns of the Unionist community in Northern Ireland.  If there is to be a political settlement on this island, we must learn to understand and appreciate the concerns of that section of the population who will live among us without comprising our basic beliefs and attitudes.  I hope whatever Administration is returned will ensure that there is continued representation in the House of the two traditions in Northern Ireland.  The House is enhanced and gifted by their presence.</P>
    <P>In common with my colleagues, I wish everybody well in the forthcoming election.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MauriceManning" hpid="Mr. Manning Mr. Manning">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Manning</NameTxt>
      <P>From what I have read and heard from Professor George Eogan, I agree with Senator Ross about what happened in County Meath.  I will contact the Minister for Arts, Culture and the Gaeltacht and the Taoiseach's Office immediately after the Order of Business to ask if something can be salvaged from those events.</P>
      <P>I also agree with Senator Ross and everybody else in hoping that Senator McAughtry returns to the House after the election.  All Members were impressed by his contribution this morning.</P>
      <P>Senator Mooney raised the addition of water to fish.  If the Senator gives me the specific report I will bring it to the attention of the Director of Consumer Affairs and the Minister.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="1068" /> Order of Business agreed to.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="ICC Bank (Amendment) Bill, 1997:" RHead="Second Stage">
    <Title>ICC Bank (Amendment) Bill, 1997: Second Stage.</Title>
    <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That the Bill be now read a Second Time.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="RuairiQuinn" hpid="Minister for Finance (Mr. R. Quinn) Ruairí Quinn">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Finance (Mr. R. Quinn)</NameTxt>
      <P>I thank Senators for agreeing at short notice to consider this Bill today.  Although the Bill is a short and technical one, it is very important to ICC Bank because it will ensure that the current phase of very rapid growth in the bank's activities will not be halted by the existing limits on its borrowings and authorised share capital.  The Bill is a reflection on how far the bank has developed since it was first established in 1933 as the Industrial Credit Corporation.  However, it is also a testimony to how faithful the bank has remained over all those years to its original mandate.</P>
      <P>The ICC was set up with the task of promoting the development of industry in Ireland.  This was a daunting task in the under-developed Ireland of the time and it was made doubly difficult by the great depression which was ravaging the world economy.  Despite this background, the ICC persevered and made a valuable contribution to the economy, while turning in a consistently profitable performance since its inception.  It is a measure of this performance that, despite an injection of less than £12 million in State equity in 64 years, the ICC has today a balance sheet amounting to more than £1,300 million.  Moreover, in the past five years alone, it contributed nearly £12 million to the Exchequer in dividends and more than £14 million in tax.  Last year operating profits came to £13 million.  The Exchequer received £4.5 million of this, roughly divided between tax and dividend payments. Retained profits will strengthen the balance sheet and enhance the value of the State's interest in the company.</P>
      <P>In recognition of the ICC's crucial role, successive Ministers for Finance have ensured the legislation governing the ICC has been amended to meet its evolving needs in light of the changing circumstances of the economy.  The last such legislation was in 1992 when the name of the company was changed to ICC Bank to underline its commercial nature.  That legislation also raised the bank's borrowing limit to £1,300 million, which is one of the subjects of the Bill before this House today.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>This Bill is a simple technical one intended to raise the present statutory limits on the bank's borrowing and authorised share capital.  It has nothing to do with, nor any implications for, any decision which may be taken in future on the structure of the State banking sector.  The Bill is needed now because the bank's rapid growth over the past two years or so is pushing it perilously close to the limit on its borrowing and also to the minimum of subscribed share capital which the Central Bank requires it to have for prudential <Col N="1069" /> purposes.  On the basis of recent trends, the borrowing limit could be reached around the middle of the year.  At that stage, the bank would have to call a halt to new lending and investment if its borrowing limit was not raised.  Such a development would hurt the bank and deprive its customers, particularly small and medium-sized enterprises, of its support.  In such circumstances, it would be remiss of the Government not to provide for the future expansion of the bank pending a decision on the restructuring of the State banking sector.</P>
    <P>I will elaborate on the bank's borrowing and capital needs.  As Senators will be aware, borrowing is a vital part of a bank's business.  As it applies to banks, the term &ldquo;borrowing&rdquo; means the sum total of deposits placed with it, as well as all other forms of borrowing.  Thus, when a bank accepts a deposit, it increases its borrowing and its capital base at the same time.  It is this which gives the bank the capacity to on-lend to its customers. The more a bank borrows for on-lending, the greater will be the size of its business.</P>
    <P>We all know what can happen if a bank develops its business on the basis of risky loans. It is here that the questions of prudence and the quality of loans as assets comes in.  Experience has shown that a certain level of bad debts may arise on any loan portfolio.  For that reason, bank supervisors and regulators have determined that credit institutions must have a minimum capital to be able to absorb these bad debts.  The minimum is set as a percentage of risk-weighted assets.  For banks such as ICC Bank, the Central Bank has set a limit of 10 per cent.  Shareholders' funds, which consist mainly of subscribed capital and retained earnings, are the basis for determining the capital adequacy of a bank.</P>
    <P>In the case of ICC Bank, borrowing at present is just £70 million short of the limit of £1,300 million set out in the 1992 Act.  Moreover, the authorised share capital of £12 million is already fully subscribed and other shareholders' funds are almost fully committed.  These limits will have to be raised if the bank is to continue to grow and support small and medium-sized enterprises, a sector whose contribution to output and employment in recent years has been crucial.</P>
    <P>Lest there be any misunderstanding, I will make two specific points about what the Bill does not provide for.  There will not be an increase in the limit on the amount of the bank's borrowing which is guaranteed by the Minister for Finance. The limit on the borrowing so guaranteed stands at £1,000 million, which is the same as it was before the overall borrowing limit was last increased in 1992.  This was a deliberate policy at the time to reduce the proportion of the bank's borrowing which carried a State guarantee and it is the firm intention to reduce the absolute amount so guaranteed in the future.  The bank's management fully agree with this intention which is in keeping with the bank's commercial mandate.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="1070" /> My second point is that the Bill does not provide for an increase in subscribed share capital. The proposed increase in the authorised share capital is an enabling provision and is completely in line with practice in the private sector where it is common for even small companies to have a large authorised share capital.  Consequently, the proposal does not commit the Minister for Finance to any additional subscription of capital. Any such decision will be taken on the basis of a rigorous assessment of the bank's evolving capital needs and of the prospective return it will yield to the Exchequer.</P>
    <P>While the proposed increases in the limits on borrowing and authorised share capital may seem sizeable, they are not in reality.  In the first place, the increase of £1,000 million to £2,300 million in the borrowing limit will, on the basis of recent trends, only provide for the bank's expansion for the next four to five years.  In this context, Senators will note that the last increase in the limit was five years ago in 1992.  Four to five years seems to be a reasonable period for which to make provision now for the bank's borrowing needs.  I should also mention that, last year, this House agreed to a similar increase from a similar base in the borrowing limit of ACC Bank.</P>
    <P>Secondly, the increase in authorised share capital to £40 million has to be judged in the light of the fact that the existing limit of £12 million has been in place since 1971, over 25 years ago.  Since then, there have been fundamental changes in the market for financial services, including the intensification of competition, the unprecedented development in the number and variety of financial instruments and services, and tighter capital adequacy requirements.  Against that background, and given the particular requirements of a niche bank such as ICC Bank, it is reasonable to provide for an adequate increase in its authorised share capital.  However, as I have already stated, and emphasise again, this is an enabling provision and not a commitment to subscribe such capital.</P>
    <P>Before addressing details of the Bill, I would like to outline for the House the salient features of the bank's development since the Act of 1992 was passed.  As I indicated already, the 1992 Act underlined the bank's commercial nature by changing its name and raising the limit on its borrowing. The Act confirmed that orientation further by enabling the bank to provide all modern banking and financial services, and by making it subject to regulation and supervision by the Central Bank, a provision which also enhanced the international reputation of the bank as a sound, well run financial institution.</P>
    <P>Since 1992, the bank has expanded the services it offers while remaining focused on the development of small and medium sized enterprises, a vital sector of our economy.  In this, I would mention in particular the bank's venture capital activities. The venture capital market in Ireland has grown rapidly in recent years as successful entrepreneurs became increasingly aware of the benefits which venture capital can bestow on their <Col N="1071" /> enterprises.  The bank responded to this by establishing a subsidiary, ICC Venture Capital, which manages a number of specialist venture capital funds.  Through this, the bank has become the prime venture capital institution in Ireland.  It has been particularly successful in attracting investors through the BES scheme.  The bank's portfolio of venture capital investments now amounts to £65 million and it has funds of over £42 million available to invest in suitable projects.</P>
    <P>In 1993, the bank set up a special deposit taking facility, ICC Investment Bank &mdash; ICCIB &mdash; to attract deposits without the benefit of a State guarantee.  The ICCIB has been very successful in this endeavour, so much so that today its funds account for about 30 per cent of the bank group's overall financing.  While the fact that ICCIB is supervised by the Central Bank has contributed to this success, the major factor has been the reputation which the bank has built for itself and its strong balance sheet.  Along with the bank's management, I very much welcome the diminishing reliance of the bank on State guarantees, and the continued success of ICCIB in attracting unguaranteed funds will sustain this positive development.</P>
    <P>Since last January, the bank also has an operation in the IFSC which provides full asset financing and treasury management for corporate customers with overseas undertakings.  In that short time, it has developed a balance sheet of the equivalent of nearly £50 million in a number of foreign currencies.</P>
    <P>The bank has been involved in international consulting and training for over ten years through its involvement with, and shareholding in, International Development Ireland Ltd., IDI.  To this end, it has built up a core staff with broad expertise in providing management and technical assistance to institutions in developing countries and transitional economies.  Following the successful and lucrative sale of IDI earlier this year, the bank made a strategic decision to continue providing international consultancy and training services directly through a subsidiary, ICC Consulting. The expertise of the bank in this area and the reputation it has already made should ensure the continued success of its consultancy arm.  The bank has also enlarged its branch network and in 1996 it opened a branch in Belfast, its first outside the State.  Excluding head office, the bank now has five branches.</P>
    <P>The achievements I have listed are considerable, especially in a context of increasing competition and eroding margins.  They have resulted in the bank being a broadly based financial institution providing a wide range of essential services to Irish business.  Much of its success in this area can be attributed to its tight control of costs.  In this context it is appropriate to mention the exceptional provision of almost £4 million which the bank made in its 1996 accounts to fund a voluntary early retirement and severance packet, internal restructuring and the development of <Col N="1072" /> new systems.  This is in keeping with the bank's relentless efforts to improve performance and profitability.  On the basis of its past performance, I have every confidence the bank will continue on its course of solid, well based development.</P>
    <P>I now turn to the main provisions.  Section 1 covers definitions and is self explanatory.  Section 2 amends section 5 of the ICC Bank Act, 1992, by providing for an increase in the statutory limit on the bank's borrowings from the current level of £1,300 million to £2,300 million.  The last increase was in 1992.  The increase now proposed is intended to accommodate projected growth in the bank's activities in the coming years.</P>
    <P>Section 3 amends section 2 of the Industrial Credit (Amendment) Act, 1971, by providing an increase in the limit on the authorised share capital from the current level of £12 million to £40 million.  The last such increase was in 1971 when the limit was increased from £10 million.  As indicated earlier, the proposed increase relates to the authorised share capital of the bank and does not commit the Minister for Finance to subscribe all or any of this capital.</P>
    <P>Section 4 is a standard provision in Bills of this kind.  It requires ICC Bank plc to alter its memorandum and articles of association to make them consistent with the provisions of the Bill.</P>
    <P>Section 5 gives the short title, collective citation and construction.  I commend this Bill to the House.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MickLanigan" hpid="Mr. Lanigan Mr. Lanigan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lanigan</NameTxt>
      <P>I welcome the Bill.  It gives us an opportunity to discuss the banking system and the anomalies within it.  Banks exist to make money and I have no problem with that but the manner in which bankers in general treat customers is disgraceful. The personalities have gone out of banking.  The plastic card has replaced the customer orientation and I hope ICC will not pursue the same direction as the major banks.</P>
      <P>No bank can be commended for the manner in which it deals with customers.  Their attitude is, the less they see of customers or have to deal with them the better.  The Minister suggested ICC is downsizing in terms of staff.  This will result in reducing customer satisfaction and relationships which is something to be deplored.</P>
      <P>It is vital for those starting in business that they develop proper banking structures.  Unfortunately, there is no such thing as customer relationships anymore.  Banks work with reams of paper.  They do not want to know the person with the big hands and the big shovel who knows how to make a few bob.  Computers do not relate to people and banks no longer relate to people either.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>In my relationship with ICC through certain companies, I have found it honourable and decent.  Its objectives have been positive.  This Bill gives the extra capital it requires to compete in the world of banking.  Banks are making inordinate profits on the sweat and blood of ordinary people and those profits are growing daily.  I sincerely hope ICC will remember where it came <Col N="1073" /> from and what it is supposed to do.  I would like to see ICC as an alternative to the major banks. Giving it a statutory increase in borrowings from £1,300 million to £2,300 million should not encourage it to join the rat race in the banking world.  I hope that by increasing its size and borrowing limit it will not become another major player in the banking market.  I hope ICC will have a role to play in servicing the borrowing requirements of small entrepreneurs who will grow with the bank and not allow it to take over their businesses as has happened with many of the major banks.</P>
    <P>The Bill is a technical one but it provides an opportunity for ICC to become more competitive in the market.  If that happens through the increase in its borrowing limit I hope it will not cease to be customer oriented.  Even though ICC can grow, the Minister should ensure it does not become totally non-customer oriented as other banks have done.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PaddyBurke" hpid="Mr. Burke Mr. Burke">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Burke</NameTxt>
      <P>I welcome the Bill.  It is only right that ICC should receive the borrowing requirements it needs.  I have some knowledge of working with the ICC in relation to loans.  Since ICC's borrowing requirement is to be increased, I hope it will stay with the small and medium sized businesses. It has operated well in the past and it is crucial that such businesses should have a bank they can rely on.</P>
      <P>I compliment the ICC.  In recent years we have seen big changes in its attitude.  It is much more customer friendly now than in the past.  It has taken on a number of big projects including a joint venture with the Urban District Council in Castlebar.  It has acquired expertise in this field which will not be lost in future.</P>
      <P>The Minister has presided over the lowest interests rates this country has ever experienced. That is because of the prudent way he has managed the economy.  However, there are too many banking institutions.  While I appreciate the point that the more such institutions one has, the more competition there is and, thus, more pressure to lower interest rates, the banking institutions still get their pound of flesh.  That means the customer must pay. The more pressure the Minister for Finance can keep on the banks the better because it will be to the benefit of customers and ordinary people generally. We have seen nothing but luxurious bank buildings in prime town sites, which all cost money. In every town with a population of 7,000 upwards one finds these banking institutions.</P>
      <P>I compliment the Minister on the way he is managing the economy and I hope interest rates will be kept at their present levels.  It is only right that ICC, which is providing a great service to small and medium sized businesses, should have its borrowing limits increased by £1,000 million to £2,300 million.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ShaneRoss" hpid="Mr. Ross Mr. Ross">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Ross</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not share the unanimity which is anticipated by the House on this Bill.  The Minister <Col N="1074" /> described it tersely as a short technical Bill, which it is not.  It is technical in the sense that it moves the figures around a bit, but it is an important Bill because it tells us something about the attitude of both Government and Opposition to the ICC &mdash; that is that it should continue to limp along from year to year until the Government decides what to do with it.</P>
      <P>As the Minister rightly said, the last Bill was introduced here in 1992 to increase the ICC's borrowing and it has survived until now.  This Bill is being introduced to increase the ICC's borrowing in case it cannot legally borrow any more during the general election campaign.  We can expect that some years down the road we will get another Bill with identical terms, apart from the figures.</P>
      <P>The Bill is significant and important but not technical because it is a cop out.  On the last sitting day of this Seanad the Bill is saying, in effect, that the Government failed in its policy towards the State banks.  The Government could not make up its mind what it was going to do about them and so it will postpone a decision, as it has done on many matters.  Unfortunately, the Government has been caught on the hop and, in postponing that decision, it has had to take this measure to keep the bank afloat or, as it would put it, to expand and operate as a normal bank.</P>
      <P>The significance is that both this Government and the last announced that a third banking force would be formed comprising the ICC, ACC and TSB.  Had that taken place there would be no necessity for this Bill.  It is necessary, however, because of the complete failure and disagreement between the parties in Government about a third banking force.</P>
      <P>I agree with the Government that the ICC is a Mickey Mouse bank.  Let us be honest about it; it is a pretty small bank operating in a very large market.  I agree with the Minister that if it is to compete with the major banks it should be a great deal larger because in its present form it has no future whatsoever.  We are now giving a lame duck a lease of life for a few more years until we either decide what to do with it or postpone a decision once more.</P>
      <P>It is a pity the Government parties could not reach agree on merging the TSB, ICC and ACC Banks.  It is obvious what the Government should have done with these three banks.  It will happen but not until the Minister, for whom I have a great deal of admiration in certain ways, is out of office.  It is sticking out a mile that the ICC Bank needs to be privatised.</P>
      <P>One of the problems about privatising this bank for many years was that there was a for sale notice outside.  While it is true nobody wanted to buy it, that was in a different climate.  The ICC should again be put up for sale to see if anyone wishes to purchase it.  I am sure the Government would obtain some money if it was floated on the Stock Exchange.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Last year the ICC's profits decreased.  I am tired of people stating that account must be taken <Col N="1075" /> of an exceptional item of £4 million in this regard. Exceptional items, such as those involving voluntary severance packages, are merely accounting tricks.  The ICC's profits rose by a minute amount, even when the exceptional item is taken into account.  These items can be used each year to reduce profits.  The ICC's exceptional item involved severance packages and voluntary redundancies and its profits were reduced.  No one can provide a guarantee that other items of that sort will not be introduced in the future.  The bank's profits have fallen to £8 million and it pays a negligible dividend of £2 million to the Government, which is of no use to it.</P>
    <P>The ICC is a prime candidate for sale, merger, entry to the private sector in a larger form or euthanasia.  I hope the first item on the agenda of the new Government will be the privatisation of the State banks.  The current Administration has an ideological block to taking such action because the Labour Party opposes the privatisation of State assets.  That is the Government's mantra and it is the root of the problem.</P>
    <P>One of the symptoms of this problem and of the bank's non-commercial nature, is its board.  I accept that the members of the board of the ICC are good people and I have no intention of referring to particular personalities.  However, the members of the boards of State banks are political appointees.  The majority of them are chosen not on the basis of talent but on their loyalty and service to political parties.  If the members of the board of a bank are chosen on the basis of past service to political parties, that institution will not be taken as seriously in the marketplace as other banks which do not appoint board members on the basis of political loyalty.</P>
    <P>I have experienced difficulties with the boards of other banks, none of which had any direct connection to the Minister.</P>
    <Speaker pid="RuairiQuinn" hpid="Mr. R. Quinn Mr. R. Quinn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. R. Quinn</NameTxt>
      <P>Is the Senator making a distinction between political loyalties and party political loyalties?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ShaneRoss" hpid="Mr. Ross Mr. Ross">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Ross</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes.  I have experienced difficulties with the boards of other banks because a large number of their members form a clique and are not appointed on merit.  That would not exclude criticism of the boards of the ACC and ICC on the basis that it is Buggins' turn.  When Fianna Fáil returns to office, its friends will be appointed and the current board members will lose their jobs.  That is not a commercial decision and it robs the boards of credibility.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MickLanigan" hpid="Mr. Lanigan Mr. Lanigan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lanigan</NameTxt>
      <P>That is not a &ldquo;daddy&rdquo; syndrome, it is a &ldquo;mammy&rdquo; syndrome.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ShaneRoss" hpid="Mr. Ross Mr. Ross">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Ross</NameTxt>
      <P>According to Senator Lanigan banks should be charities but, if they were, they would not remain in business for long.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Let us put my theory to the test.  When they are sacked by a Minister because they belong to <Col N="1076" /> the wrong party, how often are political appointees approached by other banks because of the great work they did on the boards of the ICC or the ACC?  The answer is that they are not approached.  I defy the Minister to produce a political appointee to whom such an approach was made.  Perhaps he can do so because they might have been appointed to the board of an equally Mickey Mouse operation.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PaddyBurke" hpid="Mr. Burke Mr. Burke">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Burke</NameTxt>
      <P>Does the Senator want to be the first such appointee?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ShaneRoss" hpid="Mr. Ross Mr. Ross">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Ross</NameTxt>
      <P>I am not leaving office.  As a general rule, these people are not approached because their talents are not given serious consideration in banking circles.  They are appointed because they are political heavyweights or because they have been of service to a political party.  That is a big credibility problem for the ICC.  The bank's profits and EPS were down last year &mdash; its figures were not good compared to the profit increases for other banks.  The ICC is not expanding at the same rate, nor is it likely to do so.</P>
      <P>In the past I have drawn attention to another matter connected with the ICC.  It has a non-commercial mandate and outlook in certain spheres but it has contradicted this in the most extraordinary way in the area in which it is the market leader, that is, business expansion schemes.  In this activity the ICC is guilty of the most obnoxious profiteering I have encountered from any Irish bank.  All the banks have cases to answer in terms of non-transparency and their unequal relationship with most of their customers, particularly personal customers. However, the attitude of ICC to small businesses in the BES is utterly indefensible.</P>
      <P>The first problem is non-transparency.  This Government, which is so keen on transparency, should have instructed the ICC to inform people investing in BES of the charges to the companies in which they are investing.  It is an unequal relationship.  A person who invests in a BES scheme pays the ICC or another BES promoter 3 per cent commission, so if one invests £10,000 the commission is £300.  That is upfront and no one complains about it.  The ICC does not tell the investor to which company the money goes.  Last year the ICC collected £8 million for the BES. The bank informs the company that it is considering investing in it through the BES but, in many cases, the ICC charges these companies which desperately need funds, up to 10 per cent commission. If the bank invests £8 million and charges the company 8 per cent the ICC will make £720,000 from the companies it is supposed to help.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The Minister would describe these companies as short of capital and unable to find it anywhere else.  The BES may be the cheapest way for them to get capital but they are still being charged perhaps 10 per cent commission, a sum the ICC continually refuses to stand over or reveal.  The bank does not inform investors that of the £10,000 they <Col N="1077" /> put in, £300 is commission from the investor and another £1,000 is commission from the company, so that a total of £1,300 goes to the ICC.</P>
    <P>The problem is not only the lack of transparency &mdash; the figure is never revealed and the ICC refuses to do so &mdash; but that the ICC is taking no risk.  The bank collects 3 per cent on one side and 9 per cent on the other while all the risk is taken by the investor.  The worst aspect of the BES is that there is a very dangerous and distasteful tendency on behalf of all banks, and particularly the ICC, to hold on to this money until the last minute and as a result the schemes have become six year investments.  The ICC was one of those which did not have all its investments collected up until the end of April 1996 or invested by February or March 1997.  I hope it had done so by April 1997.  It sits on the money, invests it late and then collects vast amounts of interest on top of the 9 or 10 per cent and the 3 per cent on the client's money.  This is profiteering. It is no risk banking and no bank, including the ICC, should engage in that.  They should take risks, lend and invest money but should not take a bit here and a bit there and rip clients off by taking no risk.  It is the Minister's responsibility to ensure that the State bank does not do this.</P>
    <P>The ICC, which finds this such an extraordinarily profitable business, knows that small companies, starved and desperate for capital, will accept virtually any terms dictated to them when they need money.  Last October money was collected for what was called a BES software fund. The terms except for one were the same.  It introduced a nice little clause, which most people would not notice, that gave it the right to take options on up to 10 per cent of the shares of these companies.  It did not say what the cost of these would be but it can be taken that they did not cost the ICC very much.  It now has commission from the investor, huge commission from the investee company, interest on the loans and on the money which it holds for as long as possible and shares in the investee company as well, all for absolutely nothing.  This is indefensible profiteering by the State bank and it should be the Minister's duty or the job of those he appoints to say &ldquo;That is not what banking is about.  This is a State bank with special responsibilities, until it is privatised.  There is transparency; let us see what you are charging and do not screw small companies the way you are at present and refuse to tell investors&rdquo;.</P>
    <P>I have been involved in BES schemes as a stockbroker and have looked at them as a journalist.  Investors are not aware of what is happening to their money or the fact that so much of their money is being taken on the other side. When they invest £10,000 they are really putting in £8,800 or a sum equivalent to that.  They are not told that.  I suggest the Minister does not just look at the scandalous profiteering by the ICC, but at the entire BES scheme because the terms in all the prospectuses are almost identical.  It is a <Col N="1078" /> lovely little cartel.  It sounds very interesting but in the small print it states it has a right to extract a fee from the investee company.  That is where the money comes from and it is damaging the investee company.  The ICC is damaging those it was set up to help.  Where it is putatively putting in a million pounds, it is actually contributing £900,000.  I ask the Minister to look at this before he leaves office.  I hope he is back, perhaps as leader of one of the Opposition parties but not as a socialist Minister for Finance.  He should instruct the State bank to keep to one of the great tenets and mantras of the Labour Party &mdash; transparency in relation to fees.  Once people know they are being ripped off they will not pay their fees.  They do not know this at present.</P>
    <Speaker pid="RuairiQuinn" hpid="Mr. R. Quinn Mr. R. Quinn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. R. Quinn</NameTxt>
      <P>Is that a reflection on financial journalism?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ShaneRoss" hpid="Mr. Ross Mr. Ross">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Ross</NameTxt>
      <P>No it is not.  Financial journalism is a matter I would prefer to keep out of this House. I have some hot air left if the Minister wants me to discuss that but I gather the House does not want to be delayed.</P>
      <P>I am glad this Bill has been introduced because it gives some of us an opportunity to say it is a cop-out.  The Bill challenges the Government to privatise ICC and ACC, which it has not done. It admits the total failure of the Government's banking policy which was to introduce a third banking force.  It could not agree on this.  The Bill highlights the fact that the ICC is a Mickey Mouse bank which will not be able to limp on in the jungle of the banking sector.  I oppose this Bill because it fails to tackle this lame duck bank.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FergalQuinn" hpid="Mr. F. Quinn Mr. F. Quinn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. F. Quinn</NameTxt>
      <P>I rise in fear of being criticised that since Senator Ross has joined this side of the House, I have been tainted by some of his views and beliefs.  I listened carefully to Senator Lanigan and Senator Burke.  However, I agree more with Senator Ross.  The Minister said yesterday in the Dáil that this Bill was not earthshaking.  It is not.  It would be earthshaking if he said he would abolish the ICC bank or sell it off.  Perhaps that is where I have been tainted by the views of Senator Ross.  This will not happen.  One can always be sure that semi-State bodies will be self-perpetuating. That seems to be the attitude of every Government, no matter what political hue.  Does it ever occur to someone to ask whether we need the ICC Bank anymore?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Sir Thomas Cork was the principal liquidator in Britain about ten or 15 years ago.  He wrote a book on what he discovered about companies that went into receivership.  He discovered that most companies had just moved head office.  Putting a fountain in the foyer was a sure sign they were going out of business.  The older the organisation, the more it got into the habit of doing the same things which had a value and use in a previous generation.  This is one of the reasons new companies that start lean and clean are often smarter, better, more productive and profitable <Col N="1079" /> and have lower costs than older ones.  It is the fundamental principle which is at issue, not whether we give authority to the ICC to borrow more but whether we should allow it to continue in existence when the need for it has gone.</P>
    <P>I studied in UCD under Professor George O'Brien and in those days it was considered that there was a need for State involvement because nobody else was doing the job that needed to be done.  There was a chronic shortage of funds for Irish business in those days and business had a great need for funds.  The State stepped in to fill a gap in the market which it was in the national interest to fill.  It was legitimate for the State to take that course of action and would be today if the same circumstances prevailed.</P>
    <P>At that time it was not envisaged that there would come a day when the gap in the market no longer existed, yet that is now the case.  I defy the Minister to give one example of ICC business that would not be provided by the market if ICC did not exist &mdash; perhaps the BES schemes to which Senator Ross referred is an exception.  ICC is just another commercial bank scrambling around to get whatever business it can.  It has done well and it has a good name for providing money for people who wish to buy pubs.  I am told that is one of its more important business areas&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    <Speaker pid="RuairiQuinn" hpid="Mr. R. Quinn Mr. R. Quinn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. R. Quinn</NameTxt>
      <P>Not any more.  Not for about five years.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FergalQuinn" hpid="Mr. F. Quinn Mr. F. Quinn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. F. Quinn</NameTxt>
      <P>It was the case some years ago. It does not matter for what purpose it lends money, the important point is that the money would be lent by a commercial bank if ICC did not exist.</P>
      <P>Senator Lanigan welcomed the Bill because he is favour of competitiveness and banking alternatives. I understand what he seeks but a State bank is the wrong way to achieve it.  We want competitiveness and alternatives.  Ten or 15 years ago the State was involved in the airline sector and we thought it was doing a good job until others came into the market.  The sector has been revolutionised by competitiveness, as is evidenced by the Dublin-London route.  State involvement in the market is not necessary unless there is a gap which is not filled otherwise.  In the case of ICC the gap no longer exists.  Whatever the bank or the Minister may say there is no justification nowadays for the State to be involved in running a bank.  It was justified in the past but that is no longer the case.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>People will go to any lengths to avoid closing or selling off organisations.  This applies particularly to semi-State bodies.  That is one of the reasons behind the crazy idea to create a State-owned third banking force, combining three incompatible institutions, one of which the State does not own.  It would solve the problem in that the <i>raison d'être</i> of ICC has disappeared, just as ACC's <i>raison d'être</i> has disappeared.  It was only <Col N="1080" /> last year the Minister sought a similar increase in ACC's allowances.</P>
    <P>I am sure ICC is doing a good commercial job and that its management and staff are excellent and dedicated.  My quarrel is not with them but with the ownership of the bank.  The State should stick to its remit and focus on that which it has a clear justification for doing.  Nowadays one would not argue that there is an inherent value in State ownership as such.  One cannot expect an institution to commit hara-kiri because the first instinct of an institution is to remain alive.  It is up to us to decide that the institution is not needed any longer.</P>
    <P>Senator Ross referred to the Minister as a socialist.  I do not have any problem with that because socialism seems to have changed.  We only have to look at&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    <Speaker pid="ShaneRoss" hpid="Mr. Ross Mr. Ross">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Ross</NameTxt>
      <P>It would want to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FergalQuinn" hpid="Mr. F. Quinn Mr. F. Quinn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. F. Quinn</NameTxt>
      <P>&mdash;&mdash;what the British Labour Party is talking about doing.  It seems to be questioning the need for a state owned post office and is talking about selling off half of it.  We can look at what has happened to the state run institutions in Eastern Europe.  We can look at what happened in Germany and France when the pressure of reaching economic and monetary union criteria arose and they suddenly decided to sell off state assets in contravention of fundamental socialist principles.</P>
      <P>I recently met the Mayor of Indianapolis who said that when he took over as mayor he questioned whether any of the city's activities could be done better.  They put the bin collection out for tender, for example.  The bin collectors' union successfully tendered for the contract and they immediately became much more efficient at the job than had been the case when the city was doing it.</P>
      <P>We must ask whether we are continuing with something because it was the policy one or two generations ago, although it is no longer the right course of action.  I urge the Minister to question these tenets which used to be the basis of Government thinking.  They may have been correct in the past but I am not sure they are correct now.  We, in this House, should say the time has come to sell off this entity for whatever we can get for it in the open marketplace.  That is what the Minister should have said today instead of bringing in this housekeeping Bill which perpetuates a nonsense.</P>
      <P>It is highly symbolic that this was the last Bill to go through the Dáil before it was dissolved and the second last to go through the Seanad.  It symbolises this refusal of this nation to grasp nettles which we have seen over and over again, particularly in the last few years.  I challenge our ability to face up to the fact that something which was right in the past is no longer right.  We should say enough is enough, sell it off and let somebody else do a much more efficient job.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1081" />
    <Speaker pid="RuairiQuinn" hpid="Minister for Finance (Mr. R. Quinn) Ruairí Quinn">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Finance (Mr. R. Quinn)</NameTxt>
      <P>I wish to respond to the constructive points which were made, even by Senator Ross.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ShaneRoss" hpid="Mr. Ross Mr. Ross">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Ross</NameTxt>
      <P>Thank you.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RuairiQuinn" hpid="Mr. R. Quinn Mr. R. Quinn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. R. Quinn</NameTxt>
      <P>I will deal with the points <i>seriatim.</i> Senator Lanigan expressed concern about the changes in the nature of the relationship between customers and banks.  I presume he was talking about the traditional relationship where the local bank manager understood the reality with which the customer was dealing and the ability of that customer to make sense of their business, without the necessity of hiring expensive accountants to produce gobbledygook business plans, simply because head office wants sheaves of paper to cover managerial decisions.</P>
      <P>The ICC Bank has been criticised for many years as being over-staffed, particularly in back office operations.  Most of the focus in streamlining and addressing costs in many financial institutions has been on investing a great deal of money, reducing numbers as a consequence of investing in machinery, minimising the cost of the back office operation with which the customer has no connection and putting most of the resources into front of house customer interface.  That is the sense in which the ICC Bank has been delivering its cost reduction capability.  I do not see that reducing the staff costs, among other costs, of this bank &mdash; and banks historically tend to have high staff costs &mdash; will necessarily be at a cost to the customer. That is not a <i>sine qua non.</i></P>
      <P>Senator Burke referred to the contribution made by the bank over time.  It is interesting that this bank was set up in 1933 largely because of the failure of private enterprise.  This is not, nor has it ever been, a poor country.  There has always been substantial amounts of capital, but it was held in private ownership and was not available for the kind of risk ventures with which Senator Ross is so enamoured.  Given our single currency union with the UK up to 1979, it was much safer and easier to put money into deposite in UK securities of one kind or another.  In view of this, the State had to step in.  At the time there were closed and highly protected national markets world wide.  This State was an example, but it was impoverished because of the civil war, the difficulties of the 1920s and the economic war of the 1930s.  Without making a value judgment as to whether those events should or should not have happened, that was the reality in which the State operated.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Large and successful Irish owned multinational companies, for example CRH, would not have got off the ground had it not been for ICC.  That is not to say that its role has not changed.  For example, Senator Burke raised questions about the costs of banking, head offices, etc.  Banking institutions say they are attempting to address those issues including whether, for example, a town with a population of serveral thousand or <Col N="1082" /> more needs seven or eight bank branches.  Ultimately, the banks must decide on how to maintain and deliver their services.  However, even in the electronic age and with talk of plastic banking, etc., some banks attempt to grow market share by opening branches and a number of new privately owned financial institutions have opened in towns around the country.  Notwithstanding the observations made by Senator Ross, they consider it desirable from a marketing strategy point of view.</P>
    <P>Senator Ross is inconsistent.  This bank was for sale for four or five years but nobody wanted to buy it because its internal operational costs were not attractive.  It was not considered to be very efficient and buying it as a going concern with all of the continued liabilities associated with it proved to be unattractive.  It was for sale, albeit perhaps against a fire sale background in 1989-90, but there were no takers.  Many of its staff received a good training and went on to other financial institutions, which is a testament to the skill base within the bank.</P>
    <P>However, perhaps because it was a semi-State company it was more lax in the way it addressed its cost issues compared to others.  I am happy to say that has been, and continues to be, addressed in a very satisfactory manner.  If one capitalises the cost of a voluntary early retirement scheme of the scale and size it implemented and brings forward in one year a saving that has an extended impact over a number of years it is reasonable for accountancy practices to insert a special note in the accounts to advices a saving will be made that will recur over five, ten or 15 years but that the cost is up front and must take a hit in one accounting year.  ICC Bank is not the first nor the last financial institution that will utilise that device as an explanatory note, not an excuse, to explain why profits were so low in that year.</P>
    <P>Senator Ross made an unfair comment about political appointees to State organisations and semi-State bodies.  I have been involved in many appointments to banks and State boards, especially with regard to finding people to <i>sit de novo</i> on boards.  Examples include the Great Southern Hotels Group in 1984 and the restructuring of IDA into IDA Ireland, Forfás and Forbairt. These were new institutions.</P>
    <P>The Senator's remarks were not only unfair but potentially damaging and will make the task more difficult.  Perhaps the problem will not arise if his ultimate solution is to abolish State boards.  By and large, in my experience, we set out to compose a team.  What kind of team is needed for the board of the Great Southern or the IDA?  We do not need 11 goalkeepers or strikers but a complementary, balanced team.  I sought to design the skills that would fit this team and then sought people who would have those skills and who would give their time to this.  It is frequently difficult, because of streamlining in companies, to get people such as middle managers who are not owners of their companies onto boards.  They are not free to do so because they are employees and <Col N="1083" /> the owner or managing director will take umbrage at not being approached to serve on the board when a sales executive, who may be 15 years younger, has been asked to do so.  The recent controversy surrounding various boards has given personal membership of boards a problematic profile.  People do not want the intrusion and perceived hassle that those on boards suffer. That is the inference of the Senator's criticism.</P>
    <P>I refer to the job done by my cousin, Senator Quinn, with An Post while chief executive of his own company.  I do not know what his party political allegiances are but he was kept on that board by several Administrations.  The same applied to Dr. Michael Smurifit at Telecom Éireann.  When those companies were set up, we were privileged to have the expertise and time of those people.  The Senator does no service to say that people are on boards because they are politically appointed.</P>
    <Speaker pid="ShaneRoss" hpid="Mr. Ross Mr. Ross">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Ross</NameTxt>
      <P>I accept what the Minister says.  It would be unfair to refer to people who cannot defend themselves, but I could give the Minister a long list of people who would prove the opposite point.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RuairiQuinn" hpid="Mr. R. Quinn Mr. R. Quinn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. R. Quinn</NameTxt>
      <P>I could give the Senator a list that would prove the opposite again.  If we were to move from party political appointees to &ldquo;political&rdquo; appointees to the boards of publicly quoted companies, the selection of a director has more to do with association with a particular clique, to use the Senator's phrase, than the best interests of the shareholders who own the company. The Senator must be constitent as there is a contradiction in his argument.  We will have State companies in key areas where the private sector is not capable of delivering a competitive service and we will have to make it possible to get the assistance of citizens who will give their time. They are not really getting remunerated; the level of pay such directors get is a pittance relative to the fee if one hired them on a consultancy basis.</P>
      <P>ICC was referred to as a Mickey Mouse and lame duck bank.  It is small.  The total market share, if measured against the total banking assets, would be approximately 2.5 per cent. Senator Quinn asked why we need a State owned bank when the private sector should be doing this.  We know why there was State ownership in the past and until recently, parties of the Left across Europe and elsewhere instisted on State ownership in protected national markets.  State companies could be used as instruments in the marketplace to distort, influence or bend policy in a way that the marketplace could not do.  This could be done for social reasons, for regional development or other reasons that market forces would not accommodate.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>With the globalisation of the world's economy and the introduction of competition in the European Union, those kinds of possibilities and requirements of State companies have disappeared <Col N="1084" /> or are in the process of doing so.  Telecom Éireann must face competition, which is proper. The same process applies to the ESB, though in a different manner.  That process takes account of a new and growing market.</P>
    <P>In terms of right and left attitudes to economics, the question is whether the State should retain the right to intervene in the economy or should it stand back, regulate the market and ensure the rules are adhered to.  This assumes that every social need will be met with a market response in a reasonable time.</P>
    <P>There are people who sincerely hold the view that all the State should do in those circumstances is to stand back and deny any form of direct intervention in the economy on the grounds that the economy will self-correct itself and will move in the direction which is most efficient and effective and, therefore, we will get the benign end result. I am trying not to parody or caricature that view which is sincerely held by many people on the right in economy thinking.</P>
    <P>The counter view which I hold on the left is that the State should retain the ability to intelligently and creatively intervence in the marketplace at all times because markets are not perfect. There is collusion among suppliers in the market, and Senator Ross referred to cartels in a different context.  I do not have a naive belief in the sanctity of the marketplace and its permanent orientation to do good at all times &mdash; it is not my experiences from what I have learned and seen of the operation of markets.  I retain for the State the ability to intervene in the economy through direct and indirect instruments.  The State can intervene indirectly by regulation and directly by specific action on the floor of the market.</P>
    <P>The Senator asked me for a good reason which would justify keeping ICC Bank in public ownership since it is not doing anything different from other institutions.  When I was Minister for Enterprise and Employment we received money from the EU Structural Funds to try to assist small and medium sized business.  When I set up the task force on small business which was chaired by Deputy Séamus Brennan, who was Minister of State at the time, one of the recurring demands of small and medium sized business was access to capital on reasonable terms over an extended period and at reasonable interest rates and not the A or AA rate.  It wanted terms which did not require it to throw in the family home and the wife's engagement ring as collateral and security.</P>
    <P>In the first small business expansion loan scheme over which I had control I deliberately asked ICC Bank alone to take the entire benefit of the subsidy.  It produced a loan scheme which was quickly imitated by the other large players. The total sum available was £200 million and the prevailing commercial interest rate at the time was of the order of 10 per cent.  The rate was guaranteed at 6.75 per cent for ten years with out collateral-type undertakings and guarantees which were the norm.  As a result of competitive <Col N="1085" /> pressure from one bank, the ICC Bank, the other banks had to follow, and they did so to varying degrees.  The second small business expansion loan scheme was of a higher order and a wider scale and the banks had already moved in that directrion.</P>
    <P>If we had not taken that action and if there were no ICC Bank which I could ask to take this subsidy, I would have taken the EU funds to the existing banks, which ran a cartel for many years but no longer do so.  The banks would have taken the money and run the same type of scheme keeping their own margind.  In that instance, the ability to use a small instrument in the marketplace gave me the opportunity to address a market failure which was reported to me by market participants, small and medium sized industries, and to respond to it with a mixture of EU and Irish taxpayers' money and to bring a correcting distortion into the marketplace by using a player which we owned and, therefore, could direct.  As a consequence, we forced competition to respond in a manner with which we are familiar.</P>
    <P>Debate adjourned.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Business" RHead="of Seanad">
    <Title>Business of Seanad.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I ask the Acting Leader to move an amendment to the Order of Business to enable item 2 to be taken at the conclusion of item 1 instead of at 12.15 p.m., as agreed this morning.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHoward" hpid="Mr. Howard Mr. Howard">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Howard</NameTxt>
      <P>I so move.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="ICC Bank (Amendment) Bill, 1997:" RHead="Second Stage (Resumed)">
    <Title>ICC Bank (Amendment) Bill, 1997: Second Stage (Resumed).</Title>
    <P>Question again proposed: &ldquo;That the Bill be now read a Second Time.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="RuairiQuinn" hpid="Minister for Finance (Mr. R. Quinn) Ruairí Quinn">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Finance (Mr. R. Quinn)</NameTxt>
      <P>I will conclude my remarks as quickly as possible.  As to the future of the ICC, we should not engage in a hasty sale.  Senator Quinn said it should be sold for whatever price can be obtained but we do not need to sell.  The State has a bad record in coming to the market to sell assets with open pockets.  If we were to have the land bank, owned by the IDA, which had a &ldquo;for sale&rdquo; sign put on it by a previous Administration, the asset value of the IDA today would be enormous.  Assets such as the Great Southern Hotel were sold for a song because of the view that the State should not be involved in the market.  They were sold for way below their market price or their long or mediumterm market price.  I do not agree the bank should be sold but I agree it needs a proper strategic future and I have asked it to make proposals on that.  There will be another debate on that in this House and I confidentially expect to be in a position to initiate and respond to it, notwithstanding Senator Ross's good wishes.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="1086" /> The bank has never recorded a loss, continues to return small modest dividends and has provided a service to many business people who, by their own admission, would not have been able to obatain a facility elsewhere.  If the bank were a charity, it would not be in a position to continue making profits.  In the 60 or more years since it was formed in 1933, it has consistently made either real and intagible profits or has not reported a loss.  It is not in the business of charity but it has provided a required service.</P>
    <P>As we move to a new future of the single currency and an increasingly integrated internal market, I am not clear what is the best form of lever or instrument the State should have to correct market distortions or failures.  As deputy leader of the Labour Party, as a participant member of the Party of European Socialists and on behalf of the constituencies I represent, I would, at my peril, forego the possibility of not having any lever whatsoever.  It may will be that the levers we will need for the new internal market conditions will be different to those we currently have.  Therefore, we have an obligation to change them and, possibly, to discard some of them and create new ones.  This brings us back to the ideological fault line in the European Union between those who believe the market, if left alone, will solve all problems and those, like me, who say the market will solve some problems wonderfully but not others and, given the choice in those cases, will go in an anti-social direction.  For that reason, the power and possibility to intervene creatively and intelligently must be retained.  If there has been a conversion among the left in Europe, it has been to the recognition that market forces must be understood and respected but not necessarily idealised.</P>
    <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
    <P>Agreed to take remaining Stages now.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="ICC Bank (Amendment) Bill, 1997:" RHead="Committee and Final Stages">
    <Title>ICC Bank (Amendment) Bill, 1997: Committee and Final Stages.</Title>
    <P>Section 1 agreed to.</P>
    <P Just="Center">SECTION 2.</P>
    <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That section 2 stand part of the Bill.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="ShaneRoss" hpid="Mr. Ross Mr. Ross">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Ross</NameTxt>
      <P>Will the Minister respond to questions on the business expansion scheme put to him on Second Stage and to which he did not reply?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RuairiQuinn" hpid="Minister for Finance (Mr. R. Quinn) Ruairí Quinn">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Finance (Mr. R. Quinn)</NameTxt>
      <P>The Senator raised an array of different issues concerning the BES which apply to all the institutions, such as the issues of transparency and making the cost clear.  It would be contradictory and I would be following into the trap the Senator accused me of following into, of forcing a commercial player, because if the nature of its ownership, <Col N="1087" /> to behave in a non-commercial way relative to other institutions or funds which are behaving in a similar fashion and who retain for themselves the advantages which the Senator wishes me to remove from the bank.  There is a need for the Director of Consumer Affairs, the Central Bank or the Department of Finance, acting with the Department of Enterprises and Employment, to require and demand that the full costs of the BES and associated fees and commissions are made clear to all prospective investors.</P>
      <P>Six or seven weeks ago, under the powers he was given in consumer affairs protection legislations, the Director of Consumer Affairs, Mr. Fagan, directed all mortgage lenders to state in a clear and understandable manner the precise costs and implications of the loans they offered. That kind of market information is always welcome and I will look at how it can be done. However, to specifically direct one institution to so do while the others would not operate under the same obligation would be an incorrect intervention.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ShaneRoss" hpid="Mr. Ross Mr. Ross">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Ross</NameTxt>
      <P>I accept what the Minister has said that all institutions should operate under the same rules.  I brought this to his attention because it is directly under his control.  The Minister would agree there is a flaw, a lack of transparency across the board.  He may have answered this already but would he consider directing all banks to be transparent in this area so that everyone can see what is being charged?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RuairiQuinn" hpid="Mr. R. Quinn Mr. R. Quinn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. R. Quinn</NameTxt>
      <P>I will raise this with the Director of Consumer Affairs and see if he has the remit-to so do.  I do not know whether it is my responsibility or that of the Minister for Enterprise and Employment.  I have no problem with the principle of the Senator's proposition.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MickLanigan" hpid="Mr. Lanigan Mr. Lanigan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lanigan</NameTxt>
      <P>I would not like the impression to go from this House that the ICC is a Mickey Mouse bank run by Mickey Mouse people.  Its directors have been careful in their management of the funds allotted to them and their funding of companies.  They have done much for commercial enterprises in Kilkenny and the South East.  The returns are there in terms of jobs created.  Senator Ross should not brand the bank as being run by Mickey Mouse people.  That is a disgraceful assertion and he should withdraw it.  Whether the directors are political or party political appointees, many of them have good commercial backgrounds.  I do not know who appointed many of them but they have done a good job.</P>
      <P>We are not talking about Mickey Mouse money.  We are increasing the borrowing powers of the ICC to allow it become more competitive in the marketplace.  That is necessary.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ShaneRoss" hpid="Mr. Ross Mr. Ross">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Ross</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator Lanigan is playing one of his old political tricks to which I have become accustomed. I have to correct the Senator.  I said this <Col N="1088" /> was a Mickey Mouse bank whose directors were political appointees.  I did not say they were Mickey Mouse people.  I said they were not qualified to be on the board because they were appointed for political not commercial reasons. The Senator should withdraw his accusation because he got it wrong.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Both Senators have made their positions clear.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>Sections 3 to 5, inclusive, agreed to.</P>
      <P>Title agreed to.</P>
      <P>Bill reported without amendment and received for final consideration.</P>
      <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That the Bill do now pass.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PaddyBurke" hpid="Mr. Burke Mr. Burke">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Burke</NameTxt>
      <P>I thank the Minister for Finance for bringing this Bill before the House today.  I wish him good luck in his election campaign.  I have no doubt he will be returned and will spend many more years as Minister for Finance.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ShaneRoss" hpid="Mr. Ross Mr. Ross">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Ross</NameTxt>
      <P>What about a Fine Gael Minister for Finance?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PaddyBurke" hpid="Mr. Burke Mr. Burke">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Burke</NameTxt>
      <P>I thank the Opposition for its co-operation in passing the Bill.  I also thank its Members for their courtesy and help during my tenure as Government Whip for the past few months.  It was greatly appreciated, as was the co-operation of the Independent Members.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RuairiQuinn" hpid="Minister for Finance (Mr. R. Quinn) Ruairí Quinn">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Finance (Mr. R. Quinn)</NameTxt>
      <P>I thank the Members for their contributions to the debate.  As was evident today and despite the exigencies of time, I have always found debate in the Seanad to be such that I am unable to remain silent but must respond to the contributions.  With regard to Senator Ross's observation on the prospect of a future Fine Gael Minister for Finance, he had his chance but he left the party.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ShaneRoss" hpid="Mr. Ross Mr. Ross">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Ross</NameTxt>
      <P>I know.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Prompt Payment of Accounts Bill, 1997:" RHead="Second Stage">
    <Title>Prompt Payment of Accounts Bill, 1997: Second Stage.</Title>
    <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That the Bill be now read a Second Time.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="RichardBruton" hpid="Minister for Enterprise and Employment (Mr. R. Bruton) Richard Bruton">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Enterprise and Employment (Mr. R. Bruton)</NameTxt>
      <P>The purpose of the Bill is to ensure prompt payment of amounts due to businesses for the supply of goods and services by public sector purchasers.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Late payment of business debt is a serious restriction on the cashflow of businesses and causes squandering of scarce management time in <Col N="1089" /> chasing payment of bills.  It is an unproductive use of resources which could be better spent developing the business.  The Government, as part of its programme for Government and its commitments under Partnership 2000, is committed to the introduction of legislation to provide for the prompt payment of bills by the public sector. We honour that commitment in this Bill. Indeed, we have gone beyond our commitment by including all businesses, not just small businesses, in its provisions.</P>
    <P>In recent years a number of surveys have been conducted in Ireland and other European countries which have tried to quantify the time taken to pay accounts and the extent of the late payment problem.  The small business task force estimated that payment periods in Ireland were 79 days on average, which was poorer that the European average.  A European business survey by Grant Thornton International Business Strategies Ltd. in May 1996 showed the average payment period in Ireland to be 59 days, which is two days lower than the EU average of 61 days but nine days longer than the UK average.</P>
    <P>No specific surveys were conducted on the extent on public sector <i>versus</i> private sector delays.  However, a small study was carried out in 1992 by the Society of Chartered Surveyors which covered 11 companies and 139 fee payments.  The study indicated the average payment period was 154 days.  As the study was quite unrepresentative, I commissioned a survey on the issue.  The purpose of the survey was twofold; first, to identify existing practice and, second, to establish a benchmark for the future.  The survey involved a sample of 75 public sector organisations, with 100 invoices selected for examination in each case. The results of the survey were based on an analysis of more than 7,000 payments.</P>
    <P>The key findings of the survey were: the average payment period between the date of invoice and the date on which payment is made is 55 days; the average payment period for payments made after 45 days is 76 days; almost 57 per cent of payments were made later than 45 days.  The distribution was bad also in that 26 per cent of payments were made after 60 days and 12 per cent were made later than 80 days.  Clearly, some businesses experienced long waiting periods for payment.  There is significant scope for improvement in public sector payment practices.  This underpins the need for the Bill.</P>
    <P>The legislation will require public bodies to pay amounts due to their suppliers on or before the date due under the terms of the contract, provided it is in writing.  Where the payment date is not established by a written contract, payment must be made within 45 days of receipt of an invoice or date of supply, whichever is later.  The Bill also contains appropriate safeguards to deter public bodies from seeking unduly long credit periods in written contracts.  A key provision is an automatic right to interest in respect of late payments.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="1090" /> No legislation applies to the private sector and the Government does not intend to introduce such a Bill at this stage.  However, this does not mean private sector payment practices are not without fault.  The Government is willing to give time to see whether the voluntary codes established by the various business organisations bring about improvements is private sector payments. While it would not be appropriate to introduce legislation at this stage to govern private sector payments, the Government has not closed its mind to that concept.  We will monitor the position and consider whether it is necessary to introduce such legislation.</P>
    <P>The Bill will be implemented as and from 1 January 1998.  This gives public sector bodies time to put their houses in order to ensure they are in a position to update their systems and every staff member so they can meet the new demands and reporting requirements of the Bill.</P>
    <P>Section 1 deals with interpretation and definitions. All public bodies and subsidiaries are listed in a Schedule to the Bill.  People will know at a glance who is covered by the legislation.  The definition of purchaser extends beyond public sector bodies to include contractors on public sector contracts.  If contractors will receive the benefit of the Bill, people rightly feel that subcontractors should also have that benefit.  The 45 day payment period is also defined.  It applies in cases where there is no written contract.  There is also a power under section 10 to reduce that period by order.  There is an opportunity for progressive improvements in payment practices over time.</P>
    <P>Section 2 deals with the commencement date of the Bill while section 3 provides that the Minister may changes the list of public bodies covered by the legislation.  However, a Minister cannot frivolously remove bodies.  He or she must give the reason for the deletion of a specific body. Ministers cannot decide off their own bat that certain bodies should not be covered by the Bill.</P>
    <P>Section 4 is the key provision.  It provides for the prompt payment of accounts and requires purchasers to pay for the supply of goods and services by the prescribed payment date.  If payment is not made by the due date, the purchaser must pay an interest penalty on the amount outstanding. The interest must be paid in respect of the period beginning on the day after the due date of payment and ending on the date on which payment is made.  Most importantly, the section specifically provides that the interest penalty cannot be waived by the supplier.  Moreover, the interest penalty must be paid without any demand for its payment by the supplier.</P>
    <P>The automatic entitlement to interest in respect of late payments is a fundamental requirement for the effective operation of the legislation.  Suppliers are in a vulnerable position <i>vis-á-vis</i> large purchasers.  If they were open to pressure not to demand payment, an unfair situation, which section 4 specifically prevents, would develop.  Section 4 also sets down when payments shall be taken to have been made by the purchaser <Col N="1091" /> which can be in one of three ways &mdash; when the supplier has received the appropriate amount of cash, when the appropriate amount is credited to the suppliers account or when the purchaser enables the suppliers to credit his or her account; in other words if they issue a cheque which is in the possession of the supplier.</P>
    <P>Section 5 is designed to address situations where an incorrect or inadequate invoice is furnished by a supplier.  It ensures if there is a problem with an invoice, the purchaser is given ten days to return it if he believes it has been incorrectly made out.  The interest penalty would not accure until ten days after the purchaser receives a corrected invoice or until the payment due date arrives, whichever is the later.  If the purchaser is late in returning the invoice to the supplier, then the ten day period of grace allowed for payment after receipt of the corrected invoice will be reduced by the corresponding number of days.  If the purchaser lets it drift to 15 days, the day's grace will be cut back to five days.  This will ensure people do not deliberately dispute invoices to get a period of grace.</P>
    <P>Section 6 specifies that when any payment which includes an interest payment is made, it must be accompanied by a notice stating the amount of the interest penalty included and the rate at which and the period for which the interest penalty was computed.  The Minister may prescribe additional information in the light of experience which will have to be provided in invoices or in such payments.  This ensures clarity in the way this operates and over time we can develop payment practices under the provisions of the Bill.</P>
    <P>Section 7 deals with the payment of invoices in disputes.  I have provided for the partial payment of invoices in disputed situations so that if one item in an invoice is disputed, the entire payment cannot be held up but only the disputed item.</P>
    <P>Section 8 provides for the resolution of disputes and it gives the supplier the option of submitting to arbitration disputes relating to the payment of an interest penalty.  This meets a concern which I am sure is shared by Senators that going to court is not always the best way in which to deal with these matters.  This gives the option, at the suppliers discretion, to go to arbitration as an alternative. If the purchaser refuses to co-operate with the supplier, there is a provision for the appointment of an arbitrator by the president of the Law Society or another person prescribed by the Minister.</P>
    <P>Section 9 is designed to ensure that main contractors on public sector contracts pass on to their subcontractors the benefits of being paid promptly.  That is the only area in which the private sector is affected and it is only fair. Section 10 provides that the Minister may, by order, following consultation with the Minister for Finance, fix the rate of penalty interest which will apply to late payments.  It allows the Minister to amend it as time goes on and ensures a penalty <Col N="1092" /> rate of interest which is linked to the market rate. Section 10 also allows the 45 day payment period to be reduced by ministerial order.</P>
    <P>Section 11 provides a major sareguard against public sector bodies seeking unreasonably long payment periods in written contracts.  It gives the Minister the power to police the payment practices of public bodies.  If the Minister decides the contract used by a public body is unfair and it should be compelled to pay within the 45 day period for reasons of natural justice, he will have to advise the public body of the grounds for believing its credit terms are unreasonable and afford it the opportunity to respond before the order is made.</P>
    <P>Section 12 is intended to ensure transparency in regard to payment practices by public bodies. It will require all public bodies listed in the Schedule to disclose details of their payment practices.  Where the body is required, by statute, to publish an annual report, the report must include details of the payment practices in the period covered by the report.  Where a public body is not required to publish an annual report, it must submit an annual review of its payment practices to the Minister who then has the power to specify the kind of details which must be included in the reports.</P>
    <P>Section 13 provides that every auditor auditing the affairs of a body must report on whether that body has complied with the provisions of the Act. That is an important protection which is built in to ensure this is given a high level of importance within the company and is part of their audit.</P>
    <P>Section 14 deals with the areas of tax clearance certificates and withholding tax.  The section makes it clear that the Act does not require the payment of an amount due to a supplier who has failed to comply with a request to provide a tax clearance certificate and it extends the time limit for payment where there are delays in furnishing such certificates.  The section also makes it clear that the leglislation will not affect the power to deduct withholding tax from any payment to a supplier.</P>
    <P>Section 15 is a standard section which empowers the Minister to make necessary regulations under the Act.  Section 16 is also a standard provision which deals with the short title and commencement of the Bill.</P>
    <P>This legislation has long been regarded as important as it would improve the climate for small businesses.  It will ensure that public sector bodies will move from their present payment practices to establish best practice in this area.  I commend the Bill to the House.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MickLanigan" hpid="Mr. Lanigan Mr. Lanigan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lanigan</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister for Enterprise and Employment is the last Minister to come into the House this session.  This Bill will be exceptionally well regarded by suppliers to the public service. As someone who has been a supplier to the public service since 1957, one of the problems I have had is late payments.  Sometimes the payments are late because of inefficiencies within the system, <Col N="1093" /> not because people deliberately wanted to delay payments.  Invoices often had to be transferred from one point to another and it was the norm rather than the exception for the payment to be made after 45, 60 or 70 days.</P>
      <P>Efficiencies have been achieved within the public service and I hope the Minister's wishes in regard to prompt payments will be well publicised. There are implications in the Bill which I would like the Minister to address.  How will the Minister for Finance ensure that public bodies have the necessary cash on hand to make payments? Health boards, councils, corporations and other bodies are often strapped for cash and suppliers are the last people to be paid.  If the Minister for Finance does not address the issue of payments to the public service, this Bill will not stand up.</P>
      <P>I am delighted the Minister mentioned that interest charges would be levied in the case of late payment but he did not outline what they would be.  The biggest interest charge at the moment is the 1.5 per cent per month levied by the tax authorities.  Will the Minister guarantee at least that to suppliers who are owned payments as that is the figure charged to businesses by the tax authorities for late payment of taxes?  The Minister should give suppliers a guarantee to this effect.</P>
      <P>I welcome the Bill.  It would be foolish to delay its passage.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHoward" hpid="Mr. Howard Mr. Howard">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Howard</NameTxt>
      <P>I am conscious of Senator Lanigan's comments and I will not unduly delay the passage of the Bill.  I welcome it.  I have made representations to the Minister about enacting such legislation.  I acknowledge his success in bringing this Bill forward, despite time constraints, as the last piece of legislation in this session.</P>
      <P>The Minister and Senator Lanigan outlined the difficulties suppliers, contractors and subcontractors encountered getting payments from public bodies.  I note Senator Lanigan's point about ensuring public bodies have funds to make payments as required under this legislation.  One of the reasons implementation of the legislation is being put back to the beginning of next year is to allow time for the appropriate mechanisms to be put in place ensuring the system works from the Department of Finance to the smallest, supplier or contractor.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Having received representations from suppliers, contractors and particularly subcontractors, we are aware of the cash flow problems created by late payments.  We all know of small businesses put out of business because of such problems.  Tendering, which suppliers and contractors inevitably have to undertake for the products they provide, is always competitive and margins are always tight.  In the case of small operators, delays in receiving payment create serious financial difficulties and, when they go out of business, jobs are lost.  Our priority should be the maintainance of jobs in addition to the <Col N="1094" /> creation of new ones.  I congratulate the Minister for responding to an obvious need, despite the pressures of time.</P>
    <P>While the terms of the Bill relate to the public sector and bodies specified in the Schedule, I wish to refer to difficulties which arise, for example, in the construction industry in relation to projects undertaken for public sector bodies.  The practice of delayed payments is especially difficult when the main contractor is waiting for payment and the subcontractors, who suffer most, being put at the end of the quene.  This situation was effectively outlined in the construction industries' magazine in June 1996.  Organisations representing suppliers, small businesses and subcontractors have made continuous representations to many of us about the difficulties caused by late payments.  We have raised these concerns with the Minister and his Department.</P>
    <P>A suppliers recently outlined a case to me in relation to a subcontractor supplying a main contractor. The Subcontractor was owed £44,000 for work done.  In an effort to extract payment from the main contractor, the subcontractor offered a discount of £8,000 on the £44,000, even though that represented very competitive tendering for the job.  Despite that, because of the delayed payment from the public body to the principal contractor, the subcontractor was paid only £17,000 of the £44,000 owed.  Problems like that can lead to small operations going out of business, with resultant job losses.</P>
    <P>I have discussed the Bill with some of the representative bodies.  They welcome it and regard it as a step in the right direction.  They are particularly anxious that serious consideration be given to extending the legislation to cover the private sector where similar difficulties are being experienced. The Minister has advanced reasons this has not been done.  He referred to the codes of practice in the private sector &mdash; a recent innovation. We must recognise that many organisations which operate within the private sector are not party to these codes of practice and are not compelled to abide by them.</P>
    <P>The Minister said the codes of practice and their operation will be kept under continuous review by his Department.  He indicated that a decision will be made on whether legislation to extend what is being applied to the public sector should be applied to the private sector when the Bill has been in operation for three years.  That period &mdash; in view of the circumstances and conditions that prevail &mdash; is too long.  The Bill will come into effect on 1 January 1998, which is six months away and the Minister said the Bill must have operated in the public sector for three years before the Department can consider applying it to the private sector.  This brings the period to three and a half years.  That is not good enough.</P>
    <P>I welcome what the Minister has done and congratulate him on it.  I also thank him for his response to the representations I and others have made to get this legislation on the Statute Book. The examination period of three years for the <Col N="1095" /> codes of practice and how they operate &mdash; and indications are they are not operating as satisfactorily as it was hoped &mdash; is too long.  Bearing in mind that the legislation will not came into effect until the beginning of next year, one year after that should be sufficient to enable the Department and the Minister to make a decision on the desirability of applying the provisions of this legislation to the private sector.</P>
    <P>Another point has also been made to me by subcontractors and small suppliers.  The Minister may say this is not appropriate to his Department &mdash; and this may be the case &mdash; but, they are looking for a simplified system of court procedure for the recovery of payments.  Organisations and suppliers concerned are deterred from taking legal action as the amount owed to them is quite small and may not offset the expense of going to the Circuit or High Courts.</P>
    <P>As to the European dimension in prompt repayments, in May 1995 the European Commission issued a recommendation on the payment period for commercial transactions which incorporated the public and private sectors.  Member states were requested to inform the Commission, before the end of the year, what action should be taken to implement this recommendation.  In June 1996 the European Parliament asked the Commission to bring forward a directive covering issues in the recommendation.  The issue of private contracts and their payments will have to be dealt with shortly.  While we will observe how well the codes of practice work the only option left will be to legislate after the European institutions have made their recommendations.</P>
    <P>I welcome the inclusion in the Bill of the automatic right to interest and I will raise this matter with the Minister when we reach the appropriate section.  Senator Lanigan has already referred to it.  What would the Minister consider to be the appropriate rate of interest on late payments if this Bill was enacted from today?  The Minister has included the automatic right because if he had not it would act as a deterrent to small suppliers seeking interest because of the competitive nature of tendering for these projects.</P>
    <P>The Bill has been produced against a background of time constraints.  I thank the Minister and his officials for enacting the Bill and meeting the May deadline.  In the face of a general election the Minister could have taken the easy option and left the Bill to be dealt with at a later stage.  It is a tribute to the Minister that he enacted the Bill.  He deserves the goodwill and the recognition of the organisations, suppliers and businesses that will benefit from what he has done.  In conclusion, the Minister has put an unacceptable situation right and ensured fair play for people who were left in a vulnerable situation because of the way the old system worked.  While I welcome the Bill I ask the Minister to give early consideration to its introduction to the private sector.  I do not think we will have a great deal of work on Committee <Col N="1096" /> Stage.  A letter dated 13 May which I received from the consultative committee of the Accountancy Bodies of Ireland expressed concern regarding what is required of its members under section 13.  It suggests that certain amendments or changes should be made to take account of those concerns.  However, on the basis of the practical realities and that the Lower House has been dissolved, the balance of advantage lies in proceeding with the Bill as it stands.  The accountancy bodies will have to wait for another occasion on which to deal with what appear to be genuine concerns because the balance of advantage rests with the early passage of the legislation.</P>
    <Speaker pid="FergalQuinn" hpid="Mr. Quinn Mr. Quinn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Quinn</NameTxt>
      <P>I welcome the Bill and I congratulate the Minister on meeting the deadline, particularly as this is the last legislation with which the House will deal.  I prepared a 45 minute speech but, having heard Senator Lanigan's statement that anyone who delayed the Bill would be a fool, I will risk trying to cover the points I intend to raise in a shorter time.</P>
      <P>The Bill highlights the importance of cashflow to every business, particularly smaller concerns. Few people, even those involved in business, realise the critical importance of cashflow to the survival of a business.  A company can be profitable but it can still go to the wall because it did not manage its cashflow properly.  A large proportion of the funding required for business concerns the need for working capital, which could be reduced by better cashflow management.  If the State wishes to encourage small and medium sized business &mdash; I have always argued that it should and I am aware that the Minister is committed to doing so &mdash; measures of this kind are important and necessary.  It is crazy that the State should try to encourage small businesses, while its agencies cripple those businesses by strangling their cashflow.</P>
      <P>It is not the length of time involved in obtaining payment that is important, it is the uncertainty about when one will obtain payment. If uncertainty exists proper cashflow management is almost impossible.  People await the postman's arrival each day in the hope that he will deliver a cheque.  Small businesses waste precious management time chasing those who pay late.  As Senator Lanigan stated, the Revenue Commissioners realised this many years ago and made it clear that late payment would incur a prohibitive rate of interest.  Some businesses, including Departments and State agencies, do not pay until they have been asked to do so on several occasions. As a result, the cost to suppliers is enormous.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>My next point, which was also made by the Minister and Senator Howard, relates to the focus of the Bill which, at present, is only concerned with public bodies.  The question of tackling prompt payment in the private sector is being put in abeyance to see if a voluntary code of practice can improve the situation.  It is right to move forward one step at a time and the Minister's actions are correct.  If prompt payment was made a legal <Col N="1097" /> requirement in the private sector, small businesses would probably be the worst offenders &mdash; not because they want to be bad payers but because they are obliged to be.  Small businesses cannot become better payers until the larger companies they supply improve their payment practices. Since the worst perpetrators are often State companies and organisations it makes sense to break the vicious circle at the top.  As the Minister stated, we can then proceed with other considerations.</P>
    <P>A word of caution to the Minister or whoever deals with the next stage of the process.  There is a danger this might be applied only to larger businesses and not smaller ones.  I accept this is often done for worthy motives but I fear small businesses will infer they should not expand their operations or employ further staff.  This tells small businesses that if they grow bigger or take on more people they will lose State benefits.  I urge caution about this, as I have in the past about tax and benefits.  There is a danger that if we support small businesses only we place a barrier on them getting bigger.  This nation needs businesses that are willing to grow.</P>
    <P>Why is the State such a bad payer?  Budgetary constraints are not the issue and even if they were they would not justify making suppliers suffer. The real problem is the fundamental difference in the attitude of the public and private sectors to time.  In the private sector time is of the essence; in the public sector it never or rarely is.  This shows where we must focus to bring about the change we need.  This is welcome legislation but we should not expect it to change entrenched attitudes overnight.  That is a separate and wider job which needs to be tackled in paralled.  If we could change the public sector's attitude to time, we would revolutionise at a stroke the standard and quality of the service it provides to the public. Late payment is only a symptom of a much wider disease.</P>
    <P>I am delighted the time issue is at the heart of the SMI and I hope we will make progress on it in the next few years.  On the final day of this Oireachtas, as we look back on the work the Government has done, one initiative which stands out is the SMI in its various forms.  The work put into it, in the Minister's Department and elsewhere, is elsewhere.  I hope it continues with enthusiasm and I am pleased the Minister has introduced the Bill.  I congratulate him and wish him well.</P>
    <Speaker pid="RichardBruton" hpid="Minister for Enterprise and Employment (Mr. R. Bruton) Richard Bruton">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Enterprise and Employment (Mr. R. Bruton)</NameTxt>
      <P>I thank Senators for their support for the Bill.  As to the cost and the cashflow problem, I agree with Senator Quinn &mdash; it is contradictory for the State to give £125 million to the IDA, £70 million to Forbairt and £20 million to CEBs while paying bills late and strangling the companies we are seeking to help.  This is a once-off rescheduling of payments &mdash; in other words, the State bodies make one move from late payment practice to paying on time.  That implies an interest cost <Col N="1098" /> because the debt previously lumped on businesses will have to be borne by the public sector. The mitigating factor is that the public sector can borrow at much lower rates of interest than businesses, particularly small businesses.</P>
      <P>The estimate of the cost is based on calculations made in the Goodbody study, which suggests the purchaser is at fault for late payment in only 40 per cent of cases.  The cost, therefore, will not always fall on public sector bodies.  The cost estimate, based on interest rates, is in the range £3.9 million to £10 million.  As Senator Howard said, the starting date is in 1998 so public bodies can absorb the change in their payment practices over a period and the Exchequer will have time to set aside the sums necessary to make the once-off adjustment in payments to ensure this Bill is honoured by the public sector.</P>
      <P>I assure Senators interest charges will be based on the principle that it should be a clear disincentive. Purchasers will not have an incentive to delay their payments.  They will pay a premium over interest rates but the details have yet to be worked out with the Minister for Finance and will have to be decided closer to the date on the basis of prevailing interest rates.  It is based on the principle of a penalty charge so that public sector bodies will not be allowed to see this as a form of easy finance and ignore the provisions of this Bill.</P>
      <P>I accept Senator Howard's point that there are problems in the private sector, particularly for subcontractors.  He will recognise that in respect of public sector contracts, we have made sure the benefit of prompt payments is passed on to them. The Senator is right in saying we should undertake a review before the three year period expires.  I will look to carry it out because the codes of practice are in place and the Bill will be enacted.  I will look at an earlier date for examining payment practices in the private sector as the Senator suggested.</P>
      <P>Notwithstanding that, I accept Senator Quinn's point that we must move in a phased way in this area.  Small businesses are undoubtedly the worst in payment practices.  We have to ensure the environment they operate in is sufficiently improved by public sector bodies and large businesses before we seek to introduce a legislative sledgehammer.  There is a balance to be struck and I assure Senators we will do this in consultation with representatives of small and large businesses before we move forward.  Business representatives who have been keen to see improvements in payment practices have introduced voluntary codes and we will co-operate. We should look at it earlier than the three year period and I will do so.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Senator Howard also raised the issue of a simpler court procedure.  He is right that this goes beyond the provisions of the Bill.  I hope court action will never be necessary with the arbitration provided.  A public body will not want an entry in its annual report that, not only did it pay late, but it refused to heed an arbitrator's decision on late <Col N="1099" /> payment and insisted on being dragged through the courts.  I do not envisage litigation being a main feature of this legislation.  It is part of the reason we included arbitration.  I accept the Senator's broader point that there is difficulty for businesses pursuing their payments.  Some people suggested they should go to the Small Claims Court.  It is a possibility but requires changes in the rules of court which are the responsibility of the Minister for Justice.  I will talk to her about the Senator's suggestion.</P>
    <P>There is a down side which must be borne in mind.  When the Small Claims Court in the UK was extended to deal with commercial payments it got completely swamped with business claims and consumers which it was supposed to protect found they could not have their cases processed. A balance must be struck.  I am aware of the initiative by the European Parliament.  The Commission is currently examining the Parliament's request and the recommendation is not due to be reported on by member states until December 1997.  A decision will not be taken until after that. We will watch that as it develops.</P>
    <P>Senator Howard raised the matter of the concern of auditors.  I assure him that section 13 was drafted to avoid auditors having to report on minor infringements.  The words &ldquo;in all material respects&rdquo; were deliberately included to ensure this was the case.  It is intended that auditors will conduct sufficient checks so that proper systems are in place to ensure compliance with the Bill and that breaches are reported.  It is not intended that auditors conduct detailed checks of all invoices of a purchases.  The Comptroller and Auditor General was consulted on the drafting of this section.  In the light of these discussions, I am satisfied the role of auditors will operate effectively.</P>
    <P>Senator Quinn went to the core of the issue when he said even profitable companies have problems with cashflow.  It is clearly a contradiction to have development agencies and late payment side by side.  This Bill will bring certainty into payment practices.  People will know there is an outer limit of 45 days and they will not be forced beyond that, unless public sector bodies are willing to accept interest penalties on their payments, of which the business will take advantage.</P>
    <P>The attitude to time is an important change.  I hope that in November when public agencies publish what their customers can expect from them, a key feature will be prompt responses to queries and payment of grants.  The public wants the delivery of quality service.  As Senator Quinn knows from his company, consumers cannot be kept waiting, except perhaps on Christmas Eve.  I know that to my cost from having to stand in long queues.</P>
    <P>I thank the Senators who contributed on Second Stage and I look forward to dealing with specific matters on Committee Stage.</P>
    <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="1100" /> Agreed to take remaining Stages today.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Prompt Payment of Accounts Bill, 1997:" RHead="Committee and Final Stages">
    <Title>Prompt Payment of Accounts Bill, 1997: Committee and Final Stages.</Title>
    <P>Sections 1 to 7, inclusive, agreed to.</P>
    <P Just="Center">SECTION 8.</P>
    <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That section 8 stand part of the Bill.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHoward" hpid="Mr. Howard Mr. Howard">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Howard</NameTxt>
      <P>This section covers disputes between a supplier and purchaser.  The supplier may submit the dispute to arbitration.  The arbitrator is appointed by agreement between the panels.  If there is no agreement an arbitrator may be appointed by the President of the Law Society of Ireland or another person prescribed by the Minister.  Are these terms also applicable to section 9?  Section 9 covers prompt payments to subcontractors.  The benefits available to suppliers under section 8 are not available to subcontractors. Can the Minister clarify this matter?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardBruton" hpid="Minister for Enterprise and Employment (Mr. R. Bruton) Richard Bruton">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Enterprise and Employment (Mr. R. Bruton)</NameTxt>
      <P>I assure the Senator that section 8 will apply to subcontractors.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>Sections 9 to 16, inclusive, agreed to.</P>
      <P>Schedule agreed to.</P>
      <P>Title agreed to.</P>
      <P>Bill reported without amendment and received for final consideration.</P>
      <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That the Bill do now pass.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TomFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Fitzgerald Mr. Fitzgerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Fitzgerald</NameTxt>
      <P>This is a good Bill.  My brother will be happy with it because he has often complained to me about the inability of health boards to pay their bills on time for goods he supplied to hospitals.  He used to charge the hospitals less, supplying goods on a fixed price basis.  This is a welcome Bill.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>As this is the last meeting of this Seanad before the election I wish to thank the Cathaoirleach for his courtesy.  When he was Government Chief Whip we had many discussions.  I hope the content of some of them will never be recealed.  I also wish to thank the Clerk and Clerk Assistant, the parliamentary reporters, the ushers and the media.  This Seanad was unusual because there was a change of Government without an election. I was a Whip when my party was in Government and I thank Senators for their co-operation during that period.  I thank the Leader of the House, Senator Manning, who did his job very well.  We could always rely on his word.  I thank my colleagues on this side of the House for their co-operation. I also wish to remember those who are <Col N="1101" /> no longer with us &mdash; the former Cathaoirligh, Seán Fallon and Liam Naughten, and Gordon Wilson.</P>
    <P>There are 28 Senators running for election to the Dáil.  The Minister had better be careful; he was the cause of my being elected to the Seanad in 1981.  On the second last count his surplus put me in ahead of Senator McGowan.  Hopefully, I will be as lucky this time.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHoward" hpid="Mr. Howard Mr. Howard">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Howard</NameTxt>
      <P>I endorse Senator Fitzgerald's remarks.  I thank the Minister for fulfilling his commitment on this Bill.  I thank his staff who contributed to ensuring this measure would be brought in.  It is a unique and special occasion to have completed the last item of legislation of this Parliament.  The Minister served as a distinguished Member of this House.  He has come to the House many times and has dealt constructively and responsibly with the observations and arguments made.  I am particularly grateful to him for that.  It is my sincere wish and confident expectation that he will be back in a similar role after 6 June.</P>
      <P>I thank you, a Chathaoirligh, and the Leas-Chathaoirleach for the very fair and efficient way the business of the House has been conducted.  I also thank the Seanad staff, especially Jody Blake and Deirdre Lane, for the co-operation they have always given us, often at very short notice and under trying circumstances.  The strenographers, ushers and other staff who ensure this House of Parliament can effectively operate on behalf of the people deserve our thanks.  I am glad to be associated with the comments of Senator Fitzgerald. I say to Senators Fitzgerald, Lanigan and Quinn who are present, that it is my hope that, together with the Cathaoirleach, we will be back in due course.</P>
      <P>The effectiveness of this House in ensuring the welfare and rights of citizens are protected in the legislation was referred to eloquently this morning. This is a House which works constructively. There are many occasions where an idea whose merits both sides of the House can see receives support from both sides.  That is what makes this Chamber so constructive and effective in ensuring the legislation is for the benefit of the people. I wish all my colleagues every success in the election and I hope we will return as Members of the next Seanad.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FergalQuinn" hpid="Mr. Quinn Mr. Quinn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Quinn</NameTxt>
      <P>When I referred to time in my speech I began to blush because I remembered I met the Minister at the front of a checkout queue when he was doing his shopping on Christmas Eve and he was not showing much patience at the length of time it took him to get through the checkout.  I promise we will do our best to ensure that is speeded up and that the concept of time in the private sector is improved to at least the standard at which I thought it was.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I endorse everything which has been said, especially about you, a Chathaoirligh, because you are a new body in the office.  You were elected <Col N="1102" /> after the sad deaths of Senator Fallon and Senator Naughten.  When you were elected we congratulated you on coming from an illustrious family but we added that you were not elected for that reason but in your own right.  I congratulate you on the way you have handled this House, in conjunction with a very efficient and effective staff.</P>
    <P>I hope the rest of the nation will realise that our democracy depends on the working of both Houses.  I do not think that is sufficiently recognised or understood.  When I was elected to this House four years ago I did not realise the amount of effort, work, commitment and dedication which goes into making these Houses work.  I hope more people, particularly young people, will use their opportunity to vote in the forthcoming election.  The more knowledge people have of the operation of this House, the more they will value democracy.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MickLanigan" hpid="Mr. Lanigan Mr. Lanigan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lanigan</NameTxt>
      <P>I join in the tributes paid to you, Sir, and the staff of the House.  Senator Howard and I were elected on the same day 20 years ago. In some ways it has been a short 20 years but in other ways it has been a long time.  Senator Fitzgerald said that, because of the Minister, he was elected to the Seanad.  At one count in 1977 there was a surplus of one vote from a Fine Gael Party candidate which, when transferred, resulted in 12 votes for the Fine Gael candidate, 13 votes for me and 14 votes for another candidate.  If I had not got the 13th vote I would not have been a Member of this House for the last 20 years.  I found out later that the councillor in question did not vote for the Fine Gael candidate because he asked him for a job for his son which did not materialise.</P>
      <P>It has been a privilege to be a Member of this House for the last 20 years.  The staff, including the stenographers and ushers, have done their job as we would expect them to do.</P>
      <P>I do not suggest, Sir, that you should be back in the Chair, but if that transpires, so be it.  I wish you and other Members well.  It is my intention to seek re-election.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFallon" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Point noted.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelOKennedy" hpid="Mr. O'Kennedy Mr. O'Kennedy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Kennedy</NameTxt>
      <P>I am happy to take this opportunity to join in expressing good wishes to all in the House, especially to you, Sir.  I was privileged to come into this House for the first time 32 years ago.  The standard of debate, discussion and all party analyses of various issues in this Seanad compares with anything I have experienced before.  The role of the Seanad has been enhanced and endorsed by the conduct of debate during this session.  I am privileged to have been involved with colleagues in it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The forthcoming elections are of considerable importance, not only to us as Members but to the public.  With regard to the conduct of the Dáil election.  I hope that all the resources of the State <Col N="1103" /> behave in the same impeccable fashion as they always have and that the Garda Síochána especially, to whom we own so much and which served the nation so well, will play a full and effective role in the conduct of democratic affairs, particularly on election day.  I have no doubt it will because we all owe it to those who gave us the privilege of being Members of this democratic House and to the generations that will follow, to ensure that, whatever our party differences, we fully co-operate in the conduct of democratic affairs.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="1104" /> I wish you, Sir, and all well.  I also wish to express my appreciation for those Members who departed to better places.  They made a great contribution and we are greatly indebted to them. Míle bhuíochas.</P>
    <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFallon" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>When is it proposed to sit again?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHoward" hpid="Mr. Howard Mr. Howard">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Howard</NameTxt>
      <P>
        <i>Sine die.</i>
      </P>
      <P>The Seanad adjourned at 1.35 p.m. <i>sine die.</i></P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
</Debate>