<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE Debate SYSTEM "../Debate.dtd"[]>
<Debate DocTitle="Seanad Debate" Day="Tue" Date="29" Month="Apr" Year="1997" Vol="151" No="5" DateIrish="DÈ M·irt, 29 Aibre·n 1997" DateEnglish="Tuesday, 29 April 1997" House="S" CommitteeEng="" CommitteeIr="" SubNameEng="" cnum="0">
  <MainHeading Type="Prelude" LHead="" RHead="">
    <Title>
    </Title>
    <P>
      <Col N="369" /> Chuaigh an Cathaoirleach i gceannas ar 2.30 p.m.</P>
    <P Just="Center">
      <i>Paidir.</i>
    </P>
    <P Just="Center">
      <i>Prayer.</i>
    </P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Business" RHead="of Seanad">
    <Title>Business of Seanad.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFallon" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I have notice from Senator McGowan that, on the motion for the Adjournment of the House today, he proposes to raise the following matter:</P>
      <P>The need for the Minister for Health to agree the appointment of an ombudsman to monitor the quality of the health services and equality of treatment of those needing medical care nationally.</P>
      <P>I regard the matter raised by the Senator as suitable for discussion on the Adjournment and it will be taken at the conclusion of business.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Order of" RHead="Business">
    <Title>Order of Business.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="MauriceManning" hpid="Mr. Manning Mr. Manning">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Manning</NameTxt>
      <P>Today's business is item 1 and I thank the Opposition for agreeing to take all Stages.  There will be a lengthy adjournment of up to an hour after Second Stage before the remaining Stages of the Committees of the Houses of the Oireachtas (Compellability, Privileges and Immunities of Witnesses) Bill are concluded.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GVWright" hpid="Mr. Wright Mr. Wright">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Wright</NameTxt>
      <P>The Order of Business is agreed. Regarding business for the rest of the week, Members on all sides are anxious that the Adoption (No. 2) Bill is taken this week.  Will the Leader make time available during the next couple of weeks that I understand the House will be sitting for item 33, motion 25?  Several Members are also concerned about the delay in debating the safety at sea report.  Will the Minister come to the House before the end of the session for a debate on this matter?  He initiated it and felt it should be implemented.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryHenry" hpid="Dr. Henry Dr. Henry">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Henry</NameTxt>
      <P>The Order of Business is agreed.  Is there any possibility that the Geneva Conventions Bill will be taken before the end of the session? The aspects relating to chemical and nuclear warfare do not concern us to a great extent but the ratification of the conventions has <Col N="370" /> been due since the 1970s.  Part of the conventions relates to the movement of human population as a method of warfare.  This is taking place in Africa at present and has taken place in Bosnia recently.  Irish agencies are working in these areas and perhaps the Leader could outline whether the Bill will be taken soon.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="CathyHonan" hpid="Ms Honan Ms Honan">
      <NameTxt>Ms Honan</NameTxt>
      <P>The Order of Business is agreed.  I support Senator Wright's comments regarding the Adoption (No. 2) Bill.  Will it be taken in the near future?  Many Members have received correspondence from interested parties about it and we are anxious to ensure that the Bill is passed. What progress has been made on the contact register for adopted children and birth mothers? The Minister of State at the Department of Health, Deputy Currie, has responsibility for this area.  Has any progress been made as Members are constantly lobbied on this issue?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SamMcAughtry" hpid="Mr. McAughtry Mr. McAughtry">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McAughtry</NameTxt>
      <P>There must be dozens of causes which have no chance of being taken up in view of the fever which has gripped politics all over the State.  However, I wish to mention the cause of adult literacy education and although I am sure the Minister for Education has been contacted, I want her to note that this issue has also been raised in the House.  The pathetic budget for adult literacy and community education budget is £1.9 million.  It is inadequate.  They want the second level examination fees for second chance education students waived and they would like suitable premises for the delivery of adult and community education.  This is a cause for which I have worked for years in Northern Ireland and I have seen the results.  We are talking about the casualties of the hedonistic sixties when teaching was at its lowest level of proficiency.  I do not suppose there is much chance of getting anything for this cause at present, but I ask the Leader to inform the Minister for Education that the matter has been raised in this House.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelOKennedy" hpid="Mr. O'Kennedy Mr. O'Kennedy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Kennedy</NameTxt>
      <P>I understand that Second Stage of the Shannon River Council Bill will be taken tomorrow.  An hour has been set aside which I believe will be adequate but if a further 20 minutes are needed to complete Second Stage, I ask that it be provided.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>As regards the statement attributed to the Leader over the weekend regarding the position of my party and the SDLP on all-party talks, the Leader is quoted as saying &ldquo;it is a pity that we could not maintain all-party support here for the SDLP in this last week of their general election campaign&rdquo;.  On what basis did the Leader make that statement?  If he consulted with the SDLP and its Leader, John Hume, and Deputy Leader, Seamus Mallon, he would find there is no doubt in their minds about our continuing support and commitment for their role in the peace process. Neither should there be any doubt about Fianna F·il support for the Government regarding its role in the peace process.  However, I hope the <Col N="371" /> Leader understands that support for Government does not demand an uncritical approach to its activity or inactivity, which has been the basis of Fianna F·il's comments.</P>
    <P>I hope we will not create unnecessary division regarding our principles where previously there has been consensus.  Nobody should not be deprived of the opportunity to make critical comments, particularly our party which has been so involved in building the peace process which we all want restored.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JarlathMcDonagh" hpid="Mr. McDonagh Mr. McDonagh">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McDonagh</NameTxt>
      <P>I support Senator McAughtry's call for more funding for the adult literacy and community education budgets.  I am very familiar with this issue as I am an adult education organiser.  It is an area which has been neglected over the years because of underfunding and under-resourcing.  Marvellous work has been done with the limited resources available.  I hope the Minister and the future Administration, which I am sure will be a continuation of the present one, will ensure a big increase in the allocation of funds for this area.</P>
      <P>In the context of resource and remedial teachers &mdash; I understand an announcement will be made in the coming week &mdash; I ask the Leader to ensure that an adequate number of such teachers will be provided for the Headford and Caherlistrane area of Galway.  I know this matter is more appropriate to the Adjournment but I ask the Leader to make a case for this area which is under-resourced.  I am part of the ongoing campaign on this issue and I hope the Minister will respond positively.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PaddyMcGowan" hpid="Mr. McGowan Mr. McGowan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGowan</NameTxt>
      <P>I wish to raise a problem with which I have difficulty finding advice or help.  We have a complete postal breakdown in rural Ireland, and certainly in Donegal.  A letter posted on 19 April at the central post office in Lifford reached Dublin on 23 April.  Small business people in rural areas have to survive with this type of postal service and a telephone service with local calls at least four times the price charged in other areas.  It is time we looked at this antiquated service.  When we had no technology, postmen went around on bicycles and the post was sent by steam train, letters reached Dublin in a day.  A horse and cart could deliver letters more quickly than the present disastrous system.  I ask the Leader for advice and assistance because there is no Minister responsible.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFallon" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator, I think the matter you raise would be best referred to An Post.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PaddyMcGowan" hpid="Mr. McGowan Mr. McGowan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGowan</NameTxt>
      <P>I will take your advice, a Chathaoirligh, and I appreciate the sincerity with which it is given but I do not know a responsible person in An Post who will take me, or anyone else, seriously.  I hope the Leader can provide information &mdash; if he tells me who to contact I will be happy.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="372" />
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMagner" hpid="Mr. Magner Mr. Magner">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Magner</NameTxt>
      <P>I support Senator McAughtry and Senator McDonagh.  Adult literacy work is done by vocational education committees with travellers and in prisons.  I have suggested previously that there should be an adult literacy television programme &mdash; TeilifÌs na Gaelige may be the proper vehicle.  Many people do not respond to appeals to attend adult literacy classes, even on a one to one basis, because they are too ashamed. However they may become involved in the learning process through television in the privacy of their homes.  It would be worthwhile to debate the matter.</P>
      <P>The House should not let pass the arrival of the worst aspects of Fleet Street last Sunday. People who are elected or nominated are fair game and should be treated as such but their wives and families have no input into this system. What happened was an absolute disgrace.  We are tough with each other and the public will not be left unaware of anything we do but when families are affected, someone must draw a line.  The sooner we have a press council the better.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TomFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Fitzgerald Mr. Fitzgerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Fitzgerald</NameTxt>
      <P>A Chathaoirligh, I agree to a certain extent with your answer to Senator McGowan.  However, this week's business was sent to me last week but I have not got it yet, so perhaps we should make this the business of the House.  All material is normally posted on a Thursday or, at the latest, a Friday.  I was at home yesterday but I did not receive any post &mdash; even the Order of Business sent from my own office had not reached my home.  The notification from the Seanad Office that we were sitting today had not reached me.  When I go home at the weekend I will have a pile of useless information on everything which happened this week.  I do not know whether I should address this point to the Leader or to you, A Chathaoirligh, or whether other Senators have the same problem.  This is not a political issue, it is a matter of business.  To expand the point, it is galling to send notification of a cumann meeting and to find, when at home at the weekend, that no one has received it.  This is not good enough and I ask the Leader to raise the matter.  There has been a breakdown at some point and I have plenty of proof of it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DanNeville" hpid="Mr. Neville Mr. Neville">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Neville</NameTxt>
      <P>I support Senators' remarks on An Post.  I do not know whether it affects letters from the Seanad Office or the Oireachtas as whole.  I have complained on at least three occasions on the delay in material posted here reaching my constituency and my home but I received little information.  I was told I should log everything to prove what I said.  I am pleased to support Senator Fitzgerald and others who raise this issue because I have been raising it with An Post for almost 12 months but to no avail.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MauriceManning" hpid="Mr. Manning Mr. Manning">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Manning</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator Wright and others raised the Adoption (No. 2) Bill.  I hope and expect that Bill can be taken at 8 p.m. tomorrow but I will consult with the Opposition to confirm that. <Col N="373" /> Senator Wright also asked for time to be made available to debate the motion tabled by Senator Ormonde and others.  We will take the Finance Bill for two days next week and a great deal of other business.  However, I told Senator Ormonde I would make time available for that motion.  I suggest that, rather than taking the motion, we might make an hour available for statements on that subject in the presence of the Minister.  I know from what Senator Ormonde has said that that would meet her requirements on the matter.  The Minister for the Marine will be the House before the end of the session and he will deal with the issue then.</P>
      <P>Senator Henry raised the question of chemical weapons.  The Chemical Weapons Bill will be taken in this House between now and the end of the session which will provide an opportunity for her to raise those issues.  Senator Honan raised the question of the Adoption (No. 2) Bill, with which I have dealt.</P>
      <P>Senator McAughtry raised the question of adult learning and distance learning.  Many of us feel very strongly about that issue because we see the great work which is done, especially for people who did not have the advantage of a formal education in earlier life and who want to catch up.  If there is time, a short series of statements on that matter to the Minister would be worthwhile.</P>
      <P>Senator O'Kennedy raised two issues.  The Second Stage of the Shannon River Council Bill will be completed.  If that takes a little longer than anticipated, then so be it.  He also raised the question of my comments on the SDLP.  I had the honour of working with senior members of his party last Saturday in Newry.  I do not think anybody has ever had any doubts about Fianna F·il's total support for the SDLP or the good relations between the two parties.</P>
      <P>Senator McDonagh raised questions on adult literacy and remedial teachers.  I will pass those queries on to the Minister.</P>
      <P>Senator McGowan raised a very important point about postal facilities.  There are two possibilities open to us: first, the matter can be referred to the Joint Committee on Commercial State-sponsored Bodies.  However, there is another device open to us in the short term, which is to use the procedure of statements on matters of concern at the close of business.  If between three and five Members spoke briefly on the issue of An Post, I would ensure that the points raised were on the desks of the chairman and chief executive of An Post by the next morning. That would, at least, ensure the point was made.  I suggest the Senator and others use that device tomorrow.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Senator Magner raised the question of journalistic standards.  There is something nauseating about the spectacle of newspapers condemning in their editorial columns what they call tabloid and sleaze practices while devoting column inches on their front pages to copious coverage of the same issues.  Either it is wrong and improper to journalistic <Col N="374" /> standards or it is not, but please spare us hypocrisy on the matter.</P>
    <P>Order of Business agreed to.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Committees of the Houses of the Oireachtas (Compellability," RHead="Privileges and Immunities of Witnesses) Bill, 1995: Second Stage">
    <Title>Committees of the Houses of the Oireachtas (Compellability, Privileges and Immunities of Witnesses) Bill, 1995: Second Stage.</Title>
    <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That the Bill be now read a Second Time.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="AvrilDoyle" hpid="Minister of State at the Department of Finance (Mrs. A. Doyle) Avril Doyle">
      <NameTxt>Minister of State at the Department of Finance (Mrs. A. Doyle)</NameTxt>
      <P>I have had the honour of serving the people of this country on different occasions as a Member of D·il …ireann and previously as a Member of Seanad …ireann.  There are many differences between the two Houses, each of which exercises distinct but connected constitutional functions.  These are known to Senators. Also known to Senators is the fact that, notwithstanding some important differences, there are fundamental characteristics common to both Houses.  In my own experience, the first among these characteristics is the shared commitment of the Members of D·il …ireann and Seanad …ireann to vindicate and protect the democratic rights and freedoms of the citizens of this country. While this may sound extravagant, we who serve in the Houses of the Oireachtas know that this characteristic is given substance in the reality of the daily grind of legislative and other business conducted by the Members of this House and the D·il &mdash; often unreported, frequently unobserved and usually unacknowledged.  Yet we in these Houses know, as do the citizens of the new democracies of central and eastern Europe, that the true value of our work as parliamentarians might be seen only if it were lost.</P>
      <P>One such role is to investigate and reveal the facts in relation to matters of great public importance. However, somewhere along the road from Westminster to the present, Irish parliamentarians lost the legal power to coerce witnesses into attending before them and answering their questions which was transmitted to every post-colonial parliament in the English speaking world.</P>
      <P>This loss may not have been immediately evident. Committees were solemnly entrusted in their Orders of Reference with the &ldquo;power to send for persons or papers&rdquo;.  Those for whom we sent generally came.  In recent years, as the concerns of our committees widened, situations were encountered where some of those for whom we sent declined to come; those who came from time to time declined to respond to questions which we thought important, others thought it best to withhold from us documents which we felt might throw light on murky corners.  What this Bill does, essentially, is to ensure that a call from a committee of this or our companion House is a call which cannot be denied.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>At present a committee engaged on a legitimate fact finding mission in the interest of the <Col N="375" /> public can, when blocked in its quest, call to its aid nothing more than whatever degree of public opinion it can arouse by its reaction.  Those who treat an Oireachtas committee with contempt are unlikely to be unduly influenced by reports of our criticism or endorsement of it by the press.  This Bill will give such a committee a more sure and effective sanction.  Unjustified refusal to comply with its demands will put the <i>refusenik</i> on the hazard of court action, fines and even, not to put a tooth in it, prison.</P>
    <P>Nor will a committee have to flounder around and speculate about what documents a potential witness may have and hope to strike it lucky by hitting on the precise document it wants.  It is being specifically empowered under section 3 to do as the courts can do and require a witness to &ldquo;discover&rdquo;&mdash; or list out on affidavit &mdash; what material he or she has that is relevant to the subject matter of a committee's inquiries.</P>
    <P>The basic purpose of this legislation is to increase the capacity of Oireachtas committees to investigate areas of public concern.  It is part of the Government's comprehensive programme of legislative reform under the strategic management initiative.  Taken together with other legislation it is designed to modernise and streamline the operation of the public services &mdash; including the Houses of the Oireachtas.</P>
    <P>The powers to be conferred by this Bill involve the interrelated concepts of compellability, privilege and immunity.  Compellability means that committees of both D·il …ireann and Seanad …ireann, with authority to send for papers and persons, may be given powers to require witnesses to attend hearings and to respond to questioning when they attend.  Such committees will also be able to compel the submission of documents as evidence. This is a substantial increase in the power of Oireachtas committees which will confer on Deputies and Senators acting through them a significantly enhanced capacity to inquire into and investigate matters of pressing public concern.</P>
    <P>The concepts of privilege and immunity are proper and necessary counterweights to these powers of compellability.  As the inquiries of committees acting with powers of compellability will be quasi-judicial in nature, witnesses who are compelled to attend and give evidence before hearings of such committees must have available to them an appropriate measure of protection from the consequences of the evidence they are required to give.  This is in the interests of natural justice.  Accordingly, under this Bill, committees with powers to compel witnesses to attend and give evidence will be able to grant to those witness the equivalent of &ldquo;High Court&rdquo; privilege. This means that the evidence given by such witnesses does not leave them open to defamation actions or self-incrimination.</P>
    <P>Under Article 15.13 of the Constitution, Deputies and Senators have absolute privilege in respect of utterances in either House of the <Col N="376" /> Oireachtas.  This means that they are not liable to any legal action arising from statements they make in D·il …ireann or Seanad …ireann as the case may be.  Since 1976 this absolute privilege has been extended, by legislation, to Members of the Houses of the Oireachtas speaking at committee meetings.</P>
    <P>However, under existing law, witnesses giving testimony before committees of the D·il or Seanad are entitled only to &ldquo;qualified privilege&rdquo;. This form of privilege does not prevent legal action being taken but it allows a defence against libel or slander unless it can be proven that a witness was actuated by a motive not connected with the privilege, that is, by ill-will or spite.  Qualified privilege provides such witnesses with a good defence against actions for defamation; it does not, however, prevent such actions being brought and it provides no protection against actions which could arise from the honest provision of evidence &mdash; actions for breaches of confidentiality, breach of duty or care, for example. Therefore, the risk of legal action with attendant costs, even where a good defence exists, presents a serious hazard to any witness.</P>
    <P>As this Bill will now confer on specific Oireachtas committees new statutory power to compel the attendance and co-operation of witnesses and the furnishing of documents, it is clear that the exercise of such powers could well give rise to major difficulties for such witnesses if they were to have an entitlement to qualified privilege only as at present.  Accordingly, it is right and proper that this legislation should give committees operating under compellability powers the authority to confer enhanced privilege on witnesses. The form of privilege actually conferred is equivalent to that which is available to witnesses giving evidence before the High Court.</P>
    <P>This is virtually identical to the absolute privilege enjoyed by Members of D·il …ireann or Seanad …ireann.  Such privilege is conferred on all persons directed to give evidence or to present documents to such committees.</P>
    <P>In summary, these two elements are essential to the Bill: witnesses may be compelled to give evidence and, if so, those compelled to answer questions are being given protection from any adverse legal consequences of complete responses.</P>
    <P>Issue specific legislation has been used twice in the past to confer absolute privilege for inquiries. The first such example related to the Committee of Public Accounts of D·il …ireann (Privilege and Procedure) Act, 1970.  That committee was charged with investigating events which subsequently became known as the &ldquo;arms crisis&rdquo;.</P>
    <P>More recently, the Select Committee on Legislation and Security of D·il …ireann (Privilege and Immunity) Act, 1994, conferred powers to grant privilege in order to enable that committee to conduct an investigation into the circumstances leading to the fall of the Fianna F·il-Labour Government.  This Bill now means that more permanent arrangements are being put in place <Col N="377" /> which will allow certain committees of the D·il and Seanad to assume powers to compel witnesses and to confer privilege without the need for separate legislation in each case.</P>
    <P>The Bill provides that D·il …ireann or Seanad …ireann will determine individually or jointly in framing orders of reference for existing or new committees whether they are to have the specific powers to send for persons or papers which would bring the compellability and privilege powers into effect.  The Bill before Members allows for the Committee on Procedure and Privileges of either House to establish a subcommittee on compellability to determine when these powers should be brought into effect and to apply any limitations on their exercise.</P>
    <P>This provision recognises the independence of each House and preserves the right of D·il …ireann and Seanad …ireann, individually or jointly, to make whatever arrangements it considers appropriate in utilising these new powers. It also ensures that a committee, before deciding to utilise its powers must demonstrate to an authority external to itself, but still within the relevant House, that there is a genuine need to draw on them in a particular instance.</P>
    <P>One characteristic of the way we do business in committees of these Houses has traditionally been one of minimal formality assisted by, dare I say it, indulgent chairmanship when, as happens from time to time, speakers drift away from the precise matter before them.  This lack of rigidity has served us well; it has made it possible for seasoned, intelligent and well briefed defenders of the <i>status quo</i> to be unhorsed by unpredictable but apposite questions which this process can throw up.</P>
    <P>I would be loth to see that informality end but once a committee decides to utilise its powers of coercion, to compel the attendance of witnesses or to answer questions put to them, that informality has to be replaced with a strict adherence to rules and procedures.  That change of mode will, I suspect, be difficult for many of us but it will place on chairpersons of committees a new, and possibly unwelcome, burden.  The Chair will be required to hold the ring not merely between Members but between Members and witnesses. They will also be charged with protecting the rights of those not present to whom reference may be made in the course of a committee's hearings.</P>
    <P>The Bill recognises the crucial situation of the chairperson by naming him or her as the voice through which the committee exercises its powers &mdash; as the signer of orders or requests and as the authority who can remove from a witness the wide privilege which he would otherwise enjoy.</P>
    <P>There is a clear need to provide for a limited number of restrictions and exemptions in relation to the operation of the powers conferred by this Bill.  For example, in keeping with the Constitution, the President and members of the Judiciary will be exempt from this legislation. However, virtually every other citizen is to be <Col N="378" /> compellable by Oireachtas committees acting under these new powers.  This will include members of the public, the Taoiseach, the T·naiste, Ministers, Ministers of State and officials.</P>
    <P>A partial restriction applies to civil servants, gardaÌ and members of the Defence Forces who may not question or express comments on the merits, or the merits of the objectives, of Government policies.  This issue has already given rise to considerable discussion so I propose to consider some of the key matters arising from these restrictions.</P>
    <P>The relevant section of the Bill &mdash; section 15 &mdash; does not prevent a committee, acting with powers of compellability, from calling any civil servant, garda or member of the Defence Forces and requiring that person to answer relevant questions put to him or her by that committee which do not necessitate comments on the merits of Government policy.  Equally, such public servants will be obliged to produce or send documents as evidence if directed by such a committee to do so as long as relevant comments of a public servant criticising the merits of Government policy have been excised or deleted from that document. Once before such a committee, there is no restriction on any line of questioning on matters of policy or even on what advice the relevant public servant may or may not have given to his or her Minister or to the Government.</P>
    <P>The objective of the provisions of section 15 is not in any sense to try to put a gag on any committee pursuing matters of public concern in questioning a public servant on matters of Government policy.  On the contrary, these provisions are intended to facilitate and enhance the working of such committees by providing openly and honestly, clear and comprehensible guidance on the reasonable restrictions which apply.  The purpose of these limited restrictions is to preserve the tradition of independence and the non-political character of the public service.  They are also designed to maintain the integrity of the relationship between Ministers, the Government and their public officials.</P>
    <P>From time to time, civil servants, senior Garda members and officers in the Defence Forces need to give advice or opinions to the Government or to an individual Minister which may include criticism of the merits of policy.  A public servant who demurred from giving an honest and candid view to a Minister or Minister of State would not be doing his or her job and would not last long in my company.  When I do my job as a Minister of State, I pursue Government policy and I am always conscious I am acting for and on behalf of the citizens.  I expect and demand the best and most honest advice available.  I do not want to be told what some official might think I want to hear.  I want officials who tell it like it is, even if that means having to hear a view which criticises the merits of a policy line I am committed to taking. Such advice may or may not be right.  It may <Col N="379" /> or may not be accepted, but I want it said and I want to hear it.</P>
    <P>Why then am I intent on preventing committees having the benefits of the same candour? There is a simple reason relating to the primacy of the democratic element in our governmental arrangements.  Over the past two weeks this House touched upon, in the context of the Public Service Management (No. 2) Bill, the ideal cutoff point between a Minister's responsibility and those of his or her officials.  However divergent the views we may hold on precisely where in a Department a Minister's role should ideally stop, there is a universal consensus that it must encompass decision-making on policy.  Allowing an official to comment on the merits of the policy which has been decided at the political level seems at the least to me and to my colleagues in Government to erode that position.  To do so in what is a political forum, with all the baggage of partisanship that implies, can in practical terms alter the relationship which must obtain between Minister and official where a policy must be implemented.</P>
    <P>We are not creating any new restriction here. There has long been a convention in Oireachtas committees that civil servants are not asked to comment on policy.  That convention has been given statutory form in the Comptroller and Auditor General (Amendment) Act, 1993, prepared when the current Opposition parties were in Government, which forbids accounting officers from commenting and imposes a similar obligation on a constitutional officer, the Comptroller and Auditor General.</P>
    <P>Further matters, which have already led to considerable debate on this Bill, concern the compellability of the Attorney General, the Director of Public Prosecutions and their officers.  Their compellability is to be limited to the general administration of their offices, including statistics in the case of the DPP.  Both are to be compellable before the Committee of Public Accounts.  The Attorney General will not be compellable in his or her role as legal adviser to the Government. This make sense.  I do not believe that any Member would advocate a situation in which the Attorney General might be required to give evidence which compromised the crucial lawyerclient relationship central to our system of Government.  Moreover, the Attorney General is not to be made compellable in his or her role as defender of the public interest.  This is also reasonable.  Whatever action an Attorney General might see fit to take with respect to individual cases must have the protection of confidentiality. Given these reasonable requirements, the arrangements to limit the compellability of the Attorney General to the Committee of Public Accounts constitute an appropriate and workable balance.</P>
    <P>With respect to the Director of Public Prosecutions, the original proposals excluded the Director from compellability but the Minister for <Col N="380" /> Finance signalled on Second Stage in D·il …ireann that an amendment would be brought forward to encompass certain aspects of this office within the terms of the Bill.  As Senators will be aware, the DPP chose to refuse to accept an invitation to appear before an Oireachtas committee, but shortly afterwards agreed to participate in a popular radio phone-in programme. Therefore, the Bill now before this House provides for the compellability of the DPP on much the same terms as the Attorney General.  This again is a reasonable and balanced response to this important question which also reflects the feelings of many in this House.</P>
    <P>I want to draw the attention of the House to a number of exempted matters relating to the powers of compellability provided for in this Bill. These arise in relation to evidence or documents likely to prejudice Cabinet confidentiality, matters <i>sub judice</i>, State security and relations with other States, criminal matters and tax liability assessment.  Before the Bill in its original form was published, much attention was given to working out the precise nature of these exemptions and how differences of opinion between a committee and a witness on such matters might be determined.</P>
    <P>In relation to the particular matters exempted, they do not go beyond the kind of issues which an investigative committee in a similar jurisdiction would try to avoid.  These include State security, matters <i>sub judice</i> or which are the subject of separate statutory arrangements, such as the assessment of an individual's liability for tax.  The Bill provides mechanisms to ensure that such exemptions will not be invoked frivolously or lightly.</P>
    <P>In relation to matters affecting the security of the State, relations with other states or the prevention, detection or investigation of criminal offences, we have not left the adjudication to the individual Department or Minister involved. Instead we have decided that, even within the framework of Government administration, those who feel they have grounds for invoking these exemptions will have to secure the agreement of a specific public servant &mdash; the Secretary to the Government who, by virtue of his position, will have a wider view.  Similarly, a means of referral for determination by the High Court is provided for in relation to questions arising about matters <i>sub judice.</i></P>
    <P>Witnesses may also inform a committee if they believe a direction falls within the limits of High Court privilege and a mechanism to allow for the determination of such matters by the High Court is also provided.  This mechanism replaces a more complex arrangement in the Bill as originally published, which provided for four specific exempt categories including: information given and received under pledge of confidentiality, information affecting a person's business, profession or occupation, information affecting a person's family life or private affairs and information whose disclosure would be prejudicial to relations with other states.  The letter exemption <Col N="381" /> has been included in another section, as I referred to earlier, but the other three specified exemptions have been deleted from the Bill.</P>
    <P>A further safeguard built into the details of this complex Bill concerns third parties who are identifiable from committee questioning.  In such cases, persons who are referred to by name or who might otherwise be identified during committee proceedings, will be granted the right to appear before the investigating committee to vindicate their good name.  Arrangements have also been included to enable a committee to hear evidence from an employer, a person acting on behalf of an employer or a body.</P>
    <P>The powers conferred on Oireachtas committees by this Bill are to be underwritten by substantial penalties to be imposed on those found guilty of an offence arising from a committee acting under compellability powers.  The fines provided for have been supplemented by the option of imprisonment.  I am satisfied that these penalties are appropriate to the importance of the measures being provided for in the Bill.</P>
    <P>I re-emphasise the importance of this modernising and challenging Bill.  The empowering of certain committees of the Houses of the Oireachtas to allow them to investigate substantial issues of public interest and concern has the potential to transform the role of the D·il and the Seanad in the public life of this State.  Members understand the scope and potential of the Bill but I believe that its real benefits will not become clear to the general public until the practice and techniques of investigating matters under the compellability powers provided are fully developed.  When these implications become more widely known and the powers conferred by the Bill come to be exercised, a greater appreciation of the value of these new powers will be more widely acknowledged.</P>
    <P>I am presenting this Bill not in any partisan sense but as a set of legislative proposals which have drawn together the views of a wide crosssection of public opinion.  The exercise of these new powers will make demands on the Members of this House and D·il …ireann.  There is a well-established tradition of co-operation between the two Houses in our jurisdiction, influenced, no doubt, by the regular interchange of personnel between them.  It would be improper of me to trespass on the prerogatives of either House of the Oireachtas or to try to prescribe in legislation how the relationship between the D·il and Seanad should be conducted.  However, in line with that tradition of co-operation and having regard to the independence of each House, I will, on the enactment of the Bill, draw the attention of the Committee on Procedure and Privileges of each House to the desirability of their entering a concordat on the manner in which they operate this legislation.  I commend the Bill to the House.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelMulcahyFF" hpid="Mr. Mulcahy Mr. Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Mulcahy</NameTxt>
      <P>I welcome the Minister and thank her for outlining her explanation and theory of this Bill, what it proposes to do and what <Col N="382" /> it seeks to achieve.  It would be no exaggeration to say that consideration of this Bill and its elements and powers causes concern with the very highest principles of the Constitution of Bunreacht na h…ireann.</P>
      <P>It is clear from the Constitution that there is a tripartite system of Government: executive, legislative and judicial arms.  The doctrine of the separation of powers is well known, understood and accepted by all.  It is essential that legislation fully respects the integrity of each of the three arms of Government and indeed their independence.</P>
      <P>Given that the Bill proposes a set of rules for the Oireachtas to provide working procedures why was it drafted by the Government in the first instance?  Why is one arm of the Government proposing to another how it should undertake its work?  The Government would be surprised if the Oireachtas proposed that it should work in a certain way and I would find support for that proposition in Bunreacht na h…ireann.  Article 28.4.1∫ clearly states: &ldquo;The Government shall be responsible to D·il …ireann&rdquo; and Article 15.2.1∫ states: &ldquo;The sole and exclusive power of making laws for the State is hereby vested in the Oireachtas: no other legislative authority has power to make laws for the State.&rdquo;  It is interesting to note the section on the Oireachtas in the Constitution precedes the provisions relating to the Government. In other words, the Constitution almost seems to see the Oireachtas as perhaps an even more important organ of Government than the Executive. As a general proposition this Bill should &mdash; I am not making a party political point &mdash; have been drafted by the committee inquiring into this matter because it is for the Oireachtas and should have been written, drafted and finally approved by it as it governs matters for the Oireachtas, not for the Government.</P>
      <P>The Fianna F·il Party has been calling for this legislation for some time and I believe it was contained in the original Programme for Government. When this legislation was introduced by the Minister for Finance, Deputy Quinn, he accepted it was not perfect and that it would require a great deal of amendment.  The Bill has been amended, but its net effect will be to curb rather than expand the scope and powers of the Legislature. That is not the proper way to proceed.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The provisions of the Bill are applicable only to certain committees.  Why do they not apply to all committees?  Why is there such a restriction? The Attorney General and the Director of Public Prosecutions can only be compelled to attend before the Committee of Public Accounts.  That committee has a narrow brief regarding financial provisions, administration, statistics and so forth and many areas of policy and operations where the Attorney General and the Director of Public Prosecutions are concerned are outside its remit. Why was it decided to cut off the compellability provisions regarding those office holders at that point?  Why was it decided that other committees could not compel the Director of Public Prosecutions <Col N="383" /> and the Attorney General to come before them?</P>
    <P>The Minister of State outlined the events which led to the fall of the Government in 1994, when former Attorneys General gave evidence before a committee set up by the D·il.  This Bill would restrict that right and, although the Minister of State did not say as much, the legislation in that case worked.  She also referred to the arms crisis. During the arms crisis and after the fall of the Government in 1994, important people were brought before relevant committees of the Houses.  Why are we now proposing to limit the ability of the Houses to bring people such as the Director of Public Prosecutions before their committees? That important question must be answered.</P>
    <P>In the initial draft of the Bill, the Minister for Finance proposed that if there were meetings between Ministers of State and civil servants, the civil servants could not be compelled to appear before a relevant committee.  I understand the provision regarding civil servants has been deleted but Ministers of State are still excluded from being compelled to appear before a D·il committee.  Can the Minister of State confirm that?</P>
    <P>Another important issue is journalistic privilege. It is in the interests of democracy that in certain circumstances journalists should and must be free to conceal the identity of their sources.  If they are not, it is conceivable that many important new stories and items of information will no longer come into the public domain.  Why is it proposed that journalists will not be able to retain concealment of their sources if compelled to appear before one of these committees?  Does the Minister agree that, were it not for the bravery and integrity of several journalists in the past few years, some of the most important stories would not have come into the public domain?  Is the Minister suggesting that had the late Veronica Guerin been subpoenaed before one of these committees she may have been forced to reveal one of her sources, thereby endangering her life? That is an example which could apply to many other journalists.  Journalists who for bona fide reasons, cannot reveal their sources, should enjoy some form of protection.  During the beef tribunal there was a laughable situation where a journalist was prosecuted for failing to reveal her sources while the bigger scandal went largely untouched. We all know how the public felt about that.</P>
    <P>The Minister will also be aware that in the initial publication of this Bill, the Minister for Finance proposed that the Taoiseach should be the final arbitrator in cases where a witness feels he or she cannot give evidence before a committee for various reasons contained in the Bill. Luckily, sense has prevailed and the High Court will now be the final arbitrator as to whether a witness must be compelled to give evidence.  I applaud and welcome that change.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="384" /> Perhaps the Minister can address a specific question in her reply or on Committee Stage. Once a person makes an application to the committee that they are exempt from giving evidence under a certain section and the committee then goes to the High Court for direction, will that person also be represented in High Court proceedings? Will he or she be entitled to legal expenses when the issue is heard and debated before the High Court?  I put it to the Minister that where a person has said to a committee of the D·il that he or she cannot give evidence for a valid reason under the Bill and the matter then goes to the High Court, he or she should be in a position to put their case and give their rationale for that refusal.  If they are not given the support to do that, the High Court hearing will be one sided.  I presume the High Court would automatically request the attendance of the person refusing to give evidence.  There should be a provision for legal expenses, as there should be for those appearing before the committee.  I will return to the concept of privilege against self-incrimination at a later stage.</P>
    <P>As I understand it, the reasonable expenses of people called before a committee will be reimbursed. This does not seem to be specifically mentioned in the Bill.  The legal expenses, if required, of persons appearing before these committees should also be covered.  Situations can arise where a person does not suspect that something they say will incriminate them and it is important he or she has legal advice.</P>
    <P>Why will appeal hearings in the High Court be held in private?  There is a general repugnance against private hearings in the High Court, except in well established cases concerning matrimonial, incest and rape matters.  The public has a right to know about these cases.  There should be a proper explanation given to this House why appeals from such witnesses to the High Court should be in private.</P>
    <P>I would like the Minister's reassurance on one of the most important aspects of this Bill.  How will a witness's privilege against self-incrimination be upheld before D·il committees?  Everyone is aware of the historical precedence of witchhunt committees of legislatures.  The worst and most famous example is the McCarthy hearings in the United States in the 1950s when an unscrupulous chairperson of a legislative committee took it upon himself to engage in a witch hunt and call certain witnesses before the committee.  He maligned and impugned the character of these witnesses before the committees of American Congress.  I hope the Minister is satisfied &mdash; she should also satisfy the House &mdash; that no committee or sub-committee of the Oireachtas will ever be used as a vehicle to stage a witch hunt against any individual.  I hope the good name and reputation of people will be properly protected by all the procedures in this Bill.</P>
    <P>It cannot be said often enough that only the courts are empowered by the Constitution to administer justice.  That is clear from Bunreacht <Col N="385" /> na h…ireann.  The Oireachtas must never attempt to usurp or duplicate that role.  The Oireachtas has no role in the administration of justice.  It has a function in passing laws, a role in monitoring the performance of Government and a role in performing each of its specific obligations under the Constitution &mdash; to elect a Taoiseach, etc. and it is important we underline this fact.</P>
    <P>Committees and sub-committees of the House exist to monitor, filter, assist legislation, inquire into certain matters and find out information for the benefit of Members and the public.  Under our Constitution the Oireachtas has no role in the administration of justice.  It never will have a role in deciding whether people did certain things.  We are not designed to take evidence and cross-examine witnesses.  It would be a sad day for the Oireachtas if committees or sub-committees became mini-courts with party political opinions, biases and prejudices and set themselves up as judge, jury and executioner of other politicians or witnesses.  I think the Minister will agree with this sentiment.</P>
    <P>It is also important from another point of view. Should the party whip system apply to committees where this Bill is enacted?  In the course of Committee Stage of this Bill, senior counsel was consulted.  If I am correct, that senior counsel's opinion said that if a party whip system were used where people had been compelled to appear as witnesses, such decisions would be successfully challenged by judicial review.  The party whip system should have no place in determining matters where people have been compelled before committees pursuant to this Bill.  Having said that, Fianna F·il fully supports this Bill.</P>
    <P>The Oireachtas is the voice and representative body of the people and the people speak through it.  There is no higher authority in the country.  The Minister would agree that over the past several years it has been a source of embarrassment and insult to the Oireachtas when certain chairmen and officials of semi-State companies refused to appear before committees of the Oireachtas when politely asked to do so.  It is a sad day when people who administer public funds and run companies set up by legislation say to the Oireachtas that, although it set up such companies in the first instance, they would not be accountable to it.  In recent years a senior ranking member of the Garda SÌoch·na took a similar view.</P>
    <P>Who are these people to tell the public that they will not be accountable to it?  Everybody must answer to the people in the terms prescribed by the Oireachtas, not as a court of law but as the voice of the people.  If we remember that and keep our thinking clear on the functions and powers of the Oireachtas, its committees and subcommittees and if there is no abuse of this system, the Bill should be put in place.  People must be empowered to summon their servants and agents to provide information about matters which concern them.  That is the fundamental principle of a democracy in the first instance.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="386" /> Having outlined some reservations, I welcome the Bill.  In my view, the Bill should have been drafted by the Oireachtas as a whole and not by the Government.  The Minister for Finance admitted, when introducing the Bill that, although it is not perfect, it is long overdue.  We should pass this Bill.  It will be good for democracy and it is essential so that people will know how their money is being spent and how policies are being implemented.  Subject to some amendments which we will table on Committee Stage, Fianna F·il warmly supports the Bill and commends it to the House.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PaddyBurke" hpid="Mr. Burke Mr. Burke">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Burke</NameTxt>
      <P>I congratulate the Minister on the two Bills which she has brought before this House in the past two weeks.  Last week we dealt with the Public Service Management Bill which is a very fine piece of legislation.  The Minister was not present to bring the final draft through this House&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="AvrilDoyle" hpid="Mrs. A. Doyle Mrs. A. Doyle">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. A. Doyle</NameTxt>
      <P>I was completing this Bill in the other House.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PaddyBurke" hpid="Mr. Burke Mr. Burke">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Burke</NameTxt>
      <P>&mdash;&mdash;but she was largely responsible for putting that legislation together.  The Bill will be very important to the running of the Civil Service as it will streamline it and ensure it is more accountable.</P>
      <P>I welcome this Bill and, like Senator Mulcahy, I think it will be very important legislation for the Houses of the Oireachtas.  In the D·il, the Minister said the Bill was part of a programme of legislative change which is transforming the business of the public services, including the Houses of the Oireachtas.  By providing the powers contained in this Bill to committees of the Oireachtas we are catching up with parliaments in other jurisdictions which exercise powers of compellability similar to those set out in the Bill.  The Bill enhances the institutions of democracy.  Elected public representatives meeting in a national assembly should be involved at the centre of the action when questions of major public concern need to be addressed.  The Bill challenges the members of the relevant committees of the Houses of the Oireachtas to use these new powers to demand answers, to seek the truth and to present the facts to the Oireachtas, the Government and the citizens.</P>
      <P>The Minister went on to say that the restrictions and exemptions in the Bill are included in order to make the Bill workable and to ensure that nothing is done to undermine the right conduct of public affairs, the courts or the security of the State.  The restrictions are not there to provide cover for any person who, or organisation which, would legitimately be subject to compellability on the same basis as every other citizen.  In those words the Minister summed up what the Bill is about.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Senator Mulcahy said he felt the Houses of the Oireachtas should have drafted the legislation. The Bill has been in preparation for 12 months <Col N="387" /> and it has proceeded through the Joint Committee on Finance and General Affairs over that period. A special subcommittee was set up to tease out the various aspects of the Bill and to draft amendments and the advice of senior counsel was sought on the drafting of those amendments.  The Minister has done a great job in relation to the various components of this Bill which has had a lengthy passage through the various subcommittees and the D·il.  This is well put together legislation and is very welcome.</P>
    <P>Who can we compel to come before the Houses of the Oireachtas or its committees?  The Minister listed some of the committees &mdash; the Joint Committee on Commercial State-sponsored Bodies, the Committee of Public Accounts, the Joint Committee on Women's Affairs, the Joint Committee on Sustainable Development, the Joint Committee on Small Business, the Joint Committee on the Family and the Joint Committee on Foreign Affairs and each of its subcommittees. These committees can compel members of the Civil Service, county councils, health boards, semi-State bodies, etc. to come before them. Indeed, anybody can be compelled to go before any of these committees with the exception of the Attorney General and the DPP who must go before the Committee of Public Accounts.  The Judiciary and the President are the only people who cannot be compelled to go before the various committees listed in the Bill.</P>
    <P>The Minister has given extreme powers to the various Oireachtas committees, and rightly so. The Oireachtas is a democratic organisation to which people are elected.  The Minister said that Ireland is only now catching up with other European parliaments.  This Bill will give great powers to the elected members of our national assembly and I support that.  It is high time we had the power to compel various bodies, or people representing them, to come before the Joint Committees of the Houses of the Oireachtas.  When people take up responsible positions in the Civil Service or in State-sponsored bodies, they should do so in the full knowledge that at some stage they may be held accountable and compelled to appear before the committees of the Houses of the Oireachtas.</P>
    <P>I congratulate the Minister of State on the various Bills she has introduced in the Houses of the Oireachtas in recent weeks.  The Public Services Management Bill, which was passed last week, will ensure that public servants are held accountable. This Bill will ensure that people, with the exception of the Attorney General, the Director of Public Prosecutions, members of the Judiciary and the President, can be compelled to appear before various committees of the Houses of the Oireachtas.  This must be viewed as a step forward because it gives more powers to the Oireachtas and elected representatives.  We are responsible and answerable to the people who elect us and there is no reason we should not be in a position to compel representatives to appear <Col N="388" /> before committees of the Houses.  Senator Mulcahy expressed reservations about people's rights but they are covered by the Bill.  It is fine legislation and I welcome it and congratulate the Minister for introducing it.</P>
    <Speaker pid="AvrilDoyle" hpid="Minister of State at the Department of Finance (Mrs. A. Doyle) Avril Doyle">
      <NameTxt>Minister of State at the Department of Finance (Mrs. A. Doyle)</NameTxt>
      <P>I thank the Senators for their contributions and interest in the Bill.  Senator Mulcahy raised the separation of powers and the need to respect the tripartite division of powers between the Government, the Legislature and the Judiciary.  He implied that the specification in the Bill in terms of how the system should operate intrudes on the functions or prerogatives of the Houses.  The Government accepts that its function is to propose legislation and that it is up to the Legislature to accept, amend or reject its proposals. The Legislature can do so, just as it can and does prescribe how the Government and its members carry out their business.</P>
      <P>The Senator asked why the Bill is confined to certain committees.  The Bill does not confine these particular powers of compellability, privilege and immunity of witnesses to any specific committees.  The Bill proposes powers for committees which have been empowered to send for persons or papers.  The Bill or the Government will not decide which committees shall have these powers.  The House which appoints the committee makes that decision and will continue to do so.  Likewise, each House will decide when the Bill comes into effect.</P>
      <P>Senator Mulcahy referred to the exemption of Ministers of State from compellability.  I presume his point related to the exemption of committees or subcommittees of the Government which include a Minister of State because I hope he does not consider that Ministers of State are treated differently from Ministers, Members or the public in any other context.  Ministers of State are as compellable as any other citizen, with the exception of the President and members of the Judiciary.</P>
      <P>However, Ministers of State are exempt if they are part of a properly constituted Government committee or subcommittee as defined in the relevant section.  This is the only restriction on the compellability of a Minister of State and it is tightly circumscribed.  Such a committee must be authorised by the Government, the proceedings of its meetings must be reported to the Government and the Secretary to the Government must sign a document containing assurances that it was properly constituted.  In every other respect a Minister of State is compellable on the same terms as any other Member of the D·il or Seanad or citizen of the State.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I assure the Senator that I am introducing the Bill as a parliamentarian.  The legislation was initiated by the Government but, as the Minister for Finance said on Second Stage in the other House, we are open to improvements to the Bill. As the Senator correctly said, the Select Committee on Finance and General Affairs, in response <Col N="389" /> to the Minister's invitation, made substantial improvements to the Bill by way of amendments. The committee deserves special comment because it considered the Bill over many months. It established a subcommittee to examine every section in detail and it employed an eminent senior counsel to advise it as it analysed every line of the Bill.</P>
    <P>The legislation is not being force fed by a Government with a majority because the committee spent days deliberating on it.  I appeared before the committee as it considered the Bill in detail.  We spent many days during the Christmas recess processing Committee Stage in the other House and many changes and amendments were accepted.  Given the adversarial nature of politics not every amendment was accepted but many changes were made.  We were open to accepting amendments as the Minister for Finance indicated on Second Stage in the other House some time ago.</P>
    <P>If one is interested in objectively analysing the progress of the Bill, one will agree it has had a difficult and chequered history.  It was first mooted over 20 years ago and several Governments considered it and left it.  Others had too short an innings to process it to this point, but much work was done on the legislation by the time this Government took office.  It is difficult legislation and legally and constitutionally it was always going to be difficult to get it right. However, I trust we got it right.  Much time and effort inside and outside the Houses of the Oireachtas has been put into ensuring that it complies with all the rules of natural justice and due process.  This is right given that committees will have quasi-judicial powers to investigate matters of major public concern.  We must be scrupulous about ensuring natural justice and due process applies to anybody who is compelled to appear before a committee.</P>
    <P>I appreciate the welcome the Bill has received from Senator Mulcahy and Senator Burke and I thank them.  I listened carefully to their points, some of which related to the provisions of certain sections.  I will be happy to deal with those aspects in detail on Committee Stage.  Many of Senator Mulcahy's criticisms related to the original Bill and not to the Bill as it stands because it was amended considerably.  The Bill is different from the legislation which was introduced in the other House; it is more liberal and much less restrictive than the legislation which was in gestation when the Senator's party was in Government.</P>
    <P>Senator Mulcahy emphasised the need to avoid witch hunts and to ensure that committees do not take on functions appropriate to the courts.  I agree and the Government and I took some stick in the other House about the safety measures which were included in the Bill to avoid committees running foul of the courts or the rights of witnesses.  The Bill has been reinforced in this respect by the provisions which ensure that each committee should be licensed by a subcommittee of the Committee on Procedures and Privileges <Col N="390" /> to embark on the use of its compellability powers. It must get a mandate from a subcommittee of the Committee on Procedures and Privileges to enter compellability mode.</P>
    <P>The reason for providing that committees should refer matters in dispute to the High Court is that it relieves a witness of the cost deterrent of taking proceedings.  The process is akin to the position which arises where a judge refers a case to a higher court.  A witness's rights will be vindicated and upheld.</P>
    <P>Senator Mulcahy referred to the fall of the previous Government in 1994 and said the Bill limits the authority of the House to call, for example, the Attorney General before a committee.  This is not the case.  The 1994 committee heard evidence from Attorneys General who chose to attend and answer questions.  There is nothing in this Bill to prevent an Attorney General from attending. What it does is limit the circumstances in which they can be compelled to attend.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelMulcahyFF" hpid="Mr. Mulcahy Mr. Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Mulcahy</NameTxt>
      <P>Why?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="AvrilDoyle" hpid="Mrs. A. Doyle Mrs. A. Doyle">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. A. Doyle</NameTxt>
      <P>For reasons clearly stated earlier. The Deputy has read the transcripts of the debate in the other House.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelMulcahyFF" hpid="Mr. Mulcahy Mr. Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Mulcahy</NameTxt>
      <P>Will the Minister answer my question?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="AvrilDoyle" hpid="Mrs. A. Doyle Mrs. A. Doyle">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. A. Doyle</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator Mulcahy raised the issue of applying the Whip in committees.  The Whip will apply to committees in terms of attendance and certain categories of votes.  However, it cannot operate in a manner which would diminish the role of a committee operating in a quasi-judicial mode.  It cannot be used to dictate to committees any particular conclusion in the evaluation of evidence.</P>
      <P>Regarding Senator Mulcahy's point about High Court examinations being held in private, it seems appropriate and necessary to ensure that the injury which a witness would seek to avoid by claiming privilege under section 6(1) of the Bill would not be jeopardised by a breach of confidentiality. The purpose of the section referred to by the Senator is to protect such witnesses from not concealing information properly available to a committee.</P>
      <P>I will deal with the points raised regarding the DPP, the Attorney General, committees, etc., in detail on Committee Stage.  I thank Senators for their contribution to Second Stage.  This is extremely important legislation, something that will not be evident to the public or indeed Members not present, until committees begin operating under the Bill.  The extent and importance of the powers the legislation confers on the House will then become obvious.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>In the transfer between Westminster and our own Parliament we lost the powers of compellability, powers which all other western jurisdictions have and operate successfully.  The Bill <Col N="391" /> has huge implications for the conduct of chairpersons. Much of the informality and <i>ad hoc</i> arrangements which have characterised committees and through which committees have successfully operated because of the less adversarial nature of the informality, will have to end when a committee begins operating under the Bill.</P>
    <P>In the interests of natural justice a chairperson will have a very strict role in conducting procedures under which questioning may be carried out and in deciding when a witness steps beyond the bounds in which privilege can be extended to them.  A huge responsibility attaches to the enormous powers the Bill confers on committees of the Houses.</P>
    <P>The Bill in no way restricts any committee that the Houses of the Oireachtas might decide from operating under the powers of compellability. The Houses rather than the legislation will decide to which committees the Bill will refer.  This is as it should be.  None of us should legislate regarding what committees of the Houses should do.  Terms of reference should be decided upon by the Houses.</P>
    <P>I thank Senators for welcoming the Bill and for their co-operation and constructive contributions. I will answer the points raised in more detail on Committee Stage.</P>
    <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>When it is proposed to take Committee Stage?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PaddyBurke" hpid="Mr. Burke Mr. Burke">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Burke</NameTxt>
      <P>Today at 5 o'clock.</P>
      <P>Committee Stage ordered for 5 o'clock today.</P>
      <P>
        <i>Sitting suspended at 4.5 p.m. and resumed at 5 p.m.</i>
      </P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Committees of the Houses of the Oireachtas (Compellability, Privileges" RHead="and Immunities of Witnesses) Bill, 1995: Committee and Final Stages">
    <Title>Committees of the Houses of the Oireachtas (Compellability, Privileges and Immunities of Witnesses) Bill, 1995: Committee and Final Stages.</Title>
    <P>Sections 1 to 4, inclusive, agreed to.</P>
    <P Just="Center">SECTION 5.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JarlathMcDonagh" hpid="Acting Chairman (Mr. McDonagh) Acting Chairman (Mr. McDonagh)">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman (Mr. McDonagh)</NameTxt>
      <P>There is an error in the printed version of amendment No. 1. The new subsection should be subsection (5) rather than subsection (3).  Is the amendment agreed?  Agreed.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelMulcahyFF" hpid="Mr. Mulcahy Mr. Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Mulcahy</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 1:</P>
      <P>In page 9, between lines 36 and 37, to insert the following new subsection:</P>
      <P>&ldquo;(5)  A committee may not direct a witness to give evidence or produce or send to it a document relating to the source of any information required by that committee where such witness satisfies the Committee that&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="392" /> (a)  such information was obtained by him in the course of his occupation as a journalist, and</P>
    <P>(b)  the objection to giving such evidence or producing such document is reasonably based upon the preservation of anonymity assured by him to the person the source of such information.&rdquo;.</P>
    <P>This amendment seeks to protect journalists and their sources of information.  Everyone knows this is an important topic.  In recent years, many great issues have come to light only because certain sources gave information to journalists, who subsequently communicated those stories to the public. There are provisions in English law which specifically recognise &ldquo;whistle blowing&rdquo; in public administration, so that when an official sees something wrong he or she can report it and obtain protection from the State to ensure his or her position will not be undermined.  It would be an attack on freedom of speech and all types of journalism if a journalist was forced to disclose to a committee of the Oireachtas the source of his or her information.</P>
    <P>The amendment uses the word &ldquo;and&rdquo; between paragraph (a) and (b).  In other words, it is not sufficient for the journalist to claim such information was obtained by him in the course of his occupation, it is also a prerequisite that the objection to giving this evidence or producing a document is reasonably based on the preservation of anonymity assured by him to the person who was the source of such information.  If a journalist is compellable as a witness to a House of the Oireachtas and can be forced, on sanction of fine and/or imprisonment, to reveal the source of information, sources will dry up.  If that was the case, the public will be the losers because it is they who benefit when responsible journalists bring important stories &mdash; which may have been hidden for many years &mdash; to bear on the public consciousness.  If the amendment is not accepted, might an investigative journalist &mdash; such as the late Veronica Guerin or any other journalist reporting dangerous crime stories &mdash; be forced, under pain of fine or imprisonment, to reveal sources which could place the journalist in danger from the source or a criminal third party, or place the source in danger from a criminal?</P>
    <P>Under common law and existing statute law journalists do not enjoy immunity and cannot refuse to disclose to a court the source of information. However, as I said earlier, we must differentiate between a court of law and a committee or sub-committee of the Oireachtas.  When administering justice a court may decide it is in the interests of justice that a journalist's source be revealed to it.  In non-judicial proceedings, is there necessarily a public interest in revealing the source of a journalist's story?  From the viewpoint of the D·il or Seanad, the important issue is that the committee should be aware of the information the journalist has to hand, not its source. The Minister accepted that no judicial function is <Col N="393" /> bestowed on these committees.  The public was horrified that the journalist who largely broke the beef industry story was prosecuted because she would not reveal the sources of her information. That happened in the context of a judicial tribunal, admittedly set up by the Oireachtas but administered by a judge of the High Court.</P>
    <P>It is in everyone's interest that this amendment is accepted and that a journalist's sources should be protected when a journalist appears before a committee.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MauriceManning" hpid="Mr. Manning Mr. Manning">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Manning</NameTxt>
      <P>I see Senator Mulcahy's point and have some sympathy for his objective. However, his proposal would probably not be easy to implement for one or two basic reasons. If a serious investigative journalist is summoned to appear before a committee of either House of the Oireachtas, it is almost certain that close to half the members of that committee will be very keen on what the journalist is trying to reveal while others will not.  There will be an in-built balance in the committee which will almost certainly work against any draconian attempt to force the journalist to reveal his or her sources, especially if it is a bona fide investigation.</P>
      <P>The problem is that the Senator's amendment does not differentiate &mdash; which it may not be possible to do &mdash; between a serious, bona fide, investigative journalist who is pursuing the public interest and has unearthed information which should be in the public domain but who may not be able to disclose his or her sources, and somebody who can make unfounded slanderous allegations of the most base sort against Members of the House.  When such a person is brought before a committee of this sort, and although they may have no evidence &mdash; or the flimsiest of evidence &mdash; and no sources, they can claim the protection of the code of journalistic immunity which, as the Senator said, has no standing in a court of law.</P>
      <P>Matters such as these are probably best left to the dynamics of an actual situation where, if somebody feels their case should be made, the common sense and sense of fair play of the committee will probably be sufficient to prevent any draconian measures being taken against a journalist, or any unfairness.  I worry that the Senator's amendment would almost confer a sense of total immunity on journalists whom other journalists might not respect and whose motives might not be subject to the closest scrutiny.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="AvrilDoyle" hpid="Minister of State at the Department of Finance (Mrs. A. Doyle) Avril Doyle">
      <NameTxt>Minister of State at the Department of Finance (Mrs. A. Doyle)</NameTxt>
      <P>I thank Senator Mulcahy for the points he made in his amendment, but it will not come as a surprise to him that I am not in a position to accept it.  I also thank Senator Manning for his very reasonable explanation of one of the reasons I am not, and should not, be in a position to accept the amendment and I fully support the case he made.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>While I appreciate the concerns expressed by Senator Mulcahy, as does Senator Manning, the <Col N="394" /> subsection to which the amendment refers provides for the protection of sources used by elected representatives.  It was framed in the light of the High Court finding on the beef tribunal that such sources could remain confidential.  The intention of the amendment is to extend the absolute privilege on protection of sources to journalists as well as Oireachtas Members.  As the proposal would put journalists on a par with elected Members and give them a higher level of protection than that of other High Court witnesses, I cannot accept the proposal.</P>
    <P>The position in this regard is currently being examined in the Department of Justice in the light of the Law Reform Commission report and a European court case.  We all have concerns about protecting the sources used by serious journalists.  However, as Senator Manning rightly pointed out, if this provision is made one cannot judge at that point in proceedings who is a serious journalist.  There is a balance to be struck here. Any resulting legislation from the Department of Justice will adjust this Bill in line with any revised arrangements introduced for the courts.</P>
    <P>We are staying in line with the courts procedure in this regard, rather than going ahead of what the courts may do in relation to the protection of sources, which is reasonable.  If, when the Department of Justice, the Law Reform Commission and the European courts put their heads together, the situation in relation to our courts is changed &mdash; I am not qualified to comment on whether it will be except to support the general feeling that we should look at this area to ensure what we are doing is right &mdash; this Bill will be adjusted in line with those changes.  I have no difficulty with that, but I suggest it is not our position to pre-empt any change in the Department of Justice or go ahead of what might be done in the courts.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelMulcahyFF" hpid="Mr. Mulcahy Mr. Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Mulcahy</NameTxt>
      <P>I thank the Minister of State for saying this section will be reviewed in the light of the general inquiry into the broader aspects of journalistic immunity.  However, I am not completely convinced by her arguments or those of Senator Manning.  What is the purpose of an Oireachtas committee?  I cannot see why such a committee should ever be involved in unravelling minutiae such as who said what to which journalist. That is not the function of such committees.</P>
      <P>Senator Manning and the Minister of State referred to the difference between serious and non-serious journalists.  There are serious and non-serious members of every profession. Journalists might say there are serious and non-serious politicians.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MauriceManning" hpid="Mr. Manning Mr. Manning">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Manning</NameTxt>
      <P>They do.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelMulcahyFF" hpid="Mr. Mulcahy Mr. Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Mulcahy</NameTxt>
      <P>That is not a legitimate argument. The matter is either right in principle or it is not.  If this amendment is not accepted, a Deputy, Minister or Taoiseach could make an off the cuff remark to a journalist, who could then <Col N="395" /> be subpoenaed to appear before the committee, which could demand to know who had made the remark to the journalist.  Will we open the can of worms so that even informal remarks made by politicians to journalists &mdash; the famous off the cuff and off the record briefings &mdash; will become part of the <i>matÈriel</i> of Oireachtas committees?</P>
      <P>There have always been two sides to the argument on whether journalists should enjoy privilege in regard to their sources.  However, I do not believe it can, or should, be the business of Oireachtas committees to inquire to that extent into journalists' sources.  That level of inquiry is normally a judicial or quasi-judicial route.  The Minister of State said on Second Stage that some Oireachtas committees would have quasi-judicial functions.  However, committees do not have such functions.  Quasi-Judicial functions are normally specifically set up under legislation to determine disputes, of which there are not many cases.</P>
      <P>I do not see how it is the business of those committees to get into that area.  However, if the Minister of State says this matter will be reviewed in light of the departmental review, I am prepared not to press the amendment to a vote.</P>
      <P>Amendment put and declared lost.</P>
      <P>Section 5 agreed to.</P>
      <P>Sections 6 to 14, inclusive, agreed to.</P>
      <P Just="Center">SECTION 15.</P>
      <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That section 15 stand part of the Bill.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelMulcahyFF" hpid="Mr. Mulcahy Mr. Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Mulcahy</NameTxt>
      <P>I oppose this section because it restricts certain people questioning or expressing an opinion on the merits or objectives of Government policy.  It makes a nonsense of some of the primary functions of D·il committees.  If a Government decided not to spend more money on prisons when there were no prison places left it would result in the release of those convicted of serious offences within one hour of being sent to prison.  In such circumstances it would not be open for the Garda Commissioner to criticise that policy before a D·il committee.  This would make a nonsense of the committee and the attendance of such a person before it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The public is able to differentiate between statements on policy made by public servants and the Government.  What is the point of bringing members of the Defence Forces or the Garda SÌoch·na before committees unless they can express opinions?  The only other reason for their attendance would be to provide information which should be available in the normal course of events.  The Oireachtas has just passed the Freedom of Information Bill and all aspects of information regarding statistics on the Garda SÌoch·na and the Defence Forces should be available as of right.  In view of this, why are we even allowing members of these bodies to attend committees if <Col N="396" /> they cannot express opinions on Government policy?  Members of the Defence Forces and the Garda SÌoch·na are the servants or agents of Government policy and it is their job to carry it out.  If the Government considered that it may be embarrassed by utterances published in the media should it not be provided that they may attend committees in closed sessions where Members of this House could quiz them on policy?</P>
    <P>This Bill is concerned with the procedures of this House and has nothing to do with the Government.  If the House is capable of monitoring and criticising the Government why is it not entitled to ascertain in a committee the views of members of the Defence Forces and the Garda SÌoch·na who may also wish to criticise the Government?  There is an unanswerable argument in this regard.  It is the Government's job to govern and to ensure that its civil servants are loyal and obedient, as they all are.  However, it is the job of the Oireachtas to ascertain if there is a conflict between those who make and those who execute policy.  That is why this section should be deleted from the Bill.</P>
    <Speaker pid="AvrilDoyle" hpid="Mrs. A. Doyle Mrs. A. Doyle">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. A. Doyle</NameTxt>
      <P>I accepted points made by Deputies during the D·il Committee Stage. While the extent to which the prohibition on civil servants commenting on the merits of Government policy should be specified, I also indicated that the Government decided that the central point of the section should remain.  I am strongly of this view and profoundly disagree with much of what the Senator has said.  While the text was amended to specify when and how the prohibition was to be applied, I have decided that it will remain.</P>
      <P>Public servants have traditionally provided objective, non political advice to their political masters.  This section, which I stress only prevents certain public servants from commenting on the merits of Government policy, is designed to protect this traditional and long standing neutrality, which has served this State well.  Governments have come and gone over the past 75 years, yet the Civil Service and the public service has managed to serve their political masters, whatever their political complexion, neutrally and in a non political stance.  We have been virtually free of any political scandals in the public service over the years, which is a testimony to the practice in force now.  The Government will do nothing to weaken that position and it stands fully behind a non political public service and Civil Service.  I am surprised at the Senator's suggestion that we adopt another position; perhaps he would reconsider.</P>
      <P>It is proper that public servants should be protected from being forced to answer political questions from political sources.  They will not be prohibited from answering questions of fact with regard to Government policy.  This is the best way to proceed.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="397" /> The Senator constructed the scenario of the Garda Commissioner or any garda appearing before a committee and not being able to answer points regarding, for example, revolving doors in prisons or inadequate numbers of prison spaces. The relevant Minister is the right person to put that question to in any committee operating on a compellability mode investigating this type of area.  If the issue concerned the Garda the Minister for Justice could rightly be questioned on why, for example, the Government was not making sufficient funds available to create extra prison spaces.  Similarly, rather than expect Defence Forces personnel to comment on the merits of Government policy, the Minister for Defence should be called before a committee.</P>
    <P>No public servant should deal with the merits, as distinct from the facts, of Government policy. They are there to serve Governments, of whatever political complexion, and have done so extremely well.  Creeping politicisation of the Civil Service or public service should be nipped in the bud and avoided.  The Senator's proposal does not help in this regard.  When the Senator considers the implication of his amendment, he should agree with my point on the neutrality and non-political nature of our public service.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MauriceManning" hpid="Mr. Manning Mr. Manning">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Manning</NameTxt>
      <P>I support the Minister of State on this point.  One of the great lasting qualities of our public service is that public servants at policy level have the ability to give strong and objective advice.  Any decision is political, even if that is with a small &ldquo;p&rdquo;.  Those public servants can give this advice strongly, knowing they are not being called upon to take a partisan political stance in defence of the advice given.  They have given their advice objectively &mdash; and it is up to Ministers to agree or disagree on it &mdash; but they are protected from the charge of being partisan.</P>
      <P>This is striking when one goes to the National Archives and reads the papers opened every year under the 30 year rule.  That is not so long ago, and it gets nearer as one gets older.  Many of those who were then giving advice as young servants went on to become Secretaries of Departments, and some of them are now discomfited, not at the quality of their advice, but that advice they felt was protected is now open to official scrutiny.  If the Senator's amendment were accepted, it would seriously damage civil servants' sense that their advice is given openly and honestly without their being charged with being partisan.  No matter what advice they give, some political label will be attached to them which could make life difficult for them, building needless suspicion in the subsequent administration that the civil servants were lackeys of the outgoing Government.  It might suggest to the Government of the day that the civil servants had a different ideological point of view.  The Minister of State has made a very good case and any good arising from the Senator's amendment would not compensate for the harm it could do to one of the most important values of our public service.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="398" />
    <Speaker pid="MichaelMulcahyFF" hpid="Mr. Mulcahy Mr. Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Mulcahy</NameTxt>
      <P>We should differentiate between a civil servant, garda or member of the Defence Forces making a politically biased statement of opinion and an opinion on a policy.  The Minister of State will agree that it has frequently been the case that senior civil servants have disagreed with parts of Government policy.  It should not be assumed that they are always in agreement with Government policy.  If that is the case, are Members of the Oireachtas not entitled to know that, for example, the Secretary of a Department is in disagreement with a Minister on a serious policy matter?  This amounts to muzzling of civil servants on policy matters.</P>
      <P>The Minister of State may be aware of a recent matter relating to an embassy in this country. Certain diplomats in that embassy, under their country's laws, used a procedure whereby they bypass their ambassador to report to their own Department of Foreign Affairs on disagreements with their own ambassador.  It is an internal mechanism for them to articulate differences they feel to be important.  There may be <i>bona fide</i> differences on policy matters between experienced civil servants and their Minister.  Are Members of the Oireachtas not entitled to know about that policy difference?</P>
      <P>Put politely, the Minister of State put her foot in it when she said that the Government had decided that this prohibition should remain.  The Government should not be deciding on this Bill. It is a Bill for the Oireachtas and the Oireachtas's purposes, not a Bill in which the Government can say what they like or dislike.  The Minister of State said several times that the prohibition should remain and also said that civil servants should not get involved in the debate on the merits of Government policy.</P>
      <P>Senator Manning was correct to a large degree, but that is the old interpretation of civil servants, which sees them as automatons of Government policy.  With the strategic management initiative the Minister of State is working on, civil servants are becoming a more dynamic part of the formulation of Government policy.  As Governments and Ministers change rapidly, the Secretary becomes more critically involved in all aspects of Government policy, frequently issuing statements on that policy.  That is most frequently seen in cases involving financial institutions such as the Central Bank, the Bank of England or the Federal Reserve.  These are civil servants with policies on fiscal matters.  Can the Director of the Central Bank, who is presumably a civil servant&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="AvrilDoyle" hpid="Mrs. A. Doyle Mrs. A. Doyle">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. A. Doyle</NameTxt>
      <P>He is not a civil servant.  The Senator should know that intellectual pecking order.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelMulcahyFF" hpid="Mr. Mulcahy Mr. Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Mulcahy</NameTxt>
      <P>There is no need for insults.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="AvrilDoyle" hpid="Mrs. A. Doyle Mrs. A. Doyle">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. A. Doyle</NameTxt>
      <P>Either way.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="399" />
    <Speaker pid="SeanFallon" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator Mulcahy on the section, and without interruption.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelMulcahyFF" hpid="Mr. Mulcahy Mr. Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Mulcahy</NameTxt>
      <P>It seems ludicrous that people involved in advising Ministers on serious aspects of policy are to be muzzled by the Government. That is what this section does to civil servants whose opinions may be in conflict with the Government, unless the Minister of State is about to say that such an event does not arise, which I do not accept.  In many cases there may be very serious differences of opinion.  Why then is it not up to the Oireachtas to decide if we are entitled to hear the views of a civil servant, garda or member of the Defence Forces?  Why is the Government saying that the Oireachtas cannot decide what it wants to hear?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MauriceManning" hpid="Mr. Manning Mr. Manning">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Manning</NameTxt>
      <P>There is an important distinction absent from the Senator's argument.  If a senior civil servant feels a Minister is behaving improperly, that is a different matter.  Then the civil servant has a duty, if the Minister is, <i>ultra vires</i>, behaving improperly, to go public.  I agree with that, and there are may ways it can be done.</P>
      <P>Policy is a different matter.  We had a debate last week on the Universities Bill, 1996.  For all I know, there may have been strong differences of opinion between the three advisers from the Department of Education with the Minister. Their views on certain sections of the Bill may have been different to those of the Minister and may have been closer to those of Senator Ross, Senator Norris, a Senator with strong views or the spokesperson for the main Opposition party.  Can Senator Mulcahy imagine a situation where the Minister's advisers fed scripts supporting their point of view to the Opposition benches?  Imagine the chaos, breakdown in solidarity and distrust in a Department.</P>
      <P>A Minister has a right to expect total loyalty from civil servants and in 99.9 per cent of cases, he or she gets it.  A Minister also has a right to expect his or her officials to debate the issues openly in his or her presence to devise the best possible policy.  This is a political society, decisions are political and are taken in these Houses and at the Cabinet table.  The Minister is responsible to the House and to the public and must know that he or she is not being second guessed or stabbed in the back, because that is what it would amount to, and that a careerist civil servant is not trying to carry favour with a party he or she believes may be in Government in the near future or that an opportunist ambitious civil servant is not betraying confidences from within the Department on the basis of policy disagreements.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelMulcahyFF" hpid="Mr. Mulcahy Mr. Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Mulcahy</NameTxt>
      <P>That can happen now.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MauriceManning" hpid="Mr. Manning Mr. Manning">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Manning</NameTxt>
      <P>There can be leaks and disloyal civil servants but, by and large, there has been a tradition of loyalty and coherence in Departments and of honest advice being given to the <Col N="400" /> Minister even when the people involved disagree with the general thrust of policy.  Ultimately, the buck stops with the Minister who must have the backing of Government.  The last thing a Minister wants is to fear that one of his or her closest advisers is feeding information to the Opposition and to newspapers betraying confidences all in the guise of a genuinely held difference of view on policy.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="AvrilDoyle" hpid="Mrs. A. Doyle Mrs. A. Doyle">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. A. Doyle</NameTxt>
      <P>It will always be the Government's role to propose legislation and it could not be otherwise.  I cannot envisage a system where Opposition, Government and Independents would get together to draft legislation.  Given our adversarial and democratic system of Government &mdash; wants and all, but nobody has come up with anything better &mdash; the only scenario is that a Government drafts and proposes legislation to both Houses where we can discuss the Stages of a Bill and accept amendments on Committee Stage and sometimes on Report Stage, which is as it should be.</P>
      <P>With our excellent committee system, nearly all legislation is analysed and teased out in detail by all party committees.  After Second Stage in the D·il, this legislation was sent to the Select Committee on Finance and General Affairs, an all party committee which set up an all party sub-committee comprised of legal minds, if I recall correctly, and chaired by Deputy Jim Mitchell, to tease out every aspect of this technical and complicated legislation.  The subcommittee employed an eminent senior counsel to advise it.  Amendments were forwarded on an all party basis. Indeed, Government Members of the Select Committee on Finance and General Affairs proposed amendments to me.  That is a rational, reasonable and excellent way to handle legislation. When we were not in a position to accept an amendment, lengthy, rational and reasonable explanations were given why they could not be accepted, including the two amendments Senator Mulcahy tabled which were recycled from the D·il.</P>
      <P>The object of the provisions of section 15 is not to try to put a gag on a committee pursuing matters of public concern and questioning a public servant on matters of Government policy.  On the contrary, these provisions are intended to facilitate and enhance the working of such committees by providing openly and honestly clear and comprehensive guidance on the reasonable restrictions which must apply.  The purpose of these limited restrictions is to preserve the tradition of independence and the non-political character of our public service.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I pay tribute to public servants who have given an excellent service for over eight decades.  As Senator Manning said, there is an ethos in the public service which is second to none.  The public service is neutral and non-political and can serve Governments of any political complexion.  There is no question of an incoming Government having to carry out a witch hunt, to use Senator Mulcahy's <Col N="401" /> words, to identify which senior civil servants or which civil servants at management level need to be moved because they cannot be trusted. Incoming Governments have happily worked with Secretaries, Assistant Secretaries, principal officers, assistant principal officers and other civil servants who provide objective and honest advice.  That has always been the case.  I could not accept an amendment in this House, nor could I in the D·il a week or two ago, which would weaken that.  These limited restrictions are in place to preserve this independence and non-political character and to maintain the integrity of the relationship between Ministers, the Government and public officials.</P>
    <P>From time to time civil servants and senior members of the Garda SÌoch·na and the Defence Forces need to give advice or opinions to the Government or to a Minister which may include criticisms of the merits of policy.  A public servant who demurs from giving an honest and candid view to a Minister or Minister of State would not be doing his or her job and would not last long in my company.  I like an honest straight up objective view.  When I do my job as a Minister of State I am pursuing Government policy and am always conscious that I am acting for and on behalf of the citizens.  I expect and demand the best and most honest advice available &mdash; our citizens deserve nothing less.  I do not want to be told what an official might think I want to hear.  I want officials who tell it like it is, even if it means having to hear a view which criticises the merit of a policy line to which I am committed.  I could not be straighter than that about this issue.  Such advice may or may not be right or be accepted but I want to hear it if it is the honest view of the public servant.</P>
    <P>Senator Mulcahy might reasonably ask why am I intent on preventing committees having the benefits of the same candour and why will I not accept his amendment.  The reason is simple and related to the primacy of the democratic element in our governmental arrangements which must be upheld above all.  Over the past two weeks, in the context of the Public Service Management (No. 2) Bill, this House touched upon the ideal cut off point between a Minister's responsibilities and those of his or her officials.  However divergent the views we may hold on precisely when a Department's and Minister's role should ideally stop, there is a universal consensus that it must encompass decision making on policy.  Allowing an official to comment on the merits of the policy which has been decided at political level seemed to me and my colleagues in Government to at least erode that position, if not destroy it.  To do so in what is a political forum &mdash; which is what the committees to which the compellability powers apply will be, with all the package of partnership which that implies &mdash; can, in practice, alter the relationship which must obtain between Minister and official where a policy has to be implemented.  We are not creating a new restriction.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="402" /> There has long been a convention in Oireachtas committees that civil servants are not asked to comment on Government policy.  That convention has been given statutory form in the Comptroller and Auditor General Act, 1993, prepared when Senator Mulcahy's party was in Government, which forbids Accounting Officers from commenting and imposes a like obligation on the constitutional officer, the Comptroller and Auditor General.  There is precedent in recent legislation published when the Senator's party was in Government but he appears to be slightly out of step with his party's thinking on this. Further matters which have already led to considerable debate on this Bill concern the compellability of the Attorney General, the Director of Public Prosecutions and their officers; these are separate matters.</P>
    <P>I might have been misunderstood or not heard on Second Stage so I again make the case about the honesty I demand, and any Minister or Minister of State serving the citizens of this country well would demand, from their public servants. However, it is a different matter from expecting public servants to enter the political area in which these committees are and comment on the merits of Government policy.  They are free to speak on the facts of the policy but not about their personal view of its merits.  The Minister responsible for that public servant and that area of policy would comment on its merits, if required.  The non-political and neutral nature of our public service should not be compromised.</P>
    <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
    <P>Sections 16 to 18, inclusive, agreed to.</P>
    <P>Title agreed to.</P>
    <P>Bill reported without amendment and received for final consideration.</P>
    <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That the Bill do now pass.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="AvrilDoyle" hpid="Minister of State at the Department of Finance (Mrs. A. Doyle) Avril Doyle">
      <NameTxt>Minister of State at the Department of Finance (Mrs. A. Doyle)</NameTxt>
      <P>I thank the Cathaoirleach and the officials in the House.  I also thank the Senators, especially Senators Mulcahy, Burke and Manning, for their contributions on Second and Committee Stages.  This is extremely important legislation and the work we have done today is important.  It will significantly enhance the capacity of Oireachtas committees to investigate matters of public concern.  It is a modernising Bill and brings the powers of parliamentary committees up to date and into line with other countries with similar parliamentary systems.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>It is a Bill which challenges Members of this House and D·il …ireann to develop the powers it confers to examine and expose matters which arise from time to time in Irish public life.  It is a Bill which, when in operation, can change for the better the way the Houses of the Oireachtas impact on public life.  Much of what we do in the <Col N="403" /> D·il or Seanad often goes unnoticed and unacknowledged by the public.  This Bill will change that for the better.  I am certain Oireachtas committees, utilising the powers conferred by this Bill, will emphasise to people in public office and the general public the important role of Deputies and Senators in vindicating the democratic rights and procedures of citizens.</P>
    <P>I pay tribute to the Members of this House and D·il …ireann who collectively crafted this important legislation.  This is a much changed Bill compared to the original text and is a better statutory instrument as a result of the improvements brought about at various stages of its passage through the D·il and this House.  I assure Senator Mulcahy especially that it is a Bill which is the product of the collective wisdom of the two Houses of the Oireachtas.  In that sense it is not a partisan measure or legislation which reflects only the view of the Government.  The Bill is a balance between the powers of committees to compel witnesses to give evidence or produce or send for documents and the legitimate entitlements of those witnesses to protection from the consequences.  The limited but necessary exemptions and restrictions embodied in the Bill are only intended to make these powers workable.</P>
    <P>It was said earlier that the core proposals in this Bill have been under consideration for the best part of a quarter of a century, and that is a fact.  Previous Governments of all complexions have examined the issues but this one has bitten the bullet.  We brought forward proposals, invited contributions to improve the Bill and stated we did not think our initial proposals were the final word.  As a result of the work put into this Bill by Members of both Houses, we now have a workable means of empowering committees to take the kind of action all sides in this House and the general public demand.  It is right that representatives of the people meeting in national assembly should be at the centre of the action in matters of great public interest.  This Bill makes that a reality and I have great pleasure in commending it to the House.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelMulcahyFF" hpid="Mr. Mulcahy Mr. Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Mulcahy</NameTxt>
      <P>I pay tribute to the Minister, her advisers and public servants.  This Bill strikes a fair balance between the need of the Oireachtas to subpoena witnesses and documents and the rights of people who appear before it not to have <Col N="404" /> their good names taken in vain unless deservedly so.  No one envisages that this Bill is a charter for people to judge others.  That is not the function of any D·il committee, which is to find out facts and examine matters of relevance.</P>
      <P>This Bill has had a long preparation period.  An enormous amount of work was done on Committee Stage in the D·il and tribute should be paid to Members of that committee for the long hours they put in, as well as the work of the senior counsel who helped them through some of the more technical points.  This was a classic case where good legal opinion was essential because many rights &mdash; those of the Government, the Oireachtas and those of individuals to their good name &mdash; are being balanced in one Bill.  I have never seen legislation dealing with so many different and important converging rights.  By and large, the balance has been well struck.  It is an important Bill because it is vital the Oireachtas, the voice and representation of the people, has this power.  For too long committees have been ignored, snubbed and not paid the due respect they deserve.  I commend and welcome this Bill.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MauriceManning" hpid="Mr. Manning Mr. Manning">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Manning</NameTxt>
      <P>I join in complimenting the Minister on bringing this Bill to finality.  She has been responsible for having some important Bills passed in the life of this Government which will have important long-term consequences in the restructuring of our public and political system. This Bill is one such important measure whose consequences will be felt for decades to come by those who work in this House and are affected by it.  It is an important and overdue reforming measure but one which has benefited from the long discussions surrounding it.  The Minister has handled the Bill with her usual conciliatory style. She has come a long way from the time she sat on the benches opposite and could call a quorum at 20 minutes past midnight when I would not be around.  I compliment the Minister for fine legislation which will stand to her credit.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFallon" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>When is it proposed to sit again?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MauriceManning" hpid="Mr. Manning Mr. Manning">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Manning</NameTxt>
      <P>At 10.30 tomorrow morning.</P>
      <P>The Seanad adjourned at 6 p.m. until 10.30 a.m. on Wednesday, 30 April 1997.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
</Debate>