<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE Debate SYSTEM "../Debate.dtd"[]>
<Debate DocTitle="Seanad Debate" Day="Thu" Date="13" Month="Feb" Year="1997" Vol="150" No="2" DateIrish="Déardaoin, 13 Feabhra 1997" DateEnglish="Thursday, 13 February 1997" House="S" CommitteeEng="" CommitteeIr="" SubNameEng="" cnum="0">
  <MainHeading Type="Prelude" LHead="" RHead="">
    <Title>
    </Title>
    <P>
      <Col N="121" /> Chuaigh an Cathaoirleach i gceannas ar 10.30 a.m.</P>
    <P Just="Center">
      <i>Paidir.</i>
    </P>
    <P Just="Center">
      <i>Prayer.</i>
    </P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Business" RHead="of Seanad">
    <Title>Business of Seanad.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFallon" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I have received notice from Senator Hayes that, on the motion for the Adjournment of the House today, he proposes to raise the following matter:</P>
      <P>The need for the Minister for the Environment to consider the idea of changing the day for national voting from Thursday to Sunday.</P>
      <P>I have also received notice from Senator Finneran of the following matter:</P>
      <P>The need for the Minister for Agriculture, Food and Forestry to have the Suck Valley catchment area included in the new EU category of extremely disadvantaged areas.</P>
      <P>I regard the matters raised by the Senators as suitable for discussion on the Adjournment and they can be taken at the conclusion of business.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Order of" RHead="Business">
    <Title>Order of Business.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="MauriceManning" hpid="Mr. Manning Mr. Manning">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Manning</NameTxt>
      <P>Today's business is items 1 and 2.  Item 1 will be taken until 1 p.m.  There will be a sos from 1 p.m. to 2 p.m.  Item 2 will be taken from 2 p.m. to 5 p.m.  I suggest 20 minutes per speaker on item 2.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TomFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Fitzgerald Mr. Fitzgerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Fitzgerald</NameTxt>
      <P>The Order of Business is agreed.  I thank the Leader for circulating a provisional document on proposed legislation between now and Easter.  It is a good idea that we can see ahead even though there may be changes to that schedule.</P>
      <P>Would the Leader give us an idea of the debates he intends to arrange between now and Easter?  I hope we will have a debate on fishing, safety at sea and the Naval Service.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeOToole" hpid="Mr. O'Toole Mr. O'Toole">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Toole</NameTxt>
      <P>The House should note that a 23 year old, working class man from Peterborough was shot in the back last night in a cowardly act which has brought shame on all of us and those we represent.  This man came from a city which <Col N="122" /> for generations has welcomed Irish people looking for work and who have participated in that city's football and social life.  The maiming of a woman in this incident should also be noted as it marks another new low in our history.  Would the Leader consider allowing time for brief statements on this matter today?  I do not want to interfere with the business of the House but some response is required.  The people I met last night and this morning no longer have words to describe their feelings about this, they just say &ldquo;Who is running the show and how are we to deal with this?&rdquo;  We need to show the public that their elected representatives cannot tolerate this level of outrage and the cowardly approach of those who are, supposedly, acting in our names.</P>
      <P>This morning's newspapers carried articles relating to the Buckley report on the salaries of Members of the Houses of the Oireachtas, among others.  I have not seen this report and I do not know if it has yet been published.  There is a responsibility on this House to have a public debate on that report.  For too long the questions of the salaries, allowances and expenses of political representatives have been brushed under the carpet as if there is something to be ashamed of. As someone who works outside politics and is involved in running an organisation, it is time that we put in context the appallingly low level of reward for those who make a full time career of democracy at the highest level.  We have a duty to have an open debate on this even if it elicits criticism from the media.  It is OK for people like me who have two sources of income, but I want to take on those who criticise me for having double salaries.  I also want to say that there are those in both Houses who commit themselves to full time public representation yet cannot send their children to college and have the normal rewards of life which they should expect.  This is appalling, untenable and unacceptable.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnDardis" hpid="Mr. Dardis Mr. Dardis">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dardis</NameTxt>
      <P>It is essential that we register our strongest possible condemnation of what took place yesterday in Northern Ireland and to extend our sympathy to the family of bombardier Stephen Restorick.  In this morning's newspapers Mr. Adams said that everyone must redouble their efforts to build the peace process.  Once again we have the ultimate cynicism from Sinn Féin and it is essential to state that we, as democrats, know only one way to solve problems and that is through the democratic process and not the point of a gun.  It is not acceptable for Mr. Adams to tell us that it is up to everyone else when he knows that it is within his power and the power of the IRA to advance the peace process and the only way that can be done is not through the point of a gun or with a bomb.  On several occasions in this House within the past couple of years we have hoped when we have condemned other incidents of this nature that they would be the last.  Once again we hope that this will be the last and there will be the route to peace which an end to shootings and bombings can bring us.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="123" /> The other thing which must be said clearly is that the time for the Government to have an open door to Sinn Féin is over if they conduct themselves like this.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMagner" hpid="Mr. Magner Mr. Magner">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Magner</NameTxt>
      <P>I, too, like the other speakers, join in the condemnation of the senseless and brutal killing of a young lad, albeit dressed in khaki, who was, as the Minister for Social Welfare said this morning, a mere boy.  Like Senator Dardis, I canvassed in County Donegal in the by-election on one side of the street and Mr. Gerry Adams was canvassing on the other side of the street.  As was said this morning, you cannot be half a democrat, you are either in this system or you are not. He was not saying to the electors in County Donegal &ldquo;If you do not vote for us, something is going to happen to you&rdquo; or &ldquo;If you object to us, somebody might shoot you from a distance&rdquo;, he was saying &ldquo;Vote for us and be free to vote against us&rdquo; because that is the system in this country.  We thought the idea of the armalite and the ballot box was gone from the island but it is obviously alive and well.  The stature which Mr. Adams attained was due mostly to the belief that he had control over, or at least a major say with, the armed wing.  If he does not have that sort of control, his influence is questionable.  It raises very serious questions despite all the work done by both the Irish and British Governments.  It is very sad and, like the other speakers, I, too, convey my condolences to the young man's parents and colleagues.</P>
      <P>In relation to the other matter which was raised by Senator O'Toole, we have had many debates on low wage jobs and let us put on record that this is a low wage job.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidNorris" hpid="Mr. Norris Mr. Norris">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norris</NameTxt>
      <P>Hear, hear.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMagner" hpid="Mr. Magner Mr. Magner">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Magner</NameTxt>
      <P>Whether you are at it full-time or part-time, the reality is that it is a low-wage job. It is disgraceful that the recommendation made by this committee was so derisory.  It obviously did not listen.  One point of which Senator O'Toole might be aware made across the table at those discussions, at which I was present, was &ldquo;What do you think the public's reaction might be?&rdquo;  to which I replied &ldquo;Your job was to make an objective assessment of the case, find accordingly and then it becomes a matter for the public, the Government and the Oireachtas, but it is not your job to prejudge the public's attitude&rdquo;.  It seems to me that it was a cowardly report, I agree it is time it was debated and it should be debated in this House.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The last thing to which I want to bring the Leader's attention is the Irish Life scenario, where it is almost the stuff of 1913 when you lock people out.  In this day and age that sort of conduct should have no part to play in our industrial relations landscape.  As the Government still possesses a golden share &mdash; it does not have any direct responsibility for Irish Life &mdash; I hope it is <Col N="124" /> noted that this House does not agree with the sort of tactics employed by the company in relation to its staff.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MickLanigan" hpid="Mr. Lanigan Mr. Lanigan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lanigan</NameTxt>
      <P>We all agree a cowardly act was committed in the North last night and everybody should condemn it.  It just shows that a coward takes the cowardly way out and anybody in this House would join in the condemnation.</P>
      <P>On the issue of our salaries, we should wait and see the contents of the report.  I just read <i>The Irish Press</i> this morning&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DanNeville" hpid="Mr. Neville Mr. Neville">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Neville</NameTxt>
      <P>Old tricks die hard.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MickLanigan" hpid="Mr. Lanigan Mr. Lanigan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lanigan</NameTxt>
      <P>The truth is still in the news.  It was a report in the <i>Irish Independent</i> of a report in <i>The Irish Times,</i> so I would like to wait until we see what that report contains.</P>
      <P>One of the reasons Senator O'Toole is able to hold down two jobs is he lives in Dublin.  Anybody who lives down the country and tries to hold down a job there and still be in this House is a failure and no rural business person could keep his business going and be in this House.  I must say this much against myself: if I had stayed at home in 1977 instead of coming in here, my business would be thriving.  Unfortunately, I need to be here now and I intend to try to stay here too. I ask the Leader for a comprehensive debate on that report when it is made public?</P>
      <P>There was a most disturbing report in the <i>Irish Independent</i> this morning about Ms Róisín McAliskey, a young girl who is being held pending her possible extradition to Germany.  I want the Leader to raise this with the Taoiseach.  She has been told that if she has her baby, she will have to have it in handcuffs and she will not be able to care for it afterwards.  I will not say that is medieval, but if the report is true it is an atrocious human rights attack on that girl.  If she were in this jurisdiction, she could not be extradited to Germany.  There is a probability she is not guilt&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFallon" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I would ask you, Senator, to put a question to the Leader.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MickLanigan" hpid="Mr. Lanigan Mr. Lanigan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lanigan</NameTxt>
      <P>&mdash;&mdash;but she is being extradited to Germany to face charges.  In the circumstances we should not leave it be and allow anybody to be incarcerated in handcuffs during the birth of their baby.  The strongest pressure should be put on the British Government in this instance to ensure such human rights violations do not take place. The British are always shouting about human rights violations.  If that report in this morning's <i>Irish Independent</i> is true, that is the vilest of human rights violations.  I ask the Leader to ask the Government to act on the report if it is true?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ShaneRoss" hpid="Mr. Ross Mr. Ross">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Ross</NameTxt>
      <P>I want to say a few words about the death of a British soldier.  I do not agree completely with all my colleagues about the virtues of having a debate on this here.  This is the sort of tragedy to which we have become used and, to be <Col N="125" /> honest, I am sick and tired of the Seanad, the Dáil and politicians elsewhere going through ritual condemnations in order to somehow alleviate their own consciences and disassociate themselves from such acts.  It is not enough.  It is very easy when something like this happens to come in here and say we want another few minutes of condemnation so that the world can see we do not associate ourselves with that.  There is more to it than that.  It is time that we recognised the truth, that is, that we cannot have Ministers continually coming in here disassociating themselves from each atrocity and going back and sending their civil servants out to talk to those who associate with the murderers.</P>
      <P>I would be happy to have several minutes of debate in this House today if a Minister were to come in here with a little more than that to tell us what the Government intended to do about it apart from issuing hollow words.  The reality is that the so-called peace process is over; everybody knows that but nobody will say it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFallon" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator, I would ask you to put a question to the Leader?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ShaneRoss" hpid="Mr. Ross Mr. Ross">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Ross</NameTxt>
      <P>I ask the Leader to go to a Minister or, preferably, the Taoiseach and ask them to come in here and tell us what the Government intends to do about this and if it intends to continue to talk to those people who support or connive with others to commit this sort of murder.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidNorris" hpid="Mr. Norris Mr. Norris">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norris</NameTxt>
      <P>I support my colleague, Senator O'Toole, in asking that a brief period of time be made available to make statements on this matter. It is very important that we signal our feelings to the so-called Republican minorities in south Armagh, Belfast and Derry because there is a sign in Crossmaglen, County Armagh, which states &ldquo;Sniper at Work&rdquo; and I would like to ask the people of that area are they proud of that sign today and has anybody the courage to take it down and tell the IRA exactly what they think.</P>
      <P>I was one of those who voted consistently against the renewal of section 31 of the Broadcasting Act, 1970, and I maintain that position; but I wonder why Mr. Gerry Adams was not filleted on the radio today.  He was squawking in the newspapers within the past couple of days that he was held up for ten minutes at an army checkpoint crossing the Border.  As a citizen of this country my heart goes out to Mr. Adams for that appalling inconvenience but it should be placed on the scales against the cowardly murder of someone who was scarcely more than a boy. Under the rules of hospitality we were responsible for him and his welfare is our concern.  A vote for Sinn Féin is a vote for the people who committed this atrocity against the people of the entire island.  I would like Mr. John Hume to say&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFallon" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>A question for the leader please, Senator.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="126" />
    <Speaker pid="DavidNorris" hpid="Mr. Norris Mr. Norris">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norris</NameTxt>
      <P>&mdash;&mdash;that this marks a conclusive end to any notion of an election pact with the people who are complicit in this crime, which includes Sinn Féin.</P>
      <P>I strongly support the call by my colleague, Senator O'Toole, for a debate and if we have one, let us concentrate on this issue.  I agree with Senator Lanigan about the violation of anyone's human rights but today was not the day to push that issue because it looks too much like the classic green balancing act for my liking.</P>
      <P>I congratulate Senator O'Toole and Senator Magner for having the courage to raise the issue of the pay and conditions of public representatives. We are in an appalling position.  This building is closed from Friday to Monday, we do not have access to our offices and reports of important committees are not published because of financial constraints; we are basically the mucky boys of faceless officials in the Department of Finance.</P>
      <P>The media have a responsibility in this regard; not the mainstream media by and large but the tabloid press who continually lie through their teeth about what happens here.  For example, colleagues, friends and people I work with constantly tell me that Members have a subsidised bar and drink at the taxpayers' expense.  I investigated this; we have good facilities for ourselves and the public and thank goodness for the committee under Senator Magner which achieved that.  However, not only is the Dáil bar not subsidised &mdash; we pay exactly the same price for drink bought there &mdash; we subsidise the Government by handing back £40,000 in tax to the Exchequer every year.  I want these tabloid newspapers to print that fact, because they do not always care for the truth.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFallon" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator, have you a question for the Leader?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidNorris" hpid="Mr. Norris Mr. Norris">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norris</NameTxt>
      <P>My question for the Leader is more or less the same as yesterday.  Can we put our PR people into action and have a face to face meeting with the reporters?  Let us start questioning them.  I do not mean the decent people who are here day after day and do a reasonable job, I am talking about the little squirts from the tabloid newspapers.  Let us have them in here to give them a piece of our minds.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PaddyBurke" hpid="Mr. Burke Mr. Burke">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Burke</NameTxt>
      <P>Meet them in the bar.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnDardis" hpid="Mr. Dardis Mr. Dardis">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dardis</NameTxt>
      <P>Stand them a drink.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SamMcAughtry" hpid="Mr. McAughtry Mr. McAughtry">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McAughtry</NameTxt>
      <P>When I was chairman of the Peace Train organisation and at other times I spent many hours trying to get into the minds of the people who run the IRA.  Senators might engage in this occupation also and they will come up with startling conclusions, the chief one being that the IRA is badly led both in PR terms and from a military point of view.  The whole thrust behind the so-called breaking of the ceasefire was <Col N="127" /> that the IRA would not kill civilians if it could help it but would kill policemen and soldiers. Believe it or not, this is offered as a &ldquo;half-ceasefire&rdquo;. I would give anything to be able to sit in on the musings of the IRA army council to hear these lame-brained propositions put forward by people who want and beg to be regarded as soldiers. I have tried to follow their soldierly thinking but in any other army they would not last a crack in open warfare against a proper army, because they are badly led.  They kill soldiers and policemen, the inference being, as they say to their people in south Armagh, that soldiers and policemen are <i>untermenschen</i>&mdash; they do not count, they are not people.  That is why those signs are in Armagh.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFallon" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator, please put a question to the Leader.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SamMcAughtry" hpid="Mr. McAughtry Mr. McAughtry">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McAughtry</NameTxt>
      <P>I hope the good people of south Armagh and Crossmaglen, who are noted for their hospitality and courtesy, will do as Senator Norris suggests &mdash; come out into the open and express their complete and utter horror at the IRA's policy of taking the lives of uniformed people which, because it is not taking the lives of people in mufti, it regards as a &ldquo;half-ceasefire&rdquo;. I ask the Leader to convey my personal regards to those responsible for the peace process here and to ask them not to cut off the signals to Sinn Féin.  It is essential to keep those lines open at whatever level.</P>
      <P>Some time ago I asked the Seanad for an assurance that any atrocity carried out in Northern Ireland would be treated as though it were carried out in this jurisdiction.  Senator Magner immediately replied it would be so regarded because it would be condmned just as strongly. However, I am not talking about condemnation but about public reaction to the killing of a human being on the island of Ireland.  I want this jurisdiction and the people in it to react in the same way it would if this man was killed in Meath or Thurles.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelMulcahyFF" hpid="Mr. Mulcahy Mr. Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Mulcahy</NameTxt>
      <P>I join those condemning that terrible murder.  The last speaker is incorrect if he suggests that anyone in this country is not as appalled as people in Northern Ireland.  I condemn that murder all the more because I am a member of a republican party which does not accept that the British have any right in Northern Ireland but makes that protest by constitutional and peaceful means.  Senator Ross' conclusion is based on the old military and security analysis which has failed.  Sinn Féin has a considerable degree of support in Northern Ireland and that cannot be swept under the carpet.  If there are to be statements today on this murder, there must also be statements on the peace process.  We must also consider the question, if the peace process is over, why?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="128" />
    <Speaker pid="DanNeville" hpid="Mr. Neville Mr. Neville">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Neville</NameTxt>
      <P>I join in the condemnation of this terrible, cowardly, inhuman and brutal murder of a young man who was doing his duty.  Those of us who heard the other victim on radio this morning will know how courteously this young man had treated the people of the area in carrying out his duties over a number of months.  As someone who has travelled to Northern Ireland over many years, I have always been impressed by how courteous the British Army is when stopping people and doing its duty.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PaddyMcGowan" hpid="Mr. McGowan Mr. McGowan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGowan</NameTxt>
      <P>I support those condemning the killing of the 23 year old British soldier in Bessbrook.  Those who believe Sinn Féin or the IRA have much support have misread the position; if a poll was taken this morning of people North and South, that party would have little support.  It is recognised that Sinn Féin, the IRA and all the paramilitaries have inflicted enough on the people of the north of Ireland, meaning the Six Counties and the six southern Border counties. That young man came from the British working class and he should still be attending an education establishment.  Most reasonable people know the IRA has turned back the clock.</P>
      <P>Our Taoiseach was speaking on the phone to Mr. John Major last week and the Tánaiste left the Seanad last Thursday to have dinner with Sir Patrick Mayhew but that is not enough.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFallon" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>A question for the Leader.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PaddyMcGowan" hpid="Mr. McGowan Mr. McGowan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGowan</NameTxt>
      <P>I hope this House will unanimously condemn the killing yesterday of that 23 year old soldier.  However, I ask the Leader to go to the Taoiseach and the Tánaiste this morning. It is important now not to let the paramilitaries take the centre ground.  There was a glimmer of hope in the negotiations with Gerry Adams and John Hume.  I am on the same wavelength as Senator McAughtry &mdash; let us hold on, we cannot throw in the towel.  The Taoiseach has failed because he stepped back and gave John Major space until after the election.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFallon" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Does the Senator have a question for the Leader?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MauriceManning" hpid="Mr. Manning Mr. Manning">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Manning</NameTxt>
      <P>More nonsense.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PaddyMcGowan" hpid="Mr. McGowan Mr. McGowan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGowan</NameTxt>
      <P>My question is very simple. While we totally condemn the killing, I also condemn the lack of progress being made by this Government in the negotiations to further the peace process.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JarlathMcDonagh" hpid="Mr. McDonagh Mr. McDonagh">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McDonagh</NameTxt>
      <P>Will the Leader ascertain from the Minister for Education why there is no section in the Education Bill dealing with adult education?  Adult education is the fastest growing sector in education and a great deal of concern has been expressed by bodies such as AEO and the SES on the failure to mention it in the Bill. Perhaps the Minister has another agenda for <Col N="129" /> adult education.  If that is the case, the providers would like to know about it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelFinneranFF" hpid="Mr. Finneran Mr. Finneran">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Finneran</NameTxt>
      <P>I join with Senator Lanigan in expressing my horror at the report in today's newspaper on the intentions of the prison authorities in regard to Roisín McAliskey.  Every right minded person would be appalled at somebody who has not been convicted having to give birth while handcuffed.  I join in the call on the Leader to make a protest to the British Government on this matter.  Right thinking people around the world would look very poorly on such a practice.</P>
      <P>I am getting tired asking when we will have amending legislation on the treatment of the mentally ill.  The legislation under which the mentally ill are cared for is over 50 years old and is in conflict with European legislation.  I understand that the contents of a White Paper on this matter have been with the Minister for Health for over 12 months.  Surely the Oireachtas is entitled to debate proposed legislation.  Will the Leader ask the Minister for Health to bring forward amending legislation which will deal with people who are mentally ill after the year 2000?  The current legislation is unfair to those who are being cared for and those who care for them.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PaschalMooney" hpid="Mr. Mooney Mr. Mooney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Mooney</NameTxt>
      <P>Yesterday's debate on the financing of local government ended at 6 p.m. by agreement. However, a significant number of Members on both sides of the House are still anxious to contribute to that debate.  Will the Leader initiate a discussion with his colleagues on all sides of the House to reintroduce this debate as there are a number of very important issues which affect the future of local government?</P>
      <P>It would be irresponsible of me not to join with my colleagues on all sides of the House in condemning the murder in Bessbrook of a young man from Peterborough.  I am grateful to you, a Chathaoirligh, for allowing a great deal of latitude on this important issue.  It is important that this House reflects the anger which is widespread throughout the island of Ireland, not just Northern Ireland.</P>
      <P>As Senator Neville said, anyone who heard the eyewitness report this morning could not help being moved by the overall attitude of that person who comes, I remind Senator Norris, from the town of which the Senator has been heavily critical.  It is unfair on the people of Crossmaglen and south Armagh to tar them with that brush and for there to be a perception that they are all active supporters of militarism.</P>
      <P>The message which is coming across to the Leader in the requests to convey the sense of outrage to the relevant Ministers and the Taoiseach, is that it is vital we continue with the peace process. Despite what Senator Ross says, the peace process is still up and running, otherwise there would be no point in us being here.  We must continue to believe there is a certain goodness in people and a willingness on all sides to enter into negotiations.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="130" /> It is impossible to have any solution, as Senator Mulcahy pointed out, if one ignores or excludes a party which has 15 per cent of the vote in a democratic election in Northern Ireland.  No matter if one likes, hates or loves that, it is a political reality and one which both Governments acknowledge.  They are attempting to bring in Sinn Féin, which is where the process lies.  We must not let what happened yesterday obscure many of the underlying problems in Northern Ireland.  I had intended&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFallon" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I ask the Senator to put a question to the Leader.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PaschalMooney" hpid="Mr. Mooney Mr. Mooney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Mooney</NameTxt>
      <P>&mdash;&mdash;this week to ask the Leader for a statement from the Tánaiste and Minister for Foreign Affairs on the outrageous sectarian bigotry we are witnessing every week in Harryville. This is the society out of which that man was killed.  There are no monopolies on either side of the sectarian divide.  I have not heard of any Unionist politician, with the exception of one or two gestures in the last few weeks by the Leader of the Orange Order, standing outside that church criticising&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFallon" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I ask the Senator to put a question to the Leader; I have allowed him a certain amount of latitude.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PaschalMooney" hpid="Mr. Mooney Mr. Mooney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Mooney</NameTxt>
      <P>&mdash;&mdash;these thugs and bigots who are allegedly led by a man who was convicted of the murder of a chemist, the father of seven children. He shot him dead in cold blood and has now been released on licence.  Will the Leader convey to the Tánaiste and Minister for Foreign Affairs the sense of outrage&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFallon" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I ask the Senator to conclude.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PaschalMooney" hpid="Mr. Mooney Mr. Mooney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Mooney</NameTxt>
      <P>&mdash;&mdash;that many of us feel about that situation?  The Secretary of State for Northern Ireland should withdraw the licence of that man, who is allegedly leading this sectarian attack on people going about their normal business.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaloney" hpid="Mr. Maloney Mr. Maloney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Maloney</NameTxt>
      <P>I condemn the findings of the review group on Oireachtas Members' pay.  An offer was recently made to the nurses.  Senator Finneran and I were nurses in the psychiatric service and if we were still working there we would be earning in the region of £26,000.  As Senators we earn in the region of £20,000 for working 80 to 90 hours a week.  If we were back working in our profession we would earn another £6,000 for working a 39 hour week.  It is time we took a good look at the service we deliver in the interests of the people of this country.  We should raise a hell of a stink about the findings of that review group.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Like everybody else, I feel that I must condemn the killing of the young soldier in Northern Ireland.  However, one must look at the situation in Northern Ireland since the ceasefire.  There is no point blaming just the IRA.  The British <Col N="131" /> Government and the Unionist politicians must be severely blamed and brought to book for doing absolutely nothing during the ceasefire.  At that stage, at least Sinn Féin-IRA came on board. They were prepared to stick with the ceasefire and to enter talks.  Mr. Trimble and company made damn sure they never got into those talks. All those people stand condemned this morning for the death of that young lad, not just one group.  I condemn the killing unreservedly but we should blame all sides who are responsible for this situation.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MauriceManning" hpid="Mr. Manning Mr. Manning">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Manning</NameTxt>
      <P>On behalf of the House I condemn the brutal murder of a young man doing his duty.  All in this House unreservedly condemn the taking away of his life.  We send our sympathy to his family and to the authorities in Northern Ireland.  On that, there is no ambiguity.</P>
      <P>Unlike Senator Ross, I believe that our condemnations are much more than ritual.  There is a deep sense of anger among all of us at what has happened.  We greatly resent the cowardice of the provisional IRA, who have no mandate, commit the most heinous crimes and who do so allegedly in our name.  We disparage the ambiguity, at best, of Sinn Féin, which refuses to give straight answers to straight questions and which is ambivalent in its approach to the peace process.</P>
      <P>I regret that Senator McGowan chose, in a mean spirited way, to turn a tragedy into a party political issue and to attempt to get cheap capital out of that.  It did him no good and it does the House no good.  He is the only Senator of any party who has chosen to take this line and I regret it.</P>
      <P>I agree with the suggestion by Senator O'Toole that we should make formal statements today. With the permission of the House I propose that the Order of Business be amended to include statements from 1 p.m. to 1.15 p.m. and that the sos now be from 1.15 p.m. to 2 p.m.</P>
      <P>Like Senator Lanigan, I would prefer to wait until the Buckley report is published, rather than depend on a partial report in <i>The Irish Times</i> today.  As soon as the report is published I will make available one of the new Wednesday morning slots to have the issue debated.</P>
      <P>I assure Senator Fitzgerald that the question of fisheries will be high on the agenda for the new Wednesday morning debates.  If possible, I will have it as the first debate.  I hope the reform of the House providing for topical debates of one to two hours on Wednesdays will commence within the next two weeks.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Senator Finneran raised a question on mental health.  I understand that the drafting of the relevant Bill is at an advanced stage in the Department of Health.  It is major legislation, comprising of approximately 200 sections.  The Department has made it a priority and has so indicated to the parliamentary draftsman.  We hope to see the legislation reasonably soon.  I understand the Senator's frustration.  He has been raising this <Col N="132" /> matter for some time and I will keep him informed.</P>
    <P>The treatment of Roisín McAliskey gives great cause for concern.  The matter has been raised here on a number of occasions over the past number of weeks.  I have conveyed to the Department of Foreign Affairs the concern of the House at the inhuman condition in which, in her state, she is being held.  Regardless of the rights and wrongs of the issue upon which she is being held, there is no excuse for her not being treated in the most humane way possible.  A pregnant young person in her state is not a threat to anybody.</P>
    <P>With regard to the point raised by Senator Mooney, the debate on local government financing is not concluded.  It will continue and I suspect that there will be a number of other sessions on it.  I will convey the concerns of Senator McDonagh to the Minister for Education.</P>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFallon" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Is the Order of Business, as amended, agreed to?  Agreed.</P>
      <P>Order of Business, as amended, agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Criminal Justice (Miscellaneous Provisions)" RHead="Bill, 1996: Committee and Final Stages">
    <Title>Criminal Justice (Miscellaneous Provisions) Bill, 1996: Committee and Final Stages.</Title>
    <P>SECTION 1.</P>
    <Speaker pid="TomFitzgerald" hpid="Acting Chairman (Mr. Fitzgerald) Acting Chairman (Mr. Fitzgerald)">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman (Mr. Fitzgerald)</NameTxt>
      <P>Amendments Nos. 1 and 2 are consequential on amendment No. 3 and all may be taken together.  Is that agreed?  Agreed.</P>
      <P>Government amendment No. 1:</P>
      <P>In page 3, between lines 27 and 28, to insert the following:</P>
      <P>&ldquo;&lsquo;Act of 1994&rsquo; means the Criminal Justice Act, 1994;&rdquo;.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="AustinCurrie" hpid="Minister of State at the Department of Justice (Mr. Currie) Austin Currie">
      <NameTxt>Minister of State at the Department of Justice (Mr. Currie)</NameTxt>
      <P>The purposes of amendment No. 1 is to define the Criminal Justice Act, 1994, as the Act of 1994 so as to avoid needless repetition of the full Title of that Act in this Bill in the light of the new section 15 which is being proposed. Amendment No. 2 is consequential on the amendment to section 1 and substitutes the new shorter reference to the Criminal Justice Act, 1994, for the full reference to the Act in section 14.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Amendment No. 3 proposes the insertion of a new section, section 15, in order to provide technical clarification of Part VII of the Criminal Justice Act, 1994.  Part VII of the Act provides the statutory basis for Ireland's co-operation with other countries in giving and receiving mutual legal assistance.  It enables Ireland to respond to requests from other countries for the obtaining of evidence for use in investigations into offences in these countries.  Specifically, it has made possible a significant advance in Ireland's participation in international conventions on criminal law, resulting in the ratification last year of no fewer <Col N="133" /> than three important conventions: the UN Convention against Illicit Traffic in Narcotic Drugs and Psychotropic Substances, the Council of Europe Convention on Laundering, Search, Seizure and Confiscation of the Proceeds from Crime and the Council of Europe Convention on Mutual Assistance in Criminal Matters, as well as the Protocol to that last convention.</P>
    <P>The changes proposed to Part VII are not ones of substance but are simply intended to remove possible uncertainties over its operation.  The first change brought about by this amendment is the rewording of section 55(4) of the Criminal Justice Act, 1994.  The changes from the existing wording are relatively slight and clarify two aspects of the subsection.  First, the rewording clarifies who may make a request to the Minister under section 55. Section 55 provides for the issue in the District Court of search warrants on the application of the DPP for material relevant to criminal investigations in designated countries.  This is an important element in Ireland's capacity to engage in international co-operation in criminal matters.</P>
    <P>Subsection (4) makes clear that an application to the District Court may only be made at the direction of the Minister where she has received a request from, to quote from the existing wording: &ldquo;...the Government of a country in relation to which this section applies&rdquo;.  The potential difficulty with this, which has been identified in operating Part VII of the Act, which is in effect since 15 November 1996, is that a strict interpretation could require every request to come from a Government as a whole, rather than, for example, from an individual Minister.  I do not believe this was the intention behind subsection (4) as it would severely restrict the scope of the section and correspondingly limit Ireland's capacity to co-operate with other countries in the investigation of offences.</P>
    <P>The amendment, in its rewording of subsection (4), seeks to avoid the possibility of such a restriction by permitting the request not only from a Government but also from a person acting on the authority of a Government.  In this context a person would include a body so the additional wording will cover a Government central authority for mutual assistance in criminal matters as well as a Minister of a Government.</P>
    <P>The other clarification provided in the rewording of subsection (4) relates to the operation of section 55 as it applies to section 63 of the 1994 Act.  I will first explain why there is a link between sections 55 and 63.  Section 63 provides for the making by the District Court on the application of a garda of an order requiring a person to produce material to the garda to take away or to give him or her access to it.  The section provides a useful alternative to search warrants in obtaining material relevant to criminal investigations. Section 55(2) makes use of section 63 by adapting it so that it can be used to satisfy requests received from designated countries under section 55.  However, it is not expressly stated in section 55 that the procedures outlined <Col N="134" /> in subsection (4), for example, regarding directions by the Minister, apply also to the use of section 63 as adapted by section 55.  The reworded subsection (4) makes clear, therefore, that the procedure it contains applies not only to search warrants under section 55 but also to orders for the production of material under section 3 as adapted by section 55.</P>
    <P>The second change being made to the Criminal Justice Act, 1994, is a technical amendment to remove any small doubt which may exist about the applicability of Part VII of the Act to foreign revenue offences.  One of the obligations of the Protocol to the Council of Europe Convention on Mutual Assistance on Criminal Matters is that mutual legal assistance should not be refused on the grounds that an offence is a revenue offence. A question which has arisen in the context of the practical operation of Part VII of the 1994 Act is whether the use of the word &ldquo;offence&rdquo; in Part VII in relation to the laws of other countries would be taken to include all offences, including revenue offences.</P>
    <P>This was always the objective of Part VII but there is a possibility that the word &ldquo;offence&rdquo; might be interpreted more strictly so as to exclude revenue offences on the grounds that, in international law, countries have traditionally not enforced each other's revenue law.  My advice is that, while the existing wording almost certainly achieves its objective, it would be safer to remove any small residual doubt by means of the amendment. It is a technical amendment which puts the intention of Part VII of the Act beyond doubt and copperfastens Ireland's capacity to discharge its obligations under international law.</P>
    <Speaker pid="DanNeville" hpid="Mr. Neville Mr. Neville">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Neville</NameTxt>
      <P>I welcome this vital amendment. This aspect was discussed on numerous occasions in the last 12 months in terms of ensuring Ireland fully co-operates in the control of crime internationally. Crime is not confined to the shores of any state, particularly regarding drug abuse and money laundering.  I welcome the amendment which facilitates the full implementation of the views of the Houses of the Oireachtas and the spirit of the legislation.</P>
      <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
      <P>Section 1, as amended, agreed to.</P>
      <P>Sections 2 to 5, inclusive, agreed to.</P>
      <P Just="Center">SECTION 6.</P>
      <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That section 6 stand part of the Bill.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelMulcahyFF" hpid="Mr. Mulcahy Mr. Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Mulcahy</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister may recall that I raised a general query on Second Stage about the advisability of having proof of arrest obtainable by certificate in the District Court.  I said it is only in a few instances in current practice that various forms of proof are allowed to be given by certificate &mdash; for example, road traffic offences such as <Col N="135" /> drunk driving where a certificate of blood or urine analysis is taken as evidence in court.  I also indicated that one of the most important parts of a criminal trial is the arrest.  Article 40 of the Constitution makes it clear that people have a right to their freedom until it is negatised by lawful arrest.</P>
      <P>It is dangerous to enable a certificate of arrest to be given instead of formal proof of arrest.  The Minister is aware many trials fail because the defence shows that a person was not properly arrested.  I fear that people who have not been properly arrested will be unable to test the lawfulness of their arrest if it is given by certificate. I am disappointed that the concerns I raised on Second Stage about this section do not appear to have been addressed by a Government amendment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="AustinCurrie" hpid="Mr. Currie Mr. Currie">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Currie</NameTxt>
      <P>I recall the Senator raising this matter on Second Stage when he said the process of arrest is at the heart of each criminal case.  The issue has been given due consideration, but the fears expressed by the Senator are unwarranted. I assume, because he is a member of the legal profession, that there is sufficient in this to enable him to make contributions in the courts. However, the matter has been considered and his fears are exaggerated.</P>
      <P>Question put and declared carried.</P>
      <P>Sections 7 to 13, inclusive, agreed to.</P>
      <P Just="Center">SECTION 14.</P>
      <P>Government amendment No. 2:</P>
      <P>In page 12, between line 23, to delete &ldquo;Criminal Justice Act, 1994,&rdquo; and insert &ldquo;Act of 1994&rdquo;.</P>
      <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
      <P>Section 14, as amended, agreed to.</P>
      <P Just="Center">NEW SECTION.</P>
      <P>Government amendment No. 3:</P>
      <P>In page 13, between lines 4 and 5, to insert the following new section:</P>
      <P>&ldquo;15.&mdash;The Act of 1994 is hereby amended by&mdash;</P>
      <P>(a)  the substitution of the following subsection for subsection (4) of section 55:</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>&lsquo;(4) No application for a warrant under this section, or for an order under section 63 of this Act as adapted by subsection (2) of this section, shall be made except in pursuance of a direction given by the Minister in response to a request received by him from the government of a country in relation to which this section applies, or a person acting on the <Col N="136" /> authority of such government, and made on behalf of&mdash;</P>
    <P>(a)  a court or tribunal exercising criminal jurisdiction in the country in question or a prosecuting authority in that country, or</P>
    <P>(b)  any other authority in that country which appears to the Minister to be an appropriate authority for the purposes of this section,</P>
    <P>and any evidence seized or obtained by a member of the Garda Síochána by virtue of this section shall be furnished by him to the Minister for transmission to the government or person concerned or, if that government or person so requests, to the court, tribunal or authority for which it has been seized or obtained&rsquo;., and</P>
    <P>(b) the addition in Part VII of the following new section:</P>
    <P>56A. (1) For the avoidance of doubt it is hereby declared that, in relation to an offence under the law of a country or territory other than the State, references in Part VII to an offence shall be construed as including references to a revenue offence.</P>
    <P>(2) In this section &ldquo;revenue offence&rdquo; means an offence in connection with taxes, duties or exchange control.&rsquo;.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
    <P>Sections 15 to 17, inclusive, agreed to.</P>
    <P Just="Center">SECTION 18.</P>
    <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That section 18 stand part of the Bill.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelMulcahyFF" hpid="Mr. Mulcahy Mr. Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Mulcahy</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister of State should think twice about inserting in the Bill the power to make prison rules given that the Taoiseach has said that responsibility for the Prison Service will be transferred from the Department of Justice to another executive body, and the Minister for Justice as good as said that herself last night.  It is a mockery to seek to introduce the power to make prison rules in this Bill when it is the new executive who will make the rules.  If it is intended that there will be a separate executive for the administration of prisons yet the rules are to be made by the Department of Justice, that will negate the logic of having an independent prison authority or executive.  It is crazy to insert the power to make prison rules when the Taoiseach and the Minister for Justice have publicly stated that the administration of prisons will be a matter for a new authority.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="AustinCurrie" hpid="Mr. Currie Mr. Currie">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Currie</NameTxt>
      <P>I remember the discussion on this matter on the last occasion and the Senator made <Col N="137" /> rather a meal of it.  I am glad he has not done so again.  The report of the expert group is expected by the end of this month.  This House will have every opportunity to examine legislation arising from the work of the expert group.  The provisions of section 18 do no more than update the statutory basis for the making of prison rules by the Minister and sets out the matters which these rules may address.  We need new rules to address practical administrative issues that arise now in the prison system.  Prison rules are currently being prepared and will be made subsequent to the enactment of these measures.  It is a straightforward matter.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>Sections 19 to 23, inclusive, agreed to.</P>
      <P>First Schedule agreed to.</P>
      <P>Second Schedule agreed to.</P>
      <P>Title agreed to.</P>
      <P>Bill reported with amendments and received for final consideration.</P>
      <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That the Bill do now pass.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelMulcahyFF" hpid="Mr. Mulcahy Mr. Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Mulcahy</NameTxt>
      <P>We disapproved of this matter from the outset.  If this was a local authority it is likely that a surcharge would be levied on the Government for duplication and time wasting on the prison aspects of the Bill.  In the Official Report of the Dáil of 25 July 1996, at column 928, Deputy O'Donoghue, referring to the Minister for Justice, stated:</P>
      <P>... on 11 May 1995 she announced ... &ldquo;Preparation of a Criminal Justice (Miscellaneous Provisions) Bill ... is at an advanced stage.&rdquo;</P>
      <P>The Bill was finally passed in the Dáil on 30 October 1996 and it is now being completed in this House in February 1997.  It is clear that the Government is moving at a very slow speed in the criminal justice field.</P>
      <P>The Government's criminal justice and penal policy&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I cannot allow the Senator to make a Second Stage speech at this point.  A brief comment is allowed.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelMulcahyFF" hpid="Mr. Mulcahy Mr. Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Mulcahy</NameTxt>
      <P>I am speaking on the Bill.  This Bill should have been rejected by this House because it will be made redundant by future legislation.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DanNeville" hpid="Mr. Neville Mr. Neville">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Neville</NameTxt>
      <P>I welcome the passing of this Bill. It will part of the Government's armour to ensure that crime, which has gone out of control over the past 15 years, will be tackled.  We should recognise that there was a decrease last year in the level of crime outside Dublin and this Bill will <Col N="138" /> play a part in ensuring there is a further reduction.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="AnnGallagher" hpid="Ms Gallagher Ms Gallagher">
      <NameTxt>Ms Gallagher</NameTxt>
      <P>I welcome the passage of this legislation because it is important that practical measures are taken to facilitate the detection and investigation of crime and, thus, facilitate the Garda in bringing criminals before the courts. This legislation is effective and practical.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="AustinCurrie" hpid="Minister of State at the Department of Justice (Mr. Currie) Austin Currie">
      <NameTxt>Minister of State at the Department of Justice (Mr. Currie)</NameTxt>
      <P>I thank Senators for their co-operation with one exception.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>
        <i>Sitting suspended at 11.40 a.m. and resumed at 1 p.m.</i>
      </P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Death of British Soldier:" RHead="Statements">
    <Title>Death of British Soldier: Statements.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="MauriceManning" hpid="Mr. Manning Mr. Manning">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Manning</NameTxt>
      <P>By agreement, statements will last 15 minutes and there will be not more than two minutes per speaker.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BrianHayes" hpid="Mr. Hayes Mr. Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>Last evening, a 23 year old British soldier from Peterborough was shot dead as he manned a checkpoint at Bessbrook, County Armagh. Stephen Restorick was murdered by republicans. He was systematically gunned down by the same group of people who were responsible for the death of Detective Garda Jerry McCabe. Stephen Restorick's death was an attack on the democratic process and it was the work of a fascist organisation which has consistently opposed the views of the overwhelming majority of people on this island.  In every sense, his death was an attack on the people.</P>
      <P>Those who represent the people in this jurisdiction must respond to such an attack upon them.  As a democratically elected body, the Seanad condemns this murder.  Our condemnation does not represent, as someone stated, hollow words.  Those who attack the people by eliminating members of the security forces in the Republic or Northern Ireland must be brought to justice and must be shunned by the tiny proportion of Irish people who continue to support them.</P>
      <P>It is important that loyalists do not respond to this latest provocation.  Let us be in no doubt that the intention of the IRA campaign is to provoke loyalists into re-entering its sectarian game.  The appeal of every elected Member of the Oireachtas to loyalists is to hold their nerve against such provocation.  They must have the total confidence to continue to secure their objectives, solely and exclusively, through peaceful politics.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>There is now a greater responsibility on the middle ground of Northern Irish political opinion to reach a compromise.  I appeal to the SDLP, the Alliance Party and the Ulster Unionist Party to lead the majority moderate community in Northern Ireland.  By making political compromises <Col N="139" /> they will provide the best possible example to the hardliners in both communities in Northern Ireland.  The death of Stephen Restorick must spur politicians in Britain and Ireland to solve our problems exclusively through politics.  We have the support of the people and we will not fail.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelMulcahyFF" hpid="Mr. Mulcahy Mr. Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Mulcahy</NameTxt>
      <P>I am delighted and privileged to have the honour to represent my party.  On behalf of my colleagues I must state that we utterly condemn this terrible act of brutality, not against a member of the British Army but against a fellow human being.  That is the most important point because every human being has an equal right to life.  I condemn the cold, brutal murder of Stephen Restorick.  The language of condemnation is never empty or redundant if it is spoken by those with genuine and sincere feelings.</P>
      <P>A clear message should be sent to those on both sides of the divide in Northern Ireland who engage in violence that they cannot bomb or shoot their way to a place at the negotiating table. It will not happen that way.  On the other hand, I firmly believe that the way the peace process has slipped is, in no small measure, due to the British Government's attitude since the outset.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidNorris" hpid="Mr. Norris Mr. Norris">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norris</NameTxt>
      <P>Rubbish.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelMulcahyFF" hpid="Mr. Mulcahy Mr. Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Mulcahy</NameTxt>
      <P>The insistence of the British Prime Minister and his Government on a permanent ceasefire and decommissioning has raised serious questions about the genuineness of their desire for a real, meaningful peace process and a long-term constitutional settlement.  Having said that, I condemn out of hand the terrible murder of Lance Bombardier Stephen Restorick.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaloney" hpid="Mr. Maloney Mr. Maloney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Maloney</NameTxt>
      <P>On behalf of the Labour Party, I unreservedly condemn the murder of a young soldier last night.  This callous act was carried out by an illegal organisation which does not have the right to take anyone's life, service person or civilian, in the name of the Irish people.  However, condemnation will not change the situation in Northern Ireland if the Framework Document is not put in place as the basis for talks.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Sinn Féin is not included in negotiations, and does not seem to want to be, but it represents 14 per cent of the people in Northern Ireland.  It was prepared to compromise in the interests of peace and left the attainment of a united Ireland on the back burner during the ceasefire.  The Framework Document was a joint response from the British and Irish Governments to the situation in Northern Ireland and a basis for negotiations.  The Unionist parties rejected such negotiations and do not want them to take place.  However, substantial numbers of Protestants and Catholics in Northern Ireland want discussions to take place to establish an even-handed, constitutional settlement. Sinn Féin was willing to consider arrangements under which Northern Ireland would remain part of the United Kingdom for the time <Col N="140" /> being but it has not had much help along the way. Many of the Unionist parties in Northern Ireland do not want to negotiate.  The politics of &ldquo;No surrender&rdquo; continue to obtain.</P>
    <P>Following the establishment of the ceasefire, Great Britain did nothing to try to move the situation forward.  The British Government conceded the Framework Document under pressure from the former Taoiseach, Deputy Reynolds, and President Clinton, but it has no intention to follow through on it.  It is for this reason that we are faced with the current situation.  When the talks commenced, the British did everything possible to sabotage them.  Until the British Government obtains the courage to move the process forward and bring everyone on board, including the Irish and American Governments, acts such as that perpetrated last night will continue.  I send my party's condolences to the family of Stephen Restorick.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MaryHenry" hpid="Dr. Henry Dr. Henry">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Henry</NameTxt>
      <P>I echo the words of Lorraine Mcllroy, the other victim of last night's shooting, who humanised the situation by speaking about the smiling face of a young man she knew from passing through checkpoints in the past.  She referred to the simple domestic situation, going out to buy ice cream for her children, which brought her to the checkpoint at Bessbrook and indicated the total disregard of those who shot Stephen Restorick for her and anyone who might have been travelling with her.  Ms Mcllroy spoke about the baby chair in the back of her car where her child might have been had her husband not stated that it was too cold for that child to accompany her.</P>
      <P>Those who claim they are trying to bring about a united Ireland have an absolute disregard for the vast majority of people living on this island. We cannot but keep repeating that this is not our desire.  It is important to take on board Lorraine Mcllroy's statement that, as a Catholic, she feared a message would be sent out that this is what is sought by people of her religion in Northern Ireland and she wanted to assure the international community that this is not the case.</P>
      <P>Tonight I am to chair a meeting of the Irish Association at which Cardinal Daly will deliver an address entitled &ldquo;Is Peace Still Possible?&rdquo;.  Following the actions in Bessbrook last night, I wonder if there are not a substantial number of people within these islands who do not want to make peace possible?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SamMcAughtry" hpid="Mr. McAughtry Mr. McAughtry">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McAughtry</NameTxt>
      <P>It is my desire to hasten the process whereby the spokesmen for the IRA and other organisations face each other across the negotiating table and debate the only issue that separates them.  I have already condemned last night's murder, but condemnation is really a form of steering towards the last shell burst.  We should get to the heart of the matter.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>If the talks to which I referred took place, I would expect the representatives of this State, the British Government, the Protestant people and <Col N="141" /> those Catholics in Northern Ireland who wish to remain under the United Kingdom's system of Government to assert that only the greater majority in the North may decide when, and under which form of government, Northern Ireland may detach itself from the United Kingdom to form a unity with the Republic.  The sooner this meeting takes place the sooner those in Northern Ireland who pay lip service to nationalism, while secretly praying that unity might never come about during their lifetimes, will be forced to come clean.</P>
    <P>When this happens, the stark isolation of the IRA's position by the Irish people will be apparent to everyone.  From then on, fair and unbiased government of Northern Ireland in the interests of all people will replace unity on the agenda. That is why, through all the years of tragedy, I have urged Unionists to talk to Sinn Féin.  The sooner the central core of our problem is faced the better.  Too many on both sides have made reputations by choosing the outer circle of the talks process instead of going for the bullseye of direct talks with those who believe in Republican violence and who command less than 4 per cent support on this island.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JohnDardis" hpid="Mr. Dardis Mr. Dardis">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dardis</NameTxt>
      <P>Depressingly, we must again condemn violence on this island.  It has been argued that such condemnation is meaningless but nevertheless we must express our horror and dismay at the senseless shooting of young Lance-Bombardier Stephen Restorick in Bessbrook yesterday. We extend our sympathies to his family and friends.  His mother was on the radio this morning and displayed more humanity in her little finger than is evident in the whole IRA.  The IRA should know, even if they never listen, that this House utterly and completely rejects violence as a political weapon.</P>
      <P>This is a democratic institution; our political system is founded on democratic principles and we shall continue to say as often as is necessary in this House that violence and democratic politics do not mix.  We cannot take up arms to make our point of view and at every opportunity we must restate our commitment to the negotiated compromises at the heart of democratic politics. The hidden, malign hand of the IRA is obvious in the shooting of Stephen Restorick; but even by the standards of the IRA Army Council's perverted and warped collective mind, what point do they see in the coldblooded murder of a young man?  Can they not see that they achieved more in 20 months of peace than they did in over 20 years of war?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>They had access to Government Ministers, to the Forum for Peace and Reconciliation, to the airways, to the White House and fundraising in the United States when we had peace.  If nothing else, surely Sinn Féin have learned that violence achieves no discernible political end.  What do they expect to achieve?  That question demands a more coherent reply than that postulated by Mr. Adams this morning, when he said everyone must <Col N="142" /> redouble their efforts to rebuild the peace process. We in this House and other democratic politicians will redouble our efforts, but what are Mr. Adams and his friends prepared to do?  Will their redoubled effort be to sanction another killing or two?  If the only channel of communication for the IRA is down the barrel of a gun, more and more doors will be rightly closed to them, not just in Ireland but around the world, denying access to the people who pervert the course of peace. We hope for restraint from the loyalists in the face of this provocation.  The Governments must continue to talk, but the talking with Sinn Féin is over until they restore the ceasefire we so strongly desire.</P>
    <Speaker pid="DavidNorris" hpid="Mr. Norris Mr. Norris">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norris</NameTxt>
      <P>I dissociate myself from the tenor of the remarks of Senators Mulcahy and Maloney, which attempted to blame the British Government.  That is misguided and plays into the hands of the gunmen.  I received a telephone call at 1 a.m. this morning from a friend of mine who is a brilliant young academic from a Catholic Nationalist background in the North of Ireland. He said he was sick and cannot wait to get out of the North.  That is the effect of this activity.  The decent people are leaving and the North is being left to the brutes.</P>
      <P>A cold, cynical and calculated decision was made to attempt to catapult the loyalist paramilitaries back into violence.  I appeal to those Protestant paramilitaries not to fall into this trap. A young man's life was cynically regarded as expendable by the IRA in order to achieve this sinister purpose.  Sinn Féin gets about 2 per cent of the vote in the Republic and about 12 per cent in the North.  They got that vote on a promise of peace, which they have betrayed.  It must be made clear that they have forfeited the privileges that went with that promise.</P>
      <P>I wish to speak directly to the other young man involved in this, who sat safely concealed in a hedge three quarters of a mile away and pulled the trigger in such a cowardly way.  Senator Gordon Wilson said that dirty words do not help but these words are frank and honest.  I say to that young man that he is a brute, a coward and a disgrace to this island.  I hope in coming years that his conscience begins to work and that it tortures him as the bereaved family and girlfriend must be tortured at this moment.</P>
      <P>I believe there will be an end to this in the shape of an amnesty.  The two Governments should signal clearly that for any future amnesty the terminal date is today and any crimes of this nature committed from now on will be excluded from the operation of any such amnesty.</P>
      <P>I am glad Mr. Adams was interviewed and I look to members of the media to call the spokesmen and apologists for this kind of violence. Although he may not be directly involved, Mr. Adams profits politically from this.</P>
      <P>
        <i>Sitting suspended at 1.15 p.m. and resumed at 2 p.m.</i>
      </P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="European Parliament Elections Bill," RHead="1996: Second and Subsequent Stages">
    <Title>European Parliament Elections Bill, 1996: Second and Subsequent Stages.</Title>
    <P>
      <Col N="143" /> Question proposed: &ldquo;That the Bill be now read a Second Time.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="BernardAllen" hpid="Minister of State at the Department of the Environment (Mr. Allen) Minister of State at the Department of the Environment (Mr. Allen)">
      <NameTxt>Minister of State at the Department of the Environment (Mr. Allen)</NameTxt>
      <P>The Bill before the House will consolidate and amend the domestic law relating to European elections.  It is part of a programme to consolidate and update electoral law.  It follows the Electoral Act, 1992, the Presidential Elections Act, 1993, the Referendum Act, 1994, and the Local Government Acts, 1991 and 1994, relating to local elections.  When this Bill is enacted, two electoral codes will remain to be updated.  I am sure the House can identify these as the Seanad electoral codes contained in Acts of 1937, 1947 and 1954.</P>
      <P>Given the special importance of electoral law and its direct relevance to each citizen, making the various election law codes more accessible and comprehensible to all is a necessary and desirable objective.  Unlike most other electoral codes, there are no specific constitutional provisions relating to European elections.  However, a 1976 Community Act laid down principles relating to direct elections to the Parliament which have direct application in all member states.  It may be useful for the House if I detail the main principles still in force.</P>
      <P>Representatives to the Assembly, renamed the Parliament in 1987, are elected for a term of five years, each outgoing Parliament remaining in office until the first sitting of its successor.  It is incompatible with membership of the Parliament to be a member of, or employed by, certain EU institutions or to be a member of the Government of a member state.  Further incompatibilities may be laid down in national law.  Membership of the Parliament is not incompatible with membership of a national parliament.  No one may vote more than once in an election of representatives.  The poll must be taken throughout the Union in the same Thursday to Sunday period in June every five years.  Should it prove impossible to hold the election during this period, another period not more than one month before or after may be selected.  The counting of votes may not begin until after the close of poll in the member state whose electors are last to vote.  The Parliament verifies the credentials of representatives, taking note of the results declared officially by each member state.  It is empowered to rule on any disputes arising out of the provisions of the Community Act but not on disputes arising out of national provisions.  Each member state must lay down appropriate procedures for filling any seat which falls vacant during the five year term of office of the Parliament.  Pending the entry into force of a uniform electoral procedure to the Parliament, and subject to the other provisions of the Community Act, the electoral procedure is to be governed in each member state by its national provisions.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="144" /> Article 138(3) of the European Treaty, as amended by the Maastricht Treaty, provides for European elections to be conducted in accordance with a uniform procedure in all member states.  No such procedure has been introduced to date.  A uniform procedure is likely to involve some kind of proportional representation system, but the Treaty would not appear to rule out some discretion regarding the detail of the PR system to be adopted by individual member states.  The Bill, therefore, provides for our existing PR-STV electoral system.</P>
    <P>The Maastricht Treaty inserted a provision in the European Treaty that Union citizens have the right to vote at and contest European elections in their host member state.  The detailed arrangements for the exercise of these rights were set out in a 1993 directive which was transposed into Irish law in 1994.  The provisions of the relevant regulations are incorporated in the Bill.</P>
    <P>The major change arising from the directive was the extension to resident Union citizens of the right to stand for election in Ireland to the Parliament.  Resident Union citizens have had the right to vote at European elections in Ireland since the first direct elections in 1979.  In accordance with the 1993 directive, section 6 of the Bill provides that European electors included on the register for the 1994 elections are exempt from the directive.  Furthermore, in recognition of the fact that Ireland and the United Kingdom extend reciprocal voting rights to each other's citizens at national elections, there is a derogation in the directive for Irish citizens living in the UK and British citizens living in Ireland.</P>
    <P>The first domestic Act relating to elections to the European Assembly, as it was then known, was enacted in 1977.  In the 20 years since we have had four European elections and numerous amendments to the law.  At present, a person enquiring about European electoral law would need to consult six separate statutes, as well as regulations.  With the next elections due in 1999, the time is opportune to update the law, which will bring the entire code within the pages of a single document.</P>
    <P>While the Bill is essentially a consolidation measure, designed to restate existing law in a more convenient form and in a clearer idiom, it contains a number of improvements.  I will now detail the principal changes.  The Bill omits the former provision for the office of chief returning officer and transfers the functions to the Clerk of the Dáil, who already has a substantive role in relation to the filling of casual vacancies, and to the Minister.  This will streamline administration relating to elections.</P>
    <P>Under existing law, a person who holds office as Attorney General cannot contest a European election without resigning from that office.  This is in contrast to Ministers of State who may stand for election while retaining their positions.  In view of the fact that the Attorney General is not a member of the Government, there is no justification for treating the two types of office holder differently.  Section 11 will permit the Attorney <Col N="145" /> General to stand for election while providing that, if elected to the Parliament, he or she will automatically cease to hold the office of Attorney General.  To avoid speculation, the present Attorney General has not indicated any intention of standing for election to the Parliament in the future.  The amendment is proposed solely to eliminate an existing legal anomaly.</P>
    <P>The law in relation to questioning an election by way of petition is being brought into line with petition procedures in other electoral codes. Section 21 provides that a petition may only be presented with the leave of the High Court which must be sought within seven days of the declaration of the result.  The petition itself must be presented within three days of the grant of leave by the court.</P>
    <P>The Bill also includes changes to bring the European code into line with the Dáil code. These changes include refunding the deposit to candidates whose votes exceed one quarter of the quota, rather than one third as at present.  The ballot paper is being brought more into line with the Dáil ballot paper.  The period for retaining election documents is being reduced from 12 to six months and monetary penalties are being increased in line with similar penalties in the Dáil code.</P>
    <P>During the passage of the Bill through the Dáil, amendments were agreed to include certain provisions in the Electoral (Amendment) Act, 1996, sponsored by Deputy Mary Wallace, relating to wheelchair access at elections and postal voting for electors with a physical illness or disability. This Bill goes further than the 1996 Act by making it mandatory for returning officers to conduct the count in the four European constituencies in buildings which are accessible to wheelchair users.</P>
    <P>Another important amendment agreed by the Dáil was provision for the inclusion of photographs on ballot papers.  Subject to ironing out the technical difficulties, this will be done at the 1999 European elections.  Consideration will be given to including photographs on ballot papers at other elections, including Seanad elections, if the experience at the 1999 elections is positive.</P>
    <P>The Dáil also agreed an amendment that a non-party MEP standing for election could include on the ballot paper the name of the political group in the Parliament of which he or she is a member.  This is intended to reflect the reality that the candidate would still be an MEP during the election.  Up to now the inclusion of the name of a political group in the Parliament on a ballot paper was confined to candidates belonging to registered political parties represented in the Parliament.</P>
    <P>Section 15 and the Third Schedule re-enact the existing European Parliament constituencies, each with the same number of seats recommended by an independent commission and used for the 1994 elections.  These constituencies are four seaters in Dublin city and county, in the rest of Leinster and in Munster, and a three seater in <Col N="146" /> Connacht/Ulster.  Under the terms of the Electoral Bill, 1994, an independent commission will be established on publication of the results of each census with the task of making a report within six months on the formation of Dáil and European constituencies.  The terms of reference for the commission set out in the 1994 Bill are essentially the same as those given to previous non-statutory commissions.  The present Bill provides that the Minister must submit proposals to the Oireachtas for a review of European constituencies by 1 December 2003 at the latest and at least once every ten years thereafter.</P>
    <P>There are 25 sections in the body of the Bill setting out its main provisions.  The detailed provisions are set in four Schedules.  The First Schedule lists the enactments repealed and the regulations revoked by the Bill.  The Second Schedule comprises 150 rules dealing with all aspects of an election.  The Third Schedule defines the four European constituencies and the Fourth Schedule specifies the format of the ballot paper.</P>
    <P>I will now outline the main provisions in the body of the Bill not previously referred to. Section 6 implements the 1993 directive in relation to registering Union citizens ordinarily resident in the State as European electors.  They must apply to be registered and furnish a statutory declaration in support of their application. The section also provides for information exchange between member states with a view to preventing double voting.</P>
    <P>Section 7 provides that European elections will be held according to the principle of proportional representation, each elector having a single transferable vote.  Voting will be by secret ballot.</P>
    <P>Section 9 specifies that electors may vote in person at a polling station, by post or by means of the special arrangement for voting in institutions. Under the terms of the Electoral (Amendment) Act, 1996, electors with a physical illness or disability living at home will now be able to vote by post if they are unable to go to their local polling station.  The special voting arrangement will in future be confined to electors with a physical illness or disability living in institutions.</P>
    <P>Section 11 restates the law in relation to eligibility for election to and membership of the Parliament. It also implements the 1993 directive in relation to Union citizens living and standing for election in the State.  Thus, it provides that a person who has reached 21 years of age and is either an Irish citizen or a national of another member state living in the State is eligible to stand for election to the Parliament in the State, to be nominated as a replacement candidate and to be a member of the Parliament.  However, a person is not eligible if subject to certain disqualifications applicable to Dáil membership.  It follows that a person is disqualified if a member of the Garda Síochána or a wholetime member of the Defence Forces or a civil servant whose terms of employment do not expressly permit membership of the Parliament.  As in other electoral codes, persons of unsound mind, undischarged bankrupts and persons undergoing prison sentences exceeding <Col N="147" /> six months are also disqualified.  Judges and the Comptroller and Auditor General must resign their positions if they wish to contest an election. Other persons disqualified are Irish citizens standing for election in their host member state and Union citizens deprived of the right to contest the election in their home member state.</P>
    <P>Section 11 also provides that, if elected to the Parliament, the Attorney General, the Chairman and Deputy Chairman of the Dáil or Seanad and Ministers of State cease to hold those offices.  Furthermore, if a member of the Parliament becomes subject to any of the above disqualifications or becomes the holder of any of the above offices, he or she thereupon ceases to be a member of the Parliament.</P>
    <P>Under section 12 a person may nominate himself or herself as a candidate at a European election or may, with his or her consent, be nominated by a European elector for the constituency concerned.  The section also provides that each registered political party and each non-party candidate in a constituency may nominate one or more replacement candidates for the purpose of filling vacancies in the membership of the Parliament for that constituency.</P>
    <P>Section 13 stipulates that a deposit of £1,000 must be lodged by or on behalf of each candidate before the close of nominations.  This is the same as at present.</P>
    <P>Section 15 and the Third Schedule prescribe the constituencies for the European elections. The section also provides that the Minister must take account of the report of any statutory commission before submitting proposals to the Oireachtas for a review of European constituencies.</P>
    <P>Section 16 provides that the Minister must appoint a returning officer for each European constituency from among the local returning officers in each constituency.  The returning officer is responsible for functions which must be discharged centrally in each constituency, for example, the receipt of nominations, counting the votes and declaring the election result.</P>
    <P>Section 17 provides that there shall be a local returning officer for each county or county borough contained in a constituency.  The local returning officers are the city and county sheriffs in the case of Dublin and Cork and the county registrars in every other case.  The local returning officer is responsible for taking the poll and verifying the ballot paper accounts.</P>
    <P>Section 19 provides for the filling of casual vacancies in Ireland's representation in the Parliament in accordance with Part XIII of the Second Schedule.  A vacancy is filled by the replacement candidate whose name stands highest on the replacement candidate list concerned.  A replacement candidate will not be eligible to fill a casual vacancy if he or she is already a member of the Parliament, is not eligible to be elected, is not willing to serve as a member or, in the case of a party list, is no longer a member of the party concerned. If no replacement candidate list has been <Col N="148" /> presented or the relevant list is exhausted, the Dáil may select a replacement from another replacement candidates list presented for the constituency concerned.</P>
    <P>Section 21 and Part XV of the Second Schedule specify the petitions procedure.  The grounds of a petition are limited to specific factors likely to have affected the result of the election.  These are want of eligibility of candidates, electoral offences, obstruction of the election and irregularity or failure to conduct the election in accordance with law.  The court will, if possible, determine the correct election result and if it cannot do so will declare the whole or part of the election void, giving its reasons.  Where the court declares that the whole or part of an election is void, a fresh election must be held unless a general election of representatives to the Parliament is due within six months.  The decision of the High Court on a petition is final, subject only to appeal to the Supreme Court on a question of law.</P>
    <P>The Second Schedule contains 16 Parts each dealing with a specific aspect of the election procedures. Altogether, the Schedule contains 150 rules covering the election proper, casual vacancies and election petitions.  The rules are listed on pages 19 to 25 of the Bill.  I have already referred to the main changes in these rules.  Most rules are standard for Presidential, Dáil and local elections and in some cases referenda.</P>
    <P>To conclude, this Bill is a solid piece of consolidation law, incorporating a number of worthwhile reforms.  I commend the Bill to the House.</P>
    <Speaker pid="DonLydon" hpid="Mr. Lydon Mr. Lydon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lydon</NameTxt>
      <P>When I read this Bill I was amazed at the number of existing Acts which had to be amended and the regulations to which the Minister referred.  This is a necessary Bill to consolidate and amend existing legislation.  I welcome it. It appears to be good legislation, although I have one or two questions.  However, I see no reason to delay the passage of the Bill.  I understand the Minister accepted amendments in the Lower House which served to strengthen and clarify the Bill.</P>
      <P>This legislation will clarify the whole process and will serve to standardise the rules for different elections.  This is to be welcomed &mdash; the more standardised the rules the easier it is for people to understand them.  There are some countries where different bodies are elected by different forms of election which becomes very complicated. Any move away from that has to be welcomed.</P>
      <P>The return of the deposit of £1,000 where the candidate exceeds one quarter rather than one third of the quota is reasonable; one third of the quota in European elections is huge.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>There was a lot of talk in the Lower House about the chief returning officer.  This was discussed at length.  It appears to me that the chief returning officer would be the Clerk of the Dáil and I do not see why there would be any objection to that.  Some people have objected to it, but I do not think that they have too much work to be unable to deal with that or that they would be <Col N="149" /> in any way interfering with the process.  As the Minister said, the Clerk of the Dáil does have other statutory functions for Dáil elections.</P>
    <P>Reducing the time for the retention of documents from 12 to six months in line with the Dáil is a good idea.  The increase in penalties and the provision relating to election petitions which must be sought after seven days should also be welcomed.</P>
    <P>I understand that the European Parliament intends to draw up proposals for a uniform electoral procedure which will be applied in each of the member states.  This has not happened yet. We are, of necessity, obliged to have this piece of legislation before us and to enact it without delay. I am not quite sure what this Bill will mean to the man in the street.  I suppose the intention is that it will enable ordinary citizens to understand the process better and to enable better participation.</P>
    <P>I do not think that European Parliament Elections are very high on most people's agendas.  I suppose that is because once European parliamentarians have been elected, there is little contact with them thereafter.  That is not entirely the fault of those who have been elected.  It is to all intents and purposes impossible for any member of the European Parliament to maintain intimate contact with such a huge electorate.  Their constituencies are very large and there is no national forum on which they can perform.  I think it was suggested at one stage that members of the European Parliament should come to this House from time to time.  I have no objection to that but I do not think it is what is really required.</P>
    <P>Deputy Ferris, speaking in the other House, said there was a report of the European Affairs Committee which stated that European parliamentarians from the Republic and from the six counties were welcome to attend meetings of the committee.  That is a good recommendation and proposal.  I recommend that there would be a special committee of Deputies and Senators which could meet at times which would be convenient for members of the European Parliament to attend and where they could be provided with a forum that would deal exclusively with issues relating to European parliamentary deliberations. The parliamentarians could answer questions about the work of the Parliament.  If such a committee was to meet on a monthly basis, they would have a greater chance of media coverage between elections.  This is just a suggestion, something like the tentative suggestion that they would attend the European Affairs Committee, but I think a committee should be established primarily for the European parliamentarians themselves.</P>
    <P>Unlike the European Commission, the European Parliament is, in theory, accountable for its actions.  As far as this House and the Lower House are concerned, the reality is that we have no influence over the European Parliament.  It seems to me that major lobbying groups have influence; if you get enough people and take them to Brussels you have a better chance of getting something done than Members of the <Col N="150" /> Oireachtas would.  I do not think that the outcome of the deliberations of the European Parliament take any notice of what is good, bad or indifferent about the deliberations of the Dáil and Seanad.</P>
    <P>For example, with regard to European directives, these are landed here in front of us, usually without any debate, and we are left with the task of incorporating them into the <i>corpus</i> of Irish law. Sadly, the European Parliament is very far removed from the interests of ordinary citizens. However, the decisions that the Parliament makes have enormous consequences for this country.</P>
    <P>It has been said that all politics is local and if this is so, we must look at ways and means of making the European Parliament more meaningful for Irish citizens.  We should help our European parliamentarians and give them a forum at which they explain their role and their work.  We should support them and assist them in confronting adverse publicity.  MEPs are continually blamed for getting large salaries, which is ludicrous. I know most of our MEPs and I can tell the House that they work very hard indeed.  For example, Deputy Pat the Cope Gallagher covers from Donegal down to Connacht and the whole of Ulster.  He works every weekend and he is just one example.  This is an enormous burden and I do not think you can be overpaid for it.  I heard that the Deputies were refused a pay rise today. Well, eventually people are going to get what they pay for.</P>
    <P>I want to ask the Minister a question, I do not know if he is the right person to answer me.  The next European election will be held in 1999 and the local government elections are scheduled for 1998.  Would it be possible to harmonise all of these and have them all on the same day?  I would also like to see fixed terms of office for the Dáil. I do not think that if a Government loses a majority, it should have to go for another election. It would be wonderful if we could have all elections together and get on with the business of running the country.  A politician's job is insecure enough as it is.  I would like to see the local government and the European elections harmonised for this reason: local government elections achieve a good turn out and there is nobody better at eliciting votes than a local county councillor. While people are being canvassed for local government elections, they might also be persuaded to vote in the European elections as well. There was a big reduction in the number of votes cast in the European elections, it is decreasing between elections.</P>
    <P>I would hate to see a situation here like that in America where people do not bother voting anymore.  They have a ludicrous situation there where one side of the country knows the result of the election before the other side votes.  I suppose that must only add to the apathy.  I think fixed term Governments would be a good idea.  I do not know if it would be feasible to have local, national and European elections to run together. It would be feasible for local government and the <Col N="151" /> European Parliament elections to run simultaneously.</P>
    <P>In section 11 of an explanatory leaflet there is a description of people who are eligible for election. Am I correct in thinking that somebody who is in prison is ineligible?  I wonder if that applies to political prisoners.</P>
    <Speaker pid="BrianHayes" hpid="Mr. Hayes Mr. Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>They cannot vote and they cannot stand for election if their sentence is over six months.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DonLydon" hpid="Mr. Lydon Mr. Lydon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lydon</NameTxt>
      <P>I think people who are in prison for political offences should be able to vote and should be eligible for election.  I am reminded of the late Kieran Doherty, who was elected to this House, and of other men, not too long ago, who were elected to the Dáil and who were in prison at the time.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BrianHayes" hpid="Mr. Hayes Mr. Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>Were they members of your own party, Senator?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DonLydon" hpid="Mr. Lydon Mr. Lydon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lydon</NameTxt>
      <P>I cannot remember that far back.  I think that this is something that should be kept in mind because we all seek not to discriminate against people.  There are convicted felons whom I have no time for, but perhaps a case can be made where political prisoners could vote and could stand for election.</P>
      <P>In the Minister's speech, he states that it is recognised &ldquo;that Ireland and the United Kingdom extend reciprocal voting rights to each other's citizens at national elections&mdash;&rdquo;.  I voted in England myself when I was living there.  I voted for the Conservative Party by the way.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BrianHayes" hpid="Mr. Hayes Mr. Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>Some things never change.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DonLydon" hpid="Mr. Lydon Mr. Lydon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lydon</NameTxt>
      <P>You can always be sure of where you stand.</P>
      <P>I wonder whether we should abandon these reciprocal voting rights.  We are an autonomous nation and we do not need this kind of thing.</P>
      <P>I welcome the acceptance of Deputy Mary Wallace's amendment to make it mandatory for returning officers to conduct the count.  I am concerned about wheelchair access to our polling stations.  It is hard enough for an able bodied person to enter some of these and I would like to see the Minister doing something about this.  It is only a matter of passing a law and he will find that people will obey it.</P>
      <P>I am not sure about using photographs on ballot papers.  It is all right for young men like Senators Hayes and Naughten but voters are liable to miss someone like me.  However, it is a good idea to identify oneself to the electorate.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>As regards voting by special voters, the explanatory document states that a ballot paper will be delivered to each European elector at home by a special presiding officer accompanied by a member of the Garda Siochána.  The elector makes a declaration of identity in the presence of the special presiding officer and the garda.  What <Col N="152" /> defines a special voter and why is it necessary to have a garda present?  We post votes to the gardaí, the Army, fishermen and so on, so why can this not be done in the case of special voters?</P>
    <P>People are eligible to vote at 18 years of age yet they cannot stand for election until they are 21.  Why?</P>
    <Speaker pid="BrianHayes" hpid="Mr. Hayes Mr. Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>It is in the Constitution.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DonLydon" hpid="Mr. Lydon Mr. Lydon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lydon</NameTxt>
      <P>Is it?  Perhaps it should be removed from the Constitution.  Alexander the Great conquered most of the world and he died aged 29; at 21 he should have been able to stand for election.</P>
      <P>This is a good Bill.  My questions may appear small and trifling but they deserve an answer.  We should not delay this Bill any further and I compliment the Minister on it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BrianHayes" hpid="Mr. Hayes Mr. Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister has been with us on a number of occasions recently, in particular, concerning Deputy Wallace's initiative.  That measure was supported by all sides of the House and the Minister showed great skill in introducing important and reforming legislation which will enable those with disabilities to access the political system in a more user friendly way then heretofore.</P>
      <P>This is a technical Bill which includes much detail amending out of date laws and bringing Irish law closer to the European model.  It is important that we debate this in the House because we have attempted to debate European issues over the last few months.  For example, Commissioner Kinnock addressed this House recently and we were all inspired by his words. The former Cathaoirleach, Jim Dooge, also gave an interesting address on the future shape and role of Europe and I would welcome similar exercises in the future.  The Seanad has a role to play in trying to integrate some of the important European issues which are being debated in the European parliament and throughout the member states.</P>
      <P>The European elections are vitally important for our national and European interests.  It is demoralising that the turnout for these elections has consistently been poor and continues to decline.  The turnout in 1992 was 43 per cent and it is very depressing for national parties and the country as a whole that less than one in two people came out to vote.  As political representatives we must do everything in our power to ensure a high turnout of voters.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>There is a representative from the European Commission office in the House.  I welcome him because, collectively, we must ensure that more information is given to Irish citizens about Europe.  This is particularly important following the Maastricht Treaty which gives substantially increased powers to the European Parliament in comparison with five or more years ago.  We should not treat the European parliament glibly; we must send the best representatives to it to articulate the case for Ireland and the emerging European Union.  Part of this process involves the <Col N="153" /> Oireachtas and the various European statutory bodies operational in Ireland taking a more informative role, getting out and about between elections and selling the case for Europe.</P>
    <P>The quality of the people we send to the European Parliament has never been more important because of the new powers it has.  We do not need representatives with technical expertise in certain areas; we need those who have shown great political leadership and judgment.  For instance, there are several former Prime Ministers in the European Parliament.  It is not a retirement home for those who cannot get back into the Cabinet or who thought they were going to be leaders of their parties.  We need people who have shown great judgment and experience.  Our 15 MEPs are such people and they are making a valuable contribution.</P>
    <P>It has been said that the European elections are, primarily, national ballots.  This is utterly depressing because, at the last election, the manifesto for each of the parties made it seem more like a national contest.  Fine Gael attempted to include Christian democratic ideals in our manifesto because we are associated with the EPP group.  However, there was very little focus in the media on issues such as national defence, enlargement and the single currency.  The election was seen as a contest between the Government and the Opposition and that does no credit to the European Parliament or the political system.  We should not view the European elections as a precursor to the general election.</P>
    <P>If one looks at the present membership of the European Parliament, five of Ireland's 15 members &mdash; one the Labour Party and four Fine Gael Party representatives &mdash; are connected with the two biggest groups, the Socialist Party and the Christian Democrats.  It is recognised that the European People's Party and the Socialist Party control the European Parliament as they are by far the two biggest parties.  It is worrying that only one third of the Irish members are associated with those two big groups.  The largest Irish party, Fianna Fáil, is associated with the party which has virtually no influence on European policy, and I do not mean to be disrespectful.  My argument and that of my party has always been that if we are to make a significant impact on European issues, we must be at the heart of Europe in a party which has influence in the European Parliament, and the Christian Democrats and the Socialist Party have such influence.  It is worrying that only five of Ireland's 15 members are involved in those two great groupings and there is a message in that for other parties who send representatives to the European Parliament.</P>
    <P>There are benefits from the present structure of the European Parliament.  As Senator Lydon rightly said, the fixed term Parliament is an excellent idea because it ensures that members know they have five years to present their case, develop their policies and give of their best without worrying about local considerations or an election which might crop up as frequently as a general election.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="154" /> The dual mandate dates from the 1970s and we must get away from it.  I understand that parties must put the big names up for election in order to get the vote out, but the dual mandate takes away from the Oireachtas and the European Parliament. One must consider the time involved and the workload, not to mention the amount of local community activity in which a member must be involved.  One simply cannot be a member of both Parliaments and it is up to the parties to take a stand on this to ensure, come the next European election in 1999, that we select people in the four constituencies who are not serving Members of the Oireachtas.  That will prove very difficult for the parties; but if we could collectively agree a strategy on it, it would help the standing of Irish parliamentarians in the European Parliament and in the Houses of the Oireachtas.</P>
    <P>There was the ludicrous situation at the last European elections where the vote could not be counted because other countries had not yet gone to the polls.  It is only sensible that the count takes place on the same day throughout the member states when one is electing people to one Parliament; but if that is to be the case, let us pick one election day so that everybody goes to the polls together.  I am raising this matter on the Adjournment this evening so I do not want to raise it now, but in the context of the European Parliament each member state should vote on the same day because that would ensure that the ludicrous situation which occurred following the last European election will not occur again.</P>
    <P>Some of the proposals in the Bill tidy up pieces of legislation which are already in place.  I was amused, like other Senators, to find that the Attorney General could not become a member of the European Parliament and I am glad that anomaly is soon to be removed.  If former attorney generals became members of the European Parliament they would have most interesting stories to tell.</P>
    <P>I was quite amused by section 7, which stated blatantly that voting would be by secret ballot.  I had assumed that this was already part and parcel of the Irish electoral system but it had obviously to be restated.</P>
    <P>The whole concept of parachute candidates has become an intrinsic part of European elections as people who have made a contribution in aspects of life apart from politics now feel they can take their place in the European Parliament.  As a result of section 11 of this Bill, other EU nationals can come and live in Ireland and then stand in one of the four European Parliament constituencies, so at the next election there may be international rather than national parachute candidates.  Therefore, a high profile person in France, Germany or Britain could take his or her place representing the constituency of Leinster, for example, once he or she had lived there for a certain period of time.  That is to be welcomed because if parties are standing on the basis of their political affiliations&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    <Col N="155" />
    <Speaker pid="MickLanigan" hpid="Mr. Lanigan Mr. Lanigan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lanigan</NameTxt>
      <P>This comes from a party which has had parachutists in both Houses and in the European Parliament.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BrianHayes" hpid="Mr. Hayes Mr. Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>&mdash;&mdash;and they are trying to address European issues, it is sensible that a member of the EU should be able to stand in any constituency if the person feels he or she can make a contribution to national life.</P>
      <P>On the proposal in the Bill which will decide the European constituencies, as I understand it, the new Electoral Bill will make statutory provision for the first time for the independent commission which will determine constituency boundaries.  That legislation has not been published but I am led to believe that it will contain that provision because it was contained in a previous electoral reform Bill.  If that is the case and an independent statutory commission is established for the European Parliament and the Dáil in this future piece of legislation, that commission should apply to local elections also.  I made this point yesterday to the Minister for the Environment. If it is good enough for the European Parliament and the Oireachtas, it should be good enough for local authorities also and it should be stitched into future legislation.</P>
      <P>Section 8 talks about the entitlement to vote. At present one must vote in the constituency in which one is registered; so if I live in Kildare North, for instance, I must cast my vote there in European elections, general elections, referendums and every type of national ballot.  My argument is this: if I live in Kildare North and work the day of the election in County Wexford, I should be entitled to vote in County Wexford, which is in the same European constituency, Leinster, as Kildare North.  There is no reason we cannot devise a system where somebody who might be away from where they live on election day can vote in the constituency where they may be transacting their business.  I ask the Minister to address this in his reply.</P>
      <P>I was delighted that section 9 ensures that the special voters list will be changed as a result of Deputy Mary Wallace's important Bill, which was enacted just before Christmas.</P>
      <P>Can MEPs vote in Seanad elections?  If we did not afford them the right to vote in Seanad elections as we afford that right to Deputies and outgoing Senators, it would seem to me that we would be undermining their status as MEPs.  They should be allowed to vote in Seanad elections too.</P>
      <P>In response to Senator Lydon's remarks about votes for prisoners, I stated publicly on a previous occasion that it is wrong that a prisoner should be debarred from voting, not just in a European election but in any election.  I appreciate that a person's liberty is taken if he is in prison, but he is still a member of society and has rights under our Constitution.  To help prisoners integrate into society we should allow them take part in the democratic process.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Senator Lydon referred to the voting age.  Perhaps the Minister could indicate whether the age threshold of 21 for membership of the European <Col N="156" /> Parliament, the Dáil and the Seanad applies in other European countries, because we should try to harmonise the limits.  If one is entitled to vote at 18 one should be able to take a seat in those Houses.</P>
    <P>This is timely legislation which will bring us into line with other European countries until there is agreement on the totality of electoral law. I do not think there will be agreement because member states have tried and failed to achieve it over a number of years.  We should push ahead, try to achieve consensus with other EU electoral systems and ensure that everything we do between now and the next European election is directed at pushing up our national vote and putting the best people into the European Parliament.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MickLanigan" hpid="Mr. Lanigan Mr. Lanigan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lanigan</NameTxt>
      <P>This is necessary and sensible consolidating legislation.  The Minister said elections will occur every five years and I agree that they should take place at the weekend because it has been proven that more people will vote.  To look at this from a marketing point of view, shops would not stay open on Saturdays until 9 p.m. or all day on Sunday unless they received a response from the market place which suggested this was a good thing.  Whether we are talking about a product for sale in a supermarket or casting a vote, we have to consider how best to address the marketplace.  It is good marketing to hold elections at weekends, after the five year period is over.</P>
      <P>Speakers have mentioned the democratic deficit in Europe, specifically the operation of the European Parliament and the European electoral system.  Many feel the European Parliament does not have the teeth which it should.  From reading the newspapers, listening to the radio or watching television, one would imagine it did not exist as far as the democratic process was concerned.  The Commission has too much power and the less it has, the better.  There is no democracy in the Commission and it has dictated too much of what has happened in the European institutions. Although many people do not agree with giving more power to the Parliament, it should at least have more power than it does at present.</P>
      <P>There should be a better process for reporting what goes on in the European Parliament to the Houses of the Oireachtas and through the national media.  The media has a negative attitude to the Parliament.  The only time its workings are highlighted is when its Members go on trips to outposts of what we might call the &ldquo;European empire&rdquo; and are photographed in swimming trunks coming from various meetings of importance.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnDardis" hpid="Mr. Dardis Mr. Dardis">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dardis</NameTxt>
      <P>As long as they were not naked it is all right.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MickLanigan" hpid="Mr. Lanigan Mr. Lanigan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lanigan</NameTxt>
      <P>What is wrong with being naked? We were born naked.  The media's negative reaction to the work of MEPs is not good for democracy but it also reflects the public attitude.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="157" /> European institutions are becoming increasingly important to us through regulations, laws, etc.  National parliaments have been downgraded to some extent and Europe has more power, but there must be a balance between the two.  One would imagine from the newspapers that MEPs have no power and that the public's attitude does not have as much weight with an MEP as it does with a national politician.</P>
    <P>The Oireachtas Joint Committee on Foreign Affairs is occasionally visited by MEPs, who are entitled to attend our meetings.  Some MEPs have come but they have been selective in their attendance. That may be because committee meetings have taken place on the same day as meetings of the European Parliament in Luxembourg or Brussels but the committee has also met when the European Parliament was in recess or not sitting and MEPs have been more notable for their absence than their presence.  If they are to take a more active part in national as well as international politics they should look at their attendance record at the one forum at which they have the right to attend and speak, the Oireachtas Joint Committee on Foreign Affairs.  If they want to do something to redress the democratic deficit, they should attend and contribute to meetings of that committee as regularly as possible.  Members of the committee might be enlightened by what MEPs have to say and <i>vice versa</i>, not only on issues relevant to Ireland but international issues on which we lobby on behalf of a particular group.</P>
    <P>The proceedings of the Oireachtas Joint Committee on Foreign Affairs are not publicised and the Department of Finance has refused to publish the proceedings of joint committees &mdash; the only committees whose proceedings are being published are select committees.  This creates another democratic deficit because what occurs at the committee is not put into the public arena.</P>
    <P>Only 16 current Members of the Dáil were not among the top five on the first count in their constituency at the last general election. This proves that irrespective of the electoral process, whether it is PR by single transferable vote or some other method, if one is not among the top five on the first count one has little chance of getting into the European Parliament or the Dáil.  Only two current TDs were not among the top seven on the first count.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JohnDardis" hpid="Mr. Dardis Mr. Dardis">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dardis</NameTxt>
      <P>The Senator should tell us who they were.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MickLanigan" hpid="Mr. Lanigan Mr. Lanigan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lanigan</NameTxt>
      <P>I will not because I do not want to embarrass very senior Members of the Opposition &mdash; I mean the Government.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BernardAllen" hpid="Mr. Allen Mr. Allen">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Allen</NameTxt>
      <P>It is a pub quiz.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MickLanigan" hpid="Mr. Lanigan Mr. Lanigan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lanigan</NameTxt>
      <P>I keep thinking that we are in Government.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MauriceManning" hpid="Mr. Manning Mr. Manning">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Manning</NameTxt>
      <P>The Senator will be thinking it for a long time to come.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="158" />
    <Speaker pid="MickLanigan" hpid="Mr. Lanigan Mr. Lanigan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lanigan</NameTxt>
      <P>The Bill is necessary consolidating legislation.  The Minister of State stated:</P>
      <P>When this Bill is enacted, two electoral codes will remain to be updated.  I am sure the House can identify these as the Seanad electoral codes contained in Acts of 1937, 1947 and 1954.</P>
      <P>I am not too sure what relevance that has to the European Parliament Elections Bill.  However, if the Seanad electoral codes need to be updated that should be done.  Does the Minister of State feel that the electoral codes of the Seanad should be changed or is it just that these are the only ones which have not been changed?</P>
      <P>I am not too sure how people will get more involved in the elections to the European Parliament. The number voting in every country in Europe is decreasing.  This may be because the public feels that the European Parliament is irrelevant or perhaps it has not been showing itself to be relevant.  We know it is relevant, and becoming increasingly so, but how are we going to give the public an image of the European Parliament as an institution in whose elections they should vote?</P>
      <P>The voting percentages in Europe will continue on a downgrade unless something is done in terms of publicity or making MEPs available to address on the national stage the issues which they address in the European Parliament.  The suggestion was made that they should be allowed to address the Seanad but I am not sure how that would work.  As I have said before, they have not used the forum which they are allowed to address, the Joint Committee on Foreign Affairs. They should be blamed rather than the institutions. I ask MEPs to use the Joint Committee on Foreign Affairs more effectively than they have done to date.</P>
      <P>I have no objection to non-national Union citizens standing in Ireland for election to the Parliament. They are entitled to do so, whether they are high profile, low profile or parachutists, it is a good idea for the democratic system to allow them to stand.  Some non-national candidates might enhance the role of the European Parliament. That is a good addition to the Bill.</P>
      <P>The Minister of State further stated that:</P>
      <P>A non-party MEP standing for election could include on the ballot paper the name of the political group in the Parliament of which her or she is a member.  This is intended to reflect the reality that the candidate would still be an MEP during the election.  Up to now the inclusion of the name of a political group in the Parliament on a ballot paper was confined to candidates belonging to registered political parties represented in the Parliament.</P>
      <P>That is a very important amendment because once independent candidates are elected to the Parliament they become part of a group and the public is entitled to know with which group they would be involved if they were elected.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>For example, I do not think many members of the Green Party would be elected in Ireland if the manifesto of the green parties throughout Europe <Col N="159" /> were put to the Irish people; I have a funny feeling they would be rejected out of hand.  They pick on single issues in their constituencies and are very &ldquo;green&rdquo; in terms of ecological issues. However, in Europe &ldquo;green&rdquo; does not just mean the enviornment or ecology.  It is important that people know for what they are voting.</P>
    <P>Concern has been expressed in the west that, because of the decline in population there, representation in the European Parliament will swing to the east coast.  That population decline will continue but a balance will have to be brought into the equation.  A declining population should not automatically mean that an area's representation in the European Parliament should decline in the same proportion.  There must be a built-in balance in constituencies with declining populations, such as the west of Ireland, which would ensure that votes in the area were not devalued, otherwise, there will be very few MEPs in 20 years' time from west of a line from Derry to Cork and the majority of seats will be in the east.  We should look at an electoral system where a decline in population would not be matched by an equal decline in the number of representatives of those constituencies.  Those areas probably need more work than areas in the east.</P>
    <P>The Bill is welcome consolidating legislation.  It follows such legislation as the Presidential Elections Act, 1993, and the Referendum Act, 1994. The more consolidation of legislation there can be, the better.</P>
    <P>I love the legalese used in Bills.  I was trying to look up a word in the Bill in the dictionary but I could not find it.  If I can find the word before the next speaker has concluded I would like the Minister of State to ask the draftsman to explain its meaning.</P>
    <Speaker pid="BernardAllen" hpid="Mr. Allen Mr. Allen">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Allen</NameTxt>
      <P>What was the word?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MickLanigan" hpid="Mr. Lanigan Mr. Lanigan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lanigan</NameTxt>
      <P>I will ask the question when I locate the word.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. Naughten Mr. Naughten">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Naughten</NameTxt>
      <P>I welcome this Bill which represents a continuation of the programme of electoral reform at all levels of democracy in the State, from local to presidential elections.  It is vital that electoral law is made more accessible to the public to encourage people to exercise their franchise.</P>
      <P>As we know, apathy and cynicism towards politics and politicians is on the increase and more young people feel that politics cannot make change.  The electorate perceives a growing credibility gap between politicians and their promises, which leads to the often heard phrase &ldquo;they are all the same&rdquo;.  We need to make changes before our system loses all credibility.  Cynicism towards politicians, especially among young people, has a profoundly negative effect on the political system, in both the short and long term.  A democratic society rests totally on the support and consent of its citizens.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="160" /> Politically, the most serious development is that large sections of society may feel that their political system is incapable of representing their needs and beliefs and is unable to deal with and solve problems.  One fault in the Bill is that a Member of the European Parliament can also be a Member of the Oireachtas.  This adds to the feeling that these politicians are incapable of representing the needs of their constituents to the best of their ability because they have a divided loyalty between the European Parliament and their national Parliament.</P>
    <P>When trying to encourage young voters to turn out, would it not be better to hold the polling day between Friday and Sunday rather than on a Thursday?  This would give people the opportunity to return home.  Despite these reservations, I welcome the Bill, especially the provisions regarding the inclusion of candidates' photographs and their parliamentary grouping on the ballot paper and the attempts to make voting more accessible for the disabled.</P>
    <P>The Minister of State, in his capacity as Minister of State at the Department of Education, is also responsible for youth and sport.  There must be greater emphasis on providing a broadly based political civics study course at both primary and second level schools.  Teaching children that they create the choice in our electoral system is a first step toward improving the way voters make their decisions.  If people are not aware of how they can change things, or even how our system works, then what can we expect?</P>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I compliment you, Senator, on your maiden speech.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnDardis" hpid="Mr. Dardis Mr. Dardis">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dardis</NameTxt>
      <P>I join with you, Sir, in complimenting Senator Naughten on his maiden speech. He is following a good tradition which I am glad to see is alive and well.</P>
      <P>I welcome this legislation.  It is uncontroversial and consolidates the way we regulate our European elections.  There is nothing new or different in the way the law is being consolidated, other than the inclusion of photographs.</P>
      <P>Senator Naughten raised a valid point regarding the relevance of the European Parliament to our national and parliamentary life.  The degree of apathy with regard to European elections is even greater than with general elections where fewer fewer people are voting as a percentage of the total population than was the case 20 or 30 years ago.  This begs the question how to make the European Parliament and its members more relevant to Irish parliamentary and political life. This House could serve a useful function in that respect in that there should be greater liaison between it and the members of the Parliament.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I sometimes wonder about the archaic ways in which we stand on our dignity.  It is noticeable how easy it is to visit the European Parliament or other European Parliaments; it is even easy to gain admittance to sit in the Chambers of some of them.  Before I became a Member of this Parliament I attended sessions of committees of the <Col N="161" /> European Parliament.  Democracy and parliamentary life should be accessible.</P>
    <P>During the course of debates on Seanad reform and the Constitution we addressed the issue of liaison.  The Maastricht Treaty provides that there should be greater liaison and co-operation between the Parliaments of the different EU countries.  The Seanad could play a useful role in this.</P>
    <P>It has been suggested that a Seanad election campaign is the most trying of all; it is not.  A European election is much more trying because we know the date of the election well in advance, we start campaigning very early and there is much ground to cover.  Having done all that and having reached the point of exhaustion on the Thursday evening when the polls close, we must then wait until the Sunday to be hung or elected.  That is the worst of all.  In 1989 when the general election count was over I had to wait until the following Sunday to travel to Navan to ascertain the way the votes in the constituency of Leinster had been cast.  It is not a humane way of dealing with candidates. The most practical way of overcoming this is a Sunday election.  On previous electoral legislation I have advocated that we should consider a Sunday poll.  While it should not specified as such, it should not be excluded, as it is in the Bill. It would mean that if there was a consensus, it would not require a change in the legislation to put it into effect.</P>
    <P>I welcome the provisions with regard to the rights of citizens of the EU resident in Ireland to stand for elections and vote.  If citizenship of the Union is to mean anything, it should mean that. However, during a European election which I contested I visited a local polling station where a woman was turned away.  I knew she was a British citizen.  When she left I inquired of the presiding officer why and was told she could not vote.  I said she was British and she could vote.  It was repeated to me that she could not vote, the book was produced and it was quoted to me on at least three occasions why she could not vote.  I said if the book was read a fourth time it would be discovered why she could vote.  The instructions to presiding officers should have made it clear that such a person was entitled to vote.  There was a misunderstanding in this instance because categories of people were excluded.  The person in question had walked two miles from the village to the polling station to cast her vote because she regarded it as important.  I brought her back to the station.  I do not know how she cast her vote, nor would it be proper for me to know.</P>
    <P>This incident underlines that there must be accessibility.  When dealing with general accessibility to democracy we must be as inclusive as possible.  That is why I do not like some of the provisions in general electoral Bills which impose big deposits, as is the case here where a deposit of £1,000 is required.  This is a significant amount of money.  It should be possible for a young person from the group water schemes or the Monster Raving Looney Party, as Gaeilge, to be able to <Col N="162" /> stand for election.  Why are we so pompous in insisting on the seriousness of this process?  We should encourage people to contest elections.  I saw a ballot paper in Palestine which had 90 candidates. It did not appear to cause difficulties, and it was their first election.  We get carried away at times with a sense of the importance of the occasion and of our own importance.</P>
    <P>I appeal to the Minister of State to make participation in elections as easy and as accessible as possible.  Some of the cynicism that exists would not be there if it were easier to stand in elections. We know the difficulties parties face getting people to stand.  While there are other reasons &mdash; financial not being the least of them &mdash; provisions in Bills of this kind must be as liberal as possible to allow people to stand.  Does it matter if there are eccentric candidates?  I do not see any difficulty with that.  Let the electorate make its decision.</P>
    <P>Senator Lanigan suggested that if the policies of the Green Party had been widely distributed it would not have achieved its level of support at the last European election.  However, one of the reasons for its success is that the electorate saw some relevance in its concerns for the environment in the context of the EU and the European Parliament.  The electorate perceived that central economic issues were not at the core of the work of the European Parliament and that it was desirable to elect Members who would act as watchdogs on environmental matters.  That was part of the reason for the Green Party's success in the last election.</P>
    <P>I note there is postal voting, which I favour, but this is one of the classic cases where emigrants should be entitled to vote.  I realise practical difficulties are involved; but if other democracies as large as the European Union can do it, I do not understand why it cannot be done in the EU. Irish citizens resident in other EU countries can vote for candidates in those countries and there should be no problem ensuring they can vote for candidates at home if they choose to do so.  This relates to the issue of emigrant representation, which was debated previously in the House.  It is a sop to give them seats in the Seanad and it would be preferable to allow people to vote.  We should remember that South African citizens in Ireland voted in their country's first election.</P>
    <P>I moved an amendment in November 1993 to the Presidential Elections Bill stating that there should be photographs on ballot papers.  There were photographs on the ballot papers in the South African and Palestinian elections.  Some of the reasons given at the time for not having photographs on ballot papers were strange &mdash; for example, that there would be in effect a beauty contest and the quality of the photographs would in some way influence the outcome of the election. In a time of modern communications and when most candidates have their pictures in the local papers during elections, most people know who they are and it is not an issue.</P>
    <Col N="163" />
    <Speaker pid="MickLanigan" hpid="Mr. Lanigan Mr. Lanigan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lanigan</NameTxt>
      <P>They might have colour in their hair.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnDardis" hpid="Mr. Dardis Mr. Dardis">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dardis</NameTxt>
      <P>The then Minister of State, who was a member of a different party from the Minister, stated it was difficult to maintain that there was a genuine need for the measures proposed in the amendment.  He said existing regulations were adequate and there was no need for photographs. I am glad this Bill was amended in the other House to include this point because it relates to exclusion.</P>
      <P>Illiterate people should be able to go into a polling station and vote on the basis of identifying photographs.  I have been in polling stations where there have been shouted votes and although it is necessary, it is humiliating that people must stand as the names are read to them and they indicate their preferences.  It is not desirable. If people have difficulty reading a ballot paper, it would be desirable to include photographs in addition to the logos of the parties in a separate column.  There are precedents for this; South Africa is one example.  I welcome the inclusion of this matter and I do not understand the relevance of the point that it could turn the election into a beauty contest.  Senator Lanigan and I do not have to worry about that aspect because we are not high up in the beauty contest stakes.  Even the Minister could be disqualified in that regard.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MickLanigan" hpid="Mr. Lanigan Mr. Lanigan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lanigan</NameTxt>
      <P>Beauty is in the eye of the beholder.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnDardis" hpid="Mr. Dardis Mr. Dardis">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dardis</NameTxt>
      <P>The provision in the Bill regarding non-party MEPs is reasonable.  Regarding the electoral commission, I referred to the amount of deposits, which perhaps is too large, and there should not be an exclusion regarding Sunday.</P>
      <P>Regarding the dual mandate of Deputies and Members of the European Parliament, it would be preferable if an MEP or a Deputy opted for one Parliament or the other.  They should not continue to be a Member of both institutions.  A good example in the Seanad was when former Senator, Brian Crowley, was elected to the European Parliament.  He relinquished his seat, which was a sensible thing to do.  I am not sure whether this issue should be included in a Bill.  Perhaps it is inappropriate to deal with it in legislation.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Another matter relates to rulings on valid votes.  Deputy Bell was involved in a case in the 1989 election.  The problem arises if a general election is held on the same day as the European elections because people indicate their first, second, third and fourth preferences on one ballot paper and their fifth, sixth, seventh, eighth and ninth preferences on the other.  In three of the constituencies in the 1989 election, the returning officers ruled that the fifth to ninth marks were clear preferences and the ballot papers were valid.  However, in Leinster it was decreed that such ballot papers were invalid.  The matter went to the High Court and it was held that the returning officer was entitled to make that <Col N="164" /> decision.  Returning officers should have wide discretion but there should be a system which removes any ambiguity.  It should be possible in circumstances where the two elections are held together and there are ballot papers with continuing scales of preferences to decree those papers valid.</P>
    <P>Regarding the relevance of the Parliament, difficulties will be created in the future by enlargement. The institutional aspect of the Union will cause problems.  It will be to our disadvantage if the Parliament is enlarged to a large degree and Ireland continues to have the same number of MEPs.  The system involving a base line, where countries such as Luxembourg have five MEPs and each country starts from that figure and moves up on a proportional basis, is reasonably sensible.  However, this matter will cause problems for Ireland when the Parliament expands in an enlarged Union.</P>
    <P>Another issue is the democratic deficit and the relevance of the Parliament to the legal life of the Union in terms of its input to the framing of Union policy and law.  I appreciate some improvements have resulted from the Maastricht Treaty but there is some way to go.  It is essential that Ireland continues to have a European Commissioner after enlargement.  I am not in favour of a rotating Commissioner or of Commissioners dropping out.  The <i>sine qua non</i> of Ireland's participation is that we have a Commissioner at the table.</P>
    <P>A suggestion which could be considered in terms of the Parliament is the possibility of holding all the elections on the same day every five years.  Perhaps there is some merit in the American system where half the membership is revolved at half term.  Members serve a five year term but there is an election every two and a half years.  There may also be merit in a list system in Ireland aside from the proportional representation system of the single transferable vote. However, such a move is a long way off.</P>
    <P>An aspect which causes much difficulty is the jargon of European procedures and directives from the Commission.  I made this point in the past and I am responsible for coining a piece of Euro jargon.  When it was suggested to me that there was an information deficit, I said there was not an information deficit but a comprehension deficit.  We are deluged with information but the problem is the ability to understand it.  This relates to a point made by Senator Lanigan that national legislation should be capable of being readily understood.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MickLanigan" hpid="Mr. Lanigan Mr. Lanigan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lanigan</NameTxt>
      <P>Another phrase used in Europe is &ldquo;In the influction of time&rdquo;.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnDardis" hpid="Mr. Dardis Mr. Dardis">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dardis</NameTxt>
      <P>I will attempt to grapple with that one on Senator Lanigan's behalf.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>One of the problems with European elections, particularly when they are not associated with general elections, is that the debate lapses into national politics.  It inevitably revolves round national economic and welfare matters and <Col N="165" /> occasionally local matters, such as the drainage of rivers.  One wonders at times about the relevance of the debate in terms of the European Parliament membership.  However, I accept that is a reality and it is what interests people.  They look to their public representatives to attend to such matters and I have no difficulty with that. However, I wonder at times about the relevance of the debate to the European Parliament, particularly if one is debating the EU, a European election or the European Parliament at meetings.  The audience's eyes start to glaze over and one feels one has lost the people at that stage.  I do not know how the problem can be overcome.</P>
    <P>There is no deficit of information from Europe but there is definitely a deficit of comprehension. The documents from the Commission and the Parliament should be easily understood. However, to be fair, the Parliament has made significant strides in that respect in recent years. Some of the more recent documents from the Parliament are more easily understood.  They are more relevant and more accessible to citizens.  If our citizenship of the EU is to mean anything it should mean that we can relate to the members of the Parliament whom we elect.  I welcome the Bill.</P>
    <Speaker pid="BernardAllen" hpid="Minister of State at the Department of the Environment (Mr. Allen) Minister of State at the Department of the Environment (Mr. Allen)">
      <NameTxt>Minister of State at the Department of the Environment (Mr. Allen)</NameTxt>
      <P>I thank the Senators who contributed to the debate.  I congratulate Senator Naughten on his maiden speech.  I wish him a long and fruitful career in this House and elsewhere.</P>
      <P>Senator Lydon asked about holding the next local elections with the European Parliament elections in 1999.  That matter will be considered next year.  If the two elections are held in 1999 the Local Government Act, 1994, will require amendment.</P>
      <P>Senator Lydon also asked how a person qualifies as a special voter.  The special voter scheme was introduced in 1986 after irregularities occurred in the postal voting system.  To qualify a person must have a physical illness or disability and be resident in a hospital, nursing home or another similar institution.  It was also asked why it was necessary to have a special presiding officer and a garda present.  Their presence is to ensure the secrecy and integrity of the ballot.  The officers are advised to carry out their duties in a sensitive manner and to attempt to reduce intrusiveness during the procedures as far as possible.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Senator Hayes urged political parties to ban the dual mandate at the next European elections. Article 5 of the Act annexed to a Council decision of 20 September 1976, specifically provides that membership of the European Parliament shall be compatible with membership of the parliament of a member state.  I am advised that it is not open to us to forbid the dual mandate in national law.  Not alone are we debarred from making membership of the Oireachtas a disqualification for membership of the Parliament but we are also debarred from making membership of <Col N="166" /> the Parliament a disqualification for membership of the Oireachtas.</P>
    <P>Therefore, it falls to individual political parties to decide whether their members should seek to discharge the dual mandate.  If parties do not decide to reject the concept it is a matter for the people in the final analysis to decide whether they will vote for a candidate who proposes to exercise the dual mandate.  The incidence of the dual mandate among Ireland's MEPs appears to be on the decline.  Of the 15 members elected to the Parliament in the first direct elections in 1979, 13 had a dual mandate.  However, only three of the present 15 MEPs are also Members of the Oireachtas. This will change after the next general election.</P>
    <P>Senator Hayes also asked about a voter voting at a European Parliament election in an area other than that in which he or she is registered. The Electoral Bill, 1994, which will be considered by the Select Committee on Finance and General Affairs next month, will provide postal voting for people who are away from their homes on election day.</P>
    <P>Senator Hayes and Senator Lydon also raised the issue of the constituency commission for local elections.  The existing boundaries of the electoral areas in county council and county boroughs were fixed on foot of recommendations of independent commissions.  Under the Local Government Acts of 1991 and 1994, statutory boundary commissions must be established to advise on the revision of local electoral areas.  The question of establishing such commissions will be considered when the final report of the 1996 census is available.</P>
    <P>Senator Lydon and Senator Hayes asked why the Bill entitles people to vote at 18 years of age but requires them to be at least 21 years old to stand for election.  The Bill follows to a large extent the practice set out in the Dáil electoral code.  It is a constitutional requirement that Dáil candidates must be 21 years of age or over.  If the Constitution was to be changed I am sure the same rules would then apply to European elections. Senator Lydon asked about the practice in this regard in other EU member states.  I do not have information to hand but the European Communities Act, 1976, which set out certain guiding principles for European elections, is silent on the issue of a minimum age for candidates.  I presume a uniform electoral procedure for the European Parliament would include a common minimum age for candidates.</P>
    <P>Senator Hayes asked if MEPs may vote in Seanad elections.  They may not unless they qualify as voters under the Seanad electoral laws.  This matter can be considered when the Seanad electoral laws are being reviewed.  The all-party committee considering the report of the Constitutional Review Group may have an opinion on this matter.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JohnDardis" hpid="Mr. Dardis Mr. Dardis">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dardis</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator Hayes will have to take them off his Christmas card list.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="167" />
    <Speaker pid="MickLanigan" hpid="Mr. Lanigan Mr. Lanigan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lanigan</NameTxt>
      <P>Not all of them; some are graduates.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BernardAllen" hpid="Mr. Allen Mr. Allen">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Allen</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator Dardis raised the question of the level of deposits.  An electoral deposit is a mechanism used in this and in some other countries to put an obstacle in the way of purely frivolous candidates and in recognition of the privileges to which a candidate is entitled &mdash; for example, free copies of the register, the right to demand that electors be challenged or arrested at polling stations, or the right to demand a complete recount of the votes.  Alternative ways of achieving this objective and establishing that the candidate has serious support, such as requiring a significant number of signatures or restricting the right to nominate to registered political parties, are difficult to operate or are unacceptable in principle.</P>
      <P>If there is to be a deposit it must be pitched at a reasonable level &mdash; high enough to discourage the frivolous but not so high as to be an obstacle to genuine candidates.  The present deposit of £1,000 has not been the subject of widespread complaint since its introduction in 1977.  The Bill does not propose to increase it.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>Bill put through Committee, reported without amendment and received for final consideration.</P>
      <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That the Bill do now pass.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BernardAllen" hpid="Minister of State at the Department of the Environment (Mr. Allen) Minister of State at the Department of the Environment (Mr. Allen)">
      <NameTxt>Minister of State at the Department of the Environment (Mr. Allen)</NameTxt>
      <P>I thank Senators who participated in this debate.  This legislation will be helpful to candidates from all parties and, most importantly, to the electorate.  It consolidates existing regulations under one Bill.  A good day's work has been done.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>When is it proposed to sit again?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BrianHayes" hpid="Mr. Hayes Mr. Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>Next Wednesday at 2.30 p.m.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Adjournment Matters." RHead="- Sunday Voting">
    <Title>Adjournment Matters. - Sunday Voting.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="BrianHayes" hpid="Mr. Hayes Mr. Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>My proposal, which I have put to the Government and for which I am looking for a positive response, is to consider moving the day of national voting from Thursday to Sunday.  We have had seven general elections over the past 20 years and the number of people turning out to vote has gone down in each successive election, bar one.  It has gone from an average of 76 per cent in 1977 to 68 per cent in 1992.  A consistent number of people are not coming out to vote at successive elections and that is worrying.  We should not go down the road of the United States <Col N="168" /> of America where only about 50 per cent of the electorate vote.</P>
      <P>We have to look at the day we have selected as our day of national ballot.  It is not just a day for general elections; it is also a day for referenda and local elections.  I contend that Thursday is the most impractical day in the week to vote.  I suggest for a number of reasons we should consider the proposal to move it to a Sunday or, if not Sunday, perhaps over the weekend.  One must consider the disruption caused to the school system. Thousands of schools close down as a result of voting on Thursday and it causes disruption to parents when children are off school.  Many young people are in college or work in one part of the country but live in a different constituency and many of them cannot get home to vote on a Thursday because it is impractical.  One must also consider the number of emigrants living in London or other parts of the EU who might come back if the election was held at the weekend.</P>
      <P>The number of people working away from home on the day of a national ballot is quite large.  People in my constituency spoke to me following the bail referendum and said they could not get out to vote on Thursday because they were working in Kerry or Cork that day.  All these difficulties result in the fact that the national ballot has gone down in each successive election over the past 20 years.</P>
      <P>The European example is to select a weekend day, preferably a Sunday.  The Netherlands and Great Britain are the only two countries in the EU which select a weekday for a ballot.  If it is good enough for Spain, Portugal, Italy and Germany, it should be good enough for us.  It is a simple proposal for which many people have been calling.  Given that it is election year and these matters are being considered, I ask the Government to consider this proposal.  I look forward to the Minister of State's reply.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JimmyDeenihan" hpid="Minister of State at the Department of Agriculture, Food and Forestry (Mr. Deenihan) Jimmy Deenihan">
      <NameTxt>Minister of State at the Department of Agriculture, Food and Forestry (Mr. Deenihan)</NameTxt>
      <P>I congratulate Senator Hayes for raising this matter.</P>
      <P>The statutory provision on the appointment of a polling day at a Dáil election is section 96 of the Electoral Act, 1992.  This allows the polling day at each election to be appointed by order made by the Minister for the Environment.  It is a matter for decision on each occasion which day of the week should be appointed for taking the poll.  No matter what day is appointed, there will be advantages and disadvantages.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Some of the advantages of Sunday voting would be that: it would facilitate those workers and students who are normally away from home on weekdays; reduce or eliminate school closure and give a wider choice as to the time of day at which people could vote.  Against this, there would also be some disadvantages.  There could be objections on religious grounds from some denominations.  When the question of Sunday voting was raised some years ago with church <Col N="169" /> leaders, the minority churches indicated that they would be opposed on religious and moral grounds &mdash; the Catholic Church had no objection; there could be a reduced poll because people go away at weekends, or because of clashes with sporting events, etc; persons returning home at weekends, and registered at the place where they work or study, might not be able to vote and certain sectors of the workforce, such as those in transport, hotels, etc. are required to work on weekends and would find no advantage in Sunday voting.</P>
    <P>Recent changes, and proposed changes, in electoral law are relevant to the issue of Sunday voting. A person who may be ordinarily resident in more than one place can choose the place for registration, and hence for voting.  The Electoral Bill, 1994, proposes special voting arrangements for electors who are unable to attend their polling station on polling day because of their occupation. This includes students living away from the family home.  Returning officers can hire halls and similar premises for voting purposes, even where a school is available, thus reducing the impact on schools of weekday elections. Assembly, canvassing and the use of loudspeakers in the vicinity of polling stations is prohibited, again minimising the impact on schools.</P>
    <P>Overall, it is not certain that more people would have an opportunity of voting, and would vote, if elections took place on Sundays rather than midweek as at present.  Neither is it clear that voting on Sundays is the only way, or the best way, of facilitating those for whom the existing practice is not suitable.  There are many different views on this matter and changes should not be made unless they attract broad support.  For this reason, weekend voting was one of the electoral issues referred by the Minister for the Environment in April 1995 to the Dáil Select Committee on Finance and General Affairs for consideration. The committee has yet to deal with the issue.  When they have done so, we will be in a better position to review the pros and cons of weekend voting and to decide what our future arrangements should be.</P>
    <P>I compliment Senator Hayes for raising this issue.  It is one of his favourite subjects and he has been lobbying for it.  Hopefully, we can come to the best arrangement for all electors.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Adjournment Matters. - Suck" RHead="Valley Catchment Area">
    <Title>Adjournment Matters. - Suck Valley Catchment Area.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelFinneranFF" hpid="Mr. Finneran Mr. Finneran">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Finneran</NameTxt>
      <P>This motion calls on the Minister for Agriculture, Food and Forestry to have the Suck Valley catchment area included in the new EU category of extremely disadvantaged areas. With the permission of the Chair, I wish to share time with Senator Mullooly.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFallon" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Is that agreed?  Agreed.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelFinneranFF" hpid="Mr. Finneran Mr. Finneran">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Finneran</NameTxt>
      <P>I raised this issue as a result of a recent meeting between representatives of the Suck Action Committee and Senator Mullooly and myself.  The River Suck runs between Counties <Col N="170" /> Roscommon and Galway and the committee outlined a strong case to have its catchment area included in the new EU category for extremely disadvantaged areas.  Information on when this category will come on stream, when grants will be paid and the amount of such grants remains vague.  Senator Mullooly and I wish to establish whether the Suck Valley catchment area was included in the application to Brussels in respect of this category.  Will the Minister of State inform the House about the areas that were included, the date of the application and whether the Suck Valley catchment area was included?</P>
      <P>In the region of 2,000 individuals are involved in farming in the Suck Valley catchment area which covers approximately 600 square miles. The river's 84 mile watercourse is bordered by 75,000 acres of land.  This area is subject to regular flooding which causes great hardship to farmers, mainly dry stock owners, who are in the lower income bracket.  We must also take into consideration the severe decrease in population in this area during the past number of years.  This is consequential on the fact that low incomes made young people reluctant to assume responsibility for farms or remain in farming and they moved to cities and towns in the hope of making a better living.</P>
      <P>If we are to protect and enhance the Suck Valley catchment area, comply with the jargon constantly emanating from Europe and the Government and support rural and regional development, this is a very practical and proper way to do so.  People make a meagre living from farming in the Suck Valley catchment area and we believe they are entitled to be included in the category of extremely disadvantaged areas.</P>
      <P>Unlike some other areas, alternative farming practices and enterprises are not easily operated in the Suck Valley catchment area due to flooding. For example, tourism opportunities might exist in other areas where holdings are small and land is poor.  However, those opportunities are severely diminished in the Suck Valley catchment area because of severe and unpredictable flooding which can last for up to six months.  The entire area can be left desolate as a result and it is practically impossible for farmers to plan farming practices and operations or make a decent living.</P>
      <P>Further opportunities exist in other areas in respect of forestry.  This is unsuitable to the larger part of the Suck Valley catchment area because of severe flooding which can sometimes reach a depth of five feet.  Areas between Ballinasloe and Castlerea are subject to severe flooding on many occasions during the year.  The records of local authorities in Counties Roscommon and Galway will show that severe flooding occurs each year in areas surrounding Ballyforan, Athleague, Castlestrange, Castlecoot, Donamon and Castlerea. Two years ago, flooding was so severe in these areas that many villages were cut off for up to two months.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>In making the case on behalf of people living in the Suck Valley catchment area I believe the <Col N="171" /> necessary requirements to be included in the new EU category are present.  I cannot think of another area that would be more suitable or entitled to be included in that category.  The decline in population on the Roscommon and Galway banks of the River Suck must be halted.  Senator Mullooly and I are more familiar with the situation in County Roscommon; two to three families live in many villages which were occupied by 30 to 40 families at the turn of the century.</P>
    <P>As far as I am concerned, there is a good case for inclusion.  I ask the Minister of State to inform the House whether the Suck Valley catchment area was included Department's application to the European Commission for inclusion in the category of extremely disadvantaged areas?  How many areas were included in that application? When will a decision be made and what steps are necessary to enhance the case of those living in the Suck Valley catchment area for inclusion in the new EU category?</P>
    <Speaker pid="BrianMullooly" hpid="Mr. Mullooly Mr. Mullooly">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Mullooly</NameTxt>
      <P>I thank Senator Finneran for sharing time and I support the strong case he made for inclusion of the Suck Valley catchment area in the new category of extremely disadvantaged areas.</P>
      <P>The Suck Valley catchment area is occupied by small farmers on low incomes.  The land is marginal and many of the farms are fragmented.  The difficulties of local farmers are exacerbated by the severe flooding that happens regularly.  This affects almost every farmer in the Suck Valley to a greater or lesser degree.  I understand that at certain times approximately 100,000 acres &mdash; 40,000 hectares &mdash; can be affected by flooding. That is a huge area by any standards.  Up to 66 per cent of some farm areas are liable to flooding. The farmers are hard working and industrious but it is impossible to operate a long-term farm plan because of the uncertainty with regard to flooding. It must also be recognised that much of the land subject to flooding is, as Senator Finneran stated, unsuitable for alternative activities such as forestry.  This land is only suitable for rough grazing of livestock.</P>
      <P>The Suck Valley is an area of declining population because young people are reluctant to face an uncertain future on small, fragmented, marginal farms.  I understand that the Suck Valley Action Group has had a number of meetings with the Department of Agriculture, Food and Forestry in respect of its application to have the area designated as extremely disadvantaged.  It put forward a strong case which it supported with a large volume of documentation that included statistics, maps and engineering data on the extent and cause of flooding.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Consideration should be given to including this area in the new category.  Farmers in this area have endured severe hardship and low income for years.  The next generation will not do that and there is now an opportunity to improve their situation <Col N="172" /> by granting them the designation for which they have applied.  The Minister should ensure that happens.  As Senator Finneran said, I can think of no other region with a better claim to being designated as extremely disadvantaged.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JimmyDeenihan" hpid="Minister of State at the Department of Agriculture, Food and Forestry (Mr. Deenihan) Jimmy Deenihan">
      <NameTxt>Minister of State at the Department of Agriculture, Food and Forestry (Mr. Deenihan)</NameTxt>
      <P>I wish to acknowledge the presence in the Visitors Gallery of the former member of the British Parliament, Sir Gerry Neale.  He is very welcome to Ireland.</P>
      <P>My officials are very familiar with the conditions in the Suck Valley catchment area.  These disadvantages will be taken into account when the decision on the third tier is made.  The third tier of &ldquo;extremely&rdquo; disadvantaged areas was envisaged as applying to areas, primarily in the west, in which the land is so poor as to be almost unusable.  Generally, this category would apply to mountainous or peatland areas and to inhabited islands which have the additional disadvantage of isolation.</P>
      <P>I have, together with officials of my Department, spent some time considering how best to identify the areas which would be most suitable for classification in this category.  There was a need to establish the uniqueness of the areas in order to convince the EU Commission of the special needs of farmers in these areas.  The criteria established to facilitate selection of areas were as follows: the areas must be already more severely handicapped, and should not extend beyond the boundary of the original MSH designation of 1975; there must be a high proportion of &ldquo;rough grazing&rdquo; land in the areas; the areas must be subject to extreme climatic conditions; and to ensure homogeneity of physical characteristics and farming types, areas must be at least 20,000 hectares in extent.  All areas in respect of which applications were received for inclusion in this new disadvantaged area category were considered in light of the above criteria when the submission was being prepared.</P>
      <P>The extremely disadvantaged areas proposal was submitted to the EU Commission in October 1996.  I have been informed that the proposal is being considered by the Commission in conjunction with an overall package of proposed amendments to the scheme of compensatory allowances arising out of the independent evaluation of this scheme.  Consequently, it would be difficult to predict when the new areas will be approved. However, since payments in the new category areas will be additional to those already received based on 1997 scheme applications, there will be no need for a separate application from farmers whose areas are reclassified.</P>
      <P>Since the proposals have not yet been approved, I cannot comment on whether any specific area is included in the areas submitted.  However, the merits of all potential areas were rigorously examined to ensure that the most deserving areas which satisfied the criteria were selected.</P>
      <P>The Seanad adjourned at 4.05 p.m. until 2.30 p.m. on Wednesday, 19 February 1997.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
</Debate>