<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE Debate SYSTEM "../Debate.dtd"[]>
<Debate DocTitle="Seanad Debate" Day="Thu" Date="18" Month="Oct" Year="2001" Vol="168" No="7" DateIrish="Déardaoin, 18 Deireadh Fómhair 2001" DateEnglish="Thursday, 18 October 2001" House="S" CommitteeEng="" CommitteeIr="" SubNameEng="" cnum="0">
  <MainHeading Type="Prelude" LHead="" RHead="">
    <Title>
    </Title>
    <P Just="Center">
      <Col N="381" />Chuaigh an Cathaoirleach i gceannas ar 10.30 a.m.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Business" RHead="of Seanad">
    <Title>Business of Seanad.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="BrianMullooly" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I have notice from Senator Cosgrave that, on the motion for the Adjournment today, he proposes to raise the following matter:</P>
      <P>The need for the Minister for Arts, Heritage, Gaeltacht and the Islands to outline the plans she has for the maritime museum in Dún Laoghaire; the proposals she has for moving it from its current location; and the discussions which have taken place regarding its future.</P>
      <P>I have notice from Senator Taylor-Quinn of the following matter:</P>
      <P>The need for the Minister for Health and Children to review the situation in relation to the re-opening of the Stella Maris nursing home in Lisdoonvarna; to explain the protracted delays in negotiations with his Department; and to allocate the moneys necessary to enable the nursing home to re-open prior to Christmas.</P>
      <P>I have notice from Senator Costello of the following matter:</P>
      <P>The need for the Minister for the Environment and Local Government to clarify the steps he has taken to ensure that taxi plate holders, spouses, widows and family members are not suffering hardship as a result of the Government's decision to deregulate the taxi industry last year.</P>
      <P>I regard the matters raised by the Senators as suitable for discussion on the Adjournment and they will be taken at the conclusion of business.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Messages" RHead="from Dáil">
    <Title>Messages from Dáil.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="BrianMullooly" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Dáil Éireann has agreed to the amendments made by Seanad Éireann to the Electoral (Amendment) Bill, 2000.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Dáil Éireann has made the following order in <Col N="382" /> relation to the Aer Lingus Bill, 2000, which was received from Seanad Éireann on 27 June 2000: &ldquo;That, notwithstanding Standing Order 107, leave be given to withdraw the Aer Lingus Bill, 2000.&rdquo;</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Order of" RHead="Business">
    <Title>Order of Business.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="DonnieCassidyFF" hpid="Mr. Cassidy Mr. Cassidy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cassidy</NameTxt>
      <P>The Order of Business today is No. 1, motion re the Freedom of Information Act, 1997, (Prescribed Bodies) (No. 4) Regulations, 2001, to be taken without debate; No. 2, referral of motion re the Council regulation regarding examination of asylum applications to the Joint Committee on Justice, Equality, Defence and Women's Rights, to be taken without debate; No. 3, Law of the Sea (Repression of Piracy) Bill, 2001 &ndash; Report Stage; No. 4, statements on the economy, not to be taken before 11.30 a.m. with the contributions of spokespersons not to exceed 15 minutes and those of all other Senators not to exceed ten minutes, to conclude no later than 5 p.m.; No. 5, statements on Aer Lingus, not to be taken before 5 p.m., with the contributions of spokespersons not to exceed 15 minutes and those of all other Senators not to exceed ten minutes, and to conclude not later than 8 p.m. Senators may share time.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MauriceManning" hpid="Mr. Manning Mr. Manning">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Manning</NameTxt>
      <P>I am glad the Dáil has accepted the significant amendments made by this House to the Electoral (Amendment) Bill, 2000. I congratulate all who were involved in helping change the Government's mind and making it back-track on the issue.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RoryKiely" hpid="Mr. R. Kiely Mr. R. Kiely">
      <NameTxt>Mr. R. Kiely</NameTxt>
      <P>It was a Fine Gael amendment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MauriceManning" hpid="Mr. Manning Mr. Manning">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Manning</NameTxt>
      <P>Will the Leader explain the state of the Aer Lingus Bill, 2000? It is my understanding that the Bill was passed in this House and has now been withdrawn. Why is that?</P>
      <P>I am encouraged by the hopeful signs from Northern Ireland. We may well be on the brink of decommissioning, the logjam may break and real progress may be made. Against that background and given that this House has always been very helpful and responsible in its debates on Northern Ireland, will the Leader provide time for an early debate? </P>
      <P>Many firms are facing massive increases in the cost of insurance. A firm that I dealt with this morning has had its insurance cover increased from £45,000 to £145,000 per annum. This is happening to many other companies and I ask the Leader to arrange an early debate on these massive insurance hikes, which may be largely due to external factors. It is important that we have a debate on the issue as this is a cost that will drive Irish companies out of business.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Last week, I asked for a debate on binge-drinking and the way in which the drinks industry is targeting students and vulnerable people. In <Col N="383" /> drink promotions, drink is almost thrown at young people. The drinks industry is behaving in a cynical, irresponsible and almost criminal way, and I would like a debate on the issue.</P>
    <Speaker pid="BrianMullooly" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>In relation to the query which Senator Manning raised concerning the Aer Lingus Bill, 2000, the Dáil has decided not to proceed with the Bill. The effect of the order made is to withdraw the Bill from the Dáil agenda.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeOToole" hpid="Mr. O'Toole Mr. O'Toole">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Toole</NameTxt>
      <P>Nonetheless, the Bill still passed this House.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BrianMullooly" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeOToole" hpid="Mr. O'Toole Mr. O'Toole">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Toole</NameTxt>
      <P>It is my understanding that it can be reinstated on the Dáil Order of Business at any time. I want to satisfy myself that the passing of the Bill in this House has not been made void in any way.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BrianMullooly" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes. The Bill was passed by this House but the passing of the Bill by one of the Houses of the Oireachtas does not bring it into legislation. The Dáil has withdrawn the Bill from its Order Paper. The Dáil is not proceeding with it. That is the decision of the Dáil made under a Standing Order of the Dáil.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeOToole" hpid="Mr. O'Toole Mr. O'Toole">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Toole</NameTxt>
      <P>It has no implications for us in this House.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BrianMullooly" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>None. It is the same as if the Bill lapsed on the dissolution of the Dáil.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeOToole" hpid="Mr. O'Toole Mr. O'Toole">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Toole</NameTxt>
      <P>That is precisely what I wanted to find out. Thank you.</P>
      <P>I support the call by Senator Manning for a debate on Northern Ireland. This week we will have either development or collapse. It is as simple as that. There will either be movement this week or we will have a disaster on our hands. Either way, we should focus on it next week. If things go wrong, political voices need to be raised immediately and if there are developments we need to be able to respond to them. I ask the Leader of the House to give an absolute commitment that we will have a debate on this matter next week.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I thank the Leader for fulfilling his promise to allow for statements on the economy and statements on Aer Lingus and I look forward to making a contribution on those issues. An issue we have discussed in this House regularly is housing, particularly for young people. In the national development plan there was a commitment to provide for 50,000 to 55,000 starts per annum. I am now certain that will not be achieved. Rather than wait for the collapse of this provision, I ask the Minister of State at the Department of the <Col N="384" /> Environment and Local Government, Deputy Molloy, to come to this House to facilitate a debate so that we can better understand the issue and give a clear message on it. There are builders who are used to big profits and who have now stopped building. They do not like the Minister's Bill providing for social housing and they do not like the Bacon report which is curtailing investment. They should recognise that they come under democratic control like the rest of us. These people think that they can sit on their land banks and go to Marbella for three years and wait for the demand to increase again in order to sell houses at inflated prices. We should be telling them, as a democracy, that they either use it or lose it in terms of their land banks.</P>
    <P>There is not a lack of demand for housing. The number of young people is growing and the demand for housing is simply being deferred. Prices will jump again in 18 months' time and we need to take decisions on it now. This is why we need to have a debate on housing now.   </P>
    <P>I received useful information from the Leader of the House this morning on No. 2. The reason we accept these items without debate is that they are referred to a committee. When we agreed on that procedure some years ago, it was on the basis that once the committee had discussed it, its report would return to this House for discussion. That does not appear to be happening. Someone should actively ensure that matters which we refer to committees are reported back to this House. It should be like the system of legislation &ndash; a committee followed by a report back to the House.</P>
    <P>I ask the Leader to explain why this document comes from the &lsquo;Office of Leader and Government Chief'. Does this indicate that there is a new Government chief and that the Leader now has two titles? I understand Government chief whip, but this says it is from 'Government Chief'. I thought there was only one chief in the Fianna Fáil Party.</P>
    <Speaker pid="BrianMullooly" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator O'Toole, I think you have made the point.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeOToole" hpid="Mr. O'Toole Mr. O'Toole">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Toole</NameTxt>
      <P>I would appreciate some help with that one.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeCostelloLAB" hpid="Mr. Costello Mr. Costello">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Costello</NameTxt>
      <P>We have not been given any reason why the Dáil decided to withdraw the Aer Lingus Bill, 2000 that was introduced in this House. Does this mean that the privatisation policy is being abandoned by the Government?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I have protested against items under the Freedom of Information Act coming on to the agenda so often because it is an unnecessary waste of valuable time. We should have an enabling mechanism so that only items that do not come under the terms of the Act would be dealt with in this House or the Dáil. I am sure my colleagues behind me will be glad to know that with this <Col N="385" /> regulation both the NUI and Trinity College will come under the glare of publicity and it will be open to the public to see for themselves the arcane activities carried out in those third level institutions. That is worthwhile but the mechanism is wrong for dealing with matters under the Freedom of Information Act.</P>
    <P>I agree with Senator O'Toole regarding the second item that it seems irregular to do what we are being asked. I acknowledge that the Chief Whip gave me an explanation of the intention but it seems we are being asked to approve today that the President of the Council be notified of our agreement on this matter and that we wish to take part in the adoption of an application of this option in the protocol of the Amsterdam treaty. Yet this will not come back to this House until 25 October. We are therefore approving something which goes to committee and comes back to the House on 25 October. What is the sense in approving it now? Surely the proper time to approve it would be when it returns from committee and when the matter has been laid before this House and we have been given the opportunity to examine it. It is an important issue, replacing the 1997 Dublin convention which applies to the manner in which we deal with asylum seekers in this country. This should be the subject of a debate and we should hear all views.</P>
    <P>The way we are dealing with our business is sloppy and we are quick to send issues to committee. We have a responsibility to examine regulatory matters that come before us. If we do not examine them carefully, we as legislators are not doing our jobs properly. I am worried about some examples of this which have arisen recently.</P>
    <P>I call for a debate on Northern Ireland, which is long overdue. We have called for it nearly every week since the House resumed and as we all know we are reaching a crisis point. Every time we reach such a point, it seems that the critical nature of the circumstances in themselves prevent that debate. With the prospect of decommissioning taking place at last and a question as to whether the institutions will continue or fall, it would be worthwhile to tease out the implications. I would welcome a decent debate on Northern Ireland next week.</P>
    <P>I call on the Leader of the House to have a debate on homelessness, particularly as we approach the winter. I was in the new homeless unit in Gardiner Street yesterday and noted the increase in the numbers of homeless people living rough on the street who have to be accommodated. In spite of the efforts that have been made, housing provision in general has deteriorated and for the homeless the provision is completely inadequate. It is time we brought the Minister to the House again to find out what is happening. Is it true that builders are simply sitting on parcels of land&mdash;</P>
    <Col N="386" />
    <Speaker pid="BrianMullooly" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I have given the Senator quite a good deal of latitude and the Leader of the House gave an assurance yesterday that there would be a debate on homelessness in this session.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeCostelloLAB" hpid="Mr. Costello Mr. Costello">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Costello</NameTxt>
      <P>Can we make sure that builders are not sitting on banks of land simply because there is a provision for 20% social and affordable housing?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WillieFarrell" hpid="Mr. Farrell Mr. Farrell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Farrell</NameTxt>
      <P>I asked some time ago and I ask again for a debate on Travellers. It is time we differentiated between Travellers and business people who travel. There are many small business people who cannot compete with those people who are travelling doing tarmacadam work on streets, landscaping, scrapping cars and so on. They leave the place in a mess after them. I am glad that it is starting to hit the headlines in Dublin now because we have had this for years in the country. Small businessmen cannot compete against them. The excuse made is that they are Travellers. Circus performers are travellers. They come into an area and leave the place spotless. They pay their taxes.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BrianMullooly" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>These are all points which can be made in the debate which you seek. We cannot pre-empt that debate on the Order of Business.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WillieFarrell" hpid="Mr. Farrell Mr. Farrell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Farrell</NameTxt>
      <P>I am pointing out its importance. In the west we have traditional Travellers who circulate around north Sligo, south Donegal, south Sligo and north Roscommon &ndash; they come around every so often. These communes come into the country and cause a mess. A small man was recently prosecuted and fined £50 for throwing chips to ducks on a lake, but these people throw cars, engines and scrap everywhere and seem to be immune from the law. All I want is a fair playing field so that the ordinary man living here must obey the law, as must everyone who comes here.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="HelenKeogh" hpid="Ms Keogh Ms Keogh">
      <NameTxt>Ms Keogh</NameTxt>
      <P>I ask the Leader to invite the Minister for Health and Children to come to the House and explain how he intends to eradicate child poverty. The Children's Rights Alliance maintains that at least one child in eight is living in poverty. We should all feel ashamed about this figure. This is a matter of great urgency as the budget approaches.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LabhrasOMurchu" hpid="Labhrás Ó Murchú Labhrás Ó Murchú">
      <NameTxt>Labhrás Ó Murchú</NameTxt>
      <P>There are some very encouraging messages emanating from both traditions in Northern Ireland. This is something we had all hoped for at this crisis point in the peace process and both Governments are cautiously optimistic. It is a very sensitive week in the process and the timing of any debate is important. I ask the Leader to consider an appropriate time.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="387" />
    <Speaker pid="PaddyBurke" hpid="Mr. Burke Mr. Burke">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Burke</NameTxt>
      <P>I support Senator Manning's call for a debate on the insurance industry. Several businesses are about to collapse due to the increased cost of insurance. The motor industry and young drivers also merit discussion. I also support Senator O'Toole's call for a debate on the housing industry. There is no confidence in the construction industry and a debate in relation to housing would be appropriate before the budget. Houses are not selling but rents have gone sky high. There are no fools out there who will build houses if they cannot sell them.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DrMauriceHayes" hpid="Dr. M. Hayes Dr. M. Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Dr. M. Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>The next week or two is an appropriate time for a debate on Northern Ireland. Things are delicate there at the moment and one is almost afraid of denunciation or encouragement for fear of tipping the balance, but the vibes are better than they have been for some time. A dramatic act of decommissioning or taking arms out of use, as promised, will be key. If this is available, Mr. Trimble should be prepared to guarantee the continuity of the institutions and not use them as a bargaining point.</P>
      <P>I ask the Leader of the House to convey to the Minister for Health and Children the need for straightforward, simple and rapid instructions to avoid the panic in relation to anthrax which seems to be gripping the country. We are giving a licence to every lunatic to do things. We should not wait for the encyclopaedic version of emergency instructions but should issue a small statement telling people not to panic, what to do and who to get in touch with, otherwise everybody with dandruff on his collar will have to be decontaminated. Yesterday at Independent Newspapers, of which I am a director, four unfortunate security men were stripped and sluiced and kept in an ambulance for an hour and a half while somebody decided which hospital they should go to or whether they should go to hospital at all.</P>
      <P>The Minister might issue instructions today to prevent this sort of incident and to reassure the public that we are not on the edge of a cataclysm.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryJackman" hpid="Mrs. Jackman Mrs. Jackman">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Jackman</NameTxt>
      <P>Could the Leader ask the Minister for the Environment and Local Government to come to the House to debate the role and responsibility of the Environmental Protection Agency? A particular type of waste has been left lying because the EPA stated that it could not go to landfill and could not be spread. Nobody seems to have responsibility for it. I wish to ask the Minister, because it has been ruled out of order on the Adjournment, who has the final say on a particular type of waste which may belong to another classification. If we are serious about caring for the environment, we should know where the responsibility lies.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrancisOBrien" hpid="Mr. O'Brien Mr. O'Brien">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Brien</NameTxt>
      <P>I support the call by Senator Manning for a debate on the increase in insurance rates for business people. Could the Leader include in that debate insurance for young drivers <Col N="388" /> and insurance for private and commercial motor vehicles? We have seen very steep increases in insurance costs over the last year. Young drivers find it very hard, especially in the climate that has existed since 11 September. This is all the more reason to have a debate on the question of motor insurance. Most young people need a car to take them to and from work and they cannot afford to pay their insurance.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PaulCoghlan" hpid="Mr. Coghlan Mr. Coghlan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Coghlan</NameTxt>
      <P>I support the call for a debate on insurance.</P>
      <P>There is huge concern regarding the slowdown in house building and there is evidence that land has been set aside by house builders in anticipation of more profitable periods. I heard Senator O'Toole's colourful phrase, &lsquo;Use it or lose it', but we may not go quite that far. The Minister must address this matter in the upcoming budget and I ask the Leader to convey this or to arrange for us to discuss the matter. Everything should be done to encourage house builders to get on with it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanOFearghaillFF" hpid="Mr. Ó Fearghail Mr. Ó Fearghail">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Ó Fearghail</NameTxt>
      <P>I support the call by Senator Farrell for a debate on the Traveller community. There are two aspects to this debate. Local Traveller consultative committees have made real and substantial progress on providing accommodation for indigenous Travellers. As Senator Farrell mentioned, we have just come to the end of the tourist season during which marauding traders traversed the entire country entering public and private property and demanding, and in many cases receiving, goodbye money. The Minister for Justice, Equality and Law Reform might come to the House to facilitate that debate and advise on whether legislation is needed to deal with this new phenomenon.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnConnor" hpid="Mr. Connor Mr. Connor">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Connor</NameTxt>
      <P>Two weeks ago I asked the Leader to provide time for a debate on the livestock industry, which, as a component of the whole agricultural industry, is facing bankruptcy. Our trade with Egypt has been reopened in a limited manner but that will have very little impact. It is a crisis. The Leader has always been accommodating on this issue in the past. I repeat my request for a debate next week in the presence of the Minister for Agriculture, Food and Rural Development.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TonyKett" hpid="Mr. Kett Mr. Kett">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Kett</NameTxt>
      <P>There was an excellent debate yesterday on special needs in education. I congratulate the Minister for Education and Science on the priority rating he has given to special needs schools following the review of the building programme that has taken place. It goes to show the commitment this Government has towards bettering the lives of people with a disability.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DonnieCassidyFF" hpid="Mr. Cassidy Mr. Cassidy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cassidy</NameTxt>
      <P>Yesterday I informed the House during the Order of Business that the Aer Lingus <Col N="389" /> Bill, 2000, was withdrawn from the Order Paper. It is easy to know that Senator O'Toole does not come under the Government Chief Whip because everyone on this side of the House knows that Senator Tom Fitzgerald is the Government Chief Whip.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeOToole" hpid="Mr. O'Toole Mr. O'Toole">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Toole</NameTxt>
      <P>We thought it was a new de Valera from the midlands.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DonnieCassidyFF" hpid="Mr. Cassidy Mr. Cassidy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cassidy</NameTxt>
      <P>He is a modern day de Valera from Dingle, a Kerryman like Senator O'Toole. We all know that many chiefs come from Dingle. Senators Manning, O'Toole, Costello, Ó Murchú and Hayes called for a debate on Northern Ireland. I will endeavour to have this take place next Thursday if the Minister is available. I fully agree with the sentiments that have been expressed on this subject and, like all the Members, I hope and pray that the progress will continue and something positive will happen before the debate next Thursday. It is never the wrong time to do the right thing. I would be very pleased to have a debate here where hopefully more progress will be reported.</P>
      <P>Senators Manning, Burke, O'Brien, Coghlan and many others expressed their alarm at insurance costs. Companies have been put in a position of having to trade in public buildings which do not have any public liability insurance. It is a disgraceful state of affairs that family businesses in particular cannot get a quote for public liability insurance following the collapse of a well-known insurance company in the past few weeks. There are very large establishments across the country each employing from 50 to 250 people with no public liability at present. Those families are in fear of being put out of business if a serious accident takes place on their premises. I am endeavouring to have a debate on that aspect of the insurance industry next Thursday for most of the day along with a debate on Northern Ireland.</P>
      <P>There was a call this morning for a debate on young drivers and the motor insurance industry. The motor insurance industry report is due in the early stages of next year and I give a commitment to the House that we will have an all day debate on this issue as soon as the report is published. I believe the lack of public liability insurance for business from hoteliers to all types of industry is of such seriousness that we will take statements for as long as is necessary with the Minister present next Thursday.</P>
      <P>Senator Manning called for a debate on binge drinking. I have no difficulty in this taking place, particularly in regard to the promotional activity among young people in educational institutions. No Oireachtas Member can stand over this and be proud of it. I appreciate the wealth of knowledge and the high esteem in which Senator Manning is held within that industry.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="390" />
    <Speaker pid="MairinQuill" hpid="Miss Quill Miss Quill">
      <NameTxt>Miss Quill</NameTxt>
      <P>Does the Leader mean the drinks industry?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MauriceManning" hpid="Mr. Manning Mr. Manning">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Manning</NameTxt>
      <P>The drinks industry?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DonnieCassidyFF" hpid="Mr. Cassidy Mr. Cassidy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cassidy</NameTxt>
      <P>No. The education industry. Senator Quill also came from that sector.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MauriceManning" hpid="Mr. Manning Mr. Manning">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Manning</NameTxt>
      <P>I am grateful for that clarification.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DonnieCassidyFF" hpid="Mr. Cassidy Mr. Cassidy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cassidy</NameTxt>
      <P>It is mentioned with a genuine concern and it is not to be taken in a jocular way because it is the most dangerous drug of all and costs the country an absolute fortune. Any drug that causes an excess of 7,000 admissions for first time referrals for alcohol disease has to be taken extremely seriously and I have no difficulty having time allocated for this debate.</P>
      <P>Senators O'Toole, Burke and Coghlan called for a debate on housing with the Minister for the Environment and Local Government present. Statements have been made here this morning regarding land banking and, in an effort to discourage this practice, anyone without planning permission on a development at a certain stage will have their planning permission invalidated on 31 December 2002.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeOToole" hpid="Mr. O'Toole Mr. O'Toole">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Toole</NameTxt>
      <P>That is just another year in Spain.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DonnieCassidyFF" hpid="Mr. Cassidy Mr. Cassidy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cassidy</NameTxt>
      <P>If someone owns land and does not do anything with it I do not know any law in the land that can change that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeOToole" hpid="Mr. O'Toole Mr. O'Toole">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Toole</NameTxt>
      <P>We can build social housing on it and they would soon wake up.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DonnieCassidyFF" hpid="Mr. Cassidy Mr. Cassidy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cassidy</NameTxt>
      <P>It is an individual's right. If people want to have their land for agricultural purposes they have the right to do that and no one can take it from them. We have to be realistic about this. I have a wealth of experience in dealing with people in my constituency who have this problem. I agree with most of what Senator O'Toole said. Rents increase if we do not have housing and that is happening at present.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeOToole" hpid="Mr. O'Toole Mr. O'Toole">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Toole</NameTxt>
      <P>There are developers who own large plots and tracts of land.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DonnieCassidyFF" hpid="Mr. Cassidy Mr. Cassidy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cassidy</NameTxt>
      <P>The Senator is speaking about the cities&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeOToole" hpid="Mr. O'Toole Mr. O'Toole">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Toole</NameTxt>
      <P>No.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DonnieCassidyFF" hpid="Mr. Cassidy Mr. Cassidy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cassidy</NameTxt>
      <P>&mdash;but there is no housing development and a decreasing population in larger towns and the rural part of Ireland where I come from.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Yesterday we welcomed the initiative of the Minister of State at the Department of Agriculture, Food and Rural Development, Deputy Ó Cuív, to do something for the declining parts of the country. There are haves in one part of the country and have nots in another, so we have to <Col N="391" /> look at it in a broad perspective. I have no difficulty facilitating a debate on this matter and to making a contribution on it myself.</P>
    <P>Senators O'Toole and Costello spoke about No. 2 and I hope to bring this back to the House. I take exception to Senator Costello's remark that our business is conducted in a sloppy way. I take seriously the request of Senators, particularly the leaders of the groups, when they make their requests on the Order of Business but I cannot condone a leader of a group whose party does not come to the House when the subject requested is being debated. I generally make provision for such requests one or two weeks after they have been made.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JoeCostelloLAB" hpid="Mr. Costello Mr. Costello">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Costello</NameTxt>
      <P>The Leader should withdraw that remark. The Labour Party group is in this House on a regular basis and we were here yesterday when I was allocated a spokesman's time slot&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BrianMullooly" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>We cannot enter into a debate on this matter.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeCostelloLAB" hpid="Mr. Costello Mr. Costello">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Costello</NameTxt>
      <P>&mdash;but I was not allowed to have it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DonnieCassidyFF" hpid="Mr. Cassidy Mr. Cassidy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cassidy</NameTxt>
      <P>I was indicating&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeCostelloLAB" hpid="Mr. Costello Mr. Costello">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Costello</NameTxt>
      <P>The manner in which the Leader of the House&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BrianMullooly" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator Costello, please allow the Leader his right to reply.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeCostelloLAB" hpid="Mr. Costello Mr. Costello">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Costello</NameTxt>
      <P>&mdash;allocated business yesterday ruled my party out of being able to take a proper slot.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DonnieCassidyFF" hpid="Mr. Cassidy Mr. Cassidy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cassidy</NameTxt>
      <P>Is clarification needed for the three Labour Party Senators out of 60 Members? They have been given group status in the House and on the Order of Business two weeks ago they called for something but when the time came for it to be discussed not one of the three was present. I am reluctant to say this but I have listened to their remarks over the last number of months and this morning I wish to set the record straight.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeCostelloLAB" hpid="Mr. Costello Mr. Costello">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Costello</NameTxt>
      <P>I object to the Leader's remarks.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DonnieCassidyFF" hpid="Mr. Cassidy Mr. Cassidy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cassidy</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator Costello also called for a debate on homelessness and I will certainly allocate time for that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeCostelloLAB" hpid="Mr. Costello Mr. Costello">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Costello</NameTxt>
      <P>The Leader has been casting aspersions on the Labour group. We are in this House proportionately more than any other group and we contribute to every debate and&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BrianMullooly" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>You have made your point, Senator Costello. Please allow the Leader of the House to reply without interruption.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="392" />
    <Speaker pid="JoeCostelloLAB" hpid="Mr. Costello Mr. Costello">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Costello</NameTxt>
      <P>&mdash;the Leader of the House conducted the debate yesterday in such a manner that we were unable to contribute because we did not get time to take our slot. For the Leader of the House to attack the Labour group is outrageous.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BrianMullooly" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator Costello, please resume your seat.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeCostelloLAB" hpid="Mr. Costello Mr. Costello">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Costello</NameTxt>
      <P>What I said on the Order of Business today was in regard&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DonnieCassidyFF" hpid="Mr. Cassidy Mr. Cassidy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cassidy</NameTxt>
      <P>It is very unusual for any Leader to be interrupted.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeCostelloLAB" hpid="Mr. Costello Mr. Costello">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Costello</NameTxt>
      <P>&mdash;to the two motions. I said I was dissatisfied with the manner in which the Leader was organising the motions that were being presented to us. The Leader has used the opportunity to cast aspersions on the Labour group and should withdraw his remarks.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BrianMullooly" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>The Leader is replying. The matter raised can be debated at CCP.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeCostelloLAB" hpid="Mr. Costello Mr. Costello">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Costello</NameTxt>
      <P>Good.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DonnieCassidyFF" hpid="Mr. Cassidy Mr. Cassidy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cassidy</NameTxt>
      <P>What I have said is a matter of fact and I have stood here, sat here and listened to Senator Costello preaching.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeCostelloLAB" hpid="Mr. Costello Mr. Costello">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Costello</NameTxt>
      <P>That is not accurate.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BrianMullooly" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>We cannot have&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeCostelloLAB" hpid="Mr. Costello Mr. Costello">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Costello</NameTxt>
      <P>The Leader of the House is not stating an accurate fact. It is totally inaccurate.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DonnieCassidyFF" hpid="Mr. Cassidy Mr. Cassidy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cassidy</NameTxt>
      <P>On a motion you called for two week ago&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeCostelloLAB" hpid="Mr. Costello Mr. Costello">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Costello</NameTxt>
      <P>We were here last night&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BrianMullooly" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>The Leader should address his reply through the Chair and should be allowed to reply, but he should not invite interruptions.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DonnieCassidyFF" hpid="Mr. Cassidy Mr. Cassidy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cassidy</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator Costello called for a debate on homelessness.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeCostelloLAB" hpid="Mr. Costello Mr. Costello">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Costello</NameTxt>
      <P>It was only thanks to the generosity of Senator Farrell that I was allowed to speak.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BrianMullooly" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>The Leader should not invite interruptions.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DonnieCassidyFF" hpid="Mr. Cassidy Mr. Cassidy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cassidy</NameTxt>
      <P>I have no difficulty in allowing time for such a debate to take place.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeCostelloLAB" hpid="Mr. Costello Mr. Costello">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Costello</NameTxt>
      <P>Thank you.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DonnieCassidyFF" hpid="Mr. Cassidy Mr. Cassidy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cassidy</NameTxt>
      <P>As you have stated, a Chathaoirligh, this was called for by Senator Ridge yesterday. I have no difficulty in setting time aside for such a debate. If Senator Costello is genuinely concerned about this, I suggest he include it in <Col N="393" /> Labour Private Members' time for next week, otherwise I will not be able to take it until after the Hallowe'en recess.</P>
      <P>Senators Farrell and Ó Fearghail called for a debate on Travellers, including those who are in business. I have no problem in setting time for such a debate. Senator Keogh called for a debate on child poverty, with the Minister for Health and Children present. I have no problem in allowing time for this debate. Senator Hayes called for the Minister for Health and Children to make an immediate statement on the anthrax problem and the various statements and misstatements that are circulating. I shall convey the Senator's views to the Minister after the Order of Business this morning.</P>
      <P>Senator Jackman called on the Minister for the Environment and Local Government to make a statement or come to the House to discuss the future of the Environmental Protection Agency. This is a good idea and perhaps this can happen in the coming weeks. Senator Connor called for an immediate debate on the livestock industry. As the Senator has said, I have always acceded to calls for debates on agriculture. They are the best attended and a greater number of Senators contribute to debate on agriculture. I shall certainly have time set aside for such a debate. I shall convey Senator Kett's vote of congratulations to the Minister for Education and Science.</P>
      <P>Order of Business agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Freedom of Information Act, 1997 (Prescribed" RHead="Bodies) (No. 4) Regulations, 2001: Motion">
    <Title>Freedom of Information Act, 1997 (Prescribed Bodies) (No. 4) Regulations, 2001: Motion.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="DonnieCassidyFF" hpid="Mr. Cassidy Mr. Cassidy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cassidy</NameTxt>
      <P>I move:</P>
      <P>That Seanad Éireann approves the following Regulations in draft:</P>
      <P>Freedom of Information Act, 1997 (Prescribed Bodies) (No. 4) Regulations, 2001,</P>
      <P>a copy of which was laid in draft before Seanad Éireann on 10 July 2001.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Asylum Applications:" RHead="Motion">
    <Title>Asylum Applications: Motion.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="DonnieCassidyFF" hpid="Mr. Cassidy Mr. Cassidy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cassidy</NameTxt>
      <P>I move:</P>
      <P>That the proposal that Seanad Éireann approves the exercise by the State of the option, provided by Article 3 of the fourth Protocol set out in the Treaty of Amsterdam, to notify the President of the Council that it wishes to take part in the adoption and application of the following proposed measure:</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>a proposal for a Council Regulation establishing the criteria and mechanisms for determining the Member State responsible for examining an asylum application lodged <Col N="394" /> in one of the Member States by a third country national,</P>
    <P>copy of which proposed measure was laid before Seanad Éireann on 10 October 2001, be referred to the Joint Committee on Justice, Equality, Defence and Women's Rights, in accordance with paragraph (1)<i>(a)</i>(iv) of the Orders of Reference of that committee, which shall, not later than 25 October 2001, send a message to the Seanad in the manner prescribed in Standing Order 67, and Standing Order 69(2) shall accordingly apply.</P>
    <P>Question put and declared carried.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Law of the Sea (Repression of Piracy)" RHead="Bill, 2001: Report and Final Stages">
    <Title>Law of the Sea (Repression of Piracy) Bill, 2001: Report and Final Stages.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="BrianMullooly" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I remind Senators that a Senator may speak only once on Report Stage except the proposer of an amendment who may reply to the discussion on the amendment. On Report Stage each amendment must be seconded.</P>
      <P>Government amendment No. 1:</P>
      <P>In page 4, line 11, to delete &ldquo;(other than a boat propelled by oars)&rdquo;.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="HughByrne" hpid="Mr. Byrne Mr. Byrne">
      <NameTxt>Minister of State at the Department of the Marine and Natural Resources (Mr. Byrne)</NameTxt>
      <P>During the debate last week the definition of &ldquo;ship&rdquo; was discussed. The Minister has decided that the deletion of &ldquo;other than a boat propelled by oars&rdquo; would improve the Bill. It will widen the definition of the section which now includes all boats, whether motorised vessels or manually propelled. I understand Senator Costello and others raised this issue. We are happy to propose the amendment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeCostelloLAB" hpid="Mr. Costello Mr. Costello">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Costello</NameTxt>
      <P>I thank the Minister of State for accepting the amendment. It improves the definition being discussed. I raised one other element in terms of the definition of a ship which is a submarine and asked whether it comes within the description. For example, section 3(1)(a) which deals with piracy refers to &ldquo;. . .  crew or passengers on board a private ship and directed against another ship. . . &rdquo;.  Does an underwater vessel come under the definition? I accept the amendment and agree it is an improvement, but would &ldquo;submarine&rdquo; come within the definition if there was a hostile submarine that could have the same effect as a boat or a ship that is on the water?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="HughByrne" hpid="Mr. Byrne Mr. Byrne">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Byrne</NameTxt>
      <P>A State ship is not included. I know where Senator Costello is coming from because in the area where I live there was great submarine activity. It has abated somewhat now but they are still there. A State ship is not included.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Amendment agreed to.<Col N="395" /></P>
    <Speaker pid="BrianMullooly" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>We come to Government amendment No. 2. Amendment No. 3 is an alternative and both may be discussed together by agreement.</P>
      <P>Government amendment No. 2:</P>
      <P>In page 5, to delete lines 19 and 20, and substitute the following:</P>
      <P>&ldquo;(ii)&nbsp;use of firearms or other weapons or anything capable of being used to endanger life or disable persons by such members or passengers,&rdquo;.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="HughByrne" hpid="Mr. Byrne Mr. Byrne">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Byrne</NameTxt>
      <P>This issue was debated at length on Thursday last. The Senators and the Minister agreed that a wording needed to be found which would ensure that any agents, objects or chemicals be covered which could possibly be used to endanger life or disable persons. The amendment proposed covers any possible article, tablet, chemical etc.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryHenry" hpid="Dr. Henry Dr. Henry">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Henry</NameTxt>
      <P>I think last week the Minister, Deputy Fahey, thought I was picky about this issue. I am glad to see the Government amendment but I would prefer my amendment. The Minister accused me at one stage of playing games, which I certainly was not. I had a similar type of debate with the Minister on 13 June 2000 on the Merchant Shipping (Investigation of Marine Casualties) Bill. In this House we are supposed to have vocational representation and I always felt that the least we could do was make some use of our experience. It was stated that if it was suspected that the person in charge of the vessel which had been involved in an accident was under the influence of drink or drugs, specimens could be taken from the person. I asked that that be changed to specimens of blood or urine, and I did not ask that for my own entertainment. I asked it because that is the usual method in forensic medicine of acquiring specimens.</P>
      <P>I spent some time asking the Minister why he wanted such a broad definition of just specimens and he said it was because the Attorney General wanted it. I asked for descriptions of the conditions the Attorney General felt might be necessary to have such a broad definition and if he would be seeking liver biopsies. We got to such a state that another Senator from the Government side suggested we might want to take brain specimens in case the person had a brain tumour. Let me assure the House that this is not how a diagnosis is made of a brain tumour. That is why I tabled my amendment which was defeated.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Within a short time a forensic pathologist asked why had I allowed this to happen because under the legislation someone accused of taking drink or drugs could perhaps provide toe nail clippings or some such specimen. I did not query the position last week for entertainment. Therefore, I tabled the amendment on Committee Stage. I wish to make it clear to the Minister of <Col N="396" /> State that I had good reason for tabling the amendment.</P>
    <P>The Government amendment looks fine and I am sure a great deal of care and thought went into wording it. However, I would prefer my amendment which is taken directly from the Firearms and Offensive Weapons Act, 1990, with which there has been no problem for 11 years. It is a good idea to follow legislation which has been tried and tested. There is very little difference between the amendments. Section 9(4)(<i>a</i>) of the Firearms and Offensive Weapons Act reads, &ldquo;any flick-knife, or&rdquo; (<i>b</i>) &ldquo;any other article whatsoever made or adapted for use for causing injury to or incapacitating a person&rdquo;. Given that such a useful phrase has been used for 11 years and has caused no problem, I find it difficult to understand why another phrase, which is very similar but not the same, is being inserted. I would like the Minister of State to accept my amendment to have consistency in the legislation.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JoeCostelloLAB" hpid="Mr. Costello Mr. Costello">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Costello</NameTxt>
      <P>I second Senator Henry's amendment. She makes a logical point that the definition taken from the Firearms and Offensive Weapons Act, 1990, which has stood the test of time, should be accepted. The Government amendment reads, &ldquo;or other weapons or anything capable of being used to endanger life. . . &rdquo;.  Two different words are used here, one of which is to endanger life or disable, whereas Senator Henry's amendment reads, &ldquo;adapted for use for causing injury. . . &rdquo;.  One can cause injury without endangering life. It could be a threat or one could incapacitate someone. Perhaps both are better expressions. The phrase &ldquo;endanger life&rdquo; is not as strong. The phrase &ldquo;causing injury&rdquo; is the threat of what the weapon could do. The phrase &ldquo;incapacitate a person&rdquo; is probably a better phrase than &ldquo;disable a person&rdquo;. The choice of verbs is probably better in Senator Henry's definition.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="HughByrne" hpid="Mr. Byrne Mr. Byrne">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Byrne</NameTxt>
      <P>I am happy with the amendment the Government proposes because it incorporates everything Senator Henry has in mind. I take this opportunity of complimenting her, and indeed all Senators, because it is in our interest to put through this House the best legislation possible. Suggestions made by Senators must be taken into consideration and I would like to think we have done that.</P>
      <P>There is very little difference between the amendments. Given a small element of bias, I believe my amendment may be a little stronger than Senator Henry's amendment. She is certainly going in the same direction and I take on board everything she says. However, I believe my amendment is strong enough and incorporates her concerns. It is probably because she raised the issue that we agreed to table this amendment. I believe it will make for better legislation, for which I thank her.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryHenry" hpid="Dr. Henry Dr. Henry">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Henry</NameTxt>
      <P>Forgive me for saying so but the Government has started making up meanings of <Col N="397" /> words and descriptions, which I find very foolish. That is why it would be better to include something which has worked satisfactorily for the past 11 years. This legislation has been used and has anyone heard of its being challenged? The word &ldquo;incapacitating&rdquo; is better. The Minister of State says there is very little difference between the amendments. If someone wants to refer back to the ranch perhaps it will be considered all right to accept this wording. I am not trying to be difficult but, given that there have been no court challenges to the wording which has existed for 11 years, why not take that wording?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>While I am sure a lot of work and care went into making up the wording, perhaps I should have phoned the Minister of State's Department and said that as we already have perfectly satisfactory wording on the Statute Book why not use that. However, following the bashing I got last week, I was reluctant to contact the Minister, <Col N="398" /> Deputy Fahey. Of course, I could have contacted his officials who were perfectly reasonable and charming. I believe my amendment, which is copied, is better. I thank the staff of the House for helping me because when people found out what I wanted everyone was most helpful. If something has worked it is a good idea to try to stick with that formula.</P>
    <Speaker pid="HughByrne" hpid="Mr. Byrne Mr. Byrne">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Byrne</NameTxt>
      <P>The Senator has made a very strong case. It is the Government's job to enact the best legislation possible. I understand what the Senator is saying, which was reiterated by Senator Costello, in regard to injury rather than endangering lives or disabling a person. Given that we received advice from the Attorney General, perhaps the Senator will accept that we will give the matter further consideration in the Dáil. However, I cannot withdraw the amendment.</P>
      <P>Amendment put.</P>
      <P>Tá</P>
      <P>
      </P>
    </Speaker>
    <table pgwide="1">
      <tgroup cols="2">
        <colspec colname="1" colnum="1" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <colspec colname="2" colnum="2" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry rowsep="1">Bonner, Enda.<br />Cregan, John.<br />Farrell, Willie.<br />Fitzgerald, Tom.<br />Fitzpatrick, Dermot.<br />Gibbons, Jim.<br />Glynn, Camillus.<br />Kett, Tony.</entry>
            <entry rowsep="1">Kiely, Rory.<br />Leonard, Ann.<br />Lydon, Don.<br />Mooney, Paschal.<br />O'Brien, Francis.<br />Ó Fearghail, Seán.<br />Ó Murchú, Labhrás.<br />Quill, Máirín.</entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
    <P Just="Center">Níl</P>
    <table pgwide="1">
      <tgroup cols="2">
        <colspec colname="1" colnum="1" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <colspec colname="2" colnum="2" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry rowsep="1">Burke, Paddy.<br />Caffrey, Ernie.<br />Coghlan, Paul.<br />Cosgrave, Liam T.<br />Costello, Joe.<br />Cregan, Denis (Dino).</entry>
            <entry rowsep="1">Henry, Mary.<br />Jackman, Mary.<br />Keogh, Helen.<br />Manning, Maurice.<br />O'Toole, Joe.<br />Ross, Shane.</entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
    <P Just="Center">Tellers: Tá, Senators T. Fitzgerald and Gibbons; Níl, Senators Costello and Henry.</P>
    <P>Amendment declared carried.</P>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Amendment No. 3 is in the name of Senator Henry. As amendment No. 2 has been accepted, that amendment cannot be moved. Amendment No. 4 is in the name of Senator Costello. Amendment No. 5 is related so the proposal is that we discuss amendments Nos. 4 and 5 together, by agreement.</P>
      <P>Amendment No. 3 not moved.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeCostelloLAB" hpid="Mr. Costello Mr. Costello">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Costello</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 4:</P>
      <P>In page 6, lines 1 and 2, to delete &ldquo;&euro;3,000 (£2,362.69)&rdquo; and substitute &ldquo;&euro;10,000 (£7,875.64)&rdquo;.</P>
      <P>These two amendments relate to the considerable discussion that took place here on Committee Stage when it was expressed on all sides of the House that some change in relation to the fines and prison sentence provided for in the legislation would be desirable.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>As I recollect, the Minister made the point that it was the Attorney General's function to bring all cases on indictment to a Circuit Court. It would appear that the appropriate place for as many cases as possible to be dealt with would be in the lower courts, the courts of summary jurisdiction, rather than on indictment to the higher courts. It would save the Exchequer expensive legal charges and matters could be dealt with more expeditiously. It was made clear that one had to specify a fine and that the Attorney General had agreed that the fine should be &euro;3,000. I am not sure how infallible the Attorney General's discretion is in this matter, but if the Attorney General is the person who has the sole jurisdiction it is not inappropriate to suggest a different minimum or maximum fine and a different maximum penalty. I understand the Attorney General has come up with this figure of &euro;3,000. This is the first time it has appeared. I have no <Col N="399" /> idea what criteria he used to come up with it. It is £2,362.69, so I am sure he had some difficulty in putting that together.</P>
    <P>This is probably one of the last occasions we will have both the euro and the punt specified in a Bill, but &euro;3,000 is less than £2,500. This legislation deals with serious offences including boarding a ship, mutiny, seizure of property, ramming, etc. They are all serious offences committed either on the high seas or in inland waters and I would have thought the Attorney General would have been intent on allowing the greatest flexibility possible in terms of the summary courts dealing with cases that come before them. From that point of view, an amount considerably in excess of &euro;3,000, perhaps &euro;10,000, and doubling the prison sentence from six months to 12 months would be more appropriate. A prison sentence of 12 months would be appropriate because that is the maximum sentence that can be imposed in the District Court for a single offence. If there is more than one offence, the District Court can impose a sentence of two years. We should accept the advice of the Attorney General in this matter and if this House or the other House is of the view that the District Court is the appropriate court to deal with as large a number of offences as possible, for the variety of reasons I have mentioned in terms of cost, expediency and time, why not adjust the fine and the prison penalty to accommodate that?</P>
    <Speaker pid="MaryHenry" hpid="Dr. Henry Dr. Henry">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Henry</NameTxt>
      <P>I second the amendment. Like Senator Costello, I also spoke last week in favour of trying to deal with as many cases as possible in the District Court because the costs to the State are much lower in that court but we ran into a degree of misunderstanding with the Minister because he said that in 20 years in politics he had rarely experienced the attitude he had witnessed that day, either in the Dáil or the Seanad, but he did state:</P>
      <P>Every week of the year the Attorney General brings prosecutions in the fishing industry. They are all indictable offences brought before the Circuit Court for much higher levels of fine. There is no problem here. I, therefore, fail to understand the reason we are wasting time.</P>
      <P>He later stated:</P>
      <P>. . .  there is no need to worry that the fine for a summary offence is confined to &euro;3,000. Every day in this jurisdiction, under fishery offences, the Attorney General brings fishing boats into harbour. They are indictable offences brought to the Circuit Court.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The confusion, therefore, did not necessarily arise on these benches but from what the Minister said to us. I tried to make myself as clear as possible. I said later that I was dismayed that the Attorney General always takes cases to the Circuit Court, <Col N="400" /> which costs so much more than the District Court. There may have been a level of misunderstanding, but our basic concern was to ensure that as many cases as possible should be brought to the District Court but also that the fine be realistic. Even the Minister agreed that a fine of &euro;3,000 seems low in this day and age. It is not mandatory to enforce a higher fine, a lower one could be imposed. The amendment seeks to provide for a more realistic upper level.</P>
    <Speaker pid="ErnieCaffrey" hpid="Mr. Caffrey Mr. Caffrey">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Caffrey</NameTxt>
      <P>I proposed a similar amendment on Committee Stage. It sought to remove summary jurisdiction offences from the legislation but, given that there should be a mechanism for dealing with what would be regarded as minor offences, I accepted it would be inappropriate to completely remove this provision. The amendment creates an indictable offence but I understand the maximum fine a District Court can impose is that provided for in the legislation, so if it was to be accepted, primary legislation would have to be amended. However, I support amendment No. 5, which seeks to increase the maximum imprisonment from six to 12 months. Had my amendment been accepted on Committee Stage, provision for a summary conviction would be removed from the legislation.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="HughByrne" hpid="Mr. Byrne Mr. Byrne">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Byrne</NameTxt>
      <P>The Bill provides for the following penalties for piracy offences: on summary conviction a a maximum fine of &euro;3,000, or £2,362.69, and-or up to six months imprisonment, or on conviction on indictment, an unlimited maximum fine and-or imprisonment for terms not exceeding 20 years. Penalties for obstruction, failure to comply with a reasonable requirement of, or giving false information to, an authorised officer are, on summary conviction, a maximum of &euro;3,000 and-or up to three months imprisonment and on conviction on indictment, a maximum fine of &euro;6,000, or £4,725.38, and-or up to two years imprisonment.</P>
      <P>It will be open to the Attorney General to decide in each case whether it will be taken to the District Court or there should be an indictment, with the commensurate higher penalties. My Department has received further advice from the Office of the Attorney General. Article 38.2 of the Constitution provides that minor offences may be tried by courts of summary jurisdiction. Severity of punishment is the principle criterion for determining whether an offence is minor. Accordingly, a penalty for an offence that is to be dealt with under summary conviction must not be too severe, otherwise the offence could not be designated as a minor category one and could not be dealt with by the District Court.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>From time to time the Attorney General gives directions as to what he considers to be the maximum summary fine. That may be provided for in legislation. The Office of the Parliamentary <Col N="401" /> Counsel to the Government and Departments must observe these limits in drafting legislation. The current maximum in new legislation, such as this, is &euro;3,000. Previously, the maximum was £1,500. Consequently, I do not propose to accept the amendment.</P>
    <P>Amendment No. 5 proposes to raise the maximum prison penalty upon summary conviction to 12 months. Our advice is that, in general, six months should be the maximum. This would be more in line with the maximum fine of &euro;3,000, therefore, I do not propose to accept the amendment.</P>
    <P>Senator Costello referred to minor versus indictable offences. The Attorney General will make decisions on this aspect. If the offence is serious it will be tried in a higher court where the appropriate maximum penalties would apply. The Office of the Attorney General wrote to my Department on this matter and stated:</P>
    <P>As you know, the maximum monetary penalty on summary convictions was set at £1,500 by this office in 1994. Having regard to the need to provide a rounded figure in euro and taking account of the 18% inflation between autumn 1994 and the present and the view of this office that the figure of £1,500 in 1994 as the maximum summary fine was on the cautious side, the Attorney General is of the view that &euro;3,000 is not excessive as the appropriate figure as a maximum penalty for a summary offence.</P>
    <P>Subject to the above advice it is a matter for the Departments to consider the appropriate maximum monetary penalty for summary offences in each individual case.</P>
    <P>That is within the &euro;3,000 parameter.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JoeCostelloLAB" hpid="Mr. Costello Mr. Costello">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Costello</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister of State relies on the advice of the Attorney General as though he is infallible in determining how the legislation operates. The result of this will be that all cases will be dealt with by way of indictment, as has been the case heretofore. We are concerned with relatively serious offences here, including ramming of ships, cutting fishing gear and any act of piracy. In most cases indictment is the likely end result but surely our function as legislators is to seek to ensure that legislation operates as effectively as possible and that where a court of summary jurisdiction can function, the penalties provided should be flexible enough to enable it to do so.</P>
      <P>Given the penalty of a fine of &euro;3,000 and-or six months imprisonment, it will be interesting to ascertain in a couple of years the number of cases that were tried in the District and Circuit Courts. It is likely that very few will be tried in the District Court because of the penalties to be applied. They may be dealt with there at first but not in the final instance.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="402" />I accept that the Attorney General must operate under constitutional constraint and that cases must be dealt with in terms of the severity of penalty to be applied. These principles should be taken into consideration when devising penalties, which is what these amendments seek to do. As it is, these are not severe penalties in terms of the offence, which should be the case.</P>
    <P>I accept the Attorney General has raised the fine of £1,500 to approximately £2,500, which appears to be reasonable. However, these amendments are concerned with maximum amounts which are still small, indeed meaningless, by comparison with the returns that can be made by fishing pirates in what is a multi-billion pound industry. I am not happy about it. Could the Minister look at it again, with the Attorney General, to see what could be done to improve things or is the Attorney General adamant on this matter? This is the first time in six or seven years that the fine has been changed. The last time was in 1994 when it was £1,500. I would appreciate a reply from the Minister.</P>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>This is Report Stage and the Senator has exercised his right of reply. I should put the question now, but if the Minister of State wishes to make a point he may.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="HughByrne" hpid="Mr. Byrne Mr. Byrne">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Byrne</NameTxt>
      <P>It is not proposed that this Bill will redefine what constitutes a minor offence or an indictable one. That is not the reason the Bill came into being. I accept that the hearts of the three Opposition Senators here are in the right place, but we need to accept that, as natural justice suggests, a minor offence is simply that and should be dealt with in a District Court. An indictable offence should be tried in a more senior court. That is absolutely essential. As the Senators make their case strongly and well, though I will not accept the amendment, I am prepared to increase the period of time referred to from six months to 12 months.</P>
      <P>Amendment, by leave, withdrawn.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeCostelloLAB" hpid="Mr. Costello Mr. Costello">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Costello</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 5:</P>
      <P>In page 6, lines 2 and 3, to delete &ldquo;6 months&rdquo; and substitute &ldquo;1 year&rdquo;.</P>
      <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
      <P>Bill, as amended, received for final consideration.</P>
      <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That the Bill do now pass.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="HughByrne" hpid="Mr. Byrne Mr. Byrne">
      <NameTxt>Minister of State at the Department of the Marine and Natural Resources (Mr. Byrne)</NameTxt>
      <P>I thank the Senators for their contributions. It is pleasant that this Bill was initiated in this House. Whatever the fireworks of last week, when more people become involved and take sufficient interest, it makes for better legislation. The Senators are here and they are sufficiently <Col N="403" /> interested. Together our efforts have made for a better Bill. I am prepared to accept that not I, the Minister or anyone else on the Government side has a monopoly on knowledge or right. We are prepared to accept things that are proposed to us when they are better. For that reason I thank Senators.</P>
      <P>There is, as everyone here accepts, a need to protect the lives and livelihood of fishermen pursuing their legitimate interests in our offshore area. This Bill will enable us to do that. Living, as I do, on the Hook Peninsula in County Wexford I recall the ramming of the <i>Orchidee</i> by the <i>Agena,</i> a French vessel. Two fishermen who lived in my constituency were lost. I was heavily involved in events subsequently because I live among fishermen and it was very frustrating not to have a mechanism whereby the incident could be investigated. Having followed it up for a long time we eventually had the case tried in the French courts. It was cumbersome and the result was an indictment of the crew of the <i>Agena</i> but, unfortunately, the courts left it at that and no penalty was imposed.</P>
      <P>Due to that and other incidents we are now on the road to putting that mechanism in place. This is a good day's work for the Seanad, it is a good day's work for the Oireachtas and it is a good day's work for the country. Mar sin, ba mhaith liom mo bhuíochas a ghabháil leis na Seanadóirí go léir.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ErnieCaffrey" hpid="Mr. Caffrey Mr. Caffrey">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Caffrey</NameTxt>
      <P>I thank the Minister of State and the Minister for the Marine and Natural Resources for dealing with this relatively small but important Bill. A considerable amount of time &ndash; over two days &ndash; was spent deservedly on it. We began with some misconceptions as to the purpose of the Bill. In light of what happened on 11 September, all legislation of this nature seems to suggest efforts to deal with acts of terrorism. This Bill was not designed to do that and we have been reassured that legislation is coming through that will address the issues we raised the last day in relation to that sort of activity and the potential for major outrages at sea. Many Senators dealt with the potential for disaster that exists, which is especially obvious when we think of Sellafield and the reprocessing facility that has been commissioned there.</P>
      <P>When we got down to the nitty gritty of the Bill and discovered its real purpose we eliminated many superficial issues and dealt with its reality. I am glad the Minister saw fit to accept many of our amendments and I thank him for that. It is legislation that will help the seafaring community and relieve them of many of the worries they have had over the years due to harassment and other acts on the sea.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryHenry" hpid="Dr. Henry Dr. Henry">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Henry</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister of State has just given a vivid example of why legislation like this is needed. I do not live anywhere near the sea, I only live near a canal, but this Bill is very <Col N="404" /> important and was badly needed. It is good that it was initiated in this House. It is important that it is well recognised that this House is not, and never should be, a rubber stamp. We are supposed to use our collective and individual wits when looking at legislation. I thank the Minister of State for the kind words he said about us today.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeCostelloLAB" hpid="Mr. Costello Mr. Costello">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Costello</NameTxt>
      <P>I would like to be associated with the remarks that have been made and I thank the Minister of State for the manner in which he has dealt with us today. It has certainly been refreshing considering the rather rough debate which took place on the previous occasion.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="HughByrne" hpid="Mr. Byrne Mr. Byrne">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Byrne</NameTxt>
      <P>I missed a lot.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeCostelloLAB" hpid="Mr. Costello Mr. Costello">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Costello</NameTxt>
      <P>It was quite exciting, but there were some misunderstandings. The main problem on the last occasion was that we tried to do too much in one day. We attempted to take all Stages in one sitting and, of course, when that is attempted it does not give a proper opportunity for reflection. Points raised on Second Stage and on Committee Stage are not teased out properly and it was worthwhile to postpone our final deliberations until today. I am glad the Minister of State has accepted the amendments he has. Perhaps he would look again, as he indicated, at Senator Henry's amendment so that its wording might be incorporated somehow into the final text.</P>
      <P>I raised the issue of submarines and it is one that may not have been looked at sufficiently. It could arise in terms of the difficulty of suppressing piracy at sea. It could be incorporated during the Dáil debate. I thank the Minister of State and his staff for their assistance.</P>
      <P>
      </P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EndaBonner" hpid="Mr. Bonner Mr. Bonner">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Bonner</NameTxt>
      <P>I too congratulate the Minister on bringing the Bill to Report and Final Stages. As usual, he dealt with matters in a practical and sensible way. I can see why he could not give way to Senator Costello regarding amendment No. 4, which sought to increase the fine from &euro;3,000 to &euro;10,000. I doubt the severity of the increase. I accept that the difference between &euro;6,000 and &euro;12,000 would have more major consequences for somebody.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeCostelloLAB" hpid="Mr. Costello Mr. Costello">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Costello</NameTxt>
      <P>There is sufficient severity there.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EndaBonner" hpid="Mr. Bonner Mr. Bonner">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Bonner</NameTxt>
      <P>I am questioning how the Senator arrived at a figure of &euro;10,000 given that he accused the Office of the Attorney General of being off the rails regarding the figure of &euro;3,000. I appreciate that the Minister has given Senator Henry a commitment that he may accept amendment No. 3 in the other House.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Like the Minister, I was not here on the last day we dealt with the Bill, so I obviously missed quite a bit. I congratulate the Minister, Deputy Fahey, and the Senator who deputised for me, <Col N="405" /> Senator Tom Fitzgerald. He feels that this Bill is primarily for the Dingle fishermen and the fishermen of the south-west coast. It is known that they have serious difficulties in that region, particularly with the Spanish trawlers. The Minister and his officials made a great effort to bring this very important Bill to the House, which has significant consequences for our fishermen.</P>
    <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="State of the Economy:" RHead="Statements">
    <Title>State of the Economy: Statements.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="CharlieMcCreevy" hpid="Mr. McCreevy Mr. McCreevy">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Finance (Mr. McCreevy)</NameTxt>
      <P>The brutality and wickedness of the terrorist attacks in the United States on 11 September were an affront to humanity. These attacks were such a human tragedy that it may seem inappropriate to discuss their economic implications. However, there is no denying that the economic impact of these events will be felt all over the world.</P>
      <P>It is clear that even before the terrorist attacks, the major economies of the world &ndash; those in the US, the EU and Japan &ndash; had already experienced a sharp downturn in activity. The IMF in August had forecast a slowing of world GDP growth to 2.6 % this year. However, even this forecast is now thought to be overly optimistic. Commentators have remarked that this was the first time since 1982 that all three of the major economic areas were underperforming at the same time.</P>
      <P>As far as the US economy is concerned, prior to the attacks of 11 September, it had already slowed down significantly. In August, the IMF had forecast a GDP growth rate for the US of 1.3% this year. There is no doubt that the adverse impact on the US economy of the attacks will be substantial in the future.</P>
      <P>The exact extent and duration of the economic impact on the US will very much depend on the ongoing military response and whether this leads to further terrorist activity. It will also depend on the reaction of consumer confidence in the US to these unfolding events. The latest figures from the US show a continued fall in consumer confidence. The US is therefore likely to experience recession for the remainder of this year and a recovery is now thought to be unlikely before mid-2002, at the earliest.</P>
      <P>Oil prices will also play a very important role in the world economic outlook. It is true that Saudi Arabia and Kuwait have given assurances that any disruption to oil supplies will be neutralised. However, if oil prices were to rise sharply, it would have a negative impact not just on the US economy, but on all the economies of the world.</P>
      <P>In the medium term, the interest rate cuts by the US Federal Reserve and the fiscal measures taken and proposed by the US Government will eventually boost economic activity and return the US to economic growth.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="406" />As regards the likely impact that the attacks will have on the EU economy, it must be noted that there was already a slowdown under way before 11 September. Quarter 2 GDP growth had fallen to just 1.7%, compared with 3.8 % for the same period last year. Developments in the EU will obviously have important implications for us because over 60% of our exports go there.</P>
    <P>However, the effect in the EU may be less severe than elsewhere. The economic fundamentals of the EU are felt to be sound and the recent ECB interest rate cuts should help it to avoid the worst effects of the downturn so that it can return to sustainable growth levels sooner rather than later.</P>
    <P>Since we have an open economy heavily reliant on trade and foreign investment, the attacks in the US will obviously have unfavourable implications for us too. My Department had already noted the adverse effects of the US slowdown prior to 11 September and had reduced its 2001 GNP growth estimate in the August Economic Review and Outlook by 1.5% to 6%.</P>
    <P>The latest tax revenues up to the end of September support the view that the economy is slowing, with tax receipts growing by 2.2% for the first three quarters of the year compared to a budget target for the year as a whole of a 12.5% increase over last year's outturn. The latest expectation for our Exchequer surplus this year is that it will be at least &euro;1.9 billion or £1.5 billion lower than that forecast on budget day and, possibly, significantly more.</P>
    <P>Private sector leading indicators, tax revenue and housing data had already indicated that there would be reduced carry-over of growth from 2001 to 2002. The events of 11 September will only hasten this slowing of the Irish economy, with the main effects manifesting themselves in 2002.</P>
    <P>It is very difficult, just over a month after the events, to assess the full economic impact of the attacks on Ireland's growth and employment. Obviously, much depends on the effect on the world economy as a whole and its reaction to the ongoing US military response. Estimates by market commentators for GNP growth next year vary between 1% and 5%. This illustrates the degree of uncertainty in the current global economic environment. My Department will, as usual, publish its estimates for economic growth when the budget is being delivered.</P>
    <P>Let us now consider exports. As regards the areas of our economy which will be affected by the lower world economic growth, we can expect export growth to be negatively affected. The US is a very important destination for our exports, accounting for almost 18% of total exports. However, this figure somewhat overstates our dependence on the US because firms exporting to the US are less employment-intensive and source less of their inputs domestically than other firms.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="407" />It should also be noted that 35% of our exports to the US are in the chemicals-pharmaceuticals sector, which has been holding up well to date, with 23% annual growth in the first six months of this year. Despite this, there is no doubt that our exports to the US will be affected by the terrorist attacks. If we regard tourism as an export, the effect will be greater still.</P>
    <P>A key risk to the outlook for exports would be a sharp and significant fall in the value of the dollar and sterling against the euro. This, if it occurred, would impact upon our competitiveness at a time when wage increases remain high. In the recent past, Irish exporters have benefited greatly from favourable exchange rates against both the US and the UK currencies. This provided significant competitiveness gains. However, the US slowdown had already led to some weakening of the dollar and sterling against the euro. Continued weakening would make Irish exports less competitive and reduce export growth further. This is why we must ensure that wage and cost developments generally do not add to our exposure in terms of competitiveness.</P>
    <P>However, the United States slowdown had already led to some weakening of the dollar and sterling against the euro. Continued weakening would make Irish exports less competitive and reduce export growth further. This is why we must ensure that wage and cost developments generally do not add to our exposure on the competitiveness front. We must adapt our expectations to meet the new economic environment.</P>
    <P>Foreign direct investment, or FDI, from the US will also be affected by the US attacks. Foreign direct investment has been one of the main driving forces behind our record growth rates of recent years. Employment in IDA assisted firms represents 8.5% of our total employment. The ICT sector is of particular significance to the economy as it accounted for almost 40% of exports and 5% of total employment in 2000. Job losses had already been increasing in this sector prior to the terrorist attacks. We had already expected a reduction in foreign direct investment and an adverse impact on the ICT sector due to the slowdown in the US. The attacks on 11 September will further reduce and delay investment from there.</P>
    <P>As regards the impact on the inflation rate, in the short-term weaker global demand and lower growth can be expected to have a dampening effect. Interest rates and oil prices have already fallen. If the global downturn were to be accompanied by a depreciation of the dollar and sterling against the euro or further reductions in euro area interest rates, there would also be further beneficial implications for inflation.</P>
    <P>I will mention briefly the implications the events of 11 September have for specific sectors of the economy. Our tourism sector represents <Col N="408" /> 9% of employment and 5% of GNP. This sector will be unfavourably affected for the remainder of this year and next, adding to the difficulties already experienced in the first half of this year due to foot and mouth disease. The experience following the Gulf War was that US visitor numbers fell by 20% and did not recover for three years. A similar impact on this occasion would suggest a significant fall in revenue, although any tendency toward holidaying closer to home by Irish or European tourists would offset this to some extent.</P>
    <P>The global aviation industry has been hit hard following the terrorist attacks, with revenues expected to be reduced significantly. Aer Lingus, which generates 70% of its profits from transatlantic routes, has suffered an extremely serious further downturn in traffic. Aer Lingus has already announced a programme of measures which involves significant staff reductions and cutbacks in services.</P>
    <P>As regards Dublin's International Financial Services Centre, there is unlikely to be a substantial negative impact on firms there. In the short term, there has been a pick-up in business in some areas as some firms have assisted their US counterparts by conducting operations previously undertaken in New York.</P>
    <P>Growth in Ireland both this year and next will be lower than had been previously forecast. The resulting lower tax receipts will reduce our room for manoeuvre on the budgetary front. Recent events underline the need for a prudent approach to the public finances, especially in coming months, to ensure the economy weathers current stormy conditions. A prudent approach to the public finances has served us well over the past decade, especially during those rare periods of uncertainty. It is certainly the best option now.</P>
    <P>Since there is little Ireland can do to change the external environment, the focus must be on internal policy responses. Policy at this juncture must be geared towards ensuring that when the international economy recovers, Ireland is positioned to benefit fully from that recovery. Only then can we return to a strong growth path in line with our economy's medium-term growth potential. We therefore need to avoid any weakening of competitiveness on the cost front, to sustain investor and business confidence through continued prudent management of the public finances, to prioritise public spending towards programmes which improve the long-term capacity of the economy to benefit from the eventual improved conditions and to make further progress on economic structural reform.</P>
    <P>Looking slightly further ahead, I have no doubt that the economy is in good health and that, with the right approach, we can pass through these short-term difficulties with which we have been presented. I am confident that, in the medium term, as the global economic environment <Col N="409" /> recovers, we can return to acceptable levels of economic growth which will benefit us all.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PaulCoghlan" hpid="Mr. Coghlan Mr. Coghlan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Coghlan</NameTxt>
      <P>I welcome the Minister and am grateful for this opportunity to say a few words on the economy. I thank him for his outline and overview of the state of the economy and I wish him well with the increasingly difficult budgetary situation he faces. Never before has an incident had such an immediate and extensive impact on the global economy and adversely affected us. It is possibly too early to assess the full economic impact of the appalling and horrific terrorist attacks in the US on 11 September last. Being a small, open economy so dependent on tourism, we have already experienced the adverse short-term impact. It has added to huge economic uncertainty, and stock markets throughout the world have clearly demonstrated the resultant volatility which is likely to continue for some time.</P>
      <P>I know the Minister will advance the argument that, even before the terrorist attacks, the major world economies of the US, the EU and Japan had already slowed somewhat, and some commentators remarked that this was the first time since 1982 that all three major economic areas were under-performing at the same time. Apart from the foot and mouth restrictions and consequent effects together with the &ldquo;tech bust&rdquo;, we had escaped very lightly up to that point. There is no doubt that the impact on the US economy has been both immediate and substantial. However, it is good to know that President Bush and all with influence in America are doing their damnedest to reinstill confidence.</P>
      <P>Some commentators are saying the US can experience a pick-up before the middle of next year, although the chairman of the Federal Reserve, Mr. Greenspan, admitted that forecasting the immediate future is impossible in this hostile world. He said that where risk and prices were being reassessed, the record productivity levels of recent years could not be guaranteed. He also stated that the pronounced rise in uncertainty had dampened consumer spending and capital investment. He also said no one has the capacity to fathom fully how the effects of the tragedy of 11 September would play out in economies. Economies were never more interdependent and, as the Minister said, we are hugely dependent on the US.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Despite that, it is encouraging to hear so many say that Europe can return quickly to sustainable growth levels. We know how exposed we are, given the open nature of our economy, and how dependent we are on developments elsewhere. We are like a cork in water. As one of the top three information and communications technology economies in Europe, together with Sweden and Finland, we have already taken a hit as the technology market has taken a dive. Our <Col N="410" /> outlook, however, is not altogether gloomy. GDP growth was expected to slow to about 8% in our case, and the Minister said that this has been revised downwards further to 6%. I know the planned closures by Gateway and General Semiconductors have made the IDA nervous, not just because of the job losses but also because of the loss of capital for the country. Some 4,500 jobs have been lost in the foreign owned ICT sector out of a total of 55,000. Fortunately, unemployment has yet to rise because new job offers continue to come on stream.</P>
    <P>It is true that, prior to the terrorist attacks in the US, that country had been experiencing a slowdown and we expected to be affected by that. As the Minister explained, tax figures have confirmed that the economy was slowing. Tax receipts at the end of September showed an increase of 2.2% over the same period last year compared to budget expectations of 12.5%. The Minister faces the greatest challenge of his career in the upcoming budget in that he must do everything possible to keep us properly positioned for further growth and not let the slowdown develop into a recession. One of the greatest dangers in the short term would be any sharp or significant fall in the value of the dollar and sterling against the euro which would seriously impact adversely on our competitiveness. The Minister is in an unenviable position and must do everything to ensure that wage and cost developments do not create a weakness in our competitiveness.</P>
    <P>Our economy will be helped by the reduction in interest rates and oil prices and inflation should reduce as a result. Lower tax receipts will reduce the Minister's room for manoeuvre and recent and ongoing events underline the need for an ongoing prudent approach to public finances. Because of the current good shape of our economy we will, I hope, ride out the storm with a prudent approach and the right policies.</P>
    <P>The most devastating and immediate blow has been to our tourism industry which was heavily dependent on the American market. The consequent knock-on effect has already had disastrous consequences for Aer Lingus and many other airlines. Many of our leading hotel operators relied on this market for up to 80% or 90% of their turnover, many of which were golfing visitors. These operators now have no choice but to switch to the upper ends of the British and European markets which have not been fully exploited. The Irish Tourism Industry Confederation has estimated that Irish tourism could be facing a loss of £500 million this year following the setbacks caused by the foot and mouth disease crisis earlier in the year. Hopes of a recovery in the second half of the year have been dashed by the events of 11 September.</P>
    <P>My area of Killarney and Kerry, which earns an estimated £200 million from tourism, has always been a favourite with Americans who <Col N="411" /> comprise 25% of visitors to the area. Kerry has a high dependence on tourism and there have already been job lay-offs as a result of the early closure of a number of hotels. The appalling events of 11 September have been disastrous for the county. Many of our hoteliers had 80% of the remainder of the season wiped out in the aftermath of the attacks. We all know how uncertain the situation is for next year as a result.</P>
    <P>At present the future of the North American market is unknown and unquantifiable as Americans are unlikely to travel while military engagements are ongoing. This was demonstrated at the time of the Gulf War when Americans did not begin to travel again for up to three years. Pessimists in the business believe the decline in US visitors will last that long. Marketing at a high powered level to other markets is now more necessary than ever to try to offset losses from the US. The Government could help this marketing effort and undoubtedly the Minister will address this. Europe and Britain must be targeted more seriously than ever.</P>
    <P>If airlines continue to suffer our hotels and their employees will not be far behind. Just as President Bush is encouraging Americans to get back in the air, we must encourage more people to travel and must promote Ireland as a first choice destination. We must offer better value than ever. Aer Lingus has reduced its fares somewhat but for a short period we need to publicise something spectacular such as a $99 return airfare to the US. There is scope for great improvement in relation to Europe. Only 1.5% of the 300 million EU citizens visited Ireland last year. The average spend of a tourist in Ireland is calculated at £563 from which the Exchequer receives 52p in every pound. The new Tourism Ireland chief executive needs to be seen promoting next year's marketing plans. We wish him well but have not yet heard his plans.</P>
    <P>The slowdown in house building was raised by Senator O'Toole on the Order of Business this morning. The Minister could make moves, at no great cost to the Exchequer, to encourage house building, particularly where planning is already in place. He could also provide tax incentives or allow interest relief on borrowings to people engaged in the sector. One of the auctioneering institutes spoke about this recently and pointed out that those engaged in the provision of accommodation were the only businesses where interest relief was not allowed. If that is so, will the Minister address and rectify the situation?</P>
    <P>The Minister has a difficult task. I wish him well in framing his budget and hope Ireland merely suffers from a slowdown and not a meltdown.</P>
    <Speaker pid="EndaBonner" hpid="Mr. Bonner Mr. Bonner">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Bonner</NameTxt>
      <P>I welcome the Minister of State at the Department of Tourism, Sport and <Col N="412" /> Recreation, Deputy Eoin Ryan, to the House. The events of the past year have been difficult for us and world economies generally. All the eggs in the basket appear to have been broken at the one time. The Minister for Finance, Deputy McCreevy, projected a surplus of £2.5 billion in his budget speech last December. Since then we had the foot and mouth disease problem and the forecast was revised to £1.5 billion. There has been an international recession, particularly in the US, and that would have affected the forecast even before the events of 11 September.</P>
      <P>The downturn in the IT sector was already forecast. Employment losses of 10,000 were forecast for this year before the events of 11 September. It may be years before the full economic impact of the terrorist attacks in the US will be evident. We are now told that we may have a surplus somewhere in the region of £1 billion or £800 million this year. That is not bad for such a difficult year considering that before the Minister took over our finances we regularly had deficits of £800 million.</P>
      <P>The most immediate impact of recent events is the introduction of considerable uncertainty which in itself damages confidence and is one of the main reasons we are having this debate. Some recession is inevitable but whether it is temporary or prolonged remains to be seen. Our economy can bounce back quickly as we are resilient. Most of our problems have been created from the outside. The foot and mouth disease problem originated in Britain and as its closest neighbour we suffered most. The recession in the IT sector in the United States had a knock-on effect here as many US companies are based here. The downturn with our tourism is due to the foot and mouth disease problem and the terrorist attacks.</P>
      <P>It will be necessary for international economies to begin recovery if our economy is to recover. Decisions made in December for the 2002 budget will be important. The type of budget needed may not be what the Minister had hoped earlier in the year, especially with an approaching general election. Prudent decisions must be made to keep public finances strong. We must secure value for money in both current spending and investment in infrastructure at a time when less money is available. It has been suggested that we need a budget that neither stimulates nor deflates the economy.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The downturn in world economic activity which has affected our performance will cause the Minister to keep increases in spending and services to a minimum. However, as he and the Minister for Health and Children, Deputy Martin, have promised, there may be exceptions in relation to health services. The Government must also address the inadequacies of the transport, telecommunications, electricity and waste management systems because these will delay further economic growth. Even during the short-term <Col N="413" /> downturn in the economy, the Government ought to borrow to improve infrastructural difficulties and prepare the country to avail of the upturn when it arrives.</P>
    <P>In recent years, we successfully reduced the level of unemployment from 10% to under 4%. Inevitably the downturn in the US high-tech industry will increase the numbers of unemployed. The ESRI predicted that by 2003 unemployment will be at 7%, while the Central Bank expects it to be at 4.5% by next year. We must look after our own citizens by limiting the number of permits to those entering the country to fill the employment gap that existed heretofore. Wage demands due to inflation have, through the partnership process, benefited those in professional and high skilled jobs. Such people shared in the economic growth but excessive wage demands must be curtailed. I hope I do not offend Senator O'Toole when I say&mdash;</P>
    <Speaker pid="JoeOToole" hpid="Mr. O'Toole Mr. O'Toole">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Toole</NameTxt>
      <P>I am afraid the Senator is about to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EndaBonner" hpid="Mr. Bonner Mr. Bonner">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Bonner</NameTxt>
      <P>&mdash;that some people receiving £90 per week in social welfare, while Senator O'Toole's colleagues reject £27 per hour for supervision work and labourers in the construction industry can earn up to £1,000 per week, highlights the gap that still exists in our society. The budget must concentrate on the less well off by cutting taxes to benefit the low paid. The Government reached its tax cuts targets a year ahead of time, but the coming budget must widen tax bands. It must also address the quality of life and standard of living for those on social welfare or socially disadvantaged, people suffering from disability or with learning and educational needs, and carers. The Minister for Social, Community and Family Affairs, Deputy Dermot Ahern, acknowledges that, despite a doubling of social welfare spending compared to last year, he needs an extra £4 billion to meet all the demands made on his Department. We ought to have continuing growth in that area rather than dramatic policy changes because of current economic conditions.</P>
      <P>The economic slowdown does not mean bad times but a reduction in the growth and surpluses we experienced in the last four years. The good times are not over for good and, by 2005, employment will return to levels of 11 September and earlier. Despite difficulties over foot and mouth disease, there is a silver lining for our beef industry because the Egyptian market has reopened, and the value of exports to Britain could increase to £100 million according to the British meat and livestock commission, which forecast that demand for imported beef will rise by 60% due to the return of consumer confidence in that meat. We already are the biggest exporter to Britain with 12% of the market.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Our economic health was seen as very good, particularly last year when growth was 10% with <Col N="414" /> 6% forecast for this year, but commentators are now revising that and the ESRI projects 2% growth next year. However, the economy will continue to grow and by 2005, it will still be above the European average. Difficulties will arise after 2010 when growth will fall to the European average because of our ageing population. The Minister for Finance has set aside 1% of annual GNP towards the pension reserve fund, which was itself a surplus and I hope continues to be so.</P>
    <P>It is crucial that we address the infrastructural difficulties. We must meet the national development plan's targets. Particular attention must be given to the regions that have yet to benefit from the Celtic tiger. Some commentators say that the cat is taking a nap, but some of the cream that was stored must go to the West, Midlands and south-east areas where there has been no major investment because of delays in putting programmes in place. These areas must not suffer further because of the economic downturn. In my region, employment is 17% and many jobs were lost recently. The Herdsman factory in Ballybofey closed with 85 jobs lost while other smaller factories experienced additional job losses. The effect of these losses is probably ten or even 100 times worse here than similar losses in Dublin.</P>
    <P>There is concern about the BPI factory in Gweedore. It employs 23 people full-time manufacturing good quality plastic bags, which were shown to the Minister for the Environment and Local Government, Deputy Dempsey, and are not the type seen hanging on roadside briars and fences. I hope the Minister will exempt this bag from the proposed legislation, otherwise these jobs will be lost.</P>
    <P>The continuing failure of the IDA and Údarás na Gaeltachta to get jobs for Letterkenny and other parts of the county has a devastating effect on young people who must seek employment in Dublin and elsewhere. There is an inadequate road structure through the west of the county, particularly the N56, and more money is needed than was included in the county roads programme to upgrade the road system. We have problems with sewerage and water treatment plants and some work, included in the programme from 2001 to 2004, was postponed due to the economic downturn. I ask the Ministers for Finance and the Environment and Local Government to provide for such work in the next budget.</P>
    <P>The inadequacy of the N2 creates problems in accessing the county as a whole and there are no plans to upgrade it to the same standard as other major roads. Further difficulties are created by the ESB's failure to get planning permission. There is much talk of taking gas to the north-west. I remind people that the north-west does not end in Sligo or Letterkenny. The pipeline should carry on to Letterkenny by way of Donegal town, Killybegs and Ballybofey. We fared badly in the Structural Funds from 1994 to 1999, <Col N="415" /> and the 2000-06 funding is delayed. There is concern that this will be reduced because of prevailing economic conditions.</P>
    <P>Our tourism industry was badly affected by the foot and mouth disease crisis. People from Northern Ireland did not come until August, instead of from Easter onwards. Numbers of visitors from America may be reduced by 50% which would mean a disastrous loss to the economy of £260 million in the coming year. Every year during the budget debate, I raise with the Minister for Finance, who is unfortunately absent, a rural renewal scheme for west Donegal. The town renewal scheme applied to Ardara but was a disaster. It received the same benefits as towns near Dublin and so the scheme had little impact. The Minister ought to look into this.</P>
    <P>The Government has achieved much. Although this is the gloomiest time in ten years, we must be confident that times will improve. For the present, the Minister cannot cut taxes, bow to demands for higher spending and still produce a surplus. Over the last ten years, and particularly over the last four, we have built a sound foundation. Despite recent bad news the economy is still growing well above the EU average. We are still getting richer albeit at a slower pace than before. People are wealthier, and there are more and better paid jobs. We have more disposable income, interest rates are down and there is no forced emigration.</P>
    <P>The Government has delivered £3.5 billion in tax cuts to date and reduced unemployment. There are now 1.7 million people in the workforce compared to 1.1 million in 1990. Tax has been cut from 27% to 20% and from 48% to 42%. Social welfare payments have increased, particularly the contributory old age pension which is now £106 per week. Some 40% of the labour force are outside the tax net. There has been a 67% increase in funding for education and an 86% increase in health spending. The average industrial wage after tax has increased by £60 per week and there have been huge increases in child support. These improvements are reflected in the large number of cars being sold now compared to 1992, and also in the figures for foreign holidays which were taken by nearly 1 million people last year.</P>
    <P>However, we may have to tighten our belts. Senators O'Toole and Coghlan have referred to the housing issue. The biggest advantage of the downturn in the economy is that house prices are dropping and may enable people who could not previously afford houses to get into the market. I agree that speculators and property developers are easing up and waiting for things to boom again. Property prices went up far in excess of material prices during the boom.</P>
    <P>I agree with Senator Coghlan about interest relief for investment in property, particularly <Col N="416" /> rental property. It is something that I opposed at parliamentary party level following the first Bacon report. Members who have children studying and renting accomodation in Dublin will know that rents have increased by nearly 25% in the last year. I always believed that interest relief was a legitimate business expense and the Minister should reinstate it. I do not know why it was taken away. Interest relief is a constitutional right of anyone who wants to buy property. The Minister listened to Members last year in relation to the 2% property tax at a time when developments in rural areas were being decimated. Now the building industry has contracted again.</P>
    <P>The Minister for Finance has a difficult task. Tax revenue is only up 2.2% instead of a projected 12.5%. I hope this is a short-term downturn in the economy. Growth for next year may be as low as 2%. I have great faith in the Minister for Finance who has done a great job over the last four years. He took on Commissioner Solbes last year when he tried to tell us how we should run the economy and spend our money. The Commissioner is now trying to restrict the projections that Ministers in the EU will be making in their budgetary forecasts for this year. He has no need to warn the Minister, who has done an excellent job for the economy.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JoeOToole" hpid="Mr. O'Toole Mr. O'Toole">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Toole</NameTxt>
      <P>I welcome the Minister of State at the Department of Tourism, Sport and Recreation, Deputy Eoin Ryan, who has come to the House on behalf of the Minister for Finance. It is time we looked at where we are going and made decisions in the context of our overall strategy. There has never been a financial plan based on the experience of four or six months. A good plan will be based at a minimum on a three year period, and it will be better if the period is five or seven years. We need a proper review of where the economy is going. Having established what that view is we should not deviate in any way from it.</P>
      <P>It is important to remember that this time last year the debate in this Chamber was about raging inflation. This time last year, the Government, social partners, and other groups got together and looked at what might be done. There was support for the Government in the measures it had to take and a recognition of the direction the global economy was going. Inflation is now under control and dropping, as are oil prices. On the question of growth, which is the only outstanding issue, a number of points must be made.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I want to dispose first of the subject of pay and taxation. The PPF was based on fundamental economic indicators. One of them was inflation, which we have dealt with, and the other was economic growth where an average growth of 5.6% per annum was needed to fulfil the conditions of the PPF. Growth last year was roughly 11% and this year, according to the Minister's <Col N="417" /> speech, will be in the region of 6%. Even if there were no growth next year, which there will be, those two figures give us the required average over a three year period. These things must be kept in mind. It is people like myself who must go out and sell Government policy and national partnership policies in ways that other Members do not.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PaulCoghlan" hpid="Mr. Coghlan Mr. Coghlan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Coghlan</NameTxt>
      <P>There is no better salesman than the Senator.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeOToole" hpid="Mr. O'Toole Mr. O'Toole">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Toole</NameTxt>
      <P>We must have credibility. That is the basis on which we have done our business and that is why the Government must reassure workers that they will get what they expect. The funding is there for that.</P>
      <P>I do not agree that the Government has achieved its tax objectives. It has not achieved either its objectives, with which I disagreed, or its commitments on taxation and the PPF. The Government is working towards them. It is more than half-way there and ahead of schedule but it is incorrect to think that people do not have tax improvement expectations. I accept that those expectations do not have to be fulfilled in this budget; they can be fulfilled over two budgets because the PPF stretches that far. However, people must be reassured on this and, particularly at a time of downturn in the economy, it is important that we meet our commitments.</P>
      <P>That is also the case in relation to the National Development Plan, 2000-2006, which Members have discussed in a very negative fashion. It is a multi-year plan. There can be no question of deviating or pulling back from that plan for a very important reason. To get out of a recession, we need to have solid infrastructure. Roads, telecommunications and the plan's other targets are vitally needed. The most important time to press ahead with such a plan is when we are facing a possible recession. We should be speeding up the plan rather than slowing it down.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The major question concerns where the money is to come from. I asked the Minister this before we entered the House today and told him that I looked forward to his answer. Has he the nerve to bring in a deficit budget? In recent years, we have had budget surpluses, which is a good thing and one that all Members welcome. However, budgets should be looked at over a period of time. The ESRI and Central Bank projections &ndash; and there are differences between the two bodies &ndash; agree that the downturn in the economy will be reversed. Whether we come out of the downturn on a V-graph trend or a U-graph trend I do not know, but we are coming out of it. If we believe that, the case is made for not pulling back from our national development plan commitments and investments. If necessary, we should be prepared to budget for a deficit this year in order to ensure that we bring forward investment for roads, train<Col N="418" /> ing, broadband communications and so on. We will be back in more positive growth territory in later years and we can use the surplus to do that.</P>
    <P>In 1987 this country had a debt-GNP ratio of approximately 125%. Our national debt was one and a quarter times our gross domestic product. At that time we were faced with meeting the Maastricht requirement that states should have a debt-GNP ratio no higher than 60%. The Irish Government had to argue its case with Europe. Even though the economy was improving, we know we could not make the 60% in time for Maastricht and the Government proposed a change to the requirement, allowing for the ratio to be approaching 60%. This was accepted. Our debt-GNP ratio is now under 30% &ndash; half the European average. It is no longer a millstone around our neck. I am not saying that we should be anything other than thrifty in our spending but if we need to budget for a deficit this year, then we should be prepared to do so.</P>
    <P>The Minister for Finance should listen to the advice of the economists and make his own decision. That is what makes him the man he is. He should be prepared to budget for a deficit if he is convinced the investments are important. He should forget he is an accountant. Accountants do not know how to run countries, how to run economies. They do not know any more than the bottom line. He should forget his accountancy training, look at the people, the country, the investment and the plan and make it work. That means budgeting for a deficit if necessary.</P>
    <P>The other area we need to look at is research. There was a very good business story last week which got little publicity. It pointed to the fact that in this period of downturn in the IT industry, young Irish companies in that area in progressing the product of their research and development have managed to get a greater investment in their companies on a <i>pro rata</i> basis than in any other country in the world. There has been an extraordinarily successful year for some start up companies like these, believe it or not. There is a number of statistics in the Minister's speech which we should all be aware of. I direct attention to the statistics about the IT industry.</P>
    <P>We export only 18% of our product to the US. The companies which do export to the US also have the lowest levels of employment. From memory, employment in the tourism industry is about 18% of total employment, whereas employment in the IT industry is only 6% of total employment.</P>
    <Speaker pid="EoinRyan" hpid="Mr. E. Ryan Mr. E. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Minister of State at the Department of Tourism, Sport and Recreation (Mr. E. Ryan)</NameTxt>
      <P>The figure is 9%.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeOToole" hpid="Mr. O'Toole Mr. O'Toole">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Toole</NameTxt>
      <P>It is only half. Our tourism industry is more important to us in terms of its immediate impact than the other. This is important to note.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>In his speech, the Minister did not distinguish between European investment and Euroland <Col N="419" /> investment. We need to look at UK, European and Euroland exports separately. This would allow us to see where our market is. I direct Members to the Minister's references to the chemical and pharmaceutical industry. I have been saying for 18 months that the next big thing in terms of investment globally is chemicals and pharmaceuticals. It is not just in Ireland that this industry has grown in the course of this year. People are worried and care about their health and this is an area in which we should encourage investment.</P>
    <P>Yesterday's inflation and August production figures from the European Union have been heartening. They show that Europe was moving forward before 11 September. We recognise that almost all the world's markets are at their 11 September figures. The Dow Jones and NASDAQ indices are just marginally below them. The markets are recovering.</P>
    <P>I completely disagree with Senator Bonner on the housing issue. Whatever the Senator's views were on the Bacon report, it did have the impact that the Government said it would. There was general support for it. It did have an impact on reducing the price of houses. It is not the case that there are people ready to invest in houses for rental income with the objective of reducing that rent for students or workers. It will not happen. The real issue regarding housing is that the latest figures from the Central Statistics Office show that housing completions, which are predicted in the national development plan to be at least 50,000 per annum, are estimated to be 45,000 this year and 40,000 next year. That will be 10,000 less per annum than planned for.</P>
    <P>I dispute the assertion that the prices of houses have dropped and that it will be easier to buy next year. This will not happen. Our population is rising and there are more young people and more immigrants than ever before. An increase in the housing stock is necessary. The figure of 40,000 houses per annum was based on need and even at that is not meeting demand. What we have seen in the last six months is a lack of confidence in the housing market. Instead of buying houses, people are staying with their parents or in rented accommodation. This is a deferred demand. The demand has not gone away. The people who need the houses are there and they will have to buy, a fact which informs the callous attitude of developers. They are sitting on the land with the capacity to build the houses but because over the past ten years they have become so accustomed to selfish and greedy profits &ndash; I have no objection to people making profits, I encourage it &ndash; they want to hold out for more.</P>
    <P>These people with land banks, contrary to what the Leader and Chief of the House was saying this morning, will not build because they do not like the Minister's Bill on social housing and they are not about to build social housing. My answer to them is very simple &ndash; if they do not build on the land, the Government should build social <Col N="420" /> housing on the land. There is an extraordinary shortage. There are queues for local authority housing are getting longer, as other Members who are on local authorities will know. The demand is not being met. I ask all those in the Government parties to recognise that fact. They will be coping with the fallout from this when they are canvassing for next year's election.</P>
    <P>People in the construction industry have been saying to me that builders will not build houses because of the fall off in demand. I do not know of any place where there are newly built houses that have not been sold. They are all being sold. The starter homes market has not been impacted upon. The front page story in today's edition of <i>The Irish Times</i> is about a house in Foxrock which, instead of selling for £8 million, made a paltry £6 million. How terrible. The problem is at that end of the market and we all feel sorry for the person selling that house.</P>
    <P>The question of immigration is more complex. It is not just about jobs and the people coming in. Nobody could object to looking after our neighbours' kids, but the jobs that people coming into this country will do are the jobs one does not want one's children to do. That is unanswerable and has happened in every country in the world. The Irish went to New York, Melbourne and New Orleans and built canals and roads. Do many Irish people want their children to shovel stones? The reality we have not faced is that people coming in will mostly be taking on employment that Irish people do not want, but which is nonetheless work that has to be done.</P>
    <P>We should be upbeat about the economy. In that I support both the Government and the Opposition. We can work our way out of this if we hold our nerve. We must not retreat into our corner and start building a wall around ourselves. Now is the time to take a chance, to invest, to plan for the future and to spend money.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PaschalMooney" hpid="Mr. Mooney Mr. Mooney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Mooney</NameTxt>
      <P>I welcome the Minister of State, Deputy Eoin Ryan, to the House. He is probably more acutely aware than most of house prices, considering the constituency he represents, although I do not think they are in the £8 million class yet &ndash; it depends on whether one is in Shrewsbury Avenue or Aylesbury Road.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I endorse what has been said about the presentation by the Minister for Finance, Deputy McCreevy. It is instructive to find between the lines a pointer towards our budgetary policy over the next 12 months as we attempt, as he puts it, to weather the storm of the fallout from 11 September. It is important to prioritise public spending towards programmes which improve the long-term capacity of the economy to benefit from the eventual improved conditions. This echoes the conclusions contained in the report, Medium Term Review: 2001-2007, published by the Economic and Social Research Institute in September. In its conclusions, referring to policy priorities, it is clear that the full implementation of the necessary infrastructural investment under the NDP <Col N="421" /> will play a vital role in expanding the capacity of the economy for future growth.</P>
    <P>It is vital that, notwithstanding the projected economic downturn and lower growth rates of the next year to two years, there should not be any dilution or diminution in the expenditure vote for infrastructural development as part of the NDP, as there was in the 1980s. I had this argument with economists and politicians who were in positions of influence during that period and they argued strongly against my premise that a major mistake was made by administrations, even at that time of severe economic inactivity, in cutting back severely on public services and infrastructural development. We did it at our peril and we are now reaping the whirlwind.</P>
    <P>There are massive deficiencies in the public service, health and infrastructural areas and we have been playing catch-up for the last six or seven years. Many of the road projects which should have been implemented in the early 1990s have not been implemented and those that are only now being carried out cannot possibly absorb the significant increase in traffic, especially on the east coast. We also cut back severely in the area of public health and are now reaping the whirlwind. It was argued strenuously that there was no money in the kitty and that we were borrowing beyond our needs, but there are lessons we learned in that period which can be put to good use now.</P>
    <P>We are no longer in the same economic climate. The worst-case scenario according to the ESRI is a continual slowdown of the economy in the USA, which will mean that instead of growth rates of more than 5% we will have growth rates of 2% or 3%. It is possible to budget for a small deficit instead of a surplus. Senator O'Toole pointed out that we could manage to budget for deficits for the next two years and we would still be within the benchmarking regime under the Maastricht Treaty stability pact.</P>
    <P>We have been enjoying surplus revenue over the last few years and have had huge surpluses at budget time. Now that things are beginning to get shaky, people may advise the Minister not to have budget deficits as there were in the bad old days. It would not be like the bad old days.</P>
    <P>Senator Bonner made a point about which we empathise with each other because of our geographical location and our experiences. It is vital for future economic growth and to eradicate the disparities existing between the regions that the NDP is implemented in full, not only on national primary routes but on the secondary routes and arterial roads that link various counties and areas within counties. We cannot afford to hold up progress, irrespective of what is happening in the wider world. The ESRI say, and the Minister will appreciate, that we could fall into a serious trap. If we cut back significantly in order to maintain budget parity and to store for a rainy day we could find ourselves, in five or six years' time, dealing with a far worse legacy than successive administrations have had to deal with since 1987.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="422" />There seems to be a consensus in this House that it is important to convey to the Minister the strength of feeling of people from the regions that the NDP should be continued unaltered and that money should be made available to the Department of the Environment and Local Government and to the other Departments involved in infrastructural development, notwithstanding any other problems. If this means having a neutral budget in order to maintain existing tax rates, so be it. It is a short-term pain for a long-term gain. This should not be interpreted as a suggestion of cutbacks in social welfare or in helping the needy and the socially and economically disadvantaged in our society.</P>
    <P>This would be a major plank in the Government's budgetary policies come December. My colleagues on the Government side of the House will testify that at gatherings of the Fianna Fáil parliamentary party, it has repeatedly been made clear that the issue that now needs to be addressed is that of the underclass &ndash; the socially disadvantaged and those who have fallen through the economic net, Celtic tigers notwithstanding.</P>
    <P>There may be a downturn in the American economy, but companies in Ireland should look east rather than west. Figures have been quoted about the amount of investment in America. Enterprise Ireland reports about development in the east indicate that Irish industry is not taking advantage of growth in the euro zone. Their paper, Developing Business in the EuroZone, states that with 290 million customers, continental Europe represents industry's largest potential market, yet only 29% or IR£2.726 billion of Irish company exports go to continental Europe. Some 45%, representing £4.136 billion, go to the 58 million-customer UK market. This is an extraordinary statistic &ndash; 58 million customers in the UK are receiving 45% of our exports while 290 million potential customers in continental Europe receive only 29%.</P>
    <P>Obviously the UK will remain an important and valued market for Irish exporters but the Enterprise Ireland report strongly suggests that strategic management would imply a more balanced market portfolio. It seems, sadly, that many firms have given a lower priority to continental Europe. It is a huge market with a greater percentage of world trade than even the US or Japan. Europe leads the world in many industry sectors, with particular growth in the newer industries such as telecommunications, pharmaceuticals, medical products, biotechnology, information and computer technology and financial services. There are quite a few defensive stocks, as they are called, that have long-term viability.</P>
    <P>The Enterprise Ireland report goes on to state that given the increasingly globalised nature of business, Irish firms need to be active competitors in the significant European marketplace. I was in Hungary recently and it came home to me very forcibly the way the Irish economy is developing. There are applicant countries like Hungary that have highly developed economies notwithstand<Col N="423" /> ing the fact that they were part of the former communist bloc and are outside the EU. Most importantly they have a very low cost base.</P>
    <P>One company that has taken advantage of the Enterprise Ireland initiative is Digico, which is involved in digital printing. I had the opportunity of visiting its Hungarian plant which it works with on an equity partnership arrangement. It is the third largest printing company in Hungary. Its general manager, a Scotsman, who looks after the Scottish Digico enterprise, informed me that in Ireland and Britain the cost factor of the product is based on 25% production costs and 75% labour costs, whereas in Hungary it is the opposite. He said the company is poised to ensure that any possible downturn on production line jobs here &ndash; that would be the low value jobs &ndash; would be offset by the shared equity partnership with a Hungarian company, even if products are to be exported to Hungary. Although it will possibly lose jobs here in the short-term, in global terms the company will be viable in the long-term, which would protect jobs in Ireland.</P>
    <P>Irish industry should take the message from the Government, Enterprise Ireland and the State industries to look east. Europe is where our future lies. In the context of enlargement we should give it much greater priority than companies appear to have been doing.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JoeCostelloLAB" hpid="Mr. Costello Mr. Costello">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Costello</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister began his speech today by outlining that the economy has suffered enormously because of the atrocities in New York and elsewhere on 11 September, but that there were already significant signs of a downturn in the global economy both here and elsewhere. That is now reflected in the end of year outcomes in terms of a very substantial reduction in exports and surplus. It appears that the growth rate will be approximately 2% this year, which is hugely different from last year's 10%, and there will be knock-on effects for the coming year.</P>
      <P>Nobody has a crystal ball to tell what the result of the war will be and to what extent it may further affect the world economy in the long-term. We are living in difficult times and the great prosperity that was with us over the past six years is fading fast, but I hope it will be of short duration. It is time to reflect where we are at, where we are going and what we need to do in regard to preparing the budget for the coming year.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I was amazed to read yesterday that Irish companies employ 65,000 people in the United States and US companies employ 100,000 people in Ireland. If we look at the figures proportionately, with a population of 200 million in the US, we employ roughly 33 times the number of people that US companies employ. We are clearly providing hefty employment for people in the United States. Having said that, the companies which the United States has here, which are largely in the ICT sector, produce an enormous quantity of exports. Some 40% of exports come from that sector, with 5% of the employment. It obviously <Col N="424" /> contributes enormously to the Exchequer. A downturn in that area, coupled with a downturn in tourism which provides 9% of our employment, would have serious effects on our economy. Undoubtedly with the US market providing 70% of Aer Lingus business on the transatlantic route, this is clearly another area where we are subject to an adverse impact.</P>
    <P>Last year's budget surplus was £2.5 million. The first surplus was created in 1996 under Deputy Quinn who was then Minister for Finance and every year since there has been a budget surplus. I am somewhat disappointed that in the good years of budget surplus more was not done to benefit those who are least well off. Disproportionately, it was payback time for those who were better off. The Minister, Deputy McCreevy, reflected that in his budget and the statistics are there to show that those who are better off did better from those budgets than the less well off.</P>
    <P>We have come 16th out of 17 industrialised countries in the United Nations development report for 2001. Some 15.3% of the population is living in poverty while there is only 3.5% unemployment. There is a contradiction in those figures in terms of how we distribute the benefits that have been produced by the Exchequer surplus and the high employment levels. The largest category living in poverty are lone parents. The NESF figures showed that almost half of all lone parents &ndash; 47% &ndash; said they had only primary level education and that there was only 2% participation in FÁS schemes despite the 10% limit that exists. We are clearly not moving in the right direction. Labour force participation by lone parents is 22% compared to a high of 65% in Finland. These are areas of high deprivation and social exclusion.</P>
    <P>We still have disturbingly high illiteracy levels, as revealed in the annual OECD reports. The most recent one showed that 23% of our population is both illiterate and innumerate. There are clearly serious problems to be addressed and it is a pity that there was so much payback given to those who did not need it. It is a bit rich for people to say that we should now direct our scarcer resources at those who are less well off. I agree we should do so, but we should have done so over the past four years of plenty.</P>
    <P>There are huge problems in the health sector where in the past four years the Government has recruited 4,000 extra administrative staff but only 2,000 nurses. Why was recruitment in that proportion? People are needed at the coalface, not in administration. The numbers in administration should be cut. Certainly there should be extra recruitment but the numbers dealing with patients should be increased. As a result beds have had to be closed as there are not sufficient nurses to keep them open. There has been a wrong skew in the manner in which employment has been created in many areas of the public sector.</P>
    <P>The question of housing is one of the most serious issues. There is a downturn in the number <Col N="425" /> of houses being built despite the need for an upturn. I was in the new homeless persons unit in Gardiner Street yesterday &ndash; the old one was closed down &ndash; and learned that it is facing a winter of discontent and that it is totally incapable of dealing with demands while the numbers sleeping rough are increasing. The construction industry is sitting on landbanks because it is displeased with the requirement by the Minister for the Environment and Local Government, Deputy Dempsey, to provide 20% of social and affordable housing. That industry has made enormous profits during the past decade. Property prices and house prices have shot through the roof, yet it will not take a little pain. The Government will have to ensure basic rights, such as shelter and health. I compliment the Minister, Deputy Dempsey, on his proposal to provide 20% of social and affordable housing. If policy is enunciated here on health but housing is not implemented the laws remain on the Statute Book without being of any use. There is a need for implementation action from the Government on these matters. It should be dealt with immediately because the situation has deteriorated. The great hope was that there would be sufficient social and affordable housing within the local authority and voluntary sectors.</P>
    <P>The Minister of State, Deputy Ryan, is responsible for the drugs strategy and much good work has been done in drawing up that strategy with local drugs committees, but the drugs position is still deteriorating in the Dublin area. Heroin is becoming an increasing problem. We still do not know the number of heroin addicts. It has been suggested there are 10,000 to 15,000 heroin addicts in Dublin. This is the only place they are and they are not being dealt with adequately. The health board said that every addict who presents for treatment will get it and that there is no further waiting list. Yesterday I dealt with a person who was trying to get off drugs and who had been waiting for four months. I was told in the clinic that he could expect to wait for another six months. The problem will not be dealt with unless the resources are available to get people off the waiting lists. There are hospital waiting lists, waiting lists to get into homes for the elderly and waiting lists for treatment for drug abuse, and a community service is not put in place.</P>
    <P>Given the scarce resources there are no further tax cuts. Tax cuts mean that money is given to those who will spend on imported goods or luxury goods. If, instead, the money was given to those on the minimum wage and the less well off it would circulate on bread and butter issues and would be kept within the economy, generating more activity, more employment and further consumption. If the money is given to the well off it will be spent on goods that will not necessarily bring benefits to the economy. Certainly if it is spent on new cars or such items, the money will go out of the country and is lost to the economy.</P>
    <P>I call for a quorum.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="426" />
      <i>Notice taken that 12 Members were not present; House counted and 12 Members being present,</i>
    </P>
    <Speaker pid="DonLydon" hpid="Mr. Lydon Mr. Lydon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lydon</NameTxt>
      <P>It seems strange for one to call a quorum and then not appear.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ErnieCaffrey" hpid="Mr. Caffrey Mr. Caffrey">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman (Mr. Caffrey)</NameTxt>
      <P>The Senator has returned. I call on Senator Costello who has four minutes remaining.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="HughByrne" hpid="Mr. Byrne Mr. Byrne">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Byrne</NameTxt>
      <P>We now know the Senator's interest in the economy.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeCostelloLAB" hpid="Mr. Costello Mr. Costello">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Costello</NameTxt>
      <P>As I already said, the Minister, Deputy McCreevy, should direct his attention at the less well off and those on the minimum wage.</P>
      <P>The national development plan is quite ambitious. It contains many desirable proposals in terms of infrastructure and should not be allowed to fall by the wayside. We should proceed full steam ahead in regard to the existing proposals which will generate employment and help the economy grow. We are in an attractive position in terms of our debt ratio figures which compare very favourably to any of our European neighbours, with the exception of Luxembourg. As a result I believe this country can manage to soak up a degree of borrowing. It would be great if we could continue without further borrowing and obviously public-private partnerships are a way round that. The plans that are in place are important. There needs to be investment in infrastructure because this country has never had a proper infrastructure in terms of roads, rail, IT and broadband structures. This would help the economy in rural regions and ensure there is balanced development throughout the country.</P>
      <P>We should continue to monitor the situation and try to keep the budget on an even keel. It will be a pleasure if the Minister for Finance, Deputy McCreevy, decides to give disproportionate benefits to the less well off. I look forward to that possibility.</P>
      <P>
        <i>Sitting suspended at 1.45 p.m. and resumed 5 p.m.</i>
      </P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Business" RHead="of Seanad">
    <Title>Business of Seanad.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="DonnieCassidyFF" hpid="Mr. Cassidy Mr. Cassidy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cassidy</NameTxt>
      <P>I propose an amendment to No. 5 on the Order of Business. Spokespersons will have ten minutes, all other Senators will have seven minutes and Senators may share time.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MadeleineTaylorQuinn" hpid="Mrs. Taylor-Quinn Mrs. Taylor-Quinn">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Taylor-Quinn</NameTxt>
      <P>Ten minutes is insufficient for spokespersons on such a critical issue.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryORourke" hpid="Mrs. O'Rourke Mrs. O'Rourke">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Public Enterprise (Mrs. O'Rourke)</NameTxt>
      <P>I too am getting only ten minutes.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MadeleineTaylorQuinn" hpid="Mrs. Taylor-Quinn Mrs. Taylor-Quinn">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Taylor-Quinn</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister has had opportunities elsewhere and this is really not acceptable.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="427" />
    <Speaker pid="MaryORourke" hpid="Mrs. O'Rourke Mrs. O'Rourke">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. O'Rourke</NameTxt>
      <P>During the week, I informed the Seanad Office I had another meeting about the matter at 6 p.m.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MadeleineTaylorQuinn" hpid="Mrs. Taylor-Quinn Mrs. Taylor-Quinn">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Taylor-Quinn</NameTxt>
      <P>One of the Ministers of State could come here in the Minister's place.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryORourke" hpid="Mrs. O'Rourke Mrs. O'Rourke">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. O'Rourke</NameTxt>
      <P>I put back the other meeting to get this hour to be here. I wanted to come to the Seanad.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MadeleineTaylorQuinn" hpid="Mrs. Taylor-Quinn Mrs. Taylor-Quinn">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Taylor-Quinn</NameTxt>
      <P>I appreciate it is a matter outside the control of the Minister.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BrianMullooly" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>The Leader of the House has made a proposal and the House must decide on it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MadeleineTaylorQuinn" hpid="Mrs. Taylor-Quinn Mrs. Taylor-Quinn">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Taylor-Quinn</NameTxt>
      <P>Could we not make it 15 minutes for the spokespersons?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DonnieCassidyFF" hpid="Mr. Cassidy Mr. Cassidy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cassidy</NameTxt>
      <P>I propose 12 minutes for spokespersons if that is agreeable to the House.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BrianMullooly" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Is that agreed?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MadeleineTaylorQuinn" hpid="Mrs. Taylor-Quinn Mrs. Taylor-Quinn">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Taylor-Quinn</NameTxt>
      <P>Not really, but I suppose we have no choice.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Aer Lingus:" RHead="Statements">
    <Title>Aer Lingus: Statements.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="MaryORourke" hpid="Mrs. O'Rourke Mrs. O'Rourke">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Public Enterprise (Mrs. O'Rourke)</NameTxt>
      <P>I thank the Leader and the Members of the House for the opportunity to be here today. Before I came back from Transport Council in Luxembourg, I phoned the Government Whips both here and in the Dáil to say that I wanted to go to both Houses. The Dáil had exactly one hour and I thought it would be reasonable to have the same in the Seanad. The matter will be ongoing for the next six to eight weeks and I am more than willing on any occasion to come to Seanad Éireann. As a former Member, I have affection for and trust in this House.</P>
      <P>I welcome the opportunity to report to the House on the current difficulties in Aer Lingus. As I said in the Dáil on 11 October, Aer Lingus is losing £2 million per day and without action, it will run out of cash early next year and it is forecasting significant losses in 2001 and 2002. To put it bluntly, if urgent action is not taken Aer Lingus will be insolvent within a short period of time.</P>
      <P>This morning the chairman met me to reinforce that message and to say that if the action proposed is not taken, it will result in the demise of Aer Lingus. I hope that the realism that has commenced will continue, because nobody wishes to see the demise of Aer Lingus. The Government is determined to keep Aer Lingus afloat and to retain the maximum number of sustainable jobs. It is also conscious that a company cannot continue to trade what is termed recklessly.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="428" />The horrendous events of 11 September have had a dramatic impact on the company with booking activity significantly down on last year on transatlantic, UK and European routes. Given the experts' view that there will be no recovery before the third quarter of 2002, this makes for gloomy prospects next year on all routes but particularly on the transatlantic ones.</P>
    <P>While the events of 11 September had a catastrophic effect on Aer Lingus, a number of internal and external factors had already begun to impact on company profits. These include the industrial relations disputes, the impact of the foot and mouth outbreak and the deepening global economic downturn.</P>
    <P>While losses in the region of £25 million to £30 million had been forecast by the company prior to the terrorist attacks, the company could have coped with the difficulties they were experiencing. It had already undertaken a review of operations and was about to put in place an integrated package of measures designed to yield savings from fleet reduction, operational efficiencies, reduced overheads, etc. However, following the terrorist attacks, the company advised the Department that the trading difficulties had developed into a crisis and that their previous forecast of £25 million to £30 million in losses for 2001 had now more than doubled.</P>
    <P>Aer Lingus immediately announced additional cutbacks to address the serious situation. Overall, the cutbacks will reduce the scale of the company's operations by 25%. In addition, the company has slashed fares on a number of routes in an effort to stimulate traffic. While those are very cheap &ndash; it is £169 to go to New York and Boston &ndash; no money is being made on those fares. The main purpose is to bring cash in hand to the company and it also hopes to reassure people about flying.</P>
    <P>In order to address this grave situation, Aer Lingus presented me with a survival plan last Monday. The plan, in summary, broadly confirms the key details already known in relation to the financial state of the company, including the cash crisis it will face in January. The plan sets out the various revised revenues and costs necessary to achieve viability and to take account of the company's reduced scale of operations. It also sets out the assumptions underpinning these figures and the job losses and flexibility changes required. It identifies the need for a loan guarantee in respect of a working capital facility. In addition, Aer Lingus stated that is does not have the cash resources to pay for a redundancy programme, including statutory redundancy and accordingly non-repayable funding is requested.</P>
    <P>I will be preparing a report for Cabinet next week in which I will be asking it to consider what form and extent of Government assistance would be appropriate both from the company's point of view and the view of seeking European Com<Col N="429" /> mission approval in due course for whatever form of assistance is to be provided. In addition to the requirement for approval by the European Commission, agreement within the airline for the survival plan is also critical. I cannot be more explicit than that. If the plan is not very rapidly taken on board, then the ultimate crisis faces the company.</P>
    <P>It would be lovely if I had soft words to say but I do not. There are no soft words to describe the situation which now exists. I am normally remarkably optimistic in the face of many challenges, but on this I am struck by the starkness of the crisis. If the plan is not adopted quickly, if not immediately, then it is the end of the road.</P>
    <P>Last Tuesday the Transport Council discussed the repercussions of the events of 11 September on aviation. Central to the discussions was a report by the Commission which included proposals for a limited package of horizontal measures to compensate for the events of 11 September. Those proposals are outlined in my script which I have circulated. The discussions ranged across the overall economic impact on airlines, including aviation security, insurance, air traffic control and competition issues.</P>
    <P>In preparation for the meeting, I had either face to face meetings or telephone conversations with a number of my EU ministerial colleagues, including those from Austria, France, Portugal, Italy and Greece. That is in addition to correspondence and a meeting with the Belgian President of the Transport Council. I also met Commissioner de Palacio on several occasions, most recently in a private meeting on Tuesday morning prior to the Council during which I was explicit about the position of Aer Lingus.</P>
    <P>I emphasised to the Council the exceptional nature and impact on Aer Lingus of the events of 11 September, which accounts for 70% of direct Ireland-US traffic. I highlighted that the transatlantic aviation market is proportionately more vital to our economy than it is to the economy of any other EU member state. I stated that direct transatlantic links are crucial in attracting US tourists and that it would be wrong to reward terrorism by allowing any EU airline to collapse because of the events of 11 September. I also warned against any agenda to hasten consolidation on the back of terrorism.</P>
    <P>In addition, I informed the Council that we do not advocate or seek a return to any regime of unco-ordinated or easy availability of state funding for European airlines and that we should not look at it as a normal state aid problem. I stressed that these are exceptional circumstances in aviation to which the European Commission should respond in an effective and measured way. I emphasised that we recognise the enormous strides which have been achieved under the liberalisation of the European aviation sector &ndash; more competition, new routes, greater variety and standards of service, different ownership profiles of <Col N="430" /> airlines etc. &ndash; all of which are in the consumers' overall interests. In concluding, I emphasised that the Commission proposals for compensating airlines as a result of the US terrorist attacks fell short of the measures deemed by Ireland to be necessary to address these difficulties.</P>
    <P>In relation to concerns expressed about possible distortions in competition, having regard to the assistance available to US airlines, which are in competition with European airlines, Commissioner de Palacio outlined that she had written to the US Secretary of Transport, Mr. Minetta, to convey the concerns of the European Commission on this issue. I should say, in support and approval of civil servants, it was somebody in my Department who accessed the information on the Internet, not just that Continental and Delta had received $0.5 billion in direct cash aid from the American Congress but also the amount of that aid they were using on the American routes. I presented that information to Commissioner de Palacio in the morning and she then wove it into her speech at the Council meeting. We talk about distortion of competition and what would happen if Ireland was given permission to help Aer Lingus, but it is nothing compared to the US aid to American airlines and how that is distorting the European market.</P>
    <P>Around the Council table, the majority of Ministers either backed the Commission's limited proposal or agreed that some aspects of it should be eased, but only in a horizontal manner available to all airlines. There was a significant amount of negotiating on the Council conclusions and a reference to the &ldquo;exceptional circumstances&rdquo; was included at my insistence. The relevant conclusions on the general economic situation facing airlines are set out in my script. I was glad to have the &ldquo;exceptional circumstances&rdquo; reference inserted and also the targeted aid which the Commission will examine on a case by case basis. Italy and Ireland combined on the wording of that proposal.</P>
    <P>The Taoiseach yesterday met the European Commission at which he spoke about the uniqueness of Aer Lingus's situation because of the transatlantic matter and its central role in Ireland's access transport policies. The Transport Commissioner assured him that within the framework of the state aid rules, the Commission would consider any proposal from Ireland. We face a daunting task in persuading the Commission and the Council to permit any form of direct financial assistance to Aer Lingus outside the horizontal measures I have mentioned.</P>
    <P>My officials are examining in detail every aspect of the Commission's guidelines for state aid and the Secretary General and the Assistant Secretary will travel to Brussels tomorrow to brief Commission officials on the general aviation situation appertaining to Ireland and on the Aer Lingus restructuring package. In addition, my <Col N="431" /> officials will meet Commissioner Byrne's Cabinet and other Irish officials from the Permanent Representation of Ireland to the EU.</P>
    <P>I assure the House that we will use every avenue open to us to explore these possibilities, but time is of the essence as Aer Lingus is haemorrhaging cash daily. We must find urgent solutions to this critical situation and significant work must be undertaken over the coming week.</P>
    <P>I have had several meetings with the central representatives committee of Aer Lingus unions on the current crisis. These were on 24 September, 11 October and yesterday. At yesterday's meeting I advised them, as I mentioned earlier, that I will be asking the Cabinet next Tuesday to consider the form and extent of assistance from the Government for Aer Lingus that would be appropriate, both from Aer Lingus's point of view and the view of seeking European Commission approval for whatever form of assistance will be provided.</P>
    <P>I also met the chairman of Aer Lingus this morning and I had very sobering discussions with him. Let nobody be in any doubt, there is no hidden message in my words, or any sense of joy. The situation is dire and desperate. To go back to what I said at the outset, if we do not all get together in a spirit of partnership to seek to save 4,000 plus jobs, it is the end of the road for Aer Lingus.</P>
    <P>This afternoon, the board of Aer Lingus is meeting to discuss the survival plan. We are committed to the survival of Aer Lingus, and I should imagine that is an all-party view. The time has come for all parties urgently to work together in an effort to ensure that we will have a fundamentally restructured airline going forward into the future and to protect the maximum number of sustainable jobs.</P>
    <P>The emphasis should be on the transatlantic routes, which represent the biggest percentage of Aer Lingus's operations. Highlighting that fact enables us to emphasise the distortion created by the US Congress's direct aid to airlines which are already using this route. The next four, five or six days will be crucial in terms of the survival of Aer Lingus.</P>
    <Speaker pid="BrianMullooly" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I call Senator Taylor-Quinn. The Senator has 12 minutes.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryORourke" hpid="Mrs. O'Rourke Mrs. O'Rourke">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. O'Rourke</NameTxt>
      <P>No, I believe it is 15 minutes.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MadeleineTaylorQuinn" hpid="Mrs. Taylor-Quinn Mrs. Taylor-Quinn">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Taylor-Quinn</NameTxt>
      <P>As the Minister had 20, I presume&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryORourke" hpid="Mrs. O'Rourke Mrs. O'Rourke">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. O'Rourke</NameTxt>
      <P>No, I had exactly 15 minutes.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MadeleineTaylorQuinn" hpid="Mrs. Taylor-Quinn Mrs. Taylor-Quinn">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Taylor-Quinn</NameTxt>
      <P>I presume I have 15 minutes. I welcome the Minister to the House.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="432" />
    <Speaker pid="ShaneRoss" hpid="Mr. Ross Mr. Ross">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Ross</NameTxt>
      <P>On a point of order, is it 15 or 12 minutes?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BrianMullooly" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>The House agreed that each speaker would have 12 minutes.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MadeleineTaylorQuinn" hpid="Mrs. Taylor-Quinn Mrs. Taylor-Quinn">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Taylor-Quinn</NameTxt>
      <P>I appreciate the Minister is extremely busy and is currently under a great deal of pressure. I do not propose to go into detail on the negligence of the Government and how it has dealt with the situation of Aer Lingus over the past two to three years. That has been well documented in the Lower House and I do not intend to repeat it now because time is of the essence.</P>
      <P>I am delighted the Minister has put on record that the situation of Aer Lingus is dire and desperate, and that time is of the essence. I am glad she recognises that the transatlantic element of the Aer Lingus operation is vital, although I note she did not go into detail on that in her contribution. In addressing the survival plan, I ask the Minister to make a specific proposal to the Commission on the transatlantic element of the Aer Lingus operation.</P>
      <P>There are three airlines currently operating the Atlantic route from Ireland &ndash; Delta, Continental and Aer Lingus. Both Delta and Continental are substantially subsidised by the American Government and because they are operating to transatlantic rather than European destinations, the Minister can make a strong case to the Commission in terms of providing specific assistance for that element.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryORourke" hpid="Mrs. O'Rourke Mrs. O'Rourke">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. O'Rourke</NameTxt>
      <P>That is what I did.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MadeleineTaylorQuinn" hpid="Mrs. Taylor-Quinn Mrs. Taylor-Quinn">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Taylor-Quinn</NameTxt>
      <P>It is vitally important that that case is strongly put. A company already exists in the form of Aer Rianta and this money could be channelled through Aer Rianta specifically for the transatlantic route. The Minister has said that despite being the second smallest EU member state, Ireland is the seventh largest in terms of air traffic between the USA and Europe. Given our population, that means an extraordinarily high number of passengers travel between both countries.</P>
      <P>It is vital that the survival plan is addressed seriously and that in the restructuring process the best people are not obliged to leave the company. The criteria to be used suggest that those in last will be first out. The new people on the bottom of the top layer are often the best but they would be compelled to leave the airline if these criteria were adopted. That would not be to the long-term advantage of the airline. This issue must be considered in a prudent and cautious manner.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Yesterday a number of people in the airline were told without consultation with their union that they would have to leave. That is unacceptable at a time when the Government speaks about the spirit of partnership. As the owner of the company it should be seen to be the <Col N="433" /> main standard bearer of partnership and it should insist on a consultative process, ensuring that the company first consults with the unions.</P>
    <P>The workforce faces a serious crisis. It is extraordinary that the Minister was only presented with the survival plan late on Monday night.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MaryORourke" hpid="Mrs. O'Rourke Mrs. O'Rourke">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. O'Rourke</NameTxt>
      <P>Monday morning, before I travelled to Brussels.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MadeleineTaylorQuinn" hpid="Mrs. Taylor-Quinn Mrs. Taylor-Quinn">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Taylor-Quinn</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister had to travel to Brussels with the survival plan without the opportunity for her Department or the Government to examine the proposals. There is a need to consider the plan in a broader context. Aer Lingus is a company with specific problems and proposals have been made to deal with them. Some of these would have dire consequences for Shannon Airport. It is proposed to reduce the number of Aer Lingus movements through the airport by 68 per week, or 34 return flights. These include five return flights to Newark, five return flights to Baltimore, 16 return flights to Dublin, five return flights to Belfast, two return flights to Paris and one return flight to Chicago. A number of these routes have proven to be economically successful. They are not loss making. The Minister should ascertain the specific details from the company.</P>
      <P>Arguments have been made on the number of Aer Lingus bookings. According to figures before me the company has extensive bookings for November. I would appreciate if the Minister would listen rather than talking to her colleagues on the other side of the House.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryORourke" hpid="Mrs. O'Rourke Mrs. O'Rourke">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. O'Rourke</NameTxt>
      <P>On a point of interest, I asked which of my two colleagues was to speak next. There is no point in the Senator trying to ridicule the proceedings. This matter is far too serious.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MadeleineTaylorQuinn" hpid="Mrs. Taylor-Quinn Mrs. Taylor-Quinn">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Taylor-Quinn</NameTxt>
      <P>I am aware of that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryORourke" hpid="Mrs. O'Rourke Mrs. O'Rourke">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. O'Rourke</NameTxt>
      <P>The Senator should stop shouting.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MadeleineTaylorQuinn" hpid="Mrs. Taylor-Quinn Mrs. Taylor-Quinn">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Taylor-Quinn</NameTxt>
      <P>I hope the Minister will treat the issue with the seriousness it deserves.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryORourke" hpid="Mrs. O'Rourke Mrs. O'Rourke">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. O'Rourke</NameTxt>
      <P>I hope the Senator will also.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MadeleineTaylorQuinn" hpid="Mrs. Taylor-Quinn Mrs. Taylor-Quinn">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Taylor-Quinn</NameTxt>
      <P>The figures before me detailing the numbers booked on Aer Lingus flights for November do not justify some of the propaganda given to the media by the company's management. The Minister should ascertain from management specific details on these bookings, especially with regard to the flights I detailed.</P>
      <P>The tragedy on 11 September is being widely claimed as the main cause of the crisis. The reality is that there already was a major crisis at Aer Lingus. The tragedy only accelerated it. Action should have been taken sooner.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="434" />Has the possibility of part-time and short-time work been explored? I have not heard any discussions on that aspect. The Minister has indicated that she hopes to secure the Government's approval for a guaranteed loan for the company next week. It is vital that she secures a loan or an equity injection of some kind. These issues must be urgently addressed.</P>
    <P>The Government has lost sight of the broader issue. The survival of Aer Lingus is far more critical for the economy and the country than for the airline itself. Given that we are an island nation, there could be a drastic fallout for the business, tourism and commercial sectors. For example, 168 companies export through Shannon Airport. They are located along the west coast, from counties Sligo, through Mayo, Galway, Tipperary, Clare, Limerick, Kerry and on to counties Cork and Waterford. If airlines are not providing flights which contain both cargo and passenger elements, a critical crisis will arise for the economy in terms of industrial and technological production.</P>
    <P>The crisis will also have a huge effect on the development of the regions. The Minister's colleague, the Minister for the Environment and Local Government, Deputy Dempsey, recently referred to the importance of developing a spatial strategy and the need to identify and develop regional areas. It is crucial to this strategy that Aer Lingus be viable and in a position to provide extensive services in terms of flight.</P>
    <P>Other Senators will make specific points in regard to the Shannon region. However, Aer Lingus is of crucial importance to the overall economy. There is no point in directing all airline traffic to Dublin, which faces critical congestion and traffic problems. There is a fine airport at Shannon which the Minister has visited on numerous occasions. It will be badly under utilised if it cannot generate more flights. I appeal to the Minister not to lose sight of this aspect.</P>
    <P>I understand why the management of Aer Lingus would approach the Minister with a specific agenda for saving the company. However, she and the Government are obliged to consider the matter in a far broader context. They must consider the overall impact on the national economy in terms of tourism, industry, imports and exports. There is also a need to consider the long-term attractiveness of regional locations in terms of industrial and technological development. That is vital.</P>
    <P>Ireland is the only island member state of the EU. While we have always tried to point this out, we appear only to get a deaf ear. However, given that we must travel by air or sea to reach other member states, we can make a special case.</P>
    <P>Aer Lingus has a record of producing a high quality product and delivering a first-class service. This is recognised throughout the world. The staff of the company are exceptionally well trained. <Col N="435" /> Only a few years ago the company was making very substantial profits and it is possible to do that again.</P>
    <P>We must look on this issue positively. Applying a hatchet to the current crisis could have serious national economic consequences. I ask the Minister to look at the broader implications of refining Aer Lingus at this stage, particularly in relation to Shannon Airport. The reduction in flights is disproportionately high there. Thankfully, Cork Airport has not been affected and Dublin Airport has suffered to a much lesser extent. It is very easy for Aer Lingus to make its proposals. The Minister and the Government have a responsibility to look at the broader dimensions and to recognise the fundamental importance of Aer Lingus to Shannon Airport and to development from Donegal to Waterford.</P>
    <Speaker pid="LiamFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. L. Fitzgerald Mr. L. Fitzgerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. L. Fitzgerald</NameTxt>
      <P>I welcome the Minister and commend her for the efficient and businesslike manner in which she has taken the package presented to her to Government and the EU so quickly. That manner of doing things is her hallmark. Contrary to what my esteemed colleague on the Opposition side has said, I refute completely the notion that the Minister should sit on the management rescue package, that she should bring it to Cabinet, bring it to the attention of consultants and examine it in minute detail.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MadeleineTaylorQuinn" hpid="Mrs. Taylor-Quinn Mrs. Taylor-Quinn">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Taylor-Quinn</NameTxt>
      <P>On a point of order, I did not mention consultants. Common sense and intelligence should work and I hope they exist at Cabinet.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LiamFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. L. Fitzgerald Mr. L. Fitzgerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. L. Fitzgerald</NameTxt>
      <P>The implication clearly is that time should be taken out to look at the rescue package. I must respectfully suggest that on the basis of the information available to me through the Minister, her Department and sources in Aer Lingus it would be a case of Nero fiddling while Rome burned.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MadeleineTaylorQuinn" hpid="Mrs. Taylor-Quinn Mrs. Taylor-Quinn">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Taylor-Quinn</NameTxt>
      <P>I did not remotely suggest that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LiamFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. L. Fitzgerald Mr. L. Fitzgerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. L. Fitzgerald</NameTxt>
      <P>That is not the essence of the Minister's&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MadeleineTaylorQuinn" hpid="Mrs. Taylor-Quinn Mrs. Taylor-Quinn">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Taylor-Quinn</NameTxt>
      <P>That is misrepresenting me. I am surprised at Senator Fitzgerald.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BrianMullooly" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>The Senator must be allowed to make his contribution without interruption.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LiamFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. L. Fitzgerald Mr. L. Fitzgerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. L. Fitzgerald</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not want to be seen as facetious or jesting in anything I say or do, but I had to make that response to what I considered a strange statement from my esteemed colleague. I am still using the word &ldquo;esteemed&rdquo;, mark you.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="436" />There is no doubt that the horrific events of 11 September in the USA have created disaster and chaos. They have wreaked havoc throughout the aviation industry. Irrespective of what we say about what was already happening here and in other countries in relation to national airlines, that is the nub of the matter. There were domestic problems with aviation in the months preceding those events. There had been a litany of airline closures. Aer Lingus was not the only one in trouble. Airlines across Europe and in the United States are in trouble. Airlines have collapsed and at least one and perhaps two have been temporarily rescued. That is being debated at the moment and seems to be getting a reasonably favourable hearing in the EU. In the USA thousands of jobs have been shed by major airlines with far greater traffic than their European counterparts. We have to accept that whatever difficulties there were have been rapidly accelerated to crisis and to what the Minister rightly referred to as a very stark state of affairs.</P>
    <P>The taboo on national airlines going bust was broken twice in two days at the beginning of the month. It has been no respecter of aristocrats. Swissair was usually referred to as one of the aristocrats of the sky, but it collapsed followed immediately by Sabena. Within three days we had the case of KLM. The American air travel market, which is much bigger than Europe's, is dominated by just a handful of carriers and that is very relevant globally. As the Minister has so rightly and repeatedly said, it is also relevant to the future growth of tourism and of our economy generally. Airlines have the facility to enhance growth and the export trade.</P>
    <P>Airlines in the USA include United Airlines, AMR, which is at the cheaper end of the market, American West, Delta, Continental and Northwest. That is it. They are the main players and the others are quite small as I understand it, though I am not familiar with them. American Airlines and United Airlines have cut 20,000 jobs each and Continental has cut 12,000. In Europe British Airways, Virgin, SAS and Alitalia are laying off staff. Sabena has secured a temporary reprieve and that is currently being discussed at EU level. In the USA a monumental decision has been made by President Bush. He has provided $5 billion in direct aid and a secure loan of $10 billion. That, as has been rightly stressed, has huge implications for the aviation industry globally and for the EU.</P>
    <P>This is a nightmare scenario. Never has Aer Lingus been as vulnerable as in the past few weeks. This is extremely serious and the airline faces imminent closure. It may totally collapse within a few months because cash is running out. The Minister has referred to that on each occasion she has spoken in the Dáil and when she has spoken publicly. She has reminded us of that stark reality. It is the starkest reality of all that <Col N="437" /> affects us. Problems were occurring for a year before 11 September. If we look back further than that we see some very healthy returns from Aer Lingus.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MadeleineTaylorQuinn" hpid="Mrs. Taylor-Quinn Mrs. Taylor-Quinn">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Taylor-Quinn</NameTxt>
      <P>The greater percentage of those were from cargo shipments going through Shannon.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LiamFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. L. Fitzgerald Mr. L. Fitzgerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. L. Fitzgerald</NameTxt>
      <P>Last year saw a global economic downturn and problems in the USA which impacted in terms of cost. There was an outbreak of foot and mouth disease in Britain, which strongly affected our tourism industry. Americans decided not to take to the skies and simply would not come to Ireland. The aggregate of these problems was having an effect and there is no doubt about that. The Minister readily faced up to that and in a series of reviews before and during the summer, management prepared restructuring and refocusing plans for her. Over that period she had a number of meetings with the company's management so it was not as if the Minister was remiss in her duties as a member of the Government and in her responsibilities to the national carrier as a semi-State commercial company. The case was the contrary and the evidence is there to show it.</P>
      <P>The Minister told us this evening &ndash; as she told the Dáil yesterday &ndash; that she has been to Europe. She has presented a viability plan that was presented to her by the management. That plan has serious financial implications, but I am not going to ask the Minister to spell them out to us now. They have to be presented to the Cabinet and the Cabinet has to endorse them. She will then go back and hammer them out in greater detail with the utmost vigour, as she has done with her EU partners. There will be a few friendly voices around that table when she gets to that stage. There is no doubt in my mind as to her ability to present the national case, as Senator Taylor-Quinn has so appropriately referred to it.</P>
      <P>I can easily refer to the north Dublin case and to the thousands of jobs that will be lost directly if Aer Lingus collapses. I have the right to fight to save those jobs through the good offices of the Minister and I make no apologies to Senator Taylor-Quinn. I will continue to fight to the very end as I have a duty as public representative. I have a duty to ensure that the tremendous growth that has taken place across the north city and county of Dublin is maintained. It has been facilitated and enhanced significantly by our airline.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MadeleineTaylorQuinn" hpid="Mrs. Taylor-Quinn Mrs. Taylor-Quinn">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Taylor-Quinn</NameTxt>
      <P>Do not do it at the expense of Shannon.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LiamFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. L. Fitzgerald Mr. L. Fitzgerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. L. Fitzgerald</NameTxt>
      <P>I will do it unapologetically and with full vigour. I have a tremendous empathy for Shannon, having been reared and nurtured in its catchment area. I know all about it and do not need lectures or encouragement to fly <Col N="438" /> the flag for Shannon also. I do not imply that I have received lectures. Much of the difficulty referred to by the Minister relates to the transatlantic routes, which have a direct bearing on Shannon.</P>
      <P>One of the difficult issues the Minister faces is that of competition. Any State investment in the airline cannot be seen under EU rules of competition to distort competition. There is one great problem with the argument, apart from our being an island nation on the periphery of Europe heavily dependent on a national airline to facilitate our economic growth and tourism. It is that the United States will soon have the power, by presenting a package to a few large airlines, with no due reference to competition and in the absence of any meaningful package for its European counterparts, to sink the market and create a few monopolies in the world.</P>
      <P>I have read some of the economic gurus &ndash; not headbangers &ndash; who take the matter seriously, but those who suggest flotation as a solution are bordering on that category. The gurus who suggest that it is nonsense to talk about the national interest when talking about airlines and industry and that competition and the free market should be allowed dictate matters are incorrect. What they are saying, in effect, is that privatisation should precede commercialisation. Economic science, for what it is worth &ndash; being a false science at the best of times &ndash; has come round to the view that commercialisation must precede privatisation. Whatever future intentions the Minister may have, which will be firmly in the national interest, she has a responsibility to ensure that Aer Lingus retains its commercial viability, a view that she is articulating very strongly both here and in Europe.</P>
      <P>There is an equal onus on her colleagues in Europe to ensure that there is a significant degree of competition in Europe in terms of the global airline industry. In the absence of such competition, we will end up with a few monopolies who will dictate the pace. God help a small island nation like Ireland in such circumstances because very scant regard will be paid to its economy, tourism and other vital interests.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ShaneRoss" hpid="Mr. Ross Mr. Ross">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Ross</NameTxt>
      <P>We can take it from this evening's debate and from what is to follow that Aer Lingus is no normal commercial company. One can see from the strength of feeling in the House and the geographical origins of the Senators that Aer Lingus is a political football and people have huge political interests in its future and that of the Irish airline industry. They tend to have certain regional viewpoints, perhaps because jobs or development in their areas are at stake or some other reasons.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>We have not really heard any broad vision concerning the future of the airline. What we have heard today is the cloak of a broad vision disguis<Col N="439" /> ing local interests. There are certain myths pertaining to the airline crisis that I, for one, do not accept. The atrocities on 11 September did not seal the fate of Aer Lingus. They simply accelerated that fate. What happened on 11 September, as everybody has said, was catastrophic in terms of the transatlantic services. Everybody acknowledges that the events of that day had an immediate and dramatic effect. As the Minister quite rightly said, the cashflow was appallingly affected. As Senator Liam Fitzgerald rightly said, the foot and mouth crisis, the slowing of the US economy and other factors took place beforehand. None of these factors was helping Aer Lingus and there was a downturn in the aviation industry world-wide before 11 September.</P>
    <P>What we do not acknowledge is that the lift in Aer Lingus's fortunes since the Cahill plan may well have been the aberration and that the fortunes of Aer Lingus had been in decline for a very long period before that. The Cahill plan was to address the crisis. Everybody here will remember, however uncomfortable it may be, that £175 million was pumped into the airline and it failed to solve the problem. We have had various crises since then. The real problems with Aer Lingus were not resolved.</P>
    <P>The problem &ndash; which was to be resolved if Aer Lingus was privatised because it would not be in State hands &ndash; was that it was highly politicised and remained so, whoever was in Government. It was regularly subsidised and is about to be subsidised again. It was dominated by its trade unions. Trade union practices in Aer Lingus were totally unacceptable. The airline was vastly overmanned and still is.</P>
    <P>If the events of 11 September had not happened, those problems would still exist and Aer Lingus would be heading slowly towards a crisis of this sort, not in the immediate way that it has done so. That is the first myth. The Minister has dealt with this crisis extremely well and realistically. Although I would criticise the Minister for having been too soft on the unions in the past, she has taken a very realistic line, one that is politically difficult for her. I congratulate her in that regard. It is not easy when in Government to take a line that involves any redundancies at all. It would be easier to take a much softer line.</P>
    <P>The easiest political line would be to ask Europe for the money, and, if it is not allowed, pay it anyway, give people what they want to take the Government over the general election and get the votes. That would be the popular political line &ndash; to defy Europe for local reasons. That is an election winner but the Government has not taken that line. It would keep the unions and workforce happy and retain the jobs, but it would be the wrong decision.</P>
    <P>What I do not understand is not the Minister's position &ndash; with which I am not fully happy <Col N="440" /> because I am not in Government and it is easy for me to say what should happen &ndash; but that of the Opposition. The Opposition has no position whatsoever, as far as I can see.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MadeleineTaylorQuinn" hpid="Mrs. Taylor-Quinn Mrs. Taylor-Quinn">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Taylor-Quinn</NameTxt>
      <P>The Senator was not listening.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ShaneRoss" hpid="Mr. Ross Mr. Ross">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Ross</NameTxt>
      <P>Let me say why.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MadeleineTaylorQuinn" hpid="Mrs. Taylor-Quinn Mrs. Taylor-Quinn">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Taylor-Quinn</NameTxt>
      <P>The Senator was not listening.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ShaneRoss" hpid="Mr. Ross Mr. Ross">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Ross</NameTxt>
      <P>This is what is so important.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BrianMullooly" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator Ross, without interruption.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MadeleineTaylorQuinn" hpid="Mrs. Taylor-Quinn Mrs. Taylor-Quinn">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Taylor-Quinn</NameTxt>
      <P>The monopoly of wisdom rests with Senator Ross.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BrianMullooly" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator Ross, without interruption.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ShaneRoss" hpid="Mr. Ross Mr. Ross">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Ross</NameTxt>
      <P>Let me continue. It may well be that Senator Costello will come forward with a beacon of light that will save Aer Lingus, but if he does not do so, maybe he should not attempt to interrupt me. I do know what Senator Taylor-Quinn said and I would be absolutely terrified if she were in the position of the Minister, Deputy O'Rourke. At least the Minister has some broad vision for the airline industry and she is employing a strategy, with which she will rightly or wrongly resolve this problem &ndash; for the moment, at least. As far as I can see, Senator Taylor-Quinn only wanted to save Shannon.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MadeleineTaylorQuinn" hpid="Mrs. Taylor-Quinn Mrs. Taylor-Quinn">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Taylor-Quinn</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator Ross is deliberately misinterpreting me.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BrianMullooly" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>The Senator has had her opportunity to make her contribution.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MadeleineTaylorQuinn" hpid="Mrs. Taylor-Quinn Mrs. Taylor-Quinn">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Taylor-Quinn</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator Ross believes he has a monopoly of wisdom in this House and that his commentaries are so prudent and wise.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BrianMullooly" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator Taylor-Quinn must resume her seat. Senator Ross must be allowed make his contribution without interruption&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MadeleineTaylorQuinn" hpid="Mrs. Taylor-Quinn Mrs. Taylor-Quinn">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Taylor-Quinn</NameTxt>
      <P>He has not a clue about the basic economics of this country.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BrianMullooly" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I ask Senator Taylor-Quinn to resume her seat.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ShaneRoss" hpid="Mr. Ross Mr. Ross">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Ross</NameTxt>
      <P>She has undoubtedly taken it upon herself to save Shannon, but anybody who is honest about Shannon knows perfectly well that it is a competitive anomaly. I understand the views of those who attach importance to Shannon, but the Shannon stopover will die and that will be the <Col N="441" /> end of it. I understand why it is Fine Gael policy to stand up&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MadeleineTaylorQuinn" hpid="Mrs. Taylor-Quinn Mrs. Taylor-Quinn">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Taylor-Quinn</NameTxt>
      <P>This is not an issue pertaining solely to the stopover.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ShaneRoss" hpid="Mr. Ross Mr. Ross">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Ross</NameTxt>
      <P>I understand why it is Fine Gael policy to stand up for this anomaly, but the issue is more serious than politics, and the Minister at least realises that. This is more serious than local politics. The Fine Gael motion on the Order Paper exposes the party as being so empty of vision that it is not worthy to take this type of Ministry. It calls for financial assistance, for which it is easy to call in Opposition. Senator Taylor-Quinn called for an equity injection. There is nothing specific about what the Fine Gael Party is saying. Let it be spelled out. Let us hear the plan. Do the party's members want to save the jobs? Do they want Aer Lingus to save 4,000 or 6,000 jobs? Are they prepared to make cuts or say, as the Minister said, that we do not like it but we must recognise the seriousness of the situation and do something about it, however unpalatable? It is no good screaming in this House about Shannon Airport and the Shannon stopover. That is not a policy for the nation or the airline.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MadeleineTaylorQuinn" hpid="Mrs. Taylor-Quinn Mrs. Taylor-Quinn">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Taylor-Quinn</NameTxt>
      <P>The Senator has a modest vision of what is required for the country.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ShaneRoss" hpid="Mr. Ross Mr. Ross">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Ross</NameTxt>
      <P>I wish to address the issue of Ireland being an island economy. This is a myth peddled regularly by all parties because it is convenient. They say that they are committed to the future of Aer Lingus. They do not say why but they know it appeals to people's emotions and they fly the shamrock and wrap the green flag around themselves. They justify the need for a national airline by saying we are an island economy, as if we would all be marooned and would not be able to get out were the national airline to disappear. We would be surrounded by the sea and that would be the end of it. That is nonsense and they know it. Any other airline in the world would be prepared to fly in and out of Ireland on commercial grounds provided it made sense. To suggest we have a vital interest in a national airline is like suggesting we have an interest in an airports authority. We desperately need the competition for the sake of the consumer.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Other suggestions were peddled recently, not in this House but regularly on the radio, that people were prepared to pay more money to support Aer Lingus. I understand my colleague and friend, Senator Norris, said he was prepared to pay more money to support Aer Lingus rather than fly with other airlines because he had a sentimental attachment to it. Is anyone else in the <Col N="442" /> House in this position? If so, perhaps they would put up their hands.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MadeleineTaylorQuinn" hpid="Mrs. Taylor-Quinn Mrs. Taylor-Quinn">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Taylor-Quinn</NameTxt>
      <P>Definitely not the Senator.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ShaneRoss" hpid="Mr. Ross Mr. Ross">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Ross</NameTxt>
      <P>There is not a single one. I challenged them to do so and none of them put up their hands.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeCostelloLAB" hpid="Mr. Costello Mr. Costello">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Costello</NameTxt>
      <P>SIPTU.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ShaneRoss" hpid="Mr. Ross Mr. Ross">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Ross</NameTxt>
      <P>The only people who have claimed to do it are members of SIPTU. However, they were not paying double for their fares.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PaschalMooney" hpid="Mr. Mooney Mr. Mooney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Mooney</NameTxt>
      <P>In that case everyone would fly Ryanair.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ShaneRoss" hpid="Mr. Ross Mr. Ross">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Ross</NameTxt>
      <P>I am trying to prove a point, which I believe I have done. Senator Costello may be the only one who can afford to pay extra for the fare.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeCostelloLAB" hpid="Mr. Costello Mr. Costello">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Costello</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not have three salaries.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ShaneRoss" hpid="Mr. Ross Mr. Ross">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Ross</NameTxt>
      <P>We do not have any strategic interest in supporting Aer Lingus and that is a fact. I gather that one of the ways around the EU refusal to allow us subsidise or give guaranteed loans to Aer Lingus is for it to declare insolvency.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryORourke" hpid="Mrs. O'Rourke Mrs. O'Rourke">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. O'Rourke</NameTxt>
      <P>That is what Sabena did.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ShaneRoss" hpid="Mr. Ross Mr. Ross">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Ross</NameTxt>
      <P>I gather Aer Lingus is not insolvent at this stage, despite the warnings given by the chairman about reckless trading.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryORourke" hpid="Mrs. O'Rourke Mrs. O'Rourke">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. O'Rourke</NameTxt>
      <P>Not just yet.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ShaneRoss" hpid="Mr. Ross Mr. Ross">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Ross</NameTxt>
      <P>Would it not be more sensible, honest and straightforward to go that route and declare insolvency when it occurs and invest money if we want to at that stage? A plan such as this deserves serious analysis and examination. The Government will subsidise Aer Lingus again. The following would be a better plan and would be taking an honest, if flawed, position. If the Government maintains that it is investing on commercial grounds, which it apparently is doing, why would some outside, independent merchant bank or international investors not examine the same plan, conclude that it is a good one and be prepared to invest in it? Why does the Government not put it out to tender to see if anyone else will do it rather than the Government?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JimGlennonFF" hpid="Mr. Glennon Mr. Glennon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Glennon</NameTxt>
      <P>Approximately 15 months ago I made my maiden speech in the House in the presence of the Minister on the privatisation of Aer Lingus. Little did we anticipate on that day that, in such a short period, we would be involved in the current debate. If I remember correctly, the major issues facing us at the time were the extent of employee participation in the sale of the company and adequate and improved compensation <Col N="443" /> for retired staff. We spoke at length about the success story of Aer Lingus, the role of Seán Lemass and the place of Aer Lingus in the national psyche. Similar to Senator Taylor-Quinn and the people of Clare, Aer Lingus occupies a place in the hearts and minds of the people of north County Dublin.</P>
      <P>Speaking as a native of that area whose family has been rooted there for generations, it is fair to say the entire area is in a state of profound and deep shock at the state of affairs in which we find ourselves. What is especially difficult to deal with is the strength and regard with which we always considered Aer Lingus an absolute bedrock not only of our local economy, similar to the relationship the airline has with County Clare, but also as a bedrock of the national economy. Dublin Airport is one of the largest employers in the country, if not the largest. When the core business involved at that airport or any airport is in the trouble in which Aer Lingus is, the signs and indicators for the subsidiary industries in the area cannot be healthy.</P>
      <P>I welcome the Minister to the House and thank her and her officials for the manner in which they have dealt with a sensitive issue. We, as public representatives, have been kept informed by her and her staff in what is a sensitive time for all. I wish her well in the coming weeks and months in the pursuit of a successful conclusion to our current difficulties.</P>
      <P>Our colleagues in Opposition and their colleagues in the other House are to be commended for the largely constructive and realistic nature of their participation in the debate so far. It is an issue which supersedes politics.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ShaneRoss" hpid="Mr. Ross Mr. Ross">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Ross</NameTxt>
      <P>The Senator must be joking.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JimGlennonFF" hpid="Mr. Glennon Mr. Glennon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Glennon</NameTxt>
      <P>It is an issue which has profound difficulties for the people living in the area, regardless of the views of commentators who may be more detached from the situation than the rest of us. The debate has been conducted and dealt with in a realistic and constructive manner, by and large.</P>
      <P>On commending the two main Opposition parties for their attitude, questions must be asked of those opponents of all things, but especially the manner in which the debate is being dealt with, namely, the Green Party and the Socialist Party. Unfortunately, their time honoured tradition of the facile politics of opposition has been continued into this debate. I call on them to reconsider their position and to make a more realistic and constructive input to this debate.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The point that comes across loud and clear from the Minister, the Taoiseach and others is that Aer Lingus must be a viable, commercial entity. It is difficult for us to face the loss of such a huge number of jobs but the reality is that if the cur<Col N="444" /> rent difficulties are not grappled with successfully there will be further disasters down the line. We must leave aside sentimentality and the desire to see the shamrock fly all over the world and to see our national airline as a viable entity for the sake of our pride. The reality is that the potential is there for a viable business. That is the crux of the issue and it should be protected at all costs even if it entails more lay-offs and redundancies. We must protect that potential by coming up with a viable alternative commercial plan. The Government has already committed its support subject to the delivery of the plan. The degree of realism prevalent throughout this debate leaves me in no doubt but that the plan will be produced and a successful conclusion will be delivered.</P>
    <P>Most of us have personal difficulties with Europe's intrusion in these current difficulties and on a broader basis. We enlisted in Europe back in 1973 and now we must march with it. Our role now is to influence, as far as we can, the direction of that march. In 1984 we failed miserably with Irish Shipping. When I was growing up in north County Dublin Irish Shipping was one of the major employers. It was not on the scale of Aer Lingus at present but it was a major player at the time. We must ensure there is no recurrence of the Irish Shipping debacle.</P>
    <P>The five major cargo carriers in this country are foreign owned. I accept what Senator Ross said in relation to our island status. We are unique in Europe and we must push that aspect. Our uniqueness in the European context means we deserve different treatment on account of our island status. The world has moved on over the past 30 years and no doubt that status will be recognised. I thank the Minister for the manner in which she has dealt with this sensitive issue and wish her well for the future.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JoeCostelloLAB" hpid="Mr. Costello Mr. Costello">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Costello</NameTxt>
      <P>I know the Minister is in a rush.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryORourke" hpid="Mrs. O'Rourke Mrs. O'Rourke">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. O'Rourke</NameTxt>
      <P>No, I am not. I have been here since 4.55 p.m. and I had arranged with the Leader to be here for an hour.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeCostelloLAB" hpid="Mr. Costello Mr. Costello">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Costello</NameTxt>
      <P>We understood the debate was to take place from 5 p.m. to 8 p.m.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryORourke" hpid="Mrs. O'Rourke Mrs. O'Rourke">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. O'Rourke</NameTxt>
      <P>I am sorry. The arrangement was made through my office to the Leader's secretary and it was for an hour. I would willingly have come for three hours but I then arranged other meetings about Aer Lingus, one at 7 p.m. and one at 8 p.m. There is nothing I can do about it now. I was acting according to what was said and there should be no misunderstanding about that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MadeleineTaylorQuinn" hpid="Mrs. Taylor-Quinn Mrs. Taylor-Quinn">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Taylor-Quinn</NameTxt>
      <P>We do not doubt the Minister.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeCostelloLAB" hpid="Mr. Costello Mr. Costello">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Costello</NameTxt>
      <P>Certainly not. Senator Ross and I see the face of untrammelled capitalism &ndash; the marketplace in its most blunt form &ndash; from the good Senator. We have seen that also from Mr. <Col N="445" /> Michael O'Leary of Ryanair in his uncaring attitude to the people affected. Part of our function as legislators is to regulate the marketplace. Where it does not operate efficiently or for the benefit of the people we must ensure its regulation. There should be no such thing as an absolutely unregulated, untrammelled marketplace.</P>
      <P>The events of 11 September brought about the current crisis but of course the crisis had been there since the problem of the foot and mouth disease. That was being dealt with and Aer Lingus had taken steps to absorb the £25 million to £30 million involved. That indicates that the package put together in 1994, in operation for the past seven years, was effective. There were problems as there are always problems in an organisation the size of Aer Lingus or in any international operation. That is the nature of things, but Aer Lingus was functioning effectively.</P>
      <P>We should focus on the current crisis which has hit Aer Lingus harder than any other airline on this side of the Atlantic. Why? Whether Senator Ross likes it, we are an island nation with long historical traditional ties with the other side of the Atlantic. The Minister said that 70% of direct flights between Ireland and the United States are Aer Lingus flights and they constitute 60% of Aer Lingus profit. The connection is colossal. We are surely an exception to any of the other countries of the European Union and we have to argue on exceptional terms. It is ludicrous to say that the European Commission will only make a concession for the four days the United States airports were closed. That should be rejected. It is an insult. Nobody could accept that as a logical conclusion to the situation.</P>
      <P>That point must be driven home. I am sure the Minister has made the point but it must be made again and again. We cannot accept the European Union conclusion. There has been an agenda of consolidation in the European Union. It only wants a few airlines operating. I do not agree with the idea of consolidating into a few mammoth airlines and carriers. That puts an end to competition and creates monopolies. Despite my dislike of a lot of the activities of Ryanair it has shown the benefit of competition from a small airline.</P>
      <P>We have a strong case to make for concessions. They need not be great. The Government subsidy of £175 million provided in 1994 was an effective bail-out. I suffered then because I lost the whip on that occasion&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryORourke" hpid="Mrs. O'Rourke Mrs. O'Rourke">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. O'Rourke</NameTxt>
      <P>Is that right?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeCostelloLAB" hpid="Mr. Costello Mr. Costello">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Costello</NameTxt>
      <P>It is.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryORourke" hpid="Mrs. O'Rourke Mrs. O'Rourke">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. O'Rourke</NameTxt>
      <P>Why? Was the Senator not in favour of it?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeCostelloLAB" hpid="Mr. Costello Mr. Costello">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Costello</NameTxt>
      <P>I was in favour of a little more. I know what was going on at the time and the effort and hard graft that went into saving the airline then. Exactly the same things were said that Senator Ross says now. It was said it had no <Col N="446" /> future, that we must get rid of it and that we should let the private sector reign unregulated and untrammelled. However, there is much that can be done and that we must do. There will be changes in the restructuring but the national airline can be retained at the same size, although we must get guarantees on insurance from the European Union.</P>
      <P>We must also examine the survival plan. I am unhappy that, while management and the Minister know about it, the unions and workers do not. I would like to read it. The Minister referred to parts of it in her speech. All we know is that it entails job losses because of an accounting projection on performance. What period of time is taken into account? There could be an upturn soon, depending on the response.</P>
      <P>The Minister ought to take a broader view. Lufthansa is proposing a four day week for its workers. Some American airlines are using some of the £15 million to top up pensions so that workers may retire at 55 years on 80% pension for five years. They are using it as a direct subsidy. There are many steps that could be considered, but no one knows what is in the survival plan other than job cuts. We should be discussing that plan. It seems to have changed because originally 2,500 jobs were to go but now it is 2,100. What accounting exercise took place in the interim?</P>
      <P>The letter sent out to about 100 workers, employed on a probationary period for six months, telling them that anyone employed under two years could be dismissed with one week's notice was disgraceful. There was no consultation with the unions or the workers' representatives. Some knew it before they came to work while others did not because the post did not arrive in time.</P>
      <P>There is a case to be made with the European Union on exceptional grounds regarding Aer Lingus. Much more must be done in industrial relations. Any survival plan should be rescinded until all the component parts contribute to it. We are involved in a deal now with the social partners, but is it imaginable that the survival plan to save the livestock industry during the foot and mouth disease crisis would have been drawn up without consulting the farmers? Yet the staff of the airline are not consulted about their survival plan, which is very serious. It is a unilateral decision which goes against any form of partnership and will cause untold damage to industrial relations practices.</P>
      <P>I disagree with Senator Ross's position. He is talking through his hat. Perhaps he represents the interests of certain entrepreneurs&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MadeleineTaylorQuinn" hpid="Mrs. Taylor-Quinn Mrs. Taylor-Quinn">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Taylor-Quinn</NameTxt>
      <P>Michael O'Leary.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeCostelloLAB" hpid="Mr. Costello Mr. Costello">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Costello</NameTxt>
      <P>&mdash;but he is an entrepreneur himself in that respect. He attacked Aer Lingus without giving an analysis of how it survived so well after the first survival plan was put in place and the difficulties it overcame and continues to <Col N="447" /> overcome. We ought to look at that positive side and at the human side, bearing in mind that these people's lives and families are involved. A package can be put together to repeat what was done in 1994. Then there was a similar crisis which everyone said was terminal. However, it was dealt with successfully.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryORourke" hpid="Mrs. O'Rourke Mrs. O'Rourke">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. O'Rourke</NameTxt>
      <P>I repeat that I took the initiative in coming here. I telephoned on Tuesday from Luxembourg to say that I wished to be here today. I was not dragged in here. I thank Senators Taylor-Quinn, Liam Fitzgerald, Ross, Glennon and Costello, as well as those who wished to contribute but were unable to do so. I thank also the leaders of the House and the Opposition for the opportunity to be here.</P>
      <P>I want to respond to some points. The Cahill plan was difficult for staff, but this crisis is six times greater. No one will ever forget the planes going into the twin towers and American minds are indelibly marked by that. It has brought a huge sea change to which is added the uncertainty brought about by the anthrax attacks and the war in Afghanistan &ndash; President Bush stated that he does not know how long that will last. This all makes for a greater catastrophe.</P>
      <P>I understand Senator Taylor-Quinn's loyalty because we all feel like that about our own areas, as was evidenced by what Senators on the other side of the House said about Shannon and elsewhere. I have an obligation to serve the country and, under my seal of office, not to allow Aer Lingus to fall through my inaction. When given the seal of office one is aware that there is a greater obligation than a local one.</P>
      <P>Senator Ross is correct in saying that it was when Sabena declared insolvency that it qualified for bridging finance. I do not want Aer Lingus to go that far. I tell other Senators, particularly Senator Costello, that last Sunday I phoned Aer Lingus requesting that the two unions' financial advisers be fully briefed. I confirmed on Monday morning that there were five sessions with the unions' advisers in which they were fully informed of the contents of the plan. Whether they told the unions is another matter.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeCostelloLAB" hpid="Mr. Costello Mr. Costello">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Costello</NameTxt>
      <P>I spoke to the unions yesterday and they did not know.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryORourke" hpid="Mrs. O'Rourke Mrs. O'Rourke">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. O'Rourke</NameTxt>
      <P>I refer to the financial advisers. I know the dates and times when they were consulted. We ought not to say things inadvertently which are not true. I know that the Senator did not do so deliberately. Job losses are undoubtedly sad and I regret any job loss. However, those who received the letter were employed for less than six months and were not permanent employees.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The Taoiseach, the Tánaiste, the Minister for Finance and I received the plan on Monday. It was shown to the financial advisers and the board is getting it now. It will make it public as it is its plan and it is its responsibility to do so. There <Col N="448" /> are other matters I want to discuss and with the permission of the House and the Opposition, perhaps I would have an opportunity, say next week, to come to the House again to debate the issue. I cannot emphasise enough how serious is the situation. Asking for a list of special concessions cannot be entertained. The matter is too serious for that.</P>
    <P>I feel an obligation to fulfil the duties given to me and which I am honoured to undertake. I will give a clear picture of the situation. It is not an easy role and I thank Senators who recognise that. My nature is one that instinctively wants to keep jobs, and as Senator Ross identified, I am a person who likes to be <i>au courant</i> with the wishes of trade unions. However, that is just not possible in this case. My job is to save as many jobs as possible in Aer Lingus and to ensure that it remains a viable company, and one that can grow again.</P>
    <P>I recognise the huge input of the workers into the company, and that of the various chairmen. I pay tribute to the last chairman, who has passed away. He was always very dutiful in carrying out his remit. I pay tribute also to the new chairman, Tom Mulcahy. He has said to me, &ldquo;if I knew then what I know now. . . &rdquo; and I can understand that comment in the light of recent events. He is fulfilling his duties very clearly as are all who work in Aer Lingus. I look forward to the time when that company can get over its difficulties and can grow again.</P>
    <Speaker pid="BrianMullooly" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>When it is proposed to sit again?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DonnieCassidyFF" hpid="Mr. Cassidy Mr. Cassidy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cassidy</NameTxt>
      <P>Wednesday next at 2.30 p.m.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Adjournment Matters. -" RHead="Maritime Museum Plans">
    <Title>Adjournment Matters. - Maritime Museum Plans.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="LiamTCosgrave" hpid="Mr. Cosgrave Mr. Cosgrave">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cosgrave</NameTxt>
      <P>I welcome the Minister of State to the House. While I am disappointed that the Minister for Arts, Heritage, Gaeltacht and the Islands is not here, the Minister of State with her various hats and her knowledge of the area in question will hopefully be able to take back what I have to say to the Minister.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The Maritime Museum in Dún Laoghaire has been of tremendous interest over many years and is one of the main such museums in Ireland. There are many historic aspects to it, and it contains many fine heirlooms, particularly relating to Dún Laoghaire but also to the general maritime area. It has many maritime effects and has a long history. It is very important that the museum be maintained but it needs to be relocated. The collection should be sited elsewhere, probably in a purpose built building. I appeal to the Minister of State, as a local representative, her colleague the Minister for Arts, Heritage, Gaeltacht and the Islands, and the Minister for the Marine and Natural Resources, to ensure that discussions <Col N="449" /> take place with a view to providing an alternative venue. This should be a permanent location.</P>
    <P>I accept that the Minister's Department has no statutory responsibility in this area, but I know that support has been given and that a grant was given for urgent repairs at the museum. I ask that the relevant Ministers meet with the main people in charge of the Maritime Museum with a view to carrying out necessary work. Obviously the alternative location should be in the Dún Laoghaire area. We have heard various proposals in relation to the Carlisle Pier. As the Minister of State is aware, there has been substantial development in the harbour area relating to the Town Hall, Marine Road, George's Street, and the development and improvement of the car ferry. The museum could be part and parcel of the ongoing improvements. I hope that discussions take place with the relevant authorities.</P>
    <P>I know that the Minister of State will support me, wearing both her Minister's hat and her local Deputy's hat. I ask her to be as positive as possible in her response. It is important that discussions take place. I have an open mind on where the new museum should go but there should be a decision in principle that another location be found. There are ongoing problems at the current site and money could be pumped in there wastefully. A more suitable location could be found. I thank the Minister of State for coming to the House.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MaryHanafin" hpid="Ms Hanafin Ms Hanafin">
      <NameTxt>Minister of State at the Department of Health and Children (Ms Hanafin)</NameTxt>
      <P>As Senator Cosgrave has said, the Maritime Museum in Dún Laoghaire is an independent establishment run by the Maritime Institute of Ireland. It is not an institution for which either the Minister for Arts, Heritage, Gaeltacht and the Islands, or her Department, has a statutory responsibility. Accordingly neither the Minister for Arts, Heritage, Gaeltacht and the Islands nor her Department has responsibility for any plans for the museum in Dún Laoghaire or for its possible relocation.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>That said, the Minister for Arts, Heritage, Gaeltacht and the Islands wishes the Senator's attention to be drawn to the fact that in recent years consideration has been given by her Department to facilitating a potential cultural facility at the Stack A building in the Dublin Docklands Development Area. As part of this consideration her Department was aware that the accommodation of the Maritime Museum in Dún Laoghaire, for the display and storage of its collection, was seriously inadequate. The possible availability of exhibition space in Stack A was brought to the attention of the museum. At one time the Minister for Arts, Heritage, Gaeltacht and the Islands had been given to understand that the Maritime Museum was willing to favourably consider the accommodation at Stack A. Within the past year the Maritime Museum has informed her Department that it is no longer interested in taking up this suggestion. The Minister wishes it stressed that at no time did she attempt to force <Col N="450" /> the Maritime Museum to relocate from Dún Laoghaire. The Minister's thinking in relation to the cultural use to which Stack A might be put has moved on in the light of the position adopted by the museum.</P>
    <P>Senator Cosgrave has asked that the Minister would meet the group. At my own initiation, the Minister did meet with the Maritime Institute in relation to the museum. The Minister is aware that the Maritime Institute itself is of the belief that the Mariners Church in Dún Laoghaire, the current location of the museum, is not the best location for its collection and that the institute has proposals to relocate their collection to a new purpose built building. I share Senator Cosgrave's views in relation to the cultural value of the artefacts and memorabilia which are held in the museum. However, the Minister also understands that the Maritime Institute plans to continue to use the Mariners Church &ndash; itself a beautiful and valuable building &ndash; as an educational establishment.</P>
    <P>The Minister wishes both the museum and the institute well in their endeavours. However, as I have previously stated, neither the Minister nor her Department has any statutory responsibility for these institutions and will not be in a position to make available from existing financial allocations the substantial capital funding that will undoubtedly be needed to build a new museum. I am also conscious of the great development on-going in Dún Laoghaire and perhaps there are new openings there in relation to some proposals. Perhaps a home could be found for the museum in that situation.</P>
    <P>There are serious structural problems at the Mariners Church and the Minister has offered financial assistance &ndash; on an exceptional basis &ndash; towards the cost of urgent repairs to the Mariners Church subject to certain conditions. I accept what Senator Cosgrave has said in relation to the value of the museum. It appears to be outside the direct remit of the Minister for Arts, Heritage, Gaeltacht and the Islands and her Department, but I hope that in negotiations on future development of the area a home will be found locally for the museum.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Adjournment Matters." RHead="- Nursing Homes">
    <Title>Adjournment Matters. - Nursing Homes.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="MadeleineTaylorQuinn" hpid="Mrs. Taylor-Quinn Mrs. Taylor-Quinn">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Taylor-Quinn</NameTxt>
      <P>I thank the Cathaoirleach for allowing me to raise this issue for the fourth time on the Adjournment in the Seanad. I welcome the Minister of State at the Department of Health and Children, Deputy Hanafin. It is unfortunate that neither the Minister nor the Minister of State, Deputy Moffatt, who addressed this issue in the past is here. Maybe it is a good omen that the Minister, Deputy Hanafin, is here and that she will be in a position to bring this matter to a closure this evening.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>This scenario goes back to last year when the Stella Maris was closed down by the Sisters of Charity of Our Lady of Evron. I will not put on record again all that has been done by the local <Col N="451" /> community in an attempt to ensure it is reopened. To put it bluntly, it is the internal politics in Fianna Fáil that is now the stumbling block to the reopening of the nursing home. I am sorry to have to put that on the record of this House. I know that will not rest easy with the Minister of State because she is above that.</P>
    <P>It is unfortunately the elderly people of north Clare who are being used as a political football and, frankly, this is contemptible behaviour. The Minister of State, Deputy Moffatt, visited the Stella Maris nursing home at the end of March this year and was impressed by the fine presentation that was made. Contacts were made between the Department of Health and Children and the health board. I gather that discussions were protracted but it was supposed to be only a matter of time before a solution was found. Every stumbling block appears to have been put in the way in the meantime. I had hoped that the Stella Maris would be in a position to reopen at the onset of winter, but we are in a position where nothing has been decided and the latest information is that another Minister, Deputy Éamon Ó Cuív, is to be approached for funding under a rural development initiative.</P>
    <P>It is time for the nonsense to stop. Both the health board and the Department agree that the demography of the area is such that it fully merits an elderly care nursing home. That has been conceded, yet nothing has happened. Over a year ago the Minister, Deputy Martin, told me that money was there for the purchase of a property. Research was done into the renovation work required to be done which would cost possibly another £500,000 to £600,000, therefore, in all up to £1.1 million would be required to get the home up and running.</P>
    <P>At various stages approaches were made by private individuals who wanted to invest, but now if one was to buy it outright and undertake the renovations, the costs that would have to be charged to each patient would be prohibitive. The community is prepared to run the nursing home if they get the necessary co-operation from the powers that be. It is down to the basic issue of providing funding to purchase it, refurbish it and hand it over to the local community.</P>
    <P>How can there be such a callous disregard for the elderly people of north Clare by the Department? I know that the Minister of State, Deputy Hanafin, has not had any involvement in this issue and it is unfortunate that neither the Minister nor the Minister of State, Deputy Moffatt, is here. I appeal to the Minister to end this nonsense and tell his Fianna Fáil colleagues in Clare to stop playing politics with the health of the elderly of north Clare, who deserve an elderly care unit in their area. Commitments have been made by the health board and the Department and it is now up to them to take action. It is well beyond time that the funding necessary to proceed down that route is provided.</P>
    <Col N="452" />
    <Speaker pid="MaryHanafin" hpid="Ms Hanafin Ms Hanafin">
      <NameTxt>Ms Hanafin</NameTxt>
      <P>As the Senator will be aware, decisions in relation to the provision of health services in County Clare are a matter for the Mid-Western Health Board. The Stella Maris nursing home is a privately-owned facility operated by the Sisters of Charity of Our Lady of Evron. Late in 2000 it was decided to dispose of the property on the open market and a closing date of 31 December 2000 was set. The health board informed my Department that prior to its closure residents found alternative accommodation and any person who experienced difficulty was assisted by the board. Furthermore, the health board advised that some interest had been expressed by prospective purchasers in the Stella Maris private nursing home and in this context the board would be prepared to discuss options for the contracting of services without prior commitment on the board's part.</P>
      <P>Since that time a local voluntary group, the Stella Maris Nursing Home Committee, has been established. The committee has made a detailed proposal in relation to the possible future development of the home which would require the health board to consider purchasing the property and subsequently leasing it to a board of directors operating as a charitable trust on behalf of the local communities. The committee forwarded its proposal to the Mid-Western Health Board for consideration.</P>
      <P>On foot of representations made to my Department some members of the committee met departmental officials on 19 June 2001. A presentation of the proposals was provided and it was agreed that the Department would contact the Mid-Western Health Board to canvass the views of the board on the proposals in the context of the board's regional requirements and priorities for services for older people.</P>
      <P>It was also suggested at the meeting that the committee would continue to liaise with the Mid-Western Health Board and it was pointed out that the question of acquiring the home would have to be considered in the context of the board's local service requirements and priorities. In this regard, the Department, the health board and the committee have had several discussions. The Senator may be assured that every consideration has been given to the proposals. The Department actively continues to follow up the proposal and is hopeful that an early decision will be made on it.</P>
      <P>The Mid-Western Health Board has received significant increases in funding for services for older people in recent years. The amount of additional funding has increased from £180,000 in 1997 to £225,000 in 1998, to £500,000 in 1999 and £1.994 million in 2000. The figure for 2001 is £3.573 million. In the case of the nursing home subvention scheme, the amount made available rose from £1.169 million in 1994, the first full year of the scheme, to almost £4 million in 2000. The figure for 2001 is approximately £4.5 million.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MadeleineTaylorQuinn" hpid="Mrs. Taylor-Quinn Mrs. Taylor-Quinn">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Taylor-Quinn</NameTxt>
      <P>Does the Minister of State <Col N="453" /> believe that a positive decision will be made in favour of the Stella Maris nursing home?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryHanafin" hpid="Ms Hanafin Ms Hanafin">
      <NameTxt>Ms Hanafin</NameTxt>
      <P>As the Senator well knows, it is not in my remit to say anything other than that an early decision is expected.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Adjournment Matters." RHead="- Taxi Regulations">
    <Title>Adjournment Matters. - Taxi Regulations.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="JoeCostelloLAB" hpid="Mr. Costello Mr. Costello">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Costello</NameTxt>
      <P>I welcome the Minister of State to the House. My motion on the Adjournment relates to one of the issues that has caused much grief to decision makers over a long time. It relates to the taxi service and what will happen regarding taxi plates. This matter has been badly handled over many years and when the provision of new taxi plates was conferred on the local authorities in the mid-1990s, the four local authorities in Dublin set about putting together a package of proposals in regard to a gradual introduction of extra taxi plates. An enormous degree of lobbying took place as some sectors of the industry did not want extra plates.</P>
      <P>The Taoiseach decided to intervene and stymied the whole development which was being undertaken by the local authorities, which had statutory responsibility for the matter. Out of the blue it became the responsibility of the Minister of State at the Department of the Environment and Local Government who deregulated the industry. In principle I am not in favour of deregulation. Every industry needs to be regulated. This substantial act of deregulation by the Government arose from neglect over a period and a mishandling of the industry. Once it happens there are grave consequences and there is a negative impact on many people. Obviously customer service should improve. The number of taxis has doubled. Given that there has not been a moratorium on the number of hackneys, they have been increasing all the time. An industry that had a certain amount of cohesion became scattered and incoherent. A taxi plate that had a certain value now has no value.</P>
      <P>A number of people got into the industry on a proper basis. For example, people who had taken redundancy money used it to buy a taxi plate. They saw it as a contribution towards their pension in later years and a nest egg for their family at the time. It had a value, but once deregulation was introduced it had no value. The adverse effects have been experienced by people who had mortgages and other borrowings. There are great difficulties in making such repayments. Many people are now paying for a plate which cost £70,000 or £80,000 and which now has no value. They are in hock to banks, building societies and credit unions on what they believed was a genuine asset.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Widows are probably more affected than anybody else in that they are unable to work the plate. The plate has no sale value and the breadwinner is no longer there. A number of people <Col N="454" /> have suffered as a result of the deregulation of the industry. They are the people on whose behalf I raise the matter. The organisation, Families Advocate Immediate Redress, has been established. I do not know whether it has had significant talks with the Minister on the matter. It has been lobbying and has gone to the European Commission on the matter. There is much concern in the organisation, many of whose members are suffering hardship arising from this matter. Has the Minister of State taken significant steps to ensure hardship is alleviated in the taxi industry?</P>
    <Speaker pid="MaryHanafin" hpid="Ms Hanafin Ms Hanafin">
      <NameTxt>Ms Hanafin</NameTxt>
      <P>I thank Senator Costello for raising the issue which I shall answer on behalf of my colleague, the Minister of State, Deputy Molloy.</P>
      <P>The October 2000 High Court judgment created the legal position that limitation of taxi licences in the interests of existing licence holders could not be sustained. The Road Traffic (Public Service Vehicles) (Amendment) (No. 3) Regulations, 2000, were made to respond to the reality of the new legal situation and sought to establish orderly licensing arrangements within it.</P>
      <P>The courts have clarified on a number of occasions since 1992 that there can be no legal duty on the State to compensate taxi licence holders in relation to open market values of licences. However, the Government recognised that some difficulties might be caused by the new taxi regime for some existing taxi licence holders. It was acknowledged that given the many changes which were taking place, certain recent new holders of taxi and wheelchair accessible taxi licences would be in a position of having paid much higher licence fees to local authorities than those which now obtain. Accordingly, following the making of the regulations providing for liberalisation of availability of taxi licences, arrangements were made for the introduction of a scheme of refunds by certain local authorities in relation to taxi licence fees charged at above the default level fixed in the Public Service Vehicles Regulations, 1995.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Additional mitigating measures were included in the Finance Act, 2001, which provides for a new scheme of capital allowance for expenditure incurred on the cost of taxi licences acquired on or before 21 November 2000. The allowances are effectively back-dated, with the cost deemed to have been incurred on 21 November 1997 where the licence was purchased prior to that date. The actual cost of the licence can be written off over five years at the rate of 20% per annum in line with the new write-off period for capital allowances for plant and machinery. The write-off will be allowed against the trading income only of the licence owner who drives the taxi. However, if additionally the same vehicle is rented out on a part-time basis, the cost can be written off against <Col N="455" /> both the trading income and the rental income from the vehicle in question.</P>
    <P>The Act also includes provisions targeted at addressing some hardship cases that had been brought to the attention of the Minister for Finance. Section 51 of the Act provides that where a licence was inherited from a deceased spouse who carried on a taxi trade the licence holder may offset the capital expenditure incurred on the original acquisition of the licence against the rental income from the licence, even if there is no trading income from the licence. This measure will only be available in respect of one licence. Where inheritance tax or probate tax was paid in respect of a taxi licence, the value used for such tax purposes may be used instead of the actual capital expenditure cost, if that value is higher. The capital allowance scheme also caters for the situation where a widow or widower, who has inherited the licence from his or her spouse, lets the licence to a third party who provides the associated vehicle.</P>
    <P>These provisions offer to taxi licence holders affected by liberalisation of entry to the taxi market, a much improved position on that which existed beforehand. Taxi licence holders can now offset the cost of their taxi licences against both their trading income and their rental income. Previously, a taxi licence holder would not have been allowed to write off the expenditure incurred in buying a taxi licence against his or her income.</P>
    <P>Claims for capital allowances should be made to the individual's tax office. A claim should include details of the date the licence was acquired, the actual cost of the licence, the date the individual started the taxi trade and, where a licence has been part let, the percentage use of <Col N="456" /> the taxi vehicle for trading and letting purposes. If the individual has already submitted a return of income in respect of the tax years for which the allowances are being claimed, these details should be forwarded in support of a written claim to the tax office. Otherwise the details should be included with the individual's return of income for the tax year or years in question.</P>
    <P>The value of any tax refund due in respect of the claim for the allowances will depend on the cost of the licence, the individual's marginal rate of tax for each tax year for which the allowance is claimed and the amount of income, if any, liable to tax at that rate.</P>
    <P>There are no current proposals for mitigation measures beyond the Finance Act, 2001, provisions and the scheme of taxi licence fee refunds by certain local authorities. However, I understand that at a meeting with SIPTU officials on 25 July 2001, the Minister of State, Deputy Molloy, requested the submission of a document categorising cases of specific hardship which may not be fully covered by the current mitigation measures and it is understood that this document is being prepared by SIPTU. The Minister of State is also aware of representations from Families Advocate Immediate Redress and has suggested to FAIR that it may wish to communicate with SIPTU officials in relation to their concerns on this matter or make a separate submission on the matter to the Department of the Environment and Local Government. It must be stressed, however, that there is no guarantee that further measures will be possible and the Minister of State would not wish to raise hopes or expectations unduly in this regard.</P>
    <P>The Seanad adjourned at 6.50 p.m. until 2.30 p.m. on Wednesday, 24 October 2001.</P>
  </MainHeading>
</Debate>