<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE Debate SYSTEM "../Debate.dtd"[]>
<Debate DocTitle="Seanad Debate" Day="Tue" Date="29" Month="May" Year="2001" Vol="166" No="18" DateIrish="Dé Máirt, 29 Bealtaine 2001" DateEnglish="Tuesday, 29 May 2001" House="S" CommitteeEng="" CommitteeIr="" SubNameEng="" cnum="0">
  <MainHeading Type="Prelude" LHead="" RHead="">
    <Title>
    </Title>
    <P Just="Center">
      <Col N="1305" /> Chuaigh an Cathaoirleach i gceannas ar 2.30 p.m.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Order of" RHead="Business">
    <Title>Order of Business.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="DonnieCassidyFF" hpid="Mr. Cassidy Mr. Cassidy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cassidy</NameTxt>
      <P>The Order of Business is No. 1, Health (Miscellaneous Provisions) (No. 2) Bill, 2000 [<i>Seanad Bill amended by the Dáil</i>] &ndash; Report and Final Stages; and No. 2, statements on women's cancer strategy, with contributions of Senators not to exceed ten minutes.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MauriceManning" hpid="Mr. Manning Mr. Manning">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Manning</NameTxt>
      <P>Why is the Leader of the House confining statements on No. 2 to ten minutes? I do not expect there will be too many speakers and I would give them more time. Does the Leader of the House have any plans to hold a meeting of the Seanad outside Dublin? I thank him for rescheduling the Electoral (Amendment) Bill, 2000 for Thursday instead of today. However, no amendment has yet been made available to the Opposition and we are told that there are over 100 amendments. Clearly this is not the way to do business.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BrianMullooly" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>The amendments are in the Seanad office and are being prepared for circulation.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MauriceManning" hpid="Mr. Manning Mr. Manning">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Manning</NameTxt>
      <P>Thank you, a Chathaoirligh. I was aware of that but my point was that they have not been circulated to members of the Opposition, the people who must deal with them. That will not happen until later today when some of the amendments will be made available. We have been told that the others will not be available until Thursday. I am not taking issue with the Leader on this matter. He has been treated very badly by the office of the Minister who asked him to schedule the Bill for today even though the amendments would not be available before then. This Bill was published last December.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I want an assurance from the Leader that the Bill will not be rushed on Thursday. Only a limited number of amendments &ndash; certainly none of those that have not been released with at least two days notice &ndash; should be taken to allow Members to do their preparation work. The Leader was placed in an impossible position last <Col N="1306" /> week by a Department which informed him it wanted a Bill to be taken without having a single amendment ready. When we addressed this matter on Friday, we were told we might receive the amendments on Tuesday, which is the day we were scheduled to take the Bill. That is either incompetence on the part of the Minister's office or it shows contempt for this House of Parliament. I ask for an assurance that adequate time will be allocated to this very important Bill and that no attempt will be made to rush it through on Thursday.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JoeOToole" hpid="Mr. O'Toole Mr. O'Toole">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Toole</NameTxt>
      <P>I raise the current events in the Balkan states. I ask that the Minister for Foreign Affairs, Deputy Cowen, come into the House to debate the issue. The current debate on the Nice treaty and the statement yesterday from Prime Minister Jospin on the idea of a federal Europe tie in with the wider issue of sovereignty, which this House has discussed on a number of occasions.</P>
      <P>Europe is witnessing a renewal of conflict between Albanians, Kosovars and Macedonians. I want to hear the view of the Government on this matter and on how Europe should respond to it. It would be very useful to hear the views of those people who are consistently guilty of double think on whether we should get involved in various areas of conflict. They are not easy matters to deal with but people should set the record straight so that we can find another way of dealing with sovereignty, neutrality and enlargement, issues that need to be tackled. It would be helpful if the Minister for Foreign Affairs debated the matter with us.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeCostelloLAB" hpid="Mr. Costello Mr. Costello">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Costello</NameTxt>
      <P>I add my voice to what Senator Manning has said on the Electoral (Amendment) Bill, 2000. It has been months since this Bill was taken on Second Stage. We were told that it would come before us on Tuesday, but no amendments have appeared and now we are told we will take Committee and Remaining Stages on Thursday afternoon. I know we are not supposed to bring up business that will not be taken that day, but this Bill was originally scheduled for today.</P>
      <P>This is an important Bill and a vast number of amendments have been tabled by the Government and, undoubtedly, by this side of the House. It is an insult to us to have it moved around in this fashion. We can expect that it will be guillotined given that Committee and Remaining Stages are scheduled for Thursday afternoon. I ask the Leader of the House to withdraw the Electoral (Amendment) Bill from this week's schedule and to take it instead next week with a proper timescale allocated to it. This is major legislation and we should do it justice.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>This is the 40th anniversary of Amnesty International, which links in to Senator O'Toole's comments about the conflict in the Balkans and human and civil rights which have been so much abused in that region since the break-up of Yugoslavia. It is also closely related to the two refer<Col N="1307" /> enda being held at the same time as the vote on the Nice treaty, namely, the abolition of capital punishment, with which Amnesty International has been closely identified due to its efforts to have it abolished worldwide, and the establishment of the International Criminal Court which will allow people to be brought to justice for human rights abuses.</P>
    <P>The 40th anniversary of Amnesty International is a particularly appropriate time to hold these referenda. I ask the Leader of the House to find an opportunity for us to discuss and mark the wonderful contribution Amnesty International has made to human rights in Ireland and abroad, and to honour the contribution of the late Sean McBride who received the Nobel peace prize because of his work with Amnesty International.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MaryJackman" hpid="Mrs. Jackman Mrs. Jackman">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Jackman</NameTxt>
      <P>I agree with Senator Manning that ten minutes is a derisory length of time for Members to speak on the women's cancer strategy. We have been waiting a long time for a debate on health, and ten minutes is not enough time for Members to have their say regarding the lack of effort by the Government in implementing a cancer strategy.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DonnieCassidyFF" hpid="Mr. Cassidy Mr. Cassidy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cassidy</NameTxt>
      <P>The Health (Miscellaneous Provisions) (No. 2) Bill, 2000 will be debated all afternoon.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryJackman" hpid="Mrs. Jackman Mrs. Jackman">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Jackman</NameTxt>
      <P>I would be delighted if the matter was dealt with over a full afternoon. With so many Members wishing to speak, we should have adequate time.</P>
      <P>In relation to waste management, I seek a debate with the Minister for the Environment and Local Government on the strategy for housing development. There are housing density guidelines, yet little reference is made to them in the development of towns, villages and smaller settlements. Sewerage is inadequate in many areas and there seems to be no planning or strategy for future development. This applies particularly in rural areas.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LabhrasOMurchu" hpid="Labhrás Ó Murchú Labhrás Ó Murchú">
      <NameTxt>Labhrás Ó Murchú</NameTxt>
      <P>I support Senator Costello's suggestion that we mark the 40th anniversary of Amnesty International. If it cannot be done this week, I would like to see it done in the very near future. Amnesty International has made an important contribution to human rights throughout the world. Many who suffered torture and oppression had nowhere else to go and depended on Amnesty International to come to their aid. As Ireland has a vibrant Amnesty International section, it is right that the Seanad should mark its anniversary in some way.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryHenry" hpid="Dr. Henry Dr. Henry">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Henry</NameTxt>
      <P>The issue of the manufacture of soap containing mercury has again been raised in the media. Ms Mary Banotti, MEP, did considerable work on the matter some years ago. I did not know it was still manufactured in Ireland as <Col N="1308" /> it cannot be sold here. I ask the Tánaiste to come to the House to explain the reason this product is still manufactured in Arklow. It is wrong to sell it as it has serious neurological and kidney effects. There are also health and safety risks for workers at the manufacturer plant. It is now not even possible to buy mercury thermometers in Ireland, never mind manufacture a product containing mercury.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MairinQuill" hpid="Miss Quill Miss Quill">
      <NameTxt>Miss Quill</NameTxt>
      <P>I welcome the opportunity to debate the situation in the Balkans in the context of the anniversary of Amnesty International. I would appreciate if the House could broaden the debate and take into account the punishment beatings that are becoming more common by the day in Northern Ireland and the violation of human rights there. When the Good Friday Agreement was signed, we were of the belief that communities could live and work together at a democratic and institutional level. I hope that will continue and strengthen. We need to have communities in Northern Ireland which can live together in a normal, healthy, civil society. If we can assist in the development of civil society and the eradication of punishment beatings and the conditions that give rise to them, it would be a good day's work for human rights on our island. I would like to see this included in any debate on the Balkans and human rights.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThereseRidge" hpid="Mrs. Ridge Mrs. Ridge">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Ridge</NameTxt>
      <P>The Leader of the House will be happy to know that the Garda Commissioner now agrees with me about a matter raised at last week's Garda council. The Commissioner has acknowledged that while the required funding is in place, manpower is needed to deal with the escalating crime problem in the outer suburbs and inner city. I have been asking for this for three years and it is better late than never. I ask our esteemed Leader to arrange for the Minister to come to this House and tell us what he intends to do about these reinforcements, which are necessary to secure the safety and well-being of the communities in which we live.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PaulCoghlan" hpid="Mr. Coghlan Mr. Coghlan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Coghlan</NameTxt>
      <P>The Government made a number of important decisions yesterday in Killarney.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="AnnOrmonde" hpid="Ms Ormonde Ms Ormonde">
      <NameTxt>Ms Ormonde</NameTxt>
      <P>They enjoyed it. The Senator looks very well.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PaulCoghlan" hpid="Mr. Coghlan Mr. Coghlan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Coghlan</NameTxt>
      <P>While some of those decisions, especially those in regard to tourism, are very much welcomed a number of very important matters were overlooked. One of the decisions made concerned the local government Bill. I invite the Leader to comment on this. Reading today's newspapers it appears that it is merely a decision to reopen negotiations with parties outside of the Government. I do not suppose anyone knows the timetable. Maybe the Leader knows but, as Senator Manning has said, he has been treated shabbily as a conduit between this House and the Government.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1309" />
    <Speaker pid="FergusODowdFG" hpid="Mr. O'Dowd Mr. O'Dowd">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Dowd</NameTxt>
      <P>Can we have a debate on the health services as soon as possible? The debate should focus on the fact that there are far too many managers and administrators and not enough nurses, doctors or consultants. One of my clients looked for an appointment with his consultant through me. He was told by the health board that he had missed his last three appointments. Those appointments had in fact been cancelled by the administrators and the man was never informed that he had them. It is symptomatic of the disgraceful condition of our health services that people are treated so badly and casually on such important issues.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PaddyBurke" hpid="Mr. Burke Mr. Burke">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Burke</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator Manning last week asked for a debate on sport. When will that debate take place? I also ask for a debate on the issue of funding for the BMW region. A new report indicates that the highest unemployment figures are in the Border region.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JimGlennonFF" hpid="Mr. Glennon Mr. Glennon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Glennon</NameTxt>
      <P>I join with my colleagues in calling for a debate to mark the 40th anniversary of the founding of Amnesty International. It is unfortunate that such a notable anniversary has been diminished somewhat by the nature of the advertising campaign which that organisation is currently running. It is ironic that an organisation which has for so long stood for the rights of the individual has demeaned itself by being involved in a very personalised advertising campaign.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MickLanigan" hpid="Mr. Lanigan Mr. Lanigan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lanigan</NameTxt>
      <P>I was not going to speak but Senator Burke gave me the opportunity. Yesterday's newspapers reported that Deputy Michael Noonan said that instead of building a national stadium Fine Gael would spend £500 million around the country and that part of this would be spent in such clapped out stadiums as Nowlan Park in Kilkenny and Páirc Uí Chaoimh. That was a gratuitous insult to various sports bodies, various Ministers, including former Fine Gael Ministers, and to the sports council who have spent a huge amount of money modernising both of these stadiums.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThereseRidge" hpid="Mrs. Ridge Mrs. Ridge">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Ridge</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator Lanigan should stick to the Middle East.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MickLanigan" hpid="Mr. Lanigan Mr. Lanigan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lanigan</NameTxt>
      <P>If this is the type of work which Deputy Noonan is going to do he should at least visit some of the places that he is talking about. It was an insult to everyone involved in Nowlan Park.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MauriceManning" hpid="Mr. Manning Mr. Manning">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Manning</NameTxt>
      <P>Deputy Noonan was in Páirc Uí Chaoimh on Sunday and enjoyed every moment of it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DonnieCassidyFF" hpid="Mr. Cassidy Mr. Cassidy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cassidy</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator Manning has called for additional time for speakers. I propose that 15 minutes be allocated to all contributors. It is intended that only the published amendments will be discussed next Thursday. It is also intended that the amendments to the political <Col N="1310" /> donations Bill will be published well in advance of the resumed Committee Stage debate, which will take place after next week's break.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MauriceManning" hpid="Mr. Manning Mr. Manning">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Manning</NameTxt>
      <P>Published when?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DonnieCassidyFF" hpid="Mr. Cassidy Mr. Cassidy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cassidy</NameTxt>
      <P>They have to be discussed with the Opposition parties. They will then be published well in advance of our return on 12 June.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LiamTCosgrave" hpid="Mr. Cosgrave Mr. Cosgrave">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cosgrave</NameTxt>
      <P>Would it not be much better to take all the amendments together?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DonnieCassidyFF" hpid="Mr. Cassidy Mr. Cassidy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cassidy</NameTxt>
      <P>On Committee Stage next Thursday afternoon, we will only be discussing the amendments that have been published today.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MauriceManning" hpid="Mr. Manning Mr. Manning">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Manning</NameTxt>
      <P>That have been published today.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DonnieCassidyFF" hpid="Mr. Cassidy Mr. Cassidy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cassidy</NameTxt>
      <P>Correct.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DonnieCassidyFF" hpid="Mr. Cassidy Mr. Cassidy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cassidy</NameTxt>
      <P>Senators O'Toole and Quill inquired about the Government's position on areas of conflict and called for a debate with the Minister for Foreign Affairs. Senator Quinn requested a debate on Northern Ireland on which I have already given a commitment to hold a further debate. I will pass on the views of the Senators to the Minister and can arrange to make time available for a debate at the earliest opportunity.</P>
      <P>Senators Costello, Ó Murchú and Glennon called for a debate to mark the 40th anniversary of Amnesty International, for which I will make time available. I agree with Senator Glennon's remarks about that organisation's current advertising campaign.</P>
      <P>Senator Jackman requested a debate on housing development and the various action plans being put in place. I do not know the position with Limerick County Council, but Westmeath County Council has action plans for every town and village which are to be incorporated into the county development plan&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryJackman" hpid="Mrs. Jackman Mrs. Jackman">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Jackman</NameTxt>
      <P>There is no infrastructure.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DonnieCassidyFF" hpid="Mr. Cassidy Mr. Cassidy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cassidy</NameTxt>
      <P>&mdash;and, as far as I am aware, that is the case in other council areas throughout the country. I accept, however, that such developments may not have reached as advanced a stage in certain council areas as they have in the area of responsibility of the council of which I am a member.</P>
      <P>Senator Jackman also raised a number of points in relation to health. This afternoon we are taking the Report and Final Stages of the Health (Miscellaneous Provisions) (No. 2) Bill and perhaps the Senator can deal with some of the points she raised &ndash; in which she is keenly interested &ndash; at that juncture.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I will communicate the views of Senator Henry to the relevant Minister and must inform Senator Ridge that I have agreed to have a debate on justice issues. Senator Coghlan looked very well yes<Col N="1311" /> terday in Killarney and I will pass on his views to the Taoiseach and the Government.</P>
    <P>Senator O'Dowd also requested a debate on the health service and, like Senator Jackman, I advise him to participate in the debate on the Health (Miscellaneous Provisions) (No. 2) Bill this afternoon.</P>
    <P>Senator Burke called for debates on sport and funding for the BMW region. I have agreed to make time available for both.</P>
    <P>Order of Business agreed to.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Health (Miscellaneous Provisions) (No. 2) Bill, 2000 [" RHead="Seanad Bill amended by the Dáil ]: Report and Final Stages">
    <Title>Health (Miscellaneous Provisions) (No. 2) Bill, 2000  [  Seanad Bill amended by the Dáil ]  : Report and Final Stages.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="BrianMullooly" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>This is a Seanad Bill which has been amended by the Dáil. In accordance with Standing Order 103, it is deemed to have passed its First, Second and Third Stages in the Seanad and is placed on the Order Paper for Report Stage. On the question &ldquo;That the Bill be received for final consideration&rdquo;, the Minister may explain the purpose of the amendments made by the Dáil. This is looked upon as the report of the Dáil amendments to the Seanad. The only matters, therefore, which may be discussed are the amendments made by the Dáil. For Senators' convenience, I have arranged for copies of those amendments to be made available. As Senators are aware, they may speak only once on Report Stage. I welcome the Minister.</P>
      <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That the Bill be received for final consideration.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelMartin" hpid="Mr. Martin Mr. Martin">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Health and Children (Mr. Martin)</NameTxt>
      <P>I hope not to delay proceedings unduly as I am sure Senators have already contributed to the debate and are keen to make final comments on it. The majority of amendments made to the Bill by the other House are drafting amendments of a technical nature, some of which are consequential on the more significant amendments made. For reasons of clarity, I will go through the amendments made by the other House in the sequence as printed and circulated. However, to avoid taking up time unnecessarily, I will not dwell on technical amendments but will focus on the more significant ones. I will be happy, however, to provide more detail on any technical amendment should Senators require it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Amendments Nos. 1 and 2 are technical amendments to the Long Title required in the context of significant amendments set out later. Amendment No. 3 was introduced in the other House to allow for the automatic extension of the medical card scheme to everyone over the age of 70. In the budget 2001 package, the Government announced its intention to extend eligibility for the medical card to all persons aged 70 and over, <Col N="1312" /> regardless of means, to come into effect on 1 July 2001.</P>
    <P>The background to this measure rests in the Government's decision significantly to improve eligibility for older people in recent years across a range of areas, particularly those which are the responsibility of the Department of Social, Community and Family Affairs. This decision must be seen in the broader context of a key theme of the budget, which was to improve things for the elderly in society generally. These measures included the dramatic increase in the old age pension, the extension of many free schemes to people over 70 and the extension of medical card eligibility.</P>
    <P>In An Action Programme for the Millennium, the Government identified the need to review medical card eligibility for older people and decided that the income guidelines for entitlement to medical cards for persons aged 70 years and over should be doubled. This improvement, which was introduced over a three year period, began on 1 March 1999 and the income guidelines for those aged 70 to 79 and 80 and over, which were already higher than the normal guidelines, increased by one third in 1999. The second stage of this process was implemented on 1 March 2000, followed by implementation of the third stage in March 2001.</P>
    <P>The logical conclusion to the three year programme is the granting of medical cards regardless of means to everyone over the age of 70. The measure goes some way to bringing peace of mind to our older people and a sense of security about their health care. It also acknowledges the wonderful contribution older people have made in building up the country through the difficult times which led to the creation of the tiger economy. Our current prosperity affords us the opportunity to repay our older citizens.</P>
    <P>We should also remember that most people over the age of 70 already have medical cards as a result of the three year programme initiated by the Government. Allowing for estimated increases in the elderly population since the 1996 census, it is estimated that approximately 30,000 people over 70 will receive medical cards as a result of the budget provision.</P>
    <P>Agreement was reached with representatives of the Irish Medical Organisation last month on a number of outstanding industrial relations issues, through the HSEA. As a result the IMO has agreed to meet my Department, again through the HSEA, on the subject of the extension of eligibility to all persons aged 70 and over. I look forward to a positive outcome of these talks and the timely and efficient introduction of the scheme on its official start date, 1 July 2001. Discussions are also taking place with the Irish Pharmaceutical Union on the implications of the measure for pharmacists. The precise cost of the introduction of the medical card scheme will depend on the outcome of the discussions with the IMO and the IPU and I will revert to the House on that matter.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="1313" /> On the conclusion of negotiations with the IMO and the IPU, the Department will embark on a public information campaign over the next few weeks to promote fresh awareness of the budget initiative and to inform those eligible of how they can avail of it. This campaign will be carried out in conjunction with the health boards. Newspaper advertising features, press releases and an insertion on the departmental website are the means being considered to achieve maximum coverage. Furthermore, the relevant section in my Department will continue to give the fullest information available to any person making an inquiry on the subject now or in the future.</P>
    <P>Amendments Nos. 4 and 5 are technical amendments dealing with typographical errors. The background to amendment No. 6 is that section 1(10), as passed by the Seanad, provides for the making of regulations in relation to community pharmacy contractor agreements, including that regulations may provide for the making of appeals to the Minister when an application for a community pharmacy contractor agreement has been refused by a health board. This reflects the current situation where unsuccessful applicants may appeal to the Minister for Health and Children. I indicated on Committee Stage in this House that I was not convinced that the Minister of the day should have this function and that I was examining the matter with a view to proposing an amendment in the Dáil. As the person ultimately responsible for the regulations, it is not ideal that the Minister for Health and Children should also be the decision maker in appeals by unsuccessful applicants for community pharmacy contractor agreements. The amendment made by the Dáil will, therefore, allow the establishment of an independent appeals body, thus ensuring the continuation of a transparent, equitable and accessible appeals system.</P>
    <P>Amendments Nos. 7 and 8 are technical amendments of a drafting nature. Amendment No. 9 is also essentially a technical amendment. A definition of supervising pharmacist in this amendment reflects current practice and is directly in line with the provisions of the Pharmacy Act, 1962.</P>
    <P>Amendments Nos. 10 and 11 were made following advice from the Attorney General's office that the recommended maximum limits for monetary penalties for summary offences are to be raised from £1,500 to 3,000, about £2,362, to allow for inflation since 1994 when the £1,500 limit was first established. This has allowed me to raise the maximum fine for the sale of tobacco products to persons under the age of 18 years to £2,000. That matter was the subject of considerable debate when the Bill was introduced in this House.</P>
    <P>Amendment No. 12 deals with regulations made under the Nursing Homes Act, 1990, an Act which is amended by the Bill. As Senators will be aware, the report of the Ombudsman into the nursing home subvention scheme was published earlier this year. The report deals, <i>inter alia</i>, with <Col N="1314" /> the role of the Department of Health and Children in making regulations and overseeing the introduction of the subvention scheme.</P>
    <P>Chapter 8 of the report draws some far-reaching conclusions as to how Government operates under the Constitution. The report goes on to make a number of suggestions as to how the position might be improved, including the development of a mechanism for monitoring secondary legislation by affirmative resolutions of the Oireachtas. This general question is one which must be addressed in the context of wide consultation and careful consideration of all the implications. However, in light of the Ombudsman's report, I introduced an amendment to the Bill in the Lower House to provide that regulations under the Nursing Homes Act, 1990, shall be laid in draft before both Houses of the Oireachtas and that the regulations shall not be made until a resolution approving of the draft has been passed by each House.</P>
    <P>I indicated my agreement to amendment No. 13 during the Dáil debate on Committee Stage and it was agreed on Report Stage in the Dáil. It provides that the Minister for Health and Children will make a report each year to each House of the Oireachtas on the measures taken by health boards in the preceding year to address the problem of suicide. This amendment does not refer specifically to the number of suicides each year as this information is already available to the Oireachtas by way of the annual report of the Central Statistics Office which is laid before both Houses. However, I am advised that this fact would not preclude the Minister from referring to, or commenting on, the number of suicides in the course of his or her report. In this regard I am pleased to inform the House that the CSO's recently published statistics show that the number of deaths from suicide has fallen for the second year in a row. There were 413 registered suicides in 2000. This represented a decrease on the 1999 figure of 439 and a significant decrease on the 1998 figure of 504. However, while this is a welcome development, we must not become complacent. I intend to ensure that the good work now under way in the health boards' suicide prevention programmes continues and is further developed in the coming years.</P>
    <P>Amendment No. 14 is a technical amendment which excludes the Tobacco (Health Promotion and Protection) Act, 1998, from the collective citation for the Health Acts, 1947 to 2001. The Tobacco (Health Promotion and Protection) Act, 1998, is included in the collective citation in subsection (3) of this section.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MaryJackman" hpid="Mrs. Jackman Mrs. Jackman">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Jackman</NameTxt>
      <P>The technical amendment to which the Minister referred was necessary because the Government did not have the legal framework in place at the time. We are accepting this amendment now, which is consequent to the announcement in the budget granting medical cards to people over 70 years of age. Indeed, as the Minister stated, people over 70 well deserve <Col N="1315" /> such a measure which will be crucial for their continued good health. Fine Gael's policy is to extend the free medical card scheme to people over 65, in addition to children up to the age of 18 and those in continuing education. In extending the scheme to those over 70, the Minister has in mind a very small group.</P>
      <P>There is no doubt that serious health issues are faced by people in the 65 to 69 age bracket. As of 1 January 2001, £162 is the medical card income guideline for a married couple aged between 66 and 69 but their old age contributory pension is £183, which is £21 above the medical card limit. While there is a favourable balance towards the elderly, the scheme should at least be extended to those over 65. It is rather miserly of the Minister to take 70 years as a cut-off point. He could have been more generous by amending the Health Acts to include all young people under 18 years of age and those in continuing education.</P>
      <P>I have many times met women, particularly, who cannot afford to pay for spectacles or eye tests and so on because they prioritise the health of their young children and husbands and do not get an opportunity to look after their own health. Irish women are extremely badly off by comparison to other European women in terms of their state of health, particularly in the areas of cancer and heart disease. A contributory factor is that women unselfishly do not look after their health if they are above the eligibility threshold for a medical card because the cost of doing so is astronomical and they prioritise the health of their children and husbands above their own.</P>
      <P>Granting medical cards to everyone aged over 70 years is a sop. The Minister had the money to implement the Fine Gael policy which was to reduce the age limit to 65 years and provide medical cards for all those aged under 18 years and those in continuing education in line with our European neighbours.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="CamillusGlynn" hpid="Mr. Glynn Mr. Glynn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Glynn</NameTxt>
      <P>Ba mhaith liom fáilte a chur roimh an Aire go dtí an Teach. I welcome the return of the Bill to the House. It has consolidated elements of the various Health Acts to which the old adage, &ldquo;Too many cooks spoil the broth&rdquo;, applied. I congratulate the Minister and his Department on addressing the problem. I welcome the amendments to the legislation, not least in regard to nursing home regulations. It was important that this area of heath care was identified as being in need of rectification and addressed by the Minister. We all read newspapers and were aware of the malpractices in some nursing homes and it was essential that they were addressed.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The Government will provide medical cards for everybody aged over 70 years. My colleague on the other side of the House, Senator Jackman, stated medical cards should be provided for all young people aged under 18 years. Was her party not a member of the Government which abolished medical cards for those under 18 years and <Col N="1316" /> linked their eligibility for such cards to the means of their parents? If their parents were entitled to a medical card, so were they. It is important that the people who were pathfinders and built Ireland into the great state it is are rewarded by the Government. The provision of medical cards for everyone aged over 70 years is one important step in that direction.</P>
    <P>The regulation regarding suicide is crucial, given the incidence of suicide in recent years. I am a member of the Joint Committee on Health and Children, as are Senators Jackman and Fitzpatrick, and we have received submissions from groups whose members have been adversely affected by tobacco consumption during the years. We are considering submissions, reports and evidence from those who have been affected by tobacco products and those who supply them. The World Health Organisation regards smoking and tobacco-related illness as a global epidemic causing four million to die prematurely each year and estimates that ten million will die annually from smoking by 2030. These figures are a dreadful indictment of these deadly products, yet they are legal.</P>
    <P>I welcome the increase in the fine from £1,500 to £2,000 and I congratulate the Minister and the Members of the other House, irrespective of the direction from which the proposal came, because £1,500 was minuscule. The fine should be an even greater amount. There will be no hiding place from this regulation for those who sell tobacco products to children and young people up to the age of 18. I ask the Minister to raise the age limit even further in the coming years because there is only one place for the people who sell cigarettes to children and young people, and that is behind bars or, at a minimum, they should be put out of business. I spoke on the Bill previously. I commend it to the House.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MaryHenry" hpid="Dr. Henry Dr. Henry">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Henry</NameTxt>
      <P>I welcome the Minister to the House. As he knows, there has been a considerable amount of excitement in my profession over the extension of eligibility for medical cards to those aged over 70. There is a good deal of merit in that because a considerable number of people are on small private pensions not much over the limits on which other old age pensioners get medical cards, and it will be a major gain to them. It was unfortunate, however, that the Minister did not discuss the matter with the medical profession before he went ahead with it but perhaps the man who runs the health service &ndash; he who lives in the Department of Finance &ndash; would not let him do that. It would have been a help if they had felt they were forewarned before they found it included in the Finance Bill.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The over 70s are major users of the medical service and, from what the Minister said, he does not appear to have made an agreement with family doctors on how this service will be supplied. It is a difficult issue because patients are much more demanding now and they expect a better service from their family doctor. The establishment and <Col N="1317" /> operation of a practice costs a great deal more and the remuneration for taking care of medical card patients is not that high. I hope the Minister can come to an amicable solution with them in the near future because there is a considerable number of people over 70 who are just over the eligibility level and it is much better to have them treated at primary care level rather than have them end up in accident and emergency departments. I have frequently seen people in, say, cardiac failure which they might have avoided if they had been regularly attending their doctor.</P>
    <P>I hope this issue is amicably settled between the Minister and family doctors because primary care is an area which we have neglected in our discussions about the problems in the health service. What is happening in accident and emergency is very dramatic so it is much easier to forget what may be going on in primary care. I hope the Minister manages to come to an amicable conclusion of his discussions with the Irish Medical Organisation, the College of General Practitioners and so forth.</P>
    <P>Any efforts the Minister makes in rationalising the position with pharmacies is most welcome. The possibility of deregulation must be the next item so that there is a wider number of pharmacies in society. It is an exclusive business currently, as the Minister is well aware. It is easy to say that once the price of drugs is decided in town, that is the price it shall be.</P>
    <P>I am also interested in the position regarding the use of pharmaceutical products on the Internet. As the Minister knows, the Irish Medicines Board spoke about this matter recently and I hope its funding will always be sufficient to investigate these areas because they are important. I heard Dr. Gilvarry speak about the importation of Botox from sites on the Internet for the treatment of wrinkles and other cosmetic surgery. Some international sites sell Viagra, U486 and all sorts of antibiotics, but I do not know how we can regulate the importation of these drugs. If we cannot stop large quantities of heroin coming in, how are we going to stop small packets of pharmaceutical products? We must ensure the Irish Medicines Board has sufficient resources to continue to investigate these areas.</P>
    <P>Some of the Internet sites do not even require a doctor's prescription, or only require the most rudimentary prescription. In many cases they will know little of the patient's history. It was reported some time ago that 86 sites in America were selling Viagra without prescriptions, without carrying out any investigation of the patient's condition or inquiring about other drugs which the patient may be taking. We need to be vigilant about this area.</P>
    <P>The reduction in the suicide rate is excellent news and makes one feel that the work of people such as Deputy Neville and others has been worthwhile. We are constantly addressing the number of suicides among young people. However, there have been depressing articles about suicides among older people, particularly <Col N="1318" /> among men over 65 years of age. These articles have highlighted issues of loneliness, depression, feelings of isolation and failure which need to be addressed. This is primarily an issue for social services rather than a medical issue. I would not wish to see loneliness being &ldquo;medicalised&rdquo;, but we should pay more attention to the issue.</P>
    <P>I am delighted by the increase in the fine for selling tobacco to children. The last occasion on which I objected to a child being sold cigarettes in a shop in Donnybrook, the owner said, &ldquo;But I know his mother.&rdquo; I said, &ldquo;I don't care if you know the whole family. This is against the law.&rdquo; Why is the fine not given in euros? Everyone else is converting to euros.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelMartin" hpid="Mr. Martin Mr. Martin">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Martin</NameTxt>
      <P>I got this far.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryHenry" hpid="Dr. Henry Dr. Henry">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Henry</NameTxt>
      <P>Is it too late to change the fine to 2,000 which would be a little more than £1,500? That would cheer Senator Glynn as the Seanad would have increased the fine.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelMartin" hpid="Mr. Martin Mr. Martin">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Martin</NameTxt>
      <P>The fine is going up to £2,000 which more or less corresponds with the euro amount.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FergusODowdFG" hpid="Mr. O'Dowd Mr. O'Dowd">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Dowd</NameTxt>
      <P>I welcome the Minister. There are some welcome provisions in the Bill, but other issues have been omitted. I welcome the extension of the medical card to senior citizens over 70 years of age. This is an effective recognition of their health status and the contribution pensioners have made to society.</P>
      <P>I am concerned by some of the comments of the medical profession regarding this provision. As the Minister acknowledged, senior citizens built up this country. They made the sacrifices, paid their taxes and did their duty. As people get older, they need the services of a doctor more regularly. Therefore, it is a positive and constructive measure to assist their health needs by giving the medical card to those over 70 years, regardless of income. This is what the Minister is proposing. It may be that people over 70 years will use health services more regularly. In the light of this possibility, the Minister should reach an agreement with the medical profession regarding an increased capitation for those in this age bracket. This may resolve the difficulties. However, there is no doubt that those over 70 years should have a medical card.</P>
      <P>Senator Jackman referred to the fact that some do not have a medical card. Health boards are pursuing an aggressive policy in terms of reviewing medical card eligibility. Fewer people have a medical card now than when the Government took office four years ago. This is wrong. There are those who do not have a medical card, despite the fact that they are on low income. Thousands of people in the north-east are losing their medical card because their income is above the limit. The Minister must address the fact that the income limit for medical cards is not keeping pace with inflation.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="1319" /> Senator Jackman also referred to the issue of young people and medical cards. Like me the Minister was a teacher and he will be aware that the incidence of asthma is very high among young people. Some 20% of children in the north-east are asthmatic. The Department of Health and Children estimates that extending medical cards to asthmatics would cost approximately £600 per person. The £42 drug limit does not meet their needs. Significant numbers of families on low incomes who have children with asthma are not entitled to medical cards. It is, therefore, unacceptable that the medical card scheme has not been extended to asthmatics. While it would cost money it is proper and fair to do so.</P>
    <P>There are thousands of admissions to hospitals as a result of asthma attacks, yet many parents do not have the money to pay their doctor for advice on whether different inhalers or medication is required. As a result many people, including asthmatics, are suffering under the Minster's health policy because they are not being looked after. The Asthma Society of Ireland makes clear demands on all political parties. Asthmatics should be given medical cards.</P>
    <P>Senator Glynn referred to the nursing homes regulations. The Minister rightly proposes they must be brought before the Houses of the Oireachtas before they are changed. We have repeatedly asked the Leader of the House to arranged a debate on the health services. Is the Minister prepared to participate in such a debate?</P>
    <P>Each health board has a team of doctors and nurses who seek to enforce the numerous nursing home regulations but they have far too many other responsibilities. They do not have the capacity, time or the dedicated staff to deal with them. As a result they are inadequately enforced. By law the health boards are required to visit homes twice per annum. That is all they can do at present but it is not enough.</P>
    <P>The Minister must establish an independent group of inspectors separate from the health boards who will enforce these regulations. What is happening in some of these homes is disgraceful and unacceptable. I have requested some of the inspectors' reports under the Freedom of Information Act. When I have received them all I hope to make them public. They make for shameful reading. Many nursing homes are doing an excellent job but the Minister must look at this issue urgently because the health boards do not have the capacity to deal with it. He must act to protect our senior citizens. While I welcome his move to ensure that regulations are brought before the Houses of the Oireachtas for debate more often, nothing is happening at present.</P>
    <P>The Department is spending millions of pounds per annum on nursing homes subvention. In the Eastern Regional Health Authority approximately £25 million per annum of taxpayers' money is being allocated to subventions to nursing homes, yet the implementation of the regulations is not good enough. I hope the Minister <Col N="1320" /> will respond to this when the facts are before him. I am not happy that adequate attention is being paid to this area by him and this Administration. It badly needs to be investigated at the highest level.</P>
    <Speaker pid="DermotFitzpatrickFF" hpid="Dr. Fitzpatrick Dr. Fitzpatrick">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Fitzpatrick</NameTxt>
      <P>I welcome the Minister to the House. I congratulate him on the excellent work he is doing in the Department of Health and Children, a difficult Department to run due to the constant demands and expectations of people.</P>
      <P>I am in favour of people over 70 getting medical cards without their having to have a means test. One of the big problems regarding getting old is the fear of ill health. For various reasons, many elderly people tend to postpone trips to the doctor or the receipt of care if they have to pay the bill themselves. If for no other reason than to eliminate this problem, the medical card should be welcomed for people over 70.</P>
      <P>I hope that this is only the beginning of free primary health care for everybody, not just the over 70s. This cannot be achieved overnight, but it should be the aim of the current and future Governments to bring it into effect. Some 90% of people who attend a GP do not need to go further &ndash; they do not require secondary or tertiary care. Ultimately, the extension of medical cards to everybody would be a worthwhile investment in the health of the people.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryJackman" hpid="Mrs. Jackman Mrs. Jackman">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Jackman</NameTxt>
      <P>I agree.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DermotFitzpatrickFF" hpid="Dr. Fitzpatrick Dr. Fitzpatrick">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Fitzpatrick</NameTxt>
      <P>I agree with Senator O'Dowd in that I too would welcome a wide-ranging discussion on the health services, not with a view to picking faults but to looking at their future development. Having entered the third millennium, we are moving from the poor law system upon which the health services are based to a far more sophisticated and well-funded system, a system upon which there are many demands. I would also like a discussion on the setting up of a health inspectorate similar to the inspectorate of mental hospitals, but extended to all health facilities.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FergusODowdFG" hpid="Mr. O'Dowd Mr. O'Dowd">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Dowd</NameTxt>
      <P>Hear, hear.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DermotFitzpatrickFF" hpid="Dr. Fitzpatrick Dr. Fitzpatrick">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Fitzpatrick</NameTxt>
      <P>One may think this would establish a vast bureaucracy, but we will need an independent, stand-alone, ombudsman or health inspectorate, somebody between the patient and the providers of the services who would have a value-free stance on whatever problems arose.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelMartin" hpid="Mr. Martin Mr. Martin">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Health and Children (Mr. Martin)</NameTxt>
      <P>I thank the Senators for their contributions to the debate. I particularly welcome the support on both sides of the House for the extension of the medical card to those over 70. Many desired that it should be extended further. It is important that the Oireachtas will be endorsing unanimously the decision to extend medical cards to people over 70. It is an important signal to society, demonstrating how we value older people. As Senator <Col N="1321" /> Fitzpatrick said, primary care is an essential feature of older people's lives and they should not be, in any way, inhibited from visiting a GP.</P>
      <P>As Senator Henry pointed out, we have to conclude negotiations with the Irish Medical Organisation. The Government has made its decision in this regard. We could not consult in advance of the budgetary decision and one does not normally do so. We do not negotiate the rate of the old age pension or the extension of the free schemes under the social welfare code. There is secrecy attached to the preparation and eventual publication of a budget and the medical card extension was part of that. Nonetheless, once a decision is made, it gains certain momentum and I am satisfied we will be able to implement it on 1 July.</P>
      <P>I am conscious of the role of general practice and the Government has sanctioned me to engage in the most fundamental review of general practice since the foundation of the State in collaboration with the Irish College for General Practitioners and the Irish Medical Organisation, each of which has outlined its vision of general practice in the future.</P>
      <P>Six weeks ago, we concluded an agreement with the Irish Medical Organisation in respect of a number of items it had raised. One item concerned additional allowances for practice nurses with GPs, additional allowances for secretaries of GPs, once-off payments for the GPs who are treating asylum seekers and payments for GPs in respect of the discretionary medical card. The Irish Medical Organisation has been seeking additional payments for GPs because there are thousands of discretionary medical cards that were not accounted for in terms of payments to GPs because of the discretion the chief executive officers have in the respective health boards. The full impact of that agreement, signed six weeks ago, was in the order of £10 million. The Irish Medical Organisation would have engaged in discussions earlier, but one member, Dr. Michael Boland, was recently elected president of the World Organisation of Family Doctors. Many GPs were in South Africa celebrating his success, something of which the country is very proud.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryJackman" hpid="Mrs. Jackman Mrs. Jackman">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Jackman</NameTxt>
      <P>He is a Corkman to boot.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelMartin" hpid="Mr. Martin Mr. Martin">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Martin</NameTxt>
      <P>Obviously, he is a Corkman to boot, from Skibereen. Negotiations are commencing this week on the finalisation of the issues. There was a lot of debate on the issue of means for people over 70. My view is that very few of the millionaire set would be utilising this particular facility.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Senators Jackman, O'Dowd and Fitzpatrick raised the issue of wider eligibility for medical cards. That is being examined in the context of the health strategy that is being prepared. A sub-group has been formed to consider eligibility for medical cards and the health services in general. There are a number of ways by which we can approach this. We can do so on an income threshold basis alone. In other words, we should <Col N="1322" /> increase the income threshold incrementally over time. However, that does not account for asthma sufferers or those with specific diseases or conditions. This must be examined because there are people with long-term chronic illnesses, many of whom represent small minorities. I have come across many such groups, often comprising no more than 100 people, but their condition requires ongoing regular contact with GPs and a need for medication. The existing scheme does not adequately facilitate people in that category.</P>
    <P>Do we continue with the concept of age-specific eligibility? We have taken an important decision in this regard where people over 70 are concerned. There is much concern about children in that they are a target group in terms of medical needs and their parents' peace of mind. All these competing approaches to widening eligibility for the medical card must be balanced, and our strategy aims to do that. In terms of a broader widening across all age groups, the income threshold offers, on a financial equity basis, a preferred approach. However, we must look at some of the existing schemes regarding children, particularly babies, and improve them for all concerned.</P>
    <P>We have estimated that if we brought in free GP cover for everyone, not including the cost of medication, it would cost about £600 million &ndash; that is an approximation &ndash; while the cost of providing medical card cover would be about £800 million. This must be considered in the context of the bed capacity review that we have completed and the number of beds we need, the huge capital infrastructural projects needed in the health service and the extra consultants identified in the manpower forum. The desire to fulfil the EU working directive criterion will involve bringing junior doctors' working time down to 48 hours within nine years. This will reduce the ratios between full-time consultants and junior doctors and, if we are really moving towards a consultant-provided service as opposed to a consultant-led service, have significant financial implications, not only in terms of the extra consultants required but in terms of extra backup staff, nurses, paramedics and so on.</P>
    <P>There are no quick-fix, easy solutions to all this and we must look at the free medical card, GP for all issue in the broader context of prioritising what is possible, realistic or desirable within the next seven years. Some have argued that perhaps it is more desirable to get the matter of quality in the existing services correct before we expand access to a service which is not delivering to those currently endeavouring to avail of it.</P>
    <P>With regard to penalties for selling tobacco to under age individuals, we cannot go beyond 3,000 because it is a District Court type offence. After much pressing with our legal advisers, we have gone up to £2,000, which is about £200 less than 3,000. I am advised that this is as far as we can go. A more comprehensive tobacco Bill has nearly completed its drafting stage. This will have a significant impact on people's behaviour and consumption of tobacco.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="1323" /> The recent all-island report on cancer makes for quite frightening reading in terms of the incidence of cancer, particularly in urban areas, where it is running at about 10% higher than in rural areas. Lifestyle factors seem to have a profound impact on cancer levels. Diet is a big issue, in terms of eating fruit and vegetables and so on, but cigarette smoking is the key issue. It is the one preventable measure which is within our power to take that would have a major impact on cancer statistics in the future. There are currently 2,000 deaths per year from lung cancer alone, which is almost entirely preventable. As everyone knows, we top the European league table for heart disease.</P>
    <P>The House has been very supportive and when the Bill was first discussed there were some ringing declarations of support for whatever I wanted to do, in terms of being tough on tobacco and so on. I appreciate that support from all sides of the House. I may look for that kind of support throughout the summer, because I am looking at other issues to try to improve the situation. We have been too complacent on environmental and passive smoking. We can initiate certain new measures under existing laws, and I think we are going to have to do so. The all-island cancer report is a very significant wake-up call, if we needed one. We need to get our act together as a society for the future. Unfortunately all the lifestyle research surveys, such as SLAN, are showing us that the behaviour and lifestyle patterns of the younger generation are no better than their predecessors. In some instances they are becoming worse, in terms of alcohol consumption generally and cigarette smoking among young women.</P>
    <P>I endorse what has been said about suicide and what Senator Henry said with regard to an increase in suicide among older people. The downward trend in the last two years may be an indication of the effective work of bodies such as the Suicide Research Foundation and the National Suicidology Association, which is headed by Deputy Dan Neville and others. The increased budgetary allocation for research into awareness and greater services within the health boards may also be paying dividends. It is too early to say, but we hope that is the case, and that we can continue to improve our services.</P>
    <P>We are dramatically increasing funding for the improvement of psychiatric services, particularly in the area of child and adolescent psychiatry. At the end of this year we will have for the first time a consultant-led service in this area. This is particularly important. It was obviously a huge deficiency that we did not have this basic service in some health board areas.</P>
    <P>I take Senator O'Dowd's point on nursing homes, although we also have to accept and acknowledge that whereas health boards are charged with the responsibility of inspecting private nursing homes, no one has responsibility for inspecting public sector nursing units under the care of health boards. We are going to give <Col N="1324" /> additional powers to the social services inspectorate to conduct inspections of all health board run nursing homes. We are looking at whether we should extend their remit to cover all nursing homes. This would involve significant resourcing of the social services inspectorate, which was initially focused on child care, which was also very badly needed as we have seen from recent reports that it has conducted on our behalf. Rome was not built in a day. We acknowledge that we need to improve our inspectorial regime with regard to the care of the elderly, an area in which ultimately the social services inspectorate will have an increasing role to play.</P>
    <P>In reply to Senator O'Dowd, the reduction in medical cards for the general population is due to the economic boom and the fact that we have reduced unemployment so dramatically in the last three years. Three years ago some 200,000 to 300,000 people were unemployed. We are now down to an unemployment rate of almost 3%. This will clearly have a huge impact on eligibility for medical cards because people are now earning money instead of being on the dole. Nonetheless, as part of our strategic review we will look at increasing eligibility from the current level of some 31% to 32% to a higher percentage of the population.</P>
    <Speaker pid="FergusODowdFG" hpid="Mr. O'Dowd Mr. O'Dowd">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Dowd</NameTxt>
      <P>Single parents on low incomes going back to work is a major issue.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelMartin" hpid="Mr. Martin Mr. Martin">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Martin</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes, I am aware that is a major issue that needs to be addressed.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>Question, &ldquo;That the Bill do now pass&rdquo;, put and agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Women's Cancer Strategy:" RHead="Statements">
    <Title>Women's Cancer Strategy: Statements.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelMartin" hpid="Mr. Martin Mr. Martin">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Health and Children (Mr. Martin)</NameTxt>
      <P>I am pleased to be given the opportunity today to brief the House on developments to date under the national cancer strategy and outline the areas of cancer services which have been particularly targeted under the strategy with regard to women's health and women's cancers.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The reorganisation of our cancer treatment services was an integral part of the 1994 health strategy, Shaping a Healthier Future, and targets were set for reducing the mortality from cancer in the under 65 year old age group by 15 % in the period 1994 to 2004. Health care services were to be focused on improvements in health status and quality of life and increased emphasis was to be placed on the provision of the most appropriate care for patients. Cancer was identified as one of the major sources of premature mortality in Ireland. The effect of cancer on health status in Ireland is striking. There was a clear need to address this and the national cancer strategy emerged as an evidence based initiative to enable high quality cancer services to be developed <Col N="1325" /> throughout the country. Included in the national cancer strategy was the commitment to develop screening programmes in the area of breast cancer and cervical cancer.</P>
    <P>The two principal objectives of the national cancer strategy are; to take all measures possible to reduce rates of illness and death from cancer, in line with the targets established in Shaping a Healthier Future and ensure those who develop cancer receive the most effective care and treatment and that their quality of life is enhanced to the greatest extent possible.</P>
    <P>There are specific objectives in relation to key elements of the cancer strategy concerning such areas as prevention of cancers for which a cause is known or suspected, access to equitable, effective, quality services throughout the country, improved quality of life for patients, appropriate multi-disciplinary treatment administered safely and in accordance with best practice guidelines, greater co-ordination of cancer treatment services from primary care to hospital care through to rehabilitation and palliative care, promotion of arrangements for appropriate research and education for those providing cancer services and a co-ordinated approach by all those involved in the care and treatment of patients with cancer to ensure all services are provided in a cost-effective manner.</P>
    <P>There are specific objectives in relation to key elements of the cancer strategy concerning such areas as prevention of cancers for which a cause is known or suspected; access to equitable, effective, quality services throughout the country; improved quality of life for patients; appropriate multi-disciplinary treatment administered safely and in accordance with best practice guidelines; greater co-ordination of cancer treatment services from primary care to hospital care through to rehabilitation and palliative care; promotion of arrangements for appropriate research and education for those providing cancer services; and a co-ordinated approach by all those involved in the care and treatment of patients with cancer to ensure that all services are provided in a cost-effective manner.</P>
    <P>A range of support structures were put in place to co-ordinate and take a lead role in the implementation of the national cancer strategy. The first National Cancer Forum, under the chairmanship of Professor James Fennelly, was established. The forum, a multi-disciplinary body, proved to be an extremely useful body and advised on many issues central to the successful implementation of the strategy. The term of office of the first forum expired last year and I subsequently appointed Professor Paul Redmond as chairman of the second National Cancer Forum. The forum is currently examining a number of issues of tremendous importance to the effective progression of the development of cancer services in this country. Areas such as protocols for the care and treatment of cancer patients, information requirements and audit and evaluation of our services are all important component parts of the appro<Col N="1326" /> priate future development of cancer services, and the forum, as the established expert advisory body, will report to me on these issues.</P>
    <P>Regional directors of cancer services were appointed in each health board area to oversee and co-ordinate the development of cancer services in their respective areas in conjunction with the chief executive officers of the health boards. The regional directors are proving to be of great benefit in assisting in the development of appropriate future cancer services.</P>
    <P>I am very pleased to report to the House today that there has been considerable and tangible progress to date under the national cancer strategy. The strategy has been progressed far beyond the original commitments made in the action plan for its implementation.</P>
    <P>The implementation of the national cancer strategy was estimated to cost £25 million when it was launched. The sum allocated for the strategy in 1997 was £6 million. Since then the Government has invested £54 million in cancer prevention, treatment and care services, including £11 million last year and almost £19 million this year. All the commitments made in the action plan for the implementation of the strategy have been fully funded and are implemented or are in the course of implementation. The main implementation elements of the strategy included the areas of cancer prevention, early detection and screening, additional consultant appointments in key areas of cancer treatment and care and cancer research.</P>
    <P>There have been a number of key consultant appointments since the commencement of implementation of the national cancer strategy. There have been 55 additional consultant appointments in the areas of medical oncology, haematology, histopathology, palliative care and specialist surgery. In addition, new consultant appointments have been approved in the specialty of radiation and clinical oncology at St. Luke's Hospital, Dublin.</P>
    <P>Cancers occur as a result of the interplay between genetic and environmental factors. Risk of cancer depends on age, sex, genetic make-up and where and how people live. To some extent certain aspects of cancer risk are within our control. There is strong evidence that lifestyle and environmental factors play an important role in the development of cancer. The use of tobacco, the excessive consumption of alcohol and unhealthy diet contribute to increasing the risk of developing cancer. It is important that the public is made aware of the scope for preventing many cancers by making appropriate lifestyle changes. To this end, the health promotion unit of my Department supports an extensive range of initiatives that have an impact on the levels of knowledge and awareness of the risk factors associated with many cancers. These include mass media campaigns on anti-smoking, alcohol awareness and healthy eating. The unit also provides funding to the Irish Cancer Society in support of <Col N="1327" /> cancer prevention initiatives, including the yearly Europe Against Cancer campaign.</P>
    <P>As more and more people are aware, the prevention and reduction of skin cancer can be achieved by a vigilant approach to sun exposure and artificial forms of UV radiation. Utilising sun protective clothing and creams as well as early detection can reduce deaths from skin cancer. Early detection of melanoma can be facilitated by consulting a physician if a mole changes shape, size or colour. People must be informed of the risk associated with sunburn. To this end the health promotion unit has put concise information on this subject into booklet form and made it widely available.</P>
    <P>BreastCheck, the national breast screening programme, commenced in February 2000. Phase one of the programme covers the Eastern Regional Health Authority, the North Eastern Health Board and the Midland Health Board areas. Screening is being offered free of charge to all women in the target age group of 50 to 64 years on an area by area basis.</P>
    <P>In the period January to March 2001 approximately 2,700 women per month were screened at the BreastCheck units and approximately 700 women per month were screened on the mobile unit. Less than 1% of those screened are admitted to hospital for further management.</P>
    <P>The board of BreastCheck has reviewed progress to date and has informed me that it is pleased with the uptake of women in the areas screened so far, with uptake having virtually reached its target level of 70%, while meeting the quality parameters set and providing evidence of a significant level of screen detected cancers.</P>
    <P>The successful roll-out of the programme is dependent on a number of factors, including the availability of appropriately trained staff. BreastCheck offers suitably skilled radiographers the opportunity of working in state-of-the-art facilities as well as an attractive employment package. The board has taken a number of initiatives to address the issue of the current shortage of suitably skilled radiographers, including an international advertising programme. BreastCheck, in conjunction with the School of Diagnostic Imaging at the Faculty of Medicine, UCD, has set up a post-graduate diploma in mammographic imaging, the first of its kind in Ireland. This joint initiative aims to increase levels of mammographic trained radiographers in Ireland and share the experiences of BreastCheck with other mammography services.</P>
    <P>The board of BreastCheck plans to carry out a feasibility study nationally on the availability of skilled staff for the programme and this is expected to be complete in a number of months. It expects to make recommendations to me regarding the extension of the programme to the rest of the country later this year. Breast screening has a significant part to play in reducing morbidity and mortality from breast cancer. I am committed to the extension of BreastCheck to <Col N="1328" /> ensure that women throughout the country have the highest quality breast screening services available to them. This involves not only screening services, but also the availability of quality symptomatic services so that an equally high standard of hospital care is available for those who may require it following a screening detected cancer.</P>
    <P>BreastCheck is providing an excellent, intensely quality assured service for screened women who believe that they are healthy and for the treatment of the women who, through screening, are discovered to have breast cancer. It is essential that this service is matched by an equally excellent service for those with symptomatic breast disease. As the plans for the commencement of BreastCheck progressed, it soon became apparent that the symptomatic breast cancer services in this country were not provided in the manner which would or should lead to the best outcomes for women. International experience tells us that women who are treated in a multi-disciplinary centre where all the relevant medical expertise is on one site and where there is a minimum number of patients with similar disease treated by the same team have a greater chance of long-term survival and have less of a chance of their disease recurring than those treated in smaller centres.</P>
    <P>Having regard to these concerns, my predecessor, Deputy Cowen, requested the National Cancer Forum to review symptomatic breast disease services nationally. The forum established a sub-group to undertake this task. The report on the development of services for symptomatic breast disease was presented to me in April last year. I accepted the broad thrust of this report and established an advisory group to meet all the health boards to advise and assist in formulating regional plans for the implementation of the report.</P>
    <P>Concerns were raised in many areas because of a perceived notion that certain smaller hospitals around the country would be downgraded if they did not maintain their mammography services. I stress to the House that this report was not about the downgrading or closure of any hospital. It is about the reorganisation and development of breast disease services in centres of excellence to ensure that every effort is made to reduce the number of women in this country who die from breast cancer every year. I have provided funding of over £4 million this year to enable a number of agencies to commence the development of at least seven centres of excellence for the treatment of symptomatic breast disease. Funding has been allocated to the Eastern Regional Health Authority, the Midland Health Board, the North Eastern Health Board, the South Eastern Health Board, the Southern Health Board and the Western Health Board.</P>
    <P>The National Registry Board reports that between 1994 and 1997 cervical cancer accounted for an average of 74 deaths in Ireland each year, with cervical cancer being more common in older women. The report, Developing a Policy for <Col N="1329" /> Women's Health, states that while cervical screening is simple, quick and relatively inexpensive, not all women respond to requests to attend for screening. It has been found that women in the lower socio-economic groups may fail to do so and it is mainly among these groups that deaths from cervical cancer occur. Experts in the Europe Against Cancer programme recommend that women between the age of 25 and 60 years should have a cervical smear regularly and should participate in organised screening programmes where available.</P>
    <P>With these considerations in mind, phase one of the national cervical screening programme commenced in the Mid-Western Health Board area in October 2000. Under the programme, in the region of 67,000 women aged from 25 to 60 years will be screened free of charge at minimum intervals of five years. The question of extending the programme to the rest of the country is under consideration by my Department in conjunction with the chief executive officers of the health boards and the expert advisory group on cervical screening.</P>
    <P>As the House will gather, I am very well aware of the issues relating to women's cancers. The considerable investment under the national cancer strategy will undoubtedly enhance the quality of services available to women, provide further ease of access to these services by providing for the development of quality services on a regional basis and ensure that those who develop cancer receive the appropriate treatment administered safely in accordance with established best practice. I am committed to the further implementation of the national cancer strategy to ensure that women who develop cancer have available to them the best, safest and most effective treatment and so have the best opportunity for long-term survival.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MaryJackman" hpid="Mrs. Jackman Mrs. Jackman">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Jackman</NameTxt>
      <P>I welcome the Minister to the House. I listened carefully to his contribution, and while I accept that the Minister is a compassionate man, I found his speech sterile in that it concerned funding and programmes but lacked feeling for the issue of cancer among women. When women hear they have cancer they initially believe that it is their death knell, although many cancers are treatable if caught early. If women are screened they have a high incidence of survival and can lead healthy and happy lives. However, cancer remains a frightening scenario for women. This debate is painful for me due to the many meetings I have attended recently about cancer. Many women would not speak openly up to now but there is a turn in the tide regarding discussion of the subject. Women are now looking for what has been promised for some time.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I was deeply involved with the issue during the time of Deputy Noonan's plan for women's health for the years 1997 to 1999. I have served on health boards and was conscious of what was <Col N="1330" /> happening in the area. Deputy Noonan, as Minister for Health and Children, set about a consultation process. That was a major reason women came forward. Deputy Noonan worked on policy with the National Women's Council and there was accountability on both sides. Both contributed their plans for women's health to the debate, and there was an aspiration to bring the health of Irish women up to EU levels. This was in relation to several diseases including heart disease, although we are only looking at cancer today. This process of consultation is extremely important. The Minister must begin such consultation regarding the various types of cancer. He should create increased awareness among women that help is available.</P>
    <P>The Oireachtas Joint Committee on Health and Children has debated the issue of smoking many times, whether it was in relation to proposals from Deputy Shatter or the current Government. However, there is little reduction in the incidence of smoking, and I speak as an observer of young people. It does not matter if cigarettes rise to an abnormal price; young people are still smoking and contributing seriously to ill health in the future. Irreparable damage is done even during the teenage years. There has been an impression that if a person gives up smoking, things will be fine. However, teenage and younger lungs are so tender that the damage done is very serious, as Senator Fitzpatrick can attest. Nothing seems to get through to young people, despite the most horrific advertisements. I despair of the high incidence of smoking, but the young do not think in terms of their future.</P>
    <P>Cancer accounts for approximately 20% of deaths among women in Ireland, according to the Noonan document on women's health. That is a shocking statistic. It is interesting that the scope for reducing mortality among women is greatest for cancer of the lung, breast and cervix. I am disappointed that there has been little reference &ndash; apart from a public meeting I attended some weeks ago in Limerick &ndash; to the silent killer, ovarian cancer. I was informed at that meeting that a success rate of 80% is attainable if victims are screened and targeted in time. To walk away from such an opportunity is horrific. Ovarian cancer is a type of cancer that has not been referred to enough despite the huge incidence.</P>
    <P>The fatalities per year from cancer among women break down into 500 deaths from lung cancer, 650 deaths from breast cancer and 75 deaths from cervical cancer. These cases should be treatable. Some 20% to 30% of deaths among women could be prevented by a mass screening programme for women aged 50-64. Some 60% of deaths among women from cervical cancer could be prevented by a screening programme for women aged 25-60.</P>
    <P>The Minister referred to skin cancer which claims 50 lives per year &ndash; a high figure considering that there are relatively few days when Ireland has a high sunburn risk. For all types of cancer, it is not enough to say that we are doing <Col N="1331" /> this, that or the other. The Minister should be pioneering. There should not only be screening for a percentage of the population. The target date to have all women screened should not be far off in the future. It should be a high priority to have all women screened now.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelMartin" hpid="Mr. Martin Mr. Martin">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Martin</NameTxt>
      <P>It cannot be done.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryJackman" hpid="Mrs. Jackman Mrs. Jackman">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Jackman</NameTxt>
      <P>It must be done. The Mid-Western Health Board does not operate the BreastCheck programme despite Marian Finucane's plea. Women in the mid-west feel badly about this. I am happy for women in Dublin and other areas who have access to screening. However, women in the mid-west must wait, despite its being a huge area.</P>
      <P>I am not sure whether additional funding or personnel is required. If it is personnel, it is discriminatory that some areas of the country are better served than others. The awareness is there but I would be happier if services were available around the country. All socio-economic groups of women are terrified of cancer. There is no distinction between middle-class women with access to GPs and those in lower socio-economic groups. It does not matter a damn. All are terrified. The idea of cancer is a horrific shock for individuals and their families. That is the reality for women and it grieves me.</P>
      <P>I will refer to a letter which the Minister for Health and Children, Deputy Martin, has received from Cuidiú, the Irish Childbirth Trust. They are looking for three basic facilities in Limerick, where up to 150 people gathered in March to hear a number of guest speakers. They asked for three particular facilities. I am sure the Minister will be familiar with their speakers, Mr. David McVenchie, consultant surgeon, Ms Maeve McGuinness, BreastCheck and Ms Mary Meaney, breast nurse specialist. There was an open forum and a motion was passed that the group would petition for the urgent provision of radiotherapy facilities, a specialist breast unit and BreastCheck phase two.</P>
      <P>Considerable anger was expressed at the meeting about the need for their loved ones to travel to Cork or Dublin for radiotherapy. Travelling long distances is, they stressed, extremely difficult for patients at a time when they are very ill and it places a severe financial and emotional strain on them and their families. I am echoing the voices of women at that meeting and not just saying it myself. The July 2000 report on the need for radiotherapy services for patients of the Mid-Western Health Board stated, &ldquo;In the Mid-Western Health Board region an average of 1,475 new cases of cancer were diagnosed per year between 1994 and 1996&rdquo;. That is an unbelievable figure. The report estimates that 700 of these new cases would require radiotherapy. It stated:</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Patients from the Mid-Western Health Board region currently have to travel to Cork or Dublin for radiotherapy. Both of these jour<Col N="1332" /> neys exceed the 60 minutes by road limit proposed by the Calmen-Hine report.</P>
    <P>I would like the Minister to comment on that. The report also states, &ldquo;Inequity of access to radiotherapy may mean that best practices are not carried out at all times in all health board regions.&rdquo; I consider that to be a question of equality. There were 152 signatures provided to the Minister in support of the report's recommendations that there be two linear accelerators provided in the Mid-Western Health Board region with link up to Dublin and/or Cork.</P>
    <P>They wanted a specialist breast unit established within the region. That is not an extraordinary wish. At present breast cancer services in the health board area is quite fragmented with an <i>ad hoc</i> approach to total patient care, which the people believe has an adverse effect on patient outcome. In order to provide a high quality service and standardisation of breast cancer management, the group recommended to the national cancer forum that one specialist breast unit be established in the regional hospital in Limerick where ancillary services are already available. One specialist breast unit is not too much to ask for. The Minister mentioned that he may not have the back-up or personnel, but they say that ancillary services are already available. That raises a question to be answered.</P>
    <P>Breast screening for women aged between 50 and 64 without symptoms is operational, as we know through advertisements, in the Eastern, North Eastern and Midland health boards areas. Does the Minister have a date for the commencement of phase two? I hope he does because that would extend the service to the rest of the country. The people at that meeting felt that it had led to confusion because they heard the advertisements which were broadcast nationally. It placed an increasing pressure on current breast clinics to provide a screening service. The group concluded by saying that health promotion awareness is high on the agenda of the Department of Health and Children. They asked that phase two commence immediately. They asked how many more women would have to become ill before the Department realised the urgent need for this screening programme. I passed the letter sent to me to the Minister and I hope there will be positive answers to the questions it raises.</P>
    <P>I want to talk about the need for funding for research on the treatment of ovarian cancer. A recent public meeting hosted by the Adare Zonta Club had heard a number of eminent speakers, Dr. Paula Calvert, consultant medical oncologist to the Midland Health Board, and Dr. Yvonne McGarry, clinical biochemist and expert in the field of ovarian cancer. The latter is currently involved in very promising research with the University of Pennsylvania. The meeting was also addressed by Maureen Hogan, a ward sister in the haematological oncology day unit in Limerick. That meeting was attended by over 150 women. They are in addition to those which I have already mentioned. The big issue was that <Col N="1333" /> Dr. McGarry could not get funding. Yet if she produced a particular drug which would help in this area, something that she is in the process of doing, drug companies all over the world would seek to get involved. Because she is in the transitional period approaching a breakthrough she finds its extremely difficult to get funding. She is not asking for very much. She told the meeting that if she secured funding for research that it would have implications not just for ovarian cancer but for other forms of carcinomas.</P>
    <P>There are frightening statistics surrounding ovarian cancer. It is the fifth leading cause of cancer among women and the fourth leading cause of mortality. Up to 85% of women suffering from ovarian cancer can be cured if the cancer is detected in the early stages and 30% if detected in later stages. Ovarian cancer is the saddest of all as it is a silent killer. Women, generally those over 60, have their lives suddenly shortened or ended by it.</P>
    <P>I am subdued in this debate. I find that there is not a family that has not been affected by cancer. For some unknown reason in recent years deaths from prostate cancer in men, lung, throat, breast and cervical cancers seem to be becoming more common.</P>
    <P>An immediate issue on the question of cervical screening is that laboratories are full with test samples. Cytology laboratories need recruitment and retention of screening staff. Automation may improve matters in the long term but St. Luke's is one example where they are getting a week's work per day since the &ldquo;Coronation Street&rdquo; story broke. The morale is low, they feel snowed under. They are very frustrated in that they cannot plan towards a catchment area and they want that put in place. University College Hospital in Galway has experienced a similar impact in the aftermath of that story and seek a definition of their workload by catchment area. They are specific issues which the Minister can address.</P>
    <P>I urge the Minister that this should become a priority area for the remainder of the lifetime of the Government. There is a need to do something for the young people of Ireland in all areas of cancer but particularly lung cancer.</P>
    <Speaker pid="DermotFitzpatrickFF" hpid="Dr. Fitzpatrick Dr. Fitzpatrick">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Fitzpatrick</NameTxt>
      <P>We have had an all-day approach on medical matters. We seem to have adopted tunnel vision and focused on specific areas rather than taking an overall view. Senator O'Dowd asked for a discussion on health services &ndash; which I concurred with &ndash; taking a wide ranging review of where the services are at currently and where they are going.</P>
      <P>A lot of the discussion has centred on screening. There is a body of respectable academic opinion which thinks mass screening is not the way to advance and prefers a more focused programme. A fortune could be spent on screening the whole population for cancer. Giving priority to the screening of people with a history of a specific cancer would be a better use of public money.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="1334" /> Senator Henry will be aware that some cancers are almost undetectable until they finally appear. Ovarian cancer is a case in point. Cancers of the abdomen take a long period to be diagnosed whereas brain cancers, because they cause problems at an early stage, can be diagnosed quickly. The position, therefore, in terms of dealing with cancer is not black and white. For example, genetics and environmental factors, smoking, excessive drinking, the leading of a sedentary lifestyle and eating the wrong foods must all be taken into consideration. While none of these by itself causes cancer, if one considers them together, on a global scale, one will find that they can do so.</P>
    <P>The purpose of this debate is to discuss cancers which affect women. If one goes into any public house, restaurant or other establishment where people, particularly women, congregate, one will soon see that many young ladies smoke. In my opinion, these women outnumber their male counterparts. The message has, at last, got through to fairly dim males that smoking is not good for them. However, that is not the case with females. We are not getting the message across that smoking not only causes cancer of the lungs but it can also cause cancer in other organs of the body. Smoking does not just target one organ, although it has major effects on the lungs and circulatory system; it can affect every other organ. We are not getting across the message that smoking and people's lifestyles are major causes of cancer. I have already dealt with the genetic causes of cancer and I believe we should target these and press home our message.</P>
    <P>As Senator Jackman stated, when one mentions cancer people think of pain and fear. However, those involved in the treatment of cancer will inform you that many cancers can now be cured. Not all cancers are associated with pain and a person's life can be prolonged through treatment. Even people with the most malignant melanomas can enjoy a good quality of life because of the advances being made by oncologists in methods of treatment.</P>
    <P>In my profession, medicine, we are approaching the stage where practitioners will be licensed for a set period of years. Continuing medical education will have to become the norm in the next few years. One of the areas in which there is a severe deficiency in medical training for undergraduates, GPs and anyone not involved in the specialised area of oncology is palliative care and pain control. All branches of medicine deal with this area and while individuals who become oncologists, radiologists, etc., may claim they specialise in cancer treatment, it is left to general medical operatives, such as GPs, nurses and others, to deal with the after-effects of treatment. The training these people receive is deficient. I consider myself a case in point in that regard. It is only by attending meetings and speaking with people involved in the area that one might pick up training hints.</P>
    <P>I return to my main point, namely, that there is a good story to be told about the treatment of <Col N="1335" /> cancer. However, people must be educated and we must inform them about the damage their lifestyles are having on their health. They must also be informed that if cancer is detected early, it can be treated and those affected can, after treatment, return to enjoying life to the full.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MaryHenry" hpid="Dr. Henry Dr. Henry">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Henry</NameTxt>
      <P>This is an interesting debate. It is always a pleasure to hear the comments of Senator Fitzpatrick, who has garnered a great deal of knowledge from his daily dealings with people affected by cancer. Perhaps, like me, he received All-Ireland Cancer Statistics 1994-96 in recent days. This is the first occasion on which a joint report on the incidence of cancer and mortality rates therefrom for the island of Ireland. It is a most progressive step that both cancer registries have combined their data and given figures for the entire island, because a great deal more information can be gleaned from considering statistics for five million rather than those for between 3.5 million and four million. I congratulate those involved in producing the report.</P>
      <P>Some of the findings in the report are quite extraordinary. I will concentrate on those relating in the main to women. Why is the rate of cancer of the oesophagus among Irish women almost 2.5 times greater than the European average? That is an extraordinary figure. Cancer of the oesophagus is not a pleasant disease either to contract or to deal with. As Senator Fitzpatrick correctly stated and as the Minister of State, Deputy Moffatt, will know, some cancers of the abdomen are diagnosed quite late. Another statistic, to which other Members referred, is the high rate of lung cancer among women in Ireland, which is approximately 150% of the EU average. That is extremely depressing. We must investigate these findings.</P>
      <P>We have quite good knowledge of what causes lung cancer. As Senator Fitzpatrick stated, young males appear to have taken to heart the message that smoking is bad for them to a far greater degree than their female counterparts. It is unfortunate, but the fashion industry appears to desire young women to aspire to a particular body image and this is an important factor in terms of the number of cigarettes these women smoke. Apparently, the industry has tried to make up for this by using women who weigh eight stones as opposed to six and a half or seven stones as models in fashion photographs. Many young women seem to believe that smoking makes one thinner. The only way this could happen I suppose is that it is uncomfortable to eat and smoke at the same time. Never having smoked, however, I regret to say that I do not know whether this is the case. For me, eating is quite enough to be going along with.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>This is an area we make repeated efforts to address but we do not appear to be making much headway. I commend those young female stars such as Angeline Ball and others who have stated why they gave up smoking. The more we can do <Col N="1336" /> to encourage others to do the same the better. As Senator Fitzpatrick correctly stressed, smoking does not just cause lung cancer. New evidence shows that nicotine acts directly on the DNA of the cell of whatever organ is being affected and that it influences the occurrence of abnormal cell division. It is not only the tar content in cigarettes which causes damage, it is also the nicotine.</P>
    <P>Other figures from the report which are a cause of concern relate to the high level of colorectal cancer and melanomas of the skin in this country. I know that sunlight is an important factor in causing non-melanoma cancers of the skin. I am not sure, however, that the evidence is quite so strong in the case of melanomas. Should we not do something about banning the use of sunbeds? I am aware that people are warned far more than they were in the past about using sunbeds. Any dermatologist with whom I have contact has informed me that sunbeds are a bad idea. However, some people seem to believe their skin should resemble the leather on the old saddlebags one sees on camels travelling across the desert. Should we not make a better effort, given the high rate of skin cancer and melanoma, to try to stop the use of sunbeds? I know using a sunbed is supposed to make one look more healthy, but I believe people are beginning to realise that the pale look is what is required. I urge other Senators to consider the figures to which I refer because they are important.</P>
    <P>I welcome another development which came to light today. I refer to the initiative from the Health Research Board and the Women's Health Council which seeks projects for research. The projects are very wide in scope and can range from clinical trials to epidemiological studies. This is good because, if we do not know something of the epidemiology of a disease and its natural history, it is very difficult to do much in the way of treatment. I commend the Minister for investing money in this area. I wish those who take part in these research programmes well. I am delighted to see they will be paid slightly better than usual. One sometimes wonders who would take part in these research programmes given that the pay is so bad. Those with PhDs are to be paid £10,000 a year whereas the normal rate is about £4,000.</P>
    <P>The Minister and others rightly praised BreastCheck which has been a great success in so far as it has gone. As the Minister of State is aware, it takes place in a limited part of the country. Having been part of it myself, I can say it is extremely well run. Deputy Owen said that, if the rest of the health service was as well run as BreastCheck, the situation would be quite cheerful. The centre I attended was attached to St. Vincent's Hospital. The notification was good, the appointment system was excellent, those in reception were very good, the waiting area was first class, the radiographers appeared to be very well trained, one was given information, which in my case, fortunately, was fine, within a few weeks, and those who required further investigation &ndash; I know a <Col N="1337" /> few personally &ndash; felt they had been dealt with very well. I am disappointed it has not been possible to extend BreastCheck to the rest of the country. As far as I can see from advertisements in the newspapers, the major problem is hiring radiographers, of whom there is a great shortage. The programme cannot be extended without experienced and well trained radiographers to take mammograms.</P>
    <P>What is worse is that I saw in one of the medical newspapers recently that Dr. Jane Buttimer is reported to have resigned as head of the programme. This is very bad news because she set up the scheme and has run it since. It almost has a 70% recall rate, which is excellent. Most schemes, if they are as good as that, say they are not doing too badly, because there will always be some who will not go. I would be very glad if the Minister of State would let me know if it is true that Dr. Buttimer has left the programme because, if she has, that is very bad news. As the Minister of State sometimes runs off without answering my questions, I would be grateful if he gave me an answer to this one because it is very important.</P>
    <P>The symptomatic breast disease clinics as recommended by the cancer forum are not doing badly. General practitioners to whom women, and the occasional man, come with symptomatic breast disease, such as a lump in the breast, discharge from the nipple and thickening of the skin over the breast, refer them immediately to these clinics where the necessary investigations are conducted that morning. All the results are collected together and those involved in the treatment of breast disease, such as surgeons, oncologists, physiotherapists, cancer counselling nurses and radiotherapists, meet a few days later and discuss a programme of treatment for the woman concerned.</P>
    <P>These types of clinics appear to have a better success rate in the treatment of symptomatic breast cancer than clinics which perhaps have a radiotherapist call once a month and the service of an oncologist 50 miles away. The Minister of State should hold his courage and show people how important it is that they are referred to these clinics rather than being seen in hospitals throughout the country. We all become attached to small local hospitals but it is sometimes wiser to attend a centre of excellence to try to achieve a better result. Years ago I compared the results of the major cancer units in America and France with ours, noticed how much better they were and did not think we could achieve them. However, some specialist clinics in Ireland claim good results and it is important we should try to let the public know the importance of this.</P>
    <P>One fifth of cancer deaths in women are due to breast cancer. With more modern treatment, we should be able to do something about this. The genetic element apparently only accounts for about 4% to 6% of cases, but it is important to identify women in this group because, if there is a genetic susceptibility within a family, we may <Col N="1338" /> want to screen earlier and more often. Senator Fitzpatrick made a good point when he said that, in screening, there must be a common condition and that, if it is detected, we must be able to do something about it for it to be worthwhile screening. We can do this with breast cancer.</P>
    <P>Senator Fitzpatrick was correct in saying that we must try to be selective in screening susceptible groups in some situations. This may be the situation with ovarian cancer. We are inclined to find ovarian cancer when, regrettably, it has progressed considerably. However, there is a genetic link between that form of cancer and a genetic susceptibility to breast cancer. Perhaps the grouping with which we must first deal in screening for ovarian cancer should be those in the group genetically susceptible to breast disease. This is an important issue because the development of and death rate from ovarian cancer in Ireland is quite high.</P>
    <P>The Minister and Senator Jackman both referred to cervical cancer and it is unfortunate that those most likely to have it, namely, those in lower socio-economic groups, are least likely to come forward. Cervical screening for cancer is a very emotive subject with some women but we have not done it properly yet. It is impossible to say it has not been very successful when we have not tried it properly. Has the Minister of State noted that good progress is being made on vaccines for cervical cancer? It is a sexually transmitted disease emanating almost certainly from viral infection of the cells of the cervix. Perhaps we should try to get work going in this area. There is none in Ireland of which I am aware but it could be useful in preventing deaths from cervical cancer which are always preventable. Cervical cancer does not spread rapidly and, if detected early, the removal of the uterus results in a good cure rate. It is disappointing women do not become more involved in screening for cervical cancer.</P>
    <P>Perhaps we should try to do more research in the areas of breast cancer and diet. We are aware that obese women are much more likely to get breast cancer than slimmer women. The possibility that obesity affects the production of oestrogen and progesterone which affect breast tissue is important. At one stage it appeared that countries with a high intake of dairy products, such as ourselves, had a higher incidence of breast cancer. These are areas of which the Health Research Board and the Women's Health Council could perhaps take note and ensure various projects are established within them.</P>
    <P>It is important that we have an extension of facilities for oncology and radiotherapy, which are in very short supply. St. Luke's Hospital in Dublin has been up-graded, but not before time. Some of the machinery in Cork would be suitable for a museum. There have been dreadful situations when machinery has broken down and patients have had to travel from one hospital to another by train. There have been improvements in the supply of equipment in Galway, partic<Col N="1339" /> ularly for radiotherapy. However, it is extraordinary to see oncologists and radiotherapists being appointed to units which do not have the facilities they need.</P>
    <P>Some efforts are being made but much remains to be done. More needs to be done in research, epidemiology, screening, treatment and the improvement of facilities. I support Dr. Fitzpatrick's call for training in palliative care for the medical and nursing professions.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MairinQuill" hpid="Miss Quill Miss Quill">
      <NameTxt>Miss Quill</NameTxt>
      <P>I welcome the Minister of State to the House. The House is lucky in having access to the insight and experience of medical practitioners such as Senators Mary Henry and Dermot Fitzpatrick. Their knowledgeable contributions to the debate have made it very valuable. It would not be right to discuss the topic of women's health merely from an academic viewpoint. It is good for the Minister of State and those who make important political decisions to hear these insights. I acknowledge the contributions made by our medical Members, as well as other.</P>
      <P>Credit is due to the Minister for Health and Children and his predecessors for approaching cancer in the manner in which it has been approached and for identifying cancer as a major killer in our society. The Government's approach to cancer has been ring-fenced in a coherent way by the putting in place of a national cancer strategy and by establising the cancer forum. There is now a coherent approach to cancer.</P>
      <P>Cancer is a major killer and many of its victims die needlessly. The disease could be prevented in many cases and prevention should be the primary objective of any cancer strategy. When cancer strikes a family, particularly when it strikes a young mother, the disease visits anguish on every member of the family and not merely on the victim herself. The anguish experienced by the surviving spouse and children is difficult to understand if one has not had direct experience of it. Anything which can be done to prevent cancer should be attempted.</P>
      <P>The major pillars of the national cancer strategy are prevention, early detection, treatment and palliative care. Mention has been made in every contribution this evening of the direct link between smoking and cancer, particularly lung cancer. The Minister for Health and Children is striving with might and main to come to terms with the tobacco companies, to reduce the instances of smoking and to reduce access to tobacco and cigarettes by young people and by people of all ages. The Minister is right in what he is attempting to do but in his efforts he reminds us of David fighting Goliath.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Because of the large number of very young women who are smoking I am convinced that prohibition alone will not achieve the Minister's objective. There is a tendency in all young people to go against authority. If something is forbidden it takes on an added appeal. I am not convinced <Col N="1340" /> that the problem will be solved at the level of prohibition. Our education system must include a physical education syllabus with an emphasis on lifestyle, wellbeing and respect for one's own body. Such a programme must be built into our education system from the nursery classes up to leaving certificate level. Respect for good health would derive from a well-designed and well-delivered programme of education which should be built into our education system and should become an examination subject. This is the only way to approach the scourge of smoking and drinking among our teenage population.</P>
    <P>The NCCA is preparing a new physical education programme but I understand it is not intended to make it an examination subject. This subject should be assessed within the school throughout the pupil's school career, as well as in a written examination at leaving certificate level. In its recent report, which has been widely leaked although not published, the NCCA points out that much of what is measured in the leaving certificate examination has little intellectual, emotional or vocational value in later life. I believe this to be the case. Is it not sad that young people waste time in school on matters which have so little value in later life? Can we not make time for young people, in their formative years, to cultivate a healthy approach to their personal lifestyles? We must think very carefully about the benefit of putting properly designed programmes of physical education at the heart of our education system if we are to root out the awful habit of smoking.</P>
    <P>We must also try to reduce drinking among young people. I was less than impressed this morning when I heard a spokesperson for third level students respond to something said by Dr. Don Thornhill about teenage drinking by saying he would bet there was more drinking <i>per capita </i>in the Dáil bar than in any student bar. If that was his reasoned approach to a serious topic, I wonder how much that student has learned about the assembly and presentation of evidence or about taking a serious approach to a very serious issue which is doing irreversible damage to many of his peers. The student's response was so glib it made me blush.</P>
    <P>These are the issues we must confront. The figures for the incidence of lung cancer in Ireland are 50% higher than in any EU member state. A direct link has been established between smoking and lung cancer and we must, therefore, take this issue seriously.</P>
    <P>I agree with what was said by Senator Henry about sunbeds. There should be no ambivalence about this matter. Sunbeds should be banned. We now know definitively, on foot of the best available research, that sunbeds do damage, including causing skin cancer, which is a prominent feature in this country. Sunbeds should be banned outright and why we do not do so defeats me. I know of places where children received sunbed treatment in preparation for making their Holy Communion. I am not exaggerating &ndash; it is true. The <Col N="1341" /> Minister should grasp the nettle and ban sunbeds. Many people would be grateful later if that was done and it would be a major step towards preventing cancer. The old proverb &ldquo;prevention is better than cure&rdquo; is certainly true in this case. Once cancer strikes, it hits hard and unless one is lucky it can be terminal. Prevention should be the main plank in any strategy to prevent women's cancer.</P>
    <P>I hope that what I have said will challenge politicians. While I am glad the Minister of State, Deputy Moffatt, is in the House to provide his professional expertise as a medical doctor, I am sorry the Minister, Deputy Martin, has had to leave. He was such a vibrant Minister for Education and Science and I would like to have put my points to him concerning the importance of physical education. Senators might seek to organise a debate on that issue fairly soon, however. We all feel strongly about cancer, about playing our part in trying to protect young people and preventing the prevalence of cancer.</P>
    <P>After prevention, early detection is the next most important issue in fighting cancer. Like other speakers, I pay tribute to BreastCheck for the work it has done. The breast screening service took initiatives on foot of the knowledge that breast cancer was such a major killer among women. BreastCheck identified the age groups where it was most lethal and developed the breast screening programme. We must intensify that work. Senator Fitzpatrick suggested that we should target certain families with an identifiable predisposition for cancer, rather than carrying out a universal breast screening programme. We should put more time into testing such people early and often.</P>
    <P>The term of office of the special adviser on cancer services, Professor Fennelly, has expired. As I have not been able to establish if his replacement has been appointed, will the Minister provide us with that information? It is important to have somebody in that pivotal position if we are to drive the agenda of this cancer strategy through the National Cancer Forum. The appointment should be made without delay.</P>
    <P>We need to train more radiographers because their work is an essential element of the early detection of cancer. That work should be intensified. We need to expand access to radiotherapy services. Senator Henry spoke about the importance of clinics having an integrated approach, not just on a regional basis but bringing them as near as possible to patients. I am aware of the anguish some patients suffered, particularly when the oncology and radiotherapy equipment in Cork city was, like the train service at the time, working some days but not others. Much anguish was inflicted on patients by that problem which has since been remedied by the Minister. It was appalling that women had to travel long distances for treatment elsewhere, thus adding to their pain and suffering. We should aim to extend treatment facilities as near as possible to the patients concerned.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="1342" /> Palliative care has proved to be invaluable in the overall approach to cancer. Such care confers benefits not alone on cancer patients but also on their families. The Sisters of Charity in St. Patrick's Hospice in Cork, who were pioneers in the field of palliative care, are next door neighbours of mine. I taught in a school run by that order with which I have many connections and, consequently, I know about the benefits of palliative care for cancer patients. Dr. Tony O'Brien, who works in St. Patrick's Hospice and who has had first-hand experience over a prolonged period of the benefits conferred by palliative care, has carried out a review of the current provision of such care. When that review is published we should debate it in the House with a view to heightening awareness of the benefits of palliative care.</P>
    <P>A sufficient number of palliative care nurses are required to provide supportive care as an integral part of our overall approach to cancer treatment. I welcome the opportunity to debate this serious issue and I am satisfied we are going in the right direction. I hope sufficient numbers of qualified staff and facilities can be provided to enable the objectives of this strategy to be achieved within the specified timeframe.</P>
    <Speaker pid="HelenKeogh" hpid="Ms Keogh Ms Keogh">
      <NameTxt>Ms Keogh</NameTxt>
      <P>I am delighted to have the opportunity to speak in this debate. I wish to refer to what one may consider an unusual analogy. A decade or so ago, car manufacturers completely transformed the way in which they made cars. They stopped stockpiling components and moved to a &ldquo;just-in-time&rdquo; delivery system. They drastically reduced the types of components they needed to use. They worked closely with their suppliers on quality and timeliness instead of beating them down on price. They eliminated waste by making all workers, not just inspectors, responsible for quality. The result was that new models took less time to develop, the quality improved and cars could be made to order for each customer. At the same time productivity improved and costs fell.</P>
      <P>More recently people in health care have realised that their service has a long way to go to match the performance of other industries, both in terms of manufacturing and service. Reports in many countries have documented the size of the gap between the best care that can be delivered to patients and the care they actually receive. Health systems fail to provide treatments that are known to work, persist in using treatments that do not work, enforce delays and tolerate high levels of error. Like car manufacturers, health leaders recognise that the health care system needs radical redesign.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>There is an infinite number of issues surrounding the provision of cancer treatment and support services for women, as we have already heard in this debate. I will confine my remarks to three main areas which are extremely important. The first one concerns breast cancer. It is a sad fact that the incidence of breast cancer in Ireland is among the highest in Europe, with over 1,200 new <Col N="1343" /> cases being diagnosed each year. Hereditary factors, alcohol, smoking, increasing age, late first pregnancy, late menopause and living in a western developed country are some of the factors cited as increasing the risk of breast cancer. As the causes of breast cancer remain to be established, however, it is not known how it can be prevented and therefore the emphasis is being placed on early detection through physical examination, mammography and early treatment. This year more than 600 Irish women will die of breast cancer. In its 1995 discussion document, Developing a Policy for Women's Health, the Department of Health and Children pointed out that about 20% to 30% of deaths from breast cancer in women over the age of 50 could be prevented if a quality mass screening programme was in operation.</P>
    <P>I must admit to wearing another hat in this debate since I am chairperson of the Well Woman Centre. I welcome the almost nationwide establishment of the BreastCheck programme, which should go some way towards reducing the mortality rate among Irish women. However, the programme has been hamstrung by skills shortages, meaning that it has not been able to attract sufficient numbers of medically qualified personnel to operate effectively. Senator Henry referred to the shortage of radiographers. I question the reason BreastCheck has not yet been rolled out nationally and no schedule is available as to which geographic areas it will service next, even in health board areas where it has been established.</P>
    <P>A recent experience in a Well Woman clinic was that of a woman within the target age group living in Poppintree, Dublin, who did not receive a letter from BreastCheck but was aware of friends in the area who were called for mammograms. She assumed she would be called but was omitted completely. When one of our doctors rang BreastCheck to find out what the problem was, she was told the woman was not on the register and BreastCheck would not be back in the Poppintree area for two years. Getting a routine screening mammogram through the public system is almost impossible. For example, St. Vincent's Hospital stopped taking routine appointments for mammograms almost 18 months before BreastCheck started because it was gearing up its services for the programme. In the other main centre in Dublin, the Mater Hospital, staff will often not answer the telephone in the mammogram section of the X-ray department or they will refuse to take the patient's name and ask her to call back in a number of weeks or months. If she is very lucky, she may be given an appointment far into the future.</P>
    <P>The woman from Poppintree was in the at-risk age group and the only two options open to her were to pay privately for a mammogram &ndash; currently costing between £50 and £80 &ndash; or for Well Woman to refer her to an already overworked breast clinic where the average wait is approxi<Col N="1344" /> mately three weeks. Well Woman had to add an extra patient into an overloaded system because the patient had fallen between the cracks in the BreastCheck system.</P>
    <P>BreastCheck's success or failure will be largely influenced by the lack of a comprehensive, accurate national population register. There are, without doubt, many women who will fall between the cracks in BreastCheck. A more accurate population register could have been created for the programme and other screening programmes by implementing a universal registration system such as the use of RSI numbers. It is almost impossible for Well Woman and general practitioners to recommend and effectively promote the BreastCheck service to women in a timely fashion when there is no relevant follow-through in provision of service.</P>
    <P>A possible conversation in a consultation, as illustrated to me by a Well Woman doctor is as follows: the doctor tells the patient she should go to BreastCheck for a mammogram. She asks when will that be to which the doctor replies that he does not know. The patient then asks if the doctor will find out to which he replies no because he will not be informed which area BreastCheck will write to next. That is not the way to run a service.</P>
    <P>Apart from BreastCheck, the experience of women attending breast clinics for symptomatic reasons is also less than positive. Despite women accessing the service and health care professionals providing it sharing largely the same objectives and concerns, a report published last year by the Women's Health Council found there were frustrating delays in all aspects of the service from getting a first appointment to delays in the clinics because of pressure and delays in getting the necessary diagnostic tests. Sometimes various test results came back at different times, requiring women to return, perhaps more than once, to speak to the relevant staff member. There was no reimbursement of costs incurred in travelling available to medical card patients.</P>
    <P>Women felt they were not provided with enough information on their illness and there were insufficient numbers of staff within the clinics, particularly specialist nurses, to listen to their concerns and fears and answer any questions they might have. Women did not feel the breast care nurses had a specific brief and were being diverted into administrative tasks rather than being available to provide patients with care and support. They felt there needed to be expert medical advice available to them at weekends, especially when they were undergoing treatment such as chemotherapy when they were quite likely to be ill afterwards. The breast care support system shuts down at weekends. Breast disease causes not only physical illness, but mental and emotional distress also. Women felt there was a need for trained counsellors, psychologists and other trained support staff to be available through the breast clinics.</P>
    <P>The second area which I wish to address is cervical cancer from which more than 70 women die <Col N="1345" /> each year. It is almost entirely a treatable condition if picked up in the pre-malignant, pre-cancerous stage. Women are dying unnecessarily because there is no national mass screening programme in Ireland. The Plan for Women's Health, published in 1997, states, &ldquo;A national screening programme will be established in 1999, or earlier, if resources permit&rdquo;. Even now, in 2001, only the Mid-Western Health Board area screens for cervical cancer. The need for a pilot study is questionable given that international studies clearly demonstrate that a properly implemented screening programme is effective in reducing the mortality rate among women.</P>
    <P>Well Woman is well qualified to speak on this matter as it takes more than 7,000 cervical smears each year from women who present at our clinics. The Plan for Women's Health aspires to assist cervical cytology laboratories, that is, testing laboratories, to deal with heavy workloads as part of the implementation of the national cancer strategy with the aim of ensuring the results of cervical smear tests are available as far as possible within one month. It is Well Woman's experience that, on average, smear test results take ten weeks to come back. This delay has been a consistent factor in the past two to three years and is not limited to any single laboratory. Delays in results give conflicting messages. Clinicians tell women it is important that they have a smear taken but, at the same time, the health care system tells them it is not important enough for results to be returned in a timely fashion.</P>
    <P>If the smear test result warrants further investigation, the next stage is referral to a colposcopy clinic. The waiting time for a public appointment is another eight to ten weeks. It is not unusual for a Well Woman clinic nurse to spend up to half a day on the telephone trying to obtain an appointment for a woman, particularly if it is urgent, where the clinic's doctors suspect the presence of cancer. The patient can always choose to go privately, in which case the cost of a colposcopy can be more than £200, with insurers picking up some of the cost. However, even then, there is a waiting time of two to three weeks within the private health care system. The anxiety felt by women at every stage of the system, whether they are public or private patients, is considerable.</P>
    <P>One Well Woman client, who presented with symptoms highly suggestive of cervical cancer, was referred by us and got a colposcopy appointment which showed cancer. The hospital gynaecologist referred her to a cancer treatment specialist. Unfortunately, this happened in mid-December 2000 but she was not seen until the second week in January. She was so distressed by the delay that she returned to Well Woman for advice and reassurance. As it turned out, she had invasive cancer. Had there been an effective mass screening programme in place the woman would probably have been called for a smear test on a more regular basis and might be alive today.</P>
    <P>Laboratory services in the State are completely overwhelmed, and the Department of Health and Children needs to examine ways to ease the bur<Col N="1346" /> den and support new technologies to do so. Liquid-based technology to analyse smear samples has been widely proven to be more accurate. It has the advantage of being more accurate and, therefore, reducing the number of repeat tests required, thus reducing pressure on laboratory facilities. This technology also reduces the anxiety caused to women by inconclusive results, which require them to repeat the test, and gives medical and nursing staff greater confidence in the testing process, as well as allowing them to work to current best practice. Well Woman adopted this new technology last year and recommends that the national cervical screening programme, whenever it is rolled out, should also do so.</P>
    <P>Testing for particular types of HPV, human papilloma virus, has also been shown to be an accurate indicator of whether a woman is at high risk of developing cervical cancer. Such a test is currently not available in Ireland, yet it could be undertaken at a relatively low cost as the test is done on the cervical smear sample. It is a highly accurate test, which would have the effect of reducing the number of colposcopies required, thereby reducing pressure on the hospital system. An accurate screening programme would not only save lives, it would also cut costs in the health care system.</P>
    <P>The third area I would like to mention is ovarian cancer for which there is no accurate test. In many ways, it is the forgotten cancer. It is considered by many in the field that it may kill as many women each year as cervical cancer, yet the Department's Plan for Women's Health makes no mention of it. Some ovarian cancer is genetic and there are links between breast cancer and ovarian cancer. This can sometimes be detected by looking at family groups. Pre-menopausal women with close relatives who have had ovarian cancer and/or breast cancer should therefore be automatically informed of the increased risk of cancer.</P>
    <P>To do that effectively requires dedicated staff resources and genetic counselling along with test facilities, surgical and oncology support. That is currently being done in the Dublin hospitals as a research project. The experience in other countries suggests that a combination of genetic testing and family history can quantify the risk of cancer. High risk women can then be monitored by means of pelvic ultrasound scanning and blood testing for specific cancer markers.</P>
    <P>We have the ability to deal with these issues but we do not have the type of service that can deliver in that regard. Simply throwing money at services has not worked. We need a radical redesign of our cancer care services just as we need a radical redesign of our health care services. This is one of the most important issues on the doorsteps.</P>
    <Speaker pid="DrMauriceHayes" hpid="Dr. M. Hayes Dr. M. Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Dr. M. Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>I welcome the Minister of State to the House. I welcome the debate also which I have found most instructive. I gained a great deal from the professional experience and knowledge of Senator Fitzpatrick and Senator Henry and <Col N="1347" /> from the evocative cry from the patient voiced by Senator Keogh.</P>
      <P>I congratulate the Minister of State on the progress made through the national cancer strategy. We should get behind that strategy to ensure that it is rolled out before we talk about other radical changes.</P>
      <P>I am glad the Minister talked about lifestyle, particularly the relationship between cancer and smoking and alcohol. The continued advertising of smoking and the linking of alcohol with sporting events is something that should be tackled. I know the Minister of State might have less interest in the Guinness hurling championship than some of the rest of us but, nevertheless, it is something he might examine.</P>
      <P>There is the difficulty that the greatest increase in smoking is among women, particularly among women in the D and E social grades. We have been told that these are the people who are most susceptible to various forms of cancer.</P>
      <P>I welcome the links that exist between the national cancer strategy and the cancer strategy in Northern Ireland and the National Cancer Institute in America. Each of those is benefiting from international research. It is clear now that there are better outcomes for patients who are treated in multi-disciplinary centres which handle a large volume of cases, particularly the more unusual cancers. I would encourage the Minister of State, therefore, to bite the bullet and maintain a degree of specialisation and centralisation that is needed to assemble teams of that size and for that purpose.</P>
      <P>In that context, I question the investment of large amounts of money in new equipment in a free standing hospital like St. Luke's. Increasingly, these institutions need to be brought together on the campus of a large general hospital which, among other things, will help to remove much of the mystery and fear of cancer. In that regard I congratulate the Minister on coming here for this debate because it enables us to discuss this issue and remove some of the mystery surrounding it so that people can see the improvements that have been made and the possibilities that exist of improving outcomes through early detection.</P>
      <P>If treatment is to be decentralised, diagnosis and screening should be brought as near as possible to those people we are trying to reach. The difficulty of all screening programmes is attracting the very people that are most needed. We talked about that earlier. Much of the screening is opportunistic and I share Senator Fitzpatrick's scepticism about the efficacy of universal screening programmes. In terms of health economics, some of them are questionable and perhaps we would be better putting our money into other areas. Targeted screening is important, particularly for young, sexually active women who, as Senator Henry said, are increasingly becoming vulnerable to cervical cancer, a sexually transmitted disease which needs to be treated as such.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="1348" /> To come back to the question of centralisation, there is a temptation to try to spread the goodies too thinly but it is important to build up fully staffed and properly equipped centres and then roll out the programme rather than try to maintain a weak centre and a weak periphery. That requires a certain amount of political fortitude, not only in terms of the ordinary politics we deal with but the much more dangerous medical politics of which the Minister of State would be aware.</P>
    <P>There is much to be said for support for the hospice movement and the development of palliative care. Great results have been achieved from home nursing of people at terminal stages of cancer which transforms the quality of life for the patient and is of enormous support to families as well. Underlying all of that, however, is a need for quality control. The figures Senator Keogh quoted are indefensible in terms of people having to wait months for screening or testing. Many cancer cells can grow in that period of time.</P>
    <P>On the question of waiting for results, it is interesting that when there was an economic motive we were able to get results back quickly on foot and mouth testing yet these women have to wait for test results. That points to a need to examine the laboratory service and to ensure it is fully equipped and that quality is maintained. We have seen what happens in other jurisdictions when there are false readings. The only thing worse than a false negative is probably a false positive and the amount of concern that causes.</P>
    <P>I repeat my three points to the Minister of State. First, do not weaken on the question of concentrating treatment in large, multi-disciplinary centres. Second, decentralise diagnosis and screening to the extent that it is possible and, third, underpin the whole service with a proper laboratory service, all of which is amenable to quality control so that people can be told how long they have to wait before their tests come through.</P>
    <P>I congratulate the Minister of State on the progress that has been made and the evident concern he has for the welfare of women. I wish the national cancer strategy well.</P>
    <Speaker pid="FergusODowdFG" hpid="Mr. O'Dowd Mr. O'Dowd">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Dowd</NameTxt>
      <P>I welcome the Minister to the House. This has been an important and useful debate and I was impressed by the contributions from all sides of the House on the issue.</P>
      <P>I want to make a number of points about cancer. I got a telephone call some months ago about the BreastCheck programme in the north-east. The programme is widely advertised in the North Eastern Health Board area covering counties Louth, Meath, Cavan and Monaghan. Women in the age group 50 to 64 are being asked to get in touch with the BreastCheck programme, which they do, but when women in County Louth rang up to inquire about it, they were told that the programme would get in touch with them about their appointment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>A number of these women were very concerned about that issue and they got in touch with me, following the advertisements on radio and television &ndash; I believe Marian Finucane was on <Col N="1349" /> national radio &ndash; to know when they would get their appointments. I have discovered that it will be the end of next year before the BreastCheck programme is available in County Louth. Regrettably this is creating much concern among people who have seen the media advertisements, including those in bus shelters. However, the service is not available in County Louth. There is nothing wrong with the service being offered in County Meath. However, the advertising should be restricted to the counties in which the service is operating. Otherwise a demand is created which cannot be met. This is causing stress, distress and upset to many people.</P>
    <P>The female doctor mentioned earlier informed me that it is hoped to have a new unit in place by the end of this year. However, the service is under much pressure to attract the highly qualified staff required. Perhaps the Minister of State can confirm that attempts are being made to recruit staff from as far away as Australia and New Zealand. I welcome the thrust of the policy but the Government cannot provide the qualified staff. It is unacceptable that the service is receiving further publicity in areas where it cannot be provided for almost two years.</P>
    <P>I also wish to raise the issue of women over 64 years or under 50 years. Older women have asked me why they are being excluded from the service. Do these women not face the same or, perhaps, a higher risk? I am not getting away from the medical opinion to the effect that women in the 50 to 64 age group are at the highest risk. However, what about older women?</P>
    <P>I asked my local health board what facilities it would make available for a woman in County Louth who could not get an appointment under the BreastCheck programme. This woman is concerned that she may be in the age group susceptible to cancer and wonders what she can do. What can this woman or her doctor do? I am told her doctor can do nothing as one cannot undergo a mammogram in the north-east, and, I think, in most areas, unless one is referred by a consultant. A GP cannot refer a patient to a local hospital. He or she can only refer someone to a consultant. There are many problems in this area.</P>
    <P>The excellent equipment being used in the BreastCheck programme is not available in general hospitals. This is creating significant problems. A woman cannot obtain a routine mammogram unless she goes to a consultant, or she is living in a county in which the programme is in operation. This is unacceptable. The Minister must make changes to the system to ensure that the service is more widely available and to attract the professional staff required to run the programme.</P>
    <P>I also wish to raise an issue which arose yesterday and which shocked me greatly. I am a member of the North Eastern Health Board, but I was unable to attend a meeting yesterday for family reasons. At yesterday's meeting, the health board discussed a proposal from cancer specialists that the centres of excellence for breast screening in the north-east should be based at Our Lady of Lourdes Hospital, Drogheda, and at Cavan <Col N="1350" /> hospital. However, the male members of the board decided by a majority of two votes to accept the recommendation of the cancer specialists and the deputy chief executive officer of the health board, who is in charge of the programme, but to base the centre in Navan rather than Drogheda. This is a short distance &ndash; 20 to 30 miles. However, the breast cancer consultant in the north-east has informed me that the effect of this decision will be that women who are seriously ill with cancer, or those who will develop cancer, will wait about two years longer to get the service if it is moved from the proposed site in Drogheda to Navan.</P>
    <P>I support Senator Maurice Hayes's comments that the Minister must insist that people do not play regional or local politics with this decision. The location of centres of excellence for the treatment of cancer, or any illness, must not be left to petty politicians who play their parish pump games with an issue which is far too serious. Cancer services must be above politics. All political parties agree on what should happen, but we should listen to, and follow the advice of, the experts. This decision is not a matter for the Minister and it appears he cannot intervene. It is a matter for the health board, but what has happened is disgraceful, reprehensible and unacceptable. I hope the Minister will use whatever influence he has with the members of his party who voted for this change, as I will do with mine. I will also ask my party leader to do the same.</P>
    <P>Cancer is a tragic illness. Working together as a community and a State we must provide more funding for cancer services. I support the changes made. However, we must examine the issue of research and development. Some cancers do not receive priority in this regard. Cancer of the pancreas, for example, accounts for 4% of all cancers, yet 25% of deaths from cancer. Diseases such as this are receiving no funding in America. We should ensure that the different kinds of cancers, whether they affect men or women, are properly and adequately researched. We should examine this area closely.</P>
    <P>I agree with the comments made regarding malignant melanoma &ndash; skin cancer. The Minister of State may be able to propose that pop idols such as Bono and others, who already significantly impact on the lives of young people, are used in advertising campaigns regarding health issues. Reference was made to the Guinness hurling championship. Perhaps we should call it the cancer hurling championship. We should focus on issues such as cancer in the sense that the big game is to beat cancer. It would not take many minds to work together on this issue.</P>
    <P>I agree that the abuse of alcohol and tobacco is significantly affecting the lives of young people. It is unacceptable that this continues. We can talk about this issue but let us see some action. Someone diagnosed as having cancer should be given an information pack by the family doctor, consultant or whoever. People should be given the contact number for the Irish Cancer Society <Col N="1351" /> which does excellent work. Many hospitals have their own oncology nurses and oncology units. However, some people slip through the net. The support services which are necessary for those diagnosed with cancer should be increased significantly. These groups should receive more funding and recognition. I support the comments made regarding palliative care and the hospice movement which does a fantastic job. I acknowledge the tremendous work which is done in my area and my town.</P>
    <P>This has been an important debate and the Minister of State has taken note of the points raised. So many people are dying from cancer that we must do more to help them. In this regard this debate has been constructive.</P>
    <P>While there are specific Internet sites in Ireland with information and help for families when a diagnosis is made, there are not enough. More could be done to provide information on the Internet regarding the different types of cancer. Much of the information on the Internet is from institutes in America, so more is required emanating from Ireland. I am pleased to have had the opportunity to listen to the views expressed in this important debate.</P>
    <Speaker pid="CamillusGlynn" hpid="Mr. Glynn Mr. Glynn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Glynn</NameTxt>
      <P>This debate is important. Women play a pivotal role in society. I do not wish to be patronising when I say that they bear our children and rear them. Much of what I wished to say in this debate has been said, so I will not engage in repetition.</P>
      <P>On the question of cervical screening the Minister stated:</P>
      <P>The National Registry Board reports that between 1994 and 1997 cervical cancer accounted for an average of 74 deaths in Ireland each year, with cervical cancer being more common in older women. The report, entitled Developing a Policy for Women's Health, states that while cervical screening is simple, quick and relatively inexpensive, not all women respond to requests to attend for screening. It has been found that women in the lower socio-economic groups may fail to do so and it is mainly among these groups that deaths from cervical cancer occur.</P>
      <P>There is a major need for ongoing information and contact, especially with the groups referred to by the Minister. It is important to target a programme at girls at second level and especially third level. They should be told that in seven or eight years they will fall into the age category referred to by the Minister when he states: &ldquo;Experts in the Europe Against Cancer programme recommend that women between the ages of 25 and 60 years should have a cervical smear regularly and that they should participate in organised screening programmes where available&rdquo;.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>It is important to review and amend strategies, including the national cancer strategy. Major progress has been made on implementing the strategy. At national level the main infrastructural <Col N="1352" /> elements have been put in place. These comprise the establishment of the National Cancer Forum to advise on the implementation of the national cancer strategy. The first forum met between March 1977 and April 2000 and the second forum has held two meetings &ndash; a third meeting is scheduled for May 2001. The term of office of the special adviser to the Department's cancer services, Professor Fennelly, expired on 1 April 2001. As a member of the Midland Health Board, I benefited from some of the professor's wisdom, for which I thank him.</P>
    <P>The Minister referred to the appointment of regional directors for cancer services, which was an important step forward. The establishment of a steering group, chaired by Dr. Sheelah Ryan, chief executive officer of the Western Health Board, to organise a national programme of screening for breast cancer is also to be welcomed. Dr. Ryan is an experienced general practitioner and medic. She was director of community care during my time on the Midland Health Board. She then progressed to become programme manager and, ultimately, chief executive officer of the Western Health Board. Given her experience, the steering group under her chairmanship is in safe hands. I commend the Minister and the Department for ensuring this.</P>
    <P>Dr. Michael Dowling of the Rotunda Hospital has been appointed chairman of the advisory committee to oversee the establishment of a national cervical screening programme. He is doing excellent work. The Health Research Board was allocated a grant of £80,000 per annum for each of the years 1997 to 2000 for the coordination of multi-disciplinary, multi-institutional research as indicated in the national cancer strategy.</P>
    <P>There has been a common approach by the Minister for Health and Children and his Northern counterpart working in tandem with the authorities in the US. A historic memorandum of understanding has been signed to establish an Ireland-Northern Ireland cancer consortium. This will result in the development of joint cancer research programmes, scholar exchange programmes and a range of other collaborative activities, all of which are very important.</P>
    <P>The Minister referred to the number of consultants appointed to the various health boards, which is very welcome. All the boards, including the one of which I am a member, have benefited. We should not be reticent in reviewing this strategy in view of changes to medical practice. There are new developments every day and for this reason it is important that we review what has been done, consider what must be done in the future and implement the best possible practice.</P>
    <Speaker pid="RoryOHanlon" hpid="An Leas-Cheann Comhairle Rory O'Hanlon">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Cheann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>That concludes statements. When is it proposed to sit again?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="CamillusGlynn" hpid="Mr. Glynn Mr. Glynn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Glynn</NameTxt>
      <P>At 10.30 tomorrow morning.</P>
      <P>The Seanad adjourned at 5.40 p.m. until 10.30 a.m. on Wednesday, 30 May 2001.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
</Debate>