<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE Debate SYSTEM "../Debate.dtd"[]>
<Debate DocTitle="Seanad Debate" Day="Wed" Date="17" Month="Oct" Year="2001" Vol="168" No="6" DateIrish="Dé Céadaoin, 17 Deireadh Fómhair 2001" DateEnglish="Wednesday, 17 October 2001" House="S" CommitteeEng="" CommitteeIr="" SubNameEng="" cnum="0">
  <MainHeading Type="Prelude" LHead="" RHead="">
    <Title>
    </Title>
    <P Just="Center">
      <Col N="289" />Chuaigh an Cathaoirleach i gceannas ar 2.30 p.m.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Business" RHead="of Seanad">
    <Title>Business of Seanad.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="BrianMullooly" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I have received notice from Senator Glynn that, on the motion for the Adjournment of the House today, he proposes to raise the following matter:</P>
      <P>The need for the Minister for the Environment and Local Government to approve the application of Westmeath County Council for an extension to the Killucan-Rathwire and Rochford Bridge sewerage schemes.</P>
      <P>I have also received notice from Senator Finneran of the following matter:</P>
      <P>The need for the Minister for Education and Science to sanction as a matter of urgency the provision of extra accommodation and the appointment of an extra teacher at Fuerty national school, Roscommon.</P>
      <P>I have received also notice from Senator Henry of the following matter:</P>
      <P>In view of the high incidence of breast cancer in Ireland and the extensive work done on the genetics of breast cancer here, the need for the Minister for Health and Children to support immediately the actions taken by the French and Swiss health departments and the genetic societies of Belgium, the Netherlands, Germany, Denmark and the United Kingdom against the granting of patent EP0699754 B1 to Myriad Genetics, Salt Lake City, USA, which is a serious threat to genetic testing for breast cancer in this country.</P>
      <P>I regard the matters raised by the Senators as suitable for discussion on the Adjournment and they will be taken at the conclusion of business.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Order of" RHead="Business">
    <Title>Order of Business.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="DonnieCassidyFF" hpid="Mr. Cassidy Mr. Cassidy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cassidy</NameTxt>
      <P>Today's Order of Business is No. 1, referral motion regarding Double Taxation Relief Orders, 2001, to the Joint Committee on Finance and the Public Service, to be taken without debate; No. 2, statements on the current sit<Col N="290" /> uation following the atrocities in the United States of America, to conclude not later than 6 p.m., with the contributions of spokespersons not to exceed 20 minutes and of all other Senators not to exceed 15 minutes and on which Senators may share time; and No. 18, motion 21, to be taken from 6 p.m. to 8 p.m.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnConnor" hpid="Mr. Connor Mr. Connor">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Connor</NameTxt>
      <P>I ask the Leader to amend the Order of Business today to allow for a debate on the problems facing Shannon Airport. Recent announcements by Aer Lingus concerning its economic viability and its down sizing have most serious implications for Shannon Airport in terms of its role as a major import export port for one of the most industrialised and employment providing areas of the country. Not only that, it has serious implications for a whole region of the country and the nation itself.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryHenry" hpid="Dr. Henry Dr. Henry">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Henry</NameTxt>
      <P>The Order of Business is agreed by us, I hope. May I make one point&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ShaneRoss" hpid="Mr. Ross Mr. Ross">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Ross</NameTxt>
      <P>No, absolutely not.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidNorris" hpid="Mr. Norris Mr. Norris">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norris</NameTxt>
      <P>And he is the Whip.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryHenry" hpid="Dr. Henry Dr. Henry">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Henry</NameTxt>
      <P>I thank the Cathaoirleach for calling me. Could I bring one matter to the attention&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BrianMullooly" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator Henry, on the Order of Business.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidNorris" hpid="Mr. Norris Mr. Norris">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norris</NameTxt>
      <P>We are demonstrating our independence, a Chathaoirligh, of each other&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryHenry" hpid="Dr. Henry Dr. Henry">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Henry</NameTxt>
      <P>Gentlemen, please.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidNorris" hpid="Mr. Norris Mr. Norris">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norris</NameTxt>
      <P>&mdash;I am not a gentleman.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BrianMullooly" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Order, please.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryHenry" hpid="Dr. Henry Dr. Henry">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Henry</NameTxt>
      <P>Will the Leader of the House note that the Minister for Justice, Equality and Law Reform has produced a most useful report through the Internet Advisory Board on the different perceptions of parents and children regarding the use of the Internet? It would be useful to discuss the matter in this House because, I think, we would get agreement on all sides that the campaign promoted by the Department is extremely useful.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeCostelloLAB" hpid="Mr. Costello Mr. Costello">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Costello</NameTxt>
      <P>I commend the Leader of the House for the number of issues he has recently put on the agenda for us to debate. He is covering ground pretty well, but I am tempted to add a few more issues. A major one concerns the post offices. I hear the postmasters and the postmistresses are about to embark on industrial action arising from the ballot last week concerning how the sub-post office network is being dealt with. Major issues relate to PostPoint, the retention and maintenance of the network throughout the country, in rural and in urban areas, and the 12% <Col N="291" /> remuneration that was promised, which has now been made conditional on participation in the forum. Serious issues remain to be addressed and I would like an early debate, especially given that another picket is likely to be placed on the Houses of the Oireachtas soon.</P>
      <P>The most compelling domestic issue is health and the management of the health service which has not improved under the term of the Government. We saw from the recent ESRI report that 2,000 nurses were recruited in the past four years, while 4,000 administrative staff were recruited. Last year, the number of private patients treated in public hospitals in proportion to the number of public patients doubled. These are serious matters and every day we ask more questions about waiting lists, the closure of hospital beds, the inadequacy of staffing and so on. Will the Leader allow us the opportunity to have a full-scale debate on health, the issue which directly affects most people?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="AnnOrmonde" hpid="Ms Ormonde Ms Ormonde">
      <NameTxt>Ms Ormonde</NameTxt>
      <P>In the fallout in terms of employment of the catastrophe of 11 September, we need to update ourselves on the role of FÁS and the type of programmes and courses it has, which it may have to adjust. Representatives of the agency should state how they will cope with the aftermath by holding courses relevant to those who have lost their jobs.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MadeleineTaylorQuinn" hpid="Mrs. Taylor-Quinn Mrs. Taylor-Quinn">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Taylor-Quinn</NameTxt>
      <P>It is important the House immediately debates the issue of Aer Lingus. It is especially important given that notice has been given to a number of employees without consultation with the unions and also given that the European Commission has allowed a loan to be given to Sabena while not to Aer Lingus. There is a need for the House to express its views clearly to the Minister so that she can proceed with a forceful hand in securing European Commission support. This can be done, especially for the transatlantic leg of the Aer Lingus operation. It is important we have a debate now and not tomorrow or next week. It is urgent and is needed now. The crisis is critical not just for Aer Lingus but also for the west and for the economy. It should be viewed in that light and that is why it should be given priority in the House.</P>
      <P>I refer again to an issue I raised with the Leader last week about haemophiliacs. Has he had discussions with the Minister for Health and Children about broadening the terms of reference of the Lindsay tribunal to ensure pharmaceutical companies are investigated and made accountable to the tribunal?</P>
      <P>The extraordinary scenario in Dublin city and country where women must go to hospitals in the midlands and the south-east to give birth is unacceptable and must be discussed by the House.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I join with Senator Henry in calling for a debate on the report from the Department of Justice, Equality and Law Reform about the Inter<Col N="292" /> net. This is something which could be usefully addressed in the House.</P>
    <Speaker pid="BrianMullooly" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Do I take it that Senator Taylor-Quinn wishes to second the amendment?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MadeleineTaylorQuinn" hpid="Mrs. Taylor-Quinn Mrs. Taylor-Quinn">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Taylor-Quinn</NameTxt>
      <P>I second the amendment to the Order of Business.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LabhrasOMurchu" hpid="Labhrás Ó Murchú Labhrás Ó Murchú">
      <NameTxt>Labhrás Ó Murchú</NameTxt>
      <P>Will the Leader convey to the Government our sincere appreciation of the manner in which the funeral ceremony of the ten patriots was conducted last weekend? I compliment RTE on the wonderful coverage of the event. Next weekend, the funeral of volunteer Patrick Maher will take place in Ballylanders and I have no doubt it will be another dignified occasion. There is one other patriot still buried in jail grounds, namely, Thomas Kent in Cork Prison. Will the Leader ask the Taoiseach to give favourable consideration to the reinterment of and a proper Christian burial for Thomas Kent soon?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidNorris" hpid="Mr. Norris Mr. Norris">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norris</NameTxt>
      <P>Following from what Senator Ó Murchú said, I was not present at the funerals but I was pleased to hear that Cardinal Cathal Daly said prayers for both sides. That was the Christian thing to do and was very much in the tradition of the Dean of St. Paul's who infuriated Margaret Thatcher by also praying for the fallen on the Argentinian side. That is the civilised approach.</P>
      <P>Can we have time for discussion on transport issues, particularly Luas and the underground railway promised for Dublin, so that the Minister can reassure us that there is a clear timetable and that the undertakings given to the House will be met? The situation has changed and I am concerned that we have heard nothing about the underground element. Debate would be useful so that we can hear the Minister's views.</P>
      <P>Are State-owned vehicles exempt from the MOT test? Throughout the country buses are among the principal polluters. Yesterday I was behind a Garda van which was pouring out black smoke.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnDardis" hpid="Mr. Dardis Mr. Dardis">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dardis</NameTxt>
      <P>It is lucky the Senator was not in it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidNorris" hpid="Mr. Norris Mr. Norris">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norris</NameTxt>
      <P>At least I was following it, not as in some other people's case.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BrianMullooly" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>That matter is not relevant to the Order of Business. The Senator should find another way of raising the matter.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidNorris" hpid="Mr. Norris Mr. Norris">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norris</NameTxt>
      <P>I shall do my best. I support the call for a debate on Aer Lingus. It is important to have such a debate to reassure the staff, especially in the light of the extraordinary, cavalier and unfeeling attitude expressed by the chief executive of another airline towards the fate of the Aer Lingus employees. I understood we were having statements on Aer Lingus tomorrow. Will the Leader inform the House if this is incorrect?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="293" />
    <Speaker pid="JimGlennonFF" hpid="Mr. Glennon Mr. Glennon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Glennon</NameTxt>
      <P>I would like to point out to my colleagues from west of the Shannon that airport crises are not confined to their part of the country. Will the Leader convey to the Minister, who is due here tomorrow for debate on the Aer Lingus crisis, our acknowledgement of her statement to the Dáil this morning in which she indicated that the number of jobs to be lost has been reduced by 400 to 2,100? All things are relative but that is still a huge hit for any one area. As a matter of urgency, will the Leader convey to the Minister, in advance of her visit tomorrow, the necessity for the continuation of the industrial relations procedures in a spirit of partnership which has been the bedrock of the prosperity of the country for the last number of years? Unfortunately, it would appear from correspondence I have here that certain steps have been taken today which are utterly outside the realms of partnership as we know it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThereseRidge" hpid="Mrs. Ridge Mrs. Ridge">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Ridge</NameTxt>
      <P>I support the comments of my esteemed colleague, Senator Taylor-Quinn, particularly in regard to the dearth of midwives in the Dublin region. It is time for a Dublin allowance. London has an allowance for people working in the capital because of the high cost of living in a capital city and it would be a realistic step forward to have the same for Dublin.</P>
      <P>While we reflect on the glory of what has been achieved by a Government that can do no wrong and so on&mdash;</P>
      <P>
        <i>(Interruptions.)</i>
      </P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThereseRidge" hpid="Mrs. Ridge Mrs. Ridge">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Ridge</NameTxt>
      <P>I am talking about the present lot.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BrianMullooly" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Through the Leader of the House, Senator.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThereseRidge" hpid="Mrs. Ridge Mrs. Ridge">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Ridge</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes, through the Leader for whom I have mixed feelings but generally feelings of high esteem. He has let me down once again on the issue of homelessness. At our council meeting yesterday I was informed that to be on the priority list for the homeless one would have to be in a hostel for one year, regardless of whether one has children. We had a debate on homelessness here about two years ago and many promises were made. This year in our county area we built 90 houses. There are 4,200 applicants on the list. Are we dealing with the remnants of the Celtic tiger or what in effect was always a Celtic &ldquo;cheater&rdquo;?</P>
      <P>
        <i>(Interruptions.)</i>
      </P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BrianMullooly" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Does the Senator want a debate on homelessness?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThereseRidge" hpid="Mrs. Ridge Mrs. Ridge">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Ridge</NameTxt>
      <P>I do because the situation is dire. I did not hear my esteemed colleague's interruption.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidNorris" hpid="Mr. Norris Mr. Norris">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norris</NameTxt>
      <P>The Senator said there was a man about whom she had mixed feelings but she never named him.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BrianMullooly" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Through the Chair, please.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="294" />
    <Speaker pid="ThereseRidge" hpid="Mrs. Ridge Mrs. Ridge">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Ridge</NameTxt>
      <P>I do apologise but I was provoked, as the Chair will understand.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnCreganFF" hpid="Mr. J. Cregan Mr. J. Cregan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J. Cregan</NameTxt>
      <P>Will the Leader of the House allow time for a debate on the Department of Finance's scheme of tax concessions for people with disabilities? There is inconsistency as some people are able to avail of it while others, often with more severe disabilities, are not. The scheme's criteria must be reformed and I ask the Leader to allow time for debate.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DenisDinoCregan" hpid="Mr. D. Cregan Mr. D. Cregan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. D. Cregan</NameTxt>
      <P>Last Thursday I listened to questions being asked about a debate, chaired by an Cathaoirleach and myself, the night before. It is disturbing that one of the finest debates in this House, which produced constructive ideas from all sides and included an excellent response from the Minister, was not shown at all on RTE. Only the early debates in this House get coverage. It is as if the producer goes home at 5 o'clock. This was a good debate with constructive ideas, such as Senator's Ross's proposal that we invite the British ambassador here. It should have been heard and seen by the public. If those at RTE do not listen or look, then how can the public?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidNorris" hpid="Mr. Norris Mr. Norris">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norris</NameTxt>
      <P>And the newspapers also.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DenisDinoCregan" hpid="Mr. D. Cregan Mr. D. Cregan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. D. Cregan</NameTxt>
      <P>It is unfair to this House and to the people.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="CamillusGlynn" hpid="Mr. Glynn Mr. Glynn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Glynn</NameTxt>
      <P>I support the remarks of Senator Ó Murchú about the reinterment of the remains of the volunteers last Sunday and especially his proposal on the reinterment of Thomas Kent. It is appropriate that this House acknowledge the role of the Defence Forces. They were impeccable and performed admirably. As my party's spokesman on defence, I was proud to be there.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ShaneRoss" hpid="Mr. Ross Mr. Ross">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Ross</NameTxt>
      <P>I support the call by the Leader of the Opposition for a debate on the Shannon stopover. It is high time that this was debated in this House and that it was voted on. It is time that the Shannon stopover was stopped.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MadeleineTaylorQuinn" hpid="Mrs. Taylor-Quinn Mrs. Taylor-Quinn">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Taylor-Quinn</NameTxt>
      <P>A point of information &ndash; the Leader of the Opposition called for a debate on Aer Lingus, not the Shannon stopover.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BrianMullooly" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>There is no such thing as a point of information.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MadeleineTaylorQuinn" hpid="Mrs. Taylor-Quinn Mrs. Taylor-Quinn">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Taylor-Quinn</NameTxt>
      <P>There is a difference between what Senator Ross stated and what our leader called for.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BrianMullooly" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Order, please. Let Senator Ross continue without interruption.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ShaneRoss" hpid="Mr. Ross Mr. Ross">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Ross</NameTxt>
      <P>I apologise to the House and the Senator. I did not intend to be provocative. However, let us debate the Shannon stopover, whether Fine Gael calls for it or not. I understood that was his proposal.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="295" />
    <Speaker pid="MadeleineTaylorQuinn" hpid="Mrs. Taylor-Quinn Mrs. Taylor-Quinn">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Taylor-Quinn</NameTxt>
      <P>It was a deliberate misrepresentation.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ShaneRoss" hpid="Mr. Ross Mr. Ross">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Ross</NameTxt>
      <P>We should cease having statements and instead debate a motion on the issues which the Leader proposes. It is appropriate that we will debate the economy, but it is unfortunate that on other issues we have statements with no motion to focus on so that people can pin their colours to the mast. It would be more fitting for the House and the parties to express a view on Aer Lingus because individual statements get people off the hook and vary according to the geographic location of the Senator. I understand from &ldquo;Morning Ireland&rdquo; that the Minister for Public Enterprise will come here tomorrow. Then the House should express a view on the Shannon stopover and Aer Lingus rather than present inconclusive, rambling statements.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="AnnLeonard" hpid="Ms Leonard Ms Leonard">
      <NameTxt>Ms Leonard</NameTxt>
      <P>I support the call by Senator John Cregan for a debate on tax concessions for people with disabilities. There are anomalies in relation to these concessions.</P>
      <P>I wish to clarify for Senator Taylor-Quinn that Dublin people are not being made to leave the county to have babies. Members will recognise that there has been a huge increase in the number of asylum seekers coming to our country, which puts an extra strain on maternity services in the city. This is coupled with an increase in the number of Irish people who have moved to Dublin. It is only right that we look at developing services on a regional basis as well as continuing the development of smaller county units for maternity services.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MargaretCox" hpid="Ms Cox Ms Cox">
      <NameTxt>Ms Cox</NameTxt>
      <P>I support calls for a debate on the use of the Internet and on the recent report from the Department of Justice, Equality and Law Reform. It is important that we focus on the issue of technology and access to it. For many who live in peripheral areas, broad band technology is not available and will not be available in the short-term. We need equality of access for all and we need a flat-rate access fee immediately. I would welcome an opportunity to debate with the Minister the barriers which prevent this. For some reason, Eircom has difficulties making this available to us and to the service providers.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PaschalMooney" hpid="Mr. Mooney Mr. Mooney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Mooney</NameTxt>
      <P>It is appropriate that our friend and colleague, Senator Cox, should refer to the Internet. If Members are aspiring Deputies and want to get a good website on the cheap, she will be glad to talk to them about it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I support the comments by Senators Glynn and Labhrás Ó Murchú on last weekend's commemoration. As a spokesman on broadcasting, I see last Sunday as one of the finest examples of the case for public service broadcasting. It was RTE's finest hour. When it comes to big occasions like this, there is no other broadcasting company &ndash; not even the BBC &ndash; which can rise to the occasion as RTE did. For the many people who <Col N="296" /> could not be in Dublin last Sunday, RTE captured the occasion superbly. I am interested in seeing the TAM ratings of this event.</P>
    <P>It would now be opportune for RTE to commission a series on the period from 1916 to 1921. The ignorance of this period is extraordinary. If one looks at the media comment leading up to last Sunday, there were large gaps in the knowledge of many of our so-called experts who tried to suggest that history was being re-written. In 1966 RTE commissioned such a series on the insurrection in 1916, a series that, surprisingly, was never repeated. RTE still has that series. The Taoiseach referred to the &ldquo;closure&rdquo; of this aspect of our history &ndash; with the exception of Thomas Ceannt &ndash; and it is an opportune time for such a series.</P>
    <P>I ask the Leader if he will invite the Minister of State at the Department of Agriculture, Food and Rural Development, Deputy Éamon Ó Cuív, to the House to explain the Clár initiative, which in a sense slipped by over the last two weeks. The Minister of State has identified seriously economically disadvantaged areas of the country. It is important that all sides of the House have an opportunity to debate this matter. Members representing rural Ireland have long been calling for some initiative to bring disadvantaged areas up to speed. The initiative which the Minister of State, Deputy Éamon Ó Cuiv, launched in recent weeks received minimal coverage at a national level, although it received extensive coverage at provincial level. It would be an opportunity for the Minister of State to highlight a significant initiative in terms of improving the prosperity of the areas designated.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PaddyBurke" hpid="Mr. Burke Mr. Burke">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Burke</NameTxt>
      <P>I ask the Leader for a debate on the tourism industry. Time was promised in this session for such a debate. When is it envisaged? The tourism industry is in crisis. First, the industry suffered from foot and mouth disease. Then came the 11 September attacks and the whole area is up in the clouds. I ask the Leader to arrange for an urgent debate.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DonnieCassidyFF" hpid="Mr. Cassidy Mr. Cassidy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cassidy</NameTxt>
      <P>I wish to inform the House that the Aer Lingus Bill, 2000, is being withdrawn. Senators Connor, Taylor-Quinn, Norris and Glennon called for a debate on Aer Lingus as a matter of urgency. As the Senators may be aware, the Minister for Public Enterprise will be in the Dáil at least twice today, if not three times, in regard to various matters pertaining to her portfolio but especially matters concerning Aer Lingus. The Minister has agreed to facilitate the Order of Business in this House by making herself available from 5 p.m. until 8 p.m. tomorrow evening to allow for statements on the current state of Aer Lingus. I noted the large number of Senators who requested this in the last two weeks and I look forward to their contributions.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Senators Henry, Taylor-Quinn and Cox called for the report on the Internet to be debated and <Col N="297" /> I have no difficulty in allocating time for that. Senator Costello called for a debate on post offices and I have already agreed to allocate time for it. Senators Taylor-Quinn, Henry and other Senators called for a debate on health issues. Perhaps when the new health policy is available in a few weeks' time it would be appropriate to have an all-day debate on this matter.</P>
    <P>Senator Ormonde called for a debate on the future role of FÁS. I am aware that she is very committed to the great work it has carried out over the years. Tomorrow we will have a four hour debate on the economy and perhaps this point can be raised with the Minister for Finance, Deputy McCreevy, who will be present.</P>
    <P>Senator Taylor-Quinn called for an update on the extension of powers of the Lindsay tribunal. I agreed with the sentiments which she expressed last week and hope that this will be done as soon as possible.</P>
    <P>Senators Norris, Glynn, Ó Murchú and Mooney offered their congratulations to all concerned in the organisation of the State funerals last Sunday. It was a privilege to be present and I congratulate the Taoiseach, the Government, the Defence Forces and all others associated with the event. I join with Senator Ó Murchú in calling for the reinterment of Thomas Ceannt. As Senator Mooney said, RTE excelled once again in its coverage, which was compulsive viewing. I met many people who asked to have this opinion expressed in the Seanad today to publicly congratulate RTE on their magnificent work last Sunday.</P>
    <P>Senator Norris called for a debate on the current progress of the Luas and I have no difficulty in allocating time for this. I will pass on his views <Col N="298" /> to the Minister for the Environment and Local Government regarding MOT testing.</P>
    <P>Senator Ridge called for a debate on homelessness and I have no difficulty in allocating time for this before Christmas. Senators John Cregan and Leonard called on the Minister for Finance to come into the House to clarify the tax concessions to the disabled. This has been mentioned on many occasions here, in particular on the Finance Bill by Senator Farrell. There seems to be a different view of discretion right across the board and the Minister may address this in the forthcoming budget or in the Finance Bill. I have no problem in allocating time for this.</P>
    <P>Senator Dino Cregan expressed his disappointment at RTE's coverage of the Sellafield debate. This has already been expressed in the House. I have raised it with the relevant authorities and have expressed the concern of the House that legislation should take precedence at all times over statements, motions and the Order of Business. In fairness RTE has been keeping to the 25% guideline for Seanad coverage on &ldquo;Oireachtas Report&rdquo;. Regarding the proposal by Senator Ross that the ambassador come to the House, I heard this matter covered by RTE in highlights of the week on a Saturday morning. It was a suggestion of note and I will again pass on the Senator's views on the issue of Sellafield.</P>
    <Speaker pid="BrianMullooly" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator Connor has moved an amendment to the Order of Business: &ldquo;That statements on Shannon Airport be taken today&rdquo;. Is the amendment being pressed?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnConnor" hpid="Mr. Connor Mr. Connor">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Connor</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes.</P>
      <P>Amendment put.</P>
      <P>Tá</P>
      <P>
      </P>
    </Speaker>
    <table pgwide="1">
      <tgroup cols="2">
        <colspec colname="1" colnum="1" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <colspec colname="2" colnum="2" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry rowsep="1">Burke, Paddy.<br />Connor, John.<br />Coogan, Fintan.<br />Cosgrave, Liam T.<br />Costello, Joe.<br />Cregan, Denis (Dino).<br />Henry, Mary.</entry>
            <entry rowsep="1">Jackman, Mary.<br />Keogh, Helen.<br />Norris, David.<br />Ridge, Thérèse.<br />Ross, Shane.<br />Ryan, Brendan.<br />Taylor-Quinn, Madeleine.</entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
    <P Just="Center">Níl</P>
    <table pgwide="1">
      <tgroup cols="2">
        <colspec colname="1" colnum="1" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <colspec colname="2" colnum="2" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry rowsep="1">Bohan, Eddie.<br />Bonner, Enda.<br />Cassidy, Donie.<br />Cox, Margaret.<br />Cregan, John<br />Dardis, John.<br />Farrell, Willie.<br />Finneran, Michael.<br />Fitzgerald, Liam.<br />Fitzgerald, Tom.<br />Fitzpatrick, Dermot.<br />Gibbons, Jim.<br />Glennon, Jim.<br />Glynn, Camillus.</entry>
            <entry rowsep="1">Hayes, Maurice.<br />Kett, Tony.<br />Kiely, Daniel.<br />Kiely, Rory.<br />Leonard, Ann.<br />Lydon, Don.<br />Mooney, Paschal.<br />Moylan, Pat.<br />O'Brien, Francis.<br />Ó Fearghail, Seán.<br />Ó Murchú, Labhrás.<br />Ormonde, Ann.<br />Quill, Máirín.<br /></entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
    <P Just="Center">Tellers: Tá, Senators Burke and Ridge; Níl, Senators T. Fitzgerald and Gibbons.</P>
    <P>Amendment declared lost.</P>
    <P>Order of Business agreed to.</P>
    <P>
    </P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Double Taxation Relief Orders:" RHead="Referral to Joint Committee">
    <Title>Double Taxation Relief Orders: Referral to Joint Committee.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="DonnieCassidyFF" hpid="Mr. Cassidy Mr. Cassidy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cassidy</NameTxt>
      <P>I move:</P>
      <P>That the proposals that Seanad Éireann approve the following Orders in draft:</P>
      <P>Double Taxation Relief (Taxes on Income and Capital Gains) (Kingdom of Norway) Order, 2001,</P>
      <P>Double Taxation Relief (Taxes on Income and Capital Gains) (Republic of India) Order, 2001,</P>
      <P>copies of which were laid before Dáil Éireann on 8 October 2001, be referred to the Joint Committee on Finance and the Public Service, in accordance with paragraph (1)(<i>a</i>)(iv) of the Orders of Reference of that committee, which shall, not later than 6 November 2001, send a message to the Seanad in the manner prescribed in Standing Order 67, and Standing Order 69(2) shall accordingly apply.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Atrocities in the United" RHead="States of America: Statements">
    <Title>Atrocities in the United States of America: Statements.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="LizODonnell" hpid="Ms O'Donnell Ms O'Donnell">
      <NameTxt>Minister of State at the Department of Foreign Affairs (Ms O'Donnell)</NameTxt>
      <P>I very much welcome the opportunity of reporting to the Seanad on the current situation following the terrorist atrocities committed in the United States on 11 September. We are now over one month removed from the terrible events of 11 September in the United States. The attacks on New York, Washington and Pennsylvania left more than 5,000 people dead and missing.</P>
      <P>The human impact of these attacks is not just felt in America. I note that it is now estimated that nationals of 80 countries were among the victims of the World Trade Centre attack. People of all nationalities and beliefs were cruelly murdered as they conducted their daily business. These included a now estimated eight Irish citizens.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Since the attacks of 11 September, the world has reacted in an unprecedented way. A global coalition has come together to co-operate in the fight against international terrorism. Action has taken place in the diplomatic, financial, judicial and police spheres and, in the past week or so, in the military sphere as well. As we are now aware, military action against the Taliban regime in Afghanistan by the United States and its allies is into its second week. The firm position of the Government is that military action should be undertaken only as a means of last resort, after all other means have failed. Unfortunately, that is now the situation, but we must be clear where <Col N="299" /><Col N="300" /> the primary responsibility for this outcome rests. It rests with the Taliban regime and its attitude of disdain to the wishes of the international community.</P>
    <P>Before and after the attacks of 11 September the Taliban regime was given every opportunity to respond to the demands of the Security Council. Regrettably, the Taliban regime has over the past two years defied, and continues to defy, the demands of the Security Council to hand over Osama bin Laden, who had been indicted for earlier terrorist attacks on American targets and was on record as urging further attacks on the US, and to dismantle the terrorist camps in the area under its control. The Taliban maintained this position in the face of sanctions imposed by the Security Council.</P>
    <P>Even the terrible events of 11 September in the US, with their horrendous casualties, could not convince the Taliban to surrender Osama bin Laden and his associates. This situation was exacerbated by bin Laden's ongoing incitement in television interviews of further attacks on the US and others. Given the history of this man and his organisation, we must take seriously those threats.</P>
    <P>At present we are seeing the apparently deliberate distribution of the anthrax disease in the US. There are reports of suspected cases in many other countries and I note from the statement of Tom Ridge, the new Director of Homeland Security in the US, that the authorities there are acting on the presumption that there may be a connection to Osama bin Laden and his network.</P>
    <P>The US and its allies, in carrying out targeted attacks on the military assets of Osama bin Laden's al-Qaeda network and the Taliban regime, are acting within the inherent right to individual and collective self-defence as recognised under Article 51 of the UN Charter. They are also acting in pursuit of Security Council Resolution 1368, which calls on all states to work together urgently to bring to justice the perpetrators, organisers and sponsors of the terrorist attacks of 11 September and stresses that those responsible for aiding, supporting or harbouring the perpetrators, organisers and sponsors of those acts will be held accountable.</P>
    <P>It is in this context that the Government has accorded its support for the military action now under way, as long as such action is targeted and proportionate and that every effort is made to avoid civilian casualties. Unfortunately, despite the best intentions of those carrying out the military response and despite the claims for the accuracy of modern weapons, inevitably, civilian casualties have regrettably been inflicted. There was an admission yesterday by the US military authorities of the bombing, by mistake, of a Red Cross storage depot. They have apologised for the error and such incidents must be sincerely regretted. No effort must be spared in seeking to prevent the occurrence of civilian casualties. As has been said by everybody, the ordinary people of Afghanistan are not responsible for the atroci<Col N="301" /> ties of 11 September. They have also been the victims of prolonged violence and the extremism of the Taliban regime over a number of years.</P>
    <P>Ireland has been to the forefront in keeping Afghanistan on the agenda of the international community. Since the start of the year we have been very outspoken at the Security Council on the need to focus on the humanitarian concerns of the Afghan people. We have supported and will continue to support the idea of the Security Council taking a comprehensive approach to Afghanistan, which includes addressing the political, economic, humanitarian and human rights situations. The Security Council held consultations on Afghanistan on 9 and 16 October.</P>
    <P>In this regard, the appointment by the Secretary General of a special representative for Afghanistan, Ambassador Lakhdar Brahimi, is especially welcome. He has a long and distinguished career in the service of the UN and has overall responsibility for the humanitarian and political efforts in Afghanistan. He will manage peacekeeping initiatives with a view to facilitating the establishment of a fully representative, multi-ethnic and broad based Government in Afghanistan and will initiate preparations for the development of plans for the rehabilitation of the country. At Ireland's request, Ambassador Brahimi briefed the Security Council yesterday on his contacts to date.</P>
    <P>There have been reported offers through the media that the Taliban regime might hand over Osama bin Laden to a third country. We would be very pleased if the regime was to now, belatedly, comply with the terms of UN Resolution 1333 of 2000. It requires the Taliban to turn over Osama bin Laden to appropriate authorities in a country where he has been indicted or to an appropriate authority in a country where he will be returned to such a country, or to appropriate authorities in a country where he will be arrested and effectively brought to justice. However, it is difficult to conclude from the reported comments of Taliban officials that such offers can be taken seriously.</P>
    <P>There have been concerns, as reported by the media in recent days, about the likelihood of an imminent attack on states other that Afghanistan. We are aware of no evidence which demonstrates that other states were knowingly involved in harbouring those who planned or executed the 11 September atrocities. There has, moreover, been no mention in our contacts with the US or its military allies of other possible targets for military action being under active consideration.</P>
    <P>The multi-faceted campaign against international terrorism is being pursued across a wide front. Ireland is particularly involved through the United Nations and the European Union. We are also active at a national level. Ireland is particularly conscious of its position of responsibility during its presidency of the UN Security Council. The Minister for Foreign Affairs, Deputy Cowen, spoke to UN Secretary General, Kofi Annan, and to the US Secretary of State, Colin Powell, on the <Col N="302" /> evening the US-led response commenced. The following day and at our initiative the Security Council was briefed by the US and British representatives on the action initiated by their armed forces.</P>
    <P>It is important that the role of the Council is acknowledged. The Security Council recognises the inherent right of individual and collective self-defence under Article 51 of the UN Charter and agreed that the USA and UK action was being taken in exercise of that right. Under the UN Charter measures taken by members in the exercise of the right to self-defence must be reported immediately to the Security Council. This was done immediately after the commencement of attacks on Sunday 7 October, by letters to the President of the Security Council from both the USA and UK. They made it clear that the military action is directed at terrorists and those who harbour them, not at the civilian population. By its very nature, the action taken by the US and UK armed forces is in stark contrast with the attacks by the terrorists on 11 September, who set out to deliberately attack the civilian population in New York, Washington and Pennsylvania. The UN Secretary General when commenting about the military operations, recognised the right to self-defence as contained in the UN Charter.</P>
    <P>A key priority of our presidency of the Security Council is to ensure that resolutions on terrorism are implemented, in particular the follow-up to Security Council Resolution 1373 which was agreed on 28 September. A Security Council counter-terrorism committee has been set up. This committee was established on foot of Resolution 1373 and will monitor how states comply with the provisions of the resolution in areas such as the financing of terrorism and denying safe haven to terrorists. The crucially important International Convention for the Suppression of the Financing of Terrorism, 1999, was signed in New York on 15 October by the Irish Permanent Representative to the UN. It requires states parties to make it an offence in their national law for any person, directly or indirectly, unlawfully and wilfully, to provide or collect funds with the intention or in the knowledge that they are to be used to carry out terrorist acts. Ireland will participate fully in the efforts of the international community to choke off the funds of terrorists. The preparation of primary legislation to enable ratification of the convention is being given the highest priority by the Minister for Justice, Equality and Law Reform.</P>
    <P>The role of the UN is critical to the ultimate successful resolution of the situation in Afghanistan. That country cannot be allowed to remain a failed state where continuing internal conflicts breed illegal activities and provide a safe haven for terrorists. Our long-term objective is to support a UN-led peace process towards a truly representative government for the Afghan people. As President of the Security Council, Ireland is closely involved with the multi-track consultations on the situation. It is not appropriate to <Col N="303" /> create prescriptions for post-Taliban Afghanistan. Any arrangements must be seen to come from the Afghan people themselves. We are in favour of a stable, fully representative government with the security of sustained, and well co-ordinated development and rehabilitation assistance from the international community. Ireland stands ready to assist in whatever way it can in achieving this.</P>
    <P>The EU has adopted a key role in supporting the fight against terrorism. The special European Council which met on 21 September gave a clear political impetus to confronting the challenge of terrorism. It was agreed to pursue a wide range of judicial co-operation measures. These include Commission proposals for council framework decisions on combating terrorism and on the introduction of a European arrest warrant. The meeting of EU foreign ministers on 8 October expressed its whole-hearted support for the action being taken in self defence and in conformity with the UN Charter and UN Security Council Resolution 1368. The Council also stressed that the carefully targeted response launched on 7 October was not an attack on Islam nor the people of Afghanistan, whom the EU is determined to support and sustain.</P>
    <P>Urgent work is under way in various Council formations to evolve concrete measures for consideration and adoption next December. A special general affairs council meeting is being held in Luxembourg today to review progress in advance of the informal European Council next Friday. Together with our partners in the EU, Ireland is in favour of a UN-led process in the vital next stages for Afghanistan. As with EU relations with third countries, in order to support counter terrorism and international law, we need to provide assistance and support to a category of countries in need, as recognised by Security Resolution 1373. Afghanistan's neighbours stand to benefit. Reconstruction in Afghanistan would stimulate Pakistan's economy and reinforce economic relations between the two countries. The Government has established internal arrangements to co-ordinate the follow through on our national responsibilities under the UN and EU initiatives. The newly created Office of Emergency Planning will assist in better co-ordinating our response to any threats which we may yet face.</P>
    <P>It cannot be denied or ignored that the continued failure to achieve a just and comprehensive settlement in the Middle East is one of the major factors giving rise to acts of terrorism in that region and in the wider world. Any approach to the problem of global terrorism must take account of the grievances of the Palestinian people living under Israeli occupation while recognising the right of the Israeli people to live in peace and security. Ireland has long supported the right of the Palestinian people to self-determination, including the right to their own state. The best prospect of achieving a viable, independent <Col N="304" /> state, which exists in fact and not only in name is, as the Palestinians themselves recognise, through the Middle East peace process.</P>
    <P>President Arafat visited Dublin two days ago and briefed the Taoiseach and the Minister for Foreign Affairs on the current situation in the region. He asked Ireland to use all its influence in the international community to aid the process. No one can be under any illusion that the parties to this conflict will resolve matters without international support and occasional pressure. The murder today of the Israeli tourism minister, Rehavam Ze'evi, illustrates the difficulties faced in the peace process. Further assassinations are absolutely counterproductive to progress and are clearly the work of enemies of the peace process.</P>
    <P>There has clearly been a renewal of international commitment to the region in the past few weeks, which I welcome. Ireland will contribute to peace efforts as fully as is possible through the European Union, the United Nations and other international fora, as well as through ongoing bilateral contacts with the parties. In terms of practical assistance to the Palestinian people, Ireland Aid has had a development programme for the Palestinian territories for some years. Expenditure this year is budgeted at approximately IR£1.2 million in addition to the IR£1.24 million provided in emergency relief since the start of the Intifada.</P>
    <P>I give particular attention to the humanitarian crisis in Afghanistan. As Minister of State with particular responsibility in this area, I am acutely aware of the enormous challenge the world community now faces in protecting the vulnerable people of Afghanistan. Their lives remain at risk, not only from ongoing conflict but also from the climatic hardships of drought and winter. In coming to terms with the appalling attacks perpetrated against the people of the United States, the world has also become more aware than ever of how protracted the humanitarian crisis in Afghanistan has been. It has spanned two decades of conflict and has been worsened in recent years by successive outbreaks of severe drought. To make things even worse for the Afghan people, they now face the onset of the harsh winter.</P>
    <P>Earlier this year the UN conducted a number of nutritional surveys of displaced persons at various locations within Afghanistan. Around the same time Concern conducted a nutritional survey among the settled community in northern Afghanistan. All of these surveys found that people, whether still living in their homes or displaced from them, were running out of resources with which to cope with the onset of winter in mid-November. Having used their remaining food supplies and sold their livestock and seed stocks to survive during the period of summer drought, hundreds of thousands of people are now facing into a bleak winter for which they are ill-equipped. In a country whose people rely predominantly on agricultural activity to survive, the <Col N="305" /> collapse of crop yields and of the small but important income they generate is catastrophic.</P>
    <P>Ireland and other international donors have been working for some time now to help meet the demands of the Afghan humanitarian crisis. Last October, the Government gave it priority as a then &ldquo;forgotten emergency&rdquo;. Days before the 11 September atrocities, the World Food Programme issued a $152 million humanitarian appeal. The UN Office for the Coordination of Humanitarian Affairs estimates that between 3 and 5 million people will suffer as of now if we fail to get aid to them before winter, which comes before the middle of November.</P>
    <P>Taking account of these underlying realities, the Government has focused on four main objectives in its efforts to help resolve the humanitarian crisis, namely, getting aid into Afghanistan to the hundreds of thousands at risk within its borders, including by securing or negotiating safe delivery routes through which this can reliably take place; beating the winter deadline &ndash; we have only until mid-November to get aid through before the harsh winter sets in or millions of Afghans will die; protecting emergency aid stocks, humanitarian workers and the vulnerable population &ndash; both in Afghanistan and along its borders &ndash; and we wish to see all humanitarian activity protected in accordance with international humanitarian law; and re-opening borders so that aid agencies and their staff can respond effectively and, of equal importance, so refugees can get to safety. UNHCR is prepared for an initial 1.5 million refugees; we must have the flexibility to deal with any increase in this estimate.</P>
    <P>The Government's overriding priority in humanitarian terms is to get aid to the hundreds of thousands at risk within Afghanistan as soon as possible. We are making every appropriate effort, including discussion at a special General Affairs Council in Luxembourg, to give the humanitarian emergency the urgent attention it requires. It is a core component of Ireland's working programme in its Presidency of the UN Security Council. The Minister for Foreign Affairs raised it in the course of his various meetings in Washington and New York in September. It is being actively pursued in our bilateral meetings with the key UN and regional representatives. Our permanent representation to the UN in Geneva is similarly engaged on a daily basis with the relevant UN, Red Cross and other international humanitarian agencies.</P>
    <P>At a meeting of the Security Council yesterday, Ireland highlighted the humanitarian situation in Afghanistan and commended the work of humanitarian organisations in the region. We urged Pakistan and Iran to reopen their borders to enable cross-border deliveries of aid and to facilitate preparations for an influx of refugees. We stressed the need for the international community to provide host countries with financial support in this regard. We also emphasised the need for UN involvement, with inputs from the <Col N="306" /> EU and other relevant organisations and in consultation with regional partners in the process of achieving new governmental arrangements for Afghanistan. UN involvement would also be needed in the reconstruction and development of Afghanistan and in long-term humanitarian assistance.</P>
    <P>I was able to press home the importance of all these humanitarian priorities when I attended a specially convened meeting of EU Development Ministers, which was held in Brussels last week on 10 October. At the meeting, which dealt solely with Afghanistan, we had an opportunity to discuss how the EU can effectively respond to the needs in that country and how long-term development assistance can contribute to the fight against terrorism in a broader context.</P>
    <P>Following my recent announcement of an additional £2.8 million in emergency assistance, Ireland has provided a total of £4.03 million to the people of Afghanistan this year. Similarly, the EU has committed over &euro;300 million. This expenditure represents both the gravity of the current crisis and the enormous humanitarian commitment that Ireland and other EU member states are making to Afghanistan. As I said, we now have a clear and pressing challenge &ndash; to deliver that aid to those who need it most before winter sets in. Ireland Aid is continuing to work closely with our NGOs and other partners to achieve this.</P>
    <P>Before 11 September, it was estimated that above 700,000 people were displaced within the territory of Afghanistan. Since then, more people have been uprooted from their homes and the current figure for internally displaced people is somewhere above 1 million. The anticipated mass exodus of refugees has not materialised to date. The UN High Commissioner for Refugees estimates that about 1,000 refugees have fled Afghanistan each day since the appalling events of 11 September. To date, therefore, most of those who have fled their homes have chosen to remain in the countryside in Afghanistan. However, this has created a further layer of problems for the people concerned, which must also be addressed by the international community.</P>
    <P>We cannot afford to become complacent about the low level of refugee movement to date. If the current refugee problem escalates significantly over the next few weeks the borders may have to be reopened. The UNHCR is catering for the possible influx of 1.5 million refugees across the border of Afghanistan and Iran. This is a very real possibility and we must lay plans now to deal with it. We will continue our efforts to ensure that the international donor community and countries hosting refugees can work together to respond effectively to the evolving refugee situation.</P>
    <P>We also support the ongoing work of Irish NGOs such as Trócaire, Christian Aid, GOAL and Concern in trying to improve circumstances for refugees and mitigate the impact of increasing population on local host communities. In addition, we are supporting the provision of basic <Col N="307" /> water, sanitation and nutritional needs for those stranded within the country. Our support for humanitarian efforts, both within Afghanistan and along its borders, is intended to provide balance in the focus of Ireland's humanitarian response.</P>
    <P>The humanitarian problems of Afghanistan are an enormously challenging burden for the world to carry. As a caring international community, we have to find effective means of ensuring delivery of vital humanitarian assistance to those who need it most when they need it. We have to balance the enormous international aid commitment, which is somewhere in excess of $700 million, with an adequate and co-ordinated means of reaching its intended beneficiaries. While aware of the difficulties in ensuring the effective delivery of aid to all parts of Afghanistan, I hope that these can be resolved by concerted effort between the various parties concerned.</P>
    <P>There are a number of aid delivery routes being operated by the World Food Programme and other international agencies. In addition, Irish and other NGOs are making their own efforts to source and deliver aid into Northern Afghanistan <i>via</i> neighbouring countries such as Turkmenistan and Tajikistan. While these aid delivery routes are effective in their own right, they remain vulnerable to interruption and have, in some cases, been cut off at different times. It is vital to ensure secure and unhindered access arrangements for food convoys over the coming weeks.</P>
    <P>At present, it is estimated that about 1,000 metric tonnes of aid are being delivered in Afghanistan each day by the UN agencies. This delivery rate has to be increased considerably if a humanitarian disaster is to be averted. The scale of this potential disaster is more than five times that of the refugee crisis that followed the Rwandan genocide of 1994. It is incumbent upon us all to co-operate fully in this enormous humanitarian endeavour so we can succeed in dealing with the first major humanitarian crisis of the twenty first century.</P>
    <P>I thank Senators for their attention.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JohnConnor" hpid="Mr. Connor Mr. Connor">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Connor</NameTxt>
      <P>I am delighted to be able to participate in this debate and I welcome the Minister of State to the House. I have recently taken over as the spokesperson on Foreign Affairs on this side of the House and it is my first occasion to speak in this capacity with the Minister of State present.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The terrorist outrages in New York, Washington, and Pennsylvania on 11 September were rightly condemned by the whole world community. The Government, the Members of the Houses and the people of Ireland simultaneously expressed shock and grief over the death of so many innocent people who died in such a horrible way. We offered our condolences to the bereaved families who are all over the world. Citizens of 80 countries died in the outrage in New York on 11 <Col N="308" /> September. We offered solidarity to the American people and we joined the world community in offering our co-operation to bring the perpetrators, organisers and sponsors of the terrorist attacks to justice.</P>
    <P>If the Taliban government had complied with the relevant UN Security Council resolution, to which the Minister of State has referred, it would have saved the Afghan people from a huge amount of damage. Much of what remains of their economy would have been saved because a substantial amount of natural assets are being destroyed in the current military campaign by the United States. We grieve for the innocent victims in Afghanistan, who are suffering terribly.</P>
    <P>Afghanistan has had a terrible history. Few people know that in the 19th century there were two terrible wars called the Afghan wars fought by the British and the Russians. Britain defended her interests in India while Russia wanted to expand her interests further into Afghanistan, which was one of the neighbouring countries of Tsarist Russia. Tens of thousands of people died in those conflicts. Afghanistan has also had an appalling history in the 20th century. We all remember what happened in 1979 when the then Soviet Union invaded Afghanistan and put a Communist Government in place in Kabul. That led to years of civil war in which the great powers took sides because this was the era of the Cold War. The United States of America supported and armed the Taliban and others opposed to the Russian-sponsored regime in Kabul. No principle was involved other than they were the &ldquo;enemy of my enemy&rdquo;. Principles went out the window and regimes were supported simply for that reason.</P>
    <P>It is important to highlight this because there is a lesson to be learned from what happened, namely, that it is like sowing the dragon's teeth which eventually grow into armed monsters which attack the very people who sowed the teeth. I sincerely hope that great powers in the world who meddle in civil wars in other countries because they see their interests being challenged or they believe they must defend their interests in these countries learn the lesson that what was done in such an unprincipled way in the 1970s and 1980s in Afghanistan should not be repeated.</P>
    <P>There is no point in this war on terrorism, and the American President said it will be a long war, achieving the overthrow of the Taliban regime in Afghanistan if it does not deal with the root causes of terrorism. So much of it has its root causes in the denial of justice in the Middle East. What is happening and has happened in the past nine months between Israel and Palestine is terrible. While no one is blameless, I find the greater weight of blame lies with Israel. The perception abroad in the world, especially in the Muslim and Arab worlds, is that the United States is too partial to the state of Israel. That often leads to the arrogance and inflexibility of the Israeli Government. I am glad the Bush Presidency, unlike the Clinton Administration which showed little interest in a settlement in the Middle East, is <Col N="309" /> showing a greater degree of interest. That is reflected in the recent actions, statements and visits of Mr. Tony Blair, the British Prime Minister. While we might feel we do not have great influence, nevertheless, because Members of the House are elected politicians, we should, when expressing our views, state our wish that much of what is done today and the good intentions which appear to be on the agenda had happened four or five years ago.</P>
    <P>The Minister was right not to speculate what might happen in the aftermath of the Taliban regime in Afghanistan, but I have more freedom and I will make some suggestions about what should happen. The international community must work towards establishing a multi-ethnic Government in that country which draws support from the many ethnic groups there, and there are many. They need to be represented in the governance of the country when a settlement is ultimately put in place.</P>
    <P>In tandem with the political settlement of putting in place a Government which has the consent of the people and to which people of the many ethnic groups in the country can give their allegiance &ndash; the only factor which appears to unite them is the Islamic religion and that they are all Muslims &ndash; the international community must also put in place a rehabilitation programme for the destroyed economy of Afghanistan. It should put in place a programme for the return of the millions of Afghanis who are refugees in Iran and Pakistan, the hundreds of thousands who are no doubt in Uzbekistan, Turkmenistan and other neighbouring states and those who, possibly, are in China.</P>
    <P>Millions of mines have been laid all over Afghanistan. It is said to be the most mine-laden country in the world. That is a huge problem which must be tackled if the people are to be resettled in their homesteads or the areas where they lived. The Minister made the point that, by and large, it is a rural society with a large proportion of the population relying totally on farming for its economic survival, and that farming involves patterns which have not changed for hundreds of years. While the economy needs to be brought to some modern standard, that will not happen in a quick time scale after the conflict has concluded. Most who will be returned &ndash; I presume there will be a return programme supported by the international community &ndash; will have to be returned to where they lived in the countryside. Then the problem of the millions of mines must be addressed. The infrastructure of the country, roadways, railways etc. has been destroyed and there is continuing destruction of those assets as a result of the military action.</P>
    <P>We should state to our friend, the United States of America, that this military action should be as short as possible and should be targeted at the areas that need to be dealt with &ndash; by that we mean the Taliban military installations, arms dumps, other means by which the Taliban regime has conducted its reign of terror on its own <Col N="310" /> people and, if they can be found, those camps where terrorists are trained and huge amounts of arms are no doubt stored.</P>
    <P>Bombing and warfare has changed fundamentally from 50 years ago or during the Second World War. We live in the era of the smart bomb which can be targeted on a particular location and the amount of explosives used regulated. Nevertheless, there are still terrible mistakes, such as the stray bomb which hit the International Red Cross or Red Crescent depot in Kabul yesterday. The United States has apologised for that but it is a pity that apology had to be issued. Tens of thousands of tonnes of emergency humanitarian aid, that is, food aid, in that depot was severely damaged by the explosion and the fire which followed.</P>
    <P>It is important that the House acknowledges the restraint and wise governance under enormous pressure which President Musharraf has shown. Normally we would not praise him in this House or in this country. He is a military leader who came to power more than two years ago in a military coup. There was political chaos, or something close to it, in Pakistan and power was seized by the army. I commend his conciliatory approach towards India. A few months ago he went to India, which is unusual for a leader of Pakistan, and he did not wear his military uniform as normal but went in civilian &lsquo;mufti'. He improved relations with India despite the huge tension which exists over Kashmir. He has shown enormous courage in his own country where there are so many extremists and where the Islamic belief is so deeply held in a totally unreformed way. The Reformation was the greatest thing to happen to Christianity whereas the greatest loss to Islam is that it did not have an upheaval like the Reformation.</P>
    <P>We must acknowledge the huge difficulty a man like General Musharraf has in a country with such traditional religious beliefs. It is officially called the Islamic Republic of Pakistan. He has shown restraint and wonderful courage in joining the international coalition against terrorism. He has pointed out that his Government does not support people who pervert religion in the service of evil. That is what is happening. One of the world's great religions is being perverted in the service of evil by Osama bin Laden and his al-Qaeda clique. General Musharraf has called upon the Taliban regime &ndash; his was one of the only three governments in the world to recognise that regime &ndash; to hand over Osama bin Laden to the international community to be tried for his many crimes. It is important we acknowledge that courage.</P>
    <P>The attitude taken by Iran was entirely different. Its animosities towards the United States took precedence in relation to the war against terrorism despite the fact that Iran has reason to curse the Taliban. The Taliban regime would be totally opposed to the regime in Iran and would engage in terrorism there.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="311" />There is not a lot more to add to this debate. We have expressed our absolute horror at what happened on 11 September. A number of Irish perished in the twin towers and as yet only 400 or 500 bodies have been recovered from the ruins. Thousands of people remain grieving for relatives and loved ones who lost their lives. It has had a huge effect on world opinion towards terrorism and ambivalence, often found here, towards people who take the law into their own hands. There is often a sneaking regard for terrorism but this has changed people's opinion fundamentally. I was delighted to see the restraint during the ceremonies for the reburial of the people executed during the War of Independence. The sermon by Cardinal Cahal Daly was given in a way it might not have been some years ago. Some good can come from appalling evil and attitudes can be changed.</P>
    <P>I am delighted the House has engaged itself again on this issue. It is a good idea that we are debating the issue after having some time to reflect. Unfortunately military action has been necessary and some things will be difficult to accept &ndash; the bombing of the Red Cross depot is difficult to accept. Similarly, the hitting of the Chinese embassy in the bombing in Belgrade should not have happened.</P>
    <P>We have an opportunity now and we hope that Afghanistan will emerge from this unlike what happened when the Russians left Najibullah on the throne in Kabul in the early 1980s. He was quickly overthrown, the world community's interest in Afghanistan quickly faded away and they were left to their own devices at a terrible cost. It was the chaos and political vacuum that followed after the Russians were thrown out, after the Najibullah regime was overthrown, after the Mujahidin regime had come to power, followed by the Taliban, that created the situation of lawlessness which welcomed and sheltered Osama bin Laden and allowed him operate and train the people who carried out the terrible deeds in Nairobi, New York and elsewhere.</P>
    <P>The lesson we must learn is that we must never allow that happen again. The chaos in Afghanistan was created by outside interference. That was what happened in the 19th century when the British and Russians became involved in wars. It was outside interference promoting its own interest because Afghanistan happened to lie between two great powers. When Russia invaded it became the business of the United States to oppose it. We have learned a terrible lesson. I hope some good will come of it and that we will have a reconstructed Afghanistan supported by the international community.</P>
    <Speaker pid="DonLydon" hpid="Mr. Lydon Mr. Lydon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lydon</NameTxt>
      <P>The Government response to this was swift and appropriate. It was a clear response reiterating that we have always been opposed to acts of terrorism from whatever corner they emanate. The Government expects a military response to be &ldquo;proportionate, measured and <Col N="312" /> focused on the pursuit of justice&rdquo;. The responses of the Minister for Foreign Affairs, at various fora such as the United Nations, the European Union, the Dáil and the media have been intelligent, accurate and compassionate. I am grateful at these harrowing times that Deputy Cowen is our Minister for Foreign Affairs and Chairman of the United Nations Security Council. No previous Minister in this office would have represented us better.</P>
      <P>By any measure, the events of 11 September were horrific and without justification. The people who perpetrated these acts, which resulted in the loss of so many innocent lives, did so with no regard to who died. They did not discriminate on the basis of age, sex, nationality, or even religion, as many of their co-religionists were murdered. Their only motivation was to &ldquo;hurt&rdquo; America. If thousands of innocents died, their attitude appears to have been &ldquo;So what?&rdquo;  I do not believe those who hijacked the planes realised the extent of the carnage that was to follow, but we will never know.</P>
      <P>I read and heard in the media some people say that America had it coming, that its foreign policy is bad, or that it interferes across the world. That may be true or not, but nothing &ndash; I repeat, nothing &ndash; justifies the loss of innocent life in this way or on this scale. No warning was given, no declaration of war made and no indication that it might happen. Thousands of innocent people arose on that fateful day, went to work and died horribly, being burnt or crushed, while others saw no way out but to leap from a great height to certain death. This wanton act of terrorism cannot be justified and no excuse can make it right.</P>
      <P>The scale was a defining feature of this act. One wonders how anyone could bring himself to do it, no matter what welcome he imagined awaited him in paradise. I mourn the deaths of the terrorists also. They were young men dedicated to some cause, misguided and probably manipulated by someone like Osama bin Laden. Their own lives were wasted. Should we be amazed at the capacity of people to visit such horror on others? No.</P>
      <P>Was the loss of innocent life in Birmingham and London different from what happened in New York? Of course, there was a warning and that made it all right. Was the loss of life in Omagh any different? There was a warning there too. What of the Dublin and Monaghan bombs for which there was no warning? I repeat that bombing innocent people in the pursuit of a cause which one believes to be just cannot be justified.</P>
      <P>None of us can fail to be moved by events. I was struck by the words of the Minister for Foreign Affairs after his visit to Manhattan,</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>It was for me a traumatic, emotional and deeply saddening experience. Nothing could have prepared me for the sheer immensity of the destruction of property, but even more shocking was that on this spot on that terrible Tuesday morning thousands of innocent people <Col N="313" /> going about their daily business had been slaughtered in the name of an evil hatred.</P>
    <P>We share in America's grief because it was home to many of our people. When they had no home here, it gave them a new one. There are 42 million people of Irish extraction living there. In his recent speech, the Taoiseach stated:</P>
    <P>We feel a special kinship with America and New York, with firefighters and police, office workers and corporate leaders, many of whose parents, grandparents and ancestors came from this land and made the United States the largest nation on Earth. The names on the casualty list of this terrorist attack include Boyle, Crowley, Collins, O'Hagan, MacSweeny and O'Neill, our names, the names of our families, our friends and the names of our nation. They include young people only very recently arrived from Ireland. Now they are gone. Our hearts and our prayers go out to their families.</P>
    <P>We must also support America because of the Second World War, and I am just old enough to remember it. If America had not entered the war, we might now be ruled by Nazis. We support the USA in its time of need and grief because, as I have stated many times before in the House, when the chips are down, we call on Uncle Sam, and Uncle Sam has never been found wanting.</P>
    <P>We must pause at this time and look beyond these events to ask what motivates people to take such extreme action, no matter how misguided. We must ask if they tried legitimate ways to fight for what they believe and found that their countries' systems and structures failed them. These are legitimate, important questions that must be asked, and there is no better time than now.</P>
    <P>For the first time we perceive global terrorism, a shadowy, nebulous culture with tentacles in every country. If it is not destroyed we will continue to live in a less secure world and they will strike again and we will not know where, when or how. It is imperative that we are not complacent because it is when we least expect it that an attack may occur. The anthrax attacks around the world are an example of how a few people with little resources can cause havoc. They can terrorise people and cause economic damage. The economic considerations are important. Witness the recent fall in international travel.</P>
    <P>We have no option but to respond and that response should be twofold. We must attack the terrorists and also help establish democracies. We must not support dictatorships as we have in the past in places such as Chile, Indonesia or the Central African Republic. We ought not to support immoral or illegal regimes simply because their leaders are pro-business, pro-West or pro-American. We must address injustice around the world. The Minister stated, &ldquo;We must redouble our efforts to put an end to the many conflicts and injustices which, while they can never ever justify the horrors of 11 September, are exploited by the terrorists to garner support for their warped philosophies.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="314" />Millions of people live in poverty and environments where disease and famine are rampant. We should deal fairly with developing countries, especially in the dealings of the World Trade Organisation, the International Monetary Fund and the World Bank, and we should not cripple them with debt.</P>
    <P>We ought also to address Arab grievances, particularly over the Holy Land. I witnessed the abuse of Palestinians when I was there, and as Deputy O'Donnell, the Minister of State at the Department of Foreign Affairs, stated, &ldquo;Any approach to the problem of global terrorism must take account of the grievances of the Palestinian people living under Israeli occupation, while recognising the right of the Israeli people to live in peace and security.&rdquo;  The Palestinians have lived there for centuries. It is similar to my knocking on someone's door claiming to be one of the Tuatha de Danaan who were here 3,000 years ago and demanding his land. We must help establish a <i>rapprochement</i> between the two sides, so that Palestinians and Israelis can live in peace.</P>
    <P>Let us be honest. War was declared on Afghanistan and it is said that truth is the first casualty of war. The second is probably innocent civilians. Many of them will be killed in Afghanistan, people who know little of world politics or the attack on the twin towers because of the Taliban's media black-out. They are real people. Having long hair and beards or wearing strange clothes does not mean that they do not bleed when cut, cry when they lose a loved one, or laugh when something funny happens, nor does it mean that they are not intelligent and cannot appreciate that democracy, with its guarantees of freedom of expression, may be a better form of government than the one to which they have been subjected.</P>
    <P>It is said that the King of Afghanistan may be reinstated. It has also been said that a benign monarchy is the best form of government. Maybe it is, but whatever about the old king, who knows what the new prince may begin? I will stick with democracy. Let us demonstrate that democracy means freedom, freedom to worship as people see fit, to work, trade, travel, speak out and have better lives. Then and only then will the terrorists be defeated because without a cause they will have lost their reason to exist.</P>
    <P>The Minister outlined the Government position, which is to get aid to Afghanistan. Why did we not get it there before this started? The Minister mentioned beating the winter deadline, preparing emergency aid stocks, providing humanitarian workers and re-opening borders, which are all laudable objectives, but they have not been achieved in time. The Americans armed the Taliban. They trained bin Laden before he turned against them. In future, we need to look at what we are doing in this regard. Pouring in aid for the sake of it will not do much good. We need to help developing countries like Afghanistan. This does not just mean giving the people food. We must give them schools, hospitals and industries, help them establish a democratic form of government <Col N="315" /> and then leave them to their own devices to run their country as they see fit.</P>
    <P>Terrorism must be defeated, and Members know that. However, I am concerned about the war that may ensue in Afghanistan. Many innocent people will be killed, people who would rather live under a different system. It should be remembered that Afghanistan was not always under the rule of the Taliban or unjust people. Like many other places, where injustice creeps in terrorism takes over. There are many examples of this throughout the world and they do not need explicit mention. So far, we seem to be headed in the right direction. I am pleased the Government asked for moderation in the military response, although that may not happen. Perhaps, we can do something when this is over to help Afghanistan live in a democratic fashion.</P>
    <Speaker pid="DavidNorris" hpid="Mr. Norris Mr. Norris">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norris</NameTxt>
      <P>I welcome this opportunity to contribute to the debate on this subject because I was abroad when these events occurred. Although I attempted to get back from the Middle East, it was not possible and I did not have the opportunity to say what I wanted on this matter. My contribution will be a short one as I am supposed to be at the Joint Committee on Foreign Affairs and I had also arranged to share time with one of my colleagues.</P>
      <P>One of the positive aspects of this tragedy has been the intelligent, analytical approach from this House. Members have taken a balanced view, which is important. Although we support the democratic values of the west, we should not be uncritical of the circumstances that led to this situation. The attacks were horrific. It was appalling to watch people tumble from the 101st floor of that building. One cannot imagine the feelings of those trapped in the inferno. It is still incredible to consider that the World Trade Center is gone. This morning I received the latest issue of the <i>National Geographic </i>magazine. As usual, it contains a wonderful series of photographic essays. One of the recent photographs shows the island of Manhattan with the World Trade Center's twin towers still intact. That is a current magazine but the towers have gone.</P>
      <P>I was listening to a car radio when I first heard of the attacks. At first, it seemed that a light plane had flown into the tower. I thought it was just an accident or that some idiot was clowning around, as happens frequently in New York. Not long ago, somebody tried to land in a parachute on the Statue of Liberty. Then an airliner flew into the tower, the building caught fire and it collapsed. It was almost unreal. Then the Pentagon was hit. At that stage, I began to realise that something very sinister was behind this.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>These were carefully selected targets and we would be very foolish to underestimate the acute intelligence of Mr. bin Laden, if he is the person behind the attacks, or, if he is not, whoever is behind them. It is clear that the planning of this outrage was initiated before Ariel Sharon went <Col N="316" /> on his walkabout around the Temple Mount, which I strongly condemn. That cannot be seen as the principal incendiary factor. The attackers were able to get inside the security network of American domestic airlines, which have been rightly criticised for their laxity in this area. They landed the planes at precisely those points in the building where it would lead to collapse. The ultimate cynicism came with the manipulation of the stock market by the terrorists in advance of the attacks so that they could not only create carnage but reap an unholy reward from it. That is extraordinarily cynical although it has not yet been clearly proved. If it is true, it shows a depth of human cynicism but also a remarkable logistical intelligence that should not be underestimated.</P>
    <P>It is clear that both sides are attempting to manipulate information and to create facts. By hitting back savagely and inflicting large-scale civilian casualties, the west would be playing into the hands of bin Laden. I regret the United States did not find it possible to sign up to the International Criminal Court in advance of the attacks. If it had done so, the court would be precisely the arena in which somebody like bin Laden should be tried. It is more satisfactory to have an impartial judicial process deciding on the guilt or innocence of a suspect, and whatever one's suspicions, bin Laden is as yet innocent. Nothing has been proved against him. The excuse for not providing evidence of his guilt is that the information is sensitive in security terms. It may be, but to get a conviction this evidence must be produced. We must be suspicious because of the news management by both sides.</P>
    <P>Looking back to the situation in the former Yugoslavia, we were rightly horrified by tales of mass rape, of rape being used as a political instrument and of camps being set up by the Serbs, who committed terrible atrocities, for this purpose. It was not true. These tales have been exposed as false. One of the young women who claimed in a tearful interview to have been raped was the daughter of a diplomatic family in New York and she was not near the place at the time. That is black propaganda. Its existence concerns me in terms of the news that has come out today that the only commercial satellite taking high-definition photographs which could clearly show the effect of the war on the ground &ndash; the pictures are clear enough to show bodies &ndash; has been bought by the Pentagon. That did not happen the day the war was declared. It happened the day after the UN mine-clearing mission was hit. That suggests that this action is not a strategic necessity for the Americans but part of news management so that we will not see civilian casualties. That is very worrying and I say that not as an anti-American but as one in favour of truth, honesty and clarity.</P>
    <P>I listened to American people interviewed on radio over recent weeks. Some were remarkable in the clarity of their understanding of the situation. They showed little of the spirit of vengeance. However, there were also some totally closed <Col N="317" /> minds. I remember a male Republican supporter especially. He belly-ached about what he called the anti-American attitudes of the pseudo-intellectuals of <i>The Irish Times.</i> However, he did not give a single instance of their lack of understanding or of the falsity of their statements. He simply labelled them pseudo-intellectuals, grouped them with<i> The Irish Times</i> and then dismissed them. That is not answering an argument.</P>
    <P>Regrettably and tragically, there is an argument that says that the West, or America and New York, had it coming to them. How could they? What had the civilians in those office buildings done to deserve the awful fate they met? There is no question in my mind that American foreign policy over the last 20 or 30 years has been a contributing factor. President Bush said that America was attacked because it was the greatest beacon of democracy and hope in the world but I do not completely assent to this.</P>
    <P>Let us look back at America's record and its foreign policy and take a few instances from it. The subversion by military coup in Chile in which the CIA were heavily involved because of the commercial interests of the United States got rid of the democratically elected government of President Allende. In Nicaragua, a democracy which was conducting the most important political experiment ever to find a third way between capitalism and communism was destroyed by external intervention heavily sponsored both militarily and financially by the United States of America.</P>
    <P>Then there was the Vietnam war and the involvement of Henry Kissinger, somebody who in my opinion is waiting for another arrest warrant. Not only did they intervene in the most savage way but they also carpet bombed Kampuchea which was not even involved because they thought there were supply routes going through it. Is that not terrorism? </P>
    <P>If there is one constructive contribution I can make to this debate it would be to suggest that it is important for us to look at the definition of terrorism in legal terms. I am not surprised but I am sorry that the international community is experiencing such difficulty and I know the reason is that virtually every single government is afraid that if they produce a realistic definition of terrorism then some of their own agencies may be implicated. Nevertheless I suggest the following as a definition of terrorism. Terrorism exists when an individual or state employs violence, especially against civilian targets, with the intention of influencing public policy by the inspiration of terror. That seems to me to be quite clearcut and logical but I imagine that there might be difficulties in these areas because, as Senator Lydon suggests, we had the Dublin and Monaghan bombings and where was the finger that pulled that trigger, to mix a metaphor?</P>
    <P>When looking at the issue of human rights one can be cynical. Several Senators asked why we did not intervene positively in Afghanistan before. The west had intervened before. The British attempted it in the 19th century, then the Rus<Col N="318" /> sians and Americans fought out a proxy war there. They were not invited in, it just happened to suit the Soviet Union and the United States of America to fight in somebody else's backyard. They trained the Taliban and Osama bin Laden and walked away from it leaving the unfortunate population of Afghanistan to be ruled by tyrants and despots.</P>
    <P>Senator Lydon asked, in an echo of Shakespeare, if they have funny clothes and long beards, do they not bleed? Like Shylock, do they not laugh? The answer to that is that they do not. Astonishingly that is one of the criminal offences that the police for the suppression of vice and the promotion of virtue look out for. To laugh is an offence. Why did we not go there when, in recent years, we heard of the appalling treatment of women, if we were interested in human rights? Women were dragged out of cancer wards because of the fear that a male doctor might get a glimpse of a naked ankle. Why did we not protest about that? We have known there has been a 90% crop failure in Afghanistan for the last three years. Silence. Suddenly we want to do something. Believe you me, when the history is written in 15, 20 or 30 years time one will find a little whiff of oil in the background. Very close to Afghanistan are the largest oil reserves in the world and it will probably have to be piped through there because it is the shortest and safest route. That is one of the reasons we are intervening at this point. We need to clean up our act and look at the real humanitarian issues.</P>
    <P>After all this hell that we created in Afghanistan the people fled. Of course they did, they are human beings as Senator Lydon said. What happened when they tried to escape? They got onto wretched little boats in the Indian Ocean and desperately tried to make for Australia where they thought there might be western values of liberty, freedom and dignity. The Australian Government to their unending shame sought to deny them the right to land and a proper hearing in their court.</P>
    <P>I do not exonerate Ireland either. Look at what we have been doing. We have tacitly gone along with all kinds of GATT agreements and international economic treaties which substantially disadvantage the southern hemisphere and the poorest people on our planet. To give one example of this, I read with interest about a year ago of a man in the west of Ireland who built a super trawler which cost a couple of million pounds which is not allowed to fish in European Union waters because of the damage it would do. It hoovers everything up indiscriminately and anything it does not want is just thrown over the side. Where is it fishing? Off the coast of west Africa where local tribes people have been put off their traditional fishing areas. They have been bankrupted and turned into refugees by the operation of trawlers like this and when they come here we slam the door in their faces on the grounds that they are economic migrants.</P>
    <P>This situation of terror which I deplore will <Col N="319" /> never be resolved until we achieve a more just world and we are prepared to share the good things in this life a little bit more equally and live up to the credo that we so often proclaim of Christianity and morality and justice for all. If we had more justice there would be less terrorism.</P>
    <P>I do not believe that the war on terrorism will get anywhere. We had a war on want but there is still plenty of want around. We had a war on drugs but drug taking has increased. We had a war on crime and nobody is too happy with that. Certainly the one thing that these grand wars have in common is that they never achieve their targeted result. By going in there, particularly in view of the lack of information, one is going to exacerbate the situation.</P>
    <P>Look at what is happening in Pakistan, for example, where the people perceive it as being anti-Muslim. The cosmetic attempts by the West to reassure the Islamic world and to pretend to humanitarianism would be laughable if it was not such a tragedy. Syria is now on the Security Council, that great protector of human rights. It is a hotbed where terrorism, torture and all the rest of it is fostered. Saudi Arabia is one of the allies. Where did all this originate? It is not an accident that Osama bin Laden is a principal focus. He is a Saudi Arabian and much money came from there. The state religion of Saudi Arabia is not too far removed from Osama bin Laden's attitude. It just happens to suit us because of the oil to keep the current regime in Saudi Arabia in power. It is in our interest but it is perhaps not in the interests of the ordinary people there. One could really be cynical about it.</P>
    <P>The various governments are not behind hand in being cynical either. They are using this and there is a real danger, which I hope this House will guard against, that this crisis will be used to force through an already pre-existing agenda of clipping away at human rights in legislative terms, such as removing the right to silence and so on. They are all on the cards now and things that were difficult to get through before suddenly find an opportune moment. It behoves both Houses of the Oireachtas to make sure that we clearly examine any legislation which is proposed along these lines.</P>
    <P>Today we had the sad news of the murder of the Israeli Cabinet Minister, Mr. Ze'evi, but that again is sadly instructive. President Arafat instantly condemned it and issued orders for the arrest of the perpetrators, yet Mr. Sharon holds him personally responsible. It seems that whatever Mr. Arafat does he is going to be made responsible. It makes me wonder whether Mr. Sharon was responsible for the actions of the settlers. Is the Government of Israel responsible for the murder of Yitzhak Rabin? It is the same argument and we have to have what they laughingly call a level playing field in this area.</P>
    <P>I would like to look at a few of the issues raised in the Minister's speech. She spoke about the need to dismantle terrorist camps in the area <Col N="320" /> under the control of the Taliban. I agree. What about the principal one in the United States of America, the camp of the Americas, which was established, partly at least, with the intention and certainly with the effect of training some of the death squads used against the civilian population in South America? Let us have a closure of that. I honour the Roman Catholic priest who every year protests outside and is put in jail for his trouble, as I honour the Irish priest who ministered to the firemen and was shown on television just going in to show solidarity when the building collapsed on top of him. I heard on a chat programme on RTE radio that he was an openly gay priest in New York. We have to take into account the human complexity. As all my colleagues have said, it was not just clean-cut all-American kids who were killed. The World Trade Centre was involved, not the American trade centre. As has been pointed out, Muslim people, gay people, women, Pakistanis, so many nations were savagely affected by this atrocity.</P>
    <P>I notice that the Minister of State is here in lonely state without advisers and there appears to be no media so, perhaps, we are simply talking into cotton wool. It seems it would be right in this debate to question the use of Irish airspace for these raids, especially since we are unsure of the effect of these military operations and particularly since we hear so much about smart bombs. Then we discover that the UN mine-clearing operation and the International Red Cross have been hit and they have protested strongly to the United Nations and the US. We do not really know what the effect is. It appeared we had given the Americans a blank cheque, but I do not think we should do that. We need to know more about the end product of these military operations in terms of civilian casualties.</P>
    <P>On that matter I honour the journalists. Sometimes it seems a little frivolous when someone tries to get into a country dressed in disguise and so on, but I listened to John Simpson, a very fine reporter, and I realised that it must take great courage to get in there and expose oneself to such real and terrible dangers.</P>
    <P>I would like in my final remarks to make three points. In talking about the resolution in areas such as financing terrorism and denying safe haven to terrorists, let us have Switzerland at the Bar here. Let us hear it account for the enormous amounts of money secreted away by dictators and torturers. Let us look at, perhaps, having a UN protectorate declared in Afghanistan because the Northern Alliance is no great shakes. It is up to its ears in drugs, rape and torture. Why replace a regime with one that could be even worse?</P>
    <P>There are other things I could say but I bow to the Chair's indication that my time is up. I wish to return to the one point I made that I think might be of value to the discussion, that is that our civil servants, particularly now that we have the Presidency of the United Nations Security Council, should look at the question of a definition of &ldquo;terrorism&rdquo;. I offer the one I gave to this <Col N="321" /> House. It is clear and simple and covers the points. The only reason I can imagine there are difficulties with any such definition is that the smoking gun might point back at the hand that wrote that definition.</P>
    <Speaker pid="LabhrasOMurchu" hpid="Labhrás Ó Murchú Labhrás Ó Murchú">
      <NameTxt>Labhrás Ó Murchú</NameTxt>
      <P>I expect the purpose of today's debate is to express our sympathy and solidarity with the people of the United States following the terrible events of 11 September and to make a helpful contribution, small though it may be, and point to a resolution of the present difficulties while at the same time reflect the views of the ordinary man and woman in the street who often become irrelevant and voiceless in this arena, which has now become a war arena.</P>
      <P>The date 11 September will forever remain etched on our minds and hearts. The memory will be with us for the rest of our lives, perhaps, because we saw the dramatic pictures on television but more so because of the close ties which exist, and have always existed, between Ireland and the United States.</P>
      <P>Speaking at a function in the Mansion House some months ago, long before this terrible event happened, I stated that Ireland and America are sister nations. I do not think I overstated the case. The debate was in the context of whether we are more American than European, not that it really matters because all these issues in their own right are organic. I do not think one will ever remove from the folk memory what America has meant to Ireland during our darkest days. It was an open society and by and large it welcomed the huge exodus of people who departed this land from famine times onwards. Up to the present day we sense that the Irish are a privileged people where America is concerned. Often legislation is enacted to be helpful to the Irish when, perhaps, certain difficulties are placed in the way of other nationalities entering the United States. At the same time many of our people have inter-married with Americans. For that reason the American people have been coming to Ireland for decades. They were welcome and we treated them as close friends, as we should have done, and at the same time they seem to have a particular grá for the Irish people. That is very much part of our folk memory and our folklore, and nothing will change that.</P>
      <P>When this terrible event took place on 11 September we expected that at the heart of the tragedy would be Ireland and the Irish people. In the whole rescue operation the firemen and the police had a strong Irish representation. In the intervening weeks I have learned that people with whom I was friendly had children in the fire fighting services at that time. A daughter of a good friend of mine was in the Pentagon at the time the plane struck but luckily she was not injured. It is clear that we are inextricably bound together as two nations. That will underline all our actions, concerns and emotions about 11 September.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>We hope it will be possible, difficult as it may be, for the American people to come to terms <Col N="322" /> with the lingering trauma which will be there for this and future generations. That trauma can have a devastating effect on the morale of people. It will have a devastating effect on those who are bereaved and those who have suffered. It is difficult to find words of consolation. All people, civic and religious, have endeavoured to console those who are suffering, but for future generations that suffering will continue. I can understand why the American people would want retribution &ndash; that is a word I do not particularly like and I certainly do not like the word &ldquo;revenge&rdquo;. The word &ldquo;revenge&rdquo; may not have been used, but certainly retribution is on people's minds. Over the centuries we have discovered that where people seek retribution for retribution's sake, no matter how much they have suffered, it makes absolutely no contribution whatsoever to providing them with consolation, nor does it in any way provide them with protection in the future.</P>
    <P>If, on the other hand, the American people, through their administration, wish to protect themselves in the future, I do not think any sensible person could deny them that right. We in this country have often found it difficult, even though it was a matter of right is might where we were concerned and at the same time we were the vulnerable people, but we always felt we had a moral right to defend ourselves. Every nation has that right. It is very difficult for a small nation to counsel a bigger nation as to the manner in which it should pursue that protection and ensure its security in the future. In many ways the reason what happened on 11 September has taken people by surprise is that a power like America was so vulnerable, a power that perhaps everyone thought of as being impregnable when it came to defences. This has shocked American society to the very core and the reverberations are being felt throughout the civilised world. This, together with the concern for the terrible tragedy, can be a motivating factor while at the same time it can be exceptionally dangerous.</P>
    <P>We have all listened to the many debates and discussions about the war against Afghanistan. We were given to understand that it would be directed solely towards military installations. However, we know from previous wars that in spite of advanced technology in military weapons it is not possible to ensure civilian lives will not be endangered. If that is so, one must look at the morality of the extent to which one can endanger civilian lives. I do not think it is a matter of quantity where that morality is concerned, it is a matter of quality. If one accepts that one can endanger civilian lives, one must also accept that whether 5,000, 10,000 or 500,000 lives are endangered, one is accepting civilians can be put at risk &ldquo;for the greater good&rdquo;. This requires analysis and the debate which is currently taking place is very often misinterpreted and misrepresented.</P>
    <P>I spoke recently to two young Irish-Americans who were home from Connecticut. I knew these people before they travelled to America and I <Col N="323" /> have since met them there on many occasions. When I met them at a funeral they said to me in whispered tones that they were shocked at the amount of anti-American sentiment they had discerned in Ireland during their recent visit. I think their shock came from the fact that perhaps they did not notice that sentiment in the past but they certainly noticed it this time in a very concentrated manner. I tried to give them a balanced response because, on the one hand, it is true and, on the other, it is not true. I said to them that when one endeavours to measure that anti-American sentiment, it would be wrong to measure it only by what one sees and hears in the media; one must also listen to the ordinary people. I was anxious to know if they had observed anti-American sentiment to the same extent among the ordinary people and they admitted they had not. I then said that perhaps they mistook what they heard as anti-American sentiment, that it may really have been an effort by a neutral country to provide a helpful analysis and that if something is said that does not fit strictly within the accepted guidelines of the American Administration they should not regard it as anti-American sentiment. It behoves a neutral nation, in fact it behoves all nations, in this debate to ensure we do not allow the heat of the moment to dull our sensitivities, the manner in which we judge things or dull our humanity to think the only immediate prospect is to bomb another country. That in itself is not anti-American sentiment and I expect as time passes that the American people will be pleased we engaged in such analysis.</P>
    <P>There is a grave danger in the context of the atmosphere which has followed from 11 September that terrible deeds can be done. I am thinking of what can happen in such an atmosphere, that is, that good men and good women may not express their views, which would be wrong, and that the media which are largely controlled by a monopoly, which in itself is tied to profit and is very often tied to a particular administration, in an international sense as distinct from the Irish media, may not make the normal ethical judgments which are expected from the media. I would go a step further by saying that some of the people who have stepped out of line, in particular Robert Fisk who has front line and at the coalface experience and simply used his standing as a journalist and the outlets he had to create a balanced approach, have been demonised in a very empty and cruel manner. That is wrong because, having read what Robert Fisk said, he certainly was not justifying terrorism. He sympathised with the terrible trauma and tragedy of the American people, yet he was demonised. Lesser men and lesser women may withdraw from the pitch when that type of criticism is directed towards them. For the good of the world it is important that we do not allow that to happen.</P>
    <P>Currently there are certain inherent dangers which may in time be a serious threat to world order. Every time one engenders hate and every <Col N="324" /> time one creates a further extension of a cause, that, in turn, will produce more foot soldiers down the road. We may have a much bigger problem removed from one particular country and directed at another &ndash; in fact, it may be what some people have predicted as a clash of civilisations. I do not think the PR section of the American Administration has succeeded in alleviating the fears of Muslims that this is not directed against them &ndash; I accept it is not. I do not think the Americans have alleviated Muslims' fears by the bizarre efforts of dropping minute proportions of food to the people in Afghanistan. While watching television last night I saw two or three people picking up the little yellow bags like mushrooms, taking them away and selling them. This was in no way confronting the terrible humanitarian problem which exists on the ground. It is a bizarre effort. It worries me that this is being done in tandem with the bombing campaign.</P>
    <P>Anyone who counsels caution at a time like this could easily ask what is the alternative. It is not easy to come up with answers. It is not easy to diminish the rage the American people feel nor to assuage their fears at this time. However, the danger and damage done by the approach which is being taken at present, which is largely war focused, could be much greater than what took place on 11 September. We must bear in mind that the American Administration has gone into many countries and financed irregular groups, the Taliban being one of them. It helped to put them in place in their battle against the Soviet Union. The suggestion now is that they be removed and a new administration put in their place. One can consider Chile among other countries where a similar situation happened. Fire-brigade type political action by external governments will not put an administration in place that will deliver the type of assurances regarding security that they rightly expect. This can not and will not happen. It certainly will not happen in Afghanistan where there are disparate groups of people with different traditions and religious emphases.</P>
    <P>In finding a solution, it behoves us to think of long-term solutions. For example, in Africa, millions of people are threatened by the AIDS epidemic &ndash; children, men and women. We have the medicines available to help them but the companies that own the patent rights to those medicines will not allow them to be produced at low cost so they can be made more widely available. Beef mountains and milk lakes developed while people starved. It is possible for America to deliver to Pakistan what television reports described as their reward of £500 million. It is grotesque to consider that they are being rewarded to participate in this conflict, when that same money &ndash; the billions of pounds that have been directed towards military aggression &ndash; could have been directed towards aid. This would have shown these poorer nations that the West is not just about domination and exploitation of their oil or <Col N="325" /> about helping only when our own military standing is at stake. There are much bigger issues. The humanitarian issue could have been resolved and bin Laden and his ilk would not have had the opportunity to attract supporters to his cause and provoke them to commit the atrocities that we have seen.</P>
    <P>Ireland has a particular contribution to make. The Government has been cautious and the Taoiseach said in the Dáil that the help being offered was not without condition. It is possible for Ireland to be an honest broker. In spite of the concern we all have for our American colleagues and in spite of our condemnation of the terrorism we saw in the United States, we would make a better contribution to America and to world order if we removed some of the circumstances that provoked the action that we have witnessed.</P>
    <P>I commend the Irish media for the contribution they have made to balanced coverage. We must protect the status that Ireland enjoys throughout the world. There will be a greater regard for us if we do not allow ourselves to be sucked into a situation where we are not making that contribution.</P>
    <P>Some of the language used by US spokespersons is unhelpful, such as references to bringing in people dead or alive, smoking guns and collateral damage. That language does not help, in spite of the justice of their cause. I am worried about the role that is being played by Mr. Blair in Britain. As I see him travelling throughout the world, I ask if his role is that of Prime Minister of an independent state or a puppet of America. Whatever the answer is, commentators in Britain and many of the MPs are asking the same question. This is not in criticism of Mr. Blair. I have great regard for him. He is an exceptionally fine statesman and many of us have looked up to him as a man who broke the mould. I would not like to see him lose his standing or having damaged his image when the smoke and the dust have cleared. I say the same about Ireland. We must be careful of our status, image and our neutral and independent role.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MaryHenry" hpid="Dr. Henry Dr. Henry">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Henry</NameTxt>
      <P>I am delighted with Senator Ó Murchú's assertion that our close association with America means we have to urge caution when we feel it is necessary. From the beginning, I felt that the Taoiseach did not offer support unconditionally. It is because of our long friendship and association with the USA that we act as an honest broker wherever possible.</P>
      <P>This is the third time I have addressed the House on the issue of biological weapons but it is an appropriate time to raise it again. I have also asked the Joint Committee on Foreign Affairs to bring it to the attention of the President of the Security Council, our own Foreign Minister, when they visit the UN next month.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>In 1972 a biological weapons and toxins convention was brought forward by the UN to try to prevent the proliferation and use of such grotesque weapons of mass destruction. We were <Col N="326" /> one of the early signatories and by 1975 sufficient nations had signed that the convention was ratified. Unfortunately, there was no verification protocol inserted in the original convention, so there was no method of inspecting various countries to see if they were living up to their obligations.</P>
    <P>In 1994 it was decided by a group of countries, including Ireland in a very prominent position, to try to bring forward a protocol which would insert a verification process into the 1972 weapons convention. Progress on this had been going well over the last six years and it was hoped there would be agreement for the fifth review of the convention which is to take place next month. Unfortunately, on 25 July, the US pulled out of the convention saying it was not in its interest to have this verification protocol brought forward. Since unanimity was required, there has been disarray among the countries who were in favour of the protocol.</P>
    <P>It is extraordinary that the first country to have biological weapons used against it is the United States of America. Anthrax is one of the most important of these weapons and ironically, the country that is suffering from the results of the absence of a protocol is the USA. I suggest that, as good friends of America, we should urge it to come back immediately into the <i>ad hoc</i> group which is trying to put forward this protocol next month. It is not too late. Various countries had minor objections to the protocol but the US was the only one that pulled out, leaving it in disarray.</P>
    <P>I was remarkably distressed by the contribution of Ambassador Mahley in Geneva when he spoke of the reasons America was pulling out of the convention. One of them was that it was going to research better methods of the prevention of these diseases being lethal within a nation. This is all very well for a developed country like the USA but how can it be applied to the undeveloped world? We spent years vaccinating against smallpox and finally eradicated it. It could be one of the most potent weapons of mass destruction if once again it came upon the scene.</P>
    <P>Since the Gulf War the UN, and Americans in particular, have been complaining about Iraq's tardiness in allowing inspections of its weapons dumps. Since 1998 there have not been any inspections, as it was found that they were useless. What about inspections in other countries? I was rather depressed to see the chief weapons inspector at the UN, Richard Butler, suggest last night on television that the anthrax bacteria could have come from Iraq or from some state of the former Soviet Union. All these countries have plenty of biological weapons &ndash; Iraq's, unfortunately, supplied by the USA when they were good friends &ndash; but could it not have been home-grown? Anthrax is in numerous laboratories within the USA and these laboratories are not inspected. It is said that pharmaceutical and biotechnological companies put great pressure on the Bush Administration to prevent this protocol <Col N="327" /> coming into force and unfortunately that is all too likely.</P>
    <P>It will be possible, with time, to decide where these strains of anthrax have come from. Most of the letters concerned have been posted within the USA. It has been suggested that the strain in question was present in the USA in the 1950s. It could have been given to another country in the interim, but the enemy within can often be much more difficult to deal with than the enemy without. Most European countries have a tight regime regarding the inspection of laboratories. I congratulate our own Academy of Medical Laboratory Science, which periodically runs an article in its professional magazine asking the reader what is in the back of the fridge. It is useful for everyone to check on everyone else. This view should be promoted and accepted worldwide.</P>
    <P>We need to ensure that those countries with biological weapons have the resources to get rid of them. This will require finance from the UN. I spoke at a medical lecture in Rostov-on-Don during the summer. There were fears expressed that underpaid state employees there were open to bribery. If money is needed to help the countries of the former Soviet Union to get rid of their weapons, it should be made available. Because of our position on the UN Security Council, Ireland should try to do something about this.</P>
    <P>The USA has lists of biological weapons, from Korean haemorrhagic fever to yellow fever, Rocky mountain spotted fever, bubonic plague, anthrax and smallpox along with diseases affecting animals and plants. The USA used biological weapons, for example Agent Orange, in the Vietnam war and it is now using them in Bolivia and Columbia in an attempt to eradicate the coca plant. Ireland could make a great effort in this area.</P>
    <P>The humanitarian problems in Afghanistan appear dire. In less than four weeks the first snows are expected which, according to those who know the terrain, will make the movement of large quantities of humanitarian aid very difficult. The situation is urgent. Does the bombing need to go on? It is said that all important military targets have been destroyed. With the amount of bombing that has occurred I am amazed that civilian casualty figures are so small, especially taking into account the use of cluster bombs, which have an effect similar to landmines.</P>
    <P>Like Senator Ó Murchú and others, I was fascinated by the idea of dropping packages of aid at the same time as the bombs. When I was a child, we used to study the famine of the 1840s in school. One of the criticisms of the aid sent by Great Britain was that we were incapable of cooking Indian meal and did not think much of eating it. The contents of the yellow packets dropped include the makings of a peanut butter and jelly sandwich, which is bizarre. I am sure they are very popular in New Jersey and Wisconsin, but I do not know if they eat them in downtown Kabul. It is sad that a great country like the <Col N="328" /> USA thinks this is a suitable form of humanitarian aid. The lack of insight is pathetic. It is also dangerous. Long before this bombing, 25 people per day were being killed and maimed due to landmines left over from wars in Afghanistan. I can understand the rage of humanitarian organisations who see this ridiculous effort while they lack safe passage for their trucks to bring food that is urgently needed. Iran has had refugees for more than a decade and now has more than a million refugees from Afghanistan to deal with. Support for Iran and Pakistan would be useful.</P>
    <P>The atrocity of 11 September has resulted in strange bedfellows. Those who were enemies yesterday are friends today &ndash; the payment of a few shekels seems to get people on to one's side rapidly. That is life, but it is interesting that people talk about an atrocity against the civilised world. When we were running around in goatskins, that part of the world was the civilised world. Life has ups and downs and Afghanistan is on a down swing at the moment. Considering its economic state, with statistics such as maternal and infant mortality figures among the worst in the world, is bombing necessary to subdue this nation?</P>
    <P>I spoke at a meeting of the Philosophical Society at Trinity College last week and one of the other speakers, the British Labour Party MP, George Galloway, was critical of the bombing. He said that for many years the Irish would not extradite people for political crimes. The Taliban are being asked to extradite bin Laden for what they would term a political crime. Americans may know he is in Afghanistan, but how would we have felt if the British had suddenly decided to bomb Dundalk or north or south Dublin if they knew that people liable for IRA crimes were here and they wanted us to extradite them? We would have been pretty aggrieved.</P>
    <P>The Taliban leaders also ask for evidence. Why should they be any different from us? This is especially true since the Taliban is now apparently being recognised as the government. However, until early September it was not recognised. It is very hard on the people of Afghanistan, because they are being asked to replace one appalling regime with another lot, which seems to be pretty bad too.</P>
    <P>Owing to the dreadful lack of medical care in Afghanistan, the Pakistanis are allowing seriously injured people to cross the border. However, a very large number of people are getting no medical care. This has been the case for some time. The Taliban refused education to women so that women and children have been getting virtually no health care.</P>
    <P>We are friends of the Americans and it is important to point out that we have criticisms of what they are doing. Sometimes that may put a little frisson in the friendship but that does not matter. If we keep our mouths shut, we will do them a disservice in the long run. The Taoiseach's statement that our support is not unqualified is a much wiser path to take than the attitude some people in America believe we should have, which <Col N="329" /> would not be correct from a moral and ultimately from a social point of view.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PaschalMooney" hpid="Mr. Mooney Mr. Mooney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Mooney</NameTxt>
      <P>I welcome the initiative by the Leader and agreed by the House to have this debate now. I also welcome the Minister of State, Deputy Dan Wallace.</P>
      <P>Like the other contributors and most recently my colleague, Senator Henry, I too am very pro-American for a variety of cultural and historical reasons. However, I also firmly believe we cannot allow a superpower &ndash; now the only superpower &ndash; to react militarily without some qualification for the support of countries like Ireland. We have a unique role to play. It is evident that we are punching way above our weight internationally, given our size.</P>
      <P>As I said at a meeting of the Committee on Foreign Affairs recently, the fact that we hold the chair of the Security Council is significant, but of greater significance is the 130 votes we received in getting elected. Since we are chairing the Security Council during this critical and momentous month, our influence is enormous.</P>
      <P>I know, from my experience of meeting representatives from various Arab countries, that because of our non-aligned status and because we have no colonial baggage, Ireland is seen as a beacon and a country that will stand up against human rights abuses and for those who, like us, have suffered under the yolk of colonialism and imperialism as many Middle Eastern countries did throughout history. There is a great weight of expectation from those countries. They look to Ireland in its pivotal role to be a moderately influencing factor in what is going on in Afghanistan.</P>
      <P>I echo the comments made on all sides of the House that the Americans should continue to show restraint in so far as it is possible when embarking on military action. I am very concerned about the change in modalities of the military hardware over the last week. We have gone from what we are told is precise cruise missile targeting of Taliban assets to the use of cluster bombs, really a series of mini bombs, which on hitting the ground scatter in all directions and then explode. This is happening in the second most mined country in the world after Angola.</P>
      <P>On television we see the evidence of injured boys and girls. Last week one of the news programmes showed a very poignant scene of a young girl who had lost her foot. In the culture of that country she is now effectively an outcast with very little to look forward to in the future. That is the scale of the humanitarian disaster that has befallen the people of Afghanistan. Added to that is now this ongoing war to flush out bin Laden and the al-Qaeda terrorist network.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>At a recent meeting of the Committee on Foreign Affairs, I asked a question of the Minister of State, Deputy O'Donnell, which I knew she would be unable to answer. However it is a question which should be repeatedly posed. Do the Americans have a plan B? Is this just about drop<Col N="330" /> ping cluster bombs to take out the Taliban regime and ultimately the bin Laden network, while using the same planes to drop peanut butter and jello, which is happening indiscriminately as there is no monitoring on the ground? This needs to be addressed quickly by America and Britain, the main protagonists in the war or attrition against bin Laden and the Taliban.</P>
    <P>The media do not have access to what is happening on the ground in Afghanistan. In the initial stages of the bombing campaign last week, the base offices of the various media organisations in London, New York and elsewhere had to telephone their representatives on the border in Pakistan to inform them they had picked up pictures of the first wave of bombing in Kabul from the al-Jazeera satellite transmitting from Oman. The correspondents on the ground had no knowledge of this and this is still the case. Consequently, we, the general public, have no knowledge of what is happening there.</P>
    <P>There is a military campaign that we conditionally support against a regime that is clearly using a satellite television station with access to Afghanistan for propaganda purposes as much as for truth and we have a media presence on the Afghan border unable to verify any of the statements emanating from either the allies or the Taliban. Consequently we must rely on anecdotal evidence from people in hospitals or refugee camps as they pour out of Afghanistan.</P>
    <P>Philip Knightly is a distinguished journalist who wrote a book that should be read by all those with an interest in how war is waged. The title is self-explanatory: <i>The First Casualty.</i> This comes from the saying: &ldquo;When war is declared, truth is the first casualty.&rdquo;  Throughout history, people have manipulated truth to their own ends and as there is increasing concern across the world, particularly among the allies and in countries like Ireland at the continuance of the bombing campaign, there will inevitably be some slippage in standards and the best possible spin will be put on stories coming from Afghanistan.</P>
    <P>I mention this because I come from a media background and it pales in significance when compared with the humanitarian disaster that has befallen the people of Afghanistan, referred to by the Minister, Deputy O'Donnell. I was impressed by her constant and repeated references to the critical role of the United Nations. This should be a very reassuring statement to those outside this House and perhaps some within it who assume that Ireland has in some way diluted its neutrality or shifted away from the basic tenet of its foreign policy that any overseas adventures should be UN mandated. Ireland remains very firmly within the school of thought that the United Nations is paramount in decision-making relating to any engagement in military activity, and certainly as it applies to Ireland.</P>
    <P>The Minister of State outlined initially that she recognises the right of any nation, under Article 51 of the UN Charter, to individual and collective self-defence. Nobody can argue with that. I can<Col N="331" /> not nor would I wish to argue with the Americans' righteous anger at what happened on, as they refer to it, 9.11, and on the need to respond. Like many others, however, I was taken aback by the moderating tone of the Administration statements in the immediate aftermath of 9.11 and that they did not go for the jugular. They were restrained, measured and reflective in regard to the decision it would take. Now that it has made the decision to engage in military activity, as the world's only super power and with the recognition by the US President and his Administration that America is now part of that family of nations that has experienced terrorist attacks, there is a moral as much as a practical obligation on the United States to remember that in any action it takes in any other part of the world outside its borders, there are other countries in the family of nations which have as great a concern about the progress of international terrorism because it affects all of us, directly or indirectly.</P>
    <P>American foreign policy has been changed dramatically as a result of 9.11, and one of the most positive manifestations of that is the public acknowledgement in the past few weeks by the US President, a Republican President, that Palestine has the right to self-determination and to nationhood. That change was so significant that it prompted Prime Minister Sharon to go back in history and parallel the current state of history with the state of Czechoslovakia in 1938. With all due respects to Mr. Sharon and his historical advisers, I would not agree that there is any parallel between the position of Israel today and the position of the poor people of Czechoslovakia in 1938, and its Administration who were literally thrown to the dogs of Nazism and whose country was broken up as a result.</P>
    <P>The Minister of State referred to the fact that there is now a momentum in relation to the Middle East, and specifically to Palestine, that did not exist previously. There is now an urgency about attempting to address the real inequities in the relationship between Israel and Palestine that did not exist previously. There is now a belated but genuine acknowledgement by leaders from George W. Bush to Tony Blair, who are leading the allied campaign, that the Palestine issue has to be settled fairly and justly. I would say to my Israeli friends that if the United States has, since the creation of the state of Israel, acted as a guarantor of their right to exist, the right to their own safe borders and to defend themselves from any attack that would be made on them, surely they should also recognise, at this momentous time in our history, that Palestine could be given the same rights and also would have imposed upon it the same obligations to live in peace with its neighbour fairly and justly. If that opportunity is not grasped, it may pass.</P>
    <P>I agree fully with what the Minister of State outlined on the priorities Ireland has indicated at the Security Council. I would hope that in our capacity as Chair of the Security Council we <Col N="332" /> would use whatever influence we have to impress upon the Americans the need to have an orderly and effective distribution of food and in that context where better to look than at the NGOs, of which those of us in Ireland are so proud. They were in Afghanistan when it was not popular to be there. They were also in other trouble spots which had gone off the front pages of the national newspapers and our television screens. Irish NGOs were in Afghanistan during the past ten years when the world left that country to its own devices following the Soviet withdrawal. Ireland is currently putting its money where its mouth is in that an impressive sum of money is being allocated for humanitarian aid. Politically and internationally, we are setting a standard for other countries of our size and prosperity that they too should dig deep and ensure there are sufficient resources available to address what is a very real humanitarian problem.</P>
    <P>I hope that in our discussions at Security Council level, where it is obvious that we have enormous influence, we can impress upon our American cousins that there is a need for a plan B and that it is not enough to talk about bombing on the one hand and dropping peanut butter and jello on the other. There has to be a coherent and effective food distribution programme, and they could use the expertise of Irish NGOs who have been calling for that repeatedly over the past few weeks. If that happens, and if there is some indication from the Americans in the next week or two weeks before the harsh winter sets in, that they are prepared to work in consultation and partnership with those who have the expertise to deliver food on the ground effectively to the people of Afghanistan, we will have done a good day's work.</P>
    <Speaker pid="DenisDinoCregan" hpid="Mr. D. Cregan Mr. D. Cregan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. D. Cregan</NameTxt>
      <P>I wish to share my time with Senator Quinn.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BrianMullooly" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>That is agreed.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DenisDinoCregan" hpid="Mr. D. Cregan Mr. D. Cregan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. D. Cregan</NameTxt>
      <P>Like other speakers, I would be pro-USA. I found the events of 11 September very frightening and disturbing. I listened to Senator Mooney make the point that the United States did not act speedily after the atrocities. Discussions went on as to what should be done, and we waited to see if they would act at all.</P>
      <P>The discussion that is going on is broadening to include Afghanistan and the issue of refugees all over the world, particularly in that part of the world. The amount of money going towards that problem, particularly into Afghanistan from the United States, was not small, even before the tragedy of 11 September.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I find it disturbing that we are getting away from what happened on 11 September to discuss what is happening in Afghanistan, which is frightening, but we must also ask what has been done by the people of Afghanistan and the Taliban who now have authority in that country. Afghani<Col N="333" /> stan is the second most mined country in the world. Who laid those mines? The United States did not do that. The twin towers was not a military base. Who carried out that attack? I have not heard anybody in the debate ask about the pressure that should be imposed to make sure that international terrorism comes to an end. We all agree with that but nobody has said it yet. Nobody asked why we were not discussing that question.</P>
    <P>The coalition of nations who came to the aid of America after 11 September was very impressive and heartening. The Canadians, the French, the British and Ireland came forward, and why not? American society is very liberal. The structures in America created the environment in which the twin towers incident occurred because they allowed it to happen. The Israelis do not do that. In the past 30 years they made sure that they knew what could happen. Unfortunately I am not a genius in terms of speaking about the hunger of people but I can understand it. I do not want one life to be lost because I want people to live for their country, but I do not want anybody carrying out an atrocity like that on the twin towers again. We all have a responsibility in ensuring that does not happen.</P>
    <P>We currently hold the Chair of the Security Council, and the United Nations and NATO are saying that this terrorism must stop and we must give assistance in every way. We can talk about terrorism because we have experienced it in our own land. Whether we like it or not, people who are terrorists have walked free from our courts, and we must face up to that. It is coming close to us now and we are discovering that these people are very dangerous. More than 6,000 people were killed in the twin towers, which were over 800 feet in height and extended seven stories below ground. They will never be found. That should be borne in mind before turning to Afghanistan and its people.</P>
    <P>There has been laughter at the nature of the foodstuffs that have been dropped on Afghanistan. The food packaging is more expensive than the food itself. It is a sad reflection on the propaganda campaign.</P>
    <P>Senator Mooney correctly said that truth is the first casualty of war. Will those responsible for the atrocity of the twin towers tell the truth? Enormous sums of money are at their disposal in the Arab world. These are not being spent on the people with the result that there is widespread poverty. The situation in the western world cannot be compared with that.</P>
    <P>There is jealousy in the Arab world of the way the West has developed. Two thousand years ago roles were reversed. Egypt was then the richest country in the world. Why did this happen? Is it because wealth has been concentrated among the few?</P>
    <P>My concern is for the future. We have no right to believe we do not have a responsibility to face up to the threat of international terrorism. What happened on 11 September was frightening and <Col N="334" /> we have a responsibility to our children to make sure nothing like it happens again. We also have a responsibility to the children of Afghanistan, such as the child who lost his leg.</P>
    <P>We must not forget that approximately 80 countries lost people in the twin towers. The death toll could have been as high as 60,000 and as many as ten airplanes could have been involved. Over two million people commute to Manhattan every day.</P>
    <P>The world will never be the same again and, given its power, the US could create a totally different world order. It could close its Mexican and Canadian borders and become more isolationist. The rest of the world would suffer the consequences.</P>
    <P>Everybody has a responsibility in this situation. It is alarming for the Taliban to try to give the impression that the fault lies with everyone other than themselves. They allowed this situation to arise.</P>
    <P>The extreme wealth side by side with extreme poverty in some Arab countries is alarming. The blame for this should not be directed solely at the west. We must help in every way we can. It is something at which this county is good. The destruction on 11 September was frightening. It must be faced up to. Local and international terrorism must be grasped. We all have a responsibility in this regard.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MadeleineTaylorQuinn" hpid="Mrs. Taylor-Quinn Mrs. Taylor-Quinn">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Taylor-Quinn</NameTxt>
      <P>Unlike previous speakers I will not say whether I am pro-American or anti-American. We are part of the same world and regardless of whether our backgrounds are Christian, Islamic or Jewish, we are human beings with responsibilities to each other. We all sympathise with those caught up in that awful event on 11 September, which brought such calamity and destruction to many families across the United States. It was an appalling terrorist attack.</P>
      <P>It is important to examine the reasons behind these atrocities, even though it is very difficult to understand the minds of terrorists. The world is made up of governments of various kinds, be they democratic, dictatorships or whatever. Ultimately their overriding interests appear to be economic and these colour their actions and responses.</P>
      <P>Osama bin Laden appears to have been the chief organiser and perpetrator of this event. He comes from a specific tradition and is supported by the Taliban regime in Afghanistan. With the support of the Security Council, decisions have been taken on what needs to be done.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Previous speakers referred to the fallout of the action that has been taken. At the outset the US reacted carefully. It secured support among a coalition of nations, including practically all western governments, to outlaw terrorism. However, it has now proceeded with military action and, unfortunately, despite the best intentions innocent civilians have been killed. As recently as yesterday a Red Cross storehouse was bombed in Kabul. There is no excuse for such mistakes. We cannot afford them and, given the apparent high <Col N="335" /> precision of technology, including satellites, they are unacceptable. It is fine to make apologies but they are no good to those who have been unfairly killed or injured.</P>
    <P>Some of the poorest people in the world live in Afghanistan and they face famine and droughts. It is a nonsense to drop jello on these areas, especially when the people do not have drinking water. We must be realistic. Senator Henry referred to this aspect. It is a farce.</P>
    <P>Americans have built a great country, which has provided a haven for many Irish people &ndash; approximately 44 million Americans claim Irish descent. However, while American Governments might claim to be the main proponents of the human rights agenda, they promote economic before human interests. For example, it is apparent that the economic interests of oil in the southern states of America and in the Middle East usually take precedence.</P>
    <P>There can be duplicity and hypocrisy everywhere and American Governments pursue their business with a level of duplicity and inconsistency. There is a need for them to examine their policies and to develop a greater understanding of other traditions and culture. There is also a need for further talks.</P>
    <P>I was unable to attend the meeting of the Joint Committee on Foreign Affairs at which the Minister for Foreign Affairs, Deputy Cowen, was present. I commend the Minister on the fine manner in which he has acquitted himself on behalf of Ireland. He spoke on the day subsequent to the atrocities. He was in Palestine with President Arafat and the way he spoke there and the way he empathised was second to none. It was highly commendable and has done an extraordinarily fine job. He must be commended for the role he is playing and for the way he is acquitting himself during our Presidency of the UN Security Council. We are very proud of how he has flown the Irish flag.</P>
    <P>There is, however, a need for him to raise questions and he should immediately do so with the United States of America in relation to the mistakes that have occurred already. The American aviation authority, the FAA, has issued a directive to all executive jets and to all American planes that they are not to land in Shannon or other Irish airports for security reasons. We need an explanation why we are deemed to be an area of high risk where aircraft should not land. Over the past number of weeks a number of executive jets that would normally land in Shannon to be serviced have not landed having been directed by the FAA not to do so. At the same time US planes taking part in the war in Afghanistan and travelling on to bases in Europe and the Middle East are landing at Shannon to be refuelled and resupplied. It is not good enough that the American aviation authority should give a directive of this nature in relation to this sovereign state. We are not aware that we pose a security risk. How has the USA deemed us to be one? The USA has <Col N="336" /> a responsibility to give us an answer and I ask the Minister for Foreign Affairs, Deputy Cowen, to get an answer and let us know where we stand.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JoeCostelloLAB" hpid="Mr. Costello Mr. Costello">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Costello</NameTxt>
      <P>I wish to share my time with Senator Ryan. I thank Senator Farrell for his generosity in letting us have this slot.</P>
      <P>On behalf of Senator Farrell I mention Kieran Gorman, a Sligo man who died in the twin towers. We offer all our sympathy to his wife, family and his brothers who are still in Sligo. He was very unfortunate to be there on that day.</P>
      <P>The tragic events of 11 September have resonated around the globe. Everybody has been shocked by what happened there. For the very first time war has been brought to the heart of the United States of America and it is a war of terrorism which has deeply shocked that country. It has caused enormous fear and worry. The aftermath is the war being visited on the people of Afghanistan. Most countries were at one in their sympathy for the United States in the wake of the terrorist acts perpetrated against the American people. Likewise, everybody, including the United Nations, supports the United States in bringing to justice those who committed those crimes. However, not everybody believes Afghanistan and the millions living there in poverty with poor education and who face famine after years of drought, are one and the same with those who committed those crimes. Not all the Taliban are Osama bin Ladens. Every person in Afghanistan certainly does not support him. Visiting the full force of the war on the people of Afghanistan has to be questioned in terms of what the outcome might be and how it serves the intention to bring to justice those responsible. It is one thing to say that every bomb dropped is a smart bomb that will hit its target; it is another to ensure that happens. We know from the bombing of the Red Cross depot yesterday that it does not happen. There are rumours of a school having been bombed today.</P>
      <P>We want to know what is going to happen after this. Where is the next stage? The ground war is supposed to be delayed. It is an ongoing bombing event with no activity on the ground as yet. What will be the outcome? What role is the United Nations playing in bringing about a solution and how do the United States of America and its allies intend to pursue this war to its conclusion? How many face starvation? Most people pointed out the irony of dropping bombs at the same time as distributing food. It is a strange war that is being fought. The question of where we are going from here has to be asked. The Minister said the likely refugee fallout from this will be five times that generated by the genocide in Rwanda in 1994. That figure was colossal. Many people face starvation and the winter will be upon us in a month's time and it will affect all the people of Afghanistan.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>We need to see a sense of urgency as to where the United States is going and some sense of direction. Is the United Nations playing a role? <Col N="337" /> Are we playing a role in terms of our position on the Security Council? It is very difficult to see. It is as though everybody is standing back and allowing the United States to carry on as it wishes for as long as it wants. It is time there was a sense of direction towards a peace process. What is being done about Palestine? That is really the crux of all of this. We have seen a Minister assassinated today and things could easily get out of hand in terms of perceptions and what is presented. No doubt what bin Laden wants is a show down between East and West, between Islam and what are perceived as the Christian nations of the West.</P>
    <P>From our position on the Security Council we need to ask hard questions. The Minister for Foreign Affairs needs to ask in what direction this is going, what is the timescale and what will be the eventual outcome.</P>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. Ryan Mr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>Let us reiterate that what was done on 11 September was wrong and no injustice could justify it. That needs to be said again and again, but nor can any injustice justify a war if it loses proportionality, if it goes out of control and if it begins to do more harm than good.</P>
      <P>I want to bring some figures to the attention of the House but I do not do it to in any way minimise the sin of commission and the brutality of 11 September in New York. I recount the figures to talk about the planet's sins of omission. For instance, given the average over the year, on 11 September 24,000 died of hunger around the world, the day 6,000 or 7,000 were killed in the twin towers. Based on the average, 6,000 children died of diarrhoea that day. Measles would have killed 2,700 children even as the brutality was perpetrated on the twin towers. There are 1.2 billion who live on the equivalent of less than $1 a day and 3 billion have to live on the equivalent of less than $2 a day. In the ten year period from 1990 to 2000 an average of 200,000 children a year were killed in conflicts on this planet. On average, in that period, 1.2 million children were made homeless by conflict.</P>
      <P>Brutality will never be ended by greater brutality. The brutality that took place before the attack on the twin towers will not be ended by the brutality of that act, and neither will the brutality of that act be ended by further brutality. There is only one way to peace and that is through justice. There is only one way we can ultimately achieve justice, and that is through peace.</P>
      <P>There are specific issues we now need to confront, the first of which &ndash; in terms of what I have just said about conflict &ndash; is the question of the international arms industry, particularly the alarming increase in the number of licences being issued in this State to export weapons which are at least of dual use and, in some cases, of single use. If we are to institute justice, we must deal with conflict and its sources and weapons. We can deal with all three if we wish.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Special Education:" RHead="Motion">
    <Title>Special Education: Motion.</Title>
    <Col N="338" />
    <Speaker pid="JoeOToole" hpid="Mr. O'Toole Mr. O'Toole">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Toole</NameTxt>
      <P>I move:</P>
      <P>That Seanad Éireann</P>
      <P>welcomes:</P>
      <P>&ndash;&nbsp;the substantial increases in resources being made available to special education;</P>
      <P>&ndash;&nbsp;the Minister's announcement of his intention to establish a National Council for Special Education;</P>
      <P>&ndash;&nbsp;the work of the National Council for Curriculum and Assessment in the area of curriculum for special needs;</P>
      <P>denounces:</P>
      <P>&ndash;&nbsp;the system which compels parents to resort to the courts and other legal means to get an appropriate education for those of their children with special needs;</P>
      <P>proposes:</P>
      <P>&ndash;&nbsp;that the Minister for Education recognise the right of all citizens, young and old, with special needs to an appropriate education and that the type of education provision provided by the State is in all cases determined by the needs of the person;</P>
      <P>&ndash;&nbsp;that legislation be drafted immediately to protect the rights of all those with disabilities;</P>
      <P>&ndash;&nbsp;that the Minister continue to improve the resources available to meet the needs of all those with special needs;</P>
      <P>&ndash;&nbsp;that the Minister recognise the rights of parents of those with special needs to be consulted in the determination of the appropriate placement for their children;</P>
      <P>&ndash;&nbsp;that the Minister establish a comprehensive programme of training for all teachers and other personnel working in special needs education;</P>
      <P>&ndash;&nbsp;that the Minister re-establish the Special Education Review Committee comprising all the education partners to review special education provision at pre-school, primary, post-primary and third levels;</P>
      <P>&ndash;&nbsp;that each child's psychological report list the resources required for every child with special needs and that schools be given those resources to meet the child's needs and</P>
      <P>&ndash;&nbsp;that schools be given an appropriate additional level of staffing to meet the needs of the pupils in those schools where year round programmes are in place.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>As will be seen, I have made an attempt to cover all the needs. I am not being mealy mouthed in saying that I hope the Government side of the <Col N="339" /> House will recognise the inclusive way in which we deal with the Minister for Education and Science, as we normally do in welcoming the progress that he has made.</P>
    <P>I regret that the drafters of the appalling amendment did not formulate it differently. I tabled the motion is such a way that they did not have to propose deleting all words after &ldquo;Seanad Éireann&rdquo;. They could have proposed to delete all words after &ldquo;denounces&rdquo; or something to that effect. It would make the approach a lot easier.</P>
    <P>During the summer, I sought the recall of this House to deal with this type of matter and the issues that followed from the Sinnott case. I certainly want to make some reference to those. The simple point we are addressing is that every citizen has the entitlement, whether they are young or old, to an appropriate education and the type of education provision provided by the State in all cases should be determined by the needs of the person. That is a simple point.</P>
    <P>The outcome of the Sinnott case was appalling. The State said that a person is not entitled to receive fundamental education simply because the court said that, from its perspective, Jamie Sinnott was not entitled to primary education. This was never the intention of the people who drafted the Constitution.</P>
    <P>I ask the Minister of State to recognise the need for early intervention and planning. The Minister talked about having an open cheque &ndash; it is a great thing for a Minister to say he has an open cheque, but I am not simply talking about throwing money at the problem. I would like to adopt a very detailed approach to ensure we meet the needs of those requiring special education.</P>
    <P>We need early identification of children with special needs, no matter what age. As soon as they have a problem &ndash; whether it be a learning difficulty, autism or a related condition, or a serious mental or emotional difficulty &ndash; they must be identified as early as possible. Having done that, we want every child with special needs to have an assessment to determine the precise nature of his or her needs. We want to ensure that the needs are catered for with sufficient resources. Schools must be resourced properly to ensure they can give the children the level of education they require.</P>
    <P>My colleague, Senator Norris, who is seconding the motion, will allude to the importance of educational psychologists. I will ignore that for a moment. The Minister of State will accept that it is not just a problem for teachers. I want a broad, global approach to the problem that examines it from different points of view. We have spoken to teachers and asked them what are the main difficulties. There are certain obvious ones we should all be aware of. Another is the lack of quality medical back-up. It is not just a matter for educational psychologists &ndash; who are fundamentally important &ndash; but speech and language therapists, occupational therapists and physiotherapists. All these forms of therapy are required to <Col N="340" /> assist children with special needs. There is a strong view that psychiatric services should be provided in certain cases. It must be understood that there is no one system that is suitable for every single child, even those with the same types of difficulties.</P>
    <P>With regard to the row that ensued from the Jamie Sinnott case, we were very worried because we met parents and friends who took the view that what their children needed was a particular regime because they had autism. Some had been taken down to Cork to witness the CABA system which they thought was brilliant. Another group witnessed a system in operation in Kildare and thought it was brilliant. The Department of Education and Science was extolling the virtues of an outreach system, which was the one to adopt.</P>
    <P>There are no absolutes in education. Children have multiple needs. It is probably the case that every child could make progress under any one of the systems, but we want to ensure that the system that is most appropriate for a child is available. Also, any system that is used must be properly approved and professionally sound.</P>
    <P>It is understandable that parents are at their wits end. Nobody is talking to them about their difficulties. It is no wonder that they criticise the Minister and the Government. It is a matter of communication. I have included in the motion a proposal &ldquo;that the Minister recognise the rights of parents of those with special needs to be consulted in the determination of the appropriate placement for their children&rdquo;. I am making that proposal as the General Secretary of INTO. We have seen the problems that are created if nobody talks to the parents and explains what they are doing and why a certain system is being approved for their child. When they receive inadequate professional advice, they meet one of the groups of parents &ndash; with the best of intentions &ndash; that supports one particular kind of regime, and they are told that that regime is the answer to their problems. We need a way of ensuring that any system put in place is the correct one.</P>
    <P>We are aware of the progress that has been made, but we do not want the Minister pandering to every group that demands money for a particular system. That is now happening. Six months ago, the Minister was saying that the only system he would sanction with regard to autism was the outreach system. Now he is offering support to almost any group that proposes a system. Every proposal should be properly vetted, examined and approved. That is what we want to do. Any criticism I have made of the Minister is for no other reason than to achieve what I propose in the motion.</P>
    <P>The key to the effective implementation of a more inclusive policy is that there be flexibility, provision of resources and availability of appropriate materials, including availability of ICT for children with special needs. I could speak for three hours about the extraordinary added value of information and communications technology for children with special needs. It is almost <Col N="341" /> impossible to imagine what it is like to see a child who has never been able to communicate suddenly being able to do so. I have seen many times where technology can convey speech and sound and interpret movements, pushes, eyelid movements or whatever to allow a child communicate. No matter what way we do it, that is what it is about.</P>
    <P>The provision of professional development in special education to all teachers and special needs assistants is also important. Teachers must be kept up-to-date with the latest developments and given the opportunity to improve themselves while ensuring special needs assistants are available. That is another point we raise; there should be special needs assistants in classrooms and schools dealing with children with special needs. It is something of which the Minister approves and which needs to be developed as quickly as possible.</P>
    <P>As well as open access to psychological assessment, I welcome another initiative of the Minister's which is not included in the motion. We argued with the Minister for a long time that, because there was not access to the limited educational psychological service, he should allow schools to go to a private psychologist and claim back the costs in an approved manner. I welcome that this has been put in place and that a list of qualified educational psychologists approved by the Department of Education and Science has been put on the Department's website. These can be approached directly by schools to conduct psychological assessments in the schools which can then claim back the cost from the Department. This is an important initiative and I am not in any way begrudging in recognising those issues which have been progressed, but the issue must be taken a little further.</P>
    <P>We also need a team approach involving all the professionals &ndash; the class, resource teachers, visiting and special class teachers and the multi-disciplinary teams involving professionals from other disciplines. We have also put forward a number of issues which we believe can help the Minister in this process. The establishment of a council through which we can tune in to the expertise of people would be fantastic.</P>
    <P>I wish to finish with a story about information and communications technology. About 12 years ago I was camping on a beach in west Kerry. Beside me were a family with a child who had multiple disabilities. He was in a wheelchair and was not able to speak or communicate. He tried to indicate what he had to say by pointing at pictures on a picture board. He was clearly very bright but could not communicate in any way. He became the centre of the caravan site where we were for that week. I always remember that a jackdaw befriended him and spent the week on his shoulder or his picture board, something which made the child hysterical with laughter. We tried to keep in contact with him for a few years after that and he visited us a few times but then we lost contact.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="342" />In the middle of the summer I read an article in <i>The Irish Times</i> about people with special needs and how they have evolved. There was our old friend James Brosnan now in his 20s hooked up to all types of machinery in DCU where he was finishing his degree. This is what people need to see about the value of information and communications technology. We can give new life, layers of meaning, impetus, articulation and hope to people who had all types of difficulties before. When asked what he remembered about all the technology, he replied that the day he said &ldquo;Hello, Mum&rdquo;, that is, when it came up on the screen, was his favourite day. For these reasons, I appeal to the Minister to support the motion and not press this extraordinary amendment.</P>
    <Speaker pid="DavidNorris" hpid="Mr. Norris Mr. Norris">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norris</NameTxt>
      <P>I am very happy to second the motion although I had not anticipated doing so until a few minutes ago. Once again my colleague, Senator O'Toole, has highlighted an important area and all sides of the House are concerned and committed to trying to get something done about it. It is a pity that a motion such as this has to be amended but, unfortunately, any time a word such as &ldquo;denounces&rdquo; appears in a motion, it is almost guaranteed to be opposed. Perhaps it is significant that we should have a vote on this. There are areas where all of us, including the Government side, can agree. The first section of the motion welcomes measures the Government has taken but it goes on to highlight some deficiencies. It is part of the role of the Seanad to do this although it is understandable that the Government side would prefer to have an uninterrupted paean of praise for what the Government does.</P>
      <P>I am also glad the Minister of State, Deputy Treacy, is present. We have long experience of him in the House and we know that he has a humane approach and that the points made, even if they are contentious, will be directed by him to the centres of power.</P>
      <P>It is shameful that parents have had to go to the courts in recent years and place themselves at personal financial risk and endure all the trauma in addition to caring for children with difficulties. There is an obligation on the Oireachtas, as the motion suggests, to encourage the drafting of legislation to secure and protect the rights of people, especially children, with disabilities. I hope the Minister will have some information that the Government proposes to do this.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Senator O'Toole spoke about early intervention being important. I would like to add to that and support him in what he said. There is a need for early and consistent intervention because the tragedy is that sometimes children with disabilities have a special needs teacher who, for some reason, is taken away. I am familiar with a case which I raised on the Adjournment some time ago concerning a family with several handicapped children, including one autistic child who was making some progress with a speech therapist. The therapist was taken away and the par<Col N="343" /> ents said to me that the tragedy was not just that the child was stuck at that point but that he started regressing. That is the other side to the heart warming story of the initiation of communication which Senator O'Toole, whose personal experience it was, placed on the record.</P>
    <P>The motion is timely. We need to examine how the system operates in practice. The motion includes the point that each child's psychological report list the resources required for every child with special needs and that schools be given the resources to meet the child's needs. Without a report one is operating in the dark. I understand that there are many situations where the absence of this psychological report is an impediment because, without it, the child does not get the help he or she needs. Teachers experience practical difficulties in getting these children assessed. This is a problem which needs to be examined.</P>
    <P>I have mentioned the idea of consistency. I wish to highlight how wonderful these programmes work when they are implemented but they must be extended. I attended the Marlborough Street Central Model Schools and saw the wonderful work done there as a result of the Breaking the Cycle scheme. However, these marvellous children are given hope and potential and are then dumped because the scheme does not extend into secondary and third levels. If we are serious about curing disadvantage and inequality, this scheme should be continued up to the point where a young person is fully educated in line with his or her capacity.</P>
    <P>The other reason I am glad to have an opportunity to speak in the debate is that, partly due to Senator O'Toole's promptings, I was asked to speak at a very moving and fascinating conference of special needs teachers in St. Patrick's College in Drumcondra a few months ago. I met many people and heard their difficulties. Some of them have been in touch with me since.</P>
    <P>Coincidentally, in the past couple of days I received a letter which enclosed a document, the contents of which I would like to put on record. It is from a wonderful teacher in the west. She says:</P>
    <P>I teach a language class in a particular school. My class of seven children ranges in age from four to eight. They have language disorder and other problems which mean that they do not understand what is being said and of course cannot express themselves. Their non-verbal IQs range from average to above average to superior.</P>
    <P>That is an extraordinary paragraph describing this intelligence locked into a body which finds it impossible to communicate without assistance . She goes on to say:</P>
    <P>My plea is that every language class have a full-time classroom assistant, as I understand is the case in other countries. Due to the range in age, ability, language difficulties etc. these <Col N="344" /> children need individual small-group work, seven individual curricula.</P>
    <P>Here again is a very potent point. When there are children with a variety of disabilities, each of them needs a curriculum tailor-made for his or her needs. The teacher stated:</P>
    <P>The classroom assistant ensures that while I am working with individuals and small groups she can attend to the other children under my direction. Therefore all are working to full potential. I am very lucky to have had that situation for the last three years [again this point is worth noting] as FÁS provided me with a classroom assistant. She has been invaluable but she finishes in October and my seven beautiful children will be the losers.</P>
    <P>We should not just rely on FÁS to provide classroom assistants. They should be an integral part of the scheme, and this story from the coalface indicates that.</P>
    <P>This teacher's document is clearly laid out and in it she says that a language disorder class was established in her school in 1992. Currently it caters for seven pupils as per Department regulations. The Department of Education and Science has a fine statement objective that people should be given appropriate education with as little segregation of those with special needs as is necessary. The people on the ground are the ones who have to implement these objectives.</P>
    <P>These pupils travel from various parts of the county, some leaving home at 7.30 a.m. and not returning until 5 p.m. While language disorder is their primary problem, many of them have a variety of problems, for example, autistic spectrum disorder, Asperger's syndrome, dyspraxia, ADD and ADHD. Their ages span from four years to eight years approximately, thus necessitating individual curriculum ranging from junior infants to second or third class. Because of this and due to the very personalised attention each pupil must receive, the class teacher and school principal feel strongly that a special needs assistant must be provided on a full-time basis in this class. This is to ensure that at all times all pupils are working to their full potential and getting the maximum benefits possible from their full time in the class, which is only two years.</P>
    <P>The school is now formally applying for a full-time special needs assistant to be sanctioned by the Department, commencing in September 2001. Given the short period of time the children are in the language classes &ndash; two years &ndash; a classroom assistant is needed so that this time would be fully utilised. The children are at different stages in the curriculum. In this school they range from junior infants to second or third class and they need intensive work. Classroom assistants can work with one small group under direction. Many of the children have poor concentration and therefore find it difficult to work on their own for any length of time. This is further exacerbated by their speech and language difficulties.</P>
    <P>An adult is needed to bring the children to <Col N="345" /> mainstream classes and stay with them, particularly in this school where they work on computers, take part in physical education and use computers for religion class. These children also need to be kept under observation during break times. They can be difficult in the yard. They are children with special needs and they can have special irritating qualities. There are difficulties with using toilet facilities and other physical areas such as dressing. There is a high level of administration with this class, involving outside bodies, schools, health boards, parents, meetings, the compilation of reports etc.</P>
    <P>I am glad to have the opportunity to make this case and I will be happy to give the Minister the details of this school so that he may give his attention to it.</P>
    <Speaker pid="TonyKett" hpid="Mr. Kett Mr. Kett">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Kett</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 1:</P>
      <P>To delete all words after &ldquo;Seanad Éireann&rdquo; and substitute the following:</P>
      <P>&ldquo;commends the Minister for Education and Science on the substantial increase in resources being made available to special education;</P>
      <P>welcomes the Minister's proposals:</P>
      <P>&ndash;&nbsp;to establish a National Council for Special Education,</P>
      <P>&ndash;&nbsp;to hold a Forum on Special Education, and</P>
      <P>&ndash;&nbsp;to introduce a Disabilities (Education and Training) Bill;</P>
      <P>welcomes in particular the Minister's announcement that the Disabilities (Education and Training) Bill will clarify and copperfasten the rights and entitlements of people with disabilities to appropriate support services and facilitate the delivery of these services in an efficient and effective manner which has full regard to the needs and entitlements of the children in question and their parents; and</P>
      <P>calls on the Minister for Education and Science to bring forward the Disabilities (Education and Training) Bill at the earliest possible date and to continue to build on the unprecedented progress which he has made in developing our special education services.&rdquo;.</P>
      <P>I welcome the Minister of State at the Department of Education and Science, Deputy Treacy, to the House and I thank my colleague, Senator Ormonde, for allowing me speak first.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I wholeheartedly concur with the element of the Private Members' motion which welcomes the substantial resources being made available to special education and for the consideration being given to the setting up of the national council for special education and the work of the National Council for Curriculum and Assessment in the whole area of special needs. The programme for Government was an ambitious programme as it related to disabilities. Any fair-minded person will agree when I say that our Ministers have <Col N="346" /> done a magnificent job. Those of us engaged in the area of working with people with disability accept that there is no magic wand and no quick fix solution to ridding ourselves of all the ills that prevail in the area.</P>
    <P>No Government has done as much as this one in dealing with the needs of people with disability. The motion suggests that legislation should be drafted immediately to protect the rights of people with disability. To do that would be to ignore the plethora of equality legislation brought through the House by the Minister for Justice, Equality and Law Reform, Deputy O'Donoghue. It also disregards the fact that we are introducing a disabilities Bill determined to copperfasten everything enshrined in legislation to date. I expect all of us and those working with the disabled will be pleased with the outcome of that Bill.</P>
    <P>The motion goes on to say that parents of children with special needs need to be consulted in determining appropriate placements for their children. I agree, and in my experience that happens. Parents are not always the best adjudicators and the best people to assess the needs of a child as they are not always totally objective. That is understandable because by their nature they are blinded with love, affection and a need to do the utmost for their child.</P>
    <P>I recall an incident where a teenager was seeking a placement on a skill-based training programme in computers. The whole assessment process took place and parents, paramedics and professionals were involved. At the end of the day the placement officers decided the child was not suitable for the course. The course needed good hand function, which the child did not have, to gain full benefit from the course. Of course the parents fell out with the professionals which is understandable because the option for that teenager was to stay home if there was no suitable course available. This illustrates how a parent can be blinded by a desire to do what is best and that he or she will not always be objective. I fully agree that parents must be part of decision making.</P>
    <P>The motion also refers to the need for training teachers and personnel working in the area. I agree with those sentiments. Resources are needed to provide for pre-service and in-service training for teachers and special needs assistants irrespective of what placement they are in. The cohort of teachers currently trained and working in the area also needs additional training to bring them up to speed with new approaches, the individualised programmes currently taking place and the complex issue of integration.</P>
    <P>I do not disagree with the re-establishment of the special education committee. The report produced by the education committee in 1983 was basically taken as the bible for the provision of services. It was a far-seeing report. Part of it was implemented and its recommendations were exceeded in some instances. Its re-establishment would allow for a review of progress and eval<Col N="347" /> uation of the effectiveness of its provisions, and it could assist future planning. The national council for special education, which the Minister plans and we welcome, will do that job as one of its functions is to establish regional educational officers. They will have an accurate knowledge of what is required in the regions and such information will contribute to a blueprint for the way forward.</P>
    <P>The Department does an exceptional job. I recently visited a special school and asked how the situation had improved since 1996. I was astonished to learn that in 1996 the school had 113 pupils, 12 teachers, 3 special assistants and no bus escorts. In 1999, it had 106 pupils, 17 teachers, 10 special assistants and 12 bus escorts. In 2001, the number of pupils is down to 98 as a result of integration, while there are 19 teachers, 18 special assistants and 15 bus escorts. This school was very enthusiastic about recent developments, which constitute significant progress.</P>
    <P>The Minister is also to be congratulated on the initiative financing schools to access psychological services outside the NEPS programme. This means that a school not receiving adequate psychological provision can engage suitable practitioners from outside which will shorten waiting lists in this area.</P>
    <P>The motion also refers to staff levels being increased to meet the needs of the pupils in schools where year round programmes are in place. There is a problem in recruiting staff for these programmes because people are asked to work through holidays and boards of managements are asked to supervise it. I wonder if it is workable and if more thought is required.</P>
    <P>As Senator O'Toole mentioned, technology plays a considerable part in enabling pupils to access the curriculum and I hope they receive even more technological aids. However, instead of being assigned to a school, a computer should be assigned to an individual whose learning tool it becomes. No one gets real benefit if it is used by many. Also, the resources should be provided to train teachers and children in their use because many pieces of equipment are not fully used.</P>
    <P>I again congratulate the Government on the job it is doing which, as someone who works in the area, I appreciate. We honoured our commitments given when we entered Government in 1997.</P>
    <Speaker pid="DenisDinoCregan" hpid="Mr. D. Cregan Mr. D. Cregan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. D. Cregan</NameTxt>
      <P>Why is there an amendment to this motion? There should not be a vote because no one can honestly answer Senator O'Toole's speech. He could talk for a long time on this subject. I can speak from personal experience because I have a nephew requiring special education and for many years I was involved with profoundly handicapped children in Cork. No one should be proud of speaking against this motion.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The Government wants to give the impression that all is well, yet it appealed to the Supreme <Col N="348" /> Court in the Jamie Sinnott case, even though the then Minister for Education and Science, Deputy Martin, gave an assurance that there would be no appeal. The Government should have accepted the court's recommendations. I compliment Mrs. Sinnott and those who supported her. They went through so much at a time when the State is prosperous. I acknowledge that improvements have been made, but there are still arguments over the few disabled, however they are defined, who are not being educated. There should be a Government Department for the disabled, as there is for less worthy areas.</P>
    <P>The proposals are excellent, as is what the previous speaker said, but they have been a long time coming. As someone who got only a primary education, I know that secondary and third level education here is exceptionally good. However, a disabled person finds it difficult to get beyond primary education and that level is not as good as the others. As a society, we do not have the will to help people whom we classify as a small minority. As politicians, we heard how people spoke about us after the Sinnott case and we are slowly learning the lesson that we must face this problem. The internationally known COPE foundation, which has been in Cork since the 1950s when tuberculosis was a problem, can teach us much. Why do we not listen?</P>
    <P>The amendment calls for a forum on special education but that is in the motion, as is the call for a disabilities education and training Bill. Why is there an amendment? This is my first time to make a party political speech in this House because the Government is creating a political discussion. Yet on all sides, Senators feel that this should not be a political debate, but that we should all say &ldquo;Yes&rdquo; to the motion.</P>
    <P>It is unfair to the people we talk about because for far too long they were not discussed. We have never had so much money, as the Minister knows. Once a Minister could not even promise extra hospital beds but now we talk about sporting arenas and other projects. We have bettered ourselves in recent years but there are not enough improvements. Those referred to by Senator O'Toole are the people who can tell the Government what is needed.</P>
    <P>Senator O'Toole is right in saying that trying to please different groups has been a problem. It should be left to one agency. Special people should be trained, brought in and paid. The disabled are entitled to that. I have seen many children who are taken care of by just one person, the child's mother or father, and that has gone on for too long. It is not fair to the parents and, most importantly, to the children. It is great that the first words Mr. Brosnan spoke after 20 years were &ldquo;Hello, Ma.&rdquo;  We have equipment and information technology that can help get the best out of children with special needs. The specialists say that such children can become above-average with just a little training. We have a responsibility but we are slow to act.</P>
    <P>That the State appealed the Sinnott case on a <Col N="349" /> question of principle was appalling. If I was a representative of the Government, I would let my feelings be known at parliamentary level. The State should not have appealed that case. It should have let it go and assisted the family in every way possible. Parents and children should not have been brought through the courts to prove a point, just as we should not be treating the matter in a political fashion tonight by looking for a vote. There should not be a vote on this motion. I know that the Minister of State is prepared to say that he agrees with the motion, but we should not play politics with the disabled. We have done that for long enough.</P>
    <Speaker pid="AnnOrmonde" hpid="Ms Ormonde Ms Ormonde">
      <NameTxt>Ms Ormonde</NameTxt>
      <P>I welcome the Minister of State to the House. I am glad to have the opportunity to speak on this very sensitive issue. To suggest that we would become political on this issue is wrong.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DenisDinoCregan" hpid="Mr. D. Cregan Mr. D. Cregan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. D. Cregan</NameTxt>
      <P>What is the Government side doing? It is opposing the motion.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="AnnOrmonde" hpid="Ms Ormonde Ms Ormonde">
      <NameTxt>Ms Ormonde</NameTxt>
      <P>I am delighted to endorse the amendment on the basis that I want to talk about what the Government is doing and the achievements made to date. To suggest that we are not doing anything is wrong.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DenisDinoCregan" hpid="Mr. D. Cregan Mr. D. Cregan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. D. Cregan</NameTxt>
      <P>I did not say that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="AnnOrmonde" hpid="Ms Ormonde Ms Ormonde">
      <NameTxt>Ms Ormonde</NameTxt>
      <P>I could have interrupted the Senator but I did not do so. I have clear points to make. I know as much as any Member about this area and I appreciate how knowledgeable Senator O'Toole is. To suggest that there are no other knowledgeable people preparing the legislation is wrong, and Senator O'Toole would agree with that. The Department has access to a range of expertise in dealing with this issue. This subject is a sensitive one for many parents and families, and the House should deal with it properly and support the provision of resources and facilities for special education for young people.</P>
      <P>The Government is committed to this matter and that commitment began in 1998 when the then Minister for Education and Science, Deputy Martin, acknowledged the rights of those students. He made no bones about the matter and he proceeded to set up programmes to deal with it. I welcome the establishment of the national council which is a clear indication of how we can move forward. Experts with a hands-on approach will be brought in to introduce special programmes and deliver the required services to those in need.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>It is wrong for Members to throw their eyes up and say that the Government is doing nothing. I dislike that and do not want Members to leave this House thinking that the Government has not provided a way forward. We may not have got it completely right &ndash; what Government does? It is wise not to forget that Governments before this one did nothing to deal with this issue. We are <Col N="350" /> trying to do something by putting the funding into pre-education and special education programmes. We have made a start. It may not be fully-fledged yet but parents have acknowledged the work being done. I welcome the forum that is to be set up. It will be a platform for debate where Members, parents, experts and others can make submissions. I look forward to that and hope it will be the lead-in to a Bill dealing with disability.</P>
    <P>I welcome this timely debate tonight. I do not disagree with the points made by Senator O'Toole. I dealt with this area in my other profession. I dealt with the lack of psychological services, but there is a commitment by this Government to bring in those services. Where we cannot provide those services, private psychologists will deal with the issue and the State will refund the cost. Parents and resource teachers, who have made a welcome start in most schools, must be consulted. Training is still necessary for many resource teachers and that is being done.</P>
    <P>The Government side of the House is not here to knock the ideas put forward in the motion &ndash; it is too sensitive an issue to be debated on a political basis. We are here to see how best we can move forward the special needs programme for young people from primary to secondary to adult level. We need a multi-faceted approach. We need the involvement of health boards, educational psychologists, clinicians, resource teachers and, above all, parents at the core. We should all sing the one tune and not suggest that there were no problems in the past. Since 1998, the Government has made a commitment to this issue and the measures and proposals are there.</P>
    <P>I am delighted Senator O'Toole made the points he did. Those points can be incorporated into the Bill dealing with education, training and disability that will soon be brought forward. This is a golden opportunity. There is nothing wrong with what Senator O'Toole has said tonight. I am here to make sure that the points made tonight will be incorporated in the new legislation. That legislation will come after the forum has been set up and has received submissions. We can draw conclusions from that, then draft the Bill and make it law so that never again will we see parents of children with special needs having to worry about their future. The children will be protected at primary and secondary level and into adulthood. There will be a well-funded system and programme in place and educational rights will be protected.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MaryHenry" hpid="Dr. Henry Dr. Henry">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Henry</NameTxt>
      <P>I am sorry an amendment has been put down to Senator O'Toole's motion which was very reasonable. The Government has no need to be so defensive&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="AnnOrmonde" hpid="Ms Ormonde Ms Ormonde">
      <NameTxt>Ms Ormonde</NameTxt>
      <P>I was not defensive.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryHenry" hpid="Dr. Henry Dr. Henry">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Henry</NameTxt>
      <P>&mdash;because a great deal of good work has been done. However, there is a great deal more that could be done.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I wish to speak about an area that no-one has <Col N="351" /> mentioned so far, that is the problem that many parents have in getting a diagnosis made for a child with a disability before the child goes to school. This is a serious problem because the parents are in a situation where they do not know from the physical or neurological assessment of the child whether they should make efforts to get the child into mainstream education, as is the desire of most parents, or settle for sending the child to some special school which may be more suitable for him or her.</P>
    <P>Debates on waiting lists concentrate constantly on the fact that so many adults are waiting for operations and so forth, but the number of children who are waiting for assessment of various physical, psychological and mental problems is really quite terrible. The fact that seven of the health boards have no neurologist at all let alone a paediatric neurologist is dreadful. This means that children have to be referred to the waiting lists of the three Dublin paediatric hospitals or to Cork, Limerick or Galway. This is an entirely unsatisfactory state of affairs. The Midland Health Board does not have any neurologist, nor does the Mid-Western Health Board nor the North Western Health Board. This has to be looked at because many of the disabilities which children in school have are, in fact, neurological.</P>
    <P>There are extremely long waiting lists for people with ENT problems. Much has been said tonight about communication and the fact that children are diagnosed so late with deafness. This is another serious problem for which there are some easy remedies in many cases and, if not, there are facilities available which could be used for the child. It is very important that we try to address these issues rather than just looking at the situation in isolation. Operations for the children who are on the waiting lists for ENT operations may make all the difference to how they get on in school. I know the Government is working on it but it is something we have to recognise is of great importance.</P>
    <P>Senator O'Toole stressed the various problems there can be at school for children with disabilities, and the great help provided by classroom assistants, resource teachers and so on. I am glad to be able to congratulate the Government about something tonight and I am delighted to have some constituents who are involved in hospitals &ndash; some are hospital governors &ndash; in the public gallery tonight. It is a huge leap forward that we now have proper national schools in children's hospitals. A child with any type of disability or a prolonged illness who is out of school for any length of time or on and off if it is a relapsing problem is extraordinarily serious for the child. Play therapy is important in these schools for younger children and the more support we can get there the better. I congratulate all those who have been involved in bringing this forward.</P>
    <P>The area of psychological assessment is very serious because if one does not diagnose the psychological problems the child has they may be <Col N="352" /> extremely disruptive for the class and cause problems for other children as well as for themselves. I welcome the efforts of the Minister for Education and Science, Deputy Woods, in allowing two children per hundred to be sent for psychological assessment to private psychologists to be paid for by the State. It concerns me that there may be six or seven in the hundred who actually need psychological assessment and in fact the more serious children may be sent while those who might benefit most can be the ones who did not appear to have that many problems. We have to work as fast as possible to ensure that all children get psychological assessment if they need it. It is a problem in the courts and in other places that psychological assessments are not available for children. The borderline cases are the ones in fact who are often not seen.</P>
    <P>There has been a continuous problem regarding speech therapy, which is not helped by the fact that speech therapists have no proper career structure. This must be addressed and until it is we will not see a proper determined cohort of people who are totally committed to the system. Someone told me the other day that she met a middle aged speech therapist and that she had never met one before. She wondered what happens them as they seem to work in this field for a few years and then go off to some other area of employment. It would be a step forward if we could make their hours more flexible, perhaps to tie them in with school hours which might help to retain more of them within the service. Communication is extremely important, as is language, and unless we can get people into this area we will have a serious problem. Trinity College has been asked to expand the number of places on its speech therapy courses by 15 per year. This will help to remedy the shortages to some extent but of course that will take several years to go through the system.</P>
    <P>The lack of information is very hard on parents and I have been told that the special education staff in the Department of Education and Science in Athlone are under such pressure that they are constantly asking for transfers. It is very hard when those who are trying to give out information feel under such pressure that doing their job is an uphill battle all the time. I suggest that they should get the help they need to do the job. At a conference for the parents of disabled children in Longford last weekend an inspector said that was a real problem, so Senator O'Toole's motion is very timely. It is also very important that teachers get the in-service training they need in these areas.</P>
    <P>Senator Ormonde said that resource teachers are sometimes untrained. It is bad enough if one is trained but if one is not then it must be terrible. Of course special classroom assistants are important but there is currently no training or standardisation for them either which is badly needed. FÁS did tremendous work in that area which was helped by the fact that frequently the people involved came from the locality and knew <Col N="353" /> the needs of the children in their care. That is a good effort and I would hate to see anything happen to threaten the greater flexibility in the classroom for the teacher involved.</P>
    <P>A special education council is to be set up at some point. I am not sure when this will happen or what exactly it will do but I am somewhat concerned that it will make children with special needs feel they are different. I would not like to see that happen because as I have said parents really want their children in the mainstream structure, if at all possible.</P>
    <P>Problems seem to start when there is a move to secondary school. Maybe this is because people who work within the primary system can afford to be more flexible without the pressure of exams but certainly complaints have come to me about the transition from primary to secondary. Perhaps we could be more flexible there so that the child stays in the secondary school for core curriculum studies but, if required, can go to a special school for subjects where the special school has better facilities. What we are trying to do is look at the potential of the child to ensure that this is at the centre of all our education.</P>
    <P>Many parents have come to me about the difficulties of bringing their disabled children to and from school. On the Order of Business this morning, Senator John Cregan raised the difficulty of getting a disability allowance for one's car in order to carry a disabled passenger. The system is very rigid which is not the fault of those who implement it, and I know that every now and then the Minister for Finance does adjust the system, but it needs to be far more generous than it is at present.</P>
    <P>A member of the public approached me about his teenage daughter who has a condition known as drop epilepsy since she was six. She said I told her to be patient when I wrote to her two years ago as it appeared something was going to happen but nothing has happened. One cannot send a child with drop epilepsy, and other problems as well, on the school bus even though she is well able to partake in the general education system. We need to be more flexible when it comes to giving people extra assistance towards the school transport of disabled children. We have been trying to gather all our children into the fold to ensure that none is isolated. Even a decade ago, if children with an ordinary physical illness had to go into hospital for any length of time they were bound to drop behind in the education system but that is now a thing of the past. There are other areas which we can make a thing of the past by making alterations. No parents should have to go to court looking for schooling for their children.</P>
    <Speaker pid="NoelTracey" hpid="Mr. Treacy Mr. Treacy">
      <NameTxt>Minister of State at the Department of Education and Science (Mr. Treacy)</NameTxt>
      <P>Tá áthas orm an seans seo a ghlacadh chun an rún tábhachtach seo a phlé um thráthnóna.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I very much welcome the opportunity to welcome the issues raised on this motion which is <Col N="354" /> before the House this evening. I am proud and privileged to have been part of a Government which has been responsible for an unprecedented level of development in special education services and I assure the House that the Minister for Education and Science has every intention of ensuring that the major progress achieved in recent years will continue. At the same time, I fully recognise that much work remains to be done before we can be satisfied that all children with special needs are receiving the support they require when and where they require it.</P>
    <P>It is an unfortunate reality that the educational requirements of our special needs children were seriously neglected over many years. We must all accept that and we are all culpable in that area. While other priorities were being pursued, children with special needs were left to survive on a service which was characterised by inadequate resources, an unsympathetic bureaucracy and an inefficient and often unresponsive system of service delivery.</P>
    <P>In this situation it is little wonder that parents of special needs children have felt abandoned by the State and considered that they had no alternative but to resort to litigation to assert their children's rights. As Minister of State at the Department of Education and Science, I find this situation entirely unacceptable. Parents of children with special needs have enough to contend with without having to fight their way through a bureaucratic minefield simply to have their children's needs addressed.</P>
    <Speaker pid="DenisDinoCregan" hpid="Mr. D. Cregan Mr. D. Cregan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. D. Cregan</NameTxt>
      <P>Hear, hear.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="NoelTracey" hpid="Mr. Treacy Mr. Treacy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Treacy</NameTxt>
      <P>The challenges faced by the Government were formidable. Major improvements in services were required right across the spectrum of special needs. In some cases, existing services required major expansion. In other cases, entirely new services were required to address serious gaps in provision. The reality is that the level of improvement required could not be achieved by us overnight. However, I am satisfied that enormous progress has been made and that the foundations are now being firmly laid for a special education system of which we can be truly proud.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>By way of illustration, I want to refer to some of the significant developments in special education services which have taken place under the Government since 1997. Prior to a decision taken by the Government in October 1998 children with special educational needs had no automatic entitlement to a response to those needs. The extent to which support services were provided was entirely dictated by resource availability in any given year. The Department of Education and Science was allocated a finite number of special teacher posts and special needs assistant posts. When these were allocated, no further support was available in the year in question. Invariably, the level of resources made available <Col N="355" /> was inadequate and as a consequence many children with special needs were simply left without the support they required.</P>
    <P>All this changed in 1998 when the Government took the unprecedented step of deciding that all children with special needs in the primary system should have an automatic entitlement to the supports they require, irrespective of their level of need or location. In effect, the Government introduced a demand-driven system where the needs of the child, rather than the availability of resources, became the deciding factor. As a direct result of this decision the number of resource teachers supporting children with special needs in the primary system has increased from 104 to approximately 1,000 teachers today and the number of special needs assistants in the system has increased from fewer than 300 to approximately 2,500 people.</P>
    <P>The Department of Education and Science is continuing to allocate additional resource teachers and special needs assistants in response to identified needs. The significance of this development should not be understated. No longer are children with special needs at the mercy of annual funding exercises. They are now included automatically. The level of support provided is dictated solely by the needs of the individual child.</P>
    <P>Further important developments which have been introduced by the Government include the introduction of escorts on special school transport services. Under this development, the Department of Education and Science has made funding available to schools to facilitate the appointment of escorts on more than 600 routes carrying children to special schools and special classes. In 1998 the Department of Education and Science formally recognised the distinct educational needs of certain children with autism. Prior to that decision, such children were catered for in a variety of settings, none of which was dedicated specifically to the needs of children with autism. As a result of this development a total of 89 special classes dedicated to children with autism have been established. Each such class caters for a maximum of six pupils and has the support of a class teacher and two special needs assistants. Pupils attending these classes also attract special capitation funding at a rate of £451.50 per child.</P>
    <P>In the current year the Minister for Education and Science secured extra funding of £2.5 million to facilitate the extension of education programmes for children with autism, through the month of July. The development has been welcomed as providing a valuable continuation of education services for the children in question and is based on the view that such children can regress where services are withdrawn for lengthy periods. He also secured funding of £2.6 million to support the development of a nationwide pre-school service for children with autism. In addition to the above measures, he established a special task force on autism to advise him on how <Col N="356" /> services for children with autism could be further developed. He expects to receive the report of the task force by the end of this month. I am confident that this report will make a valuable contribution to further improving services in this area.</P>
    <P>Senators O'Toole, Cregan and others referred to technology. Recent technological developments have brought on stream a range of equipment and software packages which can be of particular benefit to the educational progress of children with disabilities. The Department of Education and Science has responded to these developments by substantially increasing the funding made available to schools in this area. The scale of the increase is illustrated by the fact that in 1998 funding of just over £500,000 was made available in this area. In the current year the Department will allocate approximately £3 million for special equipment. It is important to recognise that we have invested £280 million in the IT 2000 technology investment fund. We have invested £550 million in the third level programme for research and technological development and another £550 million in Science Foundation Ireland. Huge emphasis has been put into this area and we hope to create world class research, technology and scientific centres where we may be able to develop many of the technologies needed to assist those young people who need special assistance through technology and other aids.</P>
    <P>I mention the above developments to give Members an idea of the scale of development which the Government has undertaken in the special education area. As I have said, much work remains to be done. While the substantial increase in resources made available to schools to address special needs has been warmly welcomed, such resources are only part of the answer.</P>
    <P>Our objective is to develop a special education service which is underpinned by a clear and comprehensive declaration of the rights and entitlements of children with disabilities and their parents, which is in line with best international practice, which has the special needs of the individual child and the rights of the child's parents at its core and which is structured in such a way as to ensure that all children with special needs are identified at the earliest possible stage and that their needs are responded to on an immediate and appropriate basis.</P>
    <P>During the course of last year, the Minister, Deputy Woods, arranged for a fundamental review of the Department's structures and operating procedures. This review was undertaken by Mr. Seán Cromien, former Secretary General of the Department of Finance, and the Department's role in the special education area was considered by Mr. Cromien and his team as part of this review. A key conclusion of this review was that the over-centralised structure of the Department and its excessive involvement in day to day operational issues of education in general across the country was impeding its capacity to focus on the core areas of policy development <Col N="357" /> and quality assurance. The difficulties identified were particularly evident in the area of special education where the Department's excessive involvement in day to day operational issues was seen as impeding its capacity to plan and develop a special education service, which is in line with best international practice.</P>
    <P>To address this situation, Mr. Cromien strongly endorsed the early implementation of the recommendations of the planning group on special education which had been established in the Department of Education and Science, which proposed to &ldquo;make recommendations on the arrangements which should be put in place to ensure the most effective provision of a high quality co-ordinated service at all stages of the education system, for students with disabilities.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>The key recommendation brought forward by the planning group on special education and endorsed by Mr. Cromien was for the establishment of a national council for special education. The role of the council will be to carry out research and provide expert policy advice to the Minister for Education and Science on special education issues, to have overall operational responsibility for the dissemination of information and the co-ordination and delivery of special education services at local level through a network of local offices, to establish a consultative forum to facilitate inputs from the education partners and to establish expert advisory groups to provide up-to-date research and advice on special education issues.</P>
    <P>I know Senators are supportive of this development, which I welcome, and I thank all those who spoke so positively about the developments thus far. I am confident the National Council for Special Education will make a major contribution to our aim of developing an effective and efficient special education service which is responsive to the needs of children with disabilities and their parents at local area level. I am pleased to inform the House that the Minister for Education and Science has received Government approval for the establishment of the council at the earliest possible date and it is his intention to proceed with this development with all possible speed.</P>
    <P>It has been suggested that the special education review committee be re-established. I would point out that the proposed structure of the National Council for Special Education includes provision for a consultative forum involving the education partners and the establishment of expert advisory groups to address issues relating to special education services. I would see any future reviews of policy and services as being facilitated within these structures.</P>
    <P>As I have said, I regard it as totally unacceptable that any parent, particularly a parent of a child with special needs, should find it necessary to resort to litigation to secure their entitlements to an appropriate education service. I regard it as equally unacceptable that decisions on support services for children with special needs should be taken without having due regard <Col N="358" /> to the needs and concerns of the parents of the children involved. Members of the House have highlighted the importance of placing the needs of the individual child at the centre of all decisions and the need to involve the child's parents throughout the process. The Minister, Deputy Woods, fully endorses this view. He intends to hold a forum on special education in November. The objective is to provide an opportunity for all interested parties to express their views on how we can best define and protect the rights and entitlements of people with disabilities, in particular young people.</P>
    <P>Although the Government has been responsible for a very significant development of the special education system, I am conscious that many parents of children with disabilities are uneasy about a system of funding and service which is dependent on the policies of the Government of the day. Such parents would wish to see greater statutory guarantees for their children's future. Guarantees exist at present, not least in Article 42 of the Constitution and also in the Education Act, 1998, and the Education (Welfare) Act, 2001. Both these Acts, which were promoted by the Government, provide very wide guarantees for the education of children with disabilities. In addition to these education-specific Acts, the Government has sponsored the National Disability Authority Act, 1999, and the Equal Status Act, 2000, both of which have important provisions with implications for the education of people with disabilities.</P>
    <P>It is accepted, however, that there is a need for legislation which will specifically address in a comprehensive and focused way the education of children with disabilities. For that reason, the Minister for Education and Science intends to bring proposals to Government very soon for a Bill, the working title of which is the Education (Disabilities) Bill, 2001. In preparing this Bill the Minister will be guided by the following principles.</P>
    <P>Disability is a natural part of the human experience and in no way diminishes a person's right to fully participate in society, including education. In particular, children and young people with disabilities have the same right to an appropriate education as their peers who do not have disabilities. An appropriate education is one which gives the best opportunity to the child or young person to achieve his or her full potential. Guaranteeing the right to participate in and benefit from education is a necessary prerequisite to guaranteeing equality of opportunity generally for people with disabilities. It is in the public interest that young people with disabilities should leave school with the skills necessary to participate to the greatest extent possible in an integrated and inclusive way in the social and economic activities of Irish society and to live independent and fulfilled lives. We have come a long way in this whole area of integration and opportunity.</P>
    <P>Special education provision for a child or <Col N="359" /> young person with a disability should have particular regard to his or her particular disability and special educational needs. Parents have a right to be consulted at all stages of the development of programmes of education for their children and during the delivery of the programmes and to have their views respected. The education of children and young people with disabilities requires an eclectic, multi-agency, multi-disciplinary approach where the needs of the child or young person should be the paramount concern of all professionals and agencies. To the greatest extent practicable consistent with the needs of the child, the wishes of his or her parents, the efficient provision of an education for children with whom the child is to be educated and the efficient use of resources, education for a child with disabilities should be provided in an integrated setting in an ordinary school. School environments should be safe and should to the greatest extent practicable make accommodation for children and young people with disabilities. These facilities are included in the design of all modern developments and constructions now being authorised and proceeded with. The State is obliged as a matter of constitutional duty to provide resources to ensure children with disabilities receive at least the minimum education necessary to enable them to develop their potential.</P>
    <P>We want to provide for an independent mediation and appeals process to assist in the resolution of disputes about the education of children with special educational needs. The setting up of such a process will not, of course, infringe the rights of parents to bring matters before the courts if they wish. Our objective is that in the event of disagreement this Bill will provide parents with a faster, less onerous method of resolving disputes than that provided by the courts.</P>
    <P>I am fully aware that the recent judgment of the Supreme Court in the Sinnott case has caused much concern among some parents of children with disabilities. Some of this concern has been caused because the judgment has been either misrepresented to parents or misunderstood by them as undermining the rights to education of children with special needs. Nothing could be further from the truth as the court has, in effect, copperfastened their rights as first elaborated in 1993 in the O'Donoghue case. What the Supreme Court decision says is that the constitutional duty of the State to provide for primary education does not extend beyond the age of 18 years. That was the primary focus of that Supreme Court case. It was not the political wish to appeal that case. However, the primary legal advice available was that the State was obliged to appeal the case. We took that advice, went before the Supreme Court and the learned judges on the bench of the Supreme Court took a decision that this is where primary education should end. It is reasonable and fair that we should take that into account.</P>
    <P>Notwithstanding that, however, the State <Col N="360" /> through the health boards makes very substantial provision for the training and development of young people with disabilities who have left the school system. The fact that these services are not provided in primary schools, staffed by primary school teachers, does not take from the fact that a range of services are provided for adults with disabilities in settings appropriate to their ages, abilities and stage of personal development. These services are in no way jeopardised by the Supreme Court judgment. The challenge we all face is to develop and refine these services in line with best international practice. The Forum on Special Education will provide an opportunity for debate on how best to proceed and the outcome of these discussions will inform the future Education (Disabilities) Bill.</P>
    <P>Reference was made to the standard of primary education in Ireland. Senators will be aware that the Massachusetts Institute of Technology has decided to create MediaLab Europe in the centre of Dublin city, with which we are pleased.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JoeOToole" hpid="Mr. O'Toole Mr. O'Toole">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Toole</NameTxt>
      <P>Some of the universities are very displeased with that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="NoelTracey" hpid="Mr. Treacy Mr. Treacy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Treacy</NameTxt>
      <P>They may be. They were also displeased about Science Foundation Ireland.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeOToole" hpid="Mr. O'Toole Mr. O'Toole">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Toole</NameTxt>
      <P>I support the Minister of State on this.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="NoelTracey" hpid="Mr. Treacy Mr. Treacy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Treacy</NameTxt>
      <P>Competition is the life of trade and opportunity is created by those who are prepared to create a new environment for everyone so that the maximum input can be created for the great talent of our people, which is very important. The MIT did an assessment in eight countries in Europe on all facets of education. We scored very high on second level and third level but on primary level we were so far ahead of the rest in Europe that they took the decision to come here. That is a tribute to Irish education in all areas.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeOToole" hpid="Mr. O'Toole Mr. O'Toole">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Toole</NameTxt>
      <P>It is a tribute to Irish primary teachers.</P>
      <P>
        <i>(Interruptions.)</i>
      </P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator O'Toole will be called upon in due course.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="NoelTracey" hpid="Mr. Treacy Mr. Treacy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Treacy</NameTxt>
      <P>In response to Senator O'Toole, I was about to make the point that the grounding given to the youth of this nation at primary level stands us all through life and has stood to us over the years. It is that capacity at primary level which creates the opportunity for young people to embrace so successfully second level and third level education. We respect the contribution of primary teachers and thank them for that. We respect the contribution of second level teachers and also the outstanding academics in third level. Collectively we have a quality, rounded education system equal to any in the world, if not the best in the world.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="361" />
    <Speaker pid="JoeOToole" hpid="Mr. O'Toole Mr. O'Toole">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Toole</NameTxt>
      <P>We will shortly pay them for all that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="NoelTracey" hpid="Mr. Treacy Mr. Treacy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Treacy</NameTxt>
      <P>Since the appointment of Deputy Woods as Minister for Education and Science, he has attached particular priority to the special education area. We are pleased to have been associated with the major progress achieved in this area. It is the Minister's intention to continue to build on this progress and I am confident the measures I have outlined will provide the basis for a special education service of which we can all be proud in the years ahead.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. Ryan Mr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>When I meet parents of a child with special needs, why do they always tell me about all the problems they have? They are obviously living on a different planet from the Minister. There are no more problems and there are endless resources available so they must be making it up.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="NoelTracey" hpid="Mr. Treacy Mr. Treacy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Treacy</NameTxt>
      <P>I never used the word &ldquo;endless&rdquo;.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. Ryan Mr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>At the beginning of his speech, when contrasting the situation post-1998 with that which prevails currently, the Minister said that the level of support provided is dictated solely by the needs of the individual child. He did not qualify this by specifying an amount. Either the Minister is codding us or he thinks he knows what the child needs better than the parents. I do not believe he is foolish enough to believe the latter, therefore the former is obviously true and the Minister is having us on. The parents know that it is not true. Nobody disputes the education system is better than it used to be. The very first words of Senator O'Toole's motion are: &ldquo;that Seanad Éireann welcomes the substantial increase&rdquo;. What else could we expect in a country that is nearly 100% richer than it was six years ago? However, to pretend that we have somehow found a new and wondrous panacea, where all needs are met and all problems are solved, which is the effective implication of the Minister's speech, is to fly in the face of reality.</P>
      <P>I challenge my colleagues on the other side of the House to say they do not know parents of children with special needs who still have a long list of problems not being met. They know it is not true even though the Minister has said it is true. The Minister is making it up and the only way it can become true is by getting explicit recognition that services must be based on the right of people to have their needs met and a constitutional amendment is needed to recognise that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The Department of Finance is rigorously and resolutely opposed to a rights-based framework of support for people with disabilities generally. Given that hostility, it is clear that the Department of Finance will not tolerate anything that gives people rights to services based on needs exclusively. The Education Act does not say that, it merely states &ldquo;as far as is practicable&rdquo;. When <Col N="362" /> that Bill went through this House, in my innocence I debated with parents of children with special needs whether that was significant. When Fianna Fáil was in opposition, it had enormous fun at the expense of the then Minister, Niamh Bhreathnach, in a previous case. Members of that party were in paroxysms of anger about a proposed appeal to the Supreme Court that was not pursued because the then Minister withdrew it. Having got into a paroxysm about that, they suddenly discover when in government they have to do likewise.</P>
    <P>Governments do not have to do what the Attorney General advises them. He is not the managing director of the Government. He gives it his legal advice, and the experience of judicial reviews of advice from Attorneys General shows they are wrong almost as often as they are right. It is outrageous for any politician to hide behind the arguable and disputable advice of an Attorney General.</P>
    <Speaker pid="NoelTracey" hpid="Mr. Treacy Mr. Treacy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Treacy</NameTxt>
      <P>The Senator does not believe in advice.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. Ryan Mr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>I have no problem with advice and I take it from everybody. The Minister for Finance, with whom I do not agree but for whom I have a great affection, claims to take much advice but makes up his own mind. The Government did not make up its own mind, it ducked, ran away and hid behind legal advice.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="NoelTracey" hpid="Mr. Treacy Mr. Treacy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Treacy</NameTxt>
      <P>The Government makes up its mind on everything.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. Ryan Mr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>I could respect the Government if, having decided the High Court judgment was too broad-ranging, had too many implications and needed to be constrained by further interpretation, it therefore took responsibility and did that. That would have been a decision for which people take responsibility. I cannot accept the decision to run away, hide behind advice and blame somebody who is not accountable to anybody. The advice of the Attorney General is rarely published, but I cannot accept it is not possible to publish it because there is no precedent for doing so. There has been a succession of cases of this and previous Governments refusing to disclose advice given by the Attorney General.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="AnnOrmonde" hpid="Ms Ormonde Ms Ormonde">
      <NameTxt>Ms Ormonde</NameTxt>
      <P>What is the Senator talking about?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. Ryan Mr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>If Senator Ormonde does not know what I am talking about, she and I are not living on the same planet. I am talking about the fact that the Government put Kathryn Sinnott through an extraordinary rigmarole in the name of legal advice that it could easily have ignored. It would not take responsibility for its own decision, so hid behind the unpublished advice of the Attorney General and pretended it was the fault of somebody else. It does not do this when <Col N="363" /> good things happen, only when things happen that it does not like.</P>
      <P>Although the question of whether the amount involved is £500,000 or £3 million is important, the fundamental issue is whether we accept that the service for children with special needs is a matter of right or privilege. By digging under the Minister's rhetoric, it is clear that it is essentially a privilege. The Government will do as much as it can and what it can do depends on the resources that are available. The Government made decisions over where resources should go, and 60% of the expenditure in tax cuts and other forms of expenditure went to people in the top 30% of the income bracket.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="NoelTracey" hpid="Mr. Treacy Mr. Treacy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Treacy</NameTxt>
      <P>That is not true.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. Ryan Mr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>That is what the Combat Poverty Agency said</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="NoelTracey" hpid="Mr. Treacy Mr. Treacy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Treacy</NameTxt>
      <P>The socio-economic report&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator Ryan is in possession.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. Ryan Mr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>The clear priority of the Government was to give money to the top 30% of income earners who, like me, already had enough. This is the most cosseted and best looked after group in Irish society and it has been looked after by successive Governments. The Government had more resources than any other and decided to use them to look after those people. If it does that, it cannot give rights to people who are rarely in that income bracket and are the most vulnerable. That is why in 1937, Éamon de Valera recognised there was a plateau below which he would not let society descend and therefore instituted the principle of free primary education.</P>
      <P>One can argue both sides of the Supreme Court decision because it was asked to do something that should have been resolved through the political process. It was an appalling reactionary judgment in the language used and we may be in for a succession of reactionary judgments from what is becoming manifestly a reactionary Supreme Court determined to get away from the idea of enforcing rights and hand the job back to the Oireachtas. It did not have to go to the Supreme Court and I invite somebody in the Government to say that the principle of free primary education, which Éamon de Valera insisted on putting into the Constitution, has worked extremely well and what we need to do now is extend that right.</P>
      <P>This Government listens to advice and all the advice it gets is that we should not do this, but in a progressive society with a commitment to those who get lost in the competitive marketplace, the best way to do it is through a guarantee of basic rights and the best place to guarantee basic rights is not in law but in the Constitution&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="364" />
    <Speaker pid="DenisDinoCregan" hpid="Mr. D. Cregan Mr. D. Cregan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. D. Cregan</NameTxt>
      <P>The Constitution. That is correct.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. Ryan Mr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>&mdash;and there was not a mention of that in the Minister of State's contribution. That is why the parents I meet will not recognise the world of service the Minister of State described in his contribution.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LiamFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. L. Fitzgerald Mr. L. Fitzgerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. L. Fitzgerald</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator Ryan was true to form. From the moment he stood up to the moment he sat down, he did not make one positive reference to developments in the area of special needs education over the past number of years.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DenisDinoCregan" hpid="Mr. D. Cregan Mr. D. Cregan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. D. Cregan</NameTxt>
      <P>That is not fair. The Constitution is the answer.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LiamFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. L. Fitzgerald Mr. L. Fitzgerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. L. Fitzgerald</NameTxt>
      <P>I cannot recall one positive reference; perhaps I am wrong. He was typically true to form but I would be disappointed if he was inconsistent. The consistency of his negativism never fails to amaze me, but then again&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Will the Senator address the motion?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LiamFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. L. Fitzgerald Mr. L. Fitzgerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. L. Fitzgerald</NameTxt>
      <P>I am not inclined to personalise matters but since Senator Ryan has chosen to be the supreme legal arbiter of what is right and wrong in the courts of the land, I will leave that side to him. I want to talk about real people, pre-school and pre-teenage children and those children who have been neglected to a great extent over the years, but not in recent years.</P>
      <P>I welcome the motion tabled by Senator O'Toole. I was not surprised by his contribution because he has always been extremely constructive, in so far as he can, about what can be identified as the real issues in education. Nobody here could seriously quibble with the underlying principles he has articulated. They are laudable and they are at the heart of what we all want for those who have been targeted as children with special needs.</P>
      <P>Unfortunately, I cannot support Senator O'Toole's motion tonight because parts of the process he is proposing are wrong. They are certainly not parts I could support, although I endorse fully the underlying principle. Senator O'Toole, as distinct from other Senators, was gracious enough to acknowledge that significant improvements have been made in the provision of remedial and special educational services for children with special needs.</P>
      <P>Along with other speakers on this side of the House, including Senator Kett and Senator Ormonde as well as the Minister of State, I would be the first to admit that there have been serious examples of neglect and indifference in our education system in terms of the provisions that were needed for the education of special needs children over the years.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>One of the greatest challenges confronting the State, educational institutions, policy makers, <Col N="365" /> teachers and indeed parents has been the identification of appropriate educational programmes and the provision of appropriate places, whether integrated or otherwise, for children with mild, moderate, severe and profound mental handicap. I hope I will have an opportunity to comment on that in a moment. Our record in the area of physical handicap has gone from being reasonable to varying between good and excellent. Most people would concur with me on that. Specifically in the area of mental handicap, however, our record until recently has highlighted serious flaws and gaps and the Minister of State, Senator Kett and Senator Ormonde conceded that.</P>
    <P>Successive Irish Governments have had a good record in recent times, even by any international standards, in making provisions for the mild and the moderately mentally handicapped. We have come a long way from the chaotic days of the 1970s, and Senator O'Toole would remember that time well, when I had to deal with these problems at the coal face not a mile away from here. At that time children were assessed usually by the class teacher, who had no training or special expertise, as being slow learners who were unable to keep up with the mainstream class. They had some intellectual backwardness and were put to the back of the class, and untrained teachers had to cope with them as best they could. In the school where I taught we were fortunate to have a special class but invariably the special class teachers did not have the specialist training to deal with these children, but some kind of paltry effort was made to set them aside. Some people referred to that as segregation and that it was appalling but nevertheless some kind of specialist attention was given to them in smaller groups.</P>
    <P>There was no formal system to address child care needs in those days, and no formal recognition of the distinct educational needs of such children. That was due to ignorance. We were not able to identify the problem but we have come a long way since then in the provision of programmes and services for the mild and even moderately mentally handicapped, as well as the provision of specialist training for teachers. I realise it is not enough, and all the previous speakers adverted to that, but we have come a long way in the provision of specialist training for teachers. All schools now have access to remedial education, as Senator O'Toole knows, and I have to commend him for the major campaign he waged in ensuring that successive Ministers progressively came to that point. We now have remedial education, and thank God for it. It is not before its time and it should have been provided years earlier. Special classes are no longer provided on an <i>ad hoc</i> basis. There is a clear programme for the provision of special classes.</P>
    <P>Stated policy has always been that, to the maximum extent possible, children with special needs should be integrated in the local school, a policy that is becoming more and more popular. Little provision was made for such a stated policy. <Col N="366" /> In fact, there were isolated cases of children for whom there was no provision. They were identified as special cases by local teachers and they were in a terrible plight. They were isolated and at the mercy of a system which was not flexible enough to identify and meet their special needs requirements.</P>
    <P>We have come a long way and on the basis of the few examples I have given and the examples given by the Minister of State and my colleagues in the House, a considerable number of programmes have been put in place in ordinary schools and schools in disadvantaged areas. These include remedial education and classroom support, as I know well from teachers in my constituency, and the provision of a more structured and formal system of special education in terms of special classes and special schools.</P>
    <P>One of the terrible nightmares in Irish society and indeed in other modern democracies, and this was adverted to by previous speakers, has been the plight of the severe and profoundly mentally handicapped, and the plight of their parents and families. I want to tell a brief factual story which is an example of official attitudes to this problem in the early 1980s and how they failed to face up to a terrible dilemma. I first want to chart briefly recent significant progress in this area. A landmark development, and I will provide a relevant quote in a moment, in the provision of a package of measures for children with special needs was initiated in late 1998 with the launch of a £4 million package by the Minister's predecessor to specifically target and address decades of appalling neglect. That neglect was in no small way due to profound ignorance of what was required, and my story, if I get a chance to tell it, will illustrate that very poignantly. That was profound ignorance on the part of successive Governments of the needs of the severe and profoundly mentally handicapped.</P>
    <P>In the early 1980s, four Members of the other House, of which I was one &ndash; another is a senior member of the Opposition in this House &ndash; were approached by two families, one on the north side and one on the south side. They each had a six year old son deemed to be intellectually deficient and their cases had been written off by the Department of Education. One family was advised by a senior official in the Department at the time that the best advice he could give was that the six year old boy should be placed in private long-term psychiatric care, as the family financial resources would allow, in other words, put him into a mental institution. That was the solution offered by a senior specialist in the then Department of Education.</P>
    <P>Following a request by the parents, the four of us took up the case and met the then Minister of State, Donal Creed, who confronted his officials, overruled them and established a specialist unit. One of those children, who was being directed to a psychiatric institution, has a third level qualification and is living a full life and following a professional career. This illustrates how far we have <Col N="367" /> come from the ignominious, dark days of the 1980s and the preceding decades where, from a lack of knowledge and understanding, grew ignorance, arrogance, indifference and neglect of the plight of the most acutely needful of our special needs children.</P>
    <P>I commend the Minister of State for the disability education and training Bill he is to introduce. It will address the statutory rights of children with special needs. From my perspective in a different profession in the 1970s, the problem was one of access, which was impossible because of the lack of assessment. Ordinary teachers with no special training could not assess but were told to do so. The Minister made a commitment to the establishment of a huge cohort of additional psychologists to eliminate this bottleneck. In opening up assessment, accessibility will follow. That is a profound and significant development. There is a need to establish a multi-disciplinary team that will take a more holistic approach to this problem. I welcome recent developments and I commend the Minister of State.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JimGibbons" hpid="Mr. Gibbons Mr. Gibbons">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Gibbons</NameTxt>
      <P>It was especially interesting to note Senator Fitzgerald's reference to a person who today is leading a full life but who was condemned in the past. Senator O'Toole referred to young Mr. Brosnan and the situation in which he finds himself today. These cases are indicative of the difficulties in the area of special education and our difficulties in understanding the problems these people encounter.</P>
      <P>There are keys to everybody's problems and we must find the key to open the lock. Over the past 20 to 30 years special education has become immensely successful. It will always be underfunded because no matter how much it receives it could always do with more. However, that does not mean that it should get unlimited resources. That is not possible and there must be a degree of prioritisation.</P>
      <P>Early intervention is vital. There is a need to identify the problems, in so far as they can be categorised, and deal with them. A disturbing trend is that over the past 20 years those identified in mainstream education at a relatively young age as having a problem have been retained in the mainstream system to their detriment so that student numbers do not fall. This is done to retain teachers in mainstream schools. That must be addressed more sympathetically because, ultimately, such an approach means that a person identified as having special needs is denied services. It is wrong.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>My wife works in a special school and she points out that while it is easy to identify a Down's syndrome person because of the obvious visible symptoms, we know nothing about the many others who have problems. We cannot identify them and are, therefore, unable to decide what kind of special needs education they require. The greatest deficiency is our lack of knowledge in dealing with the problem. We must <Col N="368" /> continue to try to open the locks to a better understanding.</P>
    <P>FÁS workers employed as assistants in special schools were under the aegis of the Department of Enterprise, Trade and Employment but this function has been transferred to the Department of Education and Science, with the appropriate funding. However, unfortunately, the necessary administrative structures have not been established. It is a nonsense and it means that classrooms throughout the country will lose those who have been making a very significant contribution to the education of people with special needs. That is worse than hypocrisy, it is the height of stupidity. We should not allow these things to happen because, ultimately, we only every now and again get the opportunity to unlock the cage which encloses these people. If we put obstacles in our way, we go in the wrong direction.</P>
    <P>Great strides have been made in the area of special education. I commend the former Minister for Education and Science, Deputy Martin, who made an extraordinary contribution to this area. Ultimately, it is incumbent on us all to try to ensure that we open even one more lock.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JoeOToole" hpid="Mr. O'Toole Mr. O'Toole">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Toole</NameTxt>
      <P>I thank Senators for an informed and passionate debate. Whatever agreements or disagreements I have with the views expressed, I am pleased I moved the motion. This is an election issue and any Government or party that does not recognise that will pay a price.</P>
      <P>We have made a proposal to the Minister for Education and Science which solves a difficulty and pulls the wool over the eyes of the Department of Finance. The judgments in this area provide that the needs of children as assessed can be met. It means that in the area of special needs assistance the Minister for Education and Science can ignore the strictures of the Department of Finance.</P>
      <P>Senator Gibbons referred to those involved in the FÁS classroom scheme. Those involved are called classroom assistants or school aids. We have submitted to the Minister that a school's needs should be assessed as requiring special needs assistance which means that those involved on a temporary basis under a FÁS or CE scheme can be replaced by full-time special needs assistants, of whom there are 2,500. That is the answer to this problem. We strongly advocate it and would appreciate the support of the Government parties. The Department of Education and Science supports it and would be considerate in its approach.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>My motivation in moving this motion derives from what classroom teachers have told me about their difficulties. Those involved in the Irish Association of Teachers in Special Education, who are also members of the INTO, do extraordinary work, which is highly progressive and respected, in research and ensuring that we are aware of the special needs. They are talking about the lack of flexibility, the need for medical <Col N="369" /> backup and assessing children's needs in order to determine the resources which are necessary.</P>
    <P>I thank the Minister of State for coming to the House, for his speech and for the way he delivered it but, as Senator Ryan said, I feel like sending the speech to the parents who write to me week in and week out about the problems they are having with special education. There are problems on the ground and I know where. The Minister of State said, &ldquo;The State has a constitutional duty to provide the resources to ensure that children with disability receive at least the minimum education necessary to develop their potential.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="DenisDinoCregan" hpid="Mr. D. Cregan Mr. D. Cregan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. D. Cregan</NameTxt>
      <P>The minimum is all he is saying.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeOToole" hpid="Mr. O'Toole Mr. O'Toole">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Toole</NameTxt>
      <P>I agree with that. The Minister of State went on to tell me the Supreme Court says the constitutional duty of the State is to provide primary education, though not beyond the age of 18. The question is very simple. What happens when the State does not provide the minimum education and the person is too old, according to the Supreme Court, to receive primary education?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="AnnOrmonde" hpid="Ms Ormonde Ms Ormonde">
      <NameTxt>Ms Ormonde</NameTxt>
      <P>They will.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeOToole" hpid="Mr. O'Toole Mr. O'Toole">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Toole</NameTxt>
      <P>That is completely unacceptable and that is what is wrong. That is the gap that must be bridged. It is what happened in the Sinnot case and there is no gainsaying it. The Government was wrong to appeal the case. Everybody knows it. Nobody in education could support what went on and that is why I appeal to the Minister of State to recognise the issue.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="NoelTracey" hpid="Mr. Treacy Mr. Treacy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Treacy</NameTxt>
      <P>That is a job for the professionals.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeOToole" hpid="Mr. O'Toole Mr. O'Toole">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Toole</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator Ryan said there should be a constitutional amendment and I am certain that de Valera, whatever his faults, never intended&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="NoelTracey" hpid="Mr. Treacy Mr. Treacy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Treacy</NameTxt>
      <P>He did not have any.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="370" />
    <Speaker pid="JoeOToole" hpid="Mr. O'Toole Mr. O'Toole">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Toole</NameTxt>
      <P>&mdash;primary education to mean anything other than fundamental basic education as outlined in the UN Convention on the Rights of the Child, which Charles Haughey signed in New York in the early 1990s. That is the reality.</P>
      <P>As long as that gap exists it can be filled in two ways. It can be filled by a constitutional amendment where we define what we mean by &ldquo;primary education&rdquo; as &ldquo;fundamental education&rdquo;, whatever the age. Otherwise we can legislate to ensure that never again will a family have to go through what the Sinnot family did. It was wrong and we know it. There is very little in the debate tonight which divides us. Every proposal I made has been dealt with by someone or other on the Government side. The putting down of amendments could have been done with a scalpel rather than a blunderbuss. There was no reason not to welcome the things I welcomed. They were mentioned in the Minister of State's speech. There was no reason not to denounce a system which compels parents to go to the courts to obtain rights for their children and in his speech the Minister of State agreed that it should not happen.</P>
      <P>I proposed that the Minister recognise the right of all citizens to get the education they need and that was also agreed in the speeches tonight. I also mentioned training. I could go through all of my proposals and the Minister of State mentioned them all. He could have come through with all of them. If there was an issue of contention he could have identified it and we could have had the war on that one issue. Nobody did that. It was there to be discussed, but it was not.</P>
      <P>I am glad I put down this motion. I am delighted with the level of debate and its comprehensive nature. I appeal once more to the Government side to withdraw its amendment and we would graciously, with the leave of the House, accept that withdrawal. We could then walk out of here with one voice supporting those in our society who have special needs. They need our constant support.</P>
      <P>Amendment put.</P>
      <P>Tá</P>
      <P>
      </P>
    </Speaker>
    <table pgwide="1">
      <tgroup cols="3">
        <colspec colname="1" colnum="1" colwidth="49*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <colspec colname="2" colnum="2" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <colspec colname="3" colnum="3" colwidth="1*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry rowsep="1">Bohan, Eddie.<br />Bonner, Enda.<br />Cox, Margaret.<br />Cregan, John<br />Farrell, Willie.<br />Finneran, Michael.<br />Fitzgerald, Liam.<br />Fitzgerald, Tom.<br />Fitzpatrick, Dermot.<br />Gibbons, Jim.<br />Glennon, Jim.<br />Glynn, Camillus.<br />Kett, Tony.</entry>
            <entry rowsep="1">Kiely, Daniel.<br />Kiely, Rory.<br />Leonard, Ann.<br />Lydon, Don.<br />Mooney, Paschal.<br />Moylan, Pat.<br />O'Brien, Francis.<br />Ó Fearghail, Seán.<br />Ó Murchú, Labhrás.<br />Ormonde, Ann.<br />Quill, Máirín.<br />Walsh, Jim.<br /><br /></entry>
            <entry rowsep="1">
              <Col N="371" />
            </entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
    <P Just="Center">Níl</P>
    <table pgwide="1">
      <tgroup cols="2">
        <colspec colname="1" colnum="1" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <colspec colname="2" colnum="2" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry rowsep="1">Burke, Paddy.<br />Coghlan, Paul.<br />Connor, John.<br />Coogan, Fintan.<br />Costello, Joe.<br />Cregan, Denis (Dino).<br />Henry, Mary.<br />Jackman, Mary.</entry>
            <entry rowsep="1">
              <Col N="372" />Keogh, Helen.<br />Manning, Maurice.<br />Norris, David.<br />O'Toole, Joe.<br />Ross, Shane.<br />Ryan, Brendan.<br />Taylor-Quinn, Madeleine.<br /></entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
    <P Just="Center">Tellers: Tá, Senators T. Fitzgerald and Gibbons; Níl, Senators O'Toole and Ryan.</P>
    <P>Amendment declared carried.</P>
    <P>Motion, as amended, put and declared carried.</P>
    <Speaker pid="BrianMullooly" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>When is it proposed to sit again?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TomFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. T. Fitzgerald Mr. T. Fitzgerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. T. Fitzgerald</NameTxt>
      <P>At 10.30 a.m. tomorrow.</P>
      <P>
      </P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Adjournment Matters. -" RHead="Water and Sewerage Schemes">
    <Title>Adjournment Matters. - Water and Sewerage Schemes.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="CamillusGlynn" hpid="Mr. Glynn Mr. Glynn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Glynn</NameTxt>
      <P>Cuirim fáilte roimh an Aire Stáit. The matter I wish to raise concerns the need for the Minister for the Environment and Local Government to approve the application of Westmeath County Council for an extension to the Killucan-Rathwire and Rochfortbridge sewerage schemes. The schemes are in two different locations. The villages of Killucan and Rathwire are almost connected but they have separate identities. A sewerage scheme was installed in Killucan and Rathwire in the 1980s to cater for 600 people. Given the enormous development which has taken place, especially in Rathwire, the sewage treatment plant reached capacity two years ago at least and it is necessary to increase its capacity. Perhaps the Minister will consider this matter favourably. I am very <i>au fait</i> with the area because Rathwire is the village where I went to school. Many members of my late brother's family still live there, one of whom is in business in the village.</P>
      <P>Westmeath County Council has applied for an increase in the capacity of the scheme to cater for a population of 2,000. The scheme was originally designed for a population of 600 and that was reached two years ago at least. I would not like to regard Rochfortbridge as a village because it is a small town which has seen extensive development and is on the main N6 thoroughfare. A number of developers, some local, are encountering great difficulty in obtaining planning permission from Westmeath County Council because the sewerage plant has reached capacity.</P>
      <P>I know the Department has indicated in all such situations that funding could be forthcoming under the serviced land initiative scheme and that perhaps that is the way forward in this regard. I do not suggest that is unacceptable to the councillors from the Kilbeggan electoral area in which Rochfortbridge is located, but I would be grateful if the Minister and the Department of the Environment and Local Government could see their way to funding an extension to both sewerage schemes. I have made the case and I appeal to the Minister present to be as positive as he can in response.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TomMoffatt" hpid="Dr. Moffatt Dr. Moffatt">
      <NameTxt>Minister of State at the Department of Health and Children (Dr. Moffatt)</NameTxt>
      <P>I thank Senator Glynn for raising the issue on the Adjournment. The remarkable social and economic growth of recent years has been reflected in a corresponding expansion of the water services investment programme. The provision of modern environmental infrastructure to support economic objectives has been a major focus of Government investment over the past four and a half years. Total planned spending on water services infrastructure over the period of the national development plan amounts to almost £3 billion. This investment is aimed at supporting economic and social development, employment generation and the achievement of high environmental standards.</P>
      <P>The additional water production capacity created during last year alone equalled the average daily requirements of a population equivalent to 309,000 persons. This represented in one year 36% of the corresponding figure for the entire 1994 to 1999 period. The increase in waste water treatment capacity last year represented a population equivalent to 180,000, almost half the entire increase for the 1994 to 1999 period.</P>
      <P>Funding is being provided for new water services projects in every county. The total investment proposed for County Westmeath under the first phase of the programme amounts to just more than £52 million in respect of 14 schemes. Approximately two thirds of this, more than £34 million, is in respect of four large schemes which will deal with water supplies to serve Mullingar and south Westmeath, including Athlone, and sewerage schemes for both Mullingar and Athlone. Major schemes will be added in future as the programme is progressively rolled forward to the end of the national development plan.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The current water services investment programme for Westmeath takes into account the list of water and sewerage schemes submitted by Westmeath County Council in response to the request from the Department of the Environment and Local Government to local authorities to undertake a fresh assessment of the needs for capital works in their areas and to prioritise their proposals on the basis of the assessments. The <Col N="373" /> upgrading of waste water treatment plants at Killucan-Rathwire and Rochfortbridge were included in Westmeath's assessment. However, given the level of competing national demand, the funding available and the absence of clear prioritisation by the county council of these projects, it was not possible to include them in the programme at that time.</P>
    <P>A separate proposal for a sewerage scheme for Rochfortbridge was submitted for consideration by Westmeath County Council in an early round of the serviced land initiative but was not approved because the scale of the project envisaged was not considered to be justified. No further proposal has been received from the council but we will be prepared to look at any revised plans that offer additional justification for the proposed scale of the project.</P>
    <P>Killucan-Rathwire was included with a number of other schemes in a more recent application submitted to my Department by Westmeath County Council under the serviced land initiative. Again, the scale of the project envisaged did not appear to be fully justified. Consequently, on 19 September last the council was asked to review the scale of the proposals for Killucan-Rathwire and a number of other villages mentioned in the submission. A meeting was subsequently held between officials of the Department of the Environment and Local Government and the council to discuss these proposed schemes. The council has agreed to submit revised proposals in respect of Killucan-Rathwire and these will be dealt with as soon as they are received.</P>
    <Speaker pid="CamillusGlynn" hpid="Mr. Glynn Mr. Glynn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Glynn</NameTxt>
      <P>The revised scheme for Killucan-Rathwire will be lodged with the Department within the next week.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Adjournment Matters. - School" RHead="Staffing and Accommodation">
    <Title>Adjournment Matters. - School Staffing and Accommodation.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelFinneranFF" hpid="Mr. Finneran Mr. Finneran">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Finneran</NameTxt>
      <P>I welcome the Minister of State, Deputy Moffatt, to the House. I wish to raise the need for the Minister for Education and Science to sanction as a matter of urgency the provision of extra accommodation and the appointment of an extra teacher at Fuerty national school, County Roscommon, roll number 18194P.</P>
      <P>I am disappointed the Minister is not present as this is a very important matter and something the manager and board of management have tried to resolve over a period and on which my office has made many representations. The mood of the board of management and parents is not complimentary of the Department. The visit by the inspector in recent weeks was not of benefit in terms of the request lodged with the Department.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I will outline the case briefly. The school has recently reached an enrolment of 82 pupils. It is a small, overcrowded, three teacher school. The general view of the board of management and myself is that it merits a fourth teacher. The division of classes between the three rooms leaves little room for movement. Computers and tele<Col N="374" /> visions compete for space and, in the interests of hygiene, safety and ventilation, an enlarged area is urgently needed in the school.</P>
    <P>I will give a breakdown of what these people must endure. There are 31 pupils in the senior room and they have an area of 420 sq. ft. Taking into account the teacher's table and the presses, computer, television trolley and so on, they are left with 355 sq. ft. for 31 pupils plus a teacher. That is surely not acceptable in these times. The middle room has 29 pupils and they also have a space of 355 sq. ft. when the area for the teacher's table and other equipment is discounted. The main infant room, which has 22 pupils, is 400 sq. ft. when the furniture is taken into consideration.</P>
    <P>This is unacceptable and the school would clearly benefit from a fourth teacher. It is entitled to one in September 2002, but it clearly needs one now. It would allow the bulging classrooms to be fit into four divisions. The board of management, the principal and the teachers have come forward with a proposal. They have said the 14 junior infants and eight senior infants would make one group of 22. First and second class would have 19 pupils; third and fourth class would also have 19 pupils and the last group would also have 22 pupils. It would be impossible to deal with this situation without a fourth teacher. There is a case for a fourth teacher and that teacher should be put in place now.</P>
    <P>The school itself had an increase in pupil numbers of 19% from outside the parish this year. It is a growing area and it now expects to enrol 48 local children in the next four years. The school has done its homework and has an excellent case. The inspector called recently and spoke about two prefabs and classroom and a principal's office sometime in the future. That is of no value and is unacceptable. I wish to make a strong case for this school tonight. I intend to pursue the matter if there is not an adequate response. The matter will remain on the agenda because I have a mandate from the parents and board of management and I will raise this at every opportunity.</P>
    <P>The Minister needs to make his officials aware of the situation in the school. The current overcrowded condition would clearly break fire and other regulations. It is not acceptable. I trust there will be some response from the Department. I will not be satisfied if the matter is put on the long finger until 2002 or with being told that there is a large burden on the Department. The simple fact is that Fuerty national school has children in overcrowded conditions where they cannot be taught properly. On their behalf I demand proper treatment and facilities.</P>
    <Speaker pid="TomMoffatt" hpid="Dr. Moffatt Dr. Moffatt">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Moffatt</NameTxt>
      <P>I thank Senator Finneran for raising this matter. The Minister for Education and Science, Deputy Woods, regrets that he cannot be here.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I am glad the Senator has given me the opportunity of outlining to the House the Department of Education and Science's current position regarding the provision of improved accommo<Col N="375" /> dation and the appointment of an extra teacher at Fuerty national school. The school's present facilities consist of three permanent classrooms in the main school building and a converted cloakroom houses the remedial and resource teachers.</P>
    <P>I am pleased to inform the House that over the past two years the Department approved grant aid for capital works to the school which included a new roof and the replacement of windows, doors and boiler. The Department of Education and Science has received an application for grant aid towards the cost of upgrading the school.</P>
    <P>The Senator will appreciate that there has been a massive and unprecedented increase in the funds allocated by this Government to the schools building programme at all levels. There are currently more than 850 major school building projects at various stages of planning. Decisions relating to the rate of progress to construction of these projects, including Fuerty national school, will be taken in the light of the allocations to be made for school buildings purposes in the forthcoming Estimates.</P>
    <P>In regard to the appointment of an extra teacher, the staffing of a primary school is determined by reference to the enrolment of the school on 30 September of the previous school year. The actual number of mainstream posts sanctioned is determined by reference to a staffing schedule and is finalised for a particular year following discussions with the education partners.</P>
    <P>The enrolment of the school on 30 September 2000 was 68 pupils which warrants a staffing for the 2001-02 school year of a principal and two mainstream class teachers. The only criterion by which a school may possibly gain an additional teacher post, apart from numbers as determined by reference to the enrolment on 30 September for the previous year, is developing school status.</P>
    <P>The developing school criteria for the 2001-02 school year is outlined in circular letter 12/2001, a copy of which the board of management of the school has received. To satisfy the criteria as outlined in the circular letter, the enrolment of Fuerty national school on 30 September 2001 would need to have increased by at least 25 pupils over the number enrolled on 30 September 2000. Accordingly the school would require an enrolment of at least 93 pupils on 30 September 2001.</P>
    <P>As the enrolment on 30 September 2001 according to data received from the board was only 82 pupils, an additional mainstream class teacher cannot be sanctioned for the 2001-02 school year. In addition the school has the services of a learning support teacher. If the enrolment of 82 pupils on 30 September 2001 is valid, the board of management on the basis of the existing staffing schedule would be entitled to appoint an additional mainstream class teacher from the 1 September 2002.</P>
    <P>The Department of Education and Science has requested an inspector to visit the school and to examine the overall situation regarding the enrolment of pupils, including the transfer of pupils <Col N="376" /> from other schools. The Department will be in contact with the board of management when the report is received.</P>
    <P>I have taken on board the Senator's request to have progress made on this matter.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Adjournment Matters. -" RHead="Human Gene Patenting">
    <Title>Adjournment Matters. - Human Gene Patenting.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="MaryHenry" hpid="Dr. Henry Dr. Henry">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Henry</NameTxt>
      <P>I have agreed to share time with Senator Hayes. I am delighted this Minister is here tonight because I know he will have an understanding of the matter I put forward.</P>
      <P>The issue of human gene patenting is of the greatest importance to women with breast or ovarian cancer in Ireland and to research here into the genetic basis of cancer. Test kits are permitted to be made solely by the company which holds the patent even though it may not be the most suitable test, nor the least expensive.</P>
      <P>Patenting of gene sequences has been possible in the United States of America for many years. In June 1998, after ten years of discussion, the European Parliament and Council adopted a directive for the legal protection of biotechnological inventions and all EU countries enacted laws to comply with it. The directive does not substantially alter existing patent laws which state that patents can only be obtained for advances which meet the three basic requirements of patentability &ndash; they must be new, not obvious and must have an industrial application.</P>
      <P>The directive makes clear certain processes cannot be patented on the grounds that their commercial exploitation would be contrary to morality, for example, the cloning of human beings or the commercial use of human embryos. The directive requires that patents are not obtainable for genes or other body parts in their natural state but inventions concerning isolated genes which are identical to those found in nature are not prevented from obtaining patent rights, but they must satisfy the three conditions for patentability.</P>
      <P>The directive is being interpreted by biotechnology and pharmaceutical companies and by the European Patent Office as allowing genes to be patented as they must be isolated before they can be sequenced. Many scientists, both in research and health care, object to this, feeling it to be contrary to the principles of natural justice and a distortion of the purpose of patent law &ndash; genes were there before the researchers.</P>
      <P>Matters have come to a head with an EU patent, EP 0699754B1, being granted to Myriad Genetics, Salt Lake City, USA, on the use of sequences from the BRCA1 gene, a most important gene in the diagnosis of hereditary breast and ovarian cancer. The patent enables Myriad Genetics to demand that a major part of the genetic tests for European women with an enhanced risk of hereditary breast and ovarian cancer be done in Salt Lake City. Some of the most important work in this area was done here in Dublin, in St. James's Hospital.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Geneticists object to extracting these analyses <Col N="377" /> from the European health care systems where genetic tests are performed on a non-profit basis and in close collaboration with the clinicians involved in treating the patients. Also, it will deprive European laboratories of the possibility of implementing improved technologies, which is an important part of molecular genetics world-wide. This is most important for us with our burgeoning biotechnology industry. The Myriad method is sensitive for the detection of subtle gene sequence changes but not suitable for the detection of large deletions which are a common feature in BRCA 1 genes in Europe. In the Netherlands, for example, it is suspected that it will not be suitable for about 25% of cases.</P>
    <P>Opposition to the granting of the EU patent to Myriad has been lodged in the EU Patent Office by the French and Swiss governments and the genetic societies of the Netherlands, Belgium, the United Kingdom, Germany and Denmark. On 4 October the European Parliament adopted a resolution against EP0699754b1 and decided to file its opposition, that is, against its own directive. Ireland should immediately join this opposition. Genetic testing is carried out here in a comprehensive medical genetics centre, where the skills of scientists and clinicians are combined and reinforced, which is what is best, and testing is provided free of charge.</P>
    <P>Breast cancer is a common condition in Ireland. The cost to the country will be enormous if all tests have to be done in Salt Lake City, from £150,000 to £300,000 per annum, and the tests may not be those which are needed most. Counselling of patients cannot be guaranteed if all the tests are sent abroad.</P>
    <P>There is a growing awareness that clinical medicine and research in genetics will not benefit from granting exclusive rights for testing to one commercial company. The differences between health care in the United States and Europe should be recognised and Ireland should join the opposition to the granting of this patent at once.</P>
    <Speaker pid="DrMauriceHayes" hpid="Dr. M. Hayes Dr. M. Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Dr. M. Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>I thank Senator Henry for sharing her time and support what she said. I do not intend to follow her into the underworld of genetics in which she is more expert than anyone else in the House. We should be grateful to her for calling our attention to this. It is part of a wider question about the patenting of medicine and the return that people get on their research. A side effect is to deprive people in poorer countries of the medicine they need so that countries like Argentina and South Africa had to break the rules.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>It is serious for us because some of the best work on this subject is done in hospitals in Belfast and Dublin. The close link between research, clinical practice and analysis is the key to advances being made and to be made in cancer care. Although money is important, the threat to clinical practice and the possibilities for advance in Ireland and Europe are more serious in the long-term. Other countries see the danger, and I <Col N="378" /> suggest to the Minister of State that if the United Kingdom, France and other countries think it important for the interests of patients, health service and future research into cancer to contest this, then Ireland should join them. I support Senator Henry's plea and congratulate her on bringing it to our attention.</P>
    <Speaker pid="TomMoffatt" hpid="Dr. Moffatt Dr. Moffatt">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Moffatt</NameTxt>
      <P>I thank the Senators for raising this matter on the Adjournment of the House and for giving me this opportunity on behalf of my colleague, the Minister for Health and Children, Deputy Martin, to set out the current position on the development of services in cancer genetics, both at European and national level.</P>
      <P>Patenting of gene sequences has been possible in the United States for many years. However, a moratorium on gene patenting has until recently been in force in Europe. The EC Directive on the Legal Protection of Biotechnological Inventions (98/44/EC) was adopted by the European Parliament in July 1998 after more than a decade of negotiations between member states in the Council of Ministers, the European Commission and the European Parliament. The directive's purpose is to harmonise the member states' national patent laws concerning biotechnological inventions. It obliged all members states to ensure that by 30 July 2000 their national patent laws were consistent with the terms of the directive and Ireland implemented the necessary statutory instrument on 28 July 2000. The European Patent Office altered its implementing regulations in June 1999 to put the directive into effect, so that new applications for patents are now subject to the rules contained in it.</P>
      <P>This directive does not substantially alter existing law which states that patents can only be obtained for advances which meet the three basic requirements for patentability, that is, they must be new, not obvious and have an industrial application. It requires that patents are not obtainable for genes or other body parts in their natural state. However, inventions concerning isolated genes which are identical to those found in nature are not prevented from obtaining patent rights. The interpretation of the directive is complex and has been the subject of court action at European level, but the interpretation being placed on the directive by biotechnology and pharmaceutical companies and by the European Patent Office is that genes are now patentable in the EU, as they must be isolated before they can be sequenced.</P>
      <P>Shortly after the directive was passed, the Dutch government appealed to the European Court of Justice following a vote by the Parliament of the Netherlands against its adoption. The Netherlands' challenge was supported by Norway and Italy. The case was heard by the court on 13 February 2001, and on 9 October 2001 the court dismissed the application.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>With regard to the case mentioned by the Senator, I understand that, on 4 October last, the European Parliament adopted a resolution against EP0699754 B1, the patent granted to Myr<Col N="379" /> iad Genetics, Salt Lake City, USA, on the use of sequences from the BRCA1 (breast cancer) gene and decided to file its own opposition. The patent has also been the subject of opposition by interested parties in a number of member states.</P>
    <P>Genetic research is a very exciting area with the potential to revolutionise medicine and health care. In the past ten years, there have been significant advances in our understanding of cancer genetics in particular. The chief medical officer of the Department of Health and Children has requested the national cancer forum to examine the issue of genetics and to report back on how the forum should develop and support services in cancer genetics in the country. In the course of its investigations, the forum will also consider all developments in this area at European and inter<Col N="380" /> national level and advise on the most appropriate response. In this context, I will ask the forum to take account of the case referred to by the Senator during the course of its deliberations. It is a complex area and I take on board what was said here this evening.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MaryHenry" hpid="Dr. Henry Dr. Henry">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Henry</NameTxt>
      <P>I am disappointed in the reply. There is no sense of urgency. We are at the forefront of genetics, but Irish research workers will be disadvantaged and Irish patients will suffer. I hope that Senator Hayes will press the case in Belfast and urge that the more active United Kingdom approach is supported there where splendid work in this area is done.</P>
      <P>The Seanad adjourned at 8.30 p.m. until 10.30 a.m. on Thursday, 18 October 2001.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
</Debate>