<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE Debate SYSTEM "../Debate.dtd"[]>
<Debate DocTitle="Seanad Debate" Day="Tue" Date="1" Month="May" Year="2001" Vol="166" No="7" DateIrish="Dé Máirt, 1 Bealtaine 2001" DateEnglish="Tuesday, 1 May 2001" House="S" CommitteeEng="" CommitteeIr="" SubNameEng="" cnum="0">
  <MainHeading Type="Prelude" LHead="" RHead="">
    <Title>
    </Title>
    <P Just="Center">
      <Col N="521" /> Chuaigh an Cathaoirleach i gceannas ar 2.30 p.m.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Business" RHead="of Seanad">
    <Title>Business of Seanad.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="BrianMullooly" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I have received notice from Senator Glennon that, on the motion for the Adjournment of the House today, he proposes to raise the following matter:</P>
      <P>The need for the Minister for Defence to commission a comprehensive feasibility study as to the potential development of the existing military facility at Gormanston Aerodrome for conversion to a civil aviation facility prior to a final decision being taken on the aerodrome's future.</P>
      <P>I have also received notice from Senator Costello of the following matter:</P>
      <P>The need for the Minister for Education and Science to provide funding for the refurbishment of St. Peter's national school, Phibsboro, as a matter of urgency.</P>
      <P>I have also received notice from Senator Finneran of the following matter:</P>
      <P>The need for the Minister for the Environment and Local Government to include the N5 national primary route in the national development plan and to upgrade the N5 from Longford to Charlestown.</P>
      <P>I regard the matters raised by the Senators as suitable for discussion on the Adjournment. I have selected Senator Glennon's and Senator Costello's matters and they will be taken at the conclusion of business. Senator Finneran may give notice on another day of the matter he wishes to raise.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Order of" RHead="Business">
    <Title>Order of Business.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="DonnieCassidyFF" hpid="Mr. Cassidy Mr. Cassidy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cassidy</NameTxt>
      <P>The Order of Business for today is No. 1, the Twenty-first Amendment of the Constitution (No. 2) Bill, 2001 &ndash; all Stages, with the contributions of spokespersons not to exceed 20 minutes and those of other Senators not to exceed 15 minutes, and on which Senators may share time; No. 2, motion re information to be <Col N="522" /> issued to voters in connection with the referendum on No. 1, to be debated in conjunction with Second Stage of No. 1; No. 3, motion re the Referendum (Ballot Paper) Order, 2001, to be taken without debate; No. 4, the Twenty-third Amendment of the Constitution Bill, 2001 &ndash; Second Stage, with contributions of spokespersons not to exceed 20 minutes and those of other Senators not to exceed 15 minutes, and on which Senators may share time; and No. 5, motion re information to be issued to voters in connection with the referendum on No. 4, to be debated in conjunction with Second Stage of No. 4.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MadeleineTaylorQuinn" hpid="Mrs. Taylor-Quinn Mrs. Taylor-Quinn">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Taylor-Quinn</NameTxt>
      <P>We agree to the Order of Business. Will the Leader arrange a discussion on the archival reports on the Arms Trial of 1970 and the need&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BrianMullooly" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I understand that matter is to be taken as Private Members' Business tomorrow and I do not wish the debate to be pre-empted on the Order of Business.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MadeleineTaylorQuinn" hpid="Mrs. Taylor-Quinn Mrs. Taylor-Quinn">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Taylor-Quinn</NameTxt>
      <P>I hope the Leader conveys to the Government the need for a full inquiry and investigation into the matter to resolve it once and for all.</P>
      <P>Will the Leader invite the Taoiseach to the House for a full debate on the proposed national stadium? It is important there is a full and open debate on this issue given the huge expenditure proposed. It is also important there is full clarification of the cost and other details. It is a public matter of national importance which needs to be debated in the House with the Taoiseach. Will the Leader convey to him the request of the House for his attendance at a full and open debate on the issue?</P>
      <P>A health report was issued today, a copy of which I understand none of us has received. The report is of great concern because it indicates clearly that there is a greater possibility of people in urban areas developing cancer than those in rural areas and that there is also a greater possibility of males dying prior to 74 than females. This is a matter which should be debated openly and fully. Preventative action needs to be taken.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeOToole" hpid="Mr. O'Toole Mr. O'Toole">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Toole</NameTxt>
      <P>A huge question has been raised in the past few days about the power of the Oireachtas because it has been subject to extraordinary levels of criticism by the legal profession. It is important that Members of the Oireachtas assert their right to conduct their business in line with the laws of the Oireachtas. It would help if we had a debate to indicate, explore and outline the power of the Oireachtas. It is clear that, in terms of issues such as Abbeylara &ndash; I will not speak on that specific issue &ndash; the general principle governing the conduct of our business is that it is done clearly in line with the law, and this principle applies to the operation of <Col N="523" /> any committees of the Houses which come under the most minute scrutiny.</P>
      <P>It is unacceptable to allow criticism by members of the legal profession to go unchallenged and without reply in some shape or form. There is no understanding generally about the work of committees of the Houses, such as the compellability committee, and the legal advice available which ensure everyone's rights are monitored, maintained and protected while at the same time the Oireachtas conducts its business.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeCostelloLAB" hpid="Mr. Costello Mr. Costello">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Costello</NameTxt>
      <P>May Day provides a good opportunity to reflect on the country's priorities. The Seanad should mark this occasion with a debate on the uses of the benefits of economic prosperity, the distribution of wealth, homelessness and health problems. The test of a society is how ordinary people benefit from its prosperity. We must also ensure good Government during good times. Will the Leader arrange for a May Day debate to discuss these matters?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnDardis" hpid="Mr. Dardis Mr. Dardis">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dardis</NameTxt>
      <P>Let the anarchists in.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeCostelloLAB" hpid="Mr. Costello Mr. Costello">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Costello</NameTxt>
      <P>The report on cancer to which Senator Tayor-Quinn has referred contains the alarming fact that one third of the population will have contracted this disease by the age of 74. There is a shortage of facilities to carry out operations on patients suffering from cancer. We must direct the benefits of our economic prosperity towards those most in need of them.</P>
      <P>The Taoiseach should come to the House to debate the question of Stadium Ireland, a project which is his brainchild. The House should have the opportunity of examining and listening to the arguments in favour of this £1 billion project. The questions of Stadium Ireland and cancer services fit into the wider context of a May Day debate on our priorities during this period of economic prosperity.</P>
      <P>I agree with the point made by Senator O'Toole regarding the conduct of its business by the Houses of the Oireachtas. The House should be concerned if a committee is prevented from carrying out the business it is directed to do by the Oireachtas. The Houses of the Oireachtas are the proper vehicle for examining matters of this nature which are of serious concern.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnCreganFF" hpid="Mr. J. Cregan Mr. J. Cregan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J. Cregan</NameTxt>
      <P>The pupils of two national schools in Rathkeale, County Limerick, were withdrawn by their parents this morning because of the policy of the Department of Education and Science regarding age appropriate integration. Will the Leader ask the Minister for Education and Science to bring forward his new proposals at the earliest possible date and to consult with the parents and teachers in Rathkeale to resolve this matter urgently?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThereseRidge" hpid="Mrs. Ridge Mrs. Ridge">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Ridge</NameTxt>
      <P>I ask the Leader to arrange for a debate on teenage drinking. Confirmation used <Col N="524" /> to be an occasion for children to take a pledge, not to drink. It now seems to be the occasion when they begin to drink, even at that young age. The problem is out of hand and a debate is called for. We must decide if we are to do something about the problem or, as usual, wring our hands and say nothing can be done. I know this subject is close to the Leader's heart and while that would never determine his priorities I hope this debate will be held very soon.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryHenry" hpid="Dr. Henry Dr. Henry">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Henry</NameTxt>
      <P>Will the Leader ask the Minister for Finance to come to the House to discuss the health services? The Minister for Health and Children is well aware of these problems. Important projects and the employment of personnel are constantly vetoed by the Department of Finance after they have been accepted by the Department of Health and Children. The recent manpower forum report was accepted by the Minister for Health and then vetoed by the Department of Finance. I can list projects throughout the country which were refused permission by the Department of Finance rather than the Department of Health.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelFinneranFF" hpid="Mr. Finneran Mr. Finneran">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Finneran</NameTxt>
      <P>Will the Leader of the House allow a debate on the recent Ombudsman's report? I understand there are some controversial sections in the report, particularly where it relates to local authorities, which play a major part in the election of Members to this House. It is important to take this opportunity to have a debate.</P>
      <P>We should convey our congratulations to the Minister for Agriculture, Food and Rural Development and his officials in the Department for the excellent work they have done in recent months in preventing foot and mouth disease from becoming widespread. The country owes a debt of gratitude to the Minister, Deputy Joe Walsh, and his officials, the Garda, the Army and all others involved in this national operation.</P>
      <P>I welcome the opportunity for a debate on Stadium Ireland. It is important that we do so in order to put to bed some of the myths regarding it. It might also expose the divergence of opinion evident in the Labour Party. Last night a Labour Party spokesman said he is in favour of it. There is a revolt in the Fine Gael parliamentary party against their present leader over this issue.</P>
      <P>
        <i>(Interruptions.)</i>
      </P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelFinneranFF" hpid="Mr. Finneran Mr. Finneran">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Finneran</NameTxt>
      <P>Maybe a debate will sort out some of the difficulties which the Opposition has. There is no difficulty with this issue on the Government side.</P>
      <P>
        <i>(Interruptions.)</i>
      </P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BrianMullooly" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Order please.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelFinneranFF" hpid="Mr. Finneran Mr. Finneran">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Finneran</NameTxt>
      <P>It is in the best interests of this country. The people are totally in support of this project.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="525" />
    <Speaker pid="HelenKeogh" hpid="Ms Keogh Ms Keogh">
      <NameTxt>Ms Keogh</NameTxt>
      <P>Will the Leader indicate when legislation will be introduced vindicating the rights of people with disabilities, particularly in view of the horrific experiences of disabled people travelling by rail and the appalling conditions they are put in? This is utterly disgraceful. The spokesperson for the disabled people involved referred to the vast amount of money which is allegedly being put into this stadium. I would prefer to see that kind of funding going towards people who really need it now.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PaschalMooney" hpid="Mr. Mooney Mr. Mooney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Mooney</NameTxt>
      <P>If the Senator was listening to the news today she would have heard that Iarnród Eireann has spent money on new carriages. The Senator is behind the times.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ShaneRoss" hpid="Mr. Ross Mr. Ross">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Ross</NameTxt>
      <P>I support the request from Senators Finneran and Keogh to have a debate on the so-called Bertie Bowl. It tells us something about our national priorities. Senator Keogh was trying to say, with some justification, that maybe we have our priorities wrong and should be spending more money on health and less on sport. I do not know the answer to that issue, but this is a matter of great controversy which has not yet been discussed in this House. The Government side has a case, but so too do those who say that more money should be spent on health and education. It appears that there is all-party agreement for a debate. Proposals are coming from all sides of the House, including Senator Costello, that we reflect on our priorities and where these vast sums coming from taxation in the Celtic tiger economy should be spent.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FintanACoogan" hpid="Mr. Coogan Mr. Coogan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Coogan</NameTxt>
      <P>I return to the comment made by Senator Finneran, complimenting the Minister for Agriculture, Food and Rural Development on the lack of further outbreaks of foot and mouth disease in Ireland. The last time the Senator made such a point an outbreak occurred the following day. I hope we do not have a recurrence as a result of his suggestions today. The Minister did not run around the country preventing foot and mouth disease; it is the farmers and others who are responsible for preventing it.</P>
      <P>I wish to take up the point raised by Senator Finneran on the Ombudsman's report which was unfailing in its condemnation of this Government in a number of areas, but in particular that of planning. We had a debate on the Planning Bill which was supposed to shorten the amount of time spent on planning but in fact it has not worked. I am seeking a debate with the Minister for the Environment and Local Government, Deputy Dempsey, who should tell us what we are going to do with a system that is collapsing. It is impossible to obtain planning within the limited period allowed. Planning officers spend their time trying to get planning through but they are not watching out for bad planning developments that are occurring. It is time we had an urgent debate on this issue.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="526" />
    <Speaker pid="MickLanigan" hpid="Mr. Lanigan Mr. Lanigan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lanigan</NameTxt>
      <P>Like Senator Costello, I suggest that we have a debate on workers' rights on May Day. I would like it to be a celebratory debate. There is no doubt that those who set up the May bank holiday were thinking in terms of a celebration of workers and what they have achieved. It should be a celebration rather than, as we have at present in every country in the world, a crowd of anarchists who have decided they want to get rid of the system. It seems to be obligatory for them to travel all over the world, although I do not know how they get the money to do so. The workers should have a say instead of having people who would not work in a fit but who tell everyone else where and how they should work. A debate on the celebration of labour would be worthwhile.</P>
      <P>It has been suggested that less money is being spent on health than on sport, but if more money was spent on sport, less would have to be spent on health. This must be acknowledged by anybody who makes a political football out of the cost of a stadium. They are talking about the cost of it rather than the need for it. It has been stated that there will be a discussion about costs which have overrun in many cases.</P>
      <P>I have asked the Leader for an early debate on the Middle East and he has agreed that will take place. The area, particularly Palestine, is in utter chaos. The sooner the better we at least acknowledge what is going on there.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PaulCoghlan" hpid="Mr. Coghlan Mr. Coghlan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Coghlan</NameTxt>
      <P>I fully support the calls by Senator Coogan and Senator Finneran for a debate on the report of the Ombudsman. To add to what Senator Coogan said about the planning system, we must all acknowledge that generally it is in a shambles. We should take serious note of yesterday's editorial in <i>The Irish Times</i>, which I felt was a well reasoned and factual account. It would be useful if the Minister would come to the House for a productive debate on the matter. He said recently that he was going to update the 1984 regulations which both sides of the House would agree are badly in need of revision. They need to be put in the form of a directive or another mandatory format. The Minister has indicated that he intends to proceed along those lines but that will not cure the situation which seems to exist in every local authority.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I also wish to refer to a matter about which the Leader and myself had an exchange of views before. There is no doubt that the continuing closure of some of the State's top tourist attractions, despite the easing of restrictions nationally, is unwarranted. I hope there will be a further announcement from the Minister for Agriculture, Food and Rural Development today. Given that the country has received the all clear on foot and mouth disease and that normal trading is resuming around the country, it is a matter of serious concern that there is discrimination against places such as Muckross House and Ross Castle. I am calling on the Leader to arrange with the Minister for Arts, Heritage, Gaeltacht and the Islands for <Col N="527" /> an immediate reversal of the decision which has been forced on us by faceless bureaucrats in her Department. If she cannot do so, she should produce these people in public and make them account for their actions and explain themselves.</P>
    <Speaker pid="DavidNorris" hpid="Mr. Norris Mr. Norris">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norris</NameTxt>
      <P>It would not do any good if they have no faces.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FergalQuinn" hpid="Mr. Quinn Mr. Quinn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Quinn</NameTxt>
      <P>I ask the Leader to urge the Minister for Foreign Affairs to draw to the attention of the Czech authorities the concern of the family and friends of the young man who died on the streets of Prague last week. I understand that a<i> post mortem</i> has taken place and if it confirms the suspicions that have been raised, I urge the Minister to remind the Czech authorities of the need for a thorough and immediate investigation into the matter.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JimWalsh" hpid="Mr. Walsh Mr. Walsh">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Walsh</NameTxt>
      <P>I support the call by a number of colleagues for a debate on the Ombudsman's report. However, in reply to some of the comments made, planning is far from a shambles but there is a need to address planning enforcement, which was the specific issue raised in the report. It has been a long established difficulty that resources have not been concentrated in this area. A debate would be timely, particularly given the response of the County and City Managers' Association which more or less dismissed the Ombudsman's report. If better local government is being sought, that is not the line to follow.</P>
      <P>I support Senator O'Toole's call for a debate on the primacy on the Houses of the Oireachtas to establish investigative fora and hold public inquiries. However, I understand why members of the legal profession want to avoid such an occurrence because the tribunals and public inquiries have been akin to their buying a winning lotto ticket on an annual basis.</P>
      <P>I welcome Senator Costello's call to mark May Day. A primary focus of such a debate should be to welcome the fall of communism and extreme socialism which did so much damage to freedom of movement and freedom of speech and impacted heavily on a wide area in central and eastern Europe.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeCostelloLAB" hpid="Mr. Costello Mr. Costello">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Costello</NameTxt>
      <P>And the pending fall of Fianna Fáil at the next election.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MickLanigan" hpid="Mr. Lanigan Mr. Lanigan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lanigan</NameTxt>
      <P>That slogan will not go far.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidNorris" hpid="Mr. Norris Mr. Norris">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norris</NameTxt>
      <P>I support my colleague, Senator Ross, and other colleagues in calling for a debate on the new stadium. I do not see why we should be the only ones not to enjoy the storm in the &ldquo;Bertie Bowl&rdquo;. Senator Lanigan chastised people who were penny pinching and looking for prudent management of resources. I remind the Senator that his own partners in Government, the Progressive Democrats, have adopted a sensible attitude. I am not against the stadium but, as public representatives, we ought to monitor the escal<Col N="528" /> ating costs of such projects and see if it is possible to conduct an independent inquiry into them or appoint somebody to monitor them to see what is the ultimate cost.</P>
      <P>I also support the call for a debate on planning. That would be appropriate because we have received a great deal of material recently regarding council officials which raises questions in this area once again. An article in <i>The Irish Times</i> today states: &ldquo;Kilkenny Corporation has admitted it knew that trees screening a controversial citycentre development were likely to be felled when it told An Bord Pleanála they would be protected.&rdquo;  That is a curious example of a lack of co-operation between a council and An Bord Pleanála. There is something for us to be worried about and there is material to be debated.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MickLanigan" hpid="Mr. Lanigan Mr. Lanigan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lanigan</NameTxt>
      <P>On a point of order, the officials of Kilkenny Corporation knew; the elected members did not.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidNorris" hpid="Mr. Norris Mr. Norris">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norris</NameTxt>
      <P>I was quoting precisely what was reported in the newspaper. I would not impugn anybody, as Senator Lanigan knows. I would be most delicate and scrupulous, especially regarding the city of Kilkenny and its elected representatives. The article referred to &ldquo;Kilkenny Corporation&rdquo; and I do not need to parse and analyse what that means.</P>
      <P>When will No. 9 on the Order Paper, the Transport (Railway Infrastructure) Bill, 2001, be brought before the House? Can that be done as soon as possible? The Bill seems narrowly to deal with on-street rail. Will the Minister for the Environment and Local Government come into the House and update us on what is happening with the metro, the underground section, for which the House was largely responsible?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnDardis" hpid="Mr. Dardis Mr. Dardis">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dardis</NameTxt>
      <P>I wish to raise a point which perhaps you can rule on, a Chathaoirligh, or bring to the attention of the Committee on Procedure and Privileges. I would have thought if Members asked questions of the Leader on the Order of Business that they would remain in the House to hear the answers and at least extend that courtesy to the House.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidNorris" hpid="Mr. Norris Mr. Norris">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norris</NameTxt>
      <P>Is it not correct that the absence of Members is not a subject to be raised?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BrianMullooly" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator, you have spoken already.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DonnieCassidyFF" hpid="Mr. Cassidy Mr. Cassidy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cassidy</NameTxt>
      <P>Senators Taylor-Quinn and O'Toole called for a debate on the Arms Trial. This will be taken during Private Members' time tomorrow.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>A number of Members called for a debate on the new sports stadium, Stadium Campus Ireland. I will provide time for this debate and request the presence of the Taoiseach, if possible, to discuss this magnificent proposal. Everyone in Ireland, particularly those of us born into less well off parts of <Col N="529" /> the community with parents who did not have the opportunities that we have now, should support anything that is good for young boys and girls&mdash;</P>
    <Speaker pid="MadeleineTaylorQuinn" hpid="Mrs. Taylor-Quinn Mrs. Taylor-Quinn">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Taylor-Quinn</NameTxt>
      <P>Does the Deputy Leader agree with the Leader?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DonnieCassidyFF" hpid="Mr. Cassidy Mr. Cassidy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cassidy</NameTxt>
      <P>&mdash;and enhances their opportunities in the prime of fitness. It is certainly worthwhile. As a Member of this House, I have heard similar statements on Knock Airport and look what it has done for the west. I also heard certain members of the Opposition use the term 'Taj Mahal' in relation to Government Buildings, which have become a showpiece of the new young Ireland for television cameras all over the world. When I was very young I heard similar statements about Shannon Airport, which is located in the acting leader of the Opposition's area. There is never a wrong time to do the right thing if it is good for Ireland and the right thing is to go ahead and invest in the young people of the future.</P>
      <P>Senators O'Toole, Costello and Walsh called for a debate on the powers, rights and affairs of the Oireachtas. I will allocate time for that. Senators Costello and Lanigan called for a debate on May Day and Senators Lanigan and Walsh called for a debate on the celebration of May Day. I will allocate time for that. Senator John Cregan raised a very serious and important issue for the people of Limerick. I will pass on his views to the Minister this afternoon.</P>
      <P>Senator Ridge called for a debate on teenage drinking, a matter debated in this House some time ago. Many Senators from all sides of the House, particularly Senator Farrell, have been vocal about the dangers presented by teenage drinking. There is an inherent danger that the problem will get out of control. I will allocate time for a debate.</P>
      <P>Senators Finneran, Coogan, Coghlan and Norris called for a debate on the Ombudsman's report, particularly in relation to local authorities and planning issues. I will allocate time for that.</P>
      <P>Senators Finneran and Coogan expressed their congratulations to those people who have played a major part in keeping foot and mouth from our shores, namely the Minister of Agriculture, Food and Rural Development, the farming community, the Garda, the Army and the general public, in particular those people who are suffering heavy losses in the tourism sector. As Leader of Seanad Éireann I appeal to the people of Ireland to support the tourism industry this year because it is going through a bad time. There are many opportunities on offer at present and an enormous amount of money has been invested in the industry, which is one of the three great growth industries in terms of employment. Many very professional people are involved in the sector. I ask people to support it in the same great way that they have supported measures to keep out the foot and mouth plague.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="530" /> I will come back to Senator Keogh regarding her inquiry about disability legislation and inform her of progress in this matter. In response to Senator Lanigan's request, I have already said that I will arrange a debate in the House on the Middle East at the earliest possible time. I will pass on Senator Coghlan's views to the Minister. I will pass on to the Minister Senator Quinn's views on the matter he raised. I will be able to answer Senator Norris's query regarding No. 9 tomorrow. I will allocate time for an update, with the Minister present, on the metro.</P>
    <P>The proposed legislation this term is 13 Bills. The Bills to come before the House are the Horse and Greyhound Racing Bill, the Residential Institutions Bill, the Audit of Allowances of Parliamentary Party Leaders Bill, the Dormant Accounts Bill, the State Authorities Public Private Partnership Bill, the Ombudsman's Bill for Children, the Public Health and Tobacco Bill, the Emigration (Carriers Liability) Bill, the Data Protection (Amendment) Bill, the Law of the Sea (Suppression of Piracy) Bill, the Gas (Interim Regulations) Bill, the Postal (Miscellaneous Provisions) Bill and the Pensions Bill. The Government expects to publish all that legislation before the summer recess.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MaryHenry" hpid="Dr. Henry Dr. Henry">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Henry</NameTxt>
      <P>We have a report showing the connection between poverty and ill health. Surely my request to the Minister for Finance should be addressed.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DonnieCassidyFF" hpid="Mr. Cassidy Mr. Cassidy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cassidy</NameTxt>
      <P>I omitted to reply to Senator Henry. We will do our utmost, as we always do, for the Senator in allocating the necessary time to this very serious and important request.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryHenry" hpid="Dr. Henry Dr. Henry">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Henry</NameTxt>
      <P>It is not for myself I speak, it is for poor people.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DonnieCassidyFF" hpid="Mr. Cassidy Mr. Cassidy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cassidy</NameTxt>
      <P>I represent those people myself.</P>
      <P>Order of Business agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="An Bille um an Aonú Leasú is Fiche ar an mBunreacht (Uimh. 2), 2001: An Dara Céim." RHead="Twenty-first Amendment of the Constitution (No. 2) Bill, 2001: Second Stage">
    <Title>An Bille um an Aonú Leasú is Fiche ar an mBunreacht (Uimh. 2), 2001: An Dara Céim.   Twenty-first Amendment of the Constitution (No. 2) Bill, 2001: Second Stage.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="BrianMullooly" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Item 2, motion pursuant to section 23 of the Referendum Act, 1994, prescribing a formal statement for the information of voters to be included on the polling card, which will be debated in conjunction with Second Stage of the Bill, will be formally moved when the debate on the Bill is concluded.</P>
      <P>Tairgeadh an cheist: &ldquo;Go léifear an Bille an Dara hUair anois.&rdquo;</P>
      <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That the Bill be now read a Second Time.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="531" />
    </P>
    <Speaker pid="JohnODonoghue" hpid="Mr. O'Donoghue Mr. O'Donoghue">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Justice, Equality and Law Reform (Mr. O'Donoghue)</NameTxt>
      <P>I am pleased to present to the House the Twenty-first Amendment of the Constitution (No. 2) Bill, 2001. As Senators will be aware, the death penalty has long been abandoned by the State as an appropriate form of punishment but references to it remain in the Constitution. Enactment of this Bill will enable the Government to proceed with the referendum to delete the two references to the death penalty in the Constitution and to prohibit its reintroduction in any circumstances by the inclusion of specific provisions to that effect.</P>
      <P>I do not need to describe here the terrible realities of the death penalty or indeed the torment endured, often for many years, by those awaiting execution. We can take some pride in the fact that the death penalty was abolished in this State for offences other than treason, capital murder and certain military offences under the Criminal Justice Act, 1964. Though it had not been used since 1954, the death penalty was finally abolished in statute law under the Criminal Justice Act, 1990, but the statutory changes were not reflected in our Constitution. Without a constitutional prohibition it could be reintroduced again by statute.</P>
      <P>The two references to the death penalty in the Constitution are to be found in Articles 13.6 and 40.4.5º. Article 13.6 provides:</P>
      <P>The right of pardon and the power to commute or remit punishment imposed by any court exercising criminal jurisdiction are hereby vested in the President, but such power of commutation or remission may, except in capital cases, also be conferred by law on other authorities.</P>
      <P>Article 40.4.5º, which is part of the <i>habeas corpus</i> provisions of the Constitution, provides:</P>
      <P>Where an order is made under this section by the High Court or a judge thereof for the production of the body of a person who is under sentence of death, the High Court or such judge thereof shall further order that the execution of the said sentence of death shall be deferred until after the body of such person has been produced before the High Court and the lawfulness of his detention has been determined and if, after such deferment, the detention of such person is determined to be lawful, the High Court shall appoint a day for the execution of the said sentence of death and that sentence shall have effect with the substitution of the day so appointed for the day originally fixed for the execution thereof.</P>
      <P>Article 28.3.3º is also relevant. That Article, <i>inter alia</i>, provides that nothing in the Constitution shall be invoked to invalidate any law enacted by the Oireachtas which is expressed to be for the purpose of securing the public safety and the preservation of the State in time of war or armed rebellion.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="532" /> The proposals in the Bill are for making amendments of both a technical and substantive nature to the Constitution. These amendments are intended to reflect the situation which pertained in Irish statute law since the passing of the Criminal Justice Act, 1990, and to take account of our international obligations. The Bill comprises two sections and a Schedule. Section 1 details the proposed changes to the Constitution by reference to the Schedule and section 2 is a standard citation provision.</P>
    <P>The proposed changes set out in the Schedule relate to four Articles of the Constitution, Articles 13, 15, 28 and 40. These changes are as follows: the deletion of the reference to the death penalty in Article 13.6, which deals with the commutation and remission of sentences and specifies that such powers cannot be used in capital cases except by the President; the deletion of Article 40.4.5º, which makes provision for <i>habeas corpus </i>proceedings in respect of a person who has been sentenced to death; a new subsection 15.5.2º to the effect that the Oireachtas shall not enact any law providing for the imposition of the death penalty is to be inserted in Article 15.5 which deals with the powers of the national Parliament; and the amendment of Article 28.3.3º to exclude the new Article 15.5.2º from the override provisions of that Article so that the prohibition on the reintroduction of the death penalty will apply even in time of war or armed rebellion.</P>
    <P>The approach taken in the Bill takes into account the views and recommendations of a number of important bodies. In proposing the removal of the words &ldquo;except in capital cases&rdquo; in Article 13.6, the Bill reflects the recommendation of the all-party Oireachtas Committee on the Constitution on that provision. Likewise, in proposing the prohibition of the death penalty by the inclusion of a new section in Article 15.5, the recommendation of the Constitutional Review Group is being implemented in the Bill.</P>
    <P>The Government is of the view that mere deletion of the references to the death penalty in Articles 13.6 and 40.4.5º is not enough and that any constitutional amendment relating to the death penalty should include a constitutional ban on its reintroduction. This is reflected in the Bill by the insertion of a provision in Article 15.5 to the effect that the Oireachtas shall not enact any law providing for the imposition of the death penalty. This approach is also in line with the recommendation of the Constitutional Review Group. That group further recommended that, in the event of a provision being included in the Constitution prohibiting the reintroduction of the death penalty, Article 28.3.3º should be amended so that the death penalty could not be imposed even in the circumstances contemplated by Article 28.3.3º, that is, where a state of emergency is declared in accordance with that Article.</P>
    <P>In its consideration of Article 40.4.5º, the Constitutional Review Group, noting that the death penalty had been abolished in 1990, pointed out that unless the death penalty were to be specifi<Col N="533" /> cally prohibited by the Constitution and an appropriate amendment made to Article 28.3,3º, Article 40.4.5º would not be redundant and should be retained. Its reasoning was as follows. Article 28.3.3º provides that nothing in the Constitution shall be invoked to invalidate any law passed by the Oireachtas which is expressed to be for the purpose of securing the public safety and the preservation of the State in time of war or armed rebellion. The Constitutional Review Group pointed out that unless an appropriate amendment was made to Article 28.3.3º, the override provisions of that Article, which permit the declaration of a state of emergency together with legislation in pursuance of that emergency, could be used by a future Government to re-impose the death penalty and it would be necessary as a minimum check on the legality of the operation of such emergency legislation to retain the provisions of Article 40.4.5º.</P>
    <P>The Bill follows the recommendation of the review group in relation to the amendment of Article 28.3.3º. The amendment comprises an insertion into that subsection to exclude the new Article 15.5.2º from the override provisions of the Article so that the prohibition on the reintroduction of the death penalty will apply even in time of war or armed rebellion. The Government favours this approach on the basis that since, as a matter of principle, it is of the view that the death penalty is wrong in all circumstances, Article 28.3.3º should be amended accordingly. In making the proposed changes to Articles 15.5 and 28.3.3º, the retention of Article 40.4.5º as a safeguard provision will not arise.</P>
    <P>I am aware that some people continue to express concern with regard to the abolition of the death penalty in the context of the protection of certain public servants in the course of their duties, such as members of the Garda Síochána and prison officers. The Criminal Justice Act, 1990, which finally abolished the death penalty, also put in place strong measures to deal with the protection of such public servants. Under section 4 of the Criminal Justice Act, 1990, the court, in passing sentence, shall specify a minimum period of imprisonment to be served of not less than 40 years for capital murder. In the case of an attempt to commit a capital murder, the court shall specify a minimum sentence of 20 years. Such severe penalties were introduced specifically to emphasise the seriousness with which such atrocities are viewed.</P>
    <P>There are further issues relating to our international obligations which are of relevance. Ireland has ratified two international instruments relating to the abolition of the death penalty. They are Protocol 6 to the European Convention on Human Rights, ratified on 24 June 1994, which abolishes the death penalty but allows for a derogation in time of war or imminent threat of war, and the Second Optional Protocol to the UN International Covenant on Civil and Political Rights, ratified by Ireland on 18 June 1993, which also abolishes the death penalty but allowed for <Col N="534" /> the possibility of a reservation in time of war, which possibility the Government declined to avail of on ratification in 1993.</P>
    <P>Given our stance at international level on the subject and, in particular, our ratification of the Second Optional Protocol to the UN International Covenant on Civil and Political Rights, the proposals as outlined in the Bill are in line with our international commitments. I might add that Sweden has recently introduced a proposal for an additional protocol to the European Convention on Human Rights to abolish the death penalty completely and the Government has been supportive of this proposal. I would also expect that our current position as a member of the United Nations Security Council will heighten international awareness of the measures being taken by Ireland finally to ensure that the death penalty will no longer be used in this State. The terrible reality of the death penalty has thankfully not been part of our criminal law system for some time. Although only finally abolished by the Criminal Justice Act, 1990, the death penalty has not been used in this country for almost 50 years.</P>
    <P>The deletion of the references in Articles 13.6 and 40.4.5 and the insertion of a prohibition in Article 15 give constitutional protection to what has already been done by statute. More importantly, however, the amendment relating to Article 28.3.3 means that the override provisions of that article, enabling the re-introduction of the death penalty in time of war or armed rebellion, could not be used at any stage in the future. By providing for a referendum to be held on this issue, the people of this State are being given the opportunity not only to amend the Constitution to reflect modern thinking and values, but to also send a clear message to the international community of the abhorrence with which the death penalty is viewed by the people of this State. I urge Senators to do their utmost to encourage people to turn out and vote on referendum day in support of the amendment.</P>
    <P>I commend this Bill to the House.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MadeleineTaylorQuinn" hpid="Mrs. Taylor-Quinn Mrs. Taylor-Quinn">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Taylor-Quinn</NameTxt>
      <P>I fully support the Minister's proposal to introduce an amendment to the Constitution to prohibit capital punishment. As he stated, the Bill effectively enshrines in the Constitution that which already exists in statute.</P>
      <P>There has not been an execution in this country since 1954 and it is an appropriate and opportune time to introduce this amendment which will give constitutional protection to all citizens. It will come as a surprise to many members of the public that they are being asked to vote on this particular issue because, in general, they believe that capital punishment was abolished long ago. Many people are not aware that a person can still receive the death penalty for the murder of a member of the security forces, a garda, a prisoner officer or a member of the diplomatic corps. The Fine Gael Party fully supports both the Bill and the campaign to ensure that this amendment to the Constitution is passed.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="535" /> Even when it is passed, however, it is important that protection will continue to be provided to those such as gardaí and members of the Army or diplomatic corps who serve in this country. It is important that the penalties handed down in capital cases &ndash; such as imprisonment for 40 years &ndash; are retained. The prohibition should not be lessened or the level of deterrence reduced by virtue of the fact that we are constitutionally removing the death penalty.</P>
    <P>The right to life is a basic fundamental human right and we cannot condone removing that right from anyone, regardless of what he or she does within the community. Nevertheless, substantial deterrents must be put in place. Has the Minister had discussions with the people directly affected by this, such as members of the Garda Síochána, representatives of the Army or the diplomatic corps? Perhaps the Minister might refer to that in his reply.</P>
    <P>It is also equally important that people are educated about the issue between now and referendum day. It will come as a surprise to many people that they are being asked to vote on this issue. I commend the Minister, his Department and his officials for responding to the recommendation made by the all-party Oireachtas committee in 1998 to remove the death penalty from the Constitution. It is important to include in the Constitution the Sixth Protocol of the European Convention on Human Rights, which Ireland signed.</P>
    <P>We are in a unique international position as a member of the UN Security Council and of the European Union. Although we are introducing legislation to put to the people in a referendum, our moral authority and responsibility do not end there. We have a role to play on the international stage at European Union level and in the United Nations. I urge the Minister, the Taoiseach and all the representatives of the Government to use their moral authority at international fora.</P>
    <P>It is important to clearly outline our position, particularly given our special relations with the United States. It is also important that we do not allow economic considerations to cloud our view in terms of fundamental human rights. Human rights must take priority at all times. We have a moral authority to repeatedly convey to the United States our abhorrence at the level of executions in various states. During his term as Governor of Texas, George Bush allowed a number of executions in that state. He is now President of the United States. We should be concerned about a possible hardening of attitudes in relation to the issue of the fundamental right to life. We should urge the President and the diplomatic corps to campaign for the abolition of capital punishment in the United States.</P>
    <P>The fact that the United States is a powerful economic force worldwide should not deter us from exhorting and encouraging it to protect people's basic fundamental rights, as outlined in the United Nations Charter. As a country which <Col N="536" /> sets itself up as a champion of human rights and condemns actions in some Third World countries, it is serious when an analysis of the number of capital punishments across the world shows the United States at the forefront in terms of the execution of juveniles and of handicapped or mentally retarded people. This reflects badly on the United States. We should not be shy or ashamed to convey our viewpoint because by doing so we are conveying the views of the majority of Irish people and of people in the European Union. We should encourage our European Union counterparts to express similar views at every given opportunity so this practice will be stamped out in the United States.</P>
    <P>Arguments are regularly made, particularly in the United States, that the death penalty is a deterrent to crime, but there is no evidence that this is so. The death penalty was removed in Canada, I believe in 1974, and since then statistics have shown that the level of crime has reduced dramatically. It is important that we turn that argument on its head and do so forcefully, unequivocally and fearlessly.</P>
    <P>Capital punishment, in effect, has led to cases of murder. Once a person has been killed by the electric chair or whatever method, there is no comeback. If evidence subsequently emerges which proves these people innocent, that is an appalling travesty of justice. This has happened in various places around the world. Over the past 25 or 30 years in the United States, over 73 people have been released where evidence has shown that they had not committed the crimes.</P>
    <P>For diplomatic and economic reasons, we have not been sufficiently assertive internationally. At a time when we are in a strong economic position, I believe we have the moral authority to articulate a very specific view and I encourage the Minister and the Government to do so.</P>
    <P>This is very timely. It warrants full explanation to educate the public. I hope the Government will undertake a very clear campaign at an early date. It will have the full support of the Fine Gael Party in ensuring that this amendment is passed so that there is protection in the Constitution to ensure that nobody can have their life taken for any offence in the future. I commend the Minister for bringing the Bill to the House.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JohnCreganFF" hpid="Mr. J. Cregan Mr. J. Cregan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J. Cregan</NameTxt>
      <P>I welcome the Minister to the House. I support the Twenty-first Amendment of the Constitution (No. 2) Bill, 2001, the purpose of which is to facilitate the holding of a referendum, which will remove the death penalty from the Constitution. I am pleased to be a Member of the Oireachtas which is bringing forward this referendum and I look forward to its full support by the people. I hope very few will cast their votes against it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Legislation was passed in this House in 1964 to abolish the death penalty for most offences. The death penalty was finally abolished in 1990 but references to it were not removed from the Constitution. It is approximately 50 years since the <Col N="537" /> last execution was carried out. The overwhelming majority of the people have no recollection of a death penalty being enforced. Given that the practice for at least two generations has been not to implement the death penalty, it is correct that the Constitution should reflect that reality and the wishes of the people. I look forward to this taking place in the near future.</P>
    <P>The abolition of the death penalty contributes to the enhancement of human dignity and the progressive development of human rights. It would be easy to convince the people as we know the death penalty does not work as a deterrent. In numerous countries that have the death penalty, we have seen that it does not reduce crime, does nothing for human dignity and, above all, flies in the face of God. It is God who gives life and He should take it away.</P>
    <P>Some people might be in favour of the death penalty, but it is not an effective deterrent. The USA has a much higher murder rate than most other countries, despite its extensive use of the death penalty.</P>
    <P>The legislation finally provides for the death of the death penalty. I always look with shock and horror at how the death penalty is used in countries where it still exists. While it remains in countries like China, it also remains in free countries like the United States. I know a little about the position in America based on the publicity arising from the exercise of the death penalty. The issue is more in the public domain in the US than in China.</P>
    <P>The death penalty is exercised in most states in America. Prisoners are put on death row having been convicted of a murder or murders and the horror of this in many instances is that they are held there for many years. That is one of the terrible spin-offs of the death penalty in the US. I strongly urge the authorities there to look into their hearts. They will not listen to me but there is a strong voice in many countries, including Ireland, to which they may listen. I reflect on the death penalty particularly in the context of its application in the US. There, one is placed in a death cell and then brought to a room to receive a lethal injection. It can take considerable time to descend into unconsciousness and finally death. This may be after lingering in one's death cell for up to 20 years.</P>
    <P>I thank the Minister for finally bringing Ireland to a position where the death penalty cannot be applied in any circumstances. This legislation provides for the amendment of the Constitution to delete references to the death penalty and to prohibit its reintroduction under any circumstances, even in time of war. The legislation provides for the deletion of references to capital cases in Article 13.6. In reflecting the current position on the abolition of the death penalty, the article deals with the commutation and remission of sentences and specifies that such powers cannot be used in capital cases, except by the President. The legislation also provides for the deletion of Article 40.4.5º which makes provision for <i>habeas <Col N="538" />corpus</i> proceedings in respect of a person who has been sentenced to death.</P>
    <P>The Bill provides for the inclusion of a specific provision in Article 15.5.2º that no law should be enacted providing for a sentence of death. An amendment to Article 28.3.3º, the effect of which is prohibition under the new Article 15.5.2º, would continue to apply even in time of war. Article 28.3.3º allows for the Constitution to be overridden for the purpose of securing public safety and the preservation of the State in time of war or armed rebellion. These latter provisions reflect the stand taken internationally by Ireland in its application of the sixth Protocol of the European Convention on Human Rights which abolished the death penalty except in time of war, and its ratification without reservation of the second optional Protocol of the United Nations International Convention on Civil and Political Rights which provides for the abolition of the death penalty even in time of war. This is what the people are asked to do in an upcoming referendum to amend the Constitution.</P>
    <P>It is almost 50 years since the death penalty was used in Ireland &ndash; the last execution was in 1954. The Criminal Justice Act, 1964, abolished the death penalty for offences other than treason, capital murder and certain military offences. The death penalty was finally abolished in statute law under the Criminal Justice Act, 1990, but not in constitutional law. I pay tribute to the Oireachtas All-Party Committee on the Constitution and the Constitutional Review Group which considered the death penalty provisions of the Constitution. The All-Party Committee on the Constitution which reported in November 1998 recommended the deletion of the reference to capital cases in Article 13.6. The report of the Constitutional Review Group in May 1996 recommended the deletion of Article 40.4.5º and a provision banning the reintroduction of the death penalty including an appropriate amendment to Article 28.3.3º.</P>
    <P>I welcome this very important legislation and I urge a strong vote in its favour. I hope that a full and frank explanation of the legislation will be given to citizens to ensure that we send the strongest message to countries that still exercise the death penalty. We have seen travesties of justice take place in recent years. Where prison sentences have been handed down there is some room for redress if it is found that wrong decisions were made. In the case of the death penalty, there can be no redress for the unfortunate victim. It is sensible to remove all reference to the death penalty from our Statute Book. I commend the Bill to the House.</P>
    <Speaker pid="ShaneRoss" hpid="Mr. Ross Mr. Ross">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Ross</NameTxt>
      <P>I wish to share my time with Senator Norris.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BrianMullooly" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Is that agreed? Agreed.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ShaneRoss" hpid="Mr. Ross Mr. Ross">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Ross</NameTxt>
      <P>I welcome this Bill to amend the Constitution and I congratulate the Minister for <Col N="539" /> Justice, Equality and Law Reform for bringing it in so promptly and for recognising the need for it not only in terms of the legislation but in the Constitution. Not long ago in this House, Ministers for Justice from both Fine Gael and Fianna Fáil opposed, delayed, procrastinated, put off and, in effect, defeated measures to remove the death penalty from legislation. That was in the mid to late 1980s. In the civilised world in which we live, it is easy to forget that there were many who did not wish to remove the death penalty from Irish law.</P>
      <P>At that time the death penalty was on the Statute Book &ldquo;only&rdquo; for the murder of a garda or a prison officer. It was there for a specific purpose because there was a large and vocal body of gardaí and prison officers who felt that it protected them in some way. It was never used in this period but there was a series of ghoulish circumstances where people, whose actions cannot be defended in any way, were sentenced to death. These sentences were then commuted by the President on the recommendation of the Government. It is conceivable that in the event of a ghastly murder and a public outcry, politicians might find it difficult to resist public pressure for the execution of those who had committed unacceptable and savage crimes. This has occurred in the United States.</P>
      <P>It is welcome that the death penalty should be taken completely out of the political arena where it has been for many years. The refusal of the Government until 1990 to remove it from the Statute Book was specifically because of the strength of a political lobby group. This Bill takes the death penalty one step further from a political lobby group. There are certain standards which we must uphold. This is what legislation is about, whether right or wrong. It is about what we believe is morally right. One of these things is the protection of human life at all stages. That is what this Bill is about and I commend the Minister for this. I speak from some experience as I introduced the Bill in this House to abolish the death penalty, supported by Senator Norris. I found that a frustrating experience. The Fianna Fáil Government of the day introduced a Bill which was almost identical to the one we had introduced. I welcome that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>However, there are areas of hypocrisy in this Bill with which I have difficulty. How can the Minister introduce a Bill which is so right in its thinking and so direct in its approach, yet so dishonest in its schizophrenic attitude to other countries? We do nothing about the barbaric practices in the United States where there are executions almost daily. Protests from Ireland are mute if they exist at all. Whereas we make a great virtue of this Bill, which will undoubtedly be passed by the people, we are silent in the face of barbaric executions in the United States. The posistion there is worse than elsewhere because it appears the death penalty is used as a social weapon. Why is it that 80% of the people hanged, electrocuted <Col N="540" /> or killed by other means in the US are black? How many protests have been made at a high level by the Minister for Foreign Affairs to the Bush administration about its extraordinary bloodlust? There are serious inconsistencies in what is happening here today.</P>
    <P>What action is the Government taking about the Nigerian Government with which we freely trade? The Nigerian Government appears to execute its political opponents on the basis of flimsy evidence and we must condemn that in the strongest terms. The Fianna Fáil Party made a virtue of not trading with South Africa. It continually and properly protested to the white South African Government about executions carried out in that country and imposed sanctions on its savage regime for reasons not unrelated to the death penalty. We could applaud that behaviour had the Fianna Fáil Party acted consistently in regard to the US and Nigerian Governments. The oppression of certain people in Nigeria led to executions in that country. Did Shell, which trades happily here, protest against those executions? The company did nothing. What does the Government say to Shell? The Government's attitude to the death penalty is hypocritical.</P>
    <P>This is a tremendous Bill but I will conclude with a question to the Minister. What does the Government intend to do about the imminent ghoulish execution of Timothy McVeigh in the US? The crime he committed was unforgivable and merited the imposition of the most severe sentence possible, being locked up forever. If Ireland disapproves so strongly on moral grounds of the death penalty in all circumstances, why does the Minister not call in the US ambassador to hear the Government's views on this barbaric practice? He will not do so. Rather, he will state that Ireland disapproves of the death penalty but will turn a blind eye to it in the US.</P>
    <P>Prior to the introduction of the 1990 legislation, there was a third dubious reason for executing people, namely, treason. It is extraordinary that such a crime existed up to ten years ago. The crime of treason is open to the widest possible interpretation. Treason can be covered by other crimes unless it has political connotations. This Bill takes out of the political arena a principle in which the Members of this House believe strongly and unanimously so that we will no longer be subject to fickle and sometimes bloodthirsty public opinion which, in some circumstances, is understandable. I congratulate the Minister on the introduction of this Bill.</P>
    <Speaker pid="DavidNorris" hpid="Mr. Norris Mr. Norris">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norris</NameTxt>
      <P>I welcome this Bill but I rise principally to congratulate my colleague, Senator Ross, who has been active in this area for a number of years. I recall his valiant attempts, when I was first elected to this House, to get a Bill abolishing the death penalty passed through the Seanad. The Government introduced a similar Bill at that time which has acted to the moral welfare of this country.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="541" /> The entire apparatus of death is revolting in its legal context. The charade of a judge, in his dignity, donning a black cap and reciting the ancient formula, the involvement of the State in the preparation of one of its citizens for death and the careful selection and maintenance of the instruments of death cannot have had a morally beneficial effect on the unfortunate people required to carry out murder on the State's behalf. It always struck me as laughable that we insisted on retaining the preamble to the Constitution which invokes the godhead and the Christian religion while the death penalty contradicted one of the most basic commandments, &ldquo;Thou shalt not kill&rdquo;.</P>
    <P>People commit appalling crimes, the murder of a garda being one. They carry out horrible and gruesome multiple murders and premeditated murders, and the natural human instinct, on occasion, of the family members of the people killed in this appalling manner is to seek vengeance. However, one must ask whether the State, as an institution, should ever sink to the level of the death penalty. I do not believe it should. It could never be argued that the State acted as a result of a momentary aberration or that its actions were a <i>crime passionnel</i>. A state execution must, of its nature, be deliberately and carefully premeditated and planned and that constitutes a fundamental violation of human rights.</P>
    <P>When I first read the Bill, I considered it to be unnecessary window dressing which would result in the Minister obtaining some positive publicity in the area of human rights. It is highly unlikely that we would ever again confront a situation in this country in which a Government would contemplate the introduction of the death penalty and if that were to happen, it would only happen in circumstances in which a huge majority of people exerted pressure on the Government. Indeed, this Bill would not prevent the reintroduction of the death penalty because if there were such overwhelming public feeling, the Government could reverse what it is doing today in a referendum. The Minister, in his speech, outlined the reason for this Bill. The Government's legal advice is to the effect that unless Article 28.3.3º is amended, its override provisions could, if an emergency were declared, allow a Government to introduce the death penalty without recourse to the Irish people and in defiance of their wishes. For this reason, the Bill is not merely a cosmetic exercise but has real legal purpose and validity.</P>
    <P>Senator Ross referred to the American experience which is undoubtedly horrific. I recall the death penalty in Britain. I read Ludovic Kennedy's <i>Ten Rillington Place</i> in which it was perfectly obvious that the unfortunate Timothy Evans was taken to the gallows and executed when he was completely innocent of the crime of which he was accused. His trial was manipulated by his landlord, John Christie, who was regarded as an evil genius.</P>
    <P>Senator Ross asked why 80% of the people executed in the US are black. Any analysis of statistics in this area shows that the overwhelming <Col N="542" /> number of people executed are black, mentally subnormal and come from very poor backgrounds, as a result of which they receive very inadequate defences. A number of people have been executed in the United States in recent years in circumstances which would cause great concern to anyone of a civilised disposition. When people have been inadequately represented or, subsequent to their conviction, convincing evidence of their innocence has been unearthed, it has proved impossible to reverse the death penalty. One of the reasons is that in most states of the union it is an exceedingly popular political exercise. I would be something of an admirer of former President Clinton but even he executed someone in Arkansas in the run up to the presidential election in which he was first elected. George Bush is notorious in this area.</P>
    <P>On the question of Timothy McVeigh's execution, the crime for which he was justly convicted was an appalling and monstrous one. It was a crime of mass murder which was calculated coldly and in a premeditated fashion, yet I do not believe that even in that case the state should sink to that level of premeditation. What really worries me is the ongoing attempts in the United States by some of the commercial TV networks to obtain the right to broadcast live the infliction of the death penalty. One would need the ironic satiric gifts of the late Dean Jonathan Swift to deal with the application of a licence for the live broadcast of a death, something which is grotesque and obscene. However, there are two ways of looking at it. It is a really despicable attempt on behalf of some networks to make money out of the putting to death another human being, but if it forced the American people to confront the reality of what is being done in their name and sicken them, that would be a good thing. Nevertheless, my experience of American television, particularly late at night, suggests there may be merely a hardening of attitudes as people have been desensitised by the amount of violence on American television.</P>
    <P>I always enjoy visiting the United States and I do not wish to portray myself as an enemy of that country. However, I have strong reservations about certain issues. It seems to me that one of the principal reasons for retaining the death penalty, in addition to its political popularity, is that it is cheap. It is a very cheap alternative because it costs a great deal of money to keep people in jail. The imposition of very lengthy sentences, including life imprisonment which means exactly that, will cost the state a great deal of money. Therefore it is cost effective to put people to death.</P>
    <P>One should broaden one's range and not just confine it to the United States of America. Iran, for example, and all the Gulf states routinely involve themselves in executions that are public spectacles. I suppose for that reason they are considered useful as a deterrent, even though it is extremely unlikely they operate as such. It is horrible to contemplate being placed under sentence <Col N="543" /> of death. It rarely strikes one unless there is a case like that of Timothy McVeigh or one is contacted by Amnesty International as part of its programme of writing to governments, including the United States government. I wish to put on record my admiration for the continuing work of Amnesty International in campaigning ceaselessly against the death penalty. It is horrible to contemplate that one's life will be terminated at a specific time by other human beings when there is no necessity for it. I cannot imagine what it must be like.</P>
    <P>I have just finished reading the new biography of Queen Elizabeth I by Professor Starkey. In it he retells the story of Elizabeth's mother, Anne Boleyn, who was condemned as a result of the machinations of her husband, Henry VIII, and the pathetic response of that woman who asked for the special favour that instead of being strangled or whatever, she should, as a member of the royal family, have the privilege of being beheaded standing up, which is what happened. She said, &ldquo;Mine is but a little neck&rdquo;, and so it proved. She had to stand while a man managed to cut off her head with one swipe of the sword.</P>
    <P>I found that very chilling because I had just been reading of two women who had been accused of being lesbians and who were similarly executed in a provincial city in Iran. When I raised the issue of this type of punishment in Iran at a meeting of the Committee on Foreign Affairs some years ago, some members of the Iranian delegation and our Parliament laughed. I assume on the part of the Irish parliamentarians that was because it was so remote from their experience that they could not understand it.</P>
    <Speaker pid="DonLydon" hpid="Mr. Lydon Mr. Lydon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lydon</NameTxt>
      <P>I begin by congratulating the Minister on bringing this incredibly important legislation before us. In doing so, he is following in the footsteps of another great Minister for Justice who introduced legislation in 1964 to abolish the death penalty for all but three categories of offences. I refer, of course, to Mr. Charles J. Haughey whose reforming zeal in his many ministries was ever evident. I say this legislation is incredibly important because it is.</P>
      <P>If the Bill is passed and the amendment is carried, the State will no longer be officially involved in the revengeful taking of life. However, I cannot say it is timely because the legislation should have been passed long ago in what we claim to be a civilised country. I am pleased we are becoming more civilised daily, because a great Christian existentialist, Nikolai Aleksandrovich Berdyaev, said that the condition of people's moral consciousness may be gauged in a sense by their attitude to capital punishment. As we move towards the elimination of this barbarous archaic custom, I hope we will take one step upward to a higher plain of civilisation.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>It is all too easy to give into the demands of those who call for the retention of capital punishment. I can understand their fears and empathise <Col N="544" /> with those members of our peacekeeping forces and security forces who, from time to time, may come face to face with a gangster or terrorist who, because of madness, greed or adherence to some misguided philosophy, remorselessly guns down one of their number. The Garda Síochána, in particular, have lost men in such circumstances and have called, understandably, for the retention of the death penalty.</P>
    <P>The death penalty is a punishment that is intolerable to the imagination. If one cares to contemplate this, one will be forced to agree it is a public sin of sloth. Why do those who call for the retention of capital punishment do so? Their principal argument is that it has value as an example where the State does not hang people to punish them but to intimidate by a terrifying example those who might be tempted to imitate their actions. They claim society does not hang people for revenge, it merely protects itself.</P>
    <P>I put it to the House that there exists not one whit of scientific evidence to support the claim that the existence on the Statute Book of a law requiring capital punishment, whether as a reality or a threat, will stop an angry, insane or psychopathic person committing a murder. I also put it to the House that most of the Irish people do not believe the execution of a convicted murderer or someone guilty of treason has much value as an example. If they really believed this, why are there not public executions which would be filmed and repeatedly shown on television? That is where all the potential murderers would learn from example. Of course, people no longer believe this. We no longer hang people in public or in private, nor would we agree to the publishing in our daily newspapers pictures of a condemned man swinging from a noose. If we really believed or subscribed to the idea of capital punishment being used as an example to all, surely we would be hanging people in the middle of Croke Park, where there is seating capacity for thousands. People would be invited from near and far, refreshments would be served, the whole family could attend, children could come along for the day and soon no more horrific crimes would be committed.</P>
    <P>Do we really believe this? We should not speak any more about the effectiveness of the death penalty as an example. While the scenario I sketched may appear to us in Ireland as unreal, it is not as far-fetched as it seems. Closed circuit television is used in the United States of America to view people as they go through the throes of the death penalty.</P>
    <P>The death penalty is carried out in public in many countries. An article by Patrick Comerford called &ldquo;When the state kills&rdquo; in <i>The Irish Times</i> on Thursday, 17 August 1989, stated:</P>
    <P>In many countries the death penalty is carried out in public. In Nigeria, where many prisoners have been publicly shot, thousands have come to witness the spectacle. In China, public executions are common despite being pro<Col N="545" /> hibited by law. In Saudi Arabia, the corpses of those beheaded are displayed in public for up to an hour. Public executions are staged in many countries as a deterrent against crime, but research carried out in the United States [surprisingly enough] suggests that these executions may have the opposite effect, brutalising society and causing more violence.</P>
    <P>Men, women and even children are executed around the world. They are hanged, shot, electrocuted, gassed or poisoned. In seven countries &ndash; Iran, Mauritania, North Yemen, Pakistan, Saudi Arabia, Sudan and the United Arab Emirates &ndash; certain prisoners are stoned to death, usually for adultery. Beheading by sword is used in at least five countries &ndash; Mauritania, North Yemen, Qatar Saudi Arabia and the United Arab Emirates. Several blows are sometimes needed to sever the head, depending on the weight of the sword and the strength and accuracy of the executioner, and shooting by firing squad does not make it any quicker because, as it is an easier target, a squad may be told to aim at the body rather than the head. In Taiwan, a prisoner was found to be breathing over an hour after the first two volleys had been fired.</P>
    <P>Execution still happens in many countries in public. For example, between 1983 and 1989, 900 people were executed in Nigeria, many of them in front of huge crowds, including children. In Iraq, more than 2,000 executions have taken place during the past 20 years. In Iran, since the revolution, thousands have been executed. Some of these have been carried out in public and the victims were shot, hanged or stoned. The article I mentioned earlier also describes a stoning. It states:</P>
    <P>According to one eye witness account of a stoning in Iran, a lorry &ldquo;deposited a large number of stones and pebbles beside the waste ground and then two women were led to the spot, wearing white sacks over their heads.&rdquo;  The women were &ldquo;enveloped in a shower of stones and transformed into two red sacks&rdquo;, according to the eye witness. The wounded women fell to the ground and the revolutionary guards smashed their heads in with a shovel to make sure they were dead.</P>
    <P>George Bernard Shaw said:</P>
    <P>Criminals do not die by the hands of law; they die by the hands of other men. Assassination on the scaffold is the worst form of assassination because there it is invested with the approval of society. It is a deed, they teach us, not the name we give it. Murder and capital punishment are not opposites that cancel one another, but similars that breed their kind.</P>
    <P>It is a compelling thought. I do not believe the argument that execution acts as a deterrent and I do not subscribe to the idea of capital punishment as an example. Countries which use it have not reduced crime or civil unrest &ndash; sometimes, the <Col N="546" /> opposite appears to be the case. For example, executions in South Africa during the last decade before Nelson Mandela took over averaged approximately 100 a year &ndash; sometimes the figure rose to 200 a year. The death penalty in South Africa was mandatory for murder. This included conspiracy to murder and even being present in a crowd when murder was committed. Yet, the crowds gathered ominously in that beleaguered bastion of apartheid at that time. Far from being afraid, their resolve was strengthened although the death penalty was in place.</P>
    <P>In the United States, approximately 2,000 prisoners are on death row awaiting execution while lawyers get rich from appeals and counter appeals. This is nothing short of barbarity. It is interesting to note that 50 years ago, on 21 November 1951, the late Seán MacBride said in Dáil Éireann that it was &ldquo;probably no exaggeration to say that the concept of capital punishment had its origin in barbarism.&rdquo;  Capital punishment cannot intimidate a man who does not know he will commit a murder. It will not intimidate a man who deliberately sets out to perform a pre-meditated murder. Arthur Koestler related a story from the time when pickpocketing was punishable by death in England. When a pickpocket was being hanged, other pickpockets worked the crowd.</P>
    <P>Statistics during the first 50 years of the last century show that of 250 men hanged in England, 170 had previously attended one or even two public executions. As late as 1886, from a total of 167 men condemned to death in Bristol prison, 164 had attended at least one execution. These facts speak for themselves. Other statistics show that in the countries that have abolished the death penalty, the incidence of crime remains the same. It neither increases nor falls. It appears safe to conclude that there is no connection whatsoever between the existence of capital punishment and crime. The death penalty does not intimidate anybody.</P>
    <P>It is true that nothing proves that the death penalty is exemplary. It is certain that thousands of murderers have not been intimidated by it, but one cannot know who has been intimidated by such a penalty. Consequently, nothing proves that it does not serve as an example. Some people are willing to allow the penalty that involves the ultimate forfeiture of the condemned man. Yet, the exercise of this privilege by society, that is, a fixing of the man on the definitive rigidity of death, is based on nothing more than unverifiable possibility. There are other objections &ndash; capital punishment brutalises us all. William Makepeace Thackeray went to see a man being hanged and wrote <i>On Going To See A Man</i><i>Hanged</i>. He said:</P>
    <P>Blood demands blood. Does it? The system of compensation might be carried on <i>ad infinitum</i>, an eye for an eye and a tooth for a tooth, as by the old Mosaic law. Why, because you lose your eye, is it that your opponents must be extracted? Where is the reason for the practice? Knowing that revenge is not only evil but useless, we have given up on minor points. <Col N="547" /> Only to the last, we stick firm. I came away from Snow Hill that morning with a disgust for murder, but it was for the murder I saw done. I pray to Almighty God to cause this disgraceful sin to pass from among us and cleanse our land of blood.</P>
    <P>I pray that our lust for revenge will not be satisfied by the taking of a life. All human life is sacred. Only God can give life and only God should take it away. Even Leonardo da Vinci said:</P>
    <P>And thou, man, who by these my labourers dost look upon the marvellous works of nature, if thou judges it to be an atrocious act to destroy the same, reflect that it is an infinitely atrocious act to take away the life of man.</P>
    <P>We see daily the taking of life in the name of peace. Disregard for the life of another is exemplified<i> par excellence</i> in the systematic murder daily of thousands of innocent people in our so-called civilised world. I refer to the unborn, the young nestling in their mothers' wombs who are systematically poisoned or sucked out in pieces, their tiny bodies ending mutilated in the refuse sacks of modern, sterile medical clinics. Their lives are ended almost as soon as they have begun. We should not add to this disregard for human life. We should end, once and for all, this barbarism.</P>
    <P>Seán MacBride was a distinguished lawyer and he did not lightly refer to capital punishment as barbarism. I stress the barbarity of the act because I want people to appreciate that when a man is hanged, he is hanged in their name and on their behalf, as Fr. Austin Flannery said, &ldquo;most obviously so in a democracy&rdquo;. We would all share the responsibility if a hanging occurred. It is an awesome responsibility.</P>
    <P>We claim to revere human life, yet in the name of the law, we may take it. The great Quaker reforming politician, John Bright, said:</P>
    <P>A deep reverence for human life is worth more than a thousand executions in the prevention of murder and is, in fact, the great security of human life. The law of capital punishment, whilst pretending to support this reverence, does in fact tend to destroy it.</P>
    <P>What of all the innocents who died on the gallows? We think of the execution of William Orr, whose innocent body swung from the gallows in Carrickfergus on 14 October 1797. He was a United Irishman, a champion of northern Presbyterian patriots. His execution was one of the darkest blots of the administration of English rule in our country. In our day, there have been many summary executions which, although lacking in the panoply of the courtroom, were nevertheless executions carried out at the behest of the State. Everyone asks what would have been the outcome if the Guildford Four had been hanged? The reply would probably be &ldquo;too late, too bad&rdquo;.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="548" /> The State has an awesome responsibility where it can decide to snuff out someone's life. The person may later be proved innocent of the crime of which he or she was originally accused. This awesome responsibility does not sit well upon my shoulders and I do not want to be a part of it. It is important to speak openly of the reality of capital punishment. We have a habit of pushing unpleasant things out of our awareness. Albert Camus, speaking of this tendency, said: &ldquo;The death penalty is to the body politic what cancer is to the individual body, but perhaps the single difference is that no one has ever spoken of the necessity of cancer.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>Let us move to a more enlightened age where we no longer resort to State violence as an instrument of revenge. Let me end with the words of Victor Hugo who said:</P>
    <P>In the early ages, the social edifice rested on three columns &ndash; Superstition, Tyranny, Cruelty. A long time ago, a voice exclaimed &ldquo;Superstition has departed!&rdquo;  Lately another voice has cried &ldquo;Tyranny has departed!&rdquo;  It is now full time that a third voice shall be raised to say &ldquo;The Executioner has departed!&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="MaryHenry" hpid="Dr. Henry Dr. Henry">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Henry</NameTxt>
      <P>I congratulate the Minister on bringing this legislation before the House and I congratulate the Government on bringing it forward. Is Ireland the first country in the world to bring capital punishment before the court of public opinion to have it abolished? I believe it may be. I do not remember hearing of any other country in the world where public opinion was asked to remove capital punishment from legislation. I congratulate the Minister on his courage and I am sure all Members will ensure his courage in bringing this forward is rewarded.</P>
      <P>There is a need to follow on further with legislation concerning murder, especially given the report from the Law Reform Commission in 1996 on sentencing in which, I am sure the Minister and Members will recall, it was recommended that there should not be minimum and mandatory sentences. Mandatory sentences are the only ones available to judges when they sentence people for murder. In some cases, mandatory sentences of life imprisonment may seem too little because everyone knows the person will be released in eight to ten years, while in other cases, for example, domestic murders, which comprise most murders, they may seem too harsh or too long, although taking someone else's life is a most appalling crime. I hope that, from this, we will proceed to examine changing the legislation concerning murder and, as the report suggests, removing the mandatory life sentence for murder so that judges have some discretion in sentencing those who have committed murders.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Another paper I have read, which I am sure the Minister and Members have also read, is the consultation paper of the Law Reform Commission on homicide and the mental element in murder. It makes me believe that a debate on this topic in the Seanad would be worthwhile. I am <Col N="549" /> concerned by one aspect of this report, namely, the position regarding intention. Section 4 of the Criminal Justice Act, 1964, defines the mental element in murder as &ldquo;an intention to kill or cause serious injury&rdquo;. There is, apparently, little Irish authority on intention, but the report states that, in England, intention:</P>
    <P>...has been interpreted as embracing, in addition to situations where it is the actor's conscious object or purpose to kill, situations where, although it may not be the actor's object or purpose to kill, he nevertheless foresees death as virtually certain to result from his actions.</P>
    <P>We do not know what exactly &ldquo;intention&rdquo; means in Irish law, and the Law Reform Commission report states that, because of the scarcity of reported Irish authority on the matter, it is difficult to give a precise answer to the question as to what intention means.</P>
    <P>Two questions are asked on page 16 of the report which are taken directly from a unanimous decision by the Law Lords in England. This section of the report considers the importance of foresight and says that, in rare cases, it may be necessary to direct a jury by reference to foresight of consequences. Two questions arise. First, was death or serious injury a natural consequence of the defendant's voluntary act? Second, did the defendant foresee the consequences as being a natural consequence of his act? It is concluded that, if the answers to both questions are in the affirmative, an inference could be drawn that the defendant intended the consequence. In chapter two in section 2.14, the matter of foresight of consequences is discussed and the importance that the greater the foresight of the consequences has regarding intention. In chapter three, section 3.04 states: &ldquo;A person has an &lsquo;intent to kill' if he means his actions to kill, or if he is willing for his action, though meant for another purpose, to kill in accomplishing that purpose.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>Senator Lydon raised the issue of abortion and his concern for the life of the unborn. I am concerned in this discussion with examining the life of the expectant mother, if her life is in danger, and the position of a doctor who may be obliged to perform a termination in certain circumstances. We have not introduced legislation dealing with abortion, even though we have been roundly criticised by the Judiciary for not doing so for some years and despite the promise of the former Taoiseach, Deputy Albert Reynolds, that he would introduce such legislation if any of his amendments to the Constitution were defeated in 1992. As the Minister will remember, one of those amendments was defeated.</P>
    <P>As we have given the life of the unborn the position it has in the Constitution since 1983, could a doctor who gives medical treatment to save a woman's life but which terminates the life of the unborn be accused of murder? It is certain both questions I posed could be answered in the affirmative, namely, if death or serious injury was <Col N="550" /> a natural consequence of the defendant's voluntary act, and if the defendant saw the consequence as a natural consequence of his act. There is even more trouble in the Law Reform Commission report because section 3.07 goes on to talk about oblique intention, where it is not the defendant's purpose to cause a certain result, but where it is a near irreversible by-product or almost certain consequence of his activity.</P>
    <P>In 1980, the Criminal Law Revision Committee of England and Wales felt it would be too narrow to confine intent to cases where the accused desires a certain result, preferring to include cases where the accused knows a certain result will follow. This is even more clearly put in section 3.16 of the report where, regarding oblique intention, that is, the result is a by-product of the person's activity, it states: &ldquo;If [the accused] acts in order to achieve a particular purpose&rdquo;&ndash; that would be to save the life of the mother in a situation where there could be a problem &ndash;&ldquo;knowing it cannot be done without causing another result, he must be held to intend to cause that other result&rdquo;. A doctor will know the life of the unborn child will have to be sacrificed if the child is not viable.</P>
    <P>There is considerably more discussion on oblique intent which causes the death of a person. The result of the termination of a pregnancy before the child is viable will be well known to any doctor carrying out a termination. The child will not live. However, if the mother's life is in danger, she will not live either. The proposals for reform suggest intention should be given statutory definition. I hope the Minister supports this and tries to introduce such a definition as soon as possible. We should introduce legislation regarding abortion at once to protect the expectant mother and her doctor in life-threatening situations. In its ethical guidelines the Medical Council states that it is unethical to withhold treatment to a pregnant woman whose life is in danger, even if the life of the foetus is lost because of this treatment. We should make it abundantly clear that this is also legal.</P>
    <Speaker pid="FergalQuinn" hpid="Mr. Quinn Mr. Quinn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Quinn</NameTxt>
      <P>I welcome the Bill, the Minister and this long overdue amendment to the Constitution. There is a marketing technique by which a prospective customer is encouraged into a sequence of yes answers and when the time comes for him to face the really big question he is so used to agreeing that he automatically answers yes, almost out of habit. The thought of this technique crossed my mind &ndash; I am sure the Minister will deny it &ndash; when I noticed the order in which the four referendums are to be put to the people. The big question &ndash; the Nice Treaty &ndash; is left until last. Perhaps when voters have answered yes to the first three questions they will automatically answer yes to the fourth. A cynic might be tempted to see the first three questions merely as warm-ups, designed to get the voter into the habit of answering yes. I look forward to being reassured that nothing was further from the Government's mind than that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="551" /> Whatever the motivation of putting the question of the death penalty first on the list, there is no doubt that people will say yes to this amendment. Happily, there is no controversy about the issue. Only one Deputy argued for retention of the death penalty in the Dáil. Almost everyone is agreed that State executions are barbaric.</P>
    <P>Once in Riyadh in Saudi Arabia, my colleague and I parked his car in a prohibited place. The car was towed away and we were obliged to pay a fine. We were horrified to discover that we had parked in the place where public beheadings take place, I believe, almost weekly. However, there is little difference in the ways in which executions take place, whether by lethal injection or by public beheading. It is right and proper that our Constitution should take the widely held view that we no longer want this practice in our legislation.</P>
    <P>I commend the Government on having taken the high road on this issue. I refer to the proposal to amend Article 28.3.3º, to exclude the prohibition of the death penalty from the list of measures that may be suspended in times of war or armed rebellion. The effect of this provision is not only to prohibit the Oireachtas from reinstating the death penalty by means of normal legislation but also to prohibit it from reinstating it as part of emergency legislation. This amendment to Article 28.3.3º immensely strengthens the proposed constitutional ban on the death penalty. It singles out this human right above all others and makes it sacrosanct in all circumstances. There could be no stronger way of stating the belief that the death penalty is absolutely wrong in principle and there are no circumstances in which it can be justified.</P>
    <P>The strength of this statement is made clear if we read Article 28.3.3º. It allows all the rights and freedoms enshrined in the Constitution to be overwritten by law in times of war or armed rebellion. Reading the draconian provisions of this article is enough to send a shiver down one's spine because it makes clear how fragile those rights and freedoms are. There is nothing in the Constitution which cannot be legally overwritten in a time of declared emergency, except this new provision banning the reinstatement of the death penalty. I commend the Government for taking this route because few of us would have thought of the question in this way. This measure makes it clear that forbidding the death penalty is so special that even in the direst emergency we are not prepared to allow it.</P>
    <P>One unexpected consequence of taking this route may be an immediate and highly practical impact on our extradition arrangements with other countries. Such a strong statement against the death penalty in our Constitution immediately calls into question the legality of any attempt to extradite a person from Ireland to a jurisdiction where the person concerned runs the risk of being executed. Any lawyer defending a person whose extradition was sought for a capital offence within such a jurisdiction would not be <Col N="552" /> earning his fee if he did not question the constitutionality of such an extradition. Equally, when the Supreme Court comes to consider this question it will give considerable weight to the way the ban on the death penalty has been singled out for preservation above and apart from all other human rights and freedoms. I am not a betting man but even I would be tempted to take a flutter on the likely outcome of such a case. Far from being an academic exercise with no practical consequences, the passing of this amendment could have a very real impact.</P>
    <P>Last month an American fugitive from a capital charge was apprehended in France, having spent most of the previous year hiding in Ireland. Ireland is very easy to get to from the United States, the country with the highest profile in applying the death penalty. During the discussion on this Bill in the Dáil, it was said that the passing of this amendment will strengthen the hand of the Taoiseach in seeking to persuade President Bush of the error of his ways on the death penalty. I cannot imagine President Bush losing too much sleep over a slap on the wrist from the Taoiseach but I can imagine Americans being concerned at Ireland becoming a safe haven for fugitives from American justice. I hope the Minister will comment on this aspect of the Bill. In these circumstances I can see Ireland featuring in the front line of the growing difference between Europe and the United States on the subject of capital punishment. We face some interesting times ahead. The Government is clearly happy to envisage such an outcome. I am sure the matter has been thought through. The Government could have included a saver for extradition arrangements into this amendment but it was obviously felt that it would be hypocritical to do so.</P>
    <P>I agree with that decision but while agreeing with the Government's approach it should be explained to the people before they vote on the issue. We have had troubles in the past arising from people voting on constitutional amendments without being fully aware of the consequences of what they were voting for. Let us make sure that does not happen in this case. Dangers face us if extradition from this country to the United States for a capital crime becomes almost impossible. We could become a safe haven for fugitives from the United States who will see Ireland as a place from which they cannot be extradited. I would welcome the Minister's comments on this question.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JoeCostelloLAB" hpid="Mr. Costello Mr. Costello">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Costello</NameTxt>
      <P>It is fitting that we begin the new millennium with an absolute prohibition on the death penalty. Members on all sides of the House see death as a barbaric punishment. There is no evidence of its effectiveness as a deterrent and we do not wish to have this penalty on the Statute Book. I am pleased that the Minister has prohibited the death penalty in any circumstances. In the past it might have been argued that to do so would be a step too far.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>It is interesting that it was Charles Haughey who in 1964 began quite an illustrious career in <Col N="553" /> politics as Minister for Justice and initiated the process of abolishing the death penalty. Deputy Ray Burke went a step further in 1990. I do not know if there is any moral to be derived from this, but is the present Minister for Justice, Equality and Law Reform not worried about being the one to abolish it entirely, considering what befell his illustrious predecessors? </P>
    <P>I welcome the legislation. I remember being very much involved in a campaign to abolish the death penalty at the end of the 1970s and the beginning of the 1980s. It was launched by a combination of Amnesty International, the Irish Council for Civil Liberties and the Prisoners' Rights Organisation and it eventually culminated in Gemma Hussey's introduction of a Bill in this House to abolish the death penalty during the short period of government in 1981. Thereafter, unfortunately, there was no great public acceptance or approval for it and there was too much opposition from gardaí and the prison officers at the time for anything to be done throughout the 1980s. It is amazing how much things have changed in a few years. Those of us who were around at that time, particularly the Independent Senators who were very active on the issue, will remember the degree of opposition and lobbying that took place throughout the country against the abolition of the death penalty and how the floodgates opened to those who were the public servants of the people in combating crime.</P>
    <P>At this time, the death penalty was abolished in Britain and Northern Ireland, where there was a war taking place. As Senator Lydon said, had the death penalty been in the Statute Book, the cases of the Guildford four and Birmingham six could have ended very tragically.</P>
    <P>In 1990, when the death penalty was being abolished, apart from what is left of it in the Constitution, I tabled an amendment concerning the tools of the hangman's trade that still existed in Mountjoy for the attention of the then Minister for Justice, Mr. Burke. It suggested that this paraphernalia be taken and deposited in the National Museum. The Minister asked me to withdraw the amendment on the grounds that he himself would look into it with a view to ensuring that this would happen and that it was not an item warranting an amendment of legislation. I am sure it was not. However, 11 years later, nothing has been done about it and the paraphernalia is still in a refurbished unit where the hangman carried out his trade. Some of it is missing. Will the Minister tell us what has happened to it and why it was not placed in a repository or left to the National Museum at the time, which is probably its proper place?</P>
    <P>Many have referred to the anomaly that exists regarding the attitude of the United States to the death penalty and the number of executions that have taken place in Texas, the home state of the current President, who is notorious for his support of it. The President of the United States is projected and promoted as the leader of the free world, the President of a country to which we are <Col N="554" /> supposed to look as an example in terms of its defence of the free world and international human and civil rights. However, the barbaric death penalty is carried out to an increasing extent in the United States. I hope that the Minister, or the Minister for Foreign Affairs, Deputy Cowen, uses the passage of this constitutional amendment &ndash; I am sure it will be successful &ndash; to signal strongly to the United States what Ireland's position is on the matter, in the context of membership of the Security Council of the United Nations. A meeting should be arranged between the Minister and the American ambassador immediately after this referendum has taken place to tell him what the Irish people have voted on. This can be taken back to his President to inform him of our position.</P>
    <P>We have a great relationship with the United States and nobody wants to damage it. However, we believe in the fundamental principle that it is wrong to take human life. It has been argued that the taking of human life by a state is intended to show its citizens that it is wrong for them to take human life. This is a meaningless, elliptical argument. The European Union has been quick to point out that states that wish to join must have certain standards. One of the standards required is that the death penalty does not comprise part of a state's penal regime. That is a major issue where the possibility of Turkey's joining the European Union is concerned. The European Union was to the forefront in protesting against the execution of the Kurdish leader who was arrested last year. It recognises this as a barbaric penalty and believes it should not be exercised by any country that seeks to join.</P>
    <P>Recently, we received an invitation from the Chinese city of Beijing to twin with Dublin. Our Lord Mayor has visited China in this regard. The view that has been expressed by the councillors of Dublin is that under no circumstances would they want to twin with a city in a country wherein human rights are abused to the extent that they are in China. That is a major issue in considering the invitation to twin the two cities. Yet we seem to proceed nonchalantly without anybody being too concerned that the country with which we have the greatest trading relations outside the European Union executes its citizens on a regular basis. I would like to see Ireland at the forefront of a campaign protesting against its position on the death penalty, which it believes to be inappropriate.</P>
    <P>This is also in line with our national requirements pertaining to the International Convention on Human Rights and the United Nations Covenant on Civil and Political Rights. It is in this context that I will make the rest of my remarks.</P>
    <P>Only yesterday, Amnesty International revealed a condemnatory audit of abuses of human rights here in Ireland and nearly all the areas referred to were under the Minister's auspices. We cannot, on the one hand, abolish the death penalty and place around our shoulders the mantle of protector of human rights, while on the <Col N="555" /> other hand not ensure that human and civil rights are not protected in other areas in this country. The list of issues that were condemned by Amnesty International is huge and has been around for a long time.</P>
    <P>I would refer the Minister to two non-Government motions that have been on the Order Paper for the last eight or nine months. No. 5 states:</P>
    <P>That Seanad Éireann calls on the Minister for Justice, Equality and Law Reform to establish a full-time, independent inspector of prisons; and to review the composition and operation of the prison visiting committees.</P>
    <P>The legislation that governs visiting committees is so outdated as to be unreal, as is the legislation governing prison rules. These areas should simply be addressed domestically and it does not require a constitutional amendment to do so.</P>
    <P>Non-Government motion No. 6 states:</P>
    <P>That Seanad Éireann calls on the Government to implement the recommendations of the Council of Europe Committee for the Prevention of Torture which visited Ireland in 1993 and 1998; and further calls on the Government to ratify the United Nations Convention Against Torture.</P>
    <P>Substantial complaints were made by the Council of Europe Committee for the Prevention of Torture, in 1993 and 1998, about the way in which we detain our citizens. Amnesty International has now come out with a report but very little has changed. They are looking for an independent police complaints body. Imagine having the Garda Síochána looking into complaints against themselves. Amnesty also wants effective safeguards to prevent ill-treatment of prisoners in custody. We do not seem to be able to get a camera or tape recorder into any of our detention cells.</P>
    <P>Above all, the Offences Against the State Act, which has remained on the Statute Book since the beginning of the Second World War in 1939, remains in operation, preventing a fair trial for one and all. The use of this law is quite extensive.</P>
    <P>The Amnesty International report referred to the need to have a lawyer present during interrogation in Garda custody, as well as provision for an independent inspectorate of prisons, to which I have already referred. Such an inspectorate does not exist. Nothing is happening with regard to the restructuring of prison visiting committees. We know about the debacle that took place in establishing the Irish Human Rights Commission; there were problems in getting it off the ground and it took so long to do it.</P>
    <P>Perhaps the most sensitive issue of all concerns the legal provision for asylum seekers. I saw in today's newspapers that the Minister has rejected the criticism contained in the Amnesty International report. However, there is constant criticism that we fall seriously short of the inter<Col N="556" /> national law on human rights in relation to the protection of asylum seekers. On the international front, Amnesty criticised us when we had the presidency of the Council of Ministers for our failure to act when the Russian Federation was committing atrocities in Chechnya. Our track record is not great.</P>
    <P>While I am delighted to see that we are taking such comprehensive measures in this legislation to deal with capital punishment, we are falling short in other areas that can easily be addressed by domestic legislation. I am sure the Minister would have the full support of the House if he came forward with the necessary legislation to rectify those concerns that are now being reiterated by such august organisations as Amnesty International and the Council of Europe Committee for the Prevention of Torture. They have not found the situation here to be satisfactory.</P>
    <P>We welcome the legislation which, as the Minister has heard, is supported by all sides of the House. Senator Quinn expressed some reservations about Ireland becoming a haven for criminals or other people who may face the death penalty in other countries, but that should not be our greatest worry if we regard the death penalty as being a barbaric punishment and one that is not suitable under any circumstances. If people are fleeing persecution and the threat of execution in their own countries by regimes that leave much to be desired in democratic terms, that measure should certainly be welcomed.</P>
    <P>We have struck a strong note for human rights. I hope this will be the beginning of the floodgates opening over the next 12 months the Minister may have in Government, if that is the length of time left, because so much could be done. The Minister would certainly be pushing an open door.</P>
    <Speaker pid="DennisODonovan" hpid="Mr. O'Donovan Mr. O'Donovan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Donovan</NameTxt>
      <P>I welcome the Bill. On the understanding that this legislation will get a safe passage through the House, I hope there will be a large turnout and a positive vote in the referendum due to be held later this year.</P>
      <P>As my party's spokesman on justice, it is important for me to register my support for the Bill and my absolute condemnation of the death penalty. The last person hanged in Ireland was Michael Manning from Limerick who, if he were still alive, would be just 71 years of age. We should reflect on that fact because 71 is not very old. It puts into proportion the provisions relating to the death penalty that were on the Statute Book at that time. In my view the death penalty was no answer to whatever crime Mr. Manning may have committed.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I am a member of the All-Party Oireachtas Committee on the Constitution which debated this issue. The committee fully endorsed and wholeheartedly agreed with the holding of this referendum on the abolition of the death penalty. I congratulate the Law Reform Commission on its great work in making a determined bid to <Col N="557" /> ensure that the death penalty would be abolished. In effect, this is a tidying up operation because under the 1964 and 1990 Acts, the death penalty no longer exists. However, because it was in the Constitution there was always a possibility that a future Government might re-introduce the death penalty for whatever reason.</P>
    <P>Some speakers made an interesting point with regard to the Guildford Four, Birmingham Six and other cases in England. It is quite likely that had the death penalty been available there, it might have been used in those circumstances because of the public outcry in Britain against the IRA and its supporters.</P>
    <P>I did not wish to convey the impression that by staying silent earlier I was not in support of the Bill. For other reasons, I requested my colleague, Senator Cregan, to stand in for me as spokesman on justice. He ably set out his reasoning. We have had some very interesting contributions from many Senators, and Senator Lydon in particular, who spoke with great passion and emotion about the historical, philosophical and other reasons the death penalty has no place in modern society. It is easy for us to condemn other countries which still have the death penalty, particularly the US. The perception among Americans with whom I come in contact from time to time is that if the death penalty was not in use in the US crime rates would soar. I do not support that view and I condemn it.</P>
    <P>I hope that the EU, in allowing Turkey to accede to the Union down the road, will insist on greater law reform there, a greater acknowledgement of human rights<i> vis-à-vis</i> the protocols and laws for other European countries and the abolition of the death penalty.</P>
    <P>I commend the Bill to the House and stress the importance of a large turn-out for the referendum when it is held later in the year.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JohnODonoghue" hpid="Mr. O'Donoghue Mr. O'Donoghue">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Justice, Equality and Law Reform (Mr. O'Donoghue)</NameTxt>
      <P>I express my appreciation to all Senators for their welcome for the Bill and their constructive comments. The removal of the references in the Constitution to the death penalty reflects the reality that has pertained in Irish law since 1990 and in practice since 1954. Currently, a person convicted of capital murder must obtain a mandatory sentence of 40 years or 20 years for attempted capital murder and the death penalty may not be imposed. However, it is possible for a future Government to reintroduce the death penalty under the terms of our Constitution.</P>
      <P>The inclusion of a specific provision prohibiting reintroduction of the death penalty and the amendment to the override provisions of Article 28.3.3º will give constitutional protection to our international obligations under Protocol 6 to the European Convention on Human Rights and the Second Optional Protocol to the UN International Covenant on Civil and Political Rights.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="558" /> The possibility of entering a reservation to allow for use of the death penalty in time of war was open to states only at the time of ratification of the UN protocol. When ratifying that agreement in 1993 the Government declined to avail of that possibility and, therefore, in honouring our international obligations we are precluded from using the death penalty. However, aside from those important international obligations it is the Government's fundamental belief that the death penalty is intrinsically wrong and there should be no exception to that principle, even in time of war. The Bill is a public and positive manifestation by the Government of that belief.</P>
    <P>Senators referred to the use of the death penalty in other jurisdictions. The Government believes the death penalty is intrinsically wrong, irrespective of where it is carried out, and it will continue to support its abolition in all other jurisdictions at appropriate international fora. I have noted the strong views of Members on the use of the death penalty in other jurisdictions and I will bring them to the attention of the Minister for Foreign Affairs.</P>
    <P>Senator Quinn referred to the implications which the prohibition on the death penalty enshrined in the Constitution might have for extradition of a person to the US. It is already the position in this State and in most, if not all, EU member states that a person cannot be extradited to a jurisdiction where the death penalty is used without a guarantee that the person will not be executed. Such a scenario arose during my time as Minister in the case of Beth Ann Carpenter. That occurred approximately two years ago and she was only extradited to the US after I had received an absolute guarantee from the American authorities that she would not be executed if returned there. She was subsequently returned and was not executed. I do not know how the case progressed following her departure from this jurisdiction. However, I have no wish to change this position. It would be unjustifiable to send a person abroad to suffer a fate which we in this jurisdiction consider to be fundamentally unacceptable.</P>
    <P>Senator Norris, during his familiarly colourful contribution, referred to the execution of Anne Boleyn, the mother of Queen Elizabeth I. There is no more celebrated case of abuse of the death penalty than that by the queen's father, Henry VIII, who had six wives, two of whom were executed.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MadeleineTaylorQuinn" hpid="Mrs. Taylor-Quinn Mrs. Taylor-Quinn">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Taylor-Quinn</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister has come a long way.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnODonoghue" hpid="Mr. O'Donoghue Mr. O'Donoghue">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Donoghue</NameTxt>
      <P>Queen Elizabeth I on one occasion said England may have had greater monarchs and would no doubt have a greater monarch than herself but that England never had and never would have a monarch who loved her people as well. Unfortunately, the queen was no stranger to utilising the death penalty herself.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="559" /> However, we have come a considerable way over the past 400 years and I am satisfied the constitutional amendment, when passed by the people, will signify to the entire world that we, as a civilisation, on this island do not subscribe to the death penalty. We will help, in doing so, the cause for the abolition of the death penalty in other jurisdictions. The death penalty is, unfortunately, commonplace in many jurisdictions but, as Senators outlined, it has never led to reduced crime rates. If anything, it has led to resentment and rebellion where it has been practised.</P>
    <P>I am convinced the people will follow the lead of the Members of both Houses of the Oireachtas and support the referendum. They will strike a serious blow for humanity in doing so.</P>
    <P>Cuireadh agus aontaíodh an cheist.</P>
    <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="An Bille um an Aonú Leasú is Fiche ar an mBunreacht (Uimh. 2), 2001: Céim an Choiste agus na Céimeanna a" RHead="bheidh Fágtha. Twenty-first Amendment of the Constitution (No. 2) Bill, 2001: Committee and Remaining Stages">
    <Title>An Bille um an Aonú Leasú is Fiche ar an mBunreacht (Uimh. 2), 2001: Céim an Choiste agus na Céimeanna a bheidh Fágtha.   Twenty-first Amendment of the Constitution (No. 2) Bill, 2001: Committee and Remaining Stages.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="BrianMullooly" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>As the substance of the debate on the Bill will relate to the wording of the proposed constitutional amendment contained in the Schedule to the Bill and since it would be appropriate to have that Schedule decided upon before deciding on section 1 of the Bill, which provides for its insertion into the Constitution, I suggest that the House postpone consideration of sections 1 and 2 until after the Schedule shall have been agreed.</P>
      <P>This is a procedure which has been adopted on Committee Stage in the Seanad in the case of previous Bills to amend the Constitution and which I suggest would lend itself to a more logically ordered debate. I, therefore, propose, in accordance with Standing Order 107, that consideration of sections 1 and 2 of the Bill be postponed until the Schedule shall have been disposed of. Is that agreed? Agreed.</P>
      <P>Aontaíodh an Sceideal.</P>
      <P>Schedule agreed to.</P>
      <P>Aontaíodh alt a 1 agus a 2.</P>
      <P>Sections 1 and 2 agreed to.</P>
      <P>Aontaíodh an Teideal.</P>
      <P>Title agreed to.</P>
      <P>Tuairiscíodh an Bille gan leasuithe agus ritheadh é.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Bill reported without amendment and passed.<Col N="560" /></P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Ráiteas faoi Eolas do Vótálaithe: Tairiscint." RHead="Statement for Information of Voters: Motion">
    <Title>Ráiteas faoi Eolas do Vótálaithe: Tairiscint.   Statement for Information of Voters: Motion.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="JohnCreganFF" hpid="Mr. J. Cregan Mr. J. Cregan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J. Cregan</NameTxt>
      <P>Tairgim:</P>
      <P>Go ndéanfar an ráiteas atá leagtha amach sa Sceideal a ghabhann leis an Rún seo a fhorordú mar eolas do vótálaithe de bhun alt 23 d'Acht an Reifrinn, 1994 (Uimh. 12 de 1994), i ndáil leis an togra chun an Bunreacht a leasú, atá ar áireamh sa Bhille um an Aonú Leasú is Fiche ar an mBunreacht (Uimh. 2), 2001, agus is ábhar do reifreann bunreachta.</P>
      <P Just="Center">An Sceideal</P>
      <P>1.Is é atá beartaithe leis an mBille um an Aonú Leasú is Fiche ar an mBunreacht (Uimh. 2), 2001, na leasuithe seo a leanas a dhéanamh ar an mBunreacht:</P>
      <P>In Airteagal 13.6,', taobh amuigh de chásanna breithe báis,' a scriosadh;</P>
      <P>In Airteagal 15.5, an fo-alt seo a leanas a chur isteach:</P>
      <P>&lsquo;2ºNí cead don Oireachtas aon dlí a achtú lena ndéanfar socrú chun pionós an bháis a ghearradh.';</P>
      <P>In Airteagal 28.3.3º, 'seachas Airteagal 15.5.2º' a chur isteach i ndiaidh 'sa Bhunreacht seo';</P>
      <P>In Airteagal 40.4, fo-alt 5º a scriosadh.</P>
      <P>2.MÁ THOILÍONN TÚ leis an togra, cuir X os coinne an fhocail TÁ ar an bpáipéar ballóide.</P>
      <P>3.MURA dTOILÍONN TÚ leis an togra, cuir X os coinne an fhocail NÍL ar an bpáipéar ballóide.</P>
      <P>4.Is féidir cóip den Bhille a iniúchadh nó a fháil saor in aisce in aon Phost-Oifig.</P>
      <P>I move:</P>
      <P>That the statement set out in the Schedule to this Resolution be prescribed for the information of voters pursuant to section 23 of the Referendum Act, 1994 (No. 12 of 1994), in relation to the proposal to amend the Constitution which is contained in the Twenty-first Amendment of the Constitution (No. 2) Bill, 2001, and is the subject of a constitutional referendum.</P>
      <P Just="Center">Schedule</P>
      <P>1.The Twenty-first Amendment of the Constitution (No. 2) Bill, 2001, proposes to make the following amendments to the Constitution:</P>
      <P>In Article 13.6, to delete ', except in capital cases,';</P>
      <P>In Article 15.5, to insert the following subsection:</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>&lsquo;2ºThe Oireachtas shall not enact any <Col N="561" /> law providing for the imposition of the death penalty.';</P>
    <P>In Article 28.3.3º, to insert &lsquo;other than Article 15.5.2º' after &lsquo;Constitution';</P>
    <P>In Article 40.4, to delete subsection 5º.</P>
    <P>2.IF YOU APPROVE of the proposal, mark X opposite the word YES on the ballot paper.</P>
    <P>3.IF YOU DO NOT APPROVE of the proposal, mark X opposite the word NO on the ballot paper.</P>
    <P>4.A copy of the Bill can be inspected or obtained free of charge at any Post Office.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>Cuireadh agus aontaíodh an cheist.</P>
    <P>
    </P>
    <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Ordú an Reifrinn (An Páipéar Ballóide), 2001: Tairiscint." RHead="Referendum (Ballot Paper) Order, 2001: Motion">
    <Title>Ordú an Reifrinn (An Páipéar Ballóide), 2001: Tairiscint.   Referendum (Ballot Paper) Order, 2001: Motion.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="JohnCreganFF" hpid="Mr. J. Cregan Mr. J. Cregan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J. Cregan</NameTxt>
      <P>Tairgim:</P>
      <P>Go gceadaíonn Seanad Éireann an tOrdú seo a leanas ina dhréacht:</P>
      <P>Ordú an Reifrinn (An Páipéar Ballóide), 2001,</P>
      <P>Ordú ar leagadh cóip de i bhfoirm dréachta faoi bhráid Sheanad Éireann an 4ú lá d'Aibreán, 2001.</P>
      <P>I move:</P>
      <P>That Seanad Éireann approves the following Order in draft:</P>
      <P>Referendum (Ballot Paper) Order, 2001,</P>
      <P>a copy of which Order in draft form was laid before Seanad Éireann on 4th day of April, 2001.</P>
      <P>Cuireadh agus aontaíodh an cheist.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="An Bille um an Tríú Leasú is Fiche ar an mBunreacht, 2001: An Dara Céim." RHead="Twenty-third Amendment of the Constitution Bill, 2001: Second Stage">
    <Title>An Bille um an Tríú Leasú is Fiche ar an mBunreacht, 2001: An Dara Céim.   Twenty-third Amendment of the Constitution Bill, 2001: Second Stage.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="BrianMullooly" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>No. 5, motion pursuant to section 23 of the Referendum Act, 1994, prescribing a formal statement for the information of voters to be included on the polling card will be debated in conjunction with Second Stage of the Bill and will be formally moved when the debate on the Bill is concluded.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="562" /> Tairgeadh an cheist: &ldquo;Go léifear an Bille an Dara hUair anois.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That the Bill be now read a Second Time.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="BrianCowen" hpid="Mr. Cowen Mr. Cowen">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Foreign Affairs (Mr. Cowen)</NameTxt>
      <P>On 17 July 1998 the Statute of the International Criminal Court was adopted in Rome by the United Nations Diplomatic Conference of Plenipotentiaries. Ireland was an active participant at that conference and subsequently signed the Rome statute on 7 October 1998. I have been advised that before the State may ratify the statute, and thereby become a party to it, an amendment of the Constitution is required. It is the purpose of the Twenty-third Amendment of the Constitution Bill, 2001, to provide for this amendment. If the proposed amendment is approved by the people in a referendum, as I sincerely hope it will be, the Constitution will be amended to enable the State to ratify the Rome statute.</P>
      <P>The adoption of the statute in 1998 was the conclusion of over 50 years of work towards an international criminal court, the need for which was recognised as early as 1948 by the United Nations General Assembly. A draft statute was prepared by the International Law Commission in the early 1950s but work was not resumed on it until 1989 at the request of Trinidad and Tobago. Events in the former Yugoslavia and in Rwanda in the 1990s prompted the United Nations Security Council to establish <i>ad hoc</i> tribunals to bring to justice those responsible for the atrocities committed in those places. The establishment of such tribunals for the first time since the Second World War focused minds on the need to establish a permanent international criminal court with the power to deal with such crimes in the future. In 1994 the International Law Commission submitted its draft statute to the General Assembly and from then on progress was swift. The General Assembly established the <i>Ad Hoc</i> Committee on the Establishment of an International Criminal Court to consider major substantive issues arising from the draft and this committee met twice in 1995. After considering the committee's report, the General Assembly created the Preparatory Committee on the Establishment of an International Criminal Court to draw up a draft text for submission to a diplomatic conference. That committee held its final session and completed the drafting of the text in March and April of 1998.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The United Nations Diplomatic Conference on the Establishment of an International Criminal Court was held in Rome from 15 June to 17 July 1998, and the result was the statute which we now seek to ratify. This statute provides for the establishment of a permanent international criminal court, related to the United Nations system, with jurisdiction over persons in respect of genocide, crimes against humanity, war crimes and the crime of aggression. The statute of the court is an international agreement which will enter into <Col N="563" /> force approximately two months after 60 states have become party to it. By 31 December 2000, 139 states, including Ireland, had signed the statute and to date 29 have ratified it or acceded to it.</P>
    <P>Great progress has been made in international human rights law and international humanitarian law during the twentieth century. The Universal Declaration of Human Rights, the International Covenant on Civil and Political Rights and, in Europe, the European Convention on Human Rights, all provide guarantees of respect for human rights, including during time of armed conflict. There have also been significant developments in international humanitarian law, the rules specifically intended to protect persons in time of armed conflict. The four Geneva Conventions of 1949 are the Amelioration of the Condition of the Wounded and Sick in Armed Forces in the Field, the Amelioration of the Condition of Wounded, Sick and Shipwrecked Members of Armed Forces at Sea, the Treatment of Prisoners of War and the Protection of Civilian Persons in Time of War. Two Protocols to these conventions were adopted in 1977 and relate to the protection of victims of international armed conflicts and of non-international armed conflicts respectively. While these international agreements establish clear rules which must be observed, even in a time of war, until now these have not been supported by an adequate international enforcement mechanism. The need for such a mechanism was recognised early on as illustrated by the Convention on the Prevention and Punishment of the Crime of Genocide adopted in 1948. Article 6 of that convention allows for trial by the courts of the state where an act of genocide occurs or by &ldquo;such international penal tribunal as may have jurisdiction with respect to those Contracting Parties which shall have accepted its jurisdiction&rdquo;.</P>
    <P>When the UN General Assembly adopted this convention in 1948 it invited the International Law Commission to study the desirability and possibility of establishing a judicial organ for the trial of persons charged with genocide. That was found to be both desirable and possible and a draft statute was prepared in 1951 and revised in 1953. Although the question of the establishment of an international criminal court was considered periodically thereafter, Cold War politics hindered significant developments and it was not until 1989 that the General Assembly asked the International Law Commission to resume work on a statute for an international criminal court.</P>
    <P>While work was progressing on the draft statute, events in the former Yugoslavia and in Rwanda prompted the United Nations Security Council to establish <i>ad hoc</i> tribunals to try those responsible for the grave violations of human rights and humanitarian law occurring there. The International Criminal Tribunals for the former Yugoslavia and for Rwanda have certainly done great work, nevertheless <i>ad hoc</i> tribunals of this sort suffer from many disadvantages. Such tri<Col N="564" /> bunals can only be established after crimes have been committed so there may be delays between the commission of the crime and the establishment of the tribunal. The jurisdiction of such tribunals is limited to the events which prompted their establishment and questions will always be raised as to why <i>ad hoc</i> tribunals are established to deal with some situations and not with others. This is particularly unsatisfactory as it allows both the victims and the perpetrators of international crimes to challenge the motivation behind the establishment of tribunals. The victims of crimes for which no tribunal is established will complain that tribunals are not established in the interests of justice or to vindicate their rights, but only when it is politically expedient, while accused persons brought before an <i>ad hoc</i> tribunal will claim to be the victims of victor's justice. Criticism of this sort undermines the work of <i>ad hoc</i> international criminal tribunals and the Rome Statute of the International Criminal Court addresses these difficulties by providing for a permanent independent institution within the United Nations system.</P>
    <P>In 13 parts and 128 articles, the statute deals with the establishment of the court, its jurisdiction and the general principles of criminal law to be applied. It sets out the composition of the court, its administration, the procedures for investigation, prosecution and trial, the penalties which can be imposed on conviction and provides for appeals. States parties are under obligation to co-operate with the court and provision is made for the enforcement of judgments and the carrying out of sentences. The statute further provides for an assembly of states parties and for the financing of the court. The court will sit at the Hague in the Netherlands and the assembly will be established when the statute comes into force. The assembly will consist of one representative from each state and elect 18 full-time judges who will be persons of high moral character, impartiality and integrity possessing the qualifications required in their respective states for appointment to the highest judicial offices.</P>
    <P>As is to be expected, the judges will be independent in the performance of their functions. There may not be more than one judge of the same nationality and in selecting judges the states parties will take into account the need for the membership of the court to represent the principal legal systems of the world, equitable geographical representation and a fair representation of female and male judges.</P>
    <P>There will also be an independent Office of the Prosecutor and the prosecutor, like the judges, will be elected by the Assembly of States Parties by secret ballot. A situation in which a crime appears to have been committed may be referred to the prosecutor of the court by a state party or the Security Council of the United Nations acting under Chapter VII of the UN charter, or the prosecutor may initiate an investigation. Where a state party has referred a situation to the prosecutor or the prosecutor has initiated the investi<Col N="565" /> gation, the court may exercise its jurisdiction if the state on the territory of which the alleged crime was committed is a party to the statute or if the person accused of the crime is a national of a state party. States parties are obliged to co-operate fully with the court in its investigation and prosecution of crimes within its jurisdiction. The statute contains numerous provisions governing the conduct of a trial and the rights of an accused which will ensure due process will be observed.</P>
    <P>The court will be complementary to national legal systems. The primary obligation to investigate crimes covered by the statute and prosecute the perpetrators will remain with the states parties. Only where the state party in question is unwilling or unable genuinely to investigate the crimes alleged or prosecute the accused person may the court exercise its jurisdiction. In this way, the court provides an additional means of administering justice, where serious international crimes are committed, without in any way detracting from existing domestic structures which states may have put in place.</P>
    <P>In addition to its function in electing judges and the prosecutor, the Assembly of States Parties will also be responsible for the budget of the court and provide management oversight to the president of the court, the prosecutor and the registrar regarding the administration of the court. Draft rules of procedure and evidence were adopted by the preparatory commission for the court in June last year. These provide further detail on the way in which the court will function. It is envisaged that the assembly will adopt these rules and the financial rules and regulations. The court will be funded by contributions from states parties and the United Nations and may also accept voluntary contributions.</P>
    <P>That sums up how the court will function. I will now discuss the crimes within the court's jurisdiction.</P>
    <P>Under Article 5 of the statute the court's jurisdiction shall be limited to the most serious crimes of concern to the international community as a whole, namely, the crime of genocide, crimes against humanity, war crimes and the crime of aggression. The court will exercise jurisdiction over the crime of genocide, crimes against humanity and war crimes committed after the statute enters into force. The court will not, however, exercise jurisdiction over the crime of aggression until the provision is adopted by the states parties defining the crime and setting out the conditions under which the court shall exercise jurisdiction with respect to this crime. A review conference is to be held seven years after the entry into force of the statute and a provision governing the crime of aggression may be adopted at that conference. The definitions of genocide, crimes against humanity and war crimes contained in the statute codify existing international law.</P>
    <P>The 1948 Convention on the Prevention and Punishment of the Crime of Genocide provides <Col N="566" /> that genocide means any of the following acts committed with intent to destroy in whole or in part a national, ethical, racial or religious group such as killing members of the group; causing serious bodily or mental harm to members of the group; deliberately inflicting on the group conditions of life calculated to bring about its physical destruction in whole or in part; imposing measures intended to prevent births within the group; and forcibly transferring children of the group to another group. This definition of genocide has been incorporated in the Rome statute.</P>
    <P>Like genocide, crimes against humanity can be committed both in time of war and peace. Particularly serious violations of human rights such as murder, extermination, slavery, forcible transfer of population, unlawful imprisonment, torture, sexual violence, persecution of a group, enforced disappearance and apartheid constitute crimes against humanity when committed as part of a widespread or systematic attack directed against the civilian population.</P>
    <P>War crimes, for the purpose of the statute, include grave breaches of the Geneva Convention of 1949 as well as attacks during armed conflict against civilians and humanitarian and peacekeeping missions, attacks directed against religious, educational and cultural buildings, pillaging, rape, sexual slavery and enforced prostitution and the use of child soldiers.</P>
    <P>The disgust we all feel at such crimes was illustrated by the debate in the Dáil. Many Deputies cited shocking examples of these crimes which have taken place within the past ten years. It is our duty to do all within our power to prevent the commission of such crimes and ensure that if they are committed, their perpetrators are brought to justice. The establishment of the International Criminal Court should act as a deterrent to individuals and governments contemplating the commission of such crimes in that they will be aware that if they carry out the crimes, they can no longer confidently expect to escape punishment.</P>
    <P>As I have explained, the Rome statute creates a new international jurisdiction for the trial of persons suspected of having committed the most serious crimes of concern to the international community. Article 34.1 of the Constitution provides that justice shall be administered in courts established by law by judges appointed in the manner provided by the Constitution. I have been advised by the Attorney General that the Rome statute of the International Criminal Court provides for the administration of justice outside the terms of this constitutional provision and that, consequently, an amendment of the Constitution is needed before the State may ratify the statute. It is, therefore, proposed to amend the Constitution by the addition of a new section 9 to Article 29 of the Constitution allowing the State to ratify the Rome statute of the International Criminal Court. This provision will read as follows: &ldquo;The State may ratify the Rome Statute of <Col N="567" /> the International Criminal Court done at Rome on the 17th day of July, 1998&rdquo;.</P>
    <P>Careful consideration should be given to any constitutional amendment. The Constitution is, after all, the foundation upon which the State is built. A proposed amendment should not be examined in isolation, but in the light of the Constitution as a whole. The amendment proposed in the Bill stands up to such examination and complements existing provisions of the Constitution. Under the heading &ldquo;International Relations&rdquo;, Article 29 begins by affirming Ireland's &ldquo;devotion to the ideal of peace and friendly co-operation amongst nations founded on international justice and morality&rdquo;, continues by affirming our &ldquo;adherence to the principle of the pacific settlement of international disputes by international arbitration or judicial determination&rdquo;, and then states that &ldquo;Ireland accepts the generally recognised principles of international law as its rule of conduct in its relations with other States&rdquo;.</P>
    <P>By ratifying the Rome statute and participating in the International Criminal Court we will demonstrate our belief in the principles set out at the beginning of Article 29 of the Constitution. In the Preamble to the Rome statute, the states parties recognise that the grave crimes within the court's jurisdiction threaten the peace, security and well-being of the world, determine to put an end to impunity for the perpetrators of these crimes and thus contribute to the prevention of such crimes, and resolve to guarantee lasting respect for and the enforcement of international justice. We committed ourselves to these principles when we enacted the Constitution over 60 years ago. The court will provide an international mechanism for the enforcement of these principles.</P>
    <P>The establishment of the International Criminal Court will be one of the most significant developments in international law since the Second World War. It is intended that the court will have the power to enforce human rights law and humanitarian law throughout the world. The events of the past 100 years, particularly over the past ten years, highlight the need for an international judicial body with such powers. By amending the Constitution as proposed in the Bill we take the first and most important step towards ratification of the Rome statute and demonstrate once again our support for the statute and the principles it embodies. I, therefore, unreservedly recommend the Bill to the House.<i></i></P>
    <Speaker pid="JohnConnor" hpid="Mr. Connor Mr. Connor">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Connor</NameTxt>
      <P>I welcome the Minister and particularly the fact that we are enacting this legislation to allow the constitutional amendment to be put to the people. The Cathaoirleach is aware that on numerous occasions on the Order of Business I inquired when the Government would present this House and the Lower House with the legislation necessary to ratify the Rome statute of the International Criminal Court. I understand that, yesterday, Andorra &ndash; a small European country <Col N="568" />&ndash; ratified the statute, bringing to 30 the number of states which have done so. Only when 60 of the 160 states which signed the treaty in Rome in July 1998 have ratified the statute and incorporated it into their domestic laws will we be in a position to establish the court. We are, therefore, only halfway there. Those monitoring the situation predict that during the next year up to 50 states will have ratified the statute and that it may take 18 months before the requisite 60 states ratify it. I hope the referendum in this country will pass and that whatever further legislation may be necessary will be introduced in order to incorporate the statute into law here. Nothing will be done on this side of the House to impede progress.</P>
      <P>The Minister was correct in describing this as a seminal step forward in terms of establishing human rights law throughout the world and also in engendering respect for the rule of law. Kofi Annan, the Secretary General of the United Nations, closed the Rome conference in 1997 by stating that this would be a giant step forward in the march towards universal human rights and the rule of law. In the past 100 years we have witnessed the worst violence in the history of humankind. In the past 50 years alone more than 250 conflicts have erupted around the world, more than 86 million civilians &ndash; mostly women and children &ndash; have died and more than 170 million people were stripped of their rights, property and dignity in these conflicts. Most of these victims have been forgotten and few of the perpetrators brought to justice. The figures to which I refer surely make the case in favour of the establishment of this particular court institution.</P>
      <P>The United Nations General Assembly first recognised the need for a permanent mechanism to prosecute mass murderers and war criminals as long ago as 1948, in the aftermath of the famous trials at Nuremberg and Tokyo. This matter has been under discussion at the United Nations since that date but, as the Minister stated, the advent of Cold War politics meant that agreement could not be reached. There were echoes of Cold War politics in Rome when the negotiations on the statute took place. Two <i>ad hoc</i> tribunals were established by the Security Council in recent years to deal specifically with the egregious crimes committed in the Former Yugoslavia and Rwanda during periods of internal conflict. Outrages, albeit lesser in nature to those which occurred in the 1990s, continue to occur in parts of the Former Yugoslavia such as Kosovo, Macedonia, etc., but few of the perpetrators of the most serious crimes committed there have been arraigned before the special court in The Hague. This is a great pity.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I sympathise with the new regime in Belgrade regarding the position it has adopted in respect of Mr. Milosevic. Immediately after his removal from office, the international community began a campaign to have Mr. Milosevic arrested and transported to The Hague for trial. However, the new Yugoslav authorities have indicated that he must first stand trial for the crimes he committed <Col N="569" /> in his own country and it appears that there is ample evidence against him in this regard. I am inclined to sympathise with the position of the new Yugoslav Government. If serious charges are levelled against someone such as Mr. Milosevic in his home country, the international community must recognise the right of that state to bring him to trial in the first instance.</P>
    <P>It was interesting that 160 countries were represented at the Rome convention in 1997, but seven of these &ndash; including the United States of America, China and Israel &ndash; did not sign the statute. The vote on the statute was unrecorded. Some states indicated the reason they did not vote, while others failed to say why they voted against it. It was interesting that Israel stated that it failed to comprehend the reason the action of transferring populations into an occupied territory was included in the list of war crimes and this was the reason it offered for voting against the establishment of an international criminal court. The United States had many misgivings because, on foot of its international role, it believed that many of its operatives abroad who work with the CIA and other agencies might be arrested and arraigned before the court. The statute was agreed during the regime of President Clinton and the excuses offered by the United States for not signing it were lame.</P>
    <P>It is a great pity that one of the world's greatest powers found itself in a position of being unable to sign such a statute. The same is true of China and Israel, a state which seeks sympathy and support from the international community in respect of its conflict with the Palestinians and the Arabs. It did not do much for Israel's case when it did not sign the statute, particularly in view of the lengthy discussions which took place in respect of it since 1948.</P>
    <P>I have a number of difficulties with the statute and would like the Minister to clarify some aspects of Ireland's position. During the conference in Rome, huge pressure was exerted to have aggression included as a crime to be prosecuted and dealt with by the court. It was not included, however, because there was insufficient agreement among the states negotiating at Rome on what should be the definition of aggression.</P>
    <P>Aggression is a particularly serious crime. Some of the most appalling things that happened in the 20th century resulted from acts of aggression. I refer, for example, to attacks by powerful countries on weaker states. Aggression remains a threat. I accept that wars have become more localised and are more civil or regional in nature, but major acts of aggression remain prevalent. The potential for such acts to occur remains great. I am aware that a review conference will take place seven years after the ICC comes into force. That is a long period in terms of, perhaps, finally deciding that the serious crime of aggression can be dealt with by the court.</P>
    <P>A great deal of discussion took place in Rome in relation to the crime of terrorism. Again, no agreement was reached or on how it should be <Col N="570" /> approached. That is a great deficiency of the statute because terrorism is a most serious crime. Acts of terrorism are usually carried out against humanity. Terrorism can also be part of genocide or a war crime. It is a great pity that it was not included in the statute and that a definition could not be agreed during those three days in Rome in 1997.</P>
    <P>Another matter to which I wish to refer is drug trafficking, which is a most serious crime. Nothing is more responsible for destroying the lives of great numbers across the globe than drug trafficking. This trade is carried on by some of the best organised criminal gangs in the world, which, as a result of the profits they accrue from their activities, can deploy huge resources. In Rome there was no agreement that drug trafficking should be included in the list of crimes to be dealt with by the court. That is a pity.</P>
    <P>The Minister dealt with the definitions of genocide, crimes against humanity and war crimes. My definition of genocide closely coincides with that of the Minister, for example, killings and acts causing serious harm or committed with intent to destroy in whole or in part a national, ethnic, racial or religious group. The term ethnic cleansing, which is a new term, is not used. The removal of a population from a territory is ethnic cleansing, but the term should be clearly defined. That is a new phenomenon of war. The use of sexual violence as an instrument of war is also new. The rape of women in Yugoslavia was used as a systematic weapon of war. That is not included in the definitions.</P>
    <P>There will be preliminary negotiations before the International Criminal Court starts its operations and I know the review conference cannot take place for seven years. However, we must draw attention to ethnic cleansing and to the use of rape as a systematic weapon of war, which is a serious crime. Rape is mentioned but the systematic use of rape as a weapon of war, as we saw in Yugoslavia probably for the first time, must be clearly defined.  </P>
    <P>Crimes against humanity cover those specifically listed, such as prohibited acts committed as part of a widespread or systematic attack against civilian populations. Such acts include murder, extermination, rape, sexual slavery, the enforced disappearance of persons and apartheid. Sexual slavery is mentioned but all forms of slavery should be defined. Thanks to Trócaire, there is a new awareness of the international crime of slavery. Millions of people are sold every year into various forms of slavery.</P>
    <P>I work with the Parliamentary Assembly of the Council of Europe on domestic slavery in Europe. We have found that hundreds of people are kept in servitude in diplomatic and consular missions in Europe. Certain countries bring people to work with them and they use their diplomatic immunity under the 1961 Vienna Convention, which means they are not governed by the labour laws of the host state relating to the time spent at work, minimum wages, etc. People <Col N="571" /> are kept in servitude and their passports are taken from them.</P>
    <P>Domestic slavery is one aspect of slavery, but sexual slavery is the only one mentioned. Slavery is wider than that and it is a serious crime against humanity. We need to broaden the definition and to give a lead in that regard. These definitions were supplied by a leading NGO which has tracked the progress of the International Criminal Court towards ratification. This is a narrow definition, although sexual slavery is a serious crime. The definition of slavery, whether sexual, domestic or otherwise, must be clearly outlined so that people committing these crimes are answerable before this court.</P>
    <P>As regards reparations, I do not know to what extent the court would have competence to make reparations to individuals or groups of people who have been the victims of war crimes and of crimes against humanity. It appears the statute is weak in that regard and that it needs to be strengthened. There was much argument in Rome that the competences of the court could be pushed too far to the extent that it would not have the resources to deal with such issues. That was the argument made when discussing the case for including the crime of drugs trafficking. We now pay more attention to the concept of restitution and restorative justice than we did and rightly so. This court should have a strong hand in terms of restitution, reparations and restorative justice.</P>
    <P>Some of the worst criminals who can be brought before this court are high Government officials, military leaders or leaders of their own country. One knows of many such people. How strong is the statute in terms of prosecuting military leaders who may take refuge in their own country? What is the power of the United Nations Security Council in relation to a member state which may not wish to turn over a leading army general who may have a lot of political influence where the state of democracy is weak? I hate to mention a country such as the Philippines, but there are countries around the world where the military elite is as powerful as the political elite. The political elite should not be called that if it is elected. The Minister might deal in his reply with the issue of how amenable a state party can be made to turn over someone where there is serious evidence they have committed any of the crimes mentioned.</P>
    <P>I am delighted the court will not have the power to enforce the death penalty. This afternoon we discussed the final elimination of the death penalty by a Bill to amend the Constitution. I am delighted we will not have the death penalty in this country again. I am also delighted in the context of this legislation that it is specifically outlawed. The International Criminal Court sitting in the Hague cannot impose the death penalty, irrespective of how heinous the crime with which it is dealing. That is an enlightened and civilised approach. People will get long sentences, <Col N="572" /> which they will deserve. We must always respect everyone's human dignity, irrespective of whether they have committed heinous crimes. We cannot sink to their level. I am delighted that matter has been dealt with.</P>
    <P>I raised questions about compensation for victims. If there are shortcomings, this country should highlight them. We should highlight the need to outlaw all forms of slavery, not just a narrowly defined form of sexual slavery, as is included in the definitions. There is more known today about the modern international slave trade than there was three years ago when the participants in the conference enacted this statute in Rome. Some of its definitions might be slightly dated. They must be updated before the court starts its operations, not seven years after it has come into effect. These are fundamental points.</P>
    <P>I am delighted this has been introduced. It says something about our Constitution that of the 30 states which have ratified it so far, none has had to hold a referendum before ratification. I understand that other states will not do so either. The NGO I spoke to this morning found that Ireland was the only state where it was necessary to hold a referendum to amend its Constitution or basic law. This makes us unique. It is a tribute to our Constitution in that it is very strong on sovereignty, including that of our courts.</P>
    <P>This is not an issue about which the public will get too excited. I hope the results of these referenda are given credibility by the fact that more than 50% of the people will vote in them. People may find the issues are remote and they may not know that a referendum will take place. However, as public representatives, we should do everything in our power to increase public awareness of these issues, particularly this very important human rights issue. We live in a free democracy, unlike millions of people.</P>
    <P>It is good that there will be a debate on the Nice Treaty. Clearly, I will ask people to vote yes, but others will call for a no vote and this will cause a public debate. This will increase public participation in the four referenda. People will vote on four ballot papers rather than just one, so the debate on the Nice Treaty might do us a service in getting a larger number of people out to vote.</P>
    <P>I was speaking without notes and may not have been very coherent. However, I hope the Minister understood the points I made and I ask him to take them on board.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MickLanigan" hpid="Mr. Lanigan Mr. Lanigan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lanigan</NameTxt>
      <P>I welcome the Minister here to discuss the Twenty-third Amendment of the Constitution Bill. This is a historic day for the Seanad with two proposed amendments being dealt with. The people will vote on them and they are two very important elements in ensuring our adherence to human rights throughout the world.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I welcome the fact that the Minister for Justice, Equality and Law Reform was here earlier to discuss formally abolishing the death penalty in all <Col N="573" /> circumstances. This amendment is also extremely welcome.</P>
    <P>It is a pity we have to set up an International Criminal Court. It shows that there has been a failure in the past and that the international community has not learnt lessons from past wars and other problems such as slavery. The establishment of the International Criminal Court is an advance on what we had in the recent past. The United Nations set up two <i>ad hoc</i> courts to deal with Rwanda and the former Yugoslavia. In the case of Rwanda, the tribunal met in Tanzania, under the chairmanship of Nelson Mandela at one stage. I am not sure who the previous chairman was, I believe he died. One of the chief advisers to the chair of that body was from the Department of Foreign Affairs and she played a vital role. She could see that there were huge problems with that court. It was difficult to find out who had caused the genocide and to get them to court.</P>
    <P>There was considerable publicity over the recent court appearance of people including nuns. We do not know whether these people are guilty, but the evidence against them seems quite strong. However, that tribunal has not got to the people who really created the problems in Rwanda.</P>
    <P>I visited the court in The Hague when some soldiers were brought before it. It was difficult to make certain that the right people were brought before the court and to get evidence from what was an internal conflict. Setting up the International Criminal Court, with the participation of so many states, is very important. It will ensure that if somebody comes here having escaped from a country where they might have been charged, even if we have no extradition treaty with that country, they could be brought before the courts here.</P>
    <P>There was mention of the instigators of international crimes and plunder. It is a pity major economic powers or entities will not be brought before the International Criminal Court. There have been cases of plunder on states, which subsequently descended into civil war. As mentioned by Senator Connor, in the past month or two, Trócaire has highlighted the problem of economic slavery and this needs to be looked into. In many cases, economic slavery is helped by companies from developed countries. Within the chocolate industry, there are slaves in Sierra Leone and the Côte-d'Ivoire who are involved in the production of the cocoa bean.</P>
    <P>I am glad Senator Quinn is here. I did a survey in Kilkenny about fair trade products and found that apart from the Oxfam office, they were only available in the Superquinn stores. This is very important when discussing the crime of international plunder.</P>
    <P>The Minister said that the states parties will take into account the need for the membership of the court to represent the principal legal systems of the world, equitable geographical representation and the fair representation of female and male judges. It is important that the geographical <Col N="574" /> representation element of setting up the court is adhered to in a fair manner. Most international bodies have not adhered to a policy of equitable geographical representation. One need only look at the United Nations and the unfortunate situation where too few countries, the permanent members of the Security Council, control what happens. The UN General Assembly will elect 18 full-time judges to sit on the court, although getting full-time judges is a current difficulty. Language is also a problem as we do not know who will come before the court. The impartiality of judges is of extreme importance as the court will stand or fall by the actions of the judges appointed.</P>
    <P>It is unfortunate that some major countries have not signed up to or ratified the treaty setting up the International Criminal Court. There will be major problems if these countries do not sign up. I do not want to discuss particular countries, although I could speak lengthily about the Middle Eastern situation and Israel's actions towards the Palestinians. However, we must make an attempt to get as many influential countries involved as possible, as there is no point having a group of countries which do not have the ammunition and strength to push the implementation of the working of the court. If the major powers are not involved it will be difficult to make progress.</P>
    <P>I am unsure whether the financing of the court will come through the participating states. Individual or outside donations can be given and the United Nations will give some payment, but there could still be a veto if a country not involved in ratification of the treaty were to attempt to block the workings of the court.</P>
    <P>The crime of genocide is endemic in many parts of the world. The situation in East Timor is an example of an attempt to eliminate a population. No effort has yet been made by the international community to curb the power of Indonesia because of its action in East Timor. The disgust that is felt at the situation in many parts of the world is something of which we should be cognisant. In conjunction with the setting up of the court we must try to protect cultures in areas where genocide has taken place. We must strengthen conflict prevention measures around the world. Little effort has been made in this area in the past, even in cases where it was known that conflict was imminent. Conflict prevention must go hand in hand with the setting up of the International Criminal Court.</P>
    <P>I am glad the people have the opportunity to vote in this referendum and I hope that there will be a good turn-out. The people will react to the two areas raised in the House today, the removal of the death penalty from the Constitution and the setting up of the International Criminal Court. We do not have to sell these issues very hard to the people. They are mature enough to realise that aggression and other problems need to be tackled. The International Criminal Court will be a way of demonstrating that the actions of aggressors will not go unnoticed as in the past. <Col N="575" /> The court might prevent many of the crimes committed against peoples in recent years.</P>
    <P>Senator Connor said that the greatest crimes against humanity occurred in the past 100 years, but some of the worst wars and killings happened long before this century. We must ensure that there is a change in attitude by the end of this century. This will be difficult. I welcome the proposed amendment of the Constitution. I hope that there is a large turn-out and a resounding yes vote on the question of the International Criminal Court.</P>
    <Speaker pid="FergalQuinn" hpid="Mr. Quinn Mr. Quinn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Quinn</NameTxt>
      <P>I wish to share my time with Senator Norris.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BrianMullooly" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Is that agreed? Agreed.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FergalQuinn" hpid="Mr. Quinn Mr. Quinn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Quinn</NameTxt>
      <P>I welcome this Bill and I hope and expect that the people will approve this amendment in the referendum. I was tempted to congratulate the Government and the Minister but I will refrain from making that gesture. I am impressed by the relative speed with which this important issue is being dealt with. The Rome statute was agreed nearly three years ago and 30 countries have already completed the ratification process, including a majority of our partners in the EU. Yet, by the lamentably slow standards with which Ireland normally approaches ratification of international agreements, to get to this point after only three years could almost be regarded as speeding.</P>
      <P>However, I reined in my enthusiasm when I realised that putting this issue to the people does not mean that ratification of the Rome statute by Ireland is imminent. Domestic legislation must first be put in order. It is clear from a parliamentary reply by the Minister for Foreign Affairs on 30 January last that this will be neither simple nor quick. In that reply the Minister pointed out that, apart from the people's approval, &ldquo;an in-depth analysis of the statute by the Department of Justice, Equality and Law Reform together with my Department, the Office of the Attorney General and other appropriate bodies is also necessary to determine the exact legislative and administrative measures which may need to be adopted for Ireland to be in a position to meet its obligations under this very complex statute.&rdquo;  From the detached, timeless nature of that phrasing I deduce that the in-depth analysis referred to has not yet begun. I also suspect that a gentle warning is being sent that this analysis is an open-ended process and that nobody has an idea of how long it will take to complete. Are we talking about months or years? My hunch is that it is the latter. Perhaps the Minister can be more specific as to the likely schedule. I hope that the process of in-depth analysis has already begun.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Given the uncertainty, the question arises whether this is the right time to put the issue before the people. We should agree a process by which matters would be put to referendum only <Col N="576" /> after necessary and relevant legislation was already passed. I am not sure if we have even started that process in this instance. If we adopted that as a practice, it would greatly improve the referendum process. In some cases it is desirable to publish the relevant legislation because it actually affects the question being put to the people. I am not suggesting that is the case in this instance, although it might well be in regard to the amendment on judicial behaviour which we will discuss later in the week.</P>
    <P>In the case of this Bill, the principle the people are being asked to endorse is fully spelt out in the Rome statute. However, by putting the question now rather than when the enabling legislation is ready we are asking the people to sign a cheque which, although not blank, is undated. The democratic process demands that we show our citizens greater respect. Rather than congratulate the Government on the relative speed with which it is proceeding on this matter, I question the wisdom of taking the referendum step of the process at this time. To do so is to put the cart before the horse. We should ensure all the legislation is ready before asking the people to decide on a particular issue. In that way they will be fully aware of what they are deciding on.</P>
    <P>Speed is important in ensuring the eventual success of the International Criminal Court. However, 60 ratifications are required to establish the court. The process has now reached the halfway point with some 30 ratifications having occurred. Ratification is, clearly, proceeding at a faster rate than many expected and it is important to maintain that momentum. The best way we could add to it would be to ratify the statute very quickly. As that does not seem likely, I suggest to the Minister that Ireland should make a financial contribution to the campaign for worldwide ratification. I am not sure whether such a financial contribution would be particularly helpful, but it would have a worthwhile impact on the campaign while firmly establishing Ireland's bona fides in the interval prior to us ratifying the statute.</P>
    <P>It is important that the court is established as soon as possible as it will not have any retrospective powers to try crimes committed prior to its establishment. I understand it will be unable to try crimes in a particular territory prior to the time that territory signed up to accept its jurisdiction. We must work towards obtaining the 60 ratifications necessary to bring the statute into force and push as quickly as possible for its universal adoption. Speed is of the essence in order that criminals can be apprehended and punished at an early stage and in deterring the commission of crimes in the first instance. The latter should be the court's primary objective. The law's real power is its ability to deter people from committing unlawful acts. If people know they are likely to be held responsible for their actions, they are more likely to think twice before committing crimes. It is always preferable to deter rather than punish. That is the reason it is important to have <Col N="577" /> a permanent court rather than rely on <i>ad hoc </i>tribunals of the type used in Rwanda and the former Yugoslavia.</P>
    <P>As tribunals are, invariably, established after the event, if at all, the possibility of being hauled before a tribunal is not likely to feature in a person's decision to commit a crime. If the International Criminal Court is established on a permanent footing, if the crimes within its remit are clearly defined and if it develops a good track record of investigating crimes and punishing those who commit them, it will become an effective deterrent. It will not eliminate war crimes or crimes against humanity, but it may contribute to their reduction.</P>
    <P>Such a situation is a long way down the road and today we are taking an early step on that journey. In supporting the Bill, I urge the Government to address the task of preparing the necessary legislation to make ratification possible and to give it real meaning by publishing a timeframe to complete the process. I hope the Minister will grasp that opportunity.</P>
    <Speaker pid="DavidNorris" hpid="Mr. Norris Mr. Norris">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norris</NameTxt>
      <P>I welcome the Minister and offer my unqualified support for the Bill and the proposed referendum. This is referendum season in the House and the referendum on the Rome statute is to be particularly welcomed. Some years ago I tabled a motion on the Order Paper seeking precisely what the Minister is delivering today. In 1996 I was one of a group of 800 parliamentarians from all over the world who signed a petition calling for the establishment of an international criminal court. The names of the petitioners were printed in newspapers on both sides of the Atlantic. I subsequently wrote to the then Minister in August 1997 seeking Ireland's support for the court and received a reply within three days from the then Minister's private secretary, Mr. James McIntyre, in which he indicated the positive attitude of the Department of Foreign Affairs to the matter. Earth Action and other groups have lobbied consistently for this legislation.</P>
      <P>We are really only beginning this process as a substantial number of countries are still required to ratify the statute. I visited Jerusalem during the Christmas period and was heartened to learn that the Clinton administration, prior to leaving office, decided to sign up to the statute. Its decision had a multiplier effect and, within one week, the Israelis overcame their serious reservations. That act, one of President Barak's last in government, was quite astonishing.  </P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>It is essential that the court be established. The first of these tribunals were established on an <i>ad hoc </i>basis in Tokyo and Nuremberg following World War II and we have had some similar arrangements since then. Such tribunals are not satisfactory because they convey the impression of victors' justice. They are also selective and lack the necessary machinery and consistency. I recently watched an interview with Mrs. Carla del Ponti, the Swiss female prosecutor in The Hague. She was quite convinced that she would get hold <Col N="578" /> of Milosevic. She also made the worrying statement that as far as she was aware, the whereabouts of people such as Ratko Mladic and Radovan Karadzic were well known. There was, however, a reluctance to apprehend them and Mrs. Ponti intended to make a direct request at the United Nations that an energetic attempt be made to secure the trial of these men before the appropriate tribunal in The Hague. Such practical issues would be considerably advanced by the creation of a permanent court.</P>
    <P>The Minister, helpfully, listed the definitions of the crimes which would be tried before the court. He referred to the 1946 Convention on the Prevention and Punishment of the Crime of Genocide. It is astonishing that in 1948 the first steps were taken towards the creation of this international court, the necessity for which was then recognised. It has taken more than 50 years to get to this stage.</P>
    <P>The Minister refers to forcibly transferring children of a group to another group. I would like him to bear this aspect in mind. Deputy Michael D. Higgins tabled a motion at a recent meeting of the Joint Committee on Foreign Affairs on the infringement of the human rights of the Australian Aboriginals. There was a suggestion that it would be useful if the Australian Government took action in the matter. By some mechanism which is unclear to me it was noised abroad as far as Canberra and the Australian ambassador to Ireland intervened on the issue. There was a friendly exchange of views as a result of which the motion was partly amended.</P>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>The Senator is straying.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidNorris" hpid="Mr. Norris Mr. Norris">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norris</NameTxt>
      <P>I am not and I will make it perfectly clear why this is the case. Although the motion was amended, I now read in the newspapers that there is a further row on the matter. One of the matters about which we were concerned was the well documented forcible transfer of children from the Aboriginal indigenous people of Australia within the last 50 years to white families. This comes under the description of genocide in the Minister's speech. We have, therefore, no apologies whatsoever to make to the Australians on the matter. We behaved in a most mature and responsible way and adapted the resolution, which the Minister should bear in mind. It is a squeak out of the Australians. The Minister's speech makes it quite clear why we intervened. He usefully talks about the question of genocide and states that crimes such as sexual violence, persecution of a group, enforced disappearance and apartheid constitute crimes against humanity when committed as part of a widespread or systematic attack directed against the civilian population.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>It will take a long time, but I would like to see sexual orientation included. Let us remember that during the period of Hitler's regime not only were there racial hygiene laws, there were sexual <Col N="579" /> hygiene laws. The Gay community was specifically targeted and given its own emblem of the pink triangle. Its members were the first to be medically experimented on, the first to be incarcerated and the first to be murdered. I have been asked by German groups and gone with Polish members of parliament to lay a wreath at the Nollendorf-Platz underground station entrance from where Gay people left.</P>
    <P>I dealt with the horrible attacks on those accused of being homosexual in Iran. I was chastised in this House for describing Mugabe as a dictator. Look at what he did, not just against the Gay community in his country, but against various easy target groups. I hope eventually there will be a possibility of real progress in all these areas, many of which are uncomfortable for particular cultural groups or political blocs. That is the test of something which is effective. If it makes people feel uncomfortable, it is, probably, more likely to be effective.</P>
    <P>The Minister spoke about attacks against religious, educational and cultural buildings, pillaging, rape and so on. I have just come back from Dubrovnik and Zagreb where a dinner was hosted &ndash; I regret that I cannot understand the name of the distinguished gentleman who hosted it. Following the dinner he gave me a copy of a book he had written about the situation in the area. The raw wound of the war was clear in every single line of the book which was a chilling, chilling read. When one is in cities like Zagreb and Dubrovnik one is aware of their wonderful European heritage and the fact that the people are closely culturally connected to us. The same applies to Serbia, yet these very ordinary people were capable of the most appalling crimes and it is necessary that they are brought to justice.</P>
    <P>The Armenian massacre in 1915 when 1.5 million people died was genocide. Yet, the Turkish Government introduced legislation discriminating in business matters and trading partnerships against any country the parliament of which dared to describe in an official resolution what took place as genocide. There is an interesting human story about that particular genocide because a German officer &ndash; they were allies of the Germans at that point &ndash; recorded what was happening in notebooks, letters and photographs which he sent to Berlin at the risk of his own commission and, possibly, the risk of being arraigned as a traitor. He appealed to the German Government during the World War One to do something about the matter, but it did nothing. In the 1930s the man wrote to Hitler and said that if he did not stop going down the road he was going, he would wind up doing the same thing. History tells us that is exactly what happened. As a result of this correspondence, Hitler said that nobody noticed when they did it to the Armenians. That was one of the arguments he used for continuing with the appalling programme against the Jews. That is the reason it is absolutely necessary to establish this permanent court the seat of which I <Col N="580" /> understand will be in the Hague. It is rather curious, but not entirely surprising that it was impossible to agree on a definition of terrorism. This illustrates the old adage that one person's freedom fighter is another person's terrorist.</P>
    <P>Dealing with drug offences would be a waste of time. It is another debate. I am pleased that the court is on the way to being established. Senator Lanigan suggested that a case cannot be heard against a citizen if the state to which that citizen belongs is not a party. I understand that is not correct and that the mechanism can be triggered in certain ways if the United Nations Security Council, for example, refers the matter to the court. The United Nations Security Council has the capacity to do so and, if that is so, let us have trials of those responsible for the invasion and genocide which is continuing in Tibet. It is an uncomfortable one. I said to the Minister that this law might be seen to be working at its best, its most moral and its most efficient when people, Governments and senior politicians are made uncomfortable. I look forward to a very uncomfortable period afterwards in international terms. I hope it will be effective in bringing to justice those who committed these appalling crimes against suffering and vulnerable humanity.</P>
    <Speaker pid="DonLydon" hpid="Mr. Lydon Mr. Lydon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lydon</NameTxt>
      <P>I, too, welcome the Minister. It is always nice to have someone come to the House who knows what he is talking about.</P>
      <P>The most important section in the Minister's speech relates to the adoption of the 1998 statute. It has taken 50 years for the court to be put in place, which is a long time.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidNorris" hpid="Mr. Norris Mr. Norris">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norris</NameTxt>
      <P>It is not yet in place.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DonLydon" hpid="Mr. Lydon Mr. Lydon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lydon</NameTxt>
      <P>I am aware of that. I can see many difficulties in relation to the issue. It is absolutely essential to have this type of international body in place, but I wonder if we will ever see leaders of some western nations coming before it, rather than leaders of smaller nations. It is good that it will do away with <i>ad hoc</i> tribunals. We have all heard of the Nazi war criminals, but there were also criminals on the other side who were never brought to justice. For example, the bombing of Dresden was a terrible and totally unjustified act of war by the Allies which killed thousands of innocent people. In such situations, some people will never be brought to justice.</P>
      <P>I hope the effort to get rid of the victors of war is successful. People may be brought into line if the court is put in place gradually. Senator Norris said the Clinton administration signed up to this measure and that is good. However, I foresee difficulties with a representational body of judges. I read that the legal systems throughout the world are so different and complicated that this will be practically impossible. I hope it will not be a western world body because there are many systems of justice in the world, although Ireland's is probably one of the best.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="581" /> The crimes mentioned include where there is an attempt to destroy in whole or in part a national, ethnic, racial or religious group. The indigenous Indians in Brazil are forbidden to vote under the Brazilian constitution. There is a pronounced and definite campaign against these people. They are shot and also poisoned by meat thrown from helicopters. Their land has been sequestered and their mineral wealth has been taken from them. All their rights have been taken from them, but I do not believe the Brazilian president will ever be brought before the court as a result. I hope the rights of the Indians will be recognised.</P>
    <P>I doubt an American president or general will ever be brought before the court although the United States contributed to the downfall of the democratically elected, albeit left wing, president of Chile, Mr. Allende. I doubt anybody in America will be prosecuted for the experiment in Nicaragua or the use of Agent Orange in the Vietnam War. I doubt the president of Israel will be brought before the court although there is a definite campaign against Palestinians. I have been in Israel twice and I saw where people were rolled over and their houses wiped out. Lands where Palestinians lived for 300 years have been taken.</P>
    <P>Regarding particularly serious violations of human rights, such as murder, if the referendum discussed earlier is passed, Ireland will abolish the death penalty. If the referendum on the International Criminal Court is passed, can there ever be a case where an Irish citizen could be brought before it and receive the death penalty although that penalty is banned in the citizen's own country? My point is not whether the person would deserve it, but I recognise there is a long way to go. When I first read the Bill, I thought it was a simple referendum. However, that is not the case. It is a most complicated, although necessary, referendum and I hope it can be explained adequately to the population.</P>
    <P>Regarding enforced prostitution, the use of children for prostitution is endemic in Thailand. Who would be prosecuted there? Would it be the king or the gangsters who do it? These questions must be answered and I worry at one level that an international court of this type, although it must be established, will be a tool in the hands of very powerful interests. Is there any way this can be avoided? My belief is that many of what I call the junior wars throughout the world are engineered so that stockpiles of arms can be used up and jobs can be created to manufacture more weapons. This is not a fantasy, but the court is a good idea. Many nations have signed up to it and, as the Minister said, it fits in well with Article 29 of our Constitution which deals with a devotion to the ideal of peace and friendly co-operation among nations. This is a step in that direction.</P>
    <P>If such a court is not established, some people will never be brought to justice. There are other players in the field aside from Slobodan Milosevic. For example, should something be done about the US sanctions against Iraq which result <Col N="582" /> in the deaths of thousands of Iraqi children? Even the Pope has called for the lifting of the sanctions. However, we all know it is unlikely that anybody will be brought before the international court for this crime in the immediate future. Nevertheless, mechanisms must be put in place because, if an international system of law is recognised by the many signatories and I hope eventually by all the United Nations, it will be a useful step forward. We should urge the people to accept the referendum. Senator Quinn said it will be necessary to put through a raft of legislation, but that can be done. The draftsmen are well able to prepare it and I am sure that Ministers in various Departments can fall into line with it.</P>
    <P>I welcome the legislation which is necessary. It is not foolproof by any means and it may be used in the future against smaller rather than larger nations. However, it is a necessary step forward and I urge people to support it.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MaryHenry" hpid="Dr. Henry Dr. Henry">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Henry</NameTxt>
      <P>I welcome the Minister and the Bill. It is a great development because the International Criminal Court has been needed for a long time. It is good that countries are signing up to it rapidly. I take Senator Quinn's point that the public is being asked to sign up to a concept in the absence of legislation. However, my disappointment at the speed at which Ireland ratifies UN conventions leads me to believe that it is better to put this constitutional amendment to the people now and have it carried. The ratification of the Rome statute should be made possible as quickly as possible afterwards. A considerable amount of legislation must be introduced to enable the statute to be ratified.</P>
      <P>It is not the Minister's fault, but it is dreadful that it took 25 years to ratify the UN convention on race because Ireland was so slow to introduce legislation. A few month ago I asked the Minister if, in our new position of power on the Security Council, he would try to address the need for a verification process under the 1975 UN Convention on Biological Weapons and Toxins. To my horror, after I raised the matter on the Adjournment, I discovered that Ireland has not yet ratified the convention. I doubt Ireland has dumps of anthrax or other biological weapons, but once a UN convention has been signed, the legislation should be put in place rapidly to ensure it can be ratified. I hope this is done as rapidly as possible with regard to the Rome statute. It would be a great pity if we missed the opportunity to have a judge in the court. It would also be a great pity for the court if it missed the opportunity of having an Irish judge.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Perhaps we could begin by the Minister initiating legislation in the Seanad so that our law could be brought into line as quickly as possible. I understand we must introduce legislation which will allow us co-operate with the court in the areas of extradition, investigation and arrest. We could modify our laws so that we could exercise jurisdiction over offenders for crimes committed within the remit of the court even where such <Col N="583" /> crimes are committed outside our territory. However, the more modest approach of fulfilling our obligation of sending criminals in the State before the court is perhaps preferable. I hope this is done rapidly and it would be good to see an Irish judge as part of the court. As Senator Quinn said, we are at the half-way stage. Some 60 countries are needed to ratify the Rome statute and 30 have already done so. It would be good to see us making progress in this area.</P>
    <P>Corporations can be very important where events in other countries where genocide, war crimes and crimes against humanity are concerned. This was recognised at the Nuremberg trials where some of those involved in the supply, if not the manufacture, of the gas for the death chambers were convicted of having been complicit in the crimes. I sought advice on this subject because I found it difficult to decide whether corporations could be sued. I had in mind companies such as Total in Burma, which has been involved in bringing large sections of the minority population into slavery in the laying of a pipeline across the country, and Shell in Nigeria, in the lower part of which we repeatedly see atrocities which are due in part to the fact that the area is so oil rich and yet the people of the area are so poor.</P>
    <P>I sought the advice of William Schabas, professor of human rights law in the National University of Ireland, Galway. He pointed out some interesting facts to me, one of which was that, within days of the adoption of the Rome statute of the International Criminal Court at the conclusion of the Rome conference in July 1998, there was an article in the prestigious British business daily, the <i>Financial Times</i>, in which there was a warning to commercial lawyers that the treaty's encompassed liability provision could create international criminal liabilities for employees, officers and directors of corporations. The writer, Maurice Nyberg, referred to condemnation of violations of human rights involving multinational corporations by non-governmental organisations, such as Human Rights Watch, adding that it would take little imagination to jump from complicity with human rights violations to complicity with crimes covered under the International Criminal Court treaty.</P>
    <P>He said that, besides the more obvious offences relating to involvement in arms trading and financing of security for overseas investments, the mistreatment of pregnant workers could become an area where foreign subsidiaries might attract liability as a crime against humanity as persecution based upon gender. Mr. Nyberg went on to say that, as gender discrimination is widespread and systematic in much of the world, the International Criminal Court treaty could require parent companies and financial institutions to police the global workplace under threat of the criminal liability of their senior executives. There is more than a suspicion that people could per<Col N="584" /> haps be prosecuted by the court and I would be very pleased to see this being a possibility.</P>
    <P>The UN High Commissioner for Human Rights, Mrs. Mary Robinson, has explored the question of international accountability for alleged corporate violations of human rights. She has requested the six treaty bodies, the special rapporteurs and the working groups appointed by the Commission on Human Rights to study the promotion of corporate accountability within the context of their mandates. The sub-committee on the promotion and protection of human rights has recently established a working group to examine the effects of the working methods and activities of the transnational companies on human rights. This is all extraordinarily important in the area of globalisation where corporations may find, because of weak domestic law, that it is much better to establish large factories in certain areas than in areas which have stricter laws on human rights. The first meeting of the sub-committee took place in August 1999 and it has made recommendations, including the development of a code of conduct, and is analysing the possible liability of states and transnational corporations which fail to fulfil their obligations. I hope Ireland supports these initiatives because they are very important.</P>
    <P>Participation in war crimes and crimes against humanity at the level of supply and finance is usually covered by the corporate shell rather than by the individual names of perpetrators. Prosecutors will attempt to pierce the corporate shell, as Professor Schabas explained to me, to get at the individuals behind it. Where the evidence is clear, that should not pose any great problems. Crimes against international law are committed by men, not by abstract entities. It was said at the Nuremberg trials in 1946 that it is only by punishing individuals who commit such crimes that the provisions of international law can be enforced. It is not a new concept.</P>
    <P>International law in this area has been relatively underdeveloped. Proposals were brought forward during the drafting of the Rome statute to develop it, but they were strongly resisted by some countries, although I understand the French delegation argued strongly about criminal liability of legal persons being promoted to include that of a corporation. I hope the Minister supports that because it would be dreadful to think a shield for vile acts could be brought forward by the fact that a corporation could not be sued even though it was perfectly obvious it supported grim crimes within an area. For example, the diamond traders in Sierra Leone, while extraordinarily important in the conduct of the multilateral civil war there, cannot be sued because it cannot be proved that genocide or other crimes which take place have been promoted by them.</P>
    <P>I hope the Minister can see a possibility of our developing the proposals under the Rome statute rather than taking it as a <i>fait accompli</i> that it has gone thus far and no further. We should remember the words of Parnell, whose statue is at the top of O'Connell Street, and see that there can <Col N="585" /> be no boundary to what we can do with this. I hope the Minister brings the legislation to this House &ndash; we are a co-operative group &ndash; so that we can ratify the Rome statute as quickly as possible to be in a position not only to be one of the early ones in the ratification stakes but also to be in a position to have an Irish judge on the International Criminal Court. It would benefit from having a member of the Judiciary on it. I congratulate the Minister on bringing forward the referendum.</P>
    <Speaker pid="BrianCowen" hpid="Mr. Cowen Mr. Cowen">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Foreign Affairs (Mr. Cowen)</NameTxt>
      <P>I warmly thank Senators who contributed to the debate on the Bill. It has demonstrated the significance of the Rome statute of the International Criminal Court as a development in international law and its importance for the protection of human rights throughout the world. It falls upon us to provide an amendment to the Constitution which will be put to the people in early summer and which, if passed, as I sincerely hope it will be, will enable Ireland to ratify the statute.</P>
      <P>It was not possible at the diplomatic conference in Rome to secure agreement on the inclusion of crimes such as international terrorism and drug trafficking within the jurisdiction of the International Criminal Court, but one has to start somewhere and those on which agreement was possible were genocide, war crimes and crimes against humanity. It was also possible to secure agreement that the court should have jurisdiction over the crime of aggression, but would not exercise its jurisdiction until the states parties agreed upon a definition of the crime.</P>
      <P>The list of crimes over which the court may have jurisdiction is not closed. The inclusion of further crimes within the jurisdiction of the court will, certainly, be the subject of future discussions among states parties to which Ireland will be contributing. Senator Connor made the point that it is important that we make our voice heard in those fora and we will do so. The question of the review conference not being held for seven years does not preclude an attempt to build a political consensus on the possible increase in the number of crimes which would fall within the jurisdiction of the International Criminal Court. We must remember how things were in the past. The Cold War was a serious brake on the development of the concept of an international criminal court. Much progress was made between 1948 and 1953, but there was then little progress until 1999.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>One must realise that the agreement of states parties is needed if one is to develop an international jurisdiction. This permissible jurisdiction must be created. When that is achieved enforcement mechanisms, such as an international criminal court, can be provided for in those areas which are particularly heinous and universally recognised to require an international response. If national jurisdictions, which have a primary role, do not enforce their own laws or are incapable of doing so because of a state of civil disorder or the institutions of state have col<Col N="586" /> lapsed, as can happen in areas where genocide is taking place, the International Criminal Court can step in and complement national jurisdictions.</P>
    <P>The Office of Prosecutor is an important aspect of the development of the International Criminal Court enforcement mechanism because it allows a states party to ask the prosecutor to initiate an investigation into an alleged crime which comes within the jurisdiction of the International Criminal Court. That is a new development. Typically in international law, both parties must agree to the jurisdiction of the international forum before the jurisdiction becomes effective. In this case when 60 states parties ratify the international Rome statute will be an effective jurisdiction. There is a prospect of a prosecutor to work with the court and individual states parties to investigate alleged breaches of international law consistent with the need to bring forward indictments of crime in their own statute law. That is a very important development.</P>
    <P>Since 1989 we have been able to secure that level of agreement. There are different views as to how one should accord human dignity to the individual. There are different cultural, religious and political beliefs and the ability to find a universal definition that meets that diversity without being diluted to the point of losing its credibility is an important achievement of the International Criminal Court enforcement mechanism referred to in the Rome statute. The international community is to be congratulated, despite that diversity of opinion and understanding of what human rights are, on being able to agree that genocide, crimes against humanity and war crimes must be dealt with and that aggression, on which a definition could not be agreed, is to be included while discussions on a common definition continue.</P>
    <P>Concern has been expressed at the lack of reference to sexual violence in the statute. Grave forms of sexual violence are clearly stated to be a crime against humanity and a war crime. This is in recognition of the use of such violence, especially in the last ten years, to terrorise populations. I agree with what Senator Connor said about the extent and nature of modern slavery. I am glad to assure him that the definition of enslavement involves the exercise of any or all of the powers attaching to the right of ownership over persons. This includes the exercise of such powers in the course of trafficking in persons. Article 75 of the statute deals with the question of reparations to victims. The court shall establish principles relating to reparations to victims and may make an order directly against a convicted person specifying appropriate reparations to victims, including restitution, compensation and rehabilition. Where appropriate the court may also order that the award for reparations be made through the trust fund which will be established by the Assembly of State Parties for the benefit of victims and their families.</P>
    <P>Concern has been raised at the perceived delay in processing ratification of the statute. The <Col N="587" /> speedy ratification of the statute has been given a high priority by my Department. Implementing legislation will also be required before the State may ratify the Rome statute. A number of Senators have argued that the fact that the draft legislation has not been published diminishes people's undersanding of what it is intended to transpose into domestic law if the proposed amendment is accepted in the referendum. I do not accept that contention. What will be transposed into domestic law is what is contained in the Rome statute. The idea that domestic legislation must be in place in order for people to make an informed decision on the amendment does not stand up to scrutiny. Were it the case that further legislation was required which was different from or modified or altered the Rome statute there would be issues for debate. However, as I have outlined and as is the universal view of this House and all democratic assemblies in this country, the issues are not contentious.</P>
    <P>Because of our constitutional law and our jurisprudence which has developed from it there is the prospect of a transfer of jurisdiction from the courts established under the Constitution to the International Criminal Court were, for example, at some stage in the future the shameful position to arise that a citizen of this country was arraigned before the court to be tried for any of these acts. It is, therefore, not possible for any legislation to be effective until we amend the Constitution and it is good constitutional practice to proceed with the amendment and give a commitment to transpose the Rome statute into domestic law when the people, the sovereign source of power in this republic, agree to make the statute part of our domestic law. When the people have spoken we will proceed to enact legislation. That is the logical and proper constitutional practice to adopt.</P>
    <P>The question of efficiency and speed has quite rightly been raised by Senators. It will be the responsibility of the Minister for Justice, Equality and Law Reform to transpose the Rome statute into national law, if this amendment is adopted by the people. His record is comparable to that of any of his predecessors in terms of his ability to get legislation out of the Department. Let the record speak for itself. He has produced important, complex and detailed legislation that has been very effective in the area of the drugs trade and people acquiring assets through criminal activity. This was a pioneering piece of legislation which has been adopted and investigated, not only by countries within the EU but also further afield, because of its effectiveness in dealing with the proceeds of criminal activity. If as we hope the people proceed to adopt this constitutional amendment, as the Members of both Houses are urging and as is their sovereign right in this Republic, the Government of Ireland will proceed with all due speed and consideration to transpose the Rome statute into domestic law.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="588" /> The Minister for Justice, Equality and Law Reform and I have been informed that a preliminary examination of the statute with a view to preparing the necessary legislation is already taking place within his Department. There was some concern arising from a reply to a Member of the other House in January 2000 that this process had not been started in the Department. I can confirm that a preliminary examination has started. The legal expertise of the Department of Foreign Affairs in the international area will be offered to the Minister for Justice, Equality and Law Reform. He has a busy schedule of legislation to put through on a whole range of areas in criminal law and we would be available to assist. We intend to co-ordinate that effort on a ministerial level to ensure the issue is dealt with as quickly as possible.</P>
    <P>It is not possible to state definitively when Ireland will be in a position to ratify the statute but I will endeavour to ensure that we do so in a reasonable timeframe. It has been mentioned several times during this debate that the Rome statute is a long and complex document. As a result, all of the steps towards ratification require adequate time and consideration. That is not intended to justify undue delay but we need to adopt the proper approach to ensure that we transpose this important international legislation effectively and efficiently in accordance with our own Constitution.</P>
    <P>The Government has approved the setting up of a referendum commission for this referendum and for each of the other referenda to be held on the same date. The referendum commission will provide information for the public on the implications of ratification of the Rome statute and I am sure they will perform their task well. This is another mechanism whereby detailed information can be made available to people so they can make an informed decision on this matter. The absence of the draft legislation at this stage is in no way an impediment to ensuring that the people will be fully informed as to what they are voting for in this referendum.</P>
    <P>The European Union is a strong supporter of the early establishment of the court and has undertaken to assist countries associated with it to ratify the statute, and this is something we will be involved with. The European Union urges the United States of America to ratify its own statute. The Clinton administration signed the statute but it is now a matter for the current administration which would probably take a different view. Congress has a particular view on this subject and it is an internal matter whether the US ratifies the International Criminal Court. As members of the European Union we will be joining with our partners in urging the United States to ratify the Rome statute. Ireland continues to support the European Union and its president in these efforts.</P>
    <P>The Rome Statute on the International Criminal Court represents one of the most important developments in international law since the <Col N="589" /> Second World War. We should not try to diminish or underestimate that achievement. It establishes a permanent independent court with the jurisdiction to try persons for the most serious crimes of international concern. This statute draws on international and humanitarian and human rights conventions and instruments from the beginning of the twentieth century to the present in its definitions of these crimes. The states parties statute affirms their abhorrence of these most serious breaches of human rights and pledge themselves to co-operation with the court in its investigation and prosecution.</P>
    <P>I am sure those present today and the Irish people in general share my belief that this country should join the 30 states who have to date ratified this most important statute. The proposed amendment to the Constitution constitutes a major step in our ratification process. It is a step but an important one whereby we will demonstrate our ongoing commitment to the international court and reaffirm the principles set out at the beginning of Article 29 of the Constitution. These pertain to co-operation on the basis of international justice and morality, adherence to the specific settlements of international disputes and the generally recognised principles of international law according to which the international relations of this State are to be conducted.</P>
    <P>Cuireadh agus aontaíodh an cheist.</P>
    <P>Question put and agreed.</P>
    <P>Céim an Choiste ordaithe don Chéadaoin, 2 Bealtaine 2001.</P>
    <P>Committee Stage ordered for Wednesday, 2 May 2001.</P>
    <Speaker pid="BrianMullooly" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>When does the House propose to sit again?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MickLanigan" hpid="Mr. Lanigan Mr. Lanigan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lanigan</NameTxt>
      <P>At 10.30 a.m. tomorrow.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Adjournment Matter. -" RHead="Gormanston Aerodrome">
    <Title>Adjournment Matter. - Gormanston Aerodrome.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="JimGlennonFF" hpid="Mr. Glennon Mr. Glennon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Glennon</NameTxt>
      <P>I welcome the Minister for Defence, Deputy Smith, to the House. I wish to draw attention to a possible alternative use for lands in State ownership in County Meath. I hope to ensure that these lands, which are at present under consideration for sale and disposal, are used to maximum efficiency and economy for the State and the people of the area.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The ground concerned has been in continuous use as an aerodrome since 1917 and is the oldest continuously used aviation site in the country. I am sure the British authorities could not have foreseen the present circumstances when they purchased it in 1917. I have no intention of going into the statistics for the projected development of the greater Dublin area, but it is interesting to <Col N="590" /> note that in the document, A Platform for Change, published by the Dublin Transportation Office in September 2000, there is no reference to air transport. One can only presume that air transport was outside their terms of reference. With the admitted benefit of hindsight, it is somewhat surprising to note that such a significant study on transportation was commissioned without reference to air transport.</P>
    <P>I have no doubt that a second airport is required for the greater Dublin area and I think most people would agree with that. The biggest difficulty is deciding upon a location but I hope to demonstrate that Gormanston is an ideal one for a proposed second airport. In proposing a second airport for Dublin I am not advocating a facility to compete with what we in north County Dublin call Collinstown, and what is known nationally as Dublin Airport, but rather to complement the existing facilities there. In anticipating the future needs of that facility as it develops, a properly designed and constructed second &ndash; and, almost of necessity, smaller &ndash; facility in the greater Dublin area will serve to complement the facilities at Collinstown. Such a second facility could turn out to be an essential element in the balanced development of the Collinstown facility.</P>
    <P>I would like to provide some statistics concerning Dublin Airport, which for the remainder of my contribution I will refer to as Collinstown. The projected annual passenger traffic for 2001 is 15 million and that volume is growing at the rate of one million per annum. The airport's current facilities are estimated to have an annual maximum capacity of 20 million. In other words, major infrastructural change and consequent capital expenditure will be required within the next few years to avoid future difficulties that can be foreseen. It is believed that the overall site area at Collinstown has a capacity, subject to infrastructural development, to cater for 40 million passengers per annum. While that may sound a staggering statistic today, at the rate at which airline passenger numbers are increasing it is safe to say that the 40 million level will not be considered outlandish in a relatively short period of time.</P>
    <P>Collinstown also represents the largest industrial complex in Ireland. It accounts for a remarkable 2% of our gross domestic product and currently employs 8,000 people on site. In excess of 12,000 more are employed indirectly in the immediate vicinity in jobs which are dependent upon the airport. Those statistics are absolutely staggering and show how huge the Collinstown facility has become.</P>
    <P>Although the airport authorities are trying to maximise efficiency, the airport has serious infrastructural difficulties. We are well aware of the difficulties that occurred last summer at peak time which, unfortunately, coincided with a major development of the departures and arrivals halls. That was the most obvious difficulty in the recent past but there were others. A lesser difficulty, but <Col N="591" /> one which is about to become greater, concerns access to and from Dublin Airport, both on the surface by road or rail and equally in the air. There is a major difficulty in the Portmarnock area of north County Dublin arising from what, in effect, is a traffic jam in the air. Such logjams in the flight path over Portmarnock are causing serious environmental difficulties. There is a proposal from Aer Rianta to develop a parallel flight path in precisely the same vicinity. Naturally enough, and with some justification, the residents of that area have major objections to the plan.</P>
    <P>Dublin Airport or Collinstown is creaking at the seams and any future development of the infrastructure there will of necessity be extremely expensive. Apart from facilitating the throughput of passengers, to protect the 20,000 people currently employed there, directly and indirectly, it is vital that the facility should operate to maximum efficiency. If it develops a long-term reputation for inefficiency the business will go elsewhere and the economy that has developed around the airport will begin to wither away.</P>
    <P>At Gormanston, just across the Meath border, we have the oldest aviation facility in Ireland, which has been in continuous use since 1917 when it was purchased by the British authorities. In 1919 it had a workforce of 651, 65 of whom were pilots. It has a less pleasant place in local and national history as the base for the Black and Tans at the time of the infamous sack of Balbriggan in 1920. It was subsequently taken over by the Free State Army in October 1922 and in 1945 was taken over by the Air Corps which ran it until 1986. In 1969, Gormanston was used as a refugee camp for those fleeing the troubles in Northern Ireland.</P>
    <P>The venue is only 30 miles from Dundalk and 22 miles from Dublin or Navan. That represents a journey of 45 minutes by road from anywhere within an arc from Dundalk to Kells and central Dublin. I understand that there is a site there, currently owned by the Department of Defence, of 270 acres with serviceable runways. There are significant undeveloped agricultural landholdings immediately adjoining the site. Most importantly, the Dublin-Belfast railway line runs along the site's eastern boundary, while the main Dublin-Belfast road, soon to become the M1 motorway, is on the western boundary. I emphasise the location of the existing road and rail infrastructure which would cost billions to construct from scratch today. Gormanston is the only facility in the country adjoining such major transport infrastructure. While it may seem somewhat incongruous in the context of an airport development, Gormanston is also near the Irish Sea, on the other side of the railway line. Such a natural resource can be exploited for future runway development, as we have seen in the case of several international airports around the world.</P>
    <P>We should not allow another Harcourt Street line or Navan line situation to develop whereby railways were closed down because the demand <Col N="592" /> did not justify the oversupply of infrastructure at one particular time. We all lived to regret such closures subsequently. It is also important to avoid a posts and telegraphs situation where a huge demand for phone facilities in the 1970s and 1980s totally outstripped supply. The telephone system was in absolute chaos because the necessary infrastructure was not in place. It took a radical measure by the former Taoiseach, Deputy Albert Reynolds, when Minister for Post and Telegraphs, to bring our telecommunications infrastructure into the 20th century. We are all fully aware of the major benefits that accrued. It is important that we are proactive and manage and drive development rather than allow change to be forced upon us and have to react to it.</P>
    <P>The cliché, &ldquo;It is a golden opportunity&rdquo;, is very appropriate in this context. This is an opportunity not to be missed and which I fear will never be repeated. There is a magnificent and totally unique coincidence of natural and man made resources available. There is acre upon acre of flat ground that is perfectly suitable for airport development with very few dwellings located on it. A mainline rail track immediately adjoins the land with two stations adjacent to the site, which by rail is three quarters of an hour from Dublin and an hour and a quarter from Belfast. While we think of it as an addition to Dublin, we are aware of the fortune Ryanair has made during the years by utilising airports such as Stansted, Charleroi and Beauvais, all of which are an hour and a quarter from the cities they serve.</P>
    <P>The new M1 motorway also runs adjacent to the site and there is unlimited runway expansion potential. There are prevailing westerly winds which would render the runways largely pollution free in that the vast bulk of traffic would fly into the airport over water and there would be no noise pollution in inhabited areas. I hope the key is that the availability of capital for the necessary funding of the project should not present the difficulties it would have in the past. It appears to be a fantastic opportunity to develop the magnificent confluence of natural and man made resources.</P>
    <P>I welcome the Minister and thank him for taking the time to come to the House. I look forward very much to his comments.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelSmith" hpid="Mr. M. Smith Mr. M. Smith">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Defence (Mr. M. Smith)</NameTxt>
      <P>Is cúis mhór áthais dom aon uair, teacht go dti an Teach álainn seo. Mo bhuíochas duit, a Chathaoirligh, as ucht an fháilte a thugann tú dom i gcónaí. I thank Senator Glennon for his presentation and will outline a little of the history of the use of Gormanston Camp and examine the options before us.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Gormanston Camp is situated south of Drogheda some 30 miles from Dublin and in close proximity to the M1 motorway. The camp consists of approximately 260 acres, of which 230 acres were acquired on 1 November 1917 by the British War Office. The remainder of the land was acquired in 1944 by my Department. The <Col N="593" /> aerodrome was constructed in 1918 and used by the RAF until January 1920.</P>
    <P>During the War of Independence Gormanston was used to billet a number of units of the British Army and as a depot for the RIC. Following ratification of the Treaty the camp was taken over by the National Army and used as a transport depot and became the transport base workshops. In 1928, following the disposal of a large proportion of the transport fleet, the base workshops were moved to Clancy Barracks, Dublin. Gormanston was subsequently evacuated and placed under a caretaker and only used for summer camps and as an air firing range.</P>
    <P>During the World War II emergency the camp was used as accommodation for up to 2,000 men and for a time as an internment camp for the detention of aircrews who crash landed or made emergency landings in the State. In 1944, with the pending evacuation of Rineanna &ndash; Shannon &ndash; it was decided to develop the camp for use by the Air Corps. In 1950 the control tower was completed and the camp was first connected to mains electricity. The camp has been used for many years for FCA and PDF training.</P>
    <P>In 1959 more than 600 refugees escaping the violence in Belfast were accommodated at this location. This continued on a regular basis until the end of 1971 by which stage some 12,000 persons had been assisted at the camp. The camp has continued to the present day to serve both the PDF and Air Corps units.</P>
    <P>As the House will be aware, the Government, on 15 July 1998, approved a programme of evacuation and sale of six barracks considered surplus to military requirements. This decision is part of the relocation, refurbishment and re-equipment of the Defence Forces, as recommended in the context of the Price Waterhouse report on the rationalisation of military institutions generally. The Government remains fully committed to this important programme.</P>
    <P>It is expected that in excess of £50 million will be raised from the sale of the barracks. Most of the proceeds will be invested in the redevelopment of other military installations and new equipment. The recent closure of barracks has freed up important sites in the towns concerned. Plans for important new community, health, industrial and housing initiatives are in progress. With the increasing demand for social housing and related programmes and the Government's new decentralisation initiative, it is quite likely that freeing up military locations for alternative uses would assist these programmes.</P>
    <P>There are, in addition, a number of other lands, including Gormanston, within the defence portfolio located outside of the permanently occupied military barracks and posts. The Government has decided in line with the White Paper that there should be a rigorous examination of the necessity for each such property and only those required for essential defence purposes will be retained. Those identified will be disposed of by sale or otherwise and the Government has approved that <Col N="594" /> the proceeds, with the revenue from the existing programme of barrack disposals, will be invested in Defence Forces infrastructure and equipment.</P>
    <P>It is Government policy to ensure the Defence Forces are adequately equipped to undertake the roles assigned to them. Establishing realistic equipment requirements and priorities for procurement forms a major element of strategic planning activities within the Department of Defence and the Defence Forces. The objective is to acquire, maintain and manage equipment, weapons and ammunition for the Defence Forces at the appropriate level of operational readiness in a cost effective manner. The strategic focus of the investment programme for the period 2000-10 is the acquisition of a broad range of equipment in order to achieve a balanced increase in operational capacity throughout the Defence Forces. It will be necessary to prioritise and reconcile the equipment requirements for the Army, the Air Corps, the Naval Service and the Reserve Defence Force within the total resources available. Basic to the plan is a multi-annual budgetary strategy which is vital to achieving value for money.</P>
    <P>The Air Corps is the air component of the Defence Forces. Through a fleet of fixed and rotary winged aircraft based primarily at Casement Aerodrome, Baldonnel, the Air Corps provides a variety of military and non-military air services. Air Corps military roles and functions are those of an Army Air Corps rather than a conventional military air service. The Air Corps has traditionally discharged a mix of functions based on the need to supply a range of different services such as search and rescue, SAR, fishery protection and ministerial air transport. The generally favourable security climate resulted in the need for a very limited military air capability. To exceed this capability would require a level of investment in personnel, equipment and infrastructure which could not be justified.</P>
    <P>A pragmatic approach has provided capabilities in the following areas: general utility helicopter capacity with capabilities in regard to search and rescue over land and sea, limited transport and security surveillance in aid of the civil power; ministerial and other such transport requirements; fishery protection and limited general maritime patrol; air ambulance transport tasks; air space control limited to low level and favourable visibility conditions; and limited clear weather ground attack-support capability.</P>
    <P>The Government has decided that the present broad profile of Air Corps roles will be maintained. The future development of the Air Corps will, therefore, be determined within the following policy parameters, which set out the general air-based military and non-military capabilities which the State will seek to provide: maintenance-generation of a 24 hour general helicopter capability for a variety of military and non-military tasks, including Garda support; the provision of SAR capabilities on the basis of agreed arrangements with the Department of Marine <Col N="595" /> and Natural Resources; the provision of a ministerial air transport service; the provision of fishery protection patrol services to standards agreed with the Department of the Marine and Natural Resources; the provision of an air ambulance service on the basis of agreed arrangements with the Department of Health and Children, and other transport services of a military or non-military kind; and provision of an appropriate capability to meet training requirements.</P>
    <P>The challenge for the future is to ensure that, within the likely level of available resources, the State has available to it an Air Corps which is capable of meeting on-going requirements and providing the basis for expansion should this be required. There is also the need to ensure that the Air Corps is kept on a sufficiently high professional footing by adequate investment in personnel, training and equipment.</P>
    <P>The Government recognises that there are urgent equipment modernisation requirements in the Air Corps and it has approved the allocation of an additional £5 million per annum in each of the next five years for this purpose. This investment is on top of the savings arising from Defence Forces restructuring. The precise overall funding for Air Corps equipment will be decided within the context of the work of the high level civil-military planning and procurement group and having regard to the policy approach on individual equipment issues.</P>
    <P>As the Senator is aware, proposals to establish a flying training organisation at Gormanston were considered by a steering group representing the Department of Public Enterprise, the Department of Defence and the Irish Aviation Authority. A draft report was submitted in late July 2000 and was examined by the Minister for Public Enterprise, myself and the Irish Aviation Authority. The question of establishing facilities for civil aviation purposes is primarily a matter for the Minister for Public Enterprise.</P>
    <P>Casement Aerodrome is the principal base of the Air Corps. With the withdrawal of aircraft <Col N="596" /> from Gormanston and the relocation of Air Corps headquarters to Baldonnel as outlined in the White Paper, the Air Corps has the basis for better management of its resources.</P>
    <P>In order to finance the urgent modernisation of the Air Corps as set out in the White Paper and having regard to its centralisation in Baldonnel, it was prudent that in order to finance their requirements the airfield at Gormanston should be sold to provide the vital moneys to restructure and sustain the Air Corps into the future. I am in the process of arranging discussions with the relevant State agencies with a view to putting the property in question on the market at an early date.</P>
    <P>Senator Glennon made a number of suggestions which can be examined in the context of that overall deliberation. On the one hand we have the urgency of ensuring, without leaning to heavily on the taxpayer, that the various requirements of the Defence Forces generally can be met by the property portfolio which is surplus to requirements. On the other hand, in the overall circle of management and government, there is clearly an obligation to take account of the various needs that arise from time to time. I do not have a precise objection to the use of this land resource for a different purpose provided it is in the national interest and I am open to suggestions and propositions. I am quite sure that the Government will take into account these overall considerations when the final decision is taken on this matter.</P>
    <P>We are now looking at our surplus property portfolio in an overall context. In a number of instances, State agencies have come to me suggesting, as they have done in Fermoy, Castleblayney and to some extent Cork and other places, alternative State uses or developments which we may not have envisaged when we first made this decision. I am open to suggestions as to the best use of a national asset in order that the change of use can be converted into the best interests of the people.</P>
    <P>The Seanad adjourned at 7.25 p.m. until 10.30 a.m. on Wednesday, 2 May 2001.</P>
  </MainHeading>
</Debate>