<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE Debate SYSTEM "../Debate.dtd"[]>
<Debate DocTitle="D&aacute;il Debate" Day="Tue" Date="15" Month="Mar" Year="1927" Vol="18" No="19" DateIrish="Dé Máirt, 15 Márta 1927" DateEnglish="Tuesday, 15 March 1927" House="D" CommitteeEng="" CommitteeIr="" SubNameEng="" cnum="1863">
  <MainHeading Type="Prelude" LHead="" RHead="">
    <Title>
    </Title>
    <P>
      <Col N="1863" /> Do chuaidh An Ceann Comhairle i gceannas ar 3 a clog.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="CEISTEANNA&mdash;QUESTIONS. ORAL" RHead="ANSWERS. - STATISTICAL INFORMATION">
    <Title>CEISTEANNA&mdash;QUESTIONS.   ORAL ANSWERS. - STATISTICAL INFORMATION.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamNorton" hpid="Mr. W. NORTON Mr. W. NORTON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. W. NORTON</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Finance if he will state the total number of officials employed by the Departments of State and the numbers of these in receipt of total remuneration (a) not exceeding £2 per week, (b) not exceeding £3 per week, (c) not exceeding £4 per week.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ErnestBlythe" hpid="MINISTER for FINANCE (Mr. Blythe) Ernest Blythe">
      <NameTxt>MINISTER for FINANCE (Mr. Blythe)</NameTxt>
      <P>The figures asked for in the question are not available.  Information as to the number of persons employed in subordinate capacities at different rates of pay is not necessary for ordinary official purposes, and therefore no returns from which the particulars indicated could be taken are maintained.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamNorton" hpid="Mr. NORTON Mr. NORTON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. NORTON</NameTxt>
      <P>Can the Minister give any indication as to whether the figures are likely to be available when the Estimates come up for detailed discussion?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ErnestBlythe" hpid="Mr. BLYTHE Mr. BLYTHE">
      <NameTxt>Mr. BLYTHE</NameTxt>
      <P>If the Deputy very strongly desires it, they could be available by that time.  The point is, that the compilation of a return of this kind would involve a considerable amount of labour.  It would mean circularising all the Departments and getting returns, and unless some definite purpose were likely to be served I would not like to promise it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamNorton" hpid="Mr. NORTON Mr. NORTON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. NORTON</NameTxt>
      <P>If it does not involve too much trouble, I should like the Minister to ascertain the figures.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="CEISTEANNA&mdash;QUESTIONS. ORAL ANSWERS." RHead="- THE TIGHE ESTATE (CLAREMORRIS)">
    <Title>CEISTEANNA&mdash;QUESTIONS.   ORAL ANSWERS. - THE TIGHE ESTATE (CLAREMORRIS).</Title>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelRichardHeffer" hpid="MICHEAL O hIFEARNAIN MICHEAL O hIFEARNAIN">
      <NameTxt>MICHEAL O hIFEARNAIN</NameTxt>
      <P>asked <Col N="1864" /> the Minister for Lands and Agriculture whether the result of the inquiries which are being made regarding the position of the tenants on the estate of Thomas Tighe, the Heath, Scardane, Claremorris, will be made known to them, and whether their annuities will be re-fixed on the basis of the result of the inquiries.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickJHogan" hpid="MINISTER for LANDS and AGRICULTURE (Mr. Hogan) MINISTER for LANDS and AGRICULTURE (Mr. Hogan)">
      <NameTxt>MINISTER for LANDS and AGRICULTURE (Mr. Hogan)</NameTxt>
      <P>Inquiries are being made regarding the circumstances of the estate of Thomas Tighe, Co. Mayo, and it is anticipated that these inquiries will be completed at an early date.  The Land Commission are unable to state what course they will adopt in this matter until the investigation now being made is finished.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="CEISTEANNA&mdash;QUESTIONS. ORAL" RHead="ANSWERS. - CO. KILDARE LANDS">
    <Title>CEISTEANNA&mdash;QUESTIONS.   ORAL ANSWERS. - CO. KILDARE LANDS.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="GeorgeWolfe" hpid="SEOIRSE DE BHULBH SEOIRSE DE BHULBH">
      <NameTxt>SEOIRSE DE BHULBH</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Lands and Agriculture if it is the intention of the Land Commission to acquire the lands of Ballyraggan, County Kildare, near Baltinglass, containing sixty-two acres and owned by Miss Nolan, Rickettstown, Rathvilly, for the purpose of reinstating James Lawlor, a nephew of John Lawlor, who was evicted from these lands in 1899, and possibly another congest.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. HOGAN Mr. HOGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. HOGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>The lands of Ballyraggan referred to are subject to a land purchase annuity, and the Commissioners do not propose to take any action as regards the acquisition of these lands.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="ORDER OF" RHead="BUSINESS">
    <Title>ORDER OF BUSINESS.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>I move that the Dáil sit later than 9 p.m. this evening, and that the adjournment be taken not later than 10.30 p.m.  I shall also move that the Dáil meet at 11 a.m. to-morrow and that the motion for the adjournment to-morrow be taken not later than 4 p.m.</P>
      <P>The Order of Business to-day will be: Item No. 5 first, and after that Items 1 and 2.  We propose to take the Minister's speech on the Second Stage of the Electricity (Supply Bill); at the conclusion of that statement to have the tea adjournment, and resume on Item No. 2.  I suppose it is understood that we want the Central Fund Bill by to-morrow, and the Second Stage of the Electricity (Supply) Bill.</P>
      <P>Ordered: That the Dáil sit later than 9 p.m. this evening and that the Order for the adjournment be taken not later than 10.30 p.m.</P>
      <P>Resolved: That the Dáil meet to-morrow at 11 a.m., and that the Order for the adjournment be taken not later than 4 p.m.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BryanRiccoCooper" hpid="Major COOPER Major COOPER">
      <NameTxt>Major COOPER</NameTxt>
      <P>Would the President say whether it is the intention to take the Land Bill to-day or to-morrow?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>No.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamArcherRedmond" hpid="Captain REDMOND Captain REDMOND">
      <NameTxt>Captain REDMOND</NameTxt>
      <P>Can the President say whether it is intended to sit on Friday next?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>It is not.  I am presuming, of course, that the business which I have indicated&mdash;all the stages <Col N="1866" /> of the Central Fund Bill and the Second Stage of the Electricity (Supply) Bill&mdash;is taken before the adjournment this week.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="AlfredByrne" hpid="Mr. A. BYRNE Mr. A. BYRNE">
      <NameTxt>Mr. A. BYRNE</NameTxt>
      <P>When will the debate on the Electricity (Supply) Bill be resumed?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>To-morrow.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamDavin" hpid="Mr. DAVIN Mr. DAVIN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. DAVIN</NameTxt>
      <P>On the last day, before the adjournment, we were promised a statement giving the figures available in connection with Item No. 2 on to-day's Order Paper&mdash;Supplementary Estimate for the Department of Agriculture.  We have just been handed a statement which does not appear to contain very much information.  I would like to know from the Minister for Lands and Agriculture whether it would be possible to have copies of the balance sheets of the two companies in question, which it is proposed to purchase, circulated for the information of Deputies?  I notice that the Minister, in seeking to justify this Vote, gives the trading liabilities of the two companies, but I think the figures produced before us would not be sufficient to enable any Deputy to judge what are the actual liabilities of the companies involved in this transaction.  Are we to understand that this is the only information that we will be able to get in addition to whatever the Minister may have to say in his statement this evening?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickJHogan" hpid="MINISTER for LANDS and AGRICULTURE (Mr. Hogan) MINISTER for LANDS and AGRICULTURE (Mr. Hogan)">
      <NameTxt>MINISTER for LANDS and AGRICULTURE (Mr. Hogan)</NameTxt>
      <P>The Deputy has the statement, and there is also in the Dáil Office a copy of the agreement setting out as many figures as even the Deputy will go through.  In addition to that there will be a very long statement from me.  If the Deputy were to raise this point after hearing my statement he might find that it would be easier to deal with it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamDavin" hpid="Mr. DAVIN Mr. DAVIN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. DAVIN</NameTxt>
      <P>Are we to understand that the figures are available in the Office for any Deputy who wishes to get them?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. HOGAN Mr. HOGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. HOGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>The Deputy has a copy of the statement that has been issued. In addition there is the provisional agreement between the Condensed Milk Company of Ireland and a <Col N="1867" /> nominee of the Department of Agriculture. As soon as that was printed I had it placed in the Dáil Office.  That statement sets out a considerable amount of figures.  In addition to that, these figures will be elucidated by my statement.  By the time that the Deputy has digested all these figures he may have reason to change his mind on this.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DanielMorrissey" hpid="Mr. MORRISSEY Mr. MORRISSEY">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MORRISSEY</NameTxt>
      <P>Could the Minister say why copies of the provisional agreement were not circulated among the Deputies?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. HOGAN Mr. HOGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. HOGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>Because the printing of it was not finished in time.  The printing of it was finished about two hours ago and it was not circulated. The agreement was printed, and left in the Dáil Office and it was my intention to announce that fact before making my opening statement.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamDavin" hpid="Mr. DAVIN Mr. DAVIN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. DAVIN</NameTxt>
      <P>Does the Minister not agree that it would have been more businesslike to have printed and circulated to Deputies copies of the agreement?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. HOGAN Mr. HOGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. HOGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>On the last occasion I was asked to circulate some simple figures.  I pointed out it would be very difficult to circulate a simple statement that would be intelligible, and that I would be willing to make a statement to-day lasting an hour or an hour and a half.  In addition it was urged that the agreement should be printed.  It was printed, and I was able to get that agreement as far as the Dáil Office two hours ago.  I do not see what more I could possibly have done.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnDaly" hpid="Mr. DALY Mr. DALY">
      <NameTxt>Mr. DALY</NameTxt>
      <P>Would the Minister arrange that those creameries throughout the South of Ireland will not be setting up shops?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. HOGAN Mr. HOGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. HOGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>Might not this discussion come on after my statement?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnDaly" hpid="Mr. DALY Mr. DALY">
      <NameTxt>Mr. DALY</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister intended to quote Deputy Conlan who spoke the other day and said&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>The Deputy can quote him later.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="VOTE ON ACCOUNT FOR FINANCIAL YEAR" RHead="COMMENCING ON 1st APRIL, 1927">
    <Title>VOTE ON ACCOUNT FOR FINANCIAL YEAR COMMENCING ON 1st APRIL, 1927.</Title>
    <P>
      <Col N="1868" /> Resolution passed in Committee on Finance on Friday, March 11th, 1927, reported.</P>
    <Speaker pid="ErnestBlythe" hpid="MINISTER for FINANCE (Mr. Blythe) Ernest Blythe">
      <NameTxt>MINISTER for FINANCE (Mr. Blythe)</NameTxt>
      <P>I move: &ldquo;That the Dáil agrees with the Committee on Finance in the said Resolution.&rdquo;</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="IN COMMITTEE ON FINANCE. - VOTE ON ACCOUNT FOR FINANCIAL YEAR" RHead="COMMENCING ON 1st APRIL, 1927&mdash;ISSUE OUT OF THE CENTRAL FUND">
    <Title>IN COMMITTEE ON FINANCE. - VOTE ON ACCOUNT FOR FINANCIAL YEAR COMMENCING ON 1st APRIL, 1927&mdash;ISSUE OUT OF THE CENTRAL FUND.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="ErnestBlythe" hpid="Mr. BLYTHE Mr. BLYTHE">
      <NameTxt>Mr. BLYTHE</NameTxt>
      <P>I move:&mdash;</P>
      <P>Go ndeontar suim £8,081,717 as an bPrímh-Chiste chun an soláthar do deonadh i gcóir seirbhís na bliana dar críoch an 31adh lá de Mhárta, 1928, do shlánú.</P>
      <P>That towards making good the supply granted for the service of the year ending on the 31st day of March, 1928, the sum of £8,081,717 be granted out of the Central Fund.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>The Dáil went out of Committee.</P>
      <P>Resolution reported</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ErnestBlythe" hpid="Mr. BLYTHE Mr. BLYTHE">
      <NameTxt>Mr. BLYTHE</NameTxt>
      <P>I move:&mdash;&ldquo;That the Dáil agrees with the Committee on Finance in the said Resolution.&rdquo;</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="IN COMMITTEE ON FINANCE. - SUPPLEMENTARY" RHead="ESTIMATE&mdash;VOTE 52 (DEPARTMENT OF AGRICULTURE)">
    <Title>IN COMMITTEE ON FINANCE. - SUPPLEMENTARY ESTIMATE&mdash;VOTE 52 (DEPARTMENT OF AGRICULTURE).</Title>
    <Speaker pid="ErnestBlythe" hpid="Mr. BLYTHE Mr. BLYTHE">
      <NameTxt>Mr. BLYTHE</NameTxt>
      <P>I move:&mdash;</P>
      <P>Go ndeontar Suim Bhreise ná raghaidh thar Cheithre Chéad agus Cúig Mhíle Caogad Punt chun íoctha an Mhuirir a thiocfidh chun bheith iníoctha i rith na bliana dar críoch an 31adh lá de Mhárta, 1927, chun Tuarastail agus Costaisí na Roinne Talmhaíochta agus Seirbhísí áirithe atá fé riara na Roinne sin, maraon le hIldeontaisí-i-gCabhair.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="1869" /> That a Supplementary Sum not exceeding Four Hundred and Fifty-five Thousand Pounds be granted to defray the Charge which will come in course of payment during the year ending on the 31st day of March, 1927, for the Salaries and Expenses of the Department of Agriculture and of certain Services administered by that Department, including Sundry Grants-in-Aid.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickJHogan" hpid="MINISTER for LANDS and AGRICULTURE (Mr. P. Hogan) MINISTER for LANDS and AGRICULTURE (Mr. P. Hogan)">
      <NameTxt>MINISTER for LANDS and AGRICULTURE (Mr. P. Hogan)</NameTxt>
      <P>In November, 1926, a memorandum was received in the Department of Agriculture from the Irish Agricultural Organisation Society, setting out that the Condensed Milk Company of Ireland was willing to sell its interests, urging the necessity of buying, and asking the Government, in the event of a sale, to provide the necessary credits.  This proposal was considered in all its implications&mdash;first by the Department of Agriculture, and then by the Executive Council&mdash;before a decision was come to in the end of December authorising the opening of negotiations.  It was fully realised that this decision involved the Government in a most unusual role, and could only be justified as an essential part of a general policy for the reorganisation of the whole dairying industry.</P>
      <P>The commercial organisation of dairying in every country is different from that of practically any other business. The raw material&mdash;milk&mdash;is never paid for on delivery; it is paid for at the end of the month after delivery, when the finished article, namely butter, has been sold, and the price paid for the milk is governed rigidly by the price obtained for the butter.  Proprietary concerns quite properly exist to make profits for the proprietors and not for the suppliers of the raw materials, and when the finished article is sold before the raw materials are paid for it is inevitable that, in the absence of competition or control, the suppliers of the latter are at a grave disadvantage. This is the reason that the butter industry in every agricultural country in Europe is almost entirely in the hands of the farmer suppliers.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>As a rule the first few creameries established in most countries are proprietary, <Col N="1870" /> but the results of their operations inevitably lead to the establishment of co-operatives.  This country is no exception to that rule.  Co-operative and proprietary creameries began to spring up side by side until to-day, out of a total of 580 creameries, there are 400 co-operatives and 180 proprietaries. There are some excellent proprietary creameries, and there are some very poor ones.  There are a number of prosperous and efficient co-operative creameries, and at the same time there are a number that cannot be described as either prosperous or efficient.</P>
    <P>The organisation of the co-operative creameries is to a large extent unsound. There are, of course, exceptions, but the rule is that a co-operative creamery is established by a small and enthusiastic minority composed of the most go-ahead and enterprising farmers in the district.  They collect all the share capital they can obtain, they take a large amount themselves and they borrow the balance required for erecting and working the creamery from one of the Joint Stock Banks, giving as security the joint and several guarantees of a small number who are sufficiently unselfish to offer them.  As a rule shares are taken by a minority of the suppliers and the share capital paid up is only a small proportion of the total cost.</P>
    <P>This state of affairs is unsatisfactory. On the one hand the concern is under capitalised, on the other it is not adequate security for the full capital required, and finally, even if it were, the Joint Stock Banks cannot readily offer the sort of credits that are most suitable.  The Joint Stock Banks on the whole, and especially at certain periods, have put large sums of money into the business, but the transactions have never been entirely satisfactory either to them or to the societies.  The Joint Stock Banks are deposit banks, they must keep their money on call.  They were never organised for the purpose of giving long-term credits, and these are the sort of credits that the societies really require and that are most economic&mdash; credits that can be repaid gradually over a period of six to eight years by deduction from the price of the milk <Col N="1871" /> supplies.  When the Banks give these credits, as they cannot get the security of sufficient shares to cover the whole transaction, they have to insist on the joint and several guarantees of the farmers who are prominently connected with the enterprise.  The results are obvious.  The society is not, properly speaking, a co-operative society; the only persons who have a firm interest in it are the minority&mdash;the shareholders and the collateral securities.  These, especially the latter, take all the risks and do not get the sort of support they are entitled to get, and that they would get if every supplier was financially involved in the success of the venture. Moreover, there is no co-ordination between the various societies.  They are not all even affiliated to the central body, namely, the Organisation Society.</P>
    <P>This is the only country in Europe, I think, where co-operative creameries compete with each other both for the purchase of their milk supplies and for the sale of their butter.  Practically all the other countries that compete with the Irish Free State in the British market quote their butter in quantity and at firm prices.  Danish butter does not compete with Danish; it competes with Irish.  Here, however, any one Irish creamery will under-sell the other and an English grocer can get four or five different quotations from the same number of creameries in County Limerick or Tipperary. The net result of this is to depress the price of all.  There is even a more serious side to this competition and it is that while creameries in the Free State are consigning their butter to England in small lots from different points by different routes, it is extremely difficult for the carrying companies to provide refrigerated space or cold storage, with the result that no matter how good the butter may be when leaving the creamery, conditions of transit make it very difficult to guarantee the quality by the time it reaches the British grocer.  The difficulties of societies organised in this way in an area where there is competition between co-operative and co-operative and between co-operative and proprietary are obvious.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="1872" /> The manager must be careful that he does not offend suppliers whose supplies are not up to the required standard; the committee must pay at times uneconomic&mdash;because too high&mdash; prices for milk with the inevitable result that the society runs into debt and that in the long run all the suppliers lose on the double because of the necessity for borrowing under conditions which make high rates of interest inevitable; no adequate sums can be put by for reserves, necessary repairs, or new machinery.  Large numbers of suppliers who have no firm interest in the concern must be conciliated at all costs and the necessary sacrifices must always be made by the few.  Any other policy would result in some suppliers going over to the competing concerns and leaving the shareholders and guarantors to carry all the liabilities without adequate milk supplies.</P>
    <P>To a very large extent the creamery industry here is built on the enterprise and sacrifices of the few, and in this there is a sharp distinction between our co-operative organisations and those of any other country where cooperation is properly understood and worked.  Our societies are a compromise. They are proprietary in the sense that, in fact, though not in law, they are owned by the minority who take most of the risks.  They are co-operative in the sense that the advantages are divided between all.  They represent an attempt to reconcile the irreconcilable and in practice the result is that the advantages are diminished for the many and the risks increased for the few.</P>
    <P>While some competition exists between co-operative creameries, there is intense competition between proprietaries and co-operatives for milk supplies. The extreme case is where a co-operative and a proprietary central are situate in the same district practically alongside each other, and where each has anything from three to ten auxiliaries existing side by side with those of its competitor, all competing for the same milk supplies.  This is not uncommon; while in other districts there are co-operative and proprietary groups touching and competing with <Col N="1873" /> each other at various points.  This is always the position where there is proprietorial and co-operative competition. When a proprietary creamery is operating without co-operative competition, the temptation to give what will be regarded by farmers as poor prices for milk is overwhelming, and rightly or wrongly, farmers encouraged by the example of co-operative creameries in other districts will always insit on erecting creameries themselves, so as to provide an alternative outlet for their milk supplies.  In this way, as long as there are both proprietary and co-operative creameries in the same province, there always will be redundancy.  Redundancy means increased overhead expenses, and the position at the moment in the districts where proprietary and co-operative competition exists is that the farmers of these districts are paying always twice, and often three times the overhead expenses that are required for efficient production.</P>
    <P>The present state of affairs was almost inevitable.  In every agricultural country in Europe and America farmers' organisations were provided with suitable credits, and from a very early stage their developments were guided by co-operative legislation.  Here they were left without either.  It used to be the fashion here to talk loosely about the inefficiency of farmers and farmers' organisations.  Everybody heard of the few co-operative creameries that failed, and sweeping deductions were drawn from these comparatively few failures, very much to the discredit of the industry as a whole.  The fact is that the existence, in spite of all the disadvantages, of 400 co-operative creameries out of a total of 580 is an extraordinary testimony to the pioneer work of the I.A.O.S., and to the capacity and loyalty of the Irish farmers.  In no other country had farmers' organisations to grapple unaided with the same difficulties, and they are entitled to ask from the State now the facilities which have been refused to them for so long, and the want of which has placed them at such a disadvantage as compared with their competitors.</P>
    <P>There can be no doubt whatever as to the measures that are necessary, and <Col N="1874" /> no apology need be made for putting them into operation.  Co-operative Societies are at present governed by legislation passed for the purpose of regulating the operations of Friendly Societies.  This legislation is out of date even for the purposes for which it was passed, but in any event it was never intended and is entirely unsuitable for Agricultural Co-operative Societies.  For the purposes of Agricultural Societies it is proposed to introduce a Co-operative Act which will contain the provisions which are now common form in every other agricultural country.  I do not propose to indicate its provisions except in the most general way.  It will provide that all suppliers shall be shareholders; that a reasonable proportion of the share capital shall be paid up; that regular audits shall take place; that the area of operations of a creamery may be defined; that redundant creameries shall not be permitted and that all creameries shall be affiliated to the organisation society.  This Bill ought to be non-contentious, except perhaps in regard to some of its details. It would certainly be non-contentious in any of the countries which are competing with the Irish Free State in the British market.  These countries have adopted such an Act long ago, and consequently have long ago solved the problems which we must solve now.</P>
    <P>In addition, it is proposed to introduce and pass a Bill during this Session providing for the establishment of an Agricultural Credit Corporation.  This institution will deal with the credit needs of agriculture as a whole, but for the moment. I need only refer to its activities in connection with the dairying industry. One of its most important functions will be to deal with the credit needs of existing societies, and to provide sufficient capital for new societies.  It may be well at this stage to say that this Corporation will not exist to shovel out money indiscriminately.  It is the result of a recognition of the fact that agriculture requires not only additional, but, more especially, different kinds of credit to the credit facilities which were available for it <Col N="1875" /> from the Joint Stock Banks.  This Corporation will deal with long term and intermediate term credits, but if anybody has got the notion that it will be established for the purpose of giving other people's money to borrowers who are not security for it, or handing out money philanthropically, without due regard to the necessities and desirabilities in each case, and above all to the prospects of its being repaid, they should disillusion themselves at once.  So far as the dairying industry is concerned, it is obvious that the Corporation cannot operate effectively until the societies are so reorganised as to be adequate security for the credits required, that is to say, until the Co-operative Act is passed and put into operation.</P>
    <P>At this stage, however, we are brought right up against the fact that, even if the Co-operative Act were passed, it would be extremely difficult to put it into operation in present circumstances. Consider the effect in the present circumstances of attempting to compel suppliers of co-operative creameries to take up shares.  Dovetailed in amongst the 400 co-operative creameries there are 180 proprietaries, with their creameries situated to a very great extent almost alongside the co-operatives. The suppliers against whom compulsion would be used are suppliers who up to the present have refused to take shares, and it is, to say the least of it, highly probable that the immediate effect of such a provision would be that a number of these suppliers would go over to the proprietary concerns, that a number of the co-operative creameries would thereby be left in a much worse position financially than they are in now, and that some of them would be put out of business. This would be most unfair to the creameries concerned, and it would be particularly unfair to the suppliers who are already shareholders or who have given their own personal guarantees for the finances required, and who have borne all the burdens up to the present.  The Joint Stock Banks would have no option but to attempt to realise their securities immediately, not only in the case of creameries that were <Col N="1876" /> closed, but also in the cases of creameries which, though not closed, had been weakened financially by the loss of considerable milk supplies.  The fact is that the presence of the proprietaries, and in particular of the Condensed Milk Company, has the effect of pinning down the co-operatives in their present position and making it extremely difficult to carry out essential reorganisation.</P>
    <P>The problem is particularly acute in the area of operations of the Condensed Milk Company.  The Company control 114 out of a total of 180 proprietary creameries.  For the last three years the most intense competition has gone on between it and the co-operatives of Limerick, Tipperary and Cork.  It began in competition for milk supplies for existing creameries.  Where the proprietary and co-operative creameries existed side by side they proceeded to out-bid each other.  I may say that, in my opinion, as a purely business proposition this procedure was absolutely essential from the point of view of the Condensed Milk Company. Cleeves had been taken over by the Company in 1923, while it was in liquidation.  Very large sums of money were owed by the liquidated Company to farmers for milk supplies which had been previously delivered.  The goodwill of the business had been completely lost, and the new Company had no alternative except to regain that goodwill by lavish expenditure of money on its milk supplies during the first two or three years of its operations.</P>
    <P>Once a trade war like this begins it is difficult to limit it, and the co-operative creameries proceeded to meet the competition in the only way possible, and that was by establishing new co-operative creameries alongside creameries of the Company where these had not already existed.  The Company in turn retaliated in kind.  At first view it would look as if the farmers, during this period and in this area, were in a very happy position, in view of the intensive competition for their milk supplies, but in fact this was not so. All these operations were extremely wasteful.  They meant that the milk supplies in these areas were being <Col N="1877" /> handled at from twice to three times the normal cost, and this tended to keep all prices below what they might be. In addition to this, the suppliers to co-operative creameries were losing far more than they were gaining from any increase in price of milk, by reason of the fact that their societies, in order to give an uneconomic price and to erect new creameries, were running into debt and generally developing along lines which left the societies in an unsound position financially.</P>
    <P>This competition reached a climax in 1926.  On the one hand the Company had revived Cleeves, installed about £80,000 worth of new machinery and transport and, in addition, had re-established goodwill at the cost of about £100,000 in trade losses over the whole period.  On the other hand, the co-operatives were still holding on and even developing, but had used up most of their resources both in cash and credit in the task.  This position could not remain static.  Where there are two big interests competing within a small area for the same supplies and selling in the same market there is almost certain to be a trade war; and that is inevitable when one of them is composed of a number of independent units varying in their circumstances and without any common spokesman who could make an agreement on their behalf. The competition had to go on, and more money for the purpose had to be found by both sides.  This was, perhaps, an easier task for the Company than for the co-operatives.  The principal shareholders of the Company are Messrs Lovell and Christmas, Ltd., who are amongst the three biggest wholesale grocers in England.  They had already put big sums into the business, and I have very little doubt that, if there was no other alternative, they could find more.  Most of the creameries concerned, however, could get no more from the Joint Stock Banks and, as they had to find money or get out, during the latter half of the year 1926 urgent applications were sent in to the Department of Agriculture by the Irish Agricultural Organisation Society on behalf of a number of societies involved in competition with the Company.</P>
    <P>Looked at from any point of view, <Col N="1878" /> such applications raised very grave issues indeed.  These issues were being examined in all their implications by the Department of Agriculture, and it was in this state of affairs that in November, 1926, I was informed that the Company was ready to sell its interests. The Company had presumably also taken stock of its position, and while I am sure that the finding of fresh credits was not a serious problem for it, I am equally sure that the Report of the Banking Commission on Agricultural Credit just published raised considerations that it could not afford to ignore.  In the light of these facts, it seemed to me that there were three possible courses open to the Government&mdash;(1) to refuse to interfere either for or against either side, and to confine itself simply to keeping the ring; (2) to refuse to consider the Company's proposal and, instead, to provide working capital for the co-operative creameries so as to enable them to compete with the Company and (3) to consider favourably the proposal of the Company to sell.  I need not delay to consider the second possibility.  Such a course would be out of the question; that being the case, the situation was reduced to alternatives, namely, either to refuse to interfere in any way, or to consider the application to finance the purchase of the Company.</P>
    <P>The first alternative might have been adopted.  The State might have washed its hands of the whole business, left the issue to the parties concerned, and deferred the full reorganisation of the creameries for a few years until the situation had cleared up.  There are possibly two points of view as to what would have happened if this alternative had been adopted.  This is not the first time that something approaching a trade war was waged between proprietary and co-operative creameries.  It is, in fact, quite possible for individual proprietaries and individual co-operatives to continue their operations in more or less static competition for a long time.  There has been serious competition before between co-operative creameries and a combination of proprietary creameries, and, as a rule, the <Col N="1879" /> co-operative creameries have come out of it best.  The history of Cleeves is an example of this, and there are others.  This, however, was the first time in which the competition was on such a big scale.</P>
    <P>The Condensed Milk Company of Ireland is a very powerful concern financially.  It controls 114 creameries and 10 elaborate condensing plants.  The principal shareholders, Messrs.  Lovell and Christmas, are amongst the biggest wholesale grocers in England.  Messrs. Lovell and Christmas handle large quantities of Danish, Australian and New Zealand butter and I have no doubt whatever that when the creameries here have completed their marketing arrangements, this firm will be able to offer for and obtain bigger quotas of Irish butter than they have obtained before.  The standing of the firm is such that, from a purely business point of view, they are entitled to every consideration.  They had come into the Company two years ago, primarily in order to secure a quota of Irish butter&mdash;a perfectly legitimate ambition, not only from their own point of view, but from the point of view of the Irish farmer.  They had re-established the business by putting immense sums of money into it, and it is quite obvious they were not likely to surrender their commitments just at the stage when they had brought the Company into a position where they might reasonably hope for a dividend.  The competition, therefore, would have continued, and I have little doubt that during this year a number of co-operative societies&mdash;I will not attempt to indicate the number&mdash; in the absence of further credits, would close down, and their suppliers would have no option but to transfer to the Company's creameries.  I do not believe for a moment that the Company could clear its border lines of all competition in this way, but it would go a considerable distance towards this object. It would certainly come best out of the first round.  The Company would then be in a position to achieve that on which it had expended so much money during the last two years.  It <Col N="1880" /> could then start for the first time to trade on a normal basis, and to make sufficient profits to recoup itself for the inevitable losses of the reorganisation period.  It was in a particularly fortunate position for this purpose.  Even though there still remained competition from the co-operatives at certain points, it would be much more free of competition than formerly and it would be a very much simpler proposition to meet competition at the points where it still existed, as proprietary enterprises of this sort can always recoup themselves for losses at one end where competition exists, by additional profits where competition does not exist and where they have a monopoly.</P>
    <P>On the other hand, the position of the co-operative creameries would have been changed.  Some of them would have gone out, but these would have been the weakest, and a somewhat smaller, but, in my opinion, a stronger body of co-operatives would be left in existence. They would have learned a bitter lesson, which would drive them into a certain amount of co-ordination.  A position like this could not remain static.  On the one side, there would be farmer suppliers to proprietary creameries anxious to establish co-operative creameries again.  On the other the co-operative creameries would be anxious to extend out, and in this way the two interests would meet again within a few years and the fight would begin anew.  In my opinion, by that time the result of the fight would be somewhat different, and it might very well be that the proprietary concern, having won the first round, would lose the second.  It would certainly be either that result, or a draw.  Everyone will realise that this would be a most unsatisfactory position.  During this transition period the necessities of the competition would result in waste, dissipated effort, and heavy losses to the co-operatives, and in particular to the shareholders and guarantors.  The banks would be forced to the conclusion that money invested in farmers' creameries was not secure, and in many cases they would have no option but to attempt to liquidate their guarantees.</P>
    <P>Even from the point of view of the Company, the situation would, <Col N="1881" /> at best, be unsatisfactory.  It could not meet competition effectively by remaining frozen in the same position, and it would proceed to branch out into new districts where there were no creameries.  The first signs of developments in this direction would result in the farmers of these districts coming together and asking for authority to put up co-operative societies themselves.  The body that would have the making of the decision as between the two interests would find itself in a very unsatisfactory and difficult position.  It would undoubtedly have to take the line that if farmers wished to put up their own creameries they had the first option and the net result of this would be that the Company, faced at many points with serious competition, would be prevented by State action from meeting it effectively in the only way in which it can be met, that is, by developing its business.</P>
    <P>In a word, the whole situation would be impossible, and it is quite plain that there was no real alternative except to cut the knot at once and to agree to provide credits for the purchase of the assets of the Company, provided these could be purchased at a reasonable price.  In considering the application it was obvious that in normal circumstances the attitude of the Minister for Finance should be that if the co-operative creameries concerned purchased, he would lend the money required to supplement local capital, provided he approved of the price and was offered sufficient security.  This attitude, however, could not be adopted in this case.  It would be merely another way of refusing to have anythink to do with the matter.  It is obvious that the Company could not negotiate on the basis that, if and when a price was fixed as between the negotiators, each and every one of the creameries involved should agree to it. Any small proportion of the suppliers could prevent the sale by disagreement, and the Company would then be in the invidious position of having offered to sell, having revealed its exact position and, to some extent, its trade secrets, and nevertheless <Col N="1882" /> having to carry on because the ultimate purchasers had refused to agree amongst themselves.  This was out of the question in this particular case. The farmers concerned had learned a very bitter lesson as a result of the liquidation of Cleeves, and in these circumstances the Company could not afford to allow a feeling of insecurity to grow up amongst their suppliers.  If the Company attempted to negotiate in such a way as to make it necessary to consult the suppliers to co-operative creameries all over the area, within which its operations were carried on, the inevitable result would be that at an early stage after these consultations had become public, the Company would begin to lose its own suppliers.  If a large number of the suppliers thought that the creameries which they were supplying were likely to be closed down in the near future, rightly or wrongly they would come to their own conclusions, and they would see what they regarded as very good reasons for being amongst the first to transfer their milk supplies.  It was therefore out of the question to insist on the purchase going through on the basis that the co-operative societies concerned should buy, and having come to the conclusion that it was essential to buy, we had in fact no other alternative, except the alternative which has been adopted and which, in fact, amounts to buying ourselves and transferring afterwards.</P>
    <P>The negotiations for the purchase of the fixed assets of the Condensed Milk Company commenced in November, 1926; the price was settled at £365,000 on the 22nd February, 1927, and a provisional agreement for sale was signed on the 12th March, 1927.</P>
    <P>In the Spring of 1924 the Condensed Milk Company of Ireland (1924 Ltd.) was formed for the purchase of the original Condensed Milk Company of Ireland Ltd., and Cleeves Ltd., which had gone into liquidation in the year 1923; I will call both bodies, for the sake of brevity, Cleeves&mdash;and in the year 1925 the Condensed Milk Company purchased the Newmarket Dairy Company Ltd.  The Company, therefore, owns the business and assets of Messrs.  Cleeves and of the Newmarket <Col N="1883" /> Dairy Company, and in addition, about ten creameries which were purchased or erected since 1925.</P>
    <P>The nominal capital of the Condensed Milk Company is 300,000 £1 shares, of which 240,000 are fully paid up.</P>
    <P>The principal shareholders are (1) Messrs Lovell and Christmas, of London, who hold 140,473 shares; (2) Mr. Andrew O'Shaughnessy, T.D., who holds 35,000 shares; (3) the Newmarket Dairy Company, who hold 47,058 shares; the balance, namely, 17,469 shares, is divided between seven shareholders in small amounts.  The total capital put into the business since its inception is very difficult to estimate, because very large sums were invested in the erection of buildings, etc., by Messrs. Cleeves, and all these assets were sold in the turmoil of 1923 at a sacrifice figure to the new Company. Since the liquidation of Cleeves, however, there has been about £400,000 net put into the business in one way or another.</P>
    <P>Of the 240,000 shares which have been issued fully paid-up, 225,000 represent cash shares and 15,000 bonus shares.  Of the 225,000 shares 79,000 represented moneys which had been paid to the liquidator of Cleeves.  Further investments in the Company include a cash loan by Messrs. Lovell and Christmas of £100,000, the full value of decrees obtained by the Company for compensation for property in Tipperary (namely, £16,000) and elsewhere, and advances by way of ordinary bank overdrafts. Cleeves, Ltd., was purchased while in liquidation for the sum of about £80,000, and, in addition, the sum of about £40,000 was paid to farmers in respect of milk supplied to the old Company. This was not a debt due by the new Company, but it was considered that it was necessary to pay it in order to re-establish goodwill. The Newmarket Dairy Company was subsequently purchased for £90,000.  New and additional machinery, transport, buildings, etc., cost about £90,000, making about £300,000 in all.  The difference between this figure and the net amount put into the <Col N="1884" /> concern would appear in a balance sheet as trade losses over the whole period.  These are approximate figures. There is no balance sheet for the whole period, and the 1926 balance sheet is not yet published.  The difference represents to some extent what can be described as normal trade losses, but it is mainly money expended with a view to re-establishing the goodwill of Cleeves, Ltd., regaining supplies from the co-operatives and ultimately clearing the field of operations of the Company of competition from the co-operative creameries.</P>
    <P>At present the property of the Company includes (1) 113 creameries, of which 14 are centrals and 99 auxiliaries; (2) 10 condensed milk plants, 2 of which are finishing and 8 crude centres; and (3) other assets, including an up-to-date toffee factory, mills, houses, lands, shops, motor transport, and interest in an International Condensed Milk Distributive Company. These are the assets for which £365,000 has been paid.</P>
    <P>The procedure proposed for the transfer of the Company is as follows:&mdash;The 300,000 £1 shares of the Company (of which 240,000 are fully paid-up) will be purchased for £196,513, and the trade credits and trade liabilities of the Company will be taken over by the purchaser.  The purchaser in the first instance will be a holding body nominated by the Department of Lands and Agriculture.  The trade debts exceed the trade credits by £168,487, and this sum of £168,487, when added to the price of the shares, viz., £196,513, amounts to the figure for which the Company was purchased, viz., £365,000.  It will be seen that it is vital that this figure of £168,487, being the difference between the trade debts and the trade credits, should be a firm figure, and to effect this an agreement will be entered into under which Messrs. Lovell and Christmas will guarantee that the credits and liabilities amount to certain figures, so that in the event of the difference between them being more than £168,487, the surplus will be recouped by Messrs. Lovell and Christmas.</P>
    <P>The price was fixed in the ordinary way by bargain and sale, the negotiations <Col N="1885" /> being conducted on the purchasers' side by Mr. Cox, of Messrs.  Arthur Cox and Company, solicitors to the I.A.O.S. The valuation of the machinery of the condenseries and toffee factory was made by Mr. Patchell, an ex-Chairman of the Institute of Civil Engineers. London, and by the chief engineer of one of the largest German Dairy Engineering firms.  The price of £365,000 was arrived at without reference to the moneys put into the business by the owners.  The negotiations were carried on from the point of view of purchasing at a figure which represented a fair value of the property as a going concern.  When the price was arrived at in this way, and when the difference between the trade debts and trade credits had been fixed at a firm figure by the guarantee of Messrs. Lovell and Christmas, the price of the shares was adjusted so that the total figure would amount to £365,000.</P>
    <P>It is considered essential that the liquidation of the Company and transfer of the property to the co-operative societies concerned should commence immediately, so that the necessary adjustments, at least of the creameries, should be completed before the beginning of the next milk season.</P>
    <P>A considerable number of the creameries will now become redundant.  When I speak of them as redundant I mean that they are placed alongside and are competing for milk supplies with co-operative creameries which are themselves capable, without any additions in the way of plant or buildings, of handling at least the total milk supplies of both.  An additional complication is added by the fact that a few of the Company's creameries will in the new scheme of things become partly redundant and partly non-redundant.  For example, a central creamery of the Company may become an auxiliary to an existing co-operative central, or a co-operative central may become an auxiliary to one of the Company's non-redundant creameries, where a new co-operative society is being set up, or where the Company's creamery is a good one as a central.  There are not many such cases, and they need not for the moment be taken into account.</P>
    <P>In view of the fact that roughly half <Col N="1886" /> the creameries are redundant, it will not be possible to recover the full price of all the creameries from the co-operative societies.  For the purpose of re-selling the Company's creameries to co-operative societies they may be divided into three classes:</P>
    <P>(1) non-redundant creameries operating in areas where there are no co-operative societies;</P>
    <P>(2) non-redundant creameries operating in areas where there are co-operative societies; and</P>
    <P>(3) redundant creameries</P>
    <P>The proposal in regard to (1) is simple.  These creameries will be sold to new societies, to be formed from the suppliers, at the price for which they were purchased from the Company.</P>
    <P>With regard to (2): New societies will not be formed to take over these creameries; they will be sold as operative concerns to existing societies at the full price for which they were purchased.</P>
    <P>With regard to (3), that is to say, redundant creameries: These were purchased as going concerns.  They will now be closed and dismantled.  It is obvious that in many instances the total price paid for them cannot be recovered from the co-operative societies.  These societies are only acquiring the milk supplies, and it is for the milk supplies that they will be expected to pay.  They will be dismantled and the buildings and machinery disposed of at the best price available.  To cover the difference between the price paid for the creamery as a going concern and its value as thus disposed of, where a difference exists, the Minister for Finance will contribute a grant.</P>
    <P>The position, therefore, is that so far as we are selling any portion of the property of the Condensed Milk Company to the creameries, we will only sell at the price for which we purchased it.  A grant, as opposed to a loan, can only be given in respect of property which has been purchased but which is redundant, in the sense that it is not being transferred.  We will expect that the purchase money will be covered by shares with a reasonable amount paid up, and the balance will be advanced by the Minister <Col N="1887" /> for Finance at a reasonable rate of interest.  The arrangements for repayment will be exactly the same as the arrangements for the repayment of sums advanced from the fund recently voted by the Dáil for new creameries, that is to say, by monthly deductions from milk supplies.  It is expected that the total grant which the Treasury will be asked for in respect of these redundant creameries will be between £50,000 and £60,000.  The co-operative creameries will be expected to undertake liability for the balance, viz., £150,000 or £160,000.</P>
    <P>With regard to the ten condensers, Deputies are probably aware that a considerable proportion of Irish condensed milk is made from separated milk.  The butter fat is used to make butter in the creamery attached to the condensery, and the separated milk is condensed. Four of these condenseries exist in the Limerick-Tipperary area.  In this district there is intensive dairying, and there are large supplies of separated milk to spare, over and above what is required for calf rearing and pig feeding. On the other hand, the condenseries in the southern area are in a different position.  In this area there are much smaller milk supplies, and there is at the same time more calf rearing and pig feeding, and consequently more separated milk required for these purposes.  In normal circumstances there would be very small supplies of separated milk available for condensing.  The Company obtained its milk supplies in this area, in keen competition with the co-operatives, by a complicated and expensive system of transport capable of tapping a very wide area.  It is clearly undesirable to attract away the separated milk from the feeding of calves and pigs in an area where there is considerable rearing of calves and pigs and where there are no big supplies of separated milk. The Company, of course, were not under the necessity of taking these considerations into account.  From the point of view of farmers and farmers' societies they are very relevant, and it seems clear that the condenseries in <Col N="1888" /> this area&mdash;about half the total&mdash;must be regarded as redundant.  My proposal is to get whatever advice is considered necessary on the question as soon as possible.  It may be that some of the machinery should be transferred to other areas, but it seems clear in any event that there will be something like £50,000 of redundant property amongst the condenseries and that this must be covered by grant and not by loan.  The non-redundant condensers would be taken over by some society or federation of co-operative societies at the price for which they were purchased, the whole cost being covered by share capital, a reasonable amount being paid up, and the balance being found by loan, to be repaid by periodic payments of interest and sinking fund.</P>
    <P>I am not to be taken as deprecating the condensing industry.  I consider it necessary that our dairying should be more adaptable.  There is every advantage in having more than one string to the bow.  Butter will always, of course, remain the main source of income and an absolute necessity to our present agricultural economy, but in view of increasing competition it is highly desirable to be in a position to take advantage of favourable markets for condensed milk, cream, and cheese.</P>
    <P>With regard to the &ldquo;other assets,&rdquo; these of course are not required by the farmers and must be disposed of elsewhere as soon as possible, consistent with getting their full value.  In view of the fact that they are for sale, I do not wish to indicate their cost at this stage.</P>
    <P>The taking over, disintegration and transfer of such a big business will undoubtedly prove a difficult and costly task.  The transfer would be simple if there were no condenseries, if creameries only were involved, and if these creameries could be divided into two classes&mdash;redundant and non-redundant. The case of the Lansdowne premises will illustrate the difficulties. This premises includes a central creamery, condensery, and an adjoining toffee factory.  It was necessary to concentrate huge quantities of milk there in order to keep the condensers going, and this necessitated a huge creamery as well.  The Company <Col N="1889" /> of course could not get skim or whole milk from the co-operatives.  So far as the creamery is concerned, it is one of the biggest central creameries in Europe.  The plant is designed to handle enormous quantities of milk and butter.  This might have been quite sound from the point of view of the organisation of the Company, but the position of the Lansdowne premises will be radically altered by the transfer.  The district is studded with first-class co-operative creameries, from which the necessary supplies of separated milk may be obtained, and it may very well be that the ultimate fate of the Lansdowne creamery, apart from the condensing side of the business, will be to become an auxiliary to a co-operative central in the same neighbourhood, while the condensery along with others will become the property of some federation of co-operative societies.  This central creamery, apart from the condensery and toffee factory, with its plant and equipment, and with the milk supplies which it obtained from its own auxiliaries, is valued as a going concern for £16,500, and it was bought for that figure from the Condensed Milk Company. On the other hand, if it is to be closed as a central and worked merely as an auxiliary, it is not of course worth anything like that figure, and must be regarded as partly redundant, and the societies concerned will in that event be asked only to take liability for that proportion of the price that would represent its value as an auxiliary. Of course this is all conjecture and further consideration may lead to different plans.  There are other creameries which present the same sort of problem, but not, of course, to the same extent, and the expenses of these creameries represent a considerable slice of the £50,000 grant which must be found as a portion of the total price of the creameries.</P>
    <P>Obviously the correct course is to limit the problem as much and as soon as possible.  The liquidation will commence at once and arrangements will be made for the transfer of the milk supplies of redundant creameries so as to get these out of the way with the <Col N="1890" /> least possible delay.  The organising of new societies can then be undertaken, and by the time that this work is done it will be easier to deal with the difficulties that are left.</P>
    <P>The liquidation will proceed, the redundant creameries and condenseries will be closed, and concurrently with this arrangements will be made for the transfer of non-redundant creameries to existing societies and to new co-operative societies to be formed for the purpose, and for the transfer of the milk supplies of redundant creameries to existing societies.  All this will cost money.  While a business is in liquidation there is practically no income to be put against its overhead expenses. The cost of this liquidation and transfer will be borne by the State.</P>
    <P>When it was decided that there was no alternative to purchasing, the problem resolved itself into getting good value for the dairy farmers who would be the ultimate purchasers consistent with, and I make no secret whatever of this, giving full fair play to the Company.  Whatever views its shareholders may have I am satisfied that the Company has got fair play, but I am still more satisfied that the creameries concerned and the co-operative movement generally have got real good value.  The question &ldquo;Could the Company be induced or coerced to sell for less?&rdquo; can be readily answered.  The Company could be forced to sell its assets for whatever figure the Dáil inserted in an Act of Parliament passed for the purpose of compulsory acquisition. This question is, however, entirely irrelevant.  Once the Government intervenes it is no longer a question of the lowest price but of fair compensation.</P>
    <P>The real considerations are two-fold and can be stated as follows:&mdash;Having regard to the circumstances and implications of this transaction, has the Company got fair compensation and have the dairy farmers of the country got good value?  I have not the slightest hesitation in answering both questions in the affirmative.  The creameries, as I have said, cost £210,000, and this leaves the condensers and what I have called &ldquo;other assets&rdquo; at £155,000.  These <Col N="1891" /> other assets include house property apart from dwelling-houses attached to creameries, transport, mills, toffee factory, land, shops, etc.  I do not wish to indicate the cost of those because they must be re-sold in the open market. Moreover, if I indicated precisely the cost of the condensers I would thereby be stating the exact price of the &ldquo;other assets.&rdquo;  I can, however, give a figure which I will ask the Dáil to accept as sufficient for the purposes of this discussion and which at the same time will not prejudice the position. There are three items amongst the &ldquo;other assets&rdquo; which, apart from the rest, are worth in the open market at least £40,000.</P>
    <P>The net amount in respect of creameries for which the societies will be asked to take liability is about £160,000, that is, after deducting the grant in respect of redundancy.  These creameries handle in a season 24,000,000 gallons, being the milk of about 55,000 cows.  That is a conservative estimate. An average auxiliary cannot be run for less than £600 per annum.  The closing of the redundants will save the farmers at the very least between £35,000 and £40,000 per annum in overhead expenses. This sum would pay off the debt, interest and sinking fund, in six to eight years three times over.  The total price has, of course, been apportioned between each creamery.  If, a month ago, before this transaction had become public, the committee of any co-operative creamery concerned was informed that it could buy its particular competitor at the price which has now been fixed upon it, and that a loan would be forthcoming for the purchase, it would accept the proposition not only with unanimity but with enthusiasm. From the point of view of the societies that are actually taking the property, the transaction represents real good value as a commercial transaction, but from the point of view of the industry as a whole and of the indirect benefits, the value is inestimable.</P>
    <P>I do not anticipate many difficulties. It is expected that every effort will be made to get the shares to cover the assets transferred by shares subscribed voluntarily, and I believe that far the <Col N="1892" /> greatest proportion of the shares will be forthcoming in this way, but in any event the committees of the societies concerned will, if necessary, have the aid of the Co-operative Act to compel any recalcitrant minorities to do their part by taking their just proportion of the shares.</P>
    <P>I hope that nobody will make the mistake of regarding this transaction as the beginnings of a policy under which the Government proposes to run the creameries of the country.  The exact contrary is the fact.  The purchase of these creameries has no justification other than it is a necessary preliminary to the efficient working of the Agricultural Credit Corporation and the Co-operative Act.  The Co-operative Act will regulate and define the conditions under which existing societies may operate, and new societies be established.</P>
    <P>The Agricultural Credit Corporation will provide the necessary credits for agriculture generally, and for the dairying industry in particular.  When this transaction is completed, the Co-operative Act passed, and the Credit Corporation established, the responsibility for the future of the industry will be in the hands of the farmers themselves, and the functions of the State will, to a great extent, be negative. The organisation problems which I have indicated in this statement will still remain to be solved, but they must be solved by the joint efforts of the Agricultural Organisation Society and the creameries.</P>
    <P>Nobody knows better than the Irish farmer that money is not to be &ldquo;picked up&rdquo; in dairying.  The industry has gone through hard times during the last two years, and there are hard times still ahead.  Competition is getting keener every year.  Our competitors are putting all their resources of technical skill and organisation into the fight.  We can only hold our own by going one better.  Even under the best conditions and with the measures proposed, the problems outstanding cannot be solved without good-will and without considerable hard thinking and hard work.  I am quite satisfied that there is sufficient <Col N="1893" /> capacity for both within the co-operative movement to effect the desired ends.  I conceive it to be the duty of the Government to pay off arrears, even though it is not responsible for them, to put the dairying industry on a solid foundation, and, having done that, to make it quite clear to the farmers concerned that the future is their own making.</P>
    <P>I will be told that this policy aims at a monopoly.  I admit it&mdash;a most unusual monopoly: a monopoly of all the producers.  I would point out that it is going to benefit the farmers, and would ask whom is it going to injure? The fruits of such a policy will not only manifest themselves in the countryside but also in increased prosperity in every town of the Free State.  I will be further told that this is an attempt to shelter the dairying industry from competition.  It is rather an attempt to enable the industry to meet the organised competition of Denmark, New Zealand, Australia, and Canada.  This competition is quite sufficient to go on with and to keep the industry on its mettle.</P>
    <P>Dairying is just as essential to our agricultural economy as a manured crop is to the rotation.  Our policy is to hand over the industry to the farmers themselves.  This is certain to lead to the formation of a solid and formidable organisation, around which they can shelter in difficult times, and which will grow and develop until our farmers control every phase of agricultural production and thereby obtain what they are not obtaining now, a fair proportion of the profits of their labour.</P>
    <Speaker pid="DanielMorrissey" hpid="Mr. MORRISSEY Mr. MORRISSEY">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MORRISSEY</NameTxt>
      <P>Can the Minister give us any idea of the number of employees who will be disemployed as a result of the wiping out of the redundant creameries?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. HOGAN Mr. HOGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. HOGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>I could give the Deputy estimates, but perhaps the Deputy would defer that question until 7 o'clock.</P>
      <P>Ordered: That the debate be resumed at 7 o'clock.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="IN COMMITTEE ON FINANCE. - ELECTRICITY" RHead="SUPPLY BILL, 1927&mdash;SECOND STAGE">
    <Title>IN COMMITTEE ON FINANCE. - ELECTRICITY SUPPLY BILL, 1927&mdash;SECOND STAGE.</Title>
    <Col N="1894" />
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="MINISTER for INDUSTRY and COMMERCE (Mr. McGilligan) Patrick McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>MINISTER for INDUSTRY and COMMERCE (Mr. McGilligan)</NameTxt>
      <P>In moving the Second Reading of the Electricity Supply Bill, 1927, I think, even although my time is somewhat limited this evening, that it would be better to devote a certain amount of exordial matter to relate the position in which my Department, and the Government as a whole, found itself with regard to the scheme which had been adopted and to which legislative effect had been given by the first Shannon Act of over eighteen months ago. The Bill is long and involved, but its central idea may be quite easily grasped, and I want to speak by way of a long introduction to that central idea in order to justify the Government's action in taking the step this Bill shows them to have decided upon for the whole control of electricity in this country.  After the Shannon scheme had been adopted by the House, and universally, or almost universally, applauded throughout the country, and when the first piece of legislation dealing with that scheme had been passed, the immediate business that lay before those of us who were specially concerned with the carrying out of the scheme was, first of all, the civil engineering contract which had to be entered into at once so that the work might be started without any delay and so bring the benefits of this scheme as soon as possible to the country.  That occupied the greater part of the summer of 1925, and it was seen, while that contract was going through, that the second contract for the electrical and mechanical side of the works could be postponed, and had better be postponed, for a period of almost a year, that there would be no delay occasioned to the completion of the work by such a postponement, and that there would be further time to examine and investigate all the materials and all the prices that fell for consideration in the completion of the second contract.  But during that period there also came up for consideration the whole question of the big <Col N="1895" /> problem raised&mdash;it was not the first time it had been adverted to, but it became more pressing&mdash;by the starting of the national electricity scheme for the country.  I would like to state that problem here by way of a certain amount of figures, figures which, I am afraid, I shall have to refer to very often this evening, but figures which are very material to any proper understanding of the problem that lay ahead of us.</P>
      <P>The Shannon scheme was projected to bring electrical current, it was said, to all towns and villages of 500 population and upwards.  Actually it will not do so; a certain number of smaller towns will be left out.  I may omit these as being outside consideration for the moment.  Let us get that down to figures and see what it means.  I have taken the most up-to-date returns, the provisional returns from the last census. Those show that there are in this country 225 towns and villages of 500 population and upwards, and the population of these 225 is 1,035,000.  At this moment in the country there are twenty statutory undertakings and there are ninety non-statutory, or unauthorised, undertakings.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFrancisBaxter" hpid="Mr. BAXTER Mr. BAXTER">
      <NameTxt>Mr. BAXTER</NameTxt>
      <P>Ninety?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGILLIGAN Mr. McGILLIGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGILLIGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>There are, in fact, more.  It depends upon where one draws the line with regard to what is described as a non-statutory undertaking. If one were to include every case in which a person who generates electricity supplies somebody other than himself there would be nearly 300 undertakings.  But taking into consideration only those which are of some substance, only those where there is some appreciable amount of capital involved, and where there is behind the whole thing the idea of a commercial undertaking, there are ninety non-statutory undertakings in the country.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>It may be well here to define, briefly and without pretending to be technical, the difference between the statutory and the non-statutory undertaking.  The statutory undertaking is authorised by Order under legislation.  It is generally set up after a special inquiry; it has a <Col N="1896" /> definite limitation put upon its area; it is given a monopoly within that area; consumers are protected against that monopolistic undertaking inside the area; its rates are subject to revision from time to time within certain periods, and people within the area must get supplied if they ask for it. There are twenty such undertakings in the country, twenty which have been granted under statute a monopoly with in prescribed areas, and within which areas consumers have certain rights guaranteed to them by law.</P>
    <Speaker pid="TomasOConnell" hpid="Mr. T. O'CONNELL Mr. T. O'CONNELL">
      <NameTxt>Mr. T. O'CONNELL</NameTxt>
      <P>How many of these are local authorities?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGILLIGAN Mr. McGILLIGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGILLIGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>I am coming to that.  There are then ninety non-statutory undertakings, limited to a certain type of case.  Of the twenty statutory undertakings five are privately owned&mdash;five are owned by companies&mdash;and fifteen are under the control of municipal authorities of some form or other.  The five privately owned have within their statutory areas a population of about 109,000 people, and the fifteen municipal statutory undertakings have within the areas of their supply about 502,000 people.  Of the ninety non-statutory undertakings twelve are situated in places of under 500 population, and they are omitted from this on for the purpose of my calculations.  The remaining seventy eight are in areas, the total population of which is 164,000&mdash;not, of course, the total population served by these seventy eight non-statutory undertakings.  In villages and towns with 500 population and upwards entirely without electricity, the total population is about 264,000.  That was the situation, not exactly the situation as I found it in 1925, but the situation adjusted to the most recent figures of population, the figures in the last census, and the problem that faced us with regard to the whole Shannon undertaking was that a calculation showed that round about 1929, under ordinary conditions, the consumption of electricity in this country would have advanced to the region of about 70,000,000 units and in order to make this scheme remunerative, <Col N="1897" /> 110,000,000 units would have to be sold at the experts' price.</P>
      <P>May I sum up that problem in this way?&mdash;that you had a population to be served by the Shannon scheme of about 1,035,000 people; that 75 per cent. of these people were in some way or another served, or had somewhere or another in their neighbourhood electricity undertakings, either of a statutory or non-statutory type; that the 25 per cent. of the population to be served under the projected lay-out of the Shannon system were entirely without electricity; and that in some way or another the natural growth of consumption, which would have reached about 70,000,000 units in 1929, had to be raised by extra efforts to 110,000,000.  Three-quarters of the area was already in the hands of statutory or non-statutory undertakings.  One-quarter was entirely without electricity but some way or other operating the scheme over the three-quarters already served or in the quarter without such service, sales had to be raised by 40,000,000 units.  That was the problem as I saw it late in 1925, when for other purposes I had to make a visit to the United States of America. My purpose, however, was not completely disconnected with electricity. I had to survey the ground and see if specialists of certain types could be had; but while having that my first and main object I found it was not merely easy, but it was embarrassing to have on hands at the same time such a thing as the Shannon scheme, because I found that scheme had excited intense interest in America, excited great interest among those who were anxious to see initiative and enterprise develop in this country, and also had caused great interest amongst others who, being frankly without any altruistic ideas with regard to this country, were keen on seeing how the Shannon scheme was likely to work out.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I found myself approached from many quarters, and many discussions were raised in regard to this scheme, with regard to its prospects, with regard to its financing, with regard to its management, and so on, and on many occasions I was asked if the Government <Col N="1898" /> of this State would be prepared to consider the leasing of the Shannon as a concession to certain companies. I had no authority at that time even to discuss the matter.  I had authority to learn as much as I could about electricity systems&mdash;systems of control and management, particularly on the supply side, and when I returned after that trip, when certain offers and approaches began to be made, not merely from America, but from Europe, I took the advice of the Executive Council, and with their approval sent letters to certain people who had made application to me that if they were prepared to make offers then, without giving them any guarantee that even the ideally best offer would be accepted, I was nevertheless prepared to receive their offers and to have them discussed.</P>
    <P>I always inserted one proviso&mdash;that any arrangement would be put up here for consideration and that an arrangement which gave the best results to the consumer consistent with safeguarding the national interests, would be, if it was found good enough, recommended to this Dáil for its approval or rejection.  I can come back to the results of that later on.</P>
    <P>During the conversations I had in America and Canada&mdash;conversations in which I made it quite clear to those who had come to me that a certain Article in our Constitution, Article 11, had best be interpreted as showing a certain tendency in people's minds here with regard to the ownership and the control of national undertakings and emphasising certain other things &mdash;I found myself by great good luck one day in the midst of a controversy which seemed, at first, to have no great relation to the subject I was dealing with, but which on investigation proved to be very appropriate.  I found there was a controversy in America with regard to what was called super power as against giant power, and although that controversy raged around me for several days I could not feel quite clear at the end that I could put my finger on the essential differences between super power and giant power.  I did hear any amount of arguments that the one <Col N="1899" /> meant the inter-connection of isolated systems, whereas the other meant what was described as regional integration and that left me very little wiser than I had been previously.  I found, however, there was considerable controversy and considerable heat engendered as to what were described as the social results of one or other of these two systems.  Then for the first time I did discover one thing that did seem fundamental in this whole argument. The super-power enthusiasts were financiers pure and simple, and the super-power enthusiasts' attitude was that they must skim the cream in any district, that they must only go to where the load was good, and that one thing that never entered into their calculations, or if it entered it was only to be rejected, was the question of electrification of rural districts. The other people having, or at least, professing to have, a better idea of social service and standing for the decentralisation of population rather than for its congestion in big cities aimed rather at rural electrification, and that, if not the basis of their system, was certainly pointed to as one of the most advantageous social results from their system as opposed to the other.</P>
    <P>I came on that particular difference by accident, but that particular difference I found went right through all the arguments and controversies that I ever afterwards heard either about the difference between these two systems or as between public ownership or public regulation, and private enterprise under what was called public utility regulation.  I found, for instance, that the Ontario system, which is, of course, a system of public or State ownership of the natural resources in so far as they are electrically producing and State ownership of the transmission system, and permission even to have State control and State ownership of distribution down to the consumer&mdash;that these people in the Ontario system, specially billed themselves as having had great consideration for the rural population, and that the system managed by them had, <Col N="1900" /> in fact, a greater effect upon rural electrification than any private enterprise, or private enterprise under public company regulation could ever have had in the United States of America.  I discovered, in Canada, that as well as the Ontario Hydro-Electric Commission there were systems corresponding to it in two other of the provinces, in Nova Scotia and New Brunswick, the regulations being pretty definitely the same, and that the idea of the boards, a chairman and two others to control, was identical.</P>
    <P>That led to an investigation afterwards of just what were the different systems under which plant of the electric-producing type might be either owned or administered.  A review of legislation through the countries of Europe and in America showed clearly that the whole tendency, as far as ownership of natural resources of the type of water power or fuel was concerned, was definitely coming to be regarded as a matter purely for State ownership and State control.  When one entered on the second point of inquiry as to long distance transmission, although it was not so clearly defined and so completely achieved, there was again the tendency that long distance transmission should be under the control of, and that the property should remain in the ownership of the State or of the provincial authorities.  When one got to local distribution there was somewhat a different story.  But again I found a difference which had been quite clear to me before, but never had been made so concrete as I found it when this investigation went through.</P>
    <P>I had often heard various arguments as to the results expected to accrue, on the one hand from what is called private ownership, and, on the other hand, Government or State ownership. But I never had realised just how completely absurd these two terms were to cover the variety of different organisations that might be set up under the name of one or other of them.  One hears about State control.  I found State control of about eight or nine different types operating as between railways, canals, power resources and harbours in different countries of the world.  When it came to private <Col N="1901" /> ownership, we found quite as many differences in the actual details of the control or of the administration as were to be found on the other side. Allegations are made, and counter-charges made against them, as to the defects that ordinarily would flow from State control.  Similar arguments are made, and rebutting arguments put up, as to the disadvantages likely to accrue from private ownership.  But I found myself driven to what anybody inquiring in this way must be driven to&mdash;an inquiry not as to whether there are advantages and disadvantages arising necessarily from private ownership or State control, but given such and such an amount of private ownership or given such and such an amount and such and such a type of public ownership, are there likely to be defects arising from it naturally which cannot be countered by some obvious method in the actual details of administration?</P>
    <P>That led to a further survey, and even in statutes in connection with undertakings like the South African railways or the German railway system, to explain the purpose of the Board or the administration set up in these two countries to govern the railways, the phrase used was this: that it was the duty of the administration to run the railways on business lines while keeping in mind the agricultural and industrial interests of the two countries.  One found also in looking through all the varieties of types, either of public or private ownership, that came under consideration, that where any degree of public ownership had been settled upon there was pretty definitely in every case an equally strong decision that public ownership should not mean ownership and administration by a State Department in the ordinary way.  The South African railways are handed over to two or three Commissioners plus a Minister. They are authorised to run the railways on business lines, while being mindful of the industry and agriculture of South Africa, and they are given a certain amount of freedom in regard to the employment of staff and their dismissal, and are given complete freedom with regard to the methods upon which <Col N="1902" /> the railways are to be administered. In Germany the situation is somewhat more complicated owing to the fact that the railways had originally been owned by the separate provinces, had come into the control of the Central Government, and again in 1924 were about to be leased out to a private company of a particular kind.  In fact it is a company which could hardly be regarded as a private company.  Half of it was to be nominated by the Government and the other half was to be nominated by the trustees.  Trustees afterwards got a peculiar meaning under the Dawes' Report.</P>
    <P>Getting these two items and putting them back again in relation with the Ontario Commission, or the Nova Scotia Commission, and the Commission which operated electric property in New Brunswick, one finds this, which was common to the whole lot&mdash;that all being under the ownership of the State, and the property still remaining invested in the State, there was set up an independent board with varying degrees of independence, according to the conditions of the country and the circumstances under which the board grew.  There was an attempt made to set up a board, to make it as independent as possible of government; to get it as clear away from the ordinary type of Treasury control, and to get employees as much and as far away from the ordinary type of Civil Service recruitment and conditions as could be achieved.</P>
    <P>In South Africa, about three years ago, an electricity commission was set up consisting of a chairman, and, at the beginning, two part-time members. It was definitely stated in a paper written by the chairman about the time of the World Power Conference that their whole aim and object was to achieve all that was advantageous arising out of State control and to add to that all that seemed to be advantageous from business management.  Two things that seemed to be important items for consideration when the South African Board was being constituted were that there should be such sufficient affiliation with the State that the State's backing with regard to loans and ease to credit should be maintained, and that <Col N="1903" /> there should be such removal from the State that the ordinary conditions with regard to Civil Service appointments, and Civil Service methods of control and operation, should be done away with.  That was achieved simply enough. Three men were given complete control as regards the recruitment and dismissal of employees.  They were appointed for a certain period of years; they were themselves subject to dismissal at the end of that period, and presumably would have been or would still be dismissed if the results were not good.  They had behind them the State for a certain period of years, with all the facilities for the raising of loans and the ease to credit that affiliation with the State might give.</P>
    <P>Now, that was the one big fact that emerged from all this review of the different legislations and the different methods of administration in the different countries.  There was one other thing that seemed to be quite certain, or, at least, was accepted as certain, and that was that the greater the consolidation of powers with regard to distribution, in the hands of a limited number of people, the greater the benefits that would flow to the consumer.  That was assumed as axiomatic in America and Canada; it was a little more argued on the Continent, but everyone was coming to the same type of conclusion that the more one amalgamated authorities or controllers with regard to the distribution of electricity, the greater are the benefits that obviously would accrue to the consumers.</P>
    <P>While conclusions of this sort were being formed by those interested in the matter in considering what might have to be done in this country with regard to distribution afterwards the particular interests who approached me both in America and on the Continent, again appeared.  Letters had been written to them to say if they were prepared to put up the terms that seemed to them to be the best, on which they would be allowed a concession for the running of the Shannon distribution, that this would have to be considered, and a date was put for the receipt of any <Col N="1904" /> offer likely to be sent in.  At a particular time further letters began to flow in from people who had been written to in this way, and emissaries from some of those interests began even to appear in the country.  It became clear, or fairly clear, early on, that there were two or three points of difference that seemed likely to bring to an end any expectation that these people had of securing a concession in this country.  First of all, the rates of interest on investments that ruled American conditions would be completely out of place and completely intolerable here.  Secondly, the old question of rural electrification arose.  It seemed to be always obsessing those interested in taking over concessions here that rural electrification would have to be started, that some attention would have to be paid to it, and that further attention would have to be paid to it as the years went on.  That, apparently, appeared at once to fit in with the views of the particular interests in negotiation here.</P>
    <P>There was also a third point which I argued myself in speaking to those people, and the point became clearer and clearer to them as their investigations developed in this country.  They knew Article 11.  They got its effect, or intended effect, fully explained to them when they came here, and they seemed to discover themselves that, not only did it indicate a definite tendency of the mind of people with regard to the control and ownership of such an undertaking as that of the Shannon scheme, but they got even a greater idea of the strength of that point of view than I myself had been able to get in any investigations I have made in the country.</P>
    <P>There is another point.  None of those people interested seemed to desire to appear in the light of competitors to each other.  Most of them wanted to be promised that they would be regarded as the only probable concessionaires and then would proceed to work on a scheme which, when whittled down, might prove to be desirable. That, of course, could not be acceded to either.  Nevertheless, investigations were made by three or four people who professed themselves interested in the <Col N="1905" /> beginning, and these investigations of theirs were pushed to a great point of detail in at least three instances.  I can state so much in regard to these people; I cannot state very much more, because any letters which passed between myself and them had to be under a pledge, not of complete secrecy, but secrecy on certain points, and, therefore, further developments have to be left in a certain amount of secrecy.  To one who understands the particular in-and-out play of those corporations in America and the Continent this will be understandable enough.  But the net result of the whole thing has been that &mdash;(a) on account of the necessity for attending to the rural industries here; (b) in the face of Article 11 of the Constitution; and (c) because the likely interest rates that would be looked for from investments here would not be up to American or Continental conditions &mdash;no offer that could be considered came from any of these people.  At the same time I have myself been developing the other side of that argument. The letters to those people always contained the phrase that offers that gave, or seemed to give, considerable advantage to the consumer would receive the more consideration, provided always the national interests were safeguarded. When one began to see how could that safeguard of the national interests be achieved by a concession given to a foreign company then the difficulties became greater and greater as the investigation went on.</P>
    <P>The obvious thing, of course, would have been, in case a concession had been granted, to have some sort of utility commission regulating their efforts, their prices, and their services, just as there is in America and elsewhere. But it was when one began to get that type of regulation and that type of control down to details of a particular organisation that might come into the country, and began to consider what it meant, that that feeling against leasing to a corporation, which had never been present and on which no decision had been taken, began to work definitely for rejection. There was always an argument of principle that would have to be used, as I told these people, even on the <Col N="1906" /> ideally best offer that might be made. There is no necessity to go into it in great detail, as the question hardly arises, but it arises in considering the type of board to be set up by this Bill, and in considering whether it is suitable to allow a board to be set up to do what one would have hesitated to allow an outside foreign body to do in the country.</P>
    <P>Electricity, as a service, has almost begun to be regarded as essential.  If full control of that concession had been handed over to a private company, operating for gain in this country, with financial commitments in another country, its methods of obscuring its whole charges, its wage sheets, its payments to employees and the percentage of its expenditure on its original capital would have been most difficult to follow.  Yet it would have been necessary to follow all these things, if the control of this service had been handed over to an outside body to operate for gain in this country. There would, secondly, be the thought that one was handing over to a foreign body the control over such a technical matter as the development or the blocking of industry by easing the charges in the case of some industries, or stiffening them in the case of others. How that would fit in with the programme of industrial development is hard to see, except that methods of control would be made much more distinct and easily worked than seemed possible.</P>
    <P>Similarly, on ordinary matters which the Electricity Board will have to deal with, it would seem in itself to be a dangerous thing to allow such a thing as a tariff policy with regard to electricity to be so handed over.  That is to say, the method of charging, the scales of rates, and the conditions of service, would be controlled by an outside body, under whatever regulations of a public utility type that could have been put in upon them.  Finally, there would have arisen a question which, if put to me two years ago, I would not have been disposed to regard as of the same importance as I regard it now, after two years' experience.  That would be the question of training native engineers, <Col N="1907" /> native employees, in all branches and placing them in important positions in regard to the whole control of the Shannon generation, transmission, and supply.  These are things I mention here, not as an argument to be used against concession to an outside company, as the question does not arise, but they are things which fall for consideration when one considers the Board to be set up, and whether this is the type of Board to which these things also shall be handed over.</P>
    <P>I think there are differences which will justify us in taking the steps which we propose to take in this Bill.  The net result of all investigations, letter-writing, and negotiations, came to this, that, whether or not there had been any private organisation in the field, my view decidedly would be this, that the dangers of handing over to anybody operating for gain such services as these, with all the attendant circumstances, were so great that it simply could not be attempted.  Something had to be put in its place, and that was the next matter for debate. Again, with just as little hesitation as I would have decided on granting to a private body, I would also hold that, from the efficiency point of view, to allow a scheme of this sort&mdash;down to the supply to the consumer, and serving him in a way he would have to be served, and getting from him money he would have to pay for such service&mdash;to be run by an ordinary Government Department would be quite as dangerous.  In saying that, I am passing no criticism on the Civil Service as we find it at the moment.  The Civil Service was not recruited for the purpose of running business undertakings like this, and to say that civil servants recruited in a particular way, and having certain conditions with regard to appointments, promotion and retirements, are not suitable persons to run a scheme of this sort, is simply to say that this was not in contemplation when these people were appointed.  Nobody could say that they were picked for the purposes of this Bill, and I doubt if anybody <Col N="1908" /> could say that they are suitable for the purposes of this Bill.</P>
    <P>Thus, as between an unlimited private corporation on the one hand, and an unlimited State Department on the other, the decision had to be made that they were almost equally objectionable and that something in between had to be found.  The South African situation fell for consideration again.  There you had three Commissioners&mdash;a chairman and two part-time colleagues&mdash; given complete power with regard to recruitment and dismissal of staff and payments.  They were to be judged by results.  They were given certain tasks to do and they were to be judged whether they performed those tasks successfully or not.  That situation offered lines on which an advance could be made.  Similarly, too, the Swedish Board of Control, with regard to their whole electrical system, came under review.  The Swedish system is, more or less, what we are attempting to follow in this Bill, with certain changes made to fit the circumstances here.  In Sweden there is a board comprising a chairman and four members, and associated with that board there is a managing directorate consisting of a managing director and four persons who are called bureau chiefs.  These correspond to the heads of departments of a business of this sort.  The chairman and his four colleagues&mdash;the managing director and the chiefs of bureau being present when certain things are under discussion&mdash;operate the whole Swedish system.  They have successfully operated it since 1908, when the first Act was introduced, and much more successfully since the second Act, consolidating the results of the first, was passed.</P>
    <P>All that had been discovered at this time was that there had to be set up a business board.  Its numbers were still to be debated, qualifications of members still to be considered, powers of a more detailed type still to be thought out, but there had been a decision taken of this kind early, that there should be control of the Shannon plant when built and handed over, and control of the transmission and distribution down to some point then not determined, and that <Col N="1909" /> the board set up should be independent of Parliament and of Government as far as that could reasonably be arranged; and that that board should have behind it the resources of the State in order to enable it to supply this almost essential service.  If one were to take example from abroad the best type of board would seem to be one limiting the number of people given complete control over the employees&mdash; given tasks to do, given a certain time in which to accomplish those tasks&mdash;and judged on the results they had achieved themselves, having that control of the staffs at the end of a certain period. That being to a certain extent determined, one had to get back and see at what point control by this board of electricity in this country is to stop, or how far they ought to be allowed to go.</P>
    <P>There, again, we come back to these figures I have previously given&mdash;325 towns or villages to be served, a population of 1,035,000 to be served; 110 undertakings of some sort or other occupying three-fourths of the area of possible supply for Shannon current, and one-fourth more or less a virgin field upon which this new authority could work in order to make the scheme remunerative, whilst the supply which ordinarily would have grown to 70,000,000 units in 1929, had to be increased to 110,000,000 units.  A division must be made, and a division I have already made, of these undertakings. There are fifteen municipally owned undertakings in the country set up and financed by particular local authorities, and their idea is service and not gain. These fifteen undertakings serve 502,000 of the people who may, at some time or another, be served by the Shannon current.  There seems no reason why, on an ordinary amalgamation process, the fifteen municipally-owned undertakings should not be consolidated into one and managed centrally. There were obvious advantages in that course.  There were the advantages which would ordinarily accrue from centralised control, the keeping down of overhead expenses, and the question not merely of less staff but of a better and more expert staff, on account of the <Col N="1910" /> variety of work which a central board would have to do.</P>
    <P>There was little or no hardship involved, inasmuch as the money had been raised and a certain amount paid off, and if a new authority took over the moneys not yet paid them, took over the rates that had to be paid, and gave a supply at least as good as the municipal undertakings, there seems to be no reason why there should be any outcry against that.  The five privately-owned statutory undertakings are in a different position.  They serve a certain amount of population, nothing like so much as the big municipal undertakings serve.  These companies have come into being and are operated for the purpose of gain.  They sunk a certain amount of capital in them in an endeavour to get profits.  A different situation arises in regard to them, but in the interests of the better provision of electrical supply to anybody in this country who desires it, it seems unreasonable that companies supplying five areas should be allowed to block consolidation if that consolidation seems otherwise desirable, provided always that terms can be arranged upon which the five companies could be recouped for whatever money they had put in, and some attention given to their prospects of obtaining profits from investments over a period of years.  That has been attended to in the details of the Bill.  There are 78 non-statutory undertakings, serving also a small number of the community, or rather not serving the number I have spoken of.  These 78 non-statutory undertakings would include in their areas about 164,000 people.  A non-statutory undertaker is not bound to supply except those to whom he chooses to give current.</P>
    <P>Once an undertaker applies to become regulated by statute, then he incurs certain obligations, and an area is prescribed within the limits of which anybody who asks for current at a particular rate must be supplied.  It is not so with non-statutory or unauthorised undertakers.  They are more or less free lances.  They have to get permission from the local authority with regard to the breaking up of streets and <Col N="1911" /> roads if necessary, but beyond that they have no touch with any controlling authority.  Of these non-statutory undertakings it can be said that about 50 per cent. of them supply only about 47 or 48 per cent. of the possible consumers in their areas.  When I say there are 78 of these undertakings operating in areas the population of which is 164,000 I do not by any means want to be taken as saying that these 78 undertakings actually supply current direct to 164,000 people.  In recent years attempts have been made to get these undertakings to become statutory, to put themselves under control, submit themselves to regulations and incur obligations towards consumers, and to give the consumers in the areas the protection that is given under the statutory undertakings.  It has been found impossible, or nearly impossible, to draw away the non-statutory undertakings and make them enter the fold of statutory undertakings.  The non-statutory undertakings, therefore, are in a different class from either the municipally or the privately-owned statutory concerns.  They have areas which they might have served, comprising a fairly large number of people, and they give a service which is good, bad, or indifferent, according to the particular locality and the particular state of the plant, its installation, and the condition in which it has been since maintained, but they are under no control, and they have been given no monopoly right in any area, and no promise has been held out to them that at some time they would not escape action that would have a discouraging effect on them.  With regard to them a different attitude has to be adopted, and that attitude is shown in the details of the Bill.  But having this million odd people who are possible consumers of Shannon power, having a consumption that is to be raised from 70,000,000 to 110,000,000 units, and having no injustice caused by either the consolidation of the municipal undertakings into one, or the buying out in terms to be fixed, if not by agreement, then by arbitration, of the company or privately-owned undertaking, there seem to be no real obstacles against <Col N="1912" /> that, but there seems to be a considerable argument in favour of allowing the new authority to be set up to take over the control completely and entirely of the distribution of supply.</P>
    <P>There were two other arguments which weighed in coming to that decision and in giving additional powers to the Board.  A great deal has to be done in this country by way of education as to the uses of electricity, a great deal of propaganda has to be done in order to encourage the use of it, and if one were simply to set up a centralised Board allowing all the statutory and non-statutory undertakings to operate under it, that Board would have as its field of operations a mass of people to the number of a quarter of a million, and would have removed from the scope of its authority&mdash;the way being blocked by some type of middleman&mdash; three-quarters of a million of people.</P>
    <P>The Board, the central authority, can most easily and readily appoint canvassers and propaganda agents for the purpose of increasing the sale of electricity through the country.  Was it right that it should appoint these people, that they have at their hand power generated more cheaply than the ordinary supply association could generate at, and was it going to hand over that power at a lower rate and spend money in educating the people through means of propaganda in order to get more consumers and see this greater number of consumers fall into the hands of privately owned companies&mdash;for all the non-statutory undertakings are privately owned&mdash;or else fall into the hands of the fifteen municipal under takings?</P>
    <P>Similarly, too, if the Board were to stop short, having under its control all the distribution of electricity over the whole country, and was not given one other power and facilitated in one other way, then again the achievement the Board had put forward might easily be blocked.</P>
    <P>In this Bill the central authority has a certain amount of funds at its disposal, and those funds may be utilised in accordance with the provisions of the Bill.  One of its sections speaks of the provision of electric lines, wires, apparatus and appliances.  One of the <Col N="1913" /> greatest obstacles to the spread of the use of electricity is the expense that has to be incurred at one time in wiring a house.  It was considered desirable that, in order to overcome and ease that difficulty, the Board should be given sufficient funds, so that it could enter upon such an item as the wiring of a house, and have the sum involved repaid over whatever term of years the Board itself has authority to repay in respect to the advances made to it by the Central Fund.  That is the facility that I spoke of, but the extra power given goes a little bit further. When one considers that where people in an area have the desire for electricity and have got over the difficulty of, firstly, getting a good and efficient supply and getting it at all times, and, secondly, have got over the financial difficulty of raising the money with which to pay for the wiring of houses, there is the third point on which the users of electricity sometimes find themselves disappointed in the matter of service, and that is in the provision of electrical apparatus of all types.</P>
    <P>Outside of Dublin, Cork, and possibly Limerick, there are very few houses in this country which go in, either as separate concerns or even as an identifiable part of their business, for the supply of electrical appliances.  Generally speaking, as everybody knows, what happens is that you have some man selling both electric bulbs and potatoes or electric bulbs and butter over the counter together.  The provision of electrical appliances is simply a side line with him.  Sometimes that man enters into it because he knows that a certain number of people want a particular thing, but as to making any investigation as to the proper types of appliances or marketing them in a decent way, or doing anything to give an article which will have good service&mdash;of that there is very little.  Consequently it has been decided that, in addition to the numerous powers which the Board shall have under the Bill, there shall be given to it the power to make purchases and to sell all manner and types of electrical appliances.</P>
    <P>Accordingly we have come by different stages to what is in front of the Dáil in this Bill.  The general idea of <Col N="1914" /> the Bill can be quite easily grasped. It sets out that as soon as may be after its passing there shall be set up a Central Board consisting of a Chairman and of not less than two and not more than six additional members, and that they shall be appointed by the Executive Council.  They may be appointed for a period of five years or less, and will be eligible for re-appointment at the end of that period.  The Board will, themselves, have the sole control and the sole rights with regard to the recruitment and to the dismissal of whatever staff they think fit to employ for the carrying out of the powers to be given to them under this Bill.  Certain functions are set down as the general duty of the Board.  These are set out in Section 18, and thereafter the particular duties and powers of the Board are defined.</P>
    <P>The first thing that the Board must do, once it is established, is to assist in the carrying out of the remainder of the Shannon construction, because there are certain parts of that construction which will depend upon the demand that is shown in certain areas.  Possibly the first thing that the Board must do after its appointment is to make as rapid a survey as possible of the demand or the likely demand for current throughout the country, and having made up their minds as to what that demand is likely to be, then they are to advise those who are dealing with the Shannon constructional operations as to locations, certain lines and certain other questions that will have to be decided with regard to the type of material and its location.</P>
    <P>That is one duty which the Board will have thrown upon it immediately with regard to the complete construction of the partial development of the Shannon scheme.  After that it will have other functions arising out of the Shannon scheme.  Portion of the Shannon scheme may be completed earlier than had been expected.  One portion of it, indeed, has been pushed on for a particular purpose, and that portion will be handed over to the Board as soon as it is completed and ready for use.  The Board will then have to operate it, and meet and bear the charges arising out of that operation&mdash;the <Col N="1915" /> cost of renewals and maintenance of the particular part of the plant that has been handed over.  It is common knowledge that one of the circuits&mdash;that is, No. 4 circuit, which is the south-easterly one&mdash;has been pushed forward and will be ready for the transmission of current quite soon.  That current will not be Shannon current.  It will be current derived elsewhere.  The operation of that circuit in so far as it will be property belonging to or built under the operations of the Shannon Electricity Act, will be handed over to the new Board, and that Board will have to operate, take control of, meet and bear all the expenses of its management, renewal and repair. After the Shannon undertaking has been completed in whatever particular sections may be decided on, the Board will take control as soon as the formal handing over has been made by the Minister for Industry and Commerce to it, and from that point on the Board will become responsible for the charges, the same as they will in regard to the No. 4 circuit when it is completed and handed over.</P>
    <P>The Board will become seized of the whole Shannon plan, will have to maintain, operate and bear all the management expenses and generally operate in a way that is best described under certain details of this Bill.  Outside that the Board is going to be armed, if this Bill gets through in its present form, with the fullest powers possible to enable it to enter into every phase of the supply and local distribution of electricity to the people in the country. It may enter into new areas.  It may advise, and may indeed insist, on the location of certain circuits in places where it desires them.  It may enter into the area of operation of an authorised undertaker and may enforce upon him certain powers which are set out here in detail but which may simply be described as these: They may control, in the sense of taking over and running for a period of years, the undertaking of any authorised undertaker. They may insist, instead of controlling, say, that their schedule of rates shall be such and such, and say that their services shall be of such and <Col N="1916" /> such a standard, and if the undertaker complains or raises an objection, that objection or complaint has to be considered and the Board, in the alternative, may either acquire or take over the plant.</P>
    <P>Finally, and above everything else, the Board, under the terms of this Bill, will be given at any time the power to enter upon the undertaking of any authorised or non-authorised undertaker and take it over on terms set out in the detailed sections.  With regard to the non-authorised undertakings, there is a section in this Bill which, within a certain period, if this Bill becomes an Act, lays down that there shall not be allowed in this country anybody dealing in electricity except two classes of people, those who are described as (a) permitted undertakers, or (b) authorised undertakers.  That section is meant to convey the likely fate of the non-authorised undertaker in this country.  It will be for the Board to determine, in the early months of its existence, whether or not it will elevate to the rank of an authorised undertaker some of the non-statutory undertakers at present existing.  That, of course, has its reaction also upon the non-statutory undertakers.  If elevated to that rank they fall into line with the authorised undertaker, and are subject to the regulations of its members; consumers have a right to demand a supply, and must get it under particular conditions and so on.</P>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamHewat" hpid="Mr. HEWAT Mr. HEWAT">
      <NameTxt>Mr. HEWAT</NameTxt>
      <P>Will there be any fees payable by the non-authorised undertaker?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGILLIGAN Mr. McGILLIGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGILLIGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>That will be for the Board to say.  The whole thing is left to the regulation of the Board. That is a point which can be raised and dealt with in Committee.  If the Deputy means are there any fees which a non-authorised undertaker who is becoming authorised should incur, I do not see that the fees will be very great. The process of application, inquiry and so forth does cost a certain amount of money.  I do not see in the new conditions that expenditure would ever be incurred by a non-statutory undertaking <Col N="1917" /> becoming authorised.  If the Board, in its discretion, thinks either that it has not enough time in which to make up its mind on the particular point that a non-statutory undertaking should be allowed to become authorised, or, having made up its mind, that it should not be so allowed, the Board can then issue to that non-authorised undertaker a permit, and that permit is revocable either on the terms and conditions stated in the permit itself or else it lapses simply when withdrawn.  The object of these two clauses, which may seem to be unduly roundabout, is this: that immediately the central authority comes into operation it has been decided that there should be an end put to the springing up of new undertakers until such time as that Board will be able to review the whole circumstances and see whether it is going to operate itself or whether it is going to allow operations to be carried on by its agents.  Consequently, for a certain time after the passing of this Act no one will be allowed to exist in the present condition of being unauthorised. The present unauthorised undertakers must apply and be given either a permit which is revocable at whatever time the Board wants, or else be elevated to the region of the authorised undertaker.  Of course, that does not mean any special protection.  It is a little more protection than being merely permitted.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesSprouleMyles" hpid="Major MYLES Major MYLES">
      <NameTxt>Major MYLES</NameTxt>
      <P>Does it mean that an unauthorised undertaker will become elegible for compensation in the same way as the statutory undertaker is?  Does it give an unauthorised undertaker a claim for compensation purposes if eventually he is done away with?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGILLIGAN Mr. McGILLIGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGILLIGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>I should say that is one of the effects of it.  That is one of the considerations which will weigh most deeply with the Board when deciding whether to elevate a non-authorised undertaking to the rank of an authorised undertaking or to give a permit.  The permit is merely licensing the person unauthorised. The authorisation would be putting the undertaking on a slightly higher <Col N="1918" /> plane.  Merely elevating the region of an unauthorised undertaker does not convey any implication with regard to the length of life, as a separate entity, which that unauthorised undertaker, becoming authorised, may enjoy, because even he may, at the discretion of the Board, be eventually wiped out on the terms laid down here.  The aim, therefore, is, and it should be plainly and clearly stated, that this central authority be given every power that is considered necessary to enable that authority eventually to become the sole distributor of electricity in this country. It is not made compulsory upon the Board that it should, in a limited period, become the sole distributor of electricity in the country.  It is left to its discretion.  Viewing as an amateur the duties and responsibility of the Board, immediately on its inception, I should say it will have enough to do, in the first year, eighteen months or two years of its existence with the territory and population at present without electricity and with the area at present served by the non-statutory undertakers, to make it rather disinclined to deal with some of the larger municipally owned undertakings of a statutory type in the country.  If, in order to promote the better use of electricity in the country or for any other reason within the functions and considerations of the Board, it seems good to it that it should, say right at the start, tackle and take over the big municipal undertakings in the country, it is being given definite powers to do so.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>It is also being given the powers that I spoke of, power in every way to increase the sale and promote the use of electricity, and the special things adverted to there I want to call attention to again, as I have called attention to them before.  They seem to me to be important.  They are (a) the provision that has been made with regard to the wiring of houses and the repayment of whatever moneys may be expended in such wiring of houses over a fairly lengthy period; (b) the power already referred to of engaging in the purchase and sale of electrical equipment and <Col N="1919" /> apparatus.  It will be noticed that the Board is, as I explained before, to be removed as far as it is possible from political pressure.  It is intended to remove it as far as possible from incessant Government watchfulness and from incessant Government or Parliamentary interference.  Instead of that there is the insistence that there shall be as much publicity as one can reasonably demand with regard to its operations. Accounts must be prepared, ordinary accounts in the ordinary way, and such special accounts as two Ministers may demand, and these two accounts must be audited by the auditors appointed by the Government but paid by the Board; and the auditors' report upon those accounts, with the accounts themselves, are to be published.  They are not to be presented to this House. They are to be presented to the Minister, who shall direct their publication, and there shall be laid on the Table of this House a record of each year's workings of the Board.  These two items are the two items which are meant to give the necessary publicity to what the Board does in its operations. But there are going to be no Parliamentary questionings with regard to this Board.  There are going to be no complaints from a Deputy that his area is not served at such a rate as some other Deputy's area is served, or that some other Deputy's area is being more advantageously served.  We are going to try to establish this Board so that it can run this electricity in an efficient way, and we are going to establish that this Board is not going to be regarded as a machine for wiping off all political obligations of this, that and the other Deputy.</P>
    <P>The only thing demanded is that there shall be a report of its proceedings presented each year to a particular Minister, and that Minister shall present that to the Oireachtas.  The accounts have to be published in a certain form, and they have to be audited by an outside auditor, not the Comptroller and Auditor-General.  This outside auditor shall be appointed by the Government and paid by the Board. The auditor's report on these accounts <Col N="1920" /> must be published.  Outside that there is a further provision that such statistics and returns as the Minister for Industry and Commerce may desire from them, shall be made by the Board to that particular Minister, and he may, in his discretion, include all or any of these returns and statistics in the report which is to be presented to both Houses of the Oireachtas.  I emphasise this, because if the Dáil is going to commit itself to this Bill it should do so knowing what it is about and knowing that there is to be a definite attempt made here to put this Board upon a different footing from, say, the Post Office.  There are not going to be discussions here yearly on Estimates, as in the case of the Post Office, a discussion as to whether the Board is doing what Deputies think it should do, or as to whether the Board is acting in a wrong manner.  There may be an opportunity on the presentation of this report annually to the Oireachtas for having a certain debate initiated. I would like to prevent that as much as possible.  I would like to have this central authority set up and armed with the fullest possible powers for the purpose of carrying out the certain task that is to be allotted to it.  If it does not succeed in performing that task, then it is a case for the dismissal of that Board, just as may be the fate of any employee of the Board who does not give it satisfaction.</P>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamArcherRedmond" hpid="Captain REDMOND Captain REDMOND">
      <NameTxt>Captain REDMOND</NameTxt>
      <P>In view of the Minister's statement as to the removal of this Board from Governmental pressure, I would like him to deal with the question of the appointment of the arbitrator by the Minister for Industry and Commerce, which is provided in the Bill.  The arbitrator is to be appointed if there has been no agreement as to price for the taking over of an undertaking and for generating costs, and also with regard to other matters in dispute.  I understand from the Bill that the arbitrator is to be appointed by the Minister for Industry and Commerce.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGILLIGAN Mr. McGILLIGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGILLIGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>That is the suggestion in the Bill.  I think there are <Col N="1921" /> at least three occasions in which arbitrators may be appointed, and the Bill is drafted in common form throughout; that is, an arbitrator is to be appointed, and he is to be appointed by the Minister for Industry and Commerce. I do not know that I would insist on this to the point of smashing the Government on the matter&mdash;that the arbitrator is to be appointed by the Minister for Industry and Commerce instead of by the courts, in a particular case of compensation, in default of agreement.  There are certain small things with regard to inquiries where it is going to impose expense on a recalcitrant undertaking and the Board, if an arbitrator has to be appointed in each case.  However, we can deal with that in Committee.</P>
      <P>If the Minister for Industry and Commerce is supposed to be sufficiently unbiassed to appoint a judge who will himself be unbiassed in the carrying out of his duties afterwards, then that particular confidence reposed in the Minister might be carried sufficiently far to allow him to appoint an arbitrator to adjudicate between two parties with neither of whom he has any dealings. I hope it will be understood that once this Board has been appointed, control or touch by my Department or myself with the Shannon Electricity scheme ceases.  This authority is entirely on its own and operates on its own, free from Departmental control. It gets certain moneys and there are certain returns that it must make to a particular Minister, but there is no control on it, save what may be afterwards in special circumstances exercised by the Executive Council, namely, removal from office of all or any of the members if they are not effectively carrying out their duty.  We can deal with the question of the arbitrator on the Committee Stage.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The finances of the Bill are dealt with mainly in Sections 11 to 14. In these sections there is one item to which I would like to refer. There are certain sums which may be advanced, and they are going to be advanced, out of the Central Fund; consequently, no Estimates discussion will arise upon such advances.  There will be advances out of the Central Fund <Col N="1922" /> under Section 11 (2) to an amount not exceeding the sum of £600,000, and in Section 11 (3) a maximum amount of £2,500,000.  With regard to the sum mentioned in sub-section (2), Deputies will remember that when the Shannon scheme was originally under discussion and the finances were being considered, as a result of that discussion there was set out in the first Act a sum of £5,200,000 to cover construction of necessary works and the payment of all losses, either by revenue not coming in to a point sufficient to meet expenses and also losses by way of interest during the non-working years; it was estimated that the sum for building, for materials, labour and general building operations, would run to £4,600,000, and that the sum of £600,000 included in the £5,200,000 was specially to meet interest and losses, and this was not a remunerative proposition.  Now, this is the same £600,000.</P>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamHewat" hpid="Mr. HEWAT Mr. HEWAT">
      <NameTxt>Mr. HEWAT</NameTxt>
      <P>Do you bring down your £5,200,000 to £4,600,000 by transferring the £600,000?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGILLIGAN Mr. McGILLIGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGILLIGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>It is, in fact, what will happen.  It may be necessary to tie these clauses a little more tightly to the relative clause in the Shannon Electricity Act.  There may be handed over to the Board from time to time various sections of the work and, as the Board will become responsible for the interest charges upon the moneys sunk in that particular portion of the work, and will become responsible for meeting the charges upon the work&mdash;that particular portion handed over&mdash; whether or not it is bringing in revenue sufficient to meet the charges, there is to be handed over from time to time such portion of the £600,000 as may be apportioned against the particular piece of property handed over.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>There is not an attempt to have £5,200,000 granted, or to have £2,500,000 granted, for the general purposes of distribution&mdash;wiring of houses, purchase of electrical equipment, etc.,&mdash;and an additional £600,000 with which the Board may play about.  That £600,000 is the identical amount referred to in the first Shannon Act.  If that is not sufficiently clear, and if Deputies want it tied up <Col N="1923" /> more tightly with the existing Act, I will be very glad to assist in that.</P>
    <P>There is one small point in connection with Section 24 to which I desire to draw attention.  There is leave given to the Board from time to time to &ldquo;employ such technical or other advisers as it thinks fit to advise it in regard to any matter or thing in connection with the exercise or performance by the Board of the powers, duties and functions conferred or imposed on it by or under this Act.  (2) There shall be paid out of the funds at the disposal of the Board under this Act to every person employed by the Board under this section such fees and such allowances as the Board shall determine.&rdquo; I call attention to that for this reason: I find in circles disposed to argue about this Bill a considerable amount of misapprehension with regard to the personnel of the Board.  Who or what that Board is going to be eventually I cannot say, but I would like to say that, so far as it is my intention or the Government's intention, all the members of that Board shall be Irish members, shall be natives of this State. As it has been clearly recognised that there may happen to be expert assistance of the type we cannot get in this State necessary for the full and complete operation of the Board in the early years, there ought to be special power given for the employment of technical advisers in order to assist those who would be members of the Board in the performance of their duty.</P>
    <P>What has been set out in Section 24 might, perhaps, be better placed in a section dealing with employees of the Board.  It was, however, thought wiser to make it a special section.  I rather think the Board will have to employ technical advisers, who probably will not be found in this country.  I want to make it clear that these technical advisers, if not natives of this country, will not be members of the Board.  The membership of the Board will be definitely confined to Irish nationals.  Most of the precedents I have been able to get for Boards of this sort contain clauses actually setting out that the members of the Board, the governing authority, shall be natives of the State.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="1924" /> At one time I was disposed to have such a thing set down here, but I think it as well to leave it as it is, indicating at the same time that so far as I have any intentions in this matter, the membership of the Board will be confined to Irish nationals, and they will be given power to engage for special work advisers of a technical type who cannot be found in the country.</P>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamArcherRedmond" hpid="Captain REDMOND Captain REDMOND">
      <NameTxt>Captain REDMOND</NameTxt>
      <P>Can the Minister say whether the members of the Board will, as far as possible, themselves possess expert qualifications?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGILLIGAN Mr. McGILLIGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGILLIGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>If the Deputy means that I am going to set out deliberately to appoint incompetent people, I can give him the assurance that I will not do so.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamArcherRedmond" hpid="Captain REDMOND Captain REDMOND">
      <NameTxt>Captain REDMOND</NameTxt>
      <P>Will the members of the Board have qualifications as experts?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGILLIGAN Mr. McGILLIGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGILLIGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>I wonder what would the Deputy decide as an expert qualification for, say, the sixth member of the Board?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamArcherRedmond" hpid="Captain REDMOND Captain REDMOND">
      <NameTxt>Captain REDMOND</NameTxt>
      <P>I am merely asking if they will be qualified.  The experts' report indicates that the members of the Board should be experts duly qualified.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGILLIGAN Mr. McGILLIGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGILLIGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>There is a difference between the two words.  I am not sure the word &ldquo;expert&rdquo; was used in the experts' report.  I would be very much surprised to find that they have given any such instructions to a Government&mdash;that they are to appoint people properly qualified for particular posts.  I cannot imagine them having the impudence to set such a statement down in writing unless there is some explanation contained in the context.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamArcherRedmond" hpid="Captain REDMOND Captain REDMOND">
      <NameTxt>Captain REDMOND</NameTxt>
      <P>Perhaps it would be as well for me to give the Minister the words contained in the report?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGILLIGAN Mr. McGILLIGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGILLIGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>I think you will find it on page 89.  Is the Deputy thinking of what is on page 92&mdash;organisation?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamArcherRedmond" hpid="Captain REDMOND Captain REDMOND">
      <NameTxt>Captain REDMOND</NameTxt>
      <P>So far as it goes it mentions that no man shall be appointed until his duties shall be <Col N="1925" /> clearly defined.  I am thinking of the composition of the Board itself.  I am not able to lay my hand on the particular portion of the report concerned at the moment, but I understood the experts' report to indicate that this Board should consist of people duly qualified.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGILLIGAN Mr. McGILLIGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGILLIGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>Of course that will be attended to and there is no necessity to make a point about it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamArcherRedmond" hpid="Captain REDMOND Captain REDMOND">
      <NameTxt>Captain REDMOND</NameTxt>
      <P>I was only anxious to know that the Board shall consist of people who had experience of this class of work and shall not consist of people who never had anything to do with the work before.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGILLIGAN Mr. McGILLIGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGILLIGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>If the Deputy does not raise the matter on Second Reading, presumably he will raise it on the section dealing with the Electricity Supply Board when we come to the Committee Stage.  Then he can refer to the qualifications.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamHewat" hpid="Mr. HEWAT Mr. HEWAT">
      <NameTxt>Mr. HEWAT</NameTxt>
      <P>We will hear plenty of the Electricity Supply Board before it is all over.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGILLIGAN Mr. McGILLIGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGILLIGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>To a suspicious mind it might appear that I am taking the power on myself to appoint incompetents. The Bill sets out that &ldquo;The Board shall consist of a chairman and such number (not being less than two nor more than six) of other members as the Executive Council shall from time to time determine.&rdquo;  That is a point that I can deal with much more fully in Committee, but as it has been raised I would like to say that there will be a different type of Board required as between now and 1929 or 1932 than there will be from that onwards. From now to 1929 there will obviously be one man missing from that Board who afterwards should find a place on it.  Once the station has been built and completed and once the whole transmission system has been set up, I should say a man who would immediately find himself amongst that seven on the Board would be the chief electricity man, the man looking after the power plant and the transmission system.  He would certainly be of sufficient importance <Col N="1926" /> to be brought into the meetings of the Board, and I think we should then have arrived at the point when he should be made absolutely, definitely and clearly a member of the Board. But his position will not be determined; there will be no need for him until 1929, so that consequently there will be a certain difference in the personnel of the Board in the early years and of the Board afterwards.</P>
      <P>That is one of the reasons why provision is made for appointing members of the Board for different periods of time.  It may be necessary in the beginning to appoint a man whose appointment will not be for the full five years, but to whom it will be stated in the terms of the appointment that it will hold merely to February, 1929, so that he may then retire and be replaced by the man I have described as the plant and transmission line operator. There are a great many other things that could be spoken of in detail on this Bill, but they are all Committee points.  The general idea is what I have expressed it to be, that there is the intention of appointing a board and arming it with the fullest possible powers to enable the members to become eventually, if they so please, the sole controllers of electricity distribution in the country.  That will not be imposed on them; they will be left a certain amount of discretion, so that they may at the beginning, or for many years to come, allow the distribution of electricity in certain areas by certain people who may be at present statutory undertakers or may be others who are raised from the ranks of the non-statutory people, or they may be completely new undertakers who will come into existence under the auspices and the guidance of this Board.</P>
      <P>Debate adjourned until to-morrow.</P>
      <P>Sitting suspended at 6 o'clock and resumed at 7.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="IN COMMITTEE ON FINANCE. - SUPPLEMENTARY ESTIMATE.&mdash;VOTE" RHead="52, DEPARTMENT OF AGRICULTURE (RESUMED)">
    <Title>IN COMMITTEE ON FINANCE. - SUPPLEMENTARY ESTIMATE.&mdash;VOTE 52, DEPARTMENT OF AGRICULTURE (RESUMED).</Title>
    <P>The Dáil went into Committee on Finance.</P>
    <Speaker pid="BryanRiccoCooper" hpid="Major COOPER Major COOPER">
      <NameTxt>Major COOPER</NameTxt>
      <P>This is a very unusual and extraordinary occasion. <Col N="1927" /> When the historian of the future comes to write the history of our time he will probably look at the 15th March, 1927, and say that this is where the Government took the wrong turning&mdash;the Ides of March.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DanielMorrissey" hpid="Mr. MORRISSEY Mr. MORRISSEY">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MORRISSEY</NameTxt>
      <P>Not the first wrong turning.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BryanRiccoCooper" hpid="Major COOPER Major COOPER">
      <NameTxt>Major COOPER</NameTxt>
      <P>Here is a very remarkable turning.  I followed very carefully the speeches of Ministers.  I have been under the impression that they were advancing to the forthcoming test under certain well-defined banners.  I understood that over the host was flying the banner inscribed &ldquo;The old indispensables,&rdquo; flanked on one side by another oriflamme bearing the words &ldquo;Gentlemen prefer old hands,&rdquo; and on the other side by the words &ldquo;Beware of a Coalition.&rdquo;  But now all that has gone.  Now we see what the Government banner is going to be.  The new banner is &ldquo;State Socialism.&rdquo;  Of course, I know the reason.  I know it is because Ministers are such kind-hearted men.  They could not bear that Deputy Johnson, in his absence, which we all regret, should feel that his Party was at any loss or was prejudiced in any way, and as they always follow him sooner or later, they have decided in this case to follow him sooner, and Deputy Johnson can feel that he can go away with a quiet conscience because Ministers are doing as much as he would do if he were here. This Estimate is nothing more than State Socialism, State Socialism in a somewhat unusual form.  I can understand, and I have heard of States carrying on industries and enterprises.  I can understand the State supplying electricity, and I can understand the State running railways.  But never before have I heard of a State acting as a go-between, as agents between somebody who wants to sell and somebody who wants to buy.  That is the proposition to which we are asked to assent tonight. It may be a sound proposition; there may be a profit for the State; there may be a loss, but what I should like to ask the Minister for Lands and Agriculture is: What will happen if <Col N="1928" /> these concerns that it is proposed to purchase, or some of them, are not sold?  What is going to happen then? The Minister for Lands and Agriculture is a most efficient Minister, but I am not sure that he is so efficient as the business man.  To my mind, it is not good business, to begin with, to announce that the transfer of this business will be carried through as quickly as possible.  When you proclaim that your intention is to buy something and then sell it as soon as possible, you do not get the same price as you would in other circumstances.  In the same way the Minister was rather unguarded when he told us that the bulk of condensed milk is made from separated milk.  I have no doubt that that is so, but now the State is buying the condensed milk factory and the milk will be sent out with the advertisement that it is made from separated milk.  I imagine that the Swiss, and others who are competing with us, will blazon that statement on their advertisements. That is one of the disadvantages of Ministers, absolutely efficient in their own Departments, going into business matters in which they sometimes lend themselves to unguarded actions.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>What is going to happen if these concerns are not sold?  The bulk of them are creameries and are to be sold to creamery committees.  I have been a member of the committee of a co-operative creamery for a good many years, and I have never found it possible to foretell a day in advance what that committee might do.  I do not know if the Minister has any undertakings in creameries, but if he has does he know that the majority of the committees do not attend the meetings? In my experience most co-operative creameries have far too many members. The work is done by a comparatively small number, and that small number would avail of the Minister's statement. Once you have a question of buying or selling there are a number of members, who possibly have not attended more than once or twice in the year, who will come down and say: &ldquo;You have made a very bad bargain.  You could get that cheaper.  The Minister would have to sell it whatever the price was.&rdquo; Of course, that is a misrepresentation, <Col N="1929" /> but that is the kind of attitude that a great many people will take up.  Let us consider the other businesses.  The Minister is buying the whole concern, lock, stock and barrel, and it includes a toffee factory.  What is going to happen to that?  The Minister said, I think, that the toffee factory will be sold in the open market.  What happens if it is not sold?  You cannot always sell things when you want to, unless you are prepared to sell at a price that is an absolute sacrifice.  Is the State going to carry on the toffee factory?  I have heard of State railways, State industrial undertakings, State butchers' shops, even, but I never heard of a State toffee factory.</P>
    <Speaker pid="DanielMorrissey" hpid="Mr. MORRISSEY Mr. MORRISSEY">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MORRISSEY</NameTxt>
      <P>Why not?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BryanRiccoCooper" hpid="Major COOPER Major COOPER">
      <NameTxt>Major COOPER</NameTxt>
      <P>Because there are private toffee factories in Dublin and in County Dublin, and it is not fair for the State to assist, or actually subsidise, a competitor in opposition to these.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>If the toffee industry is one of those crying out for nationalisation, if Deputy Morrissey's Party and his constituents feel that we are suffering under a load of national iniquity because of the private monopoly in the manufacture of toffee, then let a Bill be brought in to nationalise all toffee factories, but do not let one factory in Cork be subsidised and have the State competing with all other toffee factories.  The factory may not be carried on in the interval, but it must be carried on; if not it will be valueless.  Take it that it employs some labour.  That labour is disemployed and the factory shut down.  Deputy Morrissey would then be the first, and rightly, to complain. Again, if you shut it down the value of the factory lies in the connection that it had established and in the fact that people are used to buying the peculiar brand of toffee that was made there.  If it is shut down for six weeks and if the shops say to any customer: &ldquo;We have not any of that.  We have N.K.M., Sharpe's or some other foreign toffee,&rdquo; that factory will be nearly valueless, because it will have lost its connection with purchasers that it previously possessed. The State will have to carry <Col N="1930" /> that on.  That very fact illustrates the seriousness of this position.  If the State is to carry on toffee factories why should it not carry on every other form of enterprise?  Again, there is a shop in Cork.  Is that shop to be carried on?  Is the State going into the retail trade?  I have no doubt the Minister will try to sell it as soon as possible. What is going to happen to it in the interval?  All these are questions that the Dáil will have to consider before we pass this Estimate.</P>
    <P>Now I come to an important and larger question, and remove myself from the sticky neighbourhood of toffee. This Estimate provides for the advance of a very substantial sum, very nearly half a million pounds, and a great deal of that money is to be repaid, as the Minister said, by advances from the Agricultural Credit Corporation.  How are these repayments to be accounted for? Are they to be appropriations-in-aid of the Department of Lands and Agriculture? I suggest that we should not allow such a large sum as £455,000 to appear as an appropriation-in-aid, because the Minister has power to apply appropriations-in-aid to any excess expenditure in any of the other branches of his Department.  I think the sum of nearly half a million is altogether and entirely excessive as an appropriation-in-aid, and I suggest the Dáil is entitled to some information as to the accountancy in this regard.  I really think it is a pity that the Minister has elected to deal with this matter by bringing in a supplementary estimate.  It seems to be just as much a case for a Bill&mdash;it is a new departure, and it is admitted to be a new departure&mdash;as the sugar subsidy was for a Bill, because if a Bill were brought in we could move an amendment with regard to that point of the appropriations-in-aid.  For instance, we could secure that every transaction would be reviewed by the Comptroller and Auditor-General.  I suppose they will be reviewed, but we could make it more certain and there would be an opportunity of taking a division on such an amendment.  We can, of course, take a division on this, but I do not suppose it will be a successful division. We should not only have an opportunity of taking a division, but, if necessary, <Col N="1931" /> we could refer the matter to a referendum.  It is a new departure, and I think it should have been dealt with by a Bill.</P>
    <P>I have dealt with one or two aspects of the matter, but the Minister will be quite entitled to reproach me if I do not deal with the main purpose behind this Bill, and that is the problem of the redundant or superfluous creameries. We are only dealing with the fringe of that problem in this Estimate.  These redundant creameries do not only exist in the South, but all over Ireland where there are creameries, and it is not always the proprietary creamery that is redundant, while the co-operative one is all that it should be.  It is very often the case that there is unfair competition between two co-operative creameries.  I know of two co-operative creameries, each of them with auxiliaries at least twenty miles away, but where the main creameries are within two miles of one another and constantly trying to cut each other out by offering better prices for milk.  This Estimate will not deal with that.  It is only dealing with the fringe of the problem, and it is only dealing with it for the benefit of the farmers of one part of the country, at the expense of the taxpayers of the whole country.  It is a serious problem.  The Minister is only dealing with it piecemeal, but though I would have preferred that he should have dealt with it in some other manner, I think that even in dealing with it piecemeal he should have given some indication of what his policy will be with regard to the redundant co-operative creameries and with regard to the creameries in other parts of the country besides the area covered by the Estimate.</P>
    <P>I should also like to call attention to the fact, about which Ministers are singularly modest, that this is another boon conferred on the farmer at the expense of the general taxpayer. Hardly a day passes that you do not see in your newspaper that everything is done for Dublin and nothing for the man in the country.  I have gone through the Estimates and I have found items amounting to over two million pounds for things done for the <Col N="1932" /> farmer from which the taxpayer in the Dublin metropolitan area derives no direct benefit whatever.</P>
    <P>I am careful to say direct benefit, because the prosperity of the farmer is something that benefits everybody.  I accept that, but the Dublin taxpayer gets no direct benefit from the expenditure of the Department of Lands and Agriculture; he gets no direct benefit from the expenditure on forestry, from the expenses of the Land Commission, from the advances to agricultural credit societies, from the supplementary agricultural grant, and from all the expenditure, amounting to over £150,000, on drainage.  Here is another sum of very nearly half a million from which the taxpayer in the Dublin metropolitan area will derive no direct benefit.  That is to say, two and a half millions, more than one-tenth of our whole expenditure, is expended for the benefit of the farmer and for the direct benefit of nobody else.  Yet we are told that everything is done for Dublin and that the man in the country is forgotten!  I think it is a sound policy; I am not quarrelling with it; I am only indicating it.  Agriculture is the backbone of our industry.  But I would like to see it dealt with on a more general and more systematic scale than it is dealt with in this rather piecemeal fashion of buying certain creameries in certain corners of the country.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFrancisBaxter" hpid="Mr. BAXTER Mr. BAXTER">
      <NameTxt>Mr. BAXTER</NameTxt>
      <P>I am not going to enter into a discussion of this Estimate in the spirit that seems to have animated Deputy Cooper.  He tried to discover how much the farmer was getting out of the existence of this State indirect benefits in the matter of pounds, shillings and pence.  I do not know what his object was, but he did not try to discover at the same time how much the farmer was contributing to the maintenance of the State.  The Minister, in introducing the Estimate, has undoubtedly given colour to the statement of Deputy Cooper.  The Minister's action may be termed, if you like, an effort at State Socialism&mdash;the fact that the Minister has set himself up to act as a go-between between a certain group of farmers and certain other interests possessing property in the <Col N="1933" /> country, property which is of value for the manufacture of the raw material which contributes a high proportion of our total exports.  The main fact which stands out in the very lengthy and well-reasoned statement of the Minister is that there is recognition on the part of the Government that agriculture is of importance to this State; that prosperity for agriculture means prosperity for the State, and that success cannot come to agriculture or to any other industry unless it is established on a sound basis.  The Minister came up against the position that one of the main branches of the agricultural industry was established on such an unsound and uneconomic basis, that its management from the point of view of its economic value to the farmer was in such a precarious position, that something had to be done.  I take it that this action on the part of the Ministry is being taken because of the very serious condition in which they found the dairying industry in a particular part of the country, and that they could not blind themselves to the fact that if someone did not step in and take action very serious days were ahead for the dairy farmer over a very wide area in the South.  Hence it is that we are asked to vote a sum of close on half a million.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>We have to ask ourselves is this action on the part of the State requisite or justifiable under the circumstances? The Minister went to very considerable pains to give us the whole genesis of the action that he has been compelled to take, and I think the House will admit, whatever term we apply to the action taken, that there was hardly any alternative under the circumstances, and that any individual in the position of the Minister, wanting to do his best for the industry, would have been compelled to say that it was not possible by any other means to put the dairying industry in Ireland on a sound basis.  I hope it will have the results anticipated.  The sum involved is very considerable.  I agree with Deputy Cooper when he said that agriculture over a certain area is going to benefit. If benefits are to come from the action taken, they will be conferred on a certain limited area.  While that is so, <Col N="1934" /> and while I come from an area which cannot and does not expect to gain by this expenditure, I do feel that the Minister's action under the circumstances is justifiable.  We might, in fact, say that it was courageous.  In a State like ours it is necessary at times to take a bold step, particularly when dealing with agriculture.</P>
    <P>I feel that there is a certain weight in what Deputy Cooper has urged, and I think that the Minister's own statement left the impression on our minds that a good many things which he has indicated as likely to happen are only suppositions.  I confess that there are possibilities that the expectations may not be fulfilled.  The Minister's policy in the matter, from what we have learnt this evening, in getting rid of redundant creameries is to pass over to existing co-operative societies the trade hitherto done by those creameries.  I should like the Minister to give us an assurance that the co-operative societies in the area where some of these redundant creameries are, are prepared to contribute what is believed to be their share of the State's liability in this venture.  When a creamery is dismantled and the machinery is utilised by the other creameries in the area, are those creameries prepared to pay for that machinery?</P>
    <P>Has the Minister any evidence up to the present from the existing societies that that spirit is at the moment living in the areas which have been served by these redundant creameries?  One would like to feel that when the State embarks upon an effort like this, where a considerable sum of money is involved and where the benefits are to be conferred on a limited number of people over a limited area, that the people within that area are prepared to stand up to their liabilities in the matter.  I think the Minister, if he is able to give us some indication as to the outlook on the part of some of the existing co-operative societies, will do a good deal to make some of us feel that if the State is in the long run called upon to contribute something towards the efforts to put the dairying industry on a sound basis the money will not be misspent.</P>
    <P>It is rather difficult to go through all <Col N="1935" /> the figures the Minister has given to the Dáil in the short time at our disposal. I should like to have from the Minister the exact figures he anticipates the State will, in the long run, be likely to have to contribute towards the carrying through of this scheme, granted that his outlook will be justified by the policy and action of the particular societies in the particular area in question.  What exactly does the State stand to lose by the transaction? What will the Exchequer be asked to contribute, after putting the value on the machinery that the foreign experts calculate it is worth, and on the buildings and on the trade?  I thought I understood from the Minister that he put that figure at about £50,000.</P>
    <P>If, on the other hand, and this is something one would not like to contemplate, there was a certain disposition on the part of any of the co-operative creameries in these areas, now that opposition has to an extent vanished and the farmers have practically no alternative but to send their milk to the co-operative stores&mdash;if a certain attitude was taken up on the part of some of those creameries it would undoubtedly be a serious matter for the State.  One must admit that we do not like to urge that it is the State's responsibility to come in and act as the Minister has seen fit to do on this occasion.  I have no doubt that serious consideration must have been given to this before such a policy was decided upon, but if for the welfare of the industry it has been necessary to take this action, my feeling on the matter is that such action is only justifiable on the part of the State when for the sake of the industry no other course is open, and, at the same time, when the State feels that that section of the community on which the benefit is likely to be conferred shall honour their obligation and live up to their responsibilities.  I hope that over the five or six counties where this killing competition has existed for years, between proprietary concerns and co-operative creameries, competition which I know has been responsible for having brought many co-operative concerns to the brink and which concerns <Col N="1936" /> can only be saved by the action which is now being taken, people will appreciate the fact that they have, on their part, to recognise that unless they are prepared to come along and bear their fair share of the Ministry's obligation in the whole matter, undoubtedly it must prejudice any future action by the State, even in circumstances perhaps which might be more justifiable.</P>
    <P>Coming from a part of the country that cannot claim to have been given any great concessions by the State, a part of the country very far removed from the operations of the Shannon scheme, on which over £5,000,000 is to be spent, far removed from the beet factory at Carlow, where £3,000,000 is to be spent, far removed from the Barrow drainage, where, at least, £250,000 is to be spent, and now, with this additional £500,000 to be spent in putting the dairy industry on a sound basis&mdash;a total of nearly £9,000,000&mdash;I feel that some of the citizens of the State in those parts of the country less favoured in many ways, by nature, by situation, and by the action of the State, are entitled to plead with the Government to make things better in their districts.  If a considerable number of millions is being spent in certain areas, there are other parts of the country where little has been done and where little is being spent.  These districts are as worthy and as much in need of help as other regions where the people are better favoured from the point of view of things they possess in the way of land and locomotion.  When the Minister stated that this action was taken so that the dairying industry might be put on a solid basis, it should be remembered that the dairy industry is not confined to five or six counties, and that it is on an unsound basis in other parts as well as in those areas on behalf of which we are asked to take action this evening.</P>
    <P>I would say, further, to the Minister that while we have been prepared to say that the money that the State has been spending has been in the best interests of the State, from the Government point of view, it is not justifiable to continue a policy by which all citizens of the State are to be constantly <Col N="1937" /> urged to contribute their mite so that certain benefits might be conferred on certain limited areas.  I want to urge on the Minister the fact that the dairying industry in other parts of Ireland needs very careful and close attention, and requires State assistance just as much as those on whose behalf we are taking action this evening.  It has been the policy of the Government, perhaps because of geographical situation, or perhaps because of other things, to create developments in certain parts of the country.  We who speak on behalf of other parts of the country, where little has been done, and where it is necessary to do much more, would urge the Minister, in visualising the future of dairying in Ireland, to recognise, because of what it is now doing in Cork, Tipperary, Limerick and Kerry, that his statement, that the dairying industry is being put on a sound basis by what we are asked to do this evening is not justified, unless he also recognises that over the whole of the State a good deal has to be done for the industry.</P>
    <P>I want to put it to him that if the State is justified in making the venture which it is now making, and in spending and losing money so that the industry may be reorganised over a particular area, I say that the Minister will have to ask himself whether that policy is justified in any other part of the country.  I put that to him because I think it is necessary.  I am prepared to support the policy which has been put before the Dáil, because I believe, in all the circumstances, there was no alternative policy.  At the same time, feeling that the reorganisation of the dairying industry is very essential, I urge on the Minister not to think that he has done everything for the industry because he is doing a good deal for the best dairying districts in the country.  While I am not prepared to go further into that matter this evening, I hope that, in addition to those parts of the country in which an effort is being made to organise the dairying industry, consideration will be given to those districts in which no effort has previously been made.  I hope that, as a result of these operations in the south the better organisation of these new <Col N="1938" /> districts will be helped forward, and that the Minister will feel that it must be his policy to do for every part of the country, as regards the dairying industry, what he is now prepared to do for a few counties in the south.</P>
    <Speaker pid="TomasOConnell" hpid="Mr. T. O'CONNELL Mr. T. O'CONNELL">
      <NameTxt>Mr. T. O'CONNELL</NameTxt>
      <P>I think the Minister is to be congratulated on his lucid account of the history of the events which led up to the introduction of this Estimate.  Deputy Cooper, who, I am sorry to say, is not in the House at the moment, seemed to be more afraid of the name of &ldquo;State Socialism&rdquo; than of the actuality.  His case is not singular.  There are many people who applaud the Shannon scheme, or agricultural measures, like the Eggs Act, who would hold up their hands in holy horror at the very name &ldquo;State Socialism.&rdquo;  What is the Shannon scheme but an effort on behalf of the State to use the power and credit of the State in the interest of the community as a whole?  After all, the State is only a collection of individuals who live in a particular area covered by the State and who work as one co-operative society.  If they find important industries, especially a great national industry like agriculture, being weakened by overlapping and by duplication of overhead expenses, it is the duty of the State to step in and use its influence, power and credit to reorganise that industry in the interests of the community as a whole.  If that is &ldquo;State Socialism,&rdquo; I have no fear either of the term or of the actuality.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>In so far as the State has stepped in to remove what seemed to be an obvious difficulty, an obvious clog on a very important industry, I am prepared to support it.  If I were inclined to offer any criticism, it would be with regard to the wisdom of passing over, without reserving any control of, the creameries purchased to the co-operative societies.  I am considerably relieved by the Minister's statement that it is his intention in the near future to introduce a Co-operative Bill, which, I take it, will regulate and control the industry generally.  I would like to mention another matter, and I would be glad to know if the Minister has given any consideration to it.  As Deputy Cooper mentioned, this, after all, <Col N="1939" /> only deals with particular districts, and with one particular, though very large, proprietary creamery.  There are many other creameries throughout the country, and I would like to know if the Minister proposes to take steps to prevent a recurrence of what happened in the case of this proprietary creamery.  Seeing what has happened in this case, is it not likely that some proprietary creameries might get active in their opposition where the co-operative creameries exist, with possibly the idea that eventually they will be bought out at a fairly good price by the Government in order to prevent opposition? There may be nothing in that suggestion, but I would like the Minister to make our minds easy on the point.  Arising out of what Deputy Baxter said, the Minister told us that the total sum the State would have to bear in this case would be about £100,000, plus the cost of liquidation and transfer.  I took the Minister to say that he estimated the losses on the redundant creameries would be about £50,000, and on the redundant condenseries another £50,000, but he did not state what additional sum it would cost the State in liquidation and transfer.</P>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. HOGAN Mr. HOGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. HOGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>It would be hard to say.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. O'CONNELL Mr. O'CONNELL">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'CONNELL</NameTxt>
      <P>I realise that it would be difficult to do so.  With regard to these losses, could the Minister say whether there was any understanding with the co-operative creameries, or was any undertaking got from them before the bargain was finally completed, that they would be prepared to pay for these creameries what they cost the Government?  If there was no such understanding with the creameries, it was a pity, as it would ensure that, as far as possible, there would be little or no loss in the passing over of the creameries to the co-operators.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I assume that the Minister and his Department are taking every possible precaution to secure that the State will get good value for the money expended. From the statement which has been supplied, and the Minister's explanation, as far as I can see that was done.  I think on the general principle, <Col N="1940" /> and the fact that this is an effort on the part of the State to come to the aid of an industry and to regulate it so that there will be no unnecessary loss, no unnecessary overhead expenses, in so far as the State has done that, I think it is worthy of support, and I am prepared to vote for the Supplementary Estimate.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JohnDaly" hpid="Mr. DALY Mr. DALY">
      <NameTxt>Mr. DALY</NameTxt>
      <P>I congratulate the Minister on the very bold step he has taken in this matter, and I hope before long we will see other Ministers also taking bold steps to create industries, and so establish a market for the butter or the cream from the creameries.  Many of these creameries are at present operating in the district I represent. In two parishes they were promised creameries, and we expected that they would be built by now were it not for the steps taken by the Department of Agriculture.  When matters are being settled, I hope the claims of these parishes will be met by the Minister at his earliest convenience.  There are redundant creameries in the district.  We have two creameries in Mitchelstown and two in Ballindangan.  I expect that some of these will lose their licences. If they are to be sold, I hope that these two parishes I have mentioned will get a chance of buying them at their market value.  I notice in the circular issued this evening that there are three grain mills also for sale.  I have a shrewd suspicion that one of these grain mills is in East Cork.  I hope the grain mills will be retained and worked by the Ministry, because other industries, such as bacon curing, could be carried on in connection with them, as there is a splendid water supply and everything necessary for the carrying on of industries.  However, I trust the Minister will place restrictions on those creameries so that the money of the State will not be used against some members of the State, that those co-operative creameries will not be the means of closing up shops in the towns and villages, so hunting a portion of the population to a foreign land. While agriculture is the staple industry, and while we will do everything possible to help it, I think it should be recognised, and many of the <Col N="1941" /> Deputies on those Benches do recognise, that it is not a profitable enterprise, and not a fair and square deal, that a section of the community should be victimised and beaten by a whip bought by their own money.  The Minister and the Department of which he is the head, and they might well be proud of him, are doing everything possible to foster industry and help those people, but I hope, at the same time, he will see that he does not injure anybody else.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickKHogan" hpid="Mr. P.K. HOGAN Mr. P.K. HOGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P.K. HOGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>I heartily support the motion of the Minister for Lands and Agriculture.  In my opinion it will place the dairying industry on a firm footing, as, at present, its overhead charges are out of proportion owing to the superfluous creameries in the country. I am well aware that the co-operative movement has been severely criticised owing to failures of co-operative creameries here and there throughout the country for some years, but that was due solely to the overlapping of the co-operative interests and the proprietary interests in competing for the raw material.  Sir Horace Plunkett laid the foundations of the co-operative movement solidly, as we can see, viewing the circumstances of the industry to-day.  It remained for the present Minister for Lands and Agriculture, with one bold sweep, to rear a superstructure on it.  In fact, one should be familiar with the dairying industry to estimate the incalculable benefits of the project that the Minister has laid before the House.  I think it would be well if I were to place before the Dáil the concrete case of a creamery working under the old conditions, which I investigated myself.  The supply of this particular creamery was 4,000 gallons per day.  We could accept a 50 per cent. increase in that supply, with a capital expenditure of about £200 (for one cream vat), without adding one shilling to our salary or wages bill, or one hour to the day's labour for the hands.  We could, in addition, accept cream from an auxiliary handling about 4,000 gallons of milk, by installing one other cream vat&mdash;the only outlay we would require.  If we increased our output without any increase <Col N="1942" /> in overhead charges, we reduce our manufacturing costs by a corresponding percentage.  Other savings which would accrue from an increased supply, if the Minister's motion is accepted by the House, in regard to this concrete case would be that rent and rates, depreciation and coal, would be spread over a greater output.</P>
      <P>At present it takes two hours to separate 4,000 gals. of milk.  Another 2,000 gals. could be separated in corresponding time with an infinitesimal cost to the coal bill, as anybody familiar with steam engines is aware of. Having got up the proper amount of pressure it would cost practically nothing to keep on the pressure for an hour extra.  Taking into consideration the saving in wages and salaries, depreciation, and cost of coal on the increased output, I certainly would not be exaggerating by stating that the suppliers in that particular creamery district would benefit to the amount of £1,000 a year.  The particular case I have cited would be typical of 75 per cent of the co-operative creameries of the country.  The acceptance of this motion will help forward the movement at present being considered by the creameries for central marketing. The output of the creamery proposed to be bought out represents about 30 per cent of the exportable creamery butter.  I need not go into the benefits of central marketing as it does not arise on this motion.  The motion of the Minister has been welcomed wholeheartedly by co-operative creamery committees as it practically means the salvation of the industry.  I believe that practically no loss will result from the re-sale of the creameries.  I have been authorised by the committee of the co-operative creamery in which I am interested to make an offer on their behalf for two auxiliaries of the company about to be bought out.  In fact, the biggest difficulty will be allocating the sales of the creameries according to the demand.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DanielMorrissey" hpid="Mr. MORRISSEY Mr. MORRISSEY">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MORRISSEY</NameTxt>
      <P>There are just a few points in regard to which I would like to get some information from the Minister.  At the conclusion of his opening statement this evening I put <Col N="1943" /> a question to the Minister as to the number of hands likely to lose their employment as the result of this scheme.  The point is an important one, because I have heard it suggested that it is likely that 60 or 70 creameries are likely to be abolished.  That would certainly mean that a considerable number of hands will lose their employment. There is another point that I am anxious to get information on, and I would like to know if the Minister has considered it.  It is: what effect will this have on the price of butter and milk to the home consumer &mdash;this wiping out of competition and the giving of a monopoly to the co-operative creameries?  Is not that, I ask, likely to lead to an increase in the price of butter and milk to the home consumer?  I would like to know if the Minister has considered that, and if so, what steps he proposes to take to safeguard the home consumer against undue increases in price in the case of those commodities.  I think most Deputies will agree that the Minister has taken a bold step and a wise one, and personally I am glad that the farmers' representatives in this House have come to see that there is something to be said for the protection of industries.  This is essentially a measure of protection.  We have been told in this House and outside of it that it was impossible to protect the agricultural industry or any branch of it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. HOGAN Mr. HOGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. HOGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>By tariffs.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DanielMorrissey" hpid="Mr. MORRISSEY Mr. MORRISSEY">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MORRISSEY</NameTxt>
      <P>This is a subsidy of over £100,000 raised from the general taxpayers to put the Irish dairying industry in a position to meet competition from foreign countries.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DenisJohnGorey" hpid="Mr. GOREY Mr. GOREY">
      <NameTxt>Mr. GOREY</NameTxt>
      <P>That is not right.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DanielMorrissey" hpid="Mr. MORRISSEY Mr. MORRISSEY">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MORRISSEY</NameTxt>
      <P>That is what it is, call it what you like, whether the term be protection or subsidy.  At any rate it is the State coming to the aid of the agricultural industry.  I do not quarrel with that.  I think that the State has a perfect right to come to the assistance of the agricultural industry, and that it would have a perfect right to come to the aid of the several other <Col N="1944" /> industries in this country.  But, for my part, I would like to see a little consistency in the matter.  I think myself that it is a wise step, but I would like to be satisfied that the Minister is going to safeguard the home consumer in the matter of the products of those creameries. I am also anxious to hear from him as to the number likely to be disemployed as a result of this scheme and what provision, if any, is to be made for them.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DenisJohnGorey" hpid="Mr. GOREY Mr. GOREY">
      <NameTxt>Mr. GOREY</NameTxt>
      <P>I think that we will have to pass over the pleasantries indulged in by Deputy Morrissey and some other Deputies.  I think we may pass over also the speech that was made by Deputy Cooper.  It reminded me very much of the Spanish method of making love.  Listening to Deputy Cooper one could see in the window &ldquo;Miss County Dublin&rdquo; and outside the Deputy serenading her.  I think, and I am glad to observe, that the House thinks in the same way, that the Minister's proposition in this matter bears the hall-mark of statesmanship. It was impossible for anyone outside of the Government to deal with the position that had arisen.  The Government and the Minister particularly have shown their courage and their foresight by stepping in at this moment. Their action at this critical time will, I believe, tend to preserve a movement that must be the basis of the future prosperity of this country&mdash;that is the co-operative movement.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I do not view this proposition as a gift to industry.  It cannot be regarded as such inasmuch as a very small portion of the country will be affected by this.  It is no gift to the rest of the country.  The rest of the country will be called upon to subscribe their portion although this matter will, in no way, affect them.  This condensed factory, or this privately-owned creamery, only extends to a few counties. It does not touch the others. Therefore, they will be contributing as much as any other citizen in the State. The great thing the Minister sets out to preserve is the co-operative movement in the country.  I admire him for that.  I can visualise the position if the war between the two warring factions <Col N="1945" /> is carried on.  It is possible that this firm, Lovell and Christmas, may win, as he stated, the first round, and I can visualise the position of the guarantors in all those areas.  I can visualise the five, six, or twenty men connected with every creamery being ruined, being swept economically off the face of the country in order to meet their liabilities.  I can visualise the pioneers, the best men in the country, that have stood up and favoured the co-operative movement, being swept away, and that would be a sad day for this country.</P>
    <P>This, I think, cannot be regarded as a subsidy.  My only regret is that the £100,000 will not be made good by the people whom this is to benefit.  I think that is the only blot on the whole proposition. I would much prefer that those people would be able to make good the whole debt.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MartinRoddy" hpid="Mr. RODDY Mr. RODDY">
      <NameTxt>Mr. RODDY</NameTxt>
      <P>I regard this Vote as an effort on the part of the Minister for Lands and Agriculture to evolve order out of chaos.  There is no doubt that at present the dairying industry in this country is in a chaotic condition, due, in the first place, to the depression that prevails generally in agriculture, and, in the second place, to the competition in certain parts of the State between the proprietary and co-operative systems.  It has always seemed to me that in a small State like ours it is impossible for the two systems to survive side by side, and I think the Minister has acted wisely in accepting the offer made by the directors of the proprietary creameries in this country to effect a deal with them for the purchase, outright, of the proprietary system.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>After all, I think one can easily visualise the condition of the dairying industry in this country in two or three years' time if competition were allowed to continue on its present lines. Competition of that kind would have a serious effect on the dairying industry, and I believe it would mean that it would retard anything in the nature of co-operative development for a number of years.  Deputy Baxter complains that this will only confer a benefit on a certain limited area.  I am in exactly the same position as Deputy Baxter. The constituency I represent will <Col N="1946" /> derive no immediate benefit from a vote of this kind.  I recognise, however, that this is one of the preliminary problems which the Minister for Lands and Agriculture has got to deal with before he can put into operation a forward agricultural policy.  It is necessary to get the proprietary system cleared out of the way before he can put into operation a Co-operative Act or pass legislation for the purpose of establishing an agricultural credit corporation. This is certainly one of the obstacles which must, first of all, be cleared out of the way.</P>
    <P>Deputy Cooper referred to the fact that the State seemed to be spending an enormous amount of money on agricultural development.  As a matter of fact, in comparison with other States, we are spending very little money on agricultural development in this country.  Co-operation in other countries has made enormous strides, particularly since the war, and we, in this country, are at least twenty years behind countries like New Zealand, Australia, Canada and Denmark, competitors in our main markets.  A bold move such as the Minister for Lands and Agriculture has made to-day I believe will have a healthy psychological effect on the country and on the agricultural industry generally.  It will give a tremendous stimulus to the development of the dairying industry.  I cannot see that there is any point in Deputy Cooper's remark that this venture is the beginning of State Socialism. After all, it is proposed, as the Minister pointed out in his statement, to sell the proprietary creameries to other groups of co-operative creameries, and I have not the slightest doubt that the existing co-operative creameries will be very glad to avail of the opportunity of buying out the redundant proprietary creameries and availing themselves of the milk supply which these creameries are getting at the moment.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelRichardHeffer" hpid="Mr. HEFFERNAN Mr. HEFFERNAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. HEFFERNAN</NameTxt>
      <P>It is rather hard to expect that we should be able to give a considered opinion upon the financial problem connected with this Vote before us to-day in such a short time.  I rather agree with the Deputy who stated that this <Col N="1947" /> matter should have come before the House in the form of a Bill.  I can understand, in the circumstances surrounding the case, that the Minister is obliged, owing to the urgency of the matter, to bring it before us in this form.  For that reason, I do not profess to give any criticism with regard to the financial aspects of it.</P>
      <P>As some Deputies have remarked, this is a form of State Socialism.  I do not intend to argue that point, because it seems to me that, whether we like it or not, we are gradually drifting into State interference with many of our activities.  While it may not be regarded as State Socialism, it is getting away from the individualistic policy. Personally, I am inclined to be an individualist. I would like to see people helping themselves and to see business developing; but whether we like it or not, the State is going to take a larger share in the activities of the country than in the past.  We have to accept that situation.</P>
      <P>Certain Deputies are making great points with regard to protection.  They are awfully anxious to insist that farmers are being protected in every shape and form, and they refer to the grants the farmers are getting.  I would like to see protection of this kind given to industry; this is the right kind of protection. This is a case of the State stepping in, making a definite deal, giving a definite grant confined to a certain amount of money so as to place an industry on its feet.  That is very different from giving a blank cheque, as is the case with protected industries. Once those industries get protection, they batten on the consumers of the country for all time.  This is not protecting or boosting up an industry for the purpose of allowing that industry to batten on consumers, charging them an enchanced price.  This is to enable an industry to compete with other industries. When Ministers ask us to make reasonable grants to enable Irish industries to compete with those of foreign countries, we should be prepared to facilitate them.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DanielMorrissey" hpid="Mr. MORRISSEY Mr. MORRISSEY">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MORRISSEY</NameTxt>
      <P>Will the Deputy <Col N="1948" /> tell us how the price to the consumer is controlled from the creameries?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PadraicOMaille" hpid="AN LEAS-CHEANN COMHAIRLE Padraic Ó Máille">
      <NameTxt>AN LEAS-CHEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>We are not discussing protection or free trade now.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelRichardHeffer" hpid="Mr. HEFFERNAN Mr. HEFFERNAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. HEFFERNAN</NameTxt>
      <P>Deputy Morrissey is very anxious about the consumer. This is not going to have the slightest effect on the consumer, and I am sure, when the Minister is replying, he will confirm that statement.  The question for us to consider is whether the State is getting good value for its money and whether the farmers are going to get good value in the creameries which are going to be handed over to them.  We are given certain figures relating to the price paid by the State to the owners of these concerns. I am not in a position to say if the Minister is justified in paying the figure he has mentioned.  Of course, the Minister may have certain information which is not in our possession and which enables him to state whether or not he is getting good value.  The price paid for this concern is practically altogether made up of the sums which have been put into the business by the different parties concerned.  That amount comes to £365,000.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. HOGAN Mr. HOGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. HOGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>No; the amount comes to £300,000.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelRichardHeffer" hpid="Mr. HEFFERNAN Mr. HEFFERNAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. HEFFERNAN</NameTxt>
      <P>The amounts given by you came to £365,000, made up as follows:&mdash;Cleeves, Ltd., £79,000; Messrs. Lovell and Christmas, £100,000; compensation for losses, £16,000; paid to farmers for milk supplied, £40,000; value of the Newmarket Dairy Company, £39,000.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. HOGAN Mr. HOGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. HOGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>£90,000.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelRichardHeffer" hpid="Mr. HEFFERNAN Mr. HEFFERNAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. HEFFERNAN</NameTxt>
      <P>You gave an item of £39,000 for something, and £90,000 for motor-cars and other equipment. Those were the figures I got.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. HOGAN Mr. HOGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. HOGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>I think the Deputy's figures are wrong.  Perhaps the Deputy would like me to give them to him again.  They are:&mdash;Cleeves, Ltd., £80,000; paid to farmers, £40,000; Newmarket Dairy Company, £90,000; new and additional machinery, transport, <Col N="1949" /> etc., £90,000, the whole making about £300,000 odd.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelRichardHeffer" hpid="Mr. HEFFERNAN Mr. HEFFERNAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. HEFFERNAN</NameTxt>
      <P>The figures given by the Minister at another stage included £100,000 put in by Messrs. Lovell and Christmas.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. HOGAN Mr. HOGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. HOGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>That is right.  There are certain figures on the books, and they include £100,000 put in by Lovell and Christmas; £225,000 for the numbers of shares, and £16,000 for compensation. There are bank overdrafts appearing on the books.  The question is how were they spent.  Approaching it from another way, you get the figures I have just given.  The moneys that appear in the books were spent in this way:&mdash;Cleeves, Ltd., £80,000; Newmarket Dairy Company, £90,000; paid to farmers, £40,000; additional machinery, etc., £90,000.  There are two sets of figures; one set of figures indicates what was put into the business.  The next question is how were those moneys spent, and it was in order to give Deputies an idea of that, that I went down the list.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelRichardHeffer" hpid="Mr. HEFFERNAN Mr. HEFFERNAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. HEFFERNAN</NameTxt>
      <P>I hope the Minister will correct me if I am wrong in my figures.  The paid-up capital of the business is £240,000.  Messrs. Lovell and Christmas lent £100,000.  I take it the £240,000 represents money put into the business in cash by the owners?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. HOGAN Mr. HOGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. HOGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>£240,000 was paid up, but that does not mean paid up in cash. That includes bonus shares.  The exact amount representing cash in shares is £225,000.  In addition, there was £100,000 loaned by Messrs. Lovell and Christmas.  Then there are bank overdrafts, moneys for compensation, etc., and those tot to £400,000, which is the total amount I estimate was put into the business.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelRichardHeffer" hpid="Mr. HEFFERNAN Mr. HEFFERNAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. HEFFERNAN</NameTxt>
      <P>It would appear, then, that we are getting the assets of the firm at a lesser price than was paid by the owners?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. HOGAN Mr. HOGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. HOGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>Less than the money put in, but £100,000 represents trade losses&mdash;trade losses in one sense, but in another sense not trade losses, because <Col N="1950" /> it was money spent to re-establish good-will.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelRichardHeffer" hpid="Mr. HEFFERNAN Mr. HEFFERNAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. HEFFERNAN</NameTxt>
      <P>How much money did Messrs. Lovell and Christmas put into the business from start to finish?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. HOGAN Mr. HOGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. HOGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>I could not say exactly, but the Deputy can take it the figure of £400,000 which I gave, is not far wrong.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelRichardHeffer" hpid="Mr. HEFFERNAN Mr. HEFFERNAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. HEFFERNAN</NameTxt>
      <P>If that is so, my ideas have changed.  Then the owners are losing something over £35,000? What is the business worth at the present time and what would it be worth in a year's time?  I am not in a position to say, but there are people who declare that if the Government let it go for another year they would get it at probably half the price.  I do not say that is the case.  There are other factors which may have made it necessary for the Government to step in.  It is a question of balancing one thing with another, and it appears to me at this stage that we probably have got the business at just about its value.</P>
      <P>I do not say we have got it at less than its value.  I think we have paid sufficient for it.  We agree that the elimination of this competition that was obtaining was necessary and if this elimination does not take place now it should take place some time, and in the meantime an immense amount of harm might be done to the dairying industry. Some steps had to be taken by somebody to do away with the uneconomic competition which has been taking place for some time.  It undoubtedly opens the way for the development and the proper marketing of butter, which has become an absolute essential to the agricultural interest in this country. Deputy Cooper made a lot of capital out of the fact that the Government is entering into trade.  As a matter of fact the Government is not entering into trade at all.  It is simply taking over the factories of this company with the idea of getting rid of them to suitable purchasers at a suitable opportunity. I take it that Deputy Cooper was not really in earnest when he said this. I take it he was only making&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. P. HOGAN Mr. P. HOGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P. HOGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>A speech.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1951" />
    <Speaker pid="MichaelRichardHeffer" hpid="Mr. HEFFERNAN Mr. HEFFERNAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. HEFFERNAN</NameTxt>
      <P>Well, that he was making capital out of it.  I have been asked by certain people in my county to draw the Minister's attention to a certain fact in connection with the condensed milk creameries.  I have been closely in touch with the development of this particular factory, more closely than anybody in the Dáil.  The matter to which I wish to draw attention is the losses which the farmers of Tipperary suffered owing to the taking over in 1922 of the creameries by what we call the red flaggers.  Certain moneys in connection with the sale of butter by the Soviets who had charge of the creamery at the time came into the hands of the Minister for Finance. I do not know how these moneys were used.  I think they were retained as a set-off against compensation paid by the Government.  At any rate, the farmers got none of that money.  Over and over again I have emphasised the fact that the Government have dealt harshly with the farmers over those losses in 1922.</P>
      <P>The Minister has been emphasising the fact that the Government is fair to everybody.  I distinctly state that in this matter the Government is unfair to these farmers who suffered through the fact of these creameries being taken over by the red flaggers.  There is now an opportunity of making reparation. There are two classes of people who have claims in that regard.  One is the class for whom I have most sympathy&mdash;those who supplied milk to the creameries for a short time&mdash;six, seven, ten or fourteen days, in ignorance of the real state of affairs&mdash;that the creameries were not controlled by the owners.  Those people got no payment whatever for the milk supplied.  In addition, there is a second class of people who are making a claim.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PadraicOMaille" hpid="AN LEAS-CHEANN COMHAIRLE Padraic Ó Máille">
      <NameTxt>AN LEAS-CHEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>I am afraid this matter does not concern the Vote at all.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelRichardHeffer" hpid="Mr. HEFFERNAN Mr. HEFFERNAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. HEFFERNAN</NameTxt>
      <P>It is really connected with this motion.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PadraicOMaille" hpid="AN LEAS-CHEANN COMHAIRLE Padraic Ó Máille">
      <NameTxt>AN LEAS-CHEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>There is no sub-head in the Vote dealing with compensation of that sort.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelRichardHeffer" hpid="Mr. HEFFERNAN Mr. HEFFERNAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. HEFFERNAN</NameTxt>
      <P>I call attention <Col N="1952" /> to it.  The Minister is well aware of the fact, and I hope he will meet the case. By so doing the Minister would be purchasing the good-will of the suppliers. There has never been real good-will in connection with those creameries.  The difficulties the present proprietors are in are due to the fact that they took over the creameries without the good-will of the farmers in the district.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickWalterShaw" hpid="Mr. SHAW Mr. SHAW">
      <NameTxt>Mr. SHAW</NameTxt>
      <P>I join with the other Deputies in congratulating the Minister on the scheme he has formulated. I think it is a marvellous and wonderful tribute to him to say that he has received from all parts of the House congratulations on this scheme.  The reason I say that is that at the present period, on the eve of a General Election, to find that any scheme put forward by the Government is having the unanimous approval of the House, certainly looks as if the Minister for Agriculture had the four-leaf shamrock.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DanielMorrissey" hpid="Mr. MORRISSEY Mr. MORRISSEY">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MORRISSEY</NameTxt>
      <P>The other parties are broadminded.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickWalterShaw" hpid="Mr. SHAW Mr. SHAW">
      <NameTxt>Mr. SHAW</NameTxt>
      <P>Though the scheme does not in any way benefit my constituents; I am not narrowminded enough to say that we should not contribute our portion to the other counties that are benefiting by it.  I am sorry that Deputy Cooper is not here, as he complained, on behalf of the people of Dublin, that they were obliged to contribute for what the various counties in the country areas were receiving from Dublin.  My complaint is the very opposite.  I say on behalf of the country towns that there is entirely too much centralisation of authority in Dublin and too much benefit coming to Dublin.  I am not at all in agreement with Deputy Cooper's complaint that Dublin has to pay for a considerable portion of whatever benefits may be obtained.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ErnestHAlton" hpid="Mr. ALTON Mr. ALTON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. ALTON</NameTxt>
      <P>I think we ought to be just to Deputy Bryan Cooper, who is away.  He never complained.  He only pointed it out.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickWalterShaw" hpid="Mr. SHAW Mr. SHAW">
      <NameTxt>Mr. SHAW</NameTxt>
      <P>I understood Deputy Cooper to say that Dublin would have to pay a portion of whatever taxation <Col N="1953" /> would be required to carry through this scheme in the country.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ErnestHAlton" hpid="Mr. ALTON Mr. ALTON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. ALTON</NameTxt>
      <P>He expressly said he did not complain.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickWalterShaw" hpid="Mr. SHAW Mr. SHAW">
      <NameTxt>Mr. SHAW</NameTxt>
      <P>I am in complete agreement with Deputy Baxter in appealing to the Minister on behalf of the other counties which do not benefit under this scheme, and there are many others. There are six counties benefiting under this scheme.  The other counties do not benefit.  I would say that schemes on a smaller scale, that could be formulated in the various other counties, should receive some financial assistance from the Government to develop them.  I believe that this step that has been now taken might be followed up all over the country in the other counties which are not benefiting under this larger scheme.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickJosephEgan" hpid="Mr. P.J. EGAN Mr. P.J. EGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P.J. EGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>This debate seems to have developed quite an atmosphere of mutual admiration, and I will not embarrass the Minister by adding to the very many compliments that have been paid to him.  Undoubtedly he was confronted with a very grave crisis, and it was really a case of a desperate disease requiring a desperate remedy.  I am afraid it is rather late in the day now for us to be talking about taking a step in the direction of State Socialism or of not being true to our ideals about free trade or protection, or anything of that sort.  I fear that Deputy Heffernan and myself and others, by our votes on more than one occasion, have laid ourselves open to the suggestion that we have not always been, perhaps, consistent. The main point about this proposal is that the State will be paying a sum of about £100,000 to re-establish one of the premier industries in the country.  I do not consider that a very extravagant figure, because, although Deputy Heffernan suggested that the State might get a better bargain by waiting a little longer, the Minister was obviously confronted by a condition of affairs that could not afford to wait. The two interests were mutually destroying one another.  Competition was gradually eating a hole in the trade, and if the Minister had waited any <Col N="1954" /> longer the whole industry would have been in such a precarious condition that he would have found it very difficult indeed to resurrect it and put it on a firm basis.</P>
      <P>One of the benefits I can see as a result of the Minister's action is one that has not been emphasised as it should have been, that is, the gradual combination of the creamery business into one large unit, because I can see that that is the ultimate aim that the Minister has in view.  That will give the Irish butter industry an enormous advantage from the marketing point of view.  Unquestionably, one of the greatest difficulties that the Irish butter industry has to contend with is the marketing difficulty.  There is too much internal competition, too much competition between small lots going to the London and other markets, without due regard to the time when they appear there and the quantities which may be available at certain times.  Undoubtedly in this respect the bigger the unit of butter placed on the market and the more control there is over the time at which that butter will be placed on the market the better the Irish industry will be able to meet the very severe competition which comes from Denmark and other countries.  To my mind, that is really the very greatest solid advantage which will arise from this proceeding.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>As one or two Deputies said, it is difficult to give a reasoned criticism of this proposal at such short notice, and I must confess that there are one or two parts of the proposal on which I am a little bit cloudy.  I think one was referred to by Deputy O'Connell, that is, the question as to what extent the Minister can guarantee that the creameries which he is going to take over will be absorbed by the co-operative creameries which will be left, and as to whether he has any understanding with these surviving co-operative creameries with regard to the terms on which they are prepared to take them over.  I was very glad to hear from Deputy Hogan that the creamery with which he is associated is now prepared to make a definite offer for at least two of these creameries. That is a matter on which, perhaps, <Col N="1955" /> the Minister would give us a little more information.  Another point about which I am anxious to know a little is as to the extent to which the existing managentent will be taken over.  What is to become of the existing management?  There must be a great many skilled men, managers and so forth, and are their services to be at the disposal of the new combine, or is any provision to be made for taking them over?  On the whole, I think that the Minister has dealt in a very courageous fashion with what was, undoubtedly, a very serious crisis, and it is really refreshing to find such wonderful unanimity of opinion on this matter in the House.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>took the Chair.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickJHogan" hpid="MINISTER for LANDS and AGRICULTURE (Mr. Hogan) MINISTER for LANDS and AGRICULTURE (Mr. Hogan)">
      <NameTxt>MINISTER for LANDS and AGRICULTURE (Mr. Hogan)</NameTxt>
      <P>I appreciate the way this matter has been received by all Parties.  It will make a very big difference in the difficult work of disintegrating and transferring the property. I daresay that Deputy Cooper did not mean himself to be taken seriously. He talked about State Socialism. People should not use these terms loosely.  There is no use, in fact, using them without first defining them.  But I do not think there is any necessity to go into the question as to whether or not this is an essay in State Socialism. We do not propose to run a toffee factory, or mills, or creameries, or anything else.  We propose to get rid of these as soon as feasible.  Deputy Cooper, apparently, did not listen to what I had to say in the afternoon and, apparently, knows very little about the condensing industry, whatever he may know about the creamery industry.  He regretted the fact that I was not a business man.  It appears to me that business men are a kind of caste.  They need know nothing about business, provided they belong to that particular caste that is known as business men.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I am afraid in this respect that Deputy Cooper is not a business man.  He made the point that I had been most unwise, from the point of view of the <Col N="1956" /> future of the condensed milk industry, in announcing that the bulk of Irish condensed milk is made from separated milk.  If he knew anything about the business side of the organisation he would know that they advertise that fact themselves.  Equally he would know that everybody on the market is aware that unless condensed milk is advertised as made from whole milk it may be taken for granted that it is made from separated milk.  Deputy Cooper spoke about redundancy amongst co-operative creameries, and he asked me what I intended to do about that problem.  He, apparently, did not listen to what I had to say on the matter this afternoon.  He regretted that I was so foolish as to state that I proposed to transfer immediately these properties which we intend to sell, not to the creameries but in the open market.  Again he misunderstood what I said, and I think I was quite plain.  I said that we proposed to transfer the creameries as soon as possible, not the other property.  We can hold the other assets, and we do propose to hold them until we get their value.</P>
    <P>There is just one point that I would like to clear up.  It was stressed by a few speakers&mdash;Deputy Baxter, Deputy Heffernan, Deputy Cooper, Deputy Roddy, and others.  The point was made that this transaction will be a benefit to a limited area, that it will not affect other districts, and I have been asked what we are going to do with them.  I think that that is a complete misconception.  I would not delay five minutes on this transaction if it merely meant purchasing a certain number of creameries and handing them over to certain other creameries.  If the significance of this particular transaction was confined to the effect it would have in the limited areas where the company competed with the co-operative societies it would have very little significance indeed.  I did point out that even from that limited point of view the transfer was really good business to the limited number of societies concerned, that they would be saving in overhead expenses about £40,000 to £50,000 a year, and that that would more than pay twice over the interest and sinking fund on the total price of <Col N="1957" /> the creamery.  But that is only incidental. If this particular transaction has any justification it is only that it enables us to go ahead with our policy for the dairying industry as a whole, and that policy is to pass the Co-operative Act, containing all the provisions which I outlined this afternoon, and put it into operation, and, secondly, to pass the Agricultural Credits Act and to establish the Agricultural Credit Corporation.  That is the policy.  The other is a mere preliminary, a necessary preliminary, a vital preliminary, but nevertheless a mere preliminary, with only a very limited significance, except for its significance as being a preliminary to the policy itself.  That policy will affect districts where dairying is carried on directly, and indirectly, of course, it will affect every other district, because Irish agriculture is interlocked.  Dairying is carried on all over the South, even into the Midlands, to some extent in the West, and all over the North.  But even where dairying as such is not carried on there is the live stock trade, the pig trade, which in turn depends on dairying. That policy must, if it is put into operation, affect every district in the whole country.  I think Deputies should not approach any problem from the point of view of &ldquo;What is this district to get, and what is that district to get?&rdquo;</P>
    <P>This proposal is not a proposal of giving a dole here and a dole there, to give a certain amount of compensation in one direction and to make, so to speak, an equivalent grant in another. You get nowhere on that line.  That is not a policy; it is simply a system of doles you carry out for the want of a policy because you have no policy, in fact, to carry out.  That is not the idea.  The idea is to reorganise so far as it is possible the dairying industry, by passing these Acts and establishing that institution.  Again, I want to emphasise that this reorganisation must be carried out by the creameries themselves. We must give them the means but they must do it.  It is not for the State to do it, and so far from this being an essay at State Socialism or an attempt to initiate an era of State interference in all industries, it is an attempt <Col N="1958" /> on the part of the State to disentangle itself from interference in industry.  The idea is to do the necessary once and for all, to provide the means for the industry itself and then let the people concerned solve their own problems.</P>
    <P>It was mentioned that there was a problem of redundancy even amongst the co-operative creameries.  I adverted to that in my opening statement.  There is such a problem, but it is a problem which can be easily solved by a co-operative system operating within the limits and with the aid of the Co-operative Act on the one hand, and with the assistance of the Agricultural Credit Corporation on the other.  These two factors will enable them to solve that matter of redundancy, to solve their marketing problems, and any other problems they may have.  It would be quite impossible for the State to interfere, for instance, in marketing. It is purely a business, a commercial transaction, and such interference would be both costly and unsatisfactory to the State and to the people concerned. It is equally improper and wasteful for the State to interfere in the way of attempting to solve some of the other problems which are facing creameries.  They are akin to the commercial problems that face every other business.  Our duty consists, as I see it, of putting means at their disposal, of putting them in the position to solve these problems, to give them the responsibility, and I have not the slightest doubt that once they get that responsibility and the means, they will rise to it.  Responsibility is a great educating force.  I have no doubt whatever that once you have a big organisation with the requisite means, with requisite credit, the big man will appear.  It will attract him everywhere.  There will be work there that is worth while, and in that way, apart from the material benefit, it will be of great educative value to the country.</P>
    <P>There was another important point raised which I would like to deal with. It was raised by Deputy O'Connell, and again by Deputy Egan.  I was asked had we any guarantees that the creameries would do their part, had we any consultation with the creameries&mdash;<Col N="1959" /> in a word, could I indicate in any way what the attitude of the creameries concerned would be.  Would they be anxious to take these creameries over and would they be willing to pay what we purchased them for?  As to their anxiety to take them over, there is no doubt about that.  They will be extremely anxious to take them over, and, as Deputy P.K. Hogan pointed out, there will be two or three looking for the milk supply of the same redundant creamery.  There are twenty-four million gallons of milk to be divided, and that means a very big advantage. Somebody is going to do really well out of it.  In so far as the creameries are concerned, you can take it for granted that every creamery within the area and on the borders of it, will be anxious to get its share of that supply, and the real trouble will come when the supply is being apportioned to the creameries, because that, in fact, is what the closing of the redundant creameries really means.</P>
    <P>Then, there is the other question&mdash; will they take up the purchase money? Before I answer that, perhaps I would say something on the point raised by Deputy O'Connell as to whether we have consulted them.  We have not consulted them.  We have no definite guarantee, and for this reason.  Perhaps I would say again what I said this afternoon on this point:</P>
    <P>In considering the application it was obvious that in normal circumstances the attitude of the Minister for Finance would be that if the co-operative creameries concerned purchased, he would lend the money required to supplement local capital, provided he approved of the price and was offered sufficient security.</P>
    <P>There was nobody in the country that you could easily put your hand on who would negotiate and act as a carrying body and who would be willing to offer £350,000 worth of security. There was no concrete body to be had round about except a body set up for the purpose who would offer security for £350,000.</P>
    <P>This attitude, however, could not be adopted in this case.  It would be <Col N="1960" /> merely another way of refusing to have anything to do with the matter. It is obvious that the Company could not negotiate on the basis that, if and when a price was fixed as between the negotiators, each and every one of the creameries involved should agree to it.  Any small proportion of the suppliers could prevent the sale by disagreement, and the Company would then be in the invidious position of having offered to sell, having revealed its exact position, and to some extent, its trade secrets, and nevertheless having to carry on because the ultimate purchasers had refused to agree amongst themselves. This was out of the question in this particular case.  The farmers concerned had learned a very bitter lesson as a result of the liquidation of Cleeves.</P>
    <P>It would be, in my opinion, out of the question in any case; in this particular case there was no question about it.</P>
    <P>In these circumstances, the Company could not afford to allow a feeling of insecurity to grow up amongst their suppliers.  If the Company attempted to negotiate in such a way as to make it necessary to consult the suppliers to co-operative creameries all over the area, within which its operations were carried on, the inevitable result would be that at an early stage after these consultations became public, the Company would begin to lose its own suppliers.</P>
    <P>I think everybody from the district will appreciate that.</P>
    <P>If a large number of the suppliers thought that the creameries which they were supplying were likely to be closed in the near future, rightly or wrongly, they would come to their own conclusions, and they would see what they regarded as very good reasons for being amongst the first to transfer their milk supplies.</P>
    <P>There are obvious reasons why they should do that which I need not go into. That point of view was put up, of course, by the Company, and there was no answer to it.  Deputies have to remember that a committee of a co-operative <Col N="1961" /> society cannot commit its members to a financial transaction of any magnitude&mdash;there must be a general meeting.  Imagine trying to negotiate with general meetings all over the country!  The first few general meetings held would mean that the Company would have to sell at whatever price they got.  They could not draw back from it.  If they did a feeling of insecurity would have developed. It would be known that the Company was anxious to sell, and they would simply be in the position that they could not draw back.</P>
    <P>On the other hand, the Government could not consult the creameries for that reason until the price was fixed.  If the Government insisted on the creameries being consulted before the price was fixed, Messrs. Lovell and Christmas would be absolutely entitled to say to us: &ldquo;Even if the creameries do not agree, you must fix the price, you must pay the price.&rdquo;  They could not allow any representative of the Department of Agriculture or the I.A.O.S. to go down and consult all the creameries and broadcast it all over the country and at the same time give them the option of withdrawing from the bargain on the question of price.  It would be out of the question.  The difficulty was this: There were bodies to carry on negotiations.  In fact, the negotiations were carried on by the solicitor to the I.A.O.S., and he had at his back the advice of officers of that organisation and of the Department of Agriculture.  There was no difficulty about conducting the negotiations.  But there was no body that could take over and put the Government in the position that I suggest is the normal position; that could say to the Government: &ldquo;We will speak for the creameries; without consulting them; without going round to the co-operative societies, we speak for the creameries. We have bought these at £365,000; we want the money from you, and we are in a position to offer security.&rdquo;  There was no such body, and hence we had to do it ourselves.</P>
    <P>Deputy Baxter made some very useful suggestions and expressed a point of view that I was extremely glad to hear.  He pointed out that we were <Col N="1962" /> to some extent taking some risks and asked what my views were as to the eagerness of the creameries to shoulder their liabilities now.  He expressed the view that it was their duty to cooperate; to rise to the occasion and to do now what they would have gladly done three weeks ago if they were approached by a private individual, namely, to take their fair share.  He asked, quite rightly, and so did Deputy O'Connell and others, what we proposed to do in the event of the creameries taking another attitude.  All these difficulties were present to me from the beginning, as I tried to indicate in my opening statement.  We have to some extent cast our bread upon the waters, but I believe that it will be returned. We are carrying the baby, and when the Government is carrying the baby it is only natural that people should endeavour to make all they can out of it.  I will make a prediction and it is this: That in all the circumstances we will experience very little trouble from the creameries.  I have been able to consult certain prominent men who have interests in the co-operative creameries, and I know their views.  I believe that if left to themselves, if not interfered with, so to speak, the creameries will rise to the occasion, and that we will be able to place far the greatest portion of this money voluntarily and with very little trouble. I anticipate there will be some trouble. There will always be some minorities who will make some trouble&mdash;that is quite inevitable.  Of course, I am not in a position to speak firmly on this. I know the weakness of the position. We have to a great extent, for a voluntary agreement, to trust to the good-will of the creameries.  I am ready to do that, and I believe we will not be disappointed, because I am satisfied that we are in a position to give them good value.</P>
    <P>On the other hand, if things do go wrong, and if there are difficulties, we are in a position to meet them.  We have not given away all the cards.  The Co-operative Bill has to come; the Agricultural Credit Corporation has to come.  These are essential to the dairying industry&mdash;this is merely the preliminary. The Co-operative Bill will <Col N="1963" /> contain a condition that all suppliers must be shareholders.  That gives us an obvious way to deal with the suppliers to the Company's creameries who will go over to the co-operative creameries, but who at the same time will not be willing to take their liabilities.  There is an obvious way to deal with them if necessary.  I do not anticipate it will be necessary, but if it is the means are there.  On the other hand, there is the Agricultural Credit Corporation, which will be dealing with the finances of creameries in future and helping to deal with all those problems that I have indicated.  And money talks.  If necessary, the operations of the Agricultural Credit Corporation can be so used as to make it worth while for the creameries to take their fair share of those liabilities. As I said, I do not anticipate any real trouble.  There will be some; there will be confusion; there is bound to be in the liquidation of a big company like this.  There will be mistakes made; some things will be done too quickly; some things will be delayed; there will be some waste, some extravagance&mdash;there is always bound to be in the liquidation of a big company like this.  But, on the whole, making allowance for all that, I do not anticipate that there will be a lot of trouble.</P>
    <P>I anticipate that practically all the shares for the non-redundant property will be taken voluntarily and without finding it necessary to invoke the Co-operative Act.  In any event, the committees of the creameries&mdash;and I am sure we will be able to deal with the committees without very much trouble &mdash;will be in a position to know that, so far as they themselves are incurring liability, they will have the help of the Co-operative Act afterwards to see that any recalcitrant minorities honour their guarantees.  In that way it can be put through.  Trouble means delay, but it only means delay. In the end, the whole thing can be put through.  The sooner the better of course, as time means money.  The longer this is in liquidation the more it will cost; the quicker it goes through the less it will cost, and the better it will be for everybody.  My only regret, <Col N="1964" /> like that of Deputy Gorey, is that the whole price cannot be carried by the people getting the property.  I believe that even the whole price would be good value to them.  On the other hand, it is a plain simple proposition that people should be asked to pay for what they are receiving and no more. We are asking them to pay for everything they get.  We are asking the creameries to pay for everything they receive, everything that is not redundant, and grants will only be made in respect of redundant property, and, of course, only in respect of that part of any property which is redundant.</P>
    <P>The total grant I anticipate between the condensers and the creameries will be round about £100,000.  I would not like at this stage to make a guess at the cost of this transaction.  Now about the other proprietors, I am in communication with them and I shall leave it at that for the moment.  Deputy Morrissey raised a very important point as to the staffs, and that is the last question I have to deal with.  I calculate that the staffs on the redundant property number about 180.  No question arises so far as the staffs of the other properties&mdash;the non-redundant creameries, of which there are &mdash;are concerned.  They will be all required. Now the staffs of the redundant creameries, of which there are about 50, are not big.  It takes but a small staff to run an auxiliary, and although 50 are being closed, the total staffs will only be about 150.  To begin with, these are to be closed at once. It will take some time, and in any event, the staffs are entitled to full consideration and they are entitled to consideration on the basis that this is an unusual transaction.</P>
    <P>They have, of course, no fixity of tenure.  Their legal position is undefined, or rather, I should say, their legal position is that they have no fixity of tenure.  But, on the other hand, we must realise that for State reasons we have stepped in and suddenly closed up 50 institutions and we must take that into account when dealing with the staffs, and we will do so. But I must be taken to mean no more or less than what I say.  I anticipate <Col N="1965" /> that we can do justice to those staffs in many ways.  There are new creameries going to be set up.  There is Government money going to be spent; there are demands every day for new managers, and, so far as I know, as far as the I.A.O.S. and the Co-operative creameries are concerned, not to speak of our attitude, they are all anxious to do the fair thing by the staffs.</P>
    <P>I do not anticipate very much difficulty will arise, with good-will on all sides and with the position we are in to make conditions when giving Government money to the new creameries, that there will be much trouble with the staffs.  I think these are the only questions that have been raised.</P>
    <Speaker pid="DanielMorrissey" hpid="Mr. MORRISSEY Mr. MORRISSEY">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MORRISSEY</NameTxt>
      <P>Will the Minister answer the question about the home consumer?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. HOGAN Mr. HOGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. HOGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>This is not going to affect the price of butter to the home consumer, but it ought to mean that more butter of a first-class quality ought to be made, and, therefore, will fetch a higher price, but not in the sense Deputy Morrissey wants.  Further, it ought to mean that the overhead expenses will be much lessened, and between those two you have the measure of the advantages.  As we are at present the price of Irish butter is really ruled by its price in the English market. The price will, I hope, be higher for the Irish creameries, because they will turn out a better butter, but it will leave more profit apart from that, because there will be less expense, but this is not going as such to affect the price of butter on the Irish market. There is just one way it would.  The advantages in favour of a tariff on butter have been pressed on me, but I have always pointed out that a tariff, no matter how high, on butter would not affect the price of butter one iota. But there is a good time coming.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>When the creameries are owned by the co-operative societies then a tariff will make itself felt, at once, and it will become at least practical, and I shall be anxious to see if all the people who are now so anxious to press a tariff when it is not going to effect anything will be so anxious for a tariff when it is really going to mean a rise in the <Col N="1966" /> price of butter exactly corresponding to the amount of the tariff put on. That will be the acid test.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelRichardHeffer" hpid="Mr. HEFFERNAN Mr. HEFFERNAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. HEFFERNAN</NameTxt>
      <P>Will the Minister for Finance state whether he will have a tariff this year?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. HOGAN Mr. HOGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. HOGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>I have nothing else to say except that the statement made by various parties in this House will make it easier undoubtedly&mdash;I had some qualms on the matter&mdash;to put this transaction through.  What really would make it difficult would be if the creameries got a wrong lead and it would be easy to give them a wrong lead.  I do not believe that they would succumb to it, but it will go through if everybody faces it with peace and good-will.  It is in quite a delicate condition, and the debate here has made the prospects of putting this transaction through efficiently much brighter.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. O'CONNELL Mr. O'CONNELL">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'CONNELL</NameTxt>
      <P>There is one question that I would like to ask; it is rather a technical question.  What was the point of making the purchaser an unnamed individual rather than the Minister himself and his Department? Will it be the case when the agreement is completed that this individual will be the real owner of the property?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. HOGAN Mr. HOGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. HOGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>The legal position is that this individual is a trustee for undisclosed principals.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. O'CONNELL Mr. O'CONNELL">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'CONNELL</NameTxt>
      <P>Does that appear in the agreement?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. HOGAN Mr. HOGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. HOGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>You can take it that that is the legal position.  So I am informed by the lawyers, and I have to depend on them.  The principals are undisclosed because they have not yet been decided upon.  It is not yet certain who the holding body will be; it will require some consideration.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelRichardHeffer" hpid="Mr. HEFFERNAN Mr. HEFFERNAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. HEFFERNAN</NameTxt>
      <P>Has the Minister considered the position of farmers who suffered loss under the red flag régime?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. HOGAN Mr. HOGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. HOGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>They were paid £40,000 by the company.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelRichardHeffer" hpid="Mr. HEFFERNAN Mr. HEFFERNAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. HEFFERNAN</NameTxt>
      <P>I am afraid that is not so.  That sum was paid for milk <Col N="1967" /> supplied to Cleeve's creamery and for its requirements before it went into liquidation, but no payment has been made for the milk taken under the red flag régime.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. HOGAN Mr. HOGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. HOGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>I may be wrong, but I am certain that £40,000 was paid by the Condensed Milk Company of Ireland, which was not a legal liability at all, to the farmers who supplied Cleeve's creamery before the liquidation and during the events to which the Deputy refers.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelRichardHeffer" hpid="Mr. HEFFERNAN Mr. HEFFERNAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. HEFFERNAN</NameTxt>
      <P>I think the Minister is wrong.  I am sorry Deputy O'Shaughnessy is not here, for he could throw light on the subject.  It was a liability of the old company. The new company were not legally liable, but it had nothing to do with the red flag régime.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="NocholasWall" hpid="Mr. WALL Mr. WALL">
      <NameTxt>Mr. WALL</NameTxt>
      <P>I think also the Minister is wrong.  The farmers to whom Deputy Heffernan referred, were not paid.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelRichardHeffer" hpid="Mr. HEFFERNAN Mr. HEFFERNAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. HEFFERNAN</NameTxt>
      <P>The original claim would be a matter of about a quarter of a million.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. HOGAN Mr. HOGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. HOGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>Unfortunately, earlier in the discussion the Leas-Cheann Comhairle ruled this matter out of order, and I was not able to go into it.</P>
      <P>Vote put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>Resolution ordered to be reported.</P>
      <P>The Dáil went out of Committee.</P>
      <P>Resolution reported.</P>
      <P>Question: &ldquo;That the Dáil agrees with the Committee in the Resolution&rdquo;&mdash;put and agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="IN COMMITTEE ON FINANCE. - SUPPLEMENTARY AND ADDITIONAL" RHead="ESTIMATES, 1926-27&mdash; Issue out of the Central Fund">
    <Title>IN COMMITTEE ON FINANCE. - SUPPLEMENTARY AND ADDITIONAL ESTIMATES, 1926-27&mdash;   Issue out of the Central Fund.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="ErnestBlythe" hpid="Mr. BLYTHE Mr. BLYTHE">
      <NameTxt>Mr. BLYTHE</NameTxt>
      <P>I move:&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Chun slanú do dhéanamh ar an soláthar a deonadh i gcóir seirbhísí <Col N="1968" /> na bliana dar críoch an 31adh lá dé Mhárta, 1927, go ndéontar suim £687,490 as an bPrímh-Chiste.</P>
    <P>That towards making good the supply granted for the services of the year ending on the 31st day of March, 1927, the sum of £687,490 be granted out of the Central Fund.</P>
    <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
    <P>Resolution ordered to be reported.</P>
    <P>The Dáil went out of Committee.</P>
    <P>Resolution reported.</P>
    <P>Question: &ldquo;That the Dáil agrees with the Committee in the Resolution,&rdquo; put and agreed to.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="IN COMMITTEE ON FINANCE. - CENTRAL" RHead="FUND BILL, 1927.&mdash;FIRST STAGE">
    <Title>IN COMMITTEE ON FINANCE. - CENTRAL FUND BILL, 1927.&mdash;FIRST STAGE.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="ErnestBlythe" hpid="Mr. BLYTHE Mr. BLYTHE">
      <NameTxt>Mr. BLYTHE</NameTxt>
      <P>I move:</P>
      <P>&ldquo;That leave be given to introduce a Bill entitled an Act to apply certain sums out of the Central Fund to the service of the years ending on the thirty-first day of March, one thousand nine hundred and twenty-seven and one thousand nine hundred and twenty-eight.&rdquo;</P>
      <P>Leave granted.</P>
      <P>Second Stage ordered for Wednesday, 16th March.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="IN COMMITTEE ON FINANCE. - DUBLIN UNITED TRAMWAYS (LUCAN ELECTRIC" RHead="RAILWAYS) BILL, 1927&mdash;REPORT FROM THE JOINT COMMITTEE">
    <Title>IN COMMITTEE ON FINANCE. - DUBLIN UNITED TRAMWAYS (LUCAN ELECTRIC RAILWAYS) BILL, 1927&mdash;REPORT FROM THE JOINT COMMITTEE.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>The following report has been received:</P>
      <P>The Joint Committee on the Dublin United Tramways (Lucan Electric Railways) Bill, 1927 report that for the convenience of the parties they have adjourned from to-day till Wednesday, 23rd March, at 11 o'clock.</P>
      <P>Ordered: &ldquo;That the Report do lie upon the Table.&rdquo;</P>
      <P>The Dáil adjourned at 9.20 p.m. until 11 a.m. on Wednesday, 16th March.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="WA" LHead="WRITTEN ANSWER. - THE" RHead="DE CLIFFORD ESTATE">
    <Title>WRITTEN ANSWER. - THE DE CLIFFORD ESTATE.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="MartinMNally" hpid="Mr. MARTIN M. NALLY Mr. MARTIN M. NALLY">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MARTIN M. NALLY</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Lands and Agriculture if he is aware that Patrick Prendergast, Mossbrook, Claremorris, County Mayo, paid a deposit of £85 to the late Congested Districts Board in respect of lands on the De Clifford Estate, Mossbrook, and that the Irish Land Commission requested the Department of Finance to refund the deposit, and if he will state the cause of delay in discharging <Col N="1865" /> the amount due to Mr. Prendergast.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. HOGAN Mr. HOGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. HOGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>Patrick Prendergast paid a sum of money to the late Congested Districts Board in respect of lands on the De Clifford Estate and has applied to the Land Commission for a refund.  The matter is under consideration, but the Commissioners have not yet applied to the Department of Finance for authority to make a refund.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
</Debate>