<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE Debate SYSTEM "../Debate.dtd"[]>
<Debate DocTitle="Seanad Debate" Day="Thu" Date="9" Month="Feb" Year="1995" Vol="141" No="16" DateIrish="Déardaoin, 9 Feabhra 1995" DateEnglish="Thursday, 9 February 1995" House="S" CommitteeEng="" CommitteeIr="" SubNameEng="" cnum="0">
  <MainHeading Type="Prelude" LHead="" RHead="">
    <Title>
    </Title>
    <P>
      <Col N="1785" /> Chuaigh an Cathaoirleach i gceannas ar 10.30 a.m.</P>
    <P Just="Center">
      <i>Paidir.</i>
    </P>
    <P Just="Center">
      <i>Prayer.</i>
    </P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Business" RHead="of Seanad">
    <Title>Business of Seanad.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFallon" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I have notice from Senator Ross that, on the motion for the Adjournment of the House today, he proposes to raise the following matter:</P>
      <P>The need for the Minister for Education to ensure that the examination papers for the junior certificate are printed in this country.</P>
      <P>I also received notice from Senator Rory Kiely of the following matter:</P>
      <P>The proposal by the Minister for Justice to dispense with the sittings of the Circuit Court in Rathkeale, County Limerick, and to transfer the entire list for their sittings to Limerick city.</P>
      <P>I have also received notice from Senator Wall of the following:</P>
      <P>The need for the Minister for Health to outline the funding, framework of operations and rules concerning the home-help scheme as operated by the health boards.</P>
      <P>I have also received notice from Senator Maloney of the following:</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The need for the Minister for Health to request the North-Western Health Board to cease the transfer of patients from St. Conal's Hospital to <Col N="1786" /> community based nursing units, which is against the wishes of the patients.</P>
    <P>I have also received notice from Senator Mooney of the following matter:</P>
    <P>The need for the Minister for Health to provide State funding for the North-West Hospice based in Sligo at the same level as other hospices.</P>
    <P>I have also received notice from Senator Daly of the following matter:</P>
    <P>The need for the Minister for Finance to outline the action he proposes to take to deal with the very serious flooding problems at Sixmilebridge. Ballyvaughan and Leadmore, County Clare; and if funding will be provided to deal with the flooding problems in these areas.</P>
    <P>I have also received notice from Senator McGennis of the following matter:</P>
    <P>The need for the Minister for Arts, Culture and the Gaeltacht to make a statement on the Government's proposals for the public acquisition of 170 acres of land in the Liffey Valley, Lucan; if a price has been agreed with the owners and the likely time scale for the land to come into public ownership.</P>
    <P>I have also received notice from Senator Fahey of the following matter:</P>
    <P>To ask the Minister for Education the plans she has for the introduction of the early retirement scheme for teachers as promised at teachers conferences in 1993.</P>
    <P>I have also received notice from Senator Neville of the following matter:</P>
    <P>The need for the Minister for Health to introduce measures to assist in the prevention and reduction in the levels of suicide.</P>
    <P>I regard the matters raised as suitable for discussion on the Adjournment.  I have selected Senator Ross' and Senator Kiely's matters and they will be taken today at the conclusion of business. <Col N="1787" /> The other Senators may give notice on another day of the matters they wish to raise.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Order of" RHead="Business">
    <Title>Order of Business.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="MauriceManning" hpid="Mr. Manning Mr. Manning">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Manning</NameTxt>
      <P>It is proposed to take Items 1, 2, and 3 today.  On Item 1, it was proposed that there would just be one spokesperson per group with five minutes each.  Having discussed this with the Leader of the Opposition, I now propose eight minutes per group to be divided as the group wishes.  The Tánaiste will be here to contribute to this discussion.</P>
      <P>On Item 2, the Family Law Bill, I had not proposed any limits on speeches but perhaps we can talk to the Whips about that and agree half an hour per speaker. It is flexible at present as it is Second Stage of a Bill.  On the statements on the meningitis outbreak.  I am suggesting not more than ten minutes per speaker. There will be a sos.</P>
      <P>We hope to take shortly the Civil Legal Aid Bill which is a Seanad Bill. The Taoiseach will be here this day week to introduce the lifting of the emergency regulation.  On the question of flooding which was raised by a number of Senators last week, Senator Finneran in particular, I am proposing that we have a full debate on that next Thursday and attempt to look at some of the deeper causes of the recent spates of flooding.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GVWright" hpid="Mr. Wright Mr. Wright">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Wright</NameTxt>
      <P>As the Leader outlined, several Senators wished to contribute on Item 1 but we have come to an arrangement to share the eight minutes within the group.  I note what the Leader said about next Wednesday.  On the Northern Ireland issue, I take it that when the frame work document is produced this House will be afforded the opportunity of discussing it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Finally, in the interest of transparency and openness, if any future Minister intends to leak information, may I suggest <Col N="1788" /> that the Seanad would be the ideal forum?</P>
    <Speaker pid="DavidNorris" hpid="Mr. Norris Mr. Norris">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norris</NameTxt>
      <P>Hear.  Hear.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GVWright" hpid="Mr. Wright Mr. Wright">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Wright</NameTxt>
      <P>This party would make itself available at any time.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeOToole" hpid="Mr. O'Toole Mr. O'Toole">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Toole</NameTxt>
      <P>To take up that point.  I want to bring to the Leader's attention my concern that in my newspaper yesterday morning there were two, what appeared to be, typographical errors from the Budget Statement of yesterday afternoon.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFallon" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>We are not discussing the budget.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeOToole" hpid="Mr. O'Toole Mr. O'Toole">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Toole</NameTxt>
      <P>Perhaps a little more care could be taken on those issues.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMagner" hpid="Mr. Magner Mr. Magner">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Magner</NameTxt>
      <P>We apologise on behalf of the Government.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeOToole" hpid="Mr. O'Toole Mr. O'Toole">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Toole</NameTxt>
      <P>I want to refer to the debate on Northern Ireland.  We have spoken about this and the Leader indicated last week that he believed a debate before the framework document issued might not be helpful.  I am not sure I fully go along with that.  Much of this has to do with time.  The framework document could be delayed.  There is no doubt that each discussion that takes place in this House and everywhere else on the position of the ceasefire, developments and so on, brings all of us a little further down the road of understanding and hearing both points of view.  There should be debates on a regular basis, and that was Senator Manning's opinion when in Opposition.  If one had a debate every two months it would not happen at a time which might embarrass someone, either before or after the framework document, but it would be part of the normal process of discussion.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFallon" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I appeal to Senators not to make speeches.  I understand you have to make a brief introductory comment to the Leader, but we are <Col N="1789" /> prolonging the Order of Business by making unnecessary speeches.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnDardis" hpid="Mr. Dardis Mr. Dardis">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dardis</NameTxt>
      <P>Were you anticipating what I was going to say?  I ask the Leader if there will be a budget speech next year on the basis that it now seems to be surplus to requirements?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFallon" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>That is not a point on the Order of Business.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnDardis" hpid="Mr. Dardis Mr. Dardis">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dardis</NameTxt>
      <P>It was a question.  As regards Item 1 on the Order of Business, is the Leader proposing that each group will take its eight minutes in a block?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MauriceManning" hpid="Mr. Manning Mr. Manning">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Manning</NameTxt>
      <P>No, it will go from one side of the House to the other.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnDardis" hpid="Mr. Dardis Mr. Dardis">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dardis</NameTxt>
      <P>As regards Item 3, statements on the meningitis outbreak, I am pleased it is on the Order Paper because it is an important matter.  However, the Leader should ensure that we are given adequate notice of when such items will be put on the Order Paper because it was late when we were told about it.  I assume there will be a full debate next week on Item 6, which relates to the emergency legislation.  It is desirable for the Leader to give advance notice of what will happen the following week and I thank him for that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrankFahey" hpid="Mr. Fahey Mr. Fahey">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Fahey</NameTxt>
      <P>I ask the Leader if it will be possible to make a statement today on the flooding problem because yesterday's Budget Statement suggests that farmers will not get any money to alleviate the problem.  Compensation is one thing, but money must be provided to alleviate the same problems occurring next year in Galway.  Many householders whose houses have been flooded &mdash; and I am sure many people saw it on television during the past few days &mdash; cannot get insurance.  It appears they are not included in the compensation package announced in the budget.  I ask the Leader if it will be possible to make a statement today clarifying those matters because many <Col N="1790" /> householders and farmers throughout the country, and especially in Galway, are discontented and frustrated.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryHenry" hpid="Dr. Henry Dr. Henry">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Henry</NameTxt>
      <P>Northern Ireland has already been mentioned and it is fair to say that we all recognise how important economic backup is to the peace initiative. I ask the Leader to ascertain what has happened to INTERREG II monies from the European Union.  This is the inter-regional fund which allows money to be used for cross-Border community initiatives.  I have been contacted by several groups of people who are trying to make cross-Border initiatives and to get information, but it is impossible to find out what will happen.  The money from INTERREG I ran out some months ago.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PaschalMooney" hpid="Mr. Mooney Mr. Mooney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Mooney</NameTxt>
      <P>I thought Senator Henry was going to appropriate some of the INTERREG money to Dublin, but I am glad she said it was for people in the Border counties.  I am sure the Leader will have the same information as I have on that matter.</P>
      <P>As a student of constitutional politics &mdash; I do not wish to labour the point, and excuse the pun &mdash; does the Leader not think that the events of the last two days in relation to the budget have been extraordinary?  As someone who grew up accepting that leaks were followed by resignations, and we remember the famous incident of the Chancellor of the Exchequer&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFallon" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>That is not relevant to this House or to the Order of Business.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PaschalMooney" hpid="Mr. Mooney Mr. Mooney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Mooney</NameTxt>
      <P>I ask the Leader to comment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFallon" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I am sure he will reply.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PaschalMooney" hpid="Mr. Mooney Mr. Mooney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Mooney</NameTxt>
      <P>As an ordinary citizen, rather than a Senator.  I am taken aback by the events of the last few days and I am anxious to know the Leader's view. I am sure that is a legitimate question.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="1791" /> Of more concern to me is the fact that the Holocaust will be disposed of in eight minutes.  I applaud my colleague, Senator Norris, who initiated this debate, which was agreed by the Leader.  As someone who has walked through some of the gas chambers of Europe, I am disappointed that the House should dispose of this matter in eight minutes.</P>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFallon" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>The Leader said that was arranged by agreement with the House.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PaschalMooney" hpid="Mr. Mooney Mr. Mooney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Mooney</NameTxt>
      <P>I am not casting aspersions&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFallon" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Thank you.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PaschalMooney" hpid="Mr. Mooney Mr. Mooney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Mooney</NameTxt>
      <P>&mdash;&mdash;but as you more than anyone are aware, a Chathaoirligh, the business of the House is set by the Leader.  Ultimately whether there is agreement or not the Leader decides as he represents the Government.  I raise this point because I feel strongly about it.  This is penny pinching but then again, we have been living in a culture of penny pinching for the last 48 hours.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelMulcahyFF" hpid="Mr. Mulcahy Mr. Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Mulcahy</NameTxt>
      <P>I ask the Leader to make time available to discuss the content and implications of the President's address a week ago, &ldquo;Cherishing the Irish Diaspora&rdquo;.  We should consider this seriously because when the President addresses the Oireachtas she does so by virtue of a constitutional provision. It is not good enough to let such an address go unnoticed and undebated especially since all of us have relatives in different countries.</P>
      <P>The President's speech was very interesting and if it falls on deaf ears here, her constitutional initiative will not have achieved the full success it could.  Aside from any debate we may have on legislation to change the Constitution which will affect this House, we should make time available to discuss that address.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1792" />
    <Speaker pid="SeanFallon" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>That would seem to be suitable for a Private Members' Time motion and you might discuss that with your group, Senator Mulcahy.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelFinneranFF" hpid="Mr. Finneran Mr. Finneran">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Finneran</NameTxt>
      <P>I welcome the debate on meningitis.  It is a matter of major public concern at this time.  However I am disappointed at the downgrading of the debate on flooding.  This issue was raised here three weeks ago by myself and others and the issue of Auschwitz was raised last week.  It appears the debate on Auschwitz has taken precedence over the debate on flooding.  In no way do I want to&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFallon" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>You are making a speech, Senator.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelFinneranFF" hpid="Mr. Finneran Mr. Finneran">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Finneran</NameTxt>
      <P>I wish to ask the Leader why the debate on flooding was put back to next week.  The events at Auschwitz happened 50 years ago and while it was a terrible event, part of the Holocaust&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFallon" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>You are definitely making a speech at this stage.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelFinneranFF" hpid="Mr. Finneran Mr. Finneran">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Finneran</NameTxt>
      <P>I believe there is a reason &mdash; which is not being given to this House, that the flooding debate is not being taken today.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFallon" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator Finneran, please put your question to the Leader.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelFinneranFF" hpid="Mr. Finneran Mr. Finneran">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Finneran</NameTxt>
      <P>I believe the Government parties are pandering to the Independents.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFallon" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator Finneran, please stop.  You have had a good innings.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeSherlock" hpid="Mr. Sherlock Mr. Sherlock">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Sherlock</NameTxt>
      <P>Respect the Chair.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelFinneranFF" hpid="Mr. Finneran Mr. Finneran">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Finneran</NameTxt>
      <P>They have brought forward the debate although it is not urgent.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFallon" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator Finneran, you are making a speech.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1793" />
    <Speaker pid="MauriceManning" hpid="Mr. Manning Mr. Manning">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Manning</NameTxt>
      <P>On a point of order, I resent bitterly a suggestion that a discussion on Auschwitz is pandering to anyone.  It is a proper subject for debate. The suggestion is outrageous.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelFinneranFF" hpid="Mr. Finneran Mr. Finneran">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Finneran</NameTxt>
      <P>The Government parties are pandering to the Independents.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFallon" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator Finneran, I ask you to resume your seat.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MauriceManning" hpid="Mr. Manning Mr. Manning">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Manning</NameTxt>
      <P>That was a disgraceful contribution.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DonnieCassidyFF" hpid="Mr. Cassidy Mr. Cassidy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cassidy</NameTxt>
      <P>That is the Leader's opinion.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidNorris" hpid="Mr. Norris Mr. Norris">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norris</NameTxt>
      <P>I was going to begin with a lighthearted remark but I do not think in the circumstances&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFallon" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I wish you would</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidNorris" hpid="Mr. Norris Mr. Norris">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norris</NameTxt>
      <P>I was going to say I was glad you noticed my shy and shrinking signal to ask to contribute on the Order of Business.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFallon" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator Norris, I will always notice you.  I had your name on my list.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidNorris" hpid="Mr. Norris Mr. Norris">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norris</NameTxt>
      <P>I felt like Chesterton's definition of an oxymoron: &ldquo;Truth standing on its head to attract attention&rdquo;.</P>
      <P>I wish to distance myself from the atmosphere which erupted here some moments ago.  It was most unseemly, mean-spirited and wrong.  The remarks of two of my colleagues, although they appear to support my position, are not particularly welcome because they have misunderstood completely the position on the statements on Auschwitz.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFallon" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator Norris, you are making a speech.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidNorris" hpid="Mr. Norris Mr. Norris">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norris</NameTxt>
      <P>Perhaps the Leader could confirm that it was intended to be a dignified commemoration of a world tragedy so that all sides of the House <Col N="1794" /> could collaborate in marking in a dignified sense something of which we as human beings are all ashamed.  I agree with Senator Mulcahy that the President's address is worthy of analysis by this House.  If he or his party should place such a motion on the Order Paper I will be happy to speak on it.</P>
      <P>Finally, I wish to offer a friendly warning to the Leader of the House that he should not take the newspapers too seriously.  They have referred to the Independent Whip.  My friend and colleague, Senator O'Toole, is a modest and unassuming man&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnDardis" hpid="Mr. Dardis Mr. Dardis">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dardis</NameTxt>
      <P>Withdraw that remark.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidNorris" hpid="Mr. Norris Mr. Norris">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norris</NameTxt>
      <P>He knows that he is not a Whip and that we are Independents.  I, in particular, have no party affiliations and nobody can deliver my vote&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFallon" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>This is not appropriate to the Order of Business; they are private arrangements.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidNorris" hpid="Mr. Norris Mr. Norris">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norris</NameTxt>
      <P>I intend to vote on principle as an Independent.  I look forward to being placed in the same position as under the previous Government where I supported it on the majority of occasions.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFallon" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator Norris, you are making a speech.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidNorris" hpid="Mr. Norris Mr. Norris">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norris</NameTxt>
      <P>However, I am an Independent.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFallon" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Senators should direct their queries to the Leader of the House and refrain from making speeches.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MickLanigan" hpid="Mr. Lanigan Mr. Lanigan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lanigan</NameTxt>
      <P>I agree that we should have a debate on flooding as soon as possible.  We should not get caught up this morning in comparing the need for a debate on flooding with the desperate need for statements on Auschwitz.  It is an insult to the House to compare the two.  While there are problems with flooding, to compare what happened in <Col N="1795" /> Auschwitz with such problems is a disgrace.</P>
      <P>We should have a debate on the budgetary implications for people who have suffered as a result of flooding. People in the farming community should be compensated in some way for their losses.  However, we should not forget that businesses in urban areas have been wiped out, or virtually wiped out, because of flooding and we must address that aspect in addition to the implications of flooding for the farming community.  There should be balance; urban dwellers have an equal right to compensation.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFallon" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>The Senator is making a speech.  Ask a question of the Leader.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MickLanigan" hpid="Mr. Lanigan Mr. Lanigan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lanigan</NameTxt>
      <P>I seek an early debate on the flooding issue.  The second item I wish to mention is a matter of a major importance and arises from the Budget Statement yesterday.  I ask the Leader of the House to have an early debate on overseas aid.  The budget provides for changes which could have major positive implications as a result of tax concessions for donations made to specified aid agencies.  The difficulty I envisage is that the specified aid agencies could become political in a certain sense.  The Minister for Health in Rwanda was here yesterday and&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFallon" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator Lanigan, you are going on at length on this issue. I am sure the Leader will take it on board.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MickLanigan" hpid="Mr. Lanigan Mr. Lanigan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lanigan</NameTxt>
      <P>I ask the Leader to have a debate on this issue as a matter of urgency because aid is one of the most political issues in the world.  It has overtaken arms in importance and the political application of aid throughout the world is a matter we should discuss.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DickRoche" hpid="Mr. Roche Mr. Roche">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Roche</NameTxt>
      <P>I welcome the debate on Auschwitz.  It is important that at regular intervals democratic institutions <Col N="1796" /> mark the worst horror that one section of the human race has ever inflicted upon another.  The debate is timely.  In order to avoid the type of squabbling we have witnessed, would it be possible for the House to meet more regularly? Meeting for one day this week and one and a half days last week is bound to cause scheduling problems.  If we agreed to more regular meetings such unwelcome comparisions would not be made.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryKelly" hpid="Ms Kelly Ms Kelly">
      <NameTxt>Ms Kelly</NameTxt>
      <P>Nineteen ninety four was the Year of the Family and we let it pass without a debate on the family.  In view of the commitment to the family expressed in the budget I ask the Leader to hold a debate on the family in Irish society.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RoryKiely" hpid="Mr. R. Kiely Mr. R. Kiely">
      <NameTxt>Mr. R. Kiely</NameTxt>
      <P>I ask for a debate on flooding as I have received inquiries from my constituents on this matter. Will the Leader of the House indicate when such a debate will take place?  I agree with Senator Mooney that after the serious and damaging leak yesterday resignations should follow.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MauriceManning" hpid="Mr. Manning Mr. Manning">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Manning</NameTxt>
      <P>I agree with Senator Wright that a debate on Northern Ireland should wait until the framework document's is published, but there will be a debate very soon after that.  We will consider Senator O'Toole's point regarding ongoing debates on Northern Ireland in the next couple of weeks to see if something can be done to make that possible.</P>
      <P>Senator Dardis raised the point of the late notice being given for statements to be made on the meningitis issue.  The request was raised in the House last Thursday.  I made immediate attempts to have a debate, but I only got word last Monday that it was possible, and I let Members know as quickly as possible about it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The question of flooding has been raised by a number of Members.  The reason the debate is not taking place today is that the two Ministers most directly involved are on full duty in the other House because of the budget.  It <Col N="1797" /> will take place next Thursday I indicated, when this matter was first raised, that perhaps the most useful contribution we could make is not to hold a kind of fire fighting debate, but to have a deeper look at the entire problem.  We will have a chance to do this next week and I will not be imposing a time limit, within reason, on this debate.</P>
    <P>Senator Mooney raised a number of questions; perhaps he and Senator Finneran might talk to each other about their priorities on this matters.  We will try to be as flexible as we can on Auschwitz but, as has been stated, it was intended as a simple statement from all sides of the House to commemorate the horrors of that epoch.  The answer to the Senator's other question is yes.</P>
    <P>Senator Mulcahy mentioned the President's address last week.  As the Cathaoirleach said if the Senator wishes to devote Private Members' time to the matter I have no objection.  However, at present I have not intention of making time available.  I thought the issue was well ventilated last week; we may find some other way to proceed in a few weeks or months.</P>
    <P>Regarding the issue of overseas aid raised by Senator Lanigan, there is an intention, perhaps even next week, to have a discussion on this issue.  That will be proceeded with speedily.  I agree with Senator Roche that the House should and will meet more often but I would remind him that this is the first year in which the House has sat during budget week for quite some time.</P>
    <Speaker pid="DonnieCassidyFF" hpid="Mr. Cassidy Mr. Cassidy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cassidy</NameTxt>
      <P>First time in the Senator's time.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MickLanigan" hpid="Mr. Lanigan Mr. Lanigan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lanigan</NameTxt>
      <P>As Leader of the House.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MauriceManning" hpid="Mr. Manning Mr. Manning">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Manning</NameTxt>
      <P>However, I take the Senator's point and the House will meet as often as he wishes.  Senator's Kelly's suggestion that we have a debate on the family in Irish society is worthwhile and we will talk about it later.</P>
      <P>Order of Business agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Anniversary of Auschwitz Liberation:" RHead="Statements">
    <Title>Anniversary of Auschwitz Liberation: Statements.</Title>
    <Col N="1798" />
    <Speaker pid="SeanFallon" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I understand that there is a vote in the Dáil and the Tánaiste and Minister for Foreign Affairs will attend the House shortly.</P>
      <P>Before we proceed, I welcome the Acting Rabbi to the Dublin community, Mr. Vivian Silverman, Mr. Gershon Kedar, from the Embassy of Israel, and an old friend, Professor Jim Dooge, former Cathaoirleach, Leader of the House and Minister for Foreign Affairs from the House.  All three are very welcome.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MauriceManning" hpid="Mr. Manning Mr. Manning">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Manning</NameTxt>
      <P>I cede the floor to Senator Norris.  The idea of these statements was his, so perhaps he might lead the debate.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFallon" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Is that agreed? Agreed.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidNorris" hpid="Mr. Norris Mr. Norris">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norris</NameTxt>
      <P>I thank Senator Manning for his characteristic courtesy.  I had anticipated five minutes, and if there is time left over, perhaps I could share it with my colleague, Senator O'Toole.</P>
      <P>I am most grateful that the Leader of the House, Senator Manning, has acted so promptly and appropriately on my suggestion last week that this House should commemorate the fiftieth anniversary of the liberation of the concentration camp at Auschwitz.  Members of the Seanad frequently stand in tribute to the memory of relatives or former Members of the House.  Many of those are unknown to the current membership or known only by reputation.  Likewise, few if any of us can claim to have known personally any of the individuals who died in the gas chambers at Auschwitz, although some of us have had the privilege of meeting survivors of that terrible place.  It is by extension of this feeling of solidarity that we claim the right here today to honour the victims of Nazi tyranny.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="1799" /> There is nothing new in the tragic record of human history about murder of torture for reasons of religious, political or personal hatred.  What makes Auschwitz different is the clinical efficiency of its operation and the application of modern technology to the trade of torture and murder.  In addition, the sheer scale of the Holocaust sets it apart.</P>
    <P>Moreover, we as a people who are overwhelmingly although not totally Christian, at least by cultural descent, must acknowledge the part played, wittingly or unwittingly by the Christian tradition in the destruction of the Jews. Hitler was no historical accident.  He and his henchmen were the inevitable byproduct of 19 centuries of anti-Semitic propaganda and practice by the Christian Churches.  This was a point clearly and movingly acknowledged by that most sainly of men, the late Pope John XXIII.</P>
    <P>Nor did Ireland at that time cover itself in glory.  Acting on the advice of our diplomats in Berlin, reinforced by the anti-Semitic Prejudice dormant within our own culture, most of those few Jews who attempted to find sanctuary here found our otherwise hospitable doors closed firmly against them.  It is ironic that the National Library, which is next door to this building, should benefit so wonderfully from the generosity of the late Paul Leon, a friend of James Joyce.  The Leon collection of important literary material was extended a welcome which would not in the circumstances of the last war have included its benefactor.  I was interested, however, to learn recently that the British wartime leader, Winston Churchill, had actually ordered the bombing of the railway terminal at Auschwitz but his orders were secretly frustrated by anonymous bureaucrats.</P>
    <P>Few indeed in the international community held out the hand of humanity and friendship to the beleaguered Jews of Europe.  Of those few one in particular deserves our gratitude.  It is appropriate at this time that we should <Col N="1800" /> remember the name of Raoul Wallenberg, who, unarmed and defenceless, protected only by the force of his moral authority, snatched from the jaws of the Gestapo so many of the Jews of Hungary, only to be allowed by the Allies to disappear himself into the Soviet gulag at the end of the war where he may still linger to this day.</P>
    <P>It is important that we recognise and honour the principal targets of Nazi oppression.  This is particularly true in light of the disgraceful attitude of the Polish authorities who attempted to delete all specific reference to the fate of the Jews from the recent commemoration at Auschwitz.  It is very noticeable that not alone do certain elements wish to dilute the signigficance of the Jewish tragedy in the Holocaust, but some people also wished to obliterate from the record the fact that other groups were also targeted.  In particular, it is important that we remember the handicapped, the gypsies and the gay community.</P>
    <P>I feel very personally a commitment to the memory of those many thousands of gay people mutilated, medically experimented upon and murdered by the Nazis with the silent connivance of civilised Europe.  It is estimated that up to 500,000 gay people were destroyed as a specific arm of Nazi policy.  It is convenient to forget that parallel with the racial hygiene laws under which the Jews were persecute, Himmler also established sexual hygiene laws under which gay people where targeted and exterminated.  Gay people were the first into the concentration camps, the first medically experimented upon and the first murdered.  They were lower even than the Jews in the camp hierarchy. Just as the badge of the Jews was the Star of David, the pink triangle was the emblem for gay men.</P>
    <P>I wish to quote from the memoirs of Rudolph Hess, the commandant of Auschwitz:</P>
    <P>Whenever they found an opportunity they would fall into one another's arms.  Even when physically <Col N="1801" /> in a very bad way, they would continue to indulge in their vice.  They were easy enough to pick out.  Their soft and girlish affectations and fastidiousness, their sickly sweet manner of speech and their altogether too affectionate deportment towards their fellows distinguished them.</P>
    <P>Because they could not or would not give up their vice, they knew that they would never be set free.  The effect of this psychological burden, on men whose natures were for the most part delicate and sensitive, was to accelerate their physical collapse.</P>
    <P>Should one of them lose his &ldquo;friend&rdquo; through sickness, or perhaps death, then the end could at once be foreseen.  Many would commit suicide. To such natures, in such circumstances, the &ldquo;friend&rdquo; meant everything. There were many instances of &ldquo;friends&rdquo; committing suicide together.</P>
    <P>I doubt if even the great satirist Jonathan Swift could have conceived a greater irony.  That a mass murderer should reproach his victims with accusations of affection, love, gentleness, loyalty, devotion unto death is surely an unexpected and unintended tribute to the humanity of the homosexual victims of Nazi tyranny.</P>
    <P>I recall 15 years ago, at an international conference in Torino, Italy, speaking with members of the German delegation and asking them about the gay survivors of the German camps and in particular whether legal action against the German Government had been contemplated.  The reply was chilling. I was told that some indeed had survived but the response of the then German authority was not alone not to compensate the victims but to return them to prison to finish the sentences of the Nazi courts.  Let us remember that the end of the Second World War was not, unfortunately, the end of all such prejudice.</P>
    <P>It is frequently said that we must never let such things happen again. These are comforting sentiments but <Col N="1802" /> quite misleading.  Such things continue to happen all over the world and our first duty to the memory of the victims of the Holocaust is to ensure that silence no longer conceals barbarity.  It is simply not acceptable that commercial firms throughout Europe, but most particularly in Britain, France and Germany, continue to supply military hardware, landmines and the instruments of torture to tyrants and dictators all over the globe.  These companies are our equivalent in the 1990s of I. G. Farben Krupps and the manufacturers of zyklon B gas.  Why has Pol Pot not been arraigned before an international tribunal? Why is it that a large number of European countries, together with, most disgracefully, Australia and until recently the United States of America, have continued to collaborate in ways that float not just morality but international law, with the genocide committed by the Indonesian dictatorship upon the people of East Timor?  Ireland, at least, has played some honourable role in this matter.</P>
    <P>Let us not be satisfied today with ritual condemnation.  Let us call for the establishment of a permanent international war crimes tribunal which will collect and evaluate evidence of crimes against humanity and before which criminals, such as those who have operated in Rwanda, Kampuchea, Indonesia and the former Yugoslavia, may be tried, convicted and sentenced.  Only thus can we be said fully to have honoured the dead.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JoeOToole" hpid="Mr. O'Toole Mr. O'Toole">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Toole</NameTxt>
      <P>I very much appreciate Senator Norris sharing his time on this matter, which is of great importance to him.  I wish to make four brief points. First, I was the organiser of Irish Solidarnose ten to 15 years ago and I supported Lech Walesa when he was being oppressed.  I have never been so deeply ashamed as I was over the last three weeks when Lech Walesa attempted to ignore the 1.2 million Jews who were killed at Auschwitz.  It was a shameful reflection on the support he received <Col N="1803" /> from the international community on many occasions over the past 30 years.</P>
      <P>Second, I was surprised that I could not find any other Member of the Oireachtas or elected public representative at the commemoration of the Holocaust in Dublin last week.  This saddened me considerably.  However, more than 50 per cent of the 500 or 600 people who were there were at most 22 years old.  It is encouraging that people of that age are aware of this tragedy and follow it through.</P>
      <P>Third, as a person who has put forward and supported Irish neutrality in international and global affairs, I have yet to find a way in which we can explain to our children and grandchildren why we stood by&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DanNeville" hpid="Mr. Neville Mr. Neville">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Neville</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeOToole" hpid="Mr. O'Toole Mr. O'Toole">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Toole</NameTxt>
      <P>&mdash;&mdash;when people such as Pol Pot murdered and slaughtered all around him.  How can we, in terms of the Second World War, still put forward as some emblem of virtue and consistency the fact that we stood idly by &mdash; neutrally, as it were &mdash; when genocide was being perpetrated on the Jewish people and other groups, particularly travellers, gypsies and the homosexual community in Europe?</P>
      <P>Finally, we should remember that this does not ever go away.  We should remember the number of survivors who could not face being reminded of these camps over the past two months; the people who are still suffering, the suicides of people who are trying to come to terms with what happened 50 years ago; the suicide in 1988 of Primo Levi, an intellectual and a writer, who more than any other, brought the camps vividly to our knowledge.  All these things should make us aware that this continues.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I have never been to Auschwitz, although I visited a number of the other camps, Buchenwald in particular.  A survivor of Buchenwald addressed the Dublin commemoration last week.  It is very hard to describe or articulate the <Col N="1804" /> feelings generated by walking though those camps.  It is a chilling experience for anybody who has been there.  The fact that there is a kind of neo-fascism developing in Europe at the moment is worrying and should be of concern to all of us who look at European affairs.  It is something which we need to watch and monitor at all times.</P>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFallon" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I welcome the Tánaiste and Minister for Foreign Affairs to the House and I now have the pleasure of calling him to speak.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DickSpring" hpid="The Tánaiste Dick Spring">
      <NameTxt>The Tánaiste</NameTxt>
      <P>Thank you, a Chathaoirligh, for your invitation and welcome.  I am very glad to participate in these statements.</P>
      <P>Last 27th of January marked the fiftieth anniversary of the liberation of the Nazi death camp known with infamy throughout the world as Auschwitz.  On that date in 1945 Russian troops entered the gate, mockingly decorated, as were all the entrance gates of concentration camps, with the motto <i>Arbeit Macht Frei</i>&mdash;&ldquo;Work Makes Free.&rdquo;</P>
      <P>The grim scene that confronted them on that January morning and which has haunted all civilised peoples ever since, was of barely recognisable human beings, sick, starving and traumatised beyond endurance.  The 7,000 or so inmates of Auschwitz who greeted their liberators that morning in January were the few who had survived man's greatest inhumanity to his fellow man.</P>
      <P>Never before or since in human history have the leaders of an advanced country set out to exterminate a section of their own citizens and those of other countries on such a vast industrial scale. Even today it is still difficult to come to terms with the enormity of this crime. The vast number of victims gives some measure of the almost unspeakable horror involved but figures alone can never convey a full understanding of the pain and suffering of those who died.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Auschwitz is the site of the largest cemetery in human history.  Of all the Nazi death camps, it was the most elaborate and notorious centre in their <Col N="1805" /> deranged scheme to exterminate European Jewry.  It was set-up in a remote region of Poland with the express purpose of killing people.  This it proceeded to do on an industrial scale with a frightening efficiency.  The gas chambers at Auschwitz and its associated camp at Birkenau were capable of gassing to death 60,000 people a day.  The five crematoria could render to ashes the bodies of 10,000 men, women and children on a daily basis.</P>
    <P>An estimated 1.5 million of the Holocaust's six million victims were murdered at Auschwitz.  Of those, 1.1 million were Jewish; the rest were from all parts of Nazi occupied Europe &mdash; including Poland, of course, Russia, France, Netherlands, Austria, Central and Eastern Europe murdered for their nationality, their race, their opposition to Nazism, their culture &mdash; gypsies, communists, priests and religious and homosexuals.</P>
    <P>Those not immediately consigned to the gas chambers were subjected to a regime of extreme privation, humiliation and contempt for human dignity. Perhaps most harrowing of all is the thought of the many thousands of Jewish children being done to death so cruelly.  Those whom every human society must cherish and nurture most of all were not to be spared from the Holocaust.  Nobel Peace Prize Laureate Elie Wiesel gave anguished expression to this sentiment at the recent anniversary commemorations at Auschwitz when he said, &ldquo;God of forgiveness, do not forgive these murderers of Jewish children here&rdquo;.</P>
    <P>The fiftieth anniversary of the liberation of Auschwitz is first and foremost an occasion to remember and to pay dignified homage to the victims.  It should also serve as a chilling reminder and warning of the need to address with unremitting vigour the sources of ethnic tension and hatred in the world.  Since the Second World War, considerable effort has been invested by the international community in the development of international standards on the protection of human rights and mechanisms <Col N="1806" /> for conflict prevention and resolution. While some progress has been achieved, the recent resurgence of racial and ethnic conflict in Europe and elsewhere is a stark reminder of the magnitude of the task that still confronts us.  We have witnessed with horror in the past few years the so-called &ldquo;ethnic cleansing&rdquo; of parts of former Yugoslavia and the tribal massacres of Rwanda.</P>
    <P>We must be vigilant and we all have to take on the responsibility, as Senator O'Toole said, in relation to the continuing threats of ethnic cleansing and genocide which are sadly still prevalent in the world in which we live.  A renewed determination to do all in our power to prevent a recurrence of such horrors is the very least that we owe to the memory of the victims of Auschwitz and the other death camps.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MauriceManning" hpid="Mr. Manning Mr. Manning">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Manning</NameTxt>
      <P>Today in a small and very humble way in this House we try to remember the horror of Auschwitz and the greater horror of which it was a part.  A number of things come to mind. Perhaps the first is the human memory of what happened, of the individuals, the families, the ordinary people, the indescribable horrors to which they were subject.  When talking before I came in here this morning to former Senator Jim Dooge, I was very moved by his descriptions of his visit to Auschwitz. What touched him most deeply was not the efficiency and the scale of Auschwitz, but the small things, the suitcases, the clothes of the children.  All this was done with systematic callousness and cruelty, but the ordinary things brought home most vividly the horror of what Auschwitz was.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The second point &mdash; and it is a point touched on by the Tánaiste &mdash; is the memory of how easily the fundamental strengths of parliamentary democracy can crumble in the face of tyranny.  It is a lesson to all of us that the values upon which our civilisation, our State and our parliamentary structure are based, especially the values of civil liberties and human rights, were so vulnerable, so unable to defend themselves in the <Col N="1807" /> face of fascism in the 1930s.  It is a reminder to us that democracy, if it is not constantly renewed, strengthened and reinvigorated, is something which may not be able to fight back in its own defence.  That is something we should never ever forget.</P>
    <P>In remembering Auschwitz and the Jewish Holocaust 50 years on, we are not this morning in this House engaged in any empty or self-righteous gesturing. We cannot, we will not, we must not diminish the horrific culpability of the Nazis, both leaders and led, but we should recognise that their crimes were human crimes whose genocidal anti-Semitism grew out of the civilisation we all shared in and that their crimes were facilitated by a passivity that stretched from Moscow to Washington.  The slogans of &ldquo;Nie Wieder&rdquo;&mdash;&ldquo;Never again&rdquo;&mdash; and &ldquo;We must not forget&rdquo; are not only essential to the future protection of the Jews and other vulnerable peoples, they have immediate and pressing implications.</P>
    <P>Defence of the human rights of every person and people, as laid out in the UN declaration, calls for vigilance and determined activity by citizens, Parliaments and Governments around the world.  This call we must apply first of all to ourselves as Irish citizens, Irish parliamentarians and as part of an Irish Government in defence of human rights at home and abroad.  Failure to respect the basic human rights of the different, the stranger, the refugee or the otherwise powerless has too often resulted in death and destruction.  Our own troubles have been a poignant, if limited, example of that.  Current experiences in Bosnia, Rwanda and East Timor, to cite three widely dispersed areas, show how far the &ldquo;Nie Wieder&rdquo; attitude to genocide is from fulfilment. Let us remember Auschwitz for the enormous tragedy that it was for the Jews and their companions and as a salutary reminder of our continuing temptation to denial and passivity in the face of contemporary, if smaller, imitations.</P>
    <Col N="1808" />
    <Speaker pid="DanNeville" hpid="Mr. Neville Mr. Neville">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Neville</NameTxt>
      <P>A Chathaoirligh, it is difficult to contribute to this debate.  It is difficult to express one's feelings about what happened at Auschwitz and the other concentration camps, the level of tragedy, the human suffering that the peoples who were annihilated in those camps felt.  I have read on several occasions the account of Dr. Nyiszli, who survived Auschwitz, and it is chilling. It is frightening that human beings could treat their fellow human beings in such a way.  We must never forget.  We must always remind future generations of what happened in Germany to ensure that it does not happen again, and there are signs that it has happened in other areas.  One only has to look at Bosnia and places like that to see how people are still suffering.</P>
      <P>I wish to quote from Dr. Nyiszli's book where he describes the opening of the gas chamber on one occasion when he was there.  He said:</P>
      <P>The bodies were not lying here and there throughout the room, but piled in a mass to the ceiling.  The reason for this was that the gas first inundated the lower layers of air, and rose but slowly towards the ceiling.  This forced the victims to trample one another in a frantic effort to escape the gas.  Yet a few feet higher up the gas reached them.  What a struggle for life there must have been!  Nevertheless it was merely a matter of two or three minutes' respite.  If they had been able to think about what they were doing, they would have realised they were trampling their own children, their wives, their relatives.  But they couldn't think.  Their gestures were no more than the reflexes of the instinct of self-preservation.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Senator O'Toole referred to a point I feel strongly about, which was the Irish position of neutrality during the Second World War while this was taking place. It is a blot on our record that we were neutral during those terrible events. Ireland should have taken a firm approach to the genocide and should have fought against these atrocities, <Col N="1809" /> against Hitler and what he represented. We should have been strongly on the side of the Allies during the war.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PaschalMooney" hpid="Mr. Mooney Mr. Mooney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Mooney</NameTxt>
      <P>I welcome the Chief Rabbi.  Through the representatives of the Jewish community I convey the good wishes of the Fianna Fáil Party and Members on this side of the House to the Jewish community in Ireland.</P>
      <P>This year is a painful reminder of the events of 1945 and before.  I am honoured to be allowed to participate in this commemoration.  I have walked through the gas chambers of Mauthausen, I have prayed at the memorial in Dachau and, as a member of a parliamentary delegation, I have been present at a wreath laying ceremony on behalf of this House in 1991 at the execution wall in Auschwitz.</P>
      <P>I agree with Senator O'Toole's condemnation of the Polish President's actions on behalf, presumably, of the Polish people, who, despite their own wartime sufferings, which I do not wish to diminish in any way, indulged in appalling anti-semitism that stretched beyond the gates of Auschwitz when survivors of the Holocaust were shot by poles when they were repatriated to their homes.  The rise of Fascism in Europe, and especially of anti-semitism in the former eastern bloc, is a cause of concern to us.  Although I still have the slogan we heard earlier, &ldquo;Never again&rdquo;, ringing in my ears from the death camp visitors' books, I cannot but cry in pain at the return of the Holocaust to former Yugoslavia and Rwanda, as referred to by the Tánaiste.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>So much has been written about the Holocaust that any words of mine would be inadequate to attempt to describe the indescribable.  The decision to destroy all the Jews of Nazi controlled Europe was discussed and finalised at a meeting summoned in december 1941 in the Wannsee suburb of Berlin.  Those invited to Wannsee were senior officials from all the German Ministries, including the Ministry of Justice and the Foreign Office.  The details of the conference were prepared by Adolf Eichmann, head of the special Jewish section of the SS.  This detail is from <Col N="1810" /> Martin Gilbert's book <i>Auschwitz and the Allies</i> and I refer to it because people do not realise sometimes that the machine of death was a human invention. Nothing had been there before; it was all created and put in place by human endeavour.  The killing machine was created by the minds of what might be otherwise described as good people.</P>
    <P>The question has often been asked why Auschwitz was not bombed.  The Jewish Agency had been asking for the bombing of Auschwitz.  Martin Gilbert devotes a great deal of his book to this matter and he refers to it in these terms:</P>
    <P>The test of the Allied response came in the summer of 1944, when the British and American policymakers were asked to bomb Auschwitz. At the time of this request the American Government possessed a great deal of information about Auschwitz, including both its location and its function, together with the technical ability to bomb both the railways lines leading to the camp and the gas chambers in the camp itself.  The British policymakers had, in addition, Churchill's personal authority to examine a bombing scheme with a view to positive action.  Yet even then, a few individuals scotched the Prime Minister's directive because, as one of them expressed it at the time, to send British pilots to carry it out would have then risked &ldquo;valuable&rdquo; lives.</P>
    <P>I put that on the record to assuage Senator Neville and others.  While I agree with the sentiments he expressed, we should not feel culpable that because of our neutrality we contributed the Holocaust.  The Allies, who knew about it for a long time, had the means to do something.</P>
    <P>In his book <i>The Abandonment of the Jews</i>, David S. Wyman, a Christian, says:</P>
    <P>The Holocaust was certainly a Jewish tragedy.  But it was not <i>only</i>a Jewish tragedy.  It was also a Christian tragedy, a tragedy for Western civilisation, and a tragedy for all humankind. The killing was done by people, to other people, while still other people stood by.  The perpetrators, <Col N="1811" /> where they were not actually Christians arose from a Christian culture. The bystanders most capable of helping were Christians.  The point should have been obvious.  Yet comparatively few American non-Jews recognised that the plight of the European Jews was their plight too.  Most were either unaware, did not care, or saw the European Jewish catastrophe as a Jewish problem, one for Jews to deal with.  That explains, in part, why the United States did so little to help.</P>
    <P>While I do not want to be a revisionist, I would like to address the controversy surrounding the role of Pope Pius XII during the war in the light of a recent programme on British television.  I am grateful to my colleague, Senator Lydon, for posing such questions in an article.  Ribbentrob, the German Foreign Minister, once declared: &ldquo;I know that we had protests from the Vatican, that we had a whole desk full of protests&rdquo;. A question asked in this article is:</P>
    <P>If Pius XII had protested, would Jewish lives had been saved?  It was official Nazi policy to answer with reprisals.  Prisoners came to dread such public statements.</P>
    <P>Holland was the glaring example. When the Dutch bishops issued a condemnation, all Jews who had become Catholics were seized and sent to Auschwitz.  Among them was the convert Edith Stein, Sister Benedicta of the Holy Cross in Carmel, later beatified by Pope John Paul II.</P>
    <P>I can only put in context this awful part of a previous generation, a legacy which is still with us today, by referring to the foremost writer on the Holocaust, Primo Levi, a man who survived Auschwitz but who many years later could no longer live with the awful reality of it.  It is important that we understand what it was about.  In his book <i>If this is a Man &mdash; The Truce</i>, he talks about how they were put into cattle trucks and about arriving at Auschwitz in early morning.</P>
    <P>The climax came suddenly.  The door opened with a crash, and the <Col N="1812" /> dark echoed with outlandish orders in that curt, barbaric barking of Germans in command which seems to give vent to a millennial anger.  A vast platform appeared before us, lit up by reflectors.  A little beyond it, a row of lorries.  Then everything was silent again.  Someone translated: we had to climb down with our luggage and deposit it alongside the train.  In a moment the platform was swarming with shadows.  But we were afraid to break that silence: everyone busied himself with his luggage, searched for someone else, called to somebody, but timidly, in a whisper.</P>
    <P>A dozen SS men stood around, legs akimbo, with an indifferent air.  At a certain moment they moved among us, and in a subdued tone of voice, with faces of stone, began to interrogate us rapidly, one by one, in bad Italian. They did not interrogate everybody, only a few: `How old? Healthy or ill?'  And on the basis of the reply they pointed in two different directions.</P>
    <P>Everything was as silent as an aquarium, or as in certain dream sequences.  We had expected something more apocalyptic: they seemed simple police agents.  It was disconcerting and disarming.  Someone dared to ask for his luggage:  They replied, `luggage afterwards'.  Someone else did not want to leave his wife: they said,`together again afterwards'. Many mothers did not want to be separated from their children: they said `good, good, stay with the child'. They behaved with the calm assurance of people doing their normal duty of every day.  But Renzo stayed an instant too long to say good-bye to Francesca, his fiancée, and with a single blow they knocked him to the ground.  It was their everyday duty.</P>
    <P>In less than ten minutes all the fit men had been collected together in a group.  What happened to the others, to the women, to the children, to the old men, we could establish neither then nor later: the night swallowed them up, purely and simply.  Today, however, we know that in that rapid and summary choice each one of us <Col N="1813" /> had been judged capable or not of working usefully for the Reich: we know that of our convoy no more than ninety-six men and twenty-nine women entered the respective camps of Monowitz-Buna and Birkenau, and that of all the others, more than five hundred in number, not one was living two days later.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMagner" hpid="Mr. Magner Mr. Magner">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Magner</NameTxt>
      <P>I wish to share my time with Senator O'Sullivan.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFallon" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Is that agreed? Agreed.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMagner" hpid="Mr. Magner Mr. Magner">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Magner</NameTxt>
      <P>It is fitting in one sense that the Public Gallery this morning should be full of children.  It is also fitting that we have represented here members of the Jewish community, not least my dear friend and colleague, the Minister for Equality and Law Reform, Deputy Taylor.</P>
      <P>I have never failed, either when reading about or watching films on the Holocaust, to feel dehumanised and ashamed.  We are all to blame, irrespective of revisionism.  It is only in the recent past that Churches and nations have shown the maturity to shoulder the blame.  It is an event that is impossible to comprehend.  I find it hard to comprehend even now.  When I was five years of age playing in the streets the representatives of a so-called civilised nation were putting children into furnaces.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I am grateful to a distinguished member of the Jewish community, Joe Briscoe, for giving me some idea of the scope of this event.  I did not know&mdash; few possibly do&mdash;that in Berlin only 17 children survived this horror.  Even as we speak about it, the scope of the horror is still there.  The name &ldquo;Auschwitz&rdquo; can raise the hair on the back of one's neck.  I hope it always does; the day it does not is the day it will happen again. Although one third of European Jewry survived the Holocaust, only 5,000 children survived.  Therefore, in a sense, all Jews living today are survivors.  When we pay this tribute in this House, we should have the mounds of ashes in Auschwitz at the forefront of our minds. <Col N="1814" /> We salute the victims and apologise to them today.</P>
    <P>Pastor Neumueller said in his famous quote:</P>
    <P>First they came for the Socialists, but I wasn't a Socialist and so I did not protest.  Then they came for the trade unionists, but I wasn't a trade unionist so I did not protest.  Then they came for the Jews, but I was not a Jew so I did not protest.  When they came for me there was nobody left to protest.</P>
    <P>We should put that quote into our minds and hearts.  We must ensure that whenever anti-semitism or discrimination of any sort raises its head, if we are not vigilant we will then contribute, even in the smallest way, to something that may again evolve into not a human tragedy but a systematised destruction of a race.  It is fitting that this State should entrust to a member of the Jewish community, in the person of Deputy Taylor, the responsibility of vindicating the rights of our minorities in his portfolio as Minister for Equality and Law Reform.  It is also fitting that the vindication of their rights should be reposed in him, something he so ably does in his daily work.</P>
    <P>It is difficult to convey in a few minutes the sense of horror I have always felt whenever I have watched old newsreels and the sight of that child in the Warsaw ghetto with his hands up wearing a cap&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    <Speaker pid="PaschalMooney" hpid="Mr. Mooney Mr. Mooney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Mooney</NameTxt>
      <P>He survived.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMagner" hpid="Mr. Magner Mr. Magner">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Magner</NameTxt>
      <P>When I was playing in the street children like him were being fed into a furnace by a so called civilised nation.  It is right and proper that we salute those who perished.  We should pledge ourselves that whenever we are called upon to make a stand on behalf of human rights, wherever it is, we make that stand in the knowledge that we cannot afford to do nothing.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JanOSullivan" hpid="Ms O'Sullivan Ms O'Sullivan">
      <NameTxt>Ms O'Sullivan</NameTxt>
      <P>In looking back 50 years later at the horrors of Auschwitz, it is a natural reaction for us as human beings to recoil in horror rather than <Col N="1815" /> face what happened.  We are also tempted to lay the blame on the barbarity of the perpetrators in a way that dehumanises them and in doing that exonerate our own humanity.  Instead, we must learn from history and build a world society in which such barbarity will not recur.  To do that we have to try in some way to understand man's inhumanity to his fellow being and how so-called ordinary decent people, living in the society of the time, could turn a blind eye to a regime that slaughtered so many of their fellow human beings.</P>
      <P>That society built up slowly.  This did not happen overnight; its support was built up gradually in the nation.  It started by offering people a hope and the prospect of a better standard for themselves and those they saw as their own people.  It offered them pride in their own identity and culture. However, gradually &mdash; it was only gradually &mdash; this was transformed to a downgrading and denial of the humanity of the cultures, and eventually the lives, of other people on the European and world stages.  One must remember that it did not happen as a sudden horror but gradually built up within the society of the time.  While having pride in our own culture and identity, we also have to respect that of others.  That is the lesson.  If we do not do that, then there is the danger that racism and fascism will strengthen again.  This could happen in our society as easily as anybody else's society.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Indeed, as other Senators have said, there is alarming evidence that the neofascists and the far right wing are currently building and strengthening in Europe, especially eastern Europe. Other Senators have also referred to the situation in the former Yugoslavia and others to East Timor and Africa.  This is built up at times as an anger against subgroups and other members of society, against immigrants in many European situations.  There is an anger being built up against other people rather than against the inequalities in society.  That has to be confronted.  We have to support opposition to fascism and racism, irrespective of wherever it <Col N="1816" /> breaks out.  This must be done not only in other societies, cultures and peoples, but also in ourselves and our own society.</P>
    <P>In marking the fiftieth anniversary of the liberation of Auschwitz with sadness and collective guilt, we should look into our own hearts and society, into societies around the world and support in whatever way we can opposition to any tendencies towards racism and fascism and any development of such regimes wherever they may occur.</P>
    <Speaker pid="CathyHonan" hpid="Ms Honan Ms Honan">
      <NameTxt>Ms Honan</NameTxt>
      <P>I wish to share my time with Senator Dardis.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RoryKiely" hpid="Acting Chairman (Mr. R. Kiely) Acting Chairman (Mr. R. Kiely)">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman (Mr. R. Kiely)</NameTxt>
      <P>Is that agreed?  Agreed.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="CathyHonan" hpid="Ms Honan Ms Honan">
      <NameTxt>Ms Honan</NameTxt>
      <P>I am glad to have the opportunity to speak on the fiftieth anniversary of the liberation of Auschwitz. We need constant reminders of what happened there to help to ensure it never happens again.  It has been said that the price of freedom is eternal vigilance. Tolerance, understanding of discrimination and anti-discrimination in any form must be worked at and cannot be taken for granted.  Many Senators referred today to the recent happenings in Bosnia, East Timor and Rwanda.  We cannot pretend that we do not know what is happening there and that we did not know what happened in Germany. We, as a nation, should be ashamed of ourselves.  Even if the Allies, as Senator Mooney said, knew and did nothing, that is no justification for us to say that we could not do anything.  People turned a blind eye to what was happening. Because it did not directly affect us, we ignored it.</P>
      <P>I visited Auschwitz in 1981.  I remember at the time wondering how anybody could imagine and understand the horrors and chilling events which occurred in this place.  It is an old army barracks but unless one knew or read of what had happened there, the enormity of the atrocities would be very difficult to comprehend.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>On the bus journey from Craców to Auschwitz I read an interview in a magazine with a woman, now living in <Col N="1817" /> England, who had survived Auschwitz. She was 15 years old when she was a prisoner there.  Reading that interview gave me an insight into what happened and what life in Auschwitz was like for the people who were prisoners there. Senator Manning mentioned his conversation with Professor Jim Dooge this morning during which Professor Dooge spoke about the cases and mounds of shoes, including children's shoes, and the mountains of human hair.  This helped to bring back to me the scale of what happened and to realise that we are talking about ordinary human beings like all of us here.  Looking at photographs as people were admitted and their dates and details helped to focus the mind on the fact that they were human beings.  It was not just a story about which we were reading or hearing, it was something that happened.</P>
    <P>I found it extremely difficult to imagine that the people carrying out these atrocities were supposed to be civilised.  They murdered and gassed children in the chambers during the day and went home to their own families at night.  I found that very chilling.  We say we are a civilised people and say we will never allow this to happen again but, we must remember that atrocities are happening in the world today.  What are we doing about them?  The woman who gave the interview in the magazine was Kitty Harte.  She visited Auschwitz after 35 years.  The pain of going back there was indescribable.  She and her mother survived Auschwitz and went to live in England with relatives.  The most difficult thing for her was that she was not allowed to talk about what happened. She believed the rest of the world did not want to know.  It is most important that the rest of the world knows what happened.  We must hear about these atrocities and listen and talk about what is happening in the rest of the world today.  That is the only way we will ever ensure that these atrocities will never happen again.</P>
    <P>At one time I thought world leaders, such as the President of the United States and the Prime Minister of Britain, should constantly visit places <Col N="1818" /> like Auschwitz to be reminded of what happened there.  I now realise that it is up to all ordinary people and to us who are privileged to be Members of this House to articulate about what happened there and to constantly remind ourselves of it.  I am grateful to Senator Norris for raising this issue.  I, too, was ashamed of the fracas which arose on the Order of Business.  The horrors of Auschwitz are of enormous importance and must be constantly raised and discussed.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JohnDardis" hpid="Mr. Dardis Mr. Dardis">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dardis</NameTxt>
      <P>I thank Senator Honan for giving me time to speak on this very important matter.  It is important that this House records events such as this. This was the worst atrocity in recorded human history and is likely, we hope, to remain so.  That is one of the messages for us.  At the moment we have witnesses to what happened there, but as time passes, the witnesses will die and then the only evidence will be on film. It is important that we continue to see on film what happened when and before the gates were opened and that we continually remind ourselves of what happened in Auschwitz and during the Holocaust.</P>
      <P>I am very pleased that there are representatives of the Jewish community here this morning.  I am also pleased that the Minister for Equality and Law Reform, Deputy Taylor, was here at the beginning of the debate as a representative of that community.  We have to accept that it was the Jewish community who bore the brunt of the Holocaust. Other groups also suffered, such as homosexuals and gypsies.</P>
      <P>What makes the Holocaust so difficult to comprehend is that these people were murdered not because they had committed atrocities but because of who and what they were.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>It has been said that this could not happen again.  It could and is happening. It is happening in Bosnia, East Timor and Rwanda and we were reminded of that this morning.  As far as possible it must not be allowed happen again.  The Nazis were the primary agents of the atrocity but the international community bore a responsibility in terms of <Col N="1819" /> knowing at the highest level what was taking place and appearing not to do anything about it.</P>
    <P>There is a message of hope that humanity existed even in the midst of such darkness.  There were people of outstanding humanity and talent, such as artists and musicians, who brought their culture with them, and survived in the face of such atrocity.  The most famous person who comes most readily to mind is Oskar Schindler.  I read the book about him but did not see the film. He was an example of humanity surviving that period.</P>
    <P>The lesson for Irish society is that we must be conscious of our responsibilities to minorities and to people who differ from us.  Perhaps we bear a certain guilt in how we receive people in this country who are fleeing from the type of atrocities which are occurring even today; perhaps our doors are not open wide enough to people who are trying to escape such atrocities.  This may be a lesson for us.  As Senator Manning said, freedom and democracy are very delicate flowers and we have a responsibility in this Parliament and as a democracy to ensure that the freedom and democracy we treasure continue and that we remind ourselves of what happened in Auschwitz and the Holocaust.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JoeSherlock" hpid="Senator Sherlock Senator Sherlock">
      <NameTxt>Senator Sherlock</NameTxt>
      <P>May I share my time with Senator Kelly?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Acting Chairman Acting Chairman">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman</NameTxt>
      <P>I may have a problem with that as each group has only eight minutes.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeSherlock" hpid="Senator Sherlock Senator Sherlock">
      <NameTxt>Senator Sherlock</NameTxt>
      <P>I welcome the opportunity to participate in the debate on the fiftieth anniversary of the liberation of Auschwitz.  One's first insight into the Holocaust was the film <i>The Nuremberg Trials</i> and the statement to the effect that what we thought was a passing phase became a way of life in Germany.  Some 57 years ago Ireland refused entry to Jewish refugees from Hitler's Germany on a regular basis.  In 1938 an official in the Department of Justice wrote an internal memorandum to the effect that it would be unwise to <Col N="1820" /> consider admitting refugees with Jewish blood.  When commemorating the liberation of Auschwitz we should also remember the part played by Ireland and other European democracies in the Holocaust, which is marked mainly by silence.</P>
      <P>Today we are commemorating the carefully executed extermination of around six million Jews, gypsies, gays, socialists and political dissidents.  The Holocaust was unique only in its ordered thoroughness.  It is just under a year ago that we witnessed live on our television screens the wholesale genocide in Rwanda.  Even as we debate the Holocaust, several minor attempts at genocide are taking place all over the world.  The Indonesians continue their reign of terror in East Timor.  Elsewhere wars, largely of ethnic origin, continue to rage.  Bosnia and Chechnya are two of the better known conflicts.  What we are commemorating today is the end of one chapter in a continuing story of ethnic, religious and political persecution. As Europeans, however, we ought to have a particular responsibility to remember the Holocaust and to ensure that it is not repeated.  We have a responsibility to ensure that pseudo-historians, like David Irving, who continue to maintain that the Holocaust never occurred, are denied a platform everywhere in Europe.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMagner" hpid="Mr. Magner Mr. Magner">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Magner</NameTxt>
      <P>Hear, hear.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeSherlock" hpid="Mr. Sherlock Mr. Sherlock">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Sherlock</NameTxt>
      <P>We also have a responsibility to fight racism and intolerance wherever we find it, and it is often closer than we think.  As we commemorate the Holocaust let us also remember the hundreds of thousands of gypsies who were murdered between 1938 and 1945.  They have become a footnote in the story of the Holocaust and, like other groups, many of the survivors have still received no compensation from the German Government. Throughout Europe they continue to be persecuted, whether as travellers in Ireland or romany gypsies in England and mainland Europe.  Until we have cleaned up our own act and ensured that no one in our own country is subject <Col N="1821" /> to persecution simply because of their race, religion or political affiliation, we will not be able to fully celebrate the end of the Holocaust.  In this regard I look forward to Ireland's ratification of the United Nations Convention against Torture and Racial Discrimination. That will be the best commemoration of the liberation of Auschwitz.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidNorris" hpid="Mr. Norris Mr. Norris">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norris</NameTxt>
      <P>I would like to raise a point of information which I think is historically important.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Acting Chairman Acting Chairman">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman</NameTxt>
      <P>I understand that we are taking statements and I do not think that there is a procedure for raising a point of information.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PaschalMooney" hpid="Mr. Mooney Mr. Mooney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Mooney</NameTxt>
      <P>It is a point of order.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidNorris" hpid="Mr. Norris Mr. Norris">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norris</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes, it is a point of order in that case.  The argument was made that the Vatican did not intervene because of the possibility of reprisals, as had apparently happened in the case of protests by the Dutch bishops.  It must be remembered that 49 people were sent to the camps as a result of that.  Balance that on the scale with six and a half million.  What reprisal was the Vatican afraid of?  This is part of a disinformation programme.  If you look at the names Edith Stein and Maximilian Kolbe that were mentioned, Edith Stein was Jewish and was betrayed by the mother superior of her own convent&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Acting Chairman Acting Chairman">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman</NameTxt>
      <P>The Senator mentioned on the Order of Business that it would be a dignified statement, so I would like it to be maintained that way.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidNorris" hpid="Mr. Norris Mr. Norris">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norris</NameTxt>
      <P>Dignified by truth and historical accuracy and not by disinformation, which is being systematically planned by the Vatican.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Acting Chairman Acting Chairman">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman</NameTxt>
      <P>The Senator made his statement already.  He cannot come in a second time.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GordonWilson" hpid="Mr. Wilson Mr. Wilson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Wilson</NameTxt>
      <P>I hope that the words I want to say on this particular subject do <Col N="1822" /> not get the better of me emotionally because I speak with great sadness in my heart when I think of Auschwitz, but not a little joy &mdash; for an odd reason. When I think of Auschwitz, I think of a young woman, Marie Wilson, who, with me, watching a BBC documentary programme on the Holocaust was deeply affected by the documentary's account of man's inhumanity to man.  I was touched by her compassion for people so remote from her world at 15 years of age.  I was further moved when, later, we found in her diary a note she wrote on that very evening saying that she was &ldquo;converted to Christianity&rdquo; because of watching that programme.  Little did we know then the fate that awaited her.</P>
      <P>Now, through her death and the sadness it has brought to our family, I feel a link with the millions of families destroyed by the horrors of the Holocaust. Reflecting on this, I am saddened to realise how slowly we learn from history, how easily man forgets or chooses to forget that hatred and violence serve no purpose.  It is right that 50 years later we remember those who died at Auschwitz and the other camps, but let us not forget those who survived.  Their witness, courage, determination and faith are an inspiring example of the nobility of the human spirit and its refusal to be bowed by evil.</P>
      <P>I think of the Dutch lady, Corrie Tembout, a Christian, incarcerated at Ravensbruck, where her sister died.  She survived and spent the rest of her life preaching forgiveness around the world. I think of a prayer found in the pocket of a dead child in Ravensbruck which read:</P>
      <P>O Lord, remember not only the men and women of goodwill, but also those of ill will.  But do not remember all of the suffering they have inflicted upon us.  Instead remember the fruits we have borne because of this suffering; our fellowship, our loyalty to one another, our humility, our courage, our generosity, the greatness of heart that has grown from this trouble. When our persecutors come to be judged by You, let all of these fruits that we have borne be their forgiveness.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="1823" /> It is not too late to learn from that suffering that life is a precious gift to be honoured with respect and compassion. Above all, this means that we must forgive those who killed.  I will not pretend that forgiveness is easy, nor that it eases grief, but anger and bitterness eat at the soul and can bring only more pain.  We have the opportunity now in this corner of God's garden to change a history of bloodshed.  Let us remember the past without rancour and redeem it by turning away wrath and reaching out to one another with love.  The highest tribute we can pay to the victims of Auschwitz is to resolve that such cruelty can never happen again.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Family Law Bill, 1994:" RHead="Second Stage">
    <Title>Family Law Bill, 1994: Second Stage.</Title>
    <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That the Bill be now read a Second Time.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="MervynTaylor" hpid="Minister for Equality and Law Reform (Mr. Taylor) Mervyn Taylor">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Equality and Law Reform (Mr. Taylor)</NameTxt>
      <P>The Family Law Bill is a very wide ranging measure.  It provides substantial power to the courts to deal with the financial consequences of marital breakdown in cases where a foreign decree of divorce is entitled to recognition in the State.  Those powers will, in substance, be the same as the powers in any legislation on domestic divorce were the people to vote &ldquo;yes&rdquo; in the forthcoming referendum on divorce. The powers include wide powers in relation to maintenance, inheritance and property generally, including the family home and pensions.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The Bill repeals, and re-enacts with amendments, provisions in the Judicial Separation and Family Law Reform Act.  The amendments include new provisions giving the courts power in separation proceedings to make orders in relation to pensions.  The Bill strengthens the law on maintenance generally, not just in the case of separation proceedings or where financial relief is sought after a foreign decree of divorce. There are comprehensive tax provisions in the Bill to ensure that where property is transferred by our courts between <Col N="1824" /> parties following a foreign divorce, those parties will be free of the range of tax measures which might otherwise apply to their situation.</P>
    <P>To safeguard and protect the institution of marriage, the age of marriage is being increased and there is provision for notice of marriage.  With a view to having clear and simple procedures in the law to enable persons to establish the validity of their marriage in the event of foreign decrees of divorce or separation being granted, the Bill provides for updating of the law in this area.  The social reporting role of health boards and welfare officers in family law proceedings in general is put on a statutory footing under special provisions in the Bill.</P>
    <P>Jurisdiction and proceedings for decree of nullity of marriage, at present confined to the High Court, is being given also to the Circuit Court.  The purpose is to bring that jurisdiction into line with the jurisdiction for separation proceedings, to improve access to the courts and to reduce costs.  The Circuit Court is also being empowered to make the ancillary orders in support of spouses where foreign decrees of divorce or separation are entitled to recognition in the State and to make any declarations in relation to the status of a person's marriage.</P>
    <P>The District and Circuit Courts will have jurisdiction to order maintenance by way of lump sums and secured payments. That jurisdiction is at present confined to the Circuit Court in separation proceedings only.  The District Court will have jurisdiction to make orders under the Family Home Protection Act, 1976, where the rateable valuation of the home is no more than £20. Jurisdiction is at present confined to the Circuit and High Courts.</P>
    <P>In bringing forward the Bill, I am indebted to a wealth of sources, not least the White Paper on Marital Breakdown. The Bill draws on the provisions of the Family Law (No. 1) Bill contained in that paper.  I should also mention the following reports of the Law <Col N="1825" /> Reform Commission on which the Bill is based: the report on the Age of Majority, Age for Marriage and some connected subjects and the report on Jurisdiction in Proceedings for Nullity of Marriage, Recognition of Foreign Nullity Decrees and the Hague Convention on Celebration and Recognition of the Validity of Marriages.  The list of reports would not be complete without mentioning also that account has been taken of the work of the Oireachtas Joint Committee on Marital Breakdown, the Combat Poverty Agency in their report on the Financial Consequences of Marital Breakdown and the work of the Second Commission on the Status of Women.</P>
    <P>The Bill as now framed does not empower the courts to deal with the financial consequences of a decree of nullity granted in the courts.  Those provisions were based largely on those contained in a paper prepared by the Attorney General in 1976 which took account of the laws in other jurisdictions and they were contained also in the 1992 White Paper on Marital Breakdown. However, in the light of further consideration and taking into account representations made to me about possible constitutional difficulties, I decided that the best course would be to delete those provisions and to deal with them in a separate Bill in due course.</P>
    <P>Senators may note that the heading to Part II of the Bill still retains a reference to nullity and that the side note to section 5 also makes a similar reference. Those references have been included in error because of an oversight at printing stage and I mention the matter to avoid any possible confusion for those looking at the text of the Bill for the first time.</P>
    <P>Turning now to specific provisions of the Bill, Senators will appreciate that in view of its size it would not be practicable for me to go through all of the Bill in detail at this stage.  I propose, therefore, to concentrate on the main provisions.</P>
    <P>Part I of the Bill contains provisions dealing with short title, commencement <Col N="1826" /> and interpretations.  Some of those definitions &mdash; for example, in relation to &ldquo;family home&rdquo;, &ldquo;conveyance&rdquo; and &ldquo;household chattels&rdquo;&mdash; are standard provisions in other family law legislation.</P>
    <P>Part II, which runs from sections 5 to 21, is concerned with the financial, property and other ancillary orders which the court is empowered to make in or after proceedings for judicial separation. Part II also re-enacts the substance of Part II of the Judicial Separation and Family Law Reform Act, 1989, which is being repealed by section 3, concerning the powers of courts to order financial support in the context of judicial separation. The purpose is to consolidate those provisions with new provisions in relation to life assurance and occupational pensions.</P>
    <P>The provisions in section 5 of the Bill deal with preliminary orders that may be dealt with by the court in proceedings for separation and allow the court, before deciding on an application for a decree of judicial separation, to make a barring order or protection order, custody order and orders for a protection of the family home and contents.</P>
    <P>Sections 6 and 7 are in one form or another concerned with the question of maintenance of a spouse and dependent children.  Section 6 allows the court to make interim maintenance or lump sum orders pending the determination of an application for a decree of judicial separation. Provision for interim lump sum payments is new and is intended to cover situations where there may be hardship or where immediate bills have to be paid by a spouse.  Section 7 provides for the making of orders for periodical payments, secured periodical payments and lump sums for the support of a spouse or dependent children. The lump sums may be ordered to be paid by instalments and to be secured.</P>
    <P>The provision in subsection (6) of section 7 is new.  It gives important powers to the courts in separation proceedings to order attachment of earnings at the same time as maintenance is ordered to be paid.  Before deciding on <Col N="1827" /> such an attachment of earnings order, the spouse who is to make the payments must be given an opportunity to make representations in relation to the matter. I am also, under section 42 of the Bill, extending those provisions to cases where maintenance is ordered in proceedings under the Guardianship of Infants Act, 1964, and the Family Law (Maintenance of Spouses and Children) Act, 1976.</P>
    <P>There are good and valid reasons for strengthening the law in these areas. The Combat Poverty Agency in their report on the financial consequences of marital breakdown highlighted the extent to which maintenance debtors default on payments ordered by the courts.  While there are cases where the debtor may due to a change in circumstances be unable to pay &mdash; and this is allowed for in legislation already by permitting variations of maintenance &mdash; there are many other cases where the debtor simply refuses to pay and this results in the dependent spouse having to pursue separate proceedings in the courts for enforcement of the maintenance. The agency found that where enforcement was ordered by way of attachment of earnings, it doubled the chances of payment.  Those facts cannot be ignored and I think that Senators will agree that the provisions I have made are warranted and overdue.</P>
    <P>Sections 8 and 9 are the provisions which allow the courts in separation proceedings to redistribute property as between spouses for the benefit of a spouse and any dependent children.  In substance, they repeat the provisions contained in the 1989 Act.  Section 8 provides that the court may make an order for the transfer of property from one spouse to the other or to any dependent child, an order for the settlement of property, an order to very for the benefit of the other spouse or a dependent child, or both, any ante-nuptial or post-nuptial settlement made on the spouses, or an order extinguishing or reducing the interest of either of the spouses under a settlement of property.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="1828" /> Section 9 deals with a number of orders which may be made in relation to the family home.  These may include orders in relation to the right of one spouse to occupy the family home to the exclusion of the other spouse, an order for the sale of the family home and for disposal of the proceeds of sale, and orders under existing statutes, including the Family Home Protection Act, 1976.</P>
    <P>Section 10 provides a new and very practical measure for the courts to deal with life assurance for dependent spouses and children.  It enables the courts in separation proceedings to make an order for the assignment, in whole or in part, of a spouse's interest in a life assurance policy in favour of the other spouse or a dependent child of the family, or an order requiring a spouse to take out a life assurance policy in favour of the other spouse or dependent children. These orders are designed to supplement or substitute for, where necessary, other orders in support of a dependent spouse and children.</P>
    <P>Sections 11 and 12 address the questions as to what should happen to pensions in the context of marital breakdown. I am sure Senators will agree that for too long pension rights in the marital breakdown situation have been neglected and, at worst, ignored.  This is despite the case that pension rights are often the spouse's second most valuable asset after the matrimonial home.  I do not accept that pension rights are an area which should continue to remain a mystery or be left without specific provisions enabling the courts to deal with the matter.  In my view the assignability and valuation of pensions should not be foreign territory.  If necessary, spouses must be compensated in one form or another for loss of pensions or they must be assigned an interest to enable justice to be done.</P>
    <P>Some members of the pension industry may have reservations for administrative or other reasons about changes in pension schemes necessitated by marital breakdown.  The reality is that change to greater equity is with us in the context of the Bill and it is vital to <Col N="1829" /> resolve, as best as possible, all the problems of the financial consequences of marital breakdown.</P>
    <P>I would like to make a point about property provisions in the Bill, including those in relation to pensions.  All property on the breakdown of a marriage may be the subject of a court order once one of the spouses applies to the court for an order in relation to that property. The court will not make an order in relation to property of its own motion. That will also be the position in relation to pension orders.</P>
    <P>Property is property no matter how and when it is required.  It may include real or personal property, the family home, a business, shares, policies of insurance and pensions.  It does not matter if the property is owned by the wife or the husband separately or jointly. The point is that the Bill allows the court, where appropriate, to make the necessary type of order in support of a spouse or children.  It has a range of powers to do so.</P>
    <P>Sections 11 will allow the court to make one of two types of pension orders.  The first type may be described as a pension split order where the member spouse's interest in his or her scheme is reduced by order of the court and that amount used to create an entitlement to an independent and separate benefit for the dependent spouse.</P>
    <P>The second mechanism which may be described as &ldquo;earmarking&rdquo; is one that retains the dependent spouse's interest in the member spouse's scheme, including the survivor's part, with the proportion of benefit to be paid to the nonmember spouse being determined by the court.  Under section 11 notice of any application in relation to a pensions adjustment order must be given by the applicant spouse to the trustees of the pension scheme, and in making a pensions adjustment order, the court must have regard to any representations made by the trustees.  In making a pensions adjustment order, the court will give the pension trustees such directions as it considers appropriate in relation to the order.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="1830" /> I am, of course, concerned to ensure that the pension arrangements under the Bill will be as practicable as possible. In this, I greatly value the expertise given to me by members of the pension industry and the help given by them in the formulation of the provisions in the Bill.  The provisions are complex and I continue to have the benefit of consultations with pension experts.  In the light of those consultations some fine tuning of the provisions may be desirable and I shall be giving consideration to the question of some amendments on Committee Stage.  I shall take into account any points which may be raised in the course of further debate on the Bill.</P>
    <P>While section 12 deals with pensions also, its scope is narrower.  The section contains a useful provision enabling the court to order the trustees of a pension scheme not to regard the judicial separation of the spouses as a ground for disqualifying a spouse from benefiting under the scheme on the death of the other spouse.  This is intended to remove a difficulty in situations where the rules of a pensions scheme may provide that survivors' benefit will only be paid to the spouse of the deceased member if both spouses are residing together at the time of the member spouse's death.  Notice of an application under this section must be given to the trustees of the pension scheme and the court is required to have regard to any representations made by them.  I have made similar provisions in section 42 of the Bill where parties have entered into separation agreements and have those agreements made a rule of court under section 8 of the Family Law (Maintenance of Spouses and Children) Act, 1976.  That separation also may not disqualify a spouse from benefiting under the other spouse's pension scheme.</P>
    <P>Section 13 re-enacts, in substance, provisions in the 1989 Act empowering the courts in suitable cases to extinguish rights of successions of the spouses following a separation decree.  A decree of judicial separation will not end succession <Col N="1831" /> rights, but the court is empowered in certain circumstances to do so.</P>
    <P>Section 14 empowers the court to order the sale of property and re-enacts provisions in the 1989 Act.  It provides that where a court makes a secured periodical payments order, a lump sum order of a property adjustment order, it may, additionally, at any time thereafter make a further order for the sale of any property in which either spouse has a beneficial interest.  The order for sale may include provisions in relation to the manner and time of sale and disposal of the proceeds of sale.</P>
    <P>Criteria are set out in section 15 for the making of court orders under Part II in support of spouses and dependent children.  Subsection (1) sets down that a general criterion provision must be made for the spouse and children as is adequate and reasonable having regard to all the circumstances of the case.  Subsection (2) sets out more specific criteria in relation to such matters as spouses' income, earning capacity, property and financial resources, likely future obligations and age, as well as the conduct of the spouses and their accommodation needs.  The court must take into account any contribution made by either spouse to the financial and other resources of the other spouse and any contribution made by either of them by looking after the home or caring for the family.  Subsection (3) sets out specific criteria in relation to children, which take into account financial and accommodation needs and other matters.  Conduct of the spouse may also be relevant to the question of the making of financial and other orders in support of a spouse &mdash; desertion, for example, will be a bar unless the court is of the opinion that it would be unjust not to make such orders.</P>
    <P>The remaining section of importance in Part II is section 17 which empowers the court, on the application of either spouse, to vary or discharge previous orders under part II, taking into account any change in circumstances.  Variation orders are also subject to the criteria set out in section 15.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="1832" /> Part III of the Bill is new and takes into account the recommendations of the Law Reform Commission's report on recognition of foreign divorces and legal separations.  At present, where a foreign decree of divorce is entitled to recognition in the State, the courts have no power to order financial or other relief for a dependent spouse.  The Bill empowers the court to order such relief under Part II.  It also provides that where one of the parties to the foreign divorce decree dies, the other party, if he or she has not remarried, may apply to the court for financial provision to be made for him or her out of the deceased spouse's estate.  In considering whether to make an order under this section, the court must have regard to any lump sum payments or property adjustment order made in favour of the applicant, or any devise or bequest made by the deceased spouse to the applicant spouse.  The provisions which the court can make under this section, together with any lump sum payments already made or property adjustment order, must not exceed in total the share, if any, of the applicant in the estate of the deceased spouse under the Succession Act, 1965, to which the applicant was entitled or would have been entitled if the marriage was valid.</P>
    <P>There is a technical legal aspect of the proposals in Part III on which I would like to make some comment.  The Court of Justice of the European Union, in interpreting the Convention on the Recognition and Enforcement of Judgments in Civil and Commercial Matters, which has been in force in Ireland since June 1988, has ruled that a maintenance order granted in one state, on the basis of the obligation arising out of marriage of one spouse to maintain the other, is irreconcilable with a decree divorcing the spouses granted in the state where enforcement of the maintenance order is sought.  For example, if a wife had a maintenance order granted against her husband by an Irish court, and her husband subsequently obtained a divorce in England, an English court would not be <Col N="1833" /> in a position to enforce the maintenance order because it is irreconcilable with the fact that a divorce has been obtained there since the making of the original maintenance order.  In such circumstances, the only avenue at present open to an Irish person is to apply to the English court, in the divorce proceedings, for maintenance at the time of granting the divorce decree or at any time thereafter.  It will now be possible under the provisions in Part III of the Bill for the maintenance creditor, where the divorce is recognised here, to apply to the Irish courts for maintenance.  A maintenance order granted in such circumstances by an Irish court, since it will be granted following a divorce which is recognised here, will be capable of being enforced within the European Union.</P>
    <P>Part IV of the Bill deals with declarations as to marital status and its purpose is to restate the law which enables a person to apply to the court for a declaration as to the validity of his or her marriage.  The provisions implement, with certain changes, recommendations of the Law Reform Commission in their <i>Report on Restitution of Conjugal Rights, Jactitation of Marriage and Related Matters.</i>  The commission was of the view that the present law would benefit from restatement in clear terms in modern legislation.  At present, the power to give such declarations of status is confined to the High Court and its statutory basis comes from an Act of 1868.  The Bill gives the Circuit Court jurisdiction to deal with the provisions in Part III.</P>
    <P>Occasionally, the question of the marital status of a person, particularly one who has been married or divorced abroad, may be raised &mdash; for example, to determine whether he or she is free to marry here or can claim a pension or other benefit as the spouse or widow or widower of another.  Part IV enables the court to make a declaratory order regarding the marital status in these and other cases.  These provisions will be welcomed by, among others, the Registrar of Marriages, who can now refer <Col N="1834" /> persons with queries about their marital status to the straightforward procedures in Part IV.</P>
    <P>Although a declaration will normally be sought by one of the parties to the marriage, others may be legitimately interested in its validity.  For example, the trustees of a pension fund may wish to establish whether a woman is the widow of a former member of the scheme.  Applications for a declaration may therefore be brought by anyone, but the court must refuse to hear a case if it considers that the applicant does not have a sufficient interest in the outcome of those proceedings.</P>
    <P>Part V of the Bill implements a long standing recommendation in the report of the Oireachtas Joint Committee on Marriage Breakdown for an increase in the age of marriage from 16 years to 18 years.  The Law Reform Commission and the Second Commission on the Status of Women also made this recommendation.</P>
    <P>The provisions on notice of intention to marry are consistent with the requirement of most churches that notice be given by members proposing to marry. Circumstances may arise where the inflexible application of either or both of the new rules could be unfair.  In recognition of this, I am providing that a person affected in this way can apply to the court for an exemption from one or both of the requirements.</P>
    <P>Part VI of the Bill deals with a number of miscellaneous provisions, including court jurisdictions, the more important of which, in relation to nullity and jurisdiction under the Family Home Protection Act, I have dealt with in my opening comments.</P>
    <P>In the course of the its passage through the Dáil important new provisions relating to taxation were included in Part VI of the Bill.  The areas of the tax code to which these provisions relate are stamp duty, capital acquisitions tax, capital gains tax and probate tax.  The main effect of these provisions is to extend the property tax exemptions which currently apply in financial and property dealings between <Col N="1835" /> married couples to those cases covered by the Bill where the foreign divorce is recognised here.  These tax provisions will ensure that couples who are divorced abroad will not be at a disadvantage in terms of our tax code.  The added significance of these tax provisions is that they will in substance be the same as those in any future divorce legislation.</P>
    <P>This concludes my summary of the main provisions contained in the Bill.  I am confident it will be found acceptable in principle by all sides of the House.  I assure Senators I will consider fully the points they make today and during later stages of the debate.</P>
    <P>I will make brief reference to an important area associated with the Bill which is also being addressed.  My colleague in Government, the Minister for Social Welfare, Deputy De Rossa, is preparing legislative proposals to provide that no person will be disadvantaged as a result of his or her legal status being changed from married, separated or deserted to divorced.  These provisions are required as a follow-on to the provisions in the Bill and again they will be model provisions in the case of provision in our law for domestic divorce.</P>
    <P>Senators will no doubt agree that while it is essential to update and modernise our family law provisions and to give the courts full powers to enable justice to be done to parties of broken marriages, it is equally important that where parties can settle the terms of their separation they should be facilitated to do so by way of mediation and that where there is the possibility of reconciliation that should be facilitated by way of counselling.  The extra funding for support services which I secured for 1994 and 1995, together with the various legislative measures I am bringing forward this year, are a measure of the comprehensive approach I am endeavouring to achieve in relation to the issues involved in marriage breakdown.</P>
    <P>I have brought forward the Bill to put the civil legal aid scheme on a statutory <Col N="1836" /> footing.  It has been initiated in this House and I look forward to debate on that matter in addition to debate on the Family Law Bill.</P>
    <P>I commend this Bill to the House.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MarianMcGennis" hpid="Mrs. McGennis Mrs. McGennis">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. McGennis</NameTxt>
      <P>I welcome the Minister, Deputy Taylor, to the House.  In my new position as Fianna Fáil spokesperson on Equality and Law Reform.  I have no doubt he will keep both of us busy in the coming term.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MervynTaylor" hpid="Mr. Taylor Mr. Taylor">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Taylor</NameTxt>
      <P>I look forward to working with the Senator in that capacity.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MarianMcGennis" hpid="Mrs. McGennis Mrs. McGennis">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. McGennis</NameTxt>
      <P>I thank the Minister. It is now a matter of history that in 1986 the then Fine Gael / Labour Coalition Government held a referendum to enable the introduction of divorce.  My party has often been described as the villain of the piece, criticised as being responsible for the defeat of the referendum. I rejected that then and I do so now.  Nine years later we are introducing vital legislation which is a prerequisite for any referendum being put to the people.  Even if this is being done late, it is as well that the legislation be introduced correctly and well in advance of the referendum.  My party's position on the holding of a referendum is that we will be constructive in Opposition but we will pressurise the Government to ensure all necessary legislation and safeguards are in place before the matter is brought before the people.  That position should find favour with the Minister.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Any divorce referendum must be preceded by putting in place a series of laws to protect spouses and children and to enable justice to be done.  When this Bill was initiated in the Dáil, the Minister said it contained model provisions for any future divorce legislation and he has said so again today.  As such, the Bill's importance stretches far beyond the framework in which it was set. However, during the year since it was initiated the Bill has undergone radical changes.  The Minister would admit that the huge number of amendments he <Col N="1837" /> introduced on Report Stage in the Dáil alter the Bill significantly from the one presented to the Dáil on 23 February 1994.  It would have been helpful, since it has been amended so greatly, if the Department had presented an updated explanatory memorandum to accompany the Bill after it had passed through all Stages in the Dáil.  Amendments have not occurred to the same extent in any other legislation.  A new explanatory memorandum to let us know exactly what this Bill will now achieve would have been extremely helpful.</P>
    <P>The Bill has substantial provisions for the support of spouses in cases of judicial separation and foreign divorces, but it does not extend those powers to nullity.  The nullity issue must be addressed by the Oireachtas well in advance of a referendum on divorce.  As the Minister is aware, a large number of marriages have been annulled &mdash; State and Church annulments have been described as the Irish from of divorce. To proceed with legislative changes which ignore this and exclude parties who have secured either State or Church annulments is to store trouble for the future.</P>
    <P>In the Dáil the Minister stated he was removing the nullity provisions because he felt it would be better to provide for these matters &ldquo;perhaps in a modified form in separate legislation&rdquo;.  Has he been told there is a constitutional problem in dealing with marriages which have been annulled?  If this is the position, will he inform us what he intends to do to overcome constitutional challenges or difficulties with this aspect of the problem?</P>
    <P>The Bill extends powers to the courts for the support of spouses and dependent children where marriages break down in every circumstance short of domestic violence, with, as I have said, the exclusion of annulled marriages.  It also provides new powers in relation to pensions and strengthens the laws on maintenance, which I welcome.</P>
    <P>The Supreme Court decision to strike down the Matrimonial Home Bill was a <Col N="1838" /> serious blow.  Until joint ownership of the matrimonial home is established in law as a norm within marriage a large number of women will feel they are discriminated against.  This is an important equality issue which I hope the Minister will deal with and attempt to rectify.</P>
    <P>The Minister stated that the Bill allows for the redistribution of property, including the family home.  It would be preferable to have enshrined in law the right of both parties to joint ownership of the family home.  The Matrimonial Home Bill did not set out to deal with cases of separation or divorce, it was to enshrine that right in law, and the Government must do everything in its power to achieve that objective.  I am sure the Minister agrees.</P>
    <P>I do not know whether it is proposed to get around the Supreme Court decision and I ask the Minister to state if he is confident the provisions allowing for the redistribution of property, including the family home, are copper-fastened in this legislation.  I congratulate the Government on making a formal request to the Supreme Court for an early hearing of the case challenging the constitutionality of the Judicial Separation Act, 1989.  Before this Bill passes all Stages in this House, I hope we have an indication of the status of that Act.</P>
    <P>The Minister stated the Bill proposes to raise the legal age for marriage from 16 to 18 years of age.  This is a sensible proposal.  To be fair, the churches have taken an initiative already.  Although there is no legal bar on marrying at 16, the Catholic Church has for a number of years effectively refused consent for young couples.  Since my own marriage 20 years ago, the Church has insisted that couples take part in pre-marriage courses.  Three months prior notice of intention to marry is required, which is a sensible provision.  The best way to reduce the number of marriages which fail is to ensure couples get as good a start as possible.  It is acknowledged that marriages of very young couples have a much higher rate of breakdown and I welcome the raising of the age limit.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="1839" /> I welcome those provisions of the Bill which give the court power to order attachment of earnings while maintenance orders are being granted.  The Minister referred to this also.  In introducing this provision he is acknowledging the reality that in a number of cases where maintenance is granted the spouse &mdash; normally the wife &mdash; finds it difficult to ensure payment of maintenance and time and again becomes involved in further legal proceedings to obtain her entitlement.</P>
    <P>As the Minister has stated, the Combat Poverty Agency's report on the financial consequences of marriage breakdown highlighted the extent of default on maintenance orders.  It is also wasteful of the court's time if a wife must continually return to court to get what is rightfully hers.  I congratulate the Minister on this provision.</P>
    <P>The Minister referred to some consequences of this Bill.  He published the Civil Legal Aid Bill last week, which is to be initiated in this House and I welcome that.  However the provisions in both Bills will see the workload of our courts increase dramatically.  We already have complaints about long delays and in cases of marriage breakdown they can have a very damaging effect.  Does the Minister feel the District Court and Circuit Court as they currently exist are adequate to deal with family law cases?  I feel they are not and the Minister probably agrees.</P>
    <P>Prior to the introduction of the Civil Legal Aid Bill we had many complaints about backlogs from parties looking for legal aid.  In 1994 the Minister provided additional funding to reduce these delays but people are still complaining that they have to wait for almost a year for legal aid.  I know that was disputed.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MervynTaylor" hpid="Mr. Taylor Mr. Taylor">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Taylor</NameTxt>
      <P>That should not be the case now.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MarianMcGennis" hpid="Mrs. McGennis Mrs. McGennis">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. McGennis</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister has tried to ensure additional resources will be provided in this area but the knock-on effect of the legislative changes <Col N="1840" /> necessary to recognise the reality of marriage breakdown will be great pressure on the courts; there will be need for the appointment of additional members to the Judiciary and possibly the provision of additional courts.  Every Bill requires finance and back-up resources but the legislation the Minister will introduce will require more than the normal resources which attach to new legislation.  I ask the Minister for Finance to support those requests.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MervynTaylor" hpid="Mr. Taylor Mr. Taylor">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Taylor</NameTxt>
      <P>I hope when I look for those resources the Fianna Fáil spokesperson on Finance in the Dáil will not make too many difficulties for me.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MarianMcGennis" hpid="Mrs. McGennis Mrs. McGennis">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. McGennis</NameTxt>
      <P>I will make the case on the Minister's behalf.</P>
      <P>As he has said, this is a weighty document and on Second Stage I cannot go through it in the detail it requires.  On Committee Stage we will go through the nuts and bolts to see how it will work. The Minister has indicated he will be open to amendments on Committee Stage.  I may have been critical of the changes in the Bill as initiated, but the fact that amendments have been made shows the Minister is amenable to accepting recommendations and suggestions by Members on the Opposition benches.  I welcome that.  If the Bill requires fine tuning we will provide constructive opposition to ensure when it leaves this House it will be as good as we can make it.</P>
      <P>Marriage breakdown is acknowledged as a sad fact of life.  The effects of breakdown can be damaging to children.  We need legislation such as this to at least reduce the financial hardship on families. The Minister mentioned that we must have adequate and well resourced social services to provide the support needed by families who are in what can only be described as crisis and trauma. A marriage breakdown, no matter how civilised, could not be described as other than traumatic for a family.  We will need those resources for mediation and counselling the Minister mentioned.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="1841" /> This legislation will be received with mixed feelings.  Those who feel divorce legislation will cause further breakdown in marriages are deluding themselves. The introduction of such legislation will not cause an increase in the number of marriages breaking down.  The fact that we have not had divorce has not reduced the number of marriages which fail.  We, as legislators, must provide support for families finding themselves in this position and deal compassionately and capably with this sad reality.</P>
    <P>I support the Bill and look forward to teasing out various aspects on Committee Stage.</P>
    <Speaker pid="DanNeville" hpid="Mr. Neville Mr. Neville">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Neville</NameTxt>
      <P>I welcome the Minister to the House.  I also welcome the Bill which was first published almost 12 months ago.  As Senator McGennis said, it has been changed significantly on both Committee and Report Stages in the Dáil.  I compliment the Minister on his attitude towards the improvement of Bills and amendments put forward by the Opposition.  Perhaps Government Senators should be in a position to suggest amendments, although the politics of the situation sometimes makes that difficult.</P>
      <P>It is positive that the Legislature &mdash; Dáil and Seanad &mdash; is heeded by Ministers when Bills go through the Houses. That should be our purpose because too often we experience Ministers who come here single-mindedly to get a Bill through and treat the Seanad, and possibly also the Dáil, as a nuisance necessary to turn the Bill into an Act.  Thankfully this Minister and others have a different attitude.  Legislation will often be better for the application of common sense; we are not legal people but we can at least provide that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>It is important that the State recognises changes in society and responds to them with appropriate legislation.  The Minister has recognised the growing problem of marital breakdown.  This Bill responds to the necessity for strong support services within society to deal with this situation.  We must have the means of protecting the vulnerable in society, <Col N="1842" /> the children and spouses.  We must ensure that the State regulates so that all parties are treated fairly when a marriage breaks down.</P>
    <P>The issue of marriage breakdown, as Senator McGennis said, must be treated openly and honestly.  It is a fact of life and we must deal with it responsibly.  It is important that the courts' powers are strengthened to deal with the consequences of marital breakdown and with matters such as church nullity and foreign divorces.  This Bill does that.  It is vital that the courts can support the spouses and children in marriage breakdowns.</P>
    <P>This Bill deals with the situation following the breakdown of a marriage.  I wish to speak briefly about another aspect of this issue &mdash; intervention prior to marriage breakdown.  Not enough assistance is given before marriages irretrievably break down.  On too many occasion I have met people &mdash; 95 per cent of whom are women &mdash; who are in difficult marital situations.  In rural areas there are few places to which one can refer such people.  I do not have the skills to advise somebody who has difficulty in their marriage.  It is very frustrating to advise somebody to go to the nearest city when they do not want to do so or do not want to move out of their own environment.  They sometimes do not understand the type of assistance that might be available if they sought it.</P>
    <P>I remember a specific situation where a person who was experiencing great difficulty in their marriage approached me.  The marriage had not broken down at that stage but it did so eventually. However, I advised the person to travel to the city which was 15 miles away.  The person had no car and no means of transport and I could not persuade the person that such facilities were available to them.  The only advice I could give them was to approach a doctor or a priest.  I did not consider that response adequate.</P>
    <P>In other areas of life, public representatives can get great assistance in dealing with problems, If there is a health problem in a house, for example, or a <Col N="1843" /> problem with financial support for a family, one can ask the health board to intervene.  Welfare officers will travel to the house at our request to talk to the people involved and to offer assistance and advice.  However, that facility is not available for marital difficulty.  We should look seriously at institutions such as health boards as locations for a counselling service that will be available and advertised, and on which people feel they can call if they are having difficulties in their marriage.  If they are unable to pay their electricity bill or their mortgage they can go to the community welfare officer for assistance.  Counselling should be available in the same immediate way.  I appreciate the good work being done by the Family Mediation Service and by the Civil Legal Aid Board.  However, these services are not present in most rural areas.</P>
    <P>The rate of marriage breakdown has increased enormously.  It has been calculated that 70,000 couples will apply for divorce following the referendum later this year.  I welcome the sentiments expressed by Senator McGennis about the referendum.  I might talk to her privately about statements that have been made by some of her colleagues in the mid-west with regard to the position of Fianna Fáil <i>vis-a-vis</i> the divorce referendum. However, I welcome her positive approach.  I can give the Senator some documentation on this matter.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MervynTaylor" hpid="Mr. Taylor Mr. Taylor">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Taylor</NameTxt>
      <P>The important thing is to have Senator McGennis on our side.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DanNeville" hpid="Mr. Neville Mr. Neville">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Neville</NameTxt>
      <P>We must have legislation in place to ensure that all areas of concern are covered prior to the referendum. I accept that on the last occasion these areas were not covered. That was one of the difficulties.  We learn from our mistakes and, consequently, this Bill is now before the House.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I welcome the raising of the legal age for marriage to 18 years.  The waiting period of three months prior to marriage is a good provision and reflects a <Col N="1844" /> trend in society where people are getting married at an older age.  The Minister referred to the organisations and reports which he consulted.  The Oireachtas Joint Committee on Marital Breakdown was one of those organisations. A very good friend of mine, the recently deceased former Deputy Willie O'Brien, was chairman of that committee. He did an excellent job in difficult circumstances and at a difficult time for looking at social issues.  Times are better now for dealing with those issues.</P>
    <P>The Bill faces the needs of children which must remain of paramount importance.  This can be achieved by facing the fact of marital breakdown, by encouraging mediation as a means to resolve difficulties and by providing, where necessary, legal representation to protect the interests of children.  We must welcome the regulation of property rights in the Bill.  This issue created many problems ten years ago.  Pension rights is an area of interest to me as I have been involved in pension schemes in the past.  A pension is a property and an asset.  It is part of the family's assets and it is important that it is dealt with in the manner proposed by the Minister in the Bill.</P>
    <P>I welcome the Bill and I welcome the Minister's attitude to amendments which might improve it.  I look forward to its speedy passage.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MaryHenry" hpid="Dr. Henry Dr. Henry">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Henry</NameTxt>
      <P>I welcome the Minister and I welcome this Bill.  The wisdom of the last Government in separating areas of civil law from the Department of Justice &mdash; my remarks are no reflection on the Department of Justice &mdash; through the creation of the Department of Equality and Law Reform has been shown to be extremely worthwhile.  If this had not been done I doubt that we would have got through the amount of social legislation which I am delighted to see has been introduced by the Minister's Department.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The end of the Bill contains one of the most important provisions.  While this Bill is very important, the fact that a Bill will be introduced to put the civil <Col N="1845" /> legal aid scheme on a statutory footing cannot but be widely welcomed.  I realise the Minister has done his best in the last few years to secure further funding for the Civil Legal Aid Board but putting it on a statutory basis &mdash; which many of us have sought &mdash; is most important.  It is over 20 years since Mrs. Airey took her case to Strasbourg.  Our President, the then Senator Mary Robinson, took that case with her.  It is a sad fact that it has taken 20 years to have the Civil Legal Aid Board put on a statutory basis.  However, I welcome the Minister's commitment to introduce that Bill in this House in the near future.</P>
    <P>This Bill must be welcome even if for sad reasons.  It must be remembered that there is nothing but tears from everybody's point of view in the breakdown of marriage.  However, while the emotional and social breakdown is tragic we must also look at the financial worries that occur in such situations and which have been pointed out so ably by Senator McGennis and Senator Neville.</P>
    <P>We have been slow in recognising that marriage breakdown is a serious fact in our society.  In this respect Senator Neville was correct when he said that there cannot be a Senator in the House who has not had people appealing to them as to what they can do about the tragic situations in which they find themselves.  It is also important to remember that many of these situations may be very violent, where it is not simply the case that the marriage has broken down due to irreconcilable difficulties between the spouses, or that one partner has left to set up home with another partner.  A large number of cases of marriage breakdown sadly involve domestic violence. I am therefore pleased to note that the Minister is to give the probation and social welfare services a statutory role within this area.</P>
    <P>The financial aspects of this are incredibly important, because in all marriage breakdowns we know that both sides of the breakdown suffer very badly financially.  However, the marriage protection legislation which the Minister introduced last year allows for some <Col N="1846" /> attempt to be made to pursue spouses who are abroad, or in this case it would be separated or divorced spouses who are abroad.  This is important and I am pleased to note that this kind of legislation has been continued in the Bill.</P>
    <P>The area dealing with attachment of earnings is most important, because without it spouses find that they have grave difficulties in getting enforcement of payments.  However, as the Minister remarked when the House discussed the payments protection legislation, you cannot get blood out of a stone.  It is therefore important to remember that the State may have to pick up the problem in some of these cases.  In this context I was pleased to note in the budget that there has been a lessening of the distinctions between people who find themselves on social benefit for these kinds of reasons.  Examples include the amalgamation of the deserted wives benefit and the lone parent's allowance. All are in the same appalling financial position.  It is better that we try to go forward with this problem on a united front rather than addressing them in separate categories and perhaps making differences of one pound here or a status there.</P>
    <P>At the end of his speech the Minister stated:</P>
    <P>... the Minister for Social Welfare ... is preparing legislative proposals to provide that no person will be disadvantaged as a result of his or her legal status being changed from married, separated or deserted to divorced.</P>
    <P>This is very important, because this was an area where during the last divorce referendum there was a great deal of worry over whether people would be in a worse financial situation if they became divorced following the legislation which, it was suggested, would be introduced.</P>
    <P>The area of pensions is extremely difficult, but it is probably one of the most important areas which must be addressed.  Protection is especially important in, for example, the case of the woman who may have worked within the home &mdash; because in general <Col N="1847" /> it will be women &mdash; for many years to the point perhaps where her earning capacity outside the home is not what it would have been had she been working in outside employment for many years. Finding herself divorced and with no prospects of pension rights and so on is extremely serious and I am pleased this has been addressed within the Bill.</P>
    <P>It is important that all legislation provisions within the field of marriage breakdown should be as non confrontational as possible.  The Minister has made in the past, and hopes to make for the future also, better financial arrangements for counselling services and mediation.  It is essential that we put real money into this area.  Senator Neville remarked that often one really never knows whom to send people to.  Counselling services have been run for many years on a voluntary basis, but it is now proposed to expand these services so that real help can be given to the problems associated with the breakdown of marriage before it breaks down. Examples include dealing with the problems of alcoholism, violence and so on.</P>
    <P>The protection of children, which is difficult enough in these situations, is important both emotionally and socially.  However, their financial protection is extremely difficult and it is an area which must be considered very carefully.  We have the grim example of the Child Support Agency in England at present to tell us various things that we should not do.  I am sure the Minister will ensure that all the efforts which we make in this country to protect the financial situation for children is adhered to.  In this respect it is interesting that we talk about cherishing the children and the family in this State, and we blithely signed up to the UN Convention on the rights of children some years ago. However, there are large areas of the convention which could be reread and which we should perhaps address again in the House to ascertain exactly what is out attitude towards children.</P>
    <P>I welcome the child benefit increases in the budget yesterday, but there is still no provision for child care in this country. It is a matter of great importance, <Col N="1848" /> not just to those within marriage, but even more to those who are separated in marriage or have been divorced from someone elsewhere, and to lone parents. I therefore urge the Minister to have his Cabinet colleagues consider this area also.</P>
    <P>The proposal to raise the legal age of marriage is welcome, although some people I know say that it could never be raised high enough for people to be sensible.  However, it is without dispute that marriages at a very young age break down more frequently than marriages which take place when people are older.  In addition, the waiting period of three months is a good idea.</P>
    <P>We often receive reports about teenage pregnancies and the great increase in the number of single mothers in this country.  I was involved in correspondence with one of the newspapers about this recently, but it is worthwhile pointing out that in the early 1970s, or 1972 I understand, there were 54 mothers of 15 or under in the country and in 1993, which is the year for which I have the most recent figures, there were 55, so this could not be called a dramatic increase.</P>
    <P>While there is an increase in the number of single teenage mothers, it is not quite that dramatic when compared with the number of girls who were obviously pregnant and married when they were 16, 17 and 18 years of age in the past.  This is an era to which we would not like to return.  I am pleased to note that there are better social attitudes regarding teenage pregnancies and I hope that the Minister's commitment in the Bill to raising the legal age of marriage to 18 will further show that it is very unsuitable to have teenage marriages taking place where there is less than full commitment to the marriage in the first place.</P>
    <P>It is also worthwhile pointing out that there are many people in the country who have for a long time been living in second relationships.  Sadly, I was one of those who had begun to think that maybe people did not mind whether they were married or not; but I said to somebody recently, who was very disappointed about the last divorce referendum, <Col N="1849" /> that presumably it would make no difference to him now.  He replied, however, that it was a most serious issue for him.  I therefore hope that when the Minister brings forward the referendum in the summer we will all be in a position in the House to understand better the reasons why marriages breakdown, to look especially to the protection of children from those marriages, and in as calm and as rational a way as possible to bring forward the legislation for the referendum, which will not be as emotional and confrontational as on the last occasion.</P>
    <P>Debate adjourned.</P>
    <P>
      <i>Sitting suspended at 1 p.m. and resumed at 2 p.m.</i>
    </P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Meningitis Outbreak:" RHead="Statements">
    <Title>Meningitis Outbreak: Statements.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="MauriceManning" hpid="Mr. Manning Mr. Manning">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Manning</NameTxt>
      <P>I welcome the Minister of State on his first visit to the Seanad. He has been in three other Houses of Parliament but this is his first visit to this House.  As guidance, I suggest a ten minute time limit, but if Senators wish to speak for longer there will not be a problem.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LouisBelton" hpid="Acting Chairman (Mr. Belton) Acting Chairman (Mr. Belton)">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman (Mr. Belton)</NameTxt>
      <P>Is that agreed?  Agreed.  I also welcome the Minister of State and wish him well in his new position.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="AustinCurrie" hpid="Minister of State at the Department of Health (Mr. Currie) Minister of State at the Department of Health (Mr. Currie)">
      <NameTxt>Minister of State at the Department of Health (Mr. Currie)</NameTxt>
      <P>Thank you, Sir, and I thank Senator Manning for reminding people of my long and distinguished career.  It is not quite true to say that I have never been in the Seanad Chamber as I was here for committee meetings, but this is my first occasion to formally address the Seanad.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>My colleague, the Minister for Health, Deputy Noonan (<i>Limerick East</i>), who could not be here for this debate today, asked me to acknowledge the importance of this opportunity to speak to this House about meningitis.  I also wish to thank Senator McGennis for providing this opportunity to place <Col N="1850" /> on the record of the Seanad the current situation about meningococcal meningitis in this country.</P>
    <P>At the outset, I wish to reassure the Seanad that the incidence of the disease, which has been reported to my Department by the health boards, is more or less the same as in previous years and as such does not constitute an epidemic or an unusual nationwide outbreak.  The Eastern Health Board, in whose area most of the recent cases occurred, has also confirmed that there is no epidemic of the disease but there is a higher incidence than usual in the north Dublin area.  In addition, Temple Street Children's Hospital confirmed at the weekend that the meningitis infections which were confirmed in children admitted there recently were not of a single strain.  This reinforces the view that cases are not connected and that the disease has not reached epidemic proportions.</P>
    <P>The information from the monitoring of the disease shows that its incidence is running at approximately the same level as in previous years.  A total of 225 cases were reported in 1992; 203 cases in 1993 and 239 cases in 1994.  For the period between 4 November 1994 and 27 January 1995, a total of 87 cases have been notified to the Department compared with 74 cases during the same period last year.  Since 27 January 1995, a further nine cases have been reported but no new cases have been reported to my Department since.</P>
    <P>My Department and the health boards operate a very comprehensive system for monitoring the incidence of meningococcal meningitis.  Under guidelines issued by my Department to the health boards, the following measures are in place to monitor the disease at local and national level and at the level of individual cases.</P>
    <P>First, an immediate preliminary notification of a cases is made to the local director of community care by the relevant doctor or hospital based doctor, initially by telephone and then confirmed in writing.  This enables the director of community care to take any <Col N="1851" /> necessary action at local level.  Secondly, the director of community care makes an immediate notification of the disease to my Department.  This enables the Department to maintain an up-to-date picture of the situation nationwide and to assess if the incidence of the disease is unusually high.  Thirdly, as soon as possible following the preliminary notification a report on individual cases is furnished to my Department.  This enables the Department to assess if cases are related and if contacts have been treated.  Finally, every week cases of the disease occurring in their areas are notified by the directors of community care to my Department.  This also enables the Department to monitor the incidence of the disease nationwide on a week to week basis.</P>
    <P>In addition, statistics on deaths from meningococcal meningitis are sent to my Department by the Central Statistics Office.  As I have said, this represents a very prompt and comprehensive reporting system on the incidence of meningitis and it is a reflection of the seriousness with which my Department treats this disease.</P>
    <P>Following media reports last week of an epidemic of the disease in parts of Dublin, the Eastern Health Board issued a press statement last Saturday, 4 February, confirming that there is no major epidemic of meningitis in the area at present.  In this regard the board stated that any reference to &ldquo;an epidemic&rdquo; is purely technical in that there was an unusually high number of cases within a specified area and a specified period of time &mdash; that is, in north Dublin.</P>
    <P>While the incidence of meningococcal meningitis reported to my Department in recent months has not risen above its normal level, the occurrence of five deaths from the disease during a relatively short period in January of this year is unusual and is a cause for concern. I would like to sympathise most sincerely with the bereaved families and I am sure that the Members of this House join with me in this.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="1852" /> In view of those deaths, my colleague, the Minister for Health, took measures to alert health professionals and parents about possible cases of the disease, as early diagnosis and treatment are essential for a complete recovery.  On 17 January 1995, the deputy chief medical officer of my Department wrote to each director of community care requesting them to ensure that information concerning the disease is as widely available as possible to parents; that doctors should be extra vigilant in their assessment of patients, bearing the possibility of meningitis in mind, and that preventive measures be implemented as quickly as possible.</P>
    <P>The directors of community care were also asked that the leaflet prepared by my Department's health promotion unit on meningitis should be promoted appropriately in each community care area &mdash; for example, through schools, health centres and local health board offices.  In addition, directors of community care were reminded of the necessity for early and comprehensive notification of cases of meningococcal meningitis to my Department so that any unusual incidence of the disease nationally could be quickly identified and appropriate action taken.</P>
    <P>The Minister for Health also issued a press statement on 17 January 1995, which was carried on television, radio and the newspapers, advising parents and teachers that they should be aware of the symptoms of meningitis and to bring children to their general practitioners if they were worried.  The Minister advised that doctors should be extra vigilant in relation to cases or suspected cases, as early diagnosis and treatment is vital for a successful outcome in individual cases.</P>
    <P>A further letter was issued to the health boards by my Department on 31 January requesting them to disseminate the health promotion unit's leaflet on meningitis towards informing the public and professionals, such as doctors, nurses and teachers who come into regular contact with children, of the symptoms of the disease, the treatment of <Col N="1853" /> cases or suspected cases of the disease and the prevention of infection in contacts with cases or suspected cases.  The Minister also stressed the need for early detection and intervention on a television news bulletin that day.</P>
    <P>A free telephone helpline has been in operation in the Eastern Health Board since 3 January in order to give information, advice and reassurance to worried members of the public.  The helpline, which operates from 9 a.m. to 9 p.m., will continue for as long as the board considers necessary.  The level of concern among parents about the disease was demonstrated by the fact that 2,500 persons made calls to the Eastern Health Board on the first day of the helpline.  This is now averaging 300 calls a day.</P>
    <P>I am satisfied that the necessary measures have been taken by my colleague, by the Department and by the health boards to inform the public about the current incidence of the disease and in particular about the need for vigilance for early symptoms and the importance of early treatment in ensuring a complete recovery.</P>
    <P>I wish to refer briefly to reports that a vaccine for meningitis has been developed in Cuba and could be used here to prevent most cases of the disease. These reports have been thoroughly checked by my Department and in particular with the World Health Organisation.  The position is that this vaccine is still in the early trial stage and has not been tested yet to the point where it could be used on a population wide basis.  The WHO is not prepared to recommend its use at this point and we would need much more data as to its efficacy and safety before considering its use here.  I will, of course, be watching developments in this regard with a view to introducing a vaccination programme as soon as an acceptable vaccine is available.</P>
    <P>Finally, I wish to reiterate that the current incidence of meningococcal meningitis is not unusual, but this is not to say that we should be complacent. Parents, teachers and others dealing <Col N="1854" /> with children should familiarise themselves with the symptoms of this very serious disease and if they are worried they should consult their general practitioner as soon as possible.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelFinneranFF" hpid="Mr. Finneran Mr. Finneran">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Finneran</NameTxt>
      <P>I welcome the Minister to the House on his first visit.  I congratulate him on his appointment and wish him well.</P>
      <P>I extend my sympathy to the families who have suffered the loss of a loved one from this tragedy recently.  To some extent, we can thank the media for highlighting this outbreak.  The Minister and the health board do not like to call it an epidemic but the media kept this matter upfront.  Senator McGennis will elaborate further on this issue in so far as it has affected her area of north County Dublin more than any other area.  I am glad the Leader of the House responded to the call for this debate.</P>
      <P>From discussions I have found that the area of greatest concern for parents has been the sense of the unknown and the sense of fear.  It reminds me of the time when I was much younger and there was a similar sense of fear about polio.  At that time, parents were most perturbed if they heard of a case, regardless of how far away it was from them.  On this occasion, I find that this same sense of fear and the unknown is very much on parents' minds.  To a great extent, it reflects on successive Ministers for Health &mdash; not just the current Minister and Minister of State because they are a short time in office &mdash; that there is a lack of concrete information.  It may not be possible at all times to provide such information but there is a lack of sound information on meningitis.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>If one was to listen to reports on the symptoms of meningitis, one would be struck by their similarity with many other upsets in children.  This is what confused and frightened parents most.  If a child did not feel well in the morning, because of a stomach upset, parents were immediately struck with fear that it could be a symptom of meningitis.  We should provide as much information as possible about meningitis to the public. <Col N="1855" /> The telephone helpline alone is not sufficient: it is more a crisis intervention. Good health education for parents is necessary.</P>
    <P>The matter of a vaccine should be further considered.  I understand conclusive evidence in this regard is still not available.  The development of a vaccine for immunisation by the World Health Organisation or others involved in medical science would allay fears.  It would not necessarily mean that the Department of Health would have to start general immunisation of children but it would mean that there was a vaccine available as a safeguard and a backup in emergencies.  While nobody can directly blame the Minister for Health, there seemed to have been a gradual rather than a quick response to the outbreak.  If it were not for the media and the House highlighting the problem, the telephone helpline might not have been set up and we might not have received the response that eventually came.  I am not criticising the Minister but for the future, I call on the him, through his Department and officials, to make general sound information on meningitis part of a health education programme for Irish parents.  If this is done, people will appreciate it.  I am sure the Department will keep a close watch on the situation regarding a vaccine for use in Ireland for outbreaks and as a response in emergencies.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JosephDoyle" hpid="Mr. Doyle Mr. Doyle">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Doyle</NameTxt>
      <P>I welcome the Minister to the House.  I also thank Senator McGennis for raising this issue, one with which I have been familiar for some time.  As a member of the Eastern Health Board I am aware of the concern of board members and the public about the increase in the incidence of meningitis in part of the board's area at the end of last year.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Figures of cases notified during each month of last year were circulated to the board at its January meeting and it was noted that about ten cases were notified during each of the last three months of the year.  We were reassured that a similar <Col N="1856" /> incidence rate had occurred at the beginning of the year and, indeed, during two of the summer months.</P>
    <P>At its meeting last Thursday, members were informed that 20 cases had been notified during January with four deaths, one of them a teenage girl. Most of the cases have come from the north city and the south Fingal areas. Concern was expressed over the increase and over some reports in the media which magnified the problem using expressions like &ldquo;killer bug&rdquo; etc.</P>
    <P>I understand that only one or two further cases have been reported since last week's meeting and hopefully the incidence of the disease is on the wane. However, health board staff are keeping the situation under close surveillance and, in order to counter the concern and anxiety of parents, the board has set up a free telephone advice service which has been in operation continuously since last Friday and is still in operation.</P>
    <P>I noted from a television programme recently that the accident emergency department at Temple Street Hospital was overcrowded by anxious parents. My own child suffered from meningitis when he was three years of age.  It was not the meningococcal strain but the viral strain which can be treated.  Nevertheless, I can understand the anxiety of parents.</P>
    <P>It would appear that some parents. who had gone to their general practitioners and had been reassured by them that their children had not got meningitis, still insisted on going to Temple Street Hospital.  The worry is that children who are affected and need urgent attention might be deprived of that attention if that was allowed to continue. So I ask parents who have been reassured by their GPs to accept that reassurance.</P>
    <P>The health board members are aware of the leaflet produced by the Department of Health which has been widely distributed through the health centres within the board's area and has been sent by post to anxious parents and to people who phone the health board headquarters.  General practitioners <Col N="1857" /> have been circulated to be alert to the condition in children and teenagers and advised to administer penicillin if they suspect the disease before sending the patient to hospital.</P>
    <P>At the board's meeting we were informed that the drug rifampicin has been available to all the board's hospitals.  This is a preventative antibiotic. It is given, I understand, to household or school contacts of cases as a preventative measure.</P>
    <P>There is nothing new in the upsurge of meningitis in Dublin.  It has happened before and I understand that Cork city had a similar upsurge three years ago.  It had all the features of the present one with the usual emotional response from the public and the media.  That is understandable because of the nature of the disease itself.</P>
    <P>I understand this meningitis has been on the increase in most of the European countries in recent years and that epidemics of it occur regularly in Third World countries.  It would seem, therefore, that we may have further local visitations of this disease especially during the winter months, so it behoves us to have a plan to deal with this problem.  It would appear to be absolutely essential that there should be close co-operation between hospitals, GPs, health boards and staff and that the public should be kept informed of the situation on a day to day basis wherever the disease is prevalent.</P>
    <P>I was pleased to read in today's <i>The Irish Times</i> that members of a British based organisation named &ldquo;Meningitis Research&rdquo;, whose aim is to promote a search into the cause of meningitis, will be visiting Dublin next month.  This group has come to Dublin at the invitation of parents whose children have died as a result of meningitis.  A spokesman for the parents' group, Mr. Brian Cavanagh, welcomed the recent efforts of the health boards, doctors and the media in raising awareness and responding swiftly to parents' concerns.</P>
    <P>The group is hoping that when the current crisis recedes every effort will be <Col N="1858" /> made to find the vaccine to eradicate this problem.  I understand there is no vaccine available at present but there is hope to develop one in the future; I was pleased to hear from the Minister's speech that some inroads have been made into this area in Cuba and I hope that drug can be developed and tested to relieve parents of the terrible anxiety they suffer when their children have meningitis.</P>
    <P>In conclusion, I ask the Minister to allow this group to visit the Department to reassure them of our commitment to help anxious parents to overcome this problem.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MarianMcGennis" hpid="Mrs. McGennis Mrs. McGennis">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. McGennis</NameTxt>
      <P>I thank the Leader of the House for arranging statements on this subject and I join in the congratulations to Minister Currie who is a constituency colleague of mine.  I know he will do a superb job in his new position.</P>
      <P>I requested that the Minister come in and make a statement on the increased number of cases of meningitis.  I did not refer to it as an epidemic because I was acutely aware of the fact that I did not want to say or do anything which might increase the fears of people with children who are unwell.  I accept the part of the Minister's report where he states that there is not an epidemic but there certainly is an increased number of cases, particular on the northside of Dublin.</P>
      <P>I attended a funeral less than three weeks ago of a 17 year old girl in Rush. She was a lovely, intelligent, attractive and energetic young girl.  I know her mother well; she is a friend of mine.  It was a very moving funeral anyway.  It was in response to that that I felt we had to be seen to at least comment on what was happening.  When you see large rows of schoolgirls standing outside a church mourning one of their colleagues, it is important that people in positions of power at least express our sympathies, show that we are doing something to try to contain the cause and ensure that information is made available.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I convey my sympathy to the families of those who have lost children.  The <Col N="1859" /> funerals of a two year old child the previous week and this 17 year old girl show that this disease does not discriminate. When dealing with certain illnesses, we often pay special attention to very young children.  As a mother of three children, I know the first two years are an absolute nightmare.  One is watching for temperatures and every time a child gets a temperature, he is rushed to Temple Street Hospital because the parents are worried that it is something more than just a cold, a 'flu, or a temperature itself.  This disease does not restrict itself to very young children.  As we have seen, teenage children and babies have been affected and have died.</P>
    <P>The Minister has given a very lengthy reply.  I welcome aspects of it and I am not attempting to apportion blame to anybody.  It would be a shame if we were to try to do that.  As politicians from all sides of the House, we simply need to reassure the public that we are all concerned about this and that we will all attempt to do what we can within our areas of responsibility.</P>
    <P>I am quite satisfied with the Minister's explanation of the monitoring and reporting systems but the reply does not state &mdash; or maybe it is just not clear &mdash; that the Department of Health or the health boards have discovered why there is this increase in this cluster of cases in the northside of Dublin.  I wonder if that information is available.  In the report, Temple Street Hospital said there is no common link between these cases, which rules out an epidemic but why is this?  Have we any idea why we have this increase in this specific geographic area?</P>
    <P>I also thank Senator Doyle, who is a member of the health board, because he has given additional information here today.  The fact that there were 20 more cases of meningitis in January &mdash; luckily enough they were not fatal cases &mdash; is a cause for concern and I am certainly concerned about it.  The help line and the various initiatives which the Minister took may have been helpful.  I differ <Col N="1860" /> with my colleague, Senator Finneran, in that I believe that whatever politicians do helps to a certain extent; but programmes like Marian Finnucane's programme, when she had a mother on for most of the duration of the programme explaining exactly what happened with her child, probably are much more effective.  I know it is not planned and it is not a Government intervention, but when somebody puts the human face on something like this on the public airwaves it is very effective.</P>
    <P>During the last three weeks each of my three children has come down with this 'flu bug and you do find yourself standing over their beds at one or two o'clock in the morning checking temperatures and things like that, so we owe a debt of gratitude to people like the woman who went on the programme and warned parents and advised them how this disease can become fatal within a very short time.  In one case the child would have died within 45 minutes if antibiotics had not been administered.</P>
    <P>The last point I would like to make to the Minister concerns the fact that the information leaflets and other information are distributed through health boards.  As I said, I would not have much cause to visit a health board because my children are now grown and I wonder whether we are succeeding in targeting all of the people that should know about this?  We will get mothers of very young children through the health boards, district nurses and so on, but mothers of teenagers, generally speaking, have finished with that kind of involvement with health boards.  Therefore, there is probably a need to continue putting the message out in whatever way possible to try to ensure that the target market, if you like, which is all parents of children up to maybe 20 years of age, are aware that this thing can be fatal and that it can become extremely dangerous within a period of maybe half an hour if adequate medical aid is not given.</P>
    <P>I thank the Leader again and the Minister for coming into the House today and I urge him to ensure that <Col N="1861" /> whatever can be done to even save one life is done.</P>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaloney" hpid="Mr. Maloney Mr. Maloney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Maloney</NameTxt>
      <P>I welcome the Minister to the House today as a fellow Ulsterman and wish him well in his portfolio in the new Government.  I congratulate Senator McGennis for having this very emotional matter of meningitis discussed here today in this Chamber.</P>
      <P>The pain suffered by a family which has lost a young child to a sudden or fatal illness can never be fully realised. Every sympathy must go out to the families who have suffered since the outbreak of meningitis has occurred in this country.</P>
      <P>I read an article recently that meningitis has reached epidemic proportions in one area in Dublin.  The words that were used in that paper to describe the meningitis were a little too strong.  I do not believe that there was an epidemic and papers should be very concerned about the reaction of the public to words like &ldquo;epidemic.&rdquo;  Concern grows over the levels of the potentially dangerous virus countrywide.  Four people died from bacterial meningitis in Dublin last month compared to five deaths from the condition for the whole of last year in the capital.  The upsurge in the incidents of bacterial meningitis in the Eastern Health Board area is worrying.  What is required now is a sense of alertness rather than alarm.  There is no doubt that doctors are currently on the alert for meningitis, as they would be annually around this time of year when most cases seem to occur.  There has been no major evidence to show that there has been neglect on the part of the Department of Health or the health boards in dealing with meningitis.  It is a time for the community to be concerned and to make sure that everything is being done to curtail the dangers of it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>While there has been no increase in meningococcal infection in the north west region, where I come from, during recent months the illness occurring in the Western and Eastern Health Board areas is causing concern to parents.  In the past three months one Donegal <Col N="1862" /> child was diagnosed with meningitis at the end of December and there were no cases in Sligo.</P>
    <P>We know that it occurs more commonly during the winter and spring months.  It is caused by a bacteria which is carried in the nose and throat of about 10-15 per cent of the population at any time.  Most people who carry the bacteria do not get ill; however, when illness does occur the person may become very ill very quickly.  While most people who carry the virus do not get ill, a very small number will.  Children and young adults are at greater risk of developing infection, but I read recently that one 54 year old person died of the disease also.</P>
    <P>Meningococcal infection may cause meningitis, which is an inflammation of the lining of the brain and is the more usual presentation; or it may cause septicaemia, where the infection occurs in the blood and is not confined to the brain.  Septicaemia is a much more serious form of this infection.</P>
    <P>A child affected by this disease will be unwell with a temperature, off form and off their food.  With meningitis they may have a headache and may dislike bright lights &mdash; this is one of the dominant features of the disease.  These symptoms will not occur with septicaemia. The child may develop joint pains and, more importantly, may develop a rash of red or purple spots which looks like bruises or bleeding underneath the skin.  There may also be a change in the child's level of consciousness in that he or she may be difficult to wake properly.</P>
    <P>If parents are concerned about their child they should contact their family doctor immediately and this is the message that should go out from this debate here today.  If the child is very ill and the doctor is not immediately available they should take the child &mdash; on the advice, I am sure, of everyone here &mdash; to the nearest hospital casualty department.</P>
    <P>Young adults are also more susceptible to meningococcal infection.  Many are away from home working or in third <Col N="1863" /> level colleges.  More than 7,000 students in Galway have been issued with warning letters in relation to the virus by the Western Health Board.  There have been four meningitis cases among students there, three in UCG, one in Galway regional technical college, and a 20 year old Cavan student has died from the virus.  So these are a group of people &mdash; I am talking about the student type &mdash; who are vulnerable and all care must be taken to see that they are well warned about the dangers.  When someone in this situation gets ill their friends or landlady might keep an eye on them or seek medical help if their illness gets worse.  When they are away from home they do not seem to take the care that would be given to them at home in looking after themselves.</P>
    <P>What is required now is for the community to be on the alert rather than to be alarmed, and in saying this it is not an attempt to diminish the pain and grief suffered by those parents who have lost a child.  They have suffered terrible pain and we all offer our sympathies to them; but we must also support them, as we should the rest of the community, in making sure that all information is available to help the community to tackle this deadly disease.</P>
    <Speaker pid="CathyHonan" hpid="Ms Honan Ms Honan">
      <NameTxt>Ms Honan</NameTxt>
      <P>I, too, welcome the Minister to the House, congratulate him on his appointment and wish him all the best in his new portfolio.  I also thank Senator McGennis for bringing this item to the agenda and I thank the Leader of the House for allowing us time to make statements on it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I find this issue very difficult to deal with.  It is very frightening.  When I saw it on the agenda I wondered what I was going to say, because as a mother and the wife of a general practitioner I have come into contact with people who have been exposed to meningitis.  Like Senator McGennis this year I did not experience the funeral of a child, but last year a young schoolgirl in Portlaoise died of meningitis and at the funeral I expressed the same sort of grief and <Col N="1864" /> concern that Senator McGennis spoke about this morning.  The difficulty with meningitis is that nothing can be done about it.  That is what is very frightening. I compliment all the Members here who have spoken about it in a very responsible way because this is a topic that nobody should be alarmist about.</P>
    <P>I was thinking yesterday about what I would say and I went down to my husband's surgery and in the waiting room I came across a leaflet distributed by the health promotion unit of the Department of Health.  I read it and I was impressed by the contents; it told one everything one needed to know about meningitis.  I do not know if it was distributed last week &mdash; I asked my husband where he got it and he thinks he got it from the health board; it was sent to him to distribute to the patients.  If it had been issued immediately early in January, when there were a lot of media reports about meningitis, it would have been helpful.  I do not know if it was, but I became aware of it this week.  It contains all the information anybody would need to know about meningitis.</P>
    <P>I welcome what the Minister has said today and I welcome the measures in place to monitor the disease.  This is the first time I realised that all of these measures were in place and I am reassured by them.  Anybody reading the leaflet would also feel reassured that the health boards are making information available.</P>
    <P>People are worried about the disease being contagious.  The leaflet states that it is not a highly infectious disease and it is important to realise this.  It strikes so quickly and people die so quickly that it is very frightening and hysteria about it can grow quickly.  I listened to the woman on Marian Finucane's show and I listened to the parents of the 21 month old child who died last Sunday week who were on the Gay Byrne show. In their case the difficulty was that their child did not seem to have any of the symptoms that people were being asked to look for.  It is a difficulty for parents that in a short time this becomes a fatal disease.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="1865" /> It is important that what the Minister has said today would allay the fears of a lot of people.  However, such a statement could have been issued in the middle of January when people were concerned about it.  I appreciate the difficulties for the Minister, as one does not wish to be alarmist and it is a most sensitive subject; it is a difficult issue to deal with.  If we are open and tell people what we know it can help to allay parents' fears.  I only became aware of the information leaflet yesterday but I was impressed by it.  If it had been publicised immediately and perhaps an advertisement taken in the paper, it would have been helpful.</P>
    <P>I appreciate the difficulties for the Minister and the Department.  I would be a little critical of the media in calling this an epidemic.  To most people an epidemic means a widespread incidence of the disease.  From the figures the Minister has given us today as to the number of cases reported annually, the Department obviously believed there was an increased incidence in a certain area of north County Dublin but that overall it was not an epidemic.  Perhaps &ldquo;an epidemic&rdquo; is a technical term used in the Department but that should be explained.  The media should be responsible, as it must be extremely distressing for a parent to experience the death of a child from meningitis.  Many parents would wonder if they should have gone to the doctor earlier or what they should have done or if they are to blame.  The issue needs to be treated sensitively.</P>
    <P>I welcome what the Minister has said. I have read about the vaccine being talked about that is being developed in Cuba, but I appreciate that until the World Health Organisation has thoroughly checked it out it cannot be introduced.  It is reassuring to tell people that we have a vaccine against one of the forms but as yet no vaccine is available against meningococcal meningitis.</P>
    <P>The leaflet states that antibiotics would be given to members of a family. It states that: &ldquo;The bacteria are spread between people by coughing, sneezing and kissing.  They cannot survive long <Col N="1866" /> outside the body and cannot be picked up from water supplies, swimming pools, buildings or factories.&rdquo;  Making this information public is helpful as people may be scared about the disease.</P>
    <P>I thank Senator McGennis for this opportunity to have statements on this matter.  It is good that the Minister's speech is on public record.  The public should be made aware through this leaflet around this time every year when there is, I understand, an increased incidence.  Given the media hype about the matter, taking an advertisement in the papers or publishing this leaflet at the time would have been a good idea. I thank the Minister for being here.  The debate was responsible and reasonable.</P>
    <Speaker pid="DavidNorris" hpid="Mr. Norris Mr. Norris">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norris</NameTxt>
      <P>I welcome the Minister of State to the House.  I heard him say this is not his first visit as he had been in the Chamber for committee meetings.  I am sure he shares our affection and admiration for the beautiful plasterwork.</P>
      <P>A meeting such as this in the Seanad is extremely useful and I hope it will be covered by the media.  I am sorry to see that there does not seem to be anybody present, but they may well be listening on the monitors and perhaps the Minister has issued his statement to the press.  It is important that panic should be averted in this matter.  It is extremely serious and I am well aware of it.  A friend of mine has a grandson of about 14 years of age who contracted a viral form of meningitis and it was a cause of grave concern.  It is a most unpleasant disease.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>It is important that the public be given clear, accurate and non-hysterical information in the manner that this debate, to which I have been listening, has done.  Temple Street Children's Hospital is just around the corner from where I live and on the news the other day I saw a rather harassed physician there making the point that because people did not have access to information and were not quite sure what the symptoms were, a large number of rightly concerned and responsible parents had turned up and were swamping <Col N="1867" /> the hospital with a series of symptoms that were not necessarily specific to meningitis.  They were going straight into the emergency section and clogging it up; and because every case had to be treated as if it were a case of meningococcal meningitis it was possible that medical resources could be diverted away from the real cases of infection into a generalised view.</P>
    <P>I am glad this debate took place and I congratulate Senator McGennis and Senator Henry on having instigated it.  I hope it will be widely reported in order to reduce the apprehension of parents and, principally and particularly, to reduce the pressure on our hard working medical personnel, especially in the children's hospitals.</P>
    <P>That was the only point I wished to make and I have been uncharacteristically brief.</P>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFallon" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister has indicated that he would like to make a concluding comment.  I welcome him to the House.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="AustinCurrie" hpid="Minister of State at the Department of Health (Mr. Currie) Minister of State at the Department of Health (Mr. Currie)">
      <NameTxt>Minister of State at the Department of Health (Mr. Currie)</NameTxt>
      <P>Thank you, a Chathaoirligh.  I thank all the Senators who welcomed me to the House and congratulate me.  I have listened with interest to the contributions of Senator Finneran, Senator Doyle, Senator McGennis, Senator Maloney, Senator Honan and Senator Norris.  I am impressed by the amount of preparation put into the contributions and the research done.  Some people might learn from that, but I do not want to make too much of that point.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFallon" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>You are not looking for a programme manager?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="AustinCurrie" hpid="Mr. Currie Mr. Currie">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Currie</NameTxt>
      <P>One needs to be careful with advisers at present.  I thank those who contributed to the debate and I have noted the concerns of the House in relation to this serious public health matter.  I am glad of the opportunity to reiterate the need for the early diagnosis <Col N="1868" /> and treatment of cases and suspected cases.  I join with Senator Norris in the hope that some publicity will be given to our deliberations today because it is important to reassure people and to satisfy them of our concern about this outbreak.</P>
      <P>Senator Finneran mentioned the important role which the media has played.  As my colleague the Minister for Health stated on the &ldquo;The Pat Kenny Show&rdquo; last Friday, 3 February, RTE in particular has done a great job in reporting recent cases and in bringing the symptoms and the early warning signs of the disease to the public's attention. A number of Senators mentioned how useful this service has been.  It is necessary for parents, in particular, to know the symptoms.  We must, however, strike a balance between our concern and our wish to explain the symptoms to the public and going over the top.  Mothers and fathers can be easily scared if a child is not well; this is natural.  We should be concerned, but we should not overdo it.</P>
      <P>Senator Finneran mentioned the difficulties in identifying cases due to the relationship of the symptoms to other conditions.  I agree with him that information on the disease is a central and critical aspect of the containment of it. As I said earlier, the health promotion unit has disseminated an information leaflet through the health boards, schools and other outlets.  That has been very valuable.</P>
      <P>I do not agree with Senator Finneran &mdash; perhaps this was the only area of disagreement in the proceedings &mdash; that the response of the Department was slow.  The Department and the health boards monitor the disease continuously and are aware if a major problem develops.  I believe their response was right.  He suggested that this has been a problem under successive Ministers.  I do not know whether that is the case as I can only refer to one Minister.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Senator Doyle referred to the situation in the Eastern Health Board area as reported to the board last Thursday, 2 February.  The report indicated that <Col N="1869" /> eight cases were reported in January 1994, while 20 cases were reported in January 1995.  Of these 20 cases, 14 were from the greater Dublin area, mostly from north Dublin.  Professor O'Donnell, the board's chief medical officer, mentioned on &ldquo;Morning Ireland&rdquo; on Friday, 3 February, that the cases in Dublin need to be put into perspective. Most of the cases occurred in an area with a population of approximately 400,000.  As I mentioned, those admitted to Temple Street Children's Hospital did not suffer from the same strain of the disease.</P>
    <P>Senator Finneran and Senator Doyle referred to the need for a vaccine against the disease.  Unfortunately, there is no proven, effective vaccine. Senator Doyle also referred to the visit to Dublin of the meningitis research group from the UK, who I would be happy to meet.  I also read the press report to which Senator Doyle referred and I noted a telephone number in County Antrim, which I am sure will be available.</P>
    <P>Senator McGennis expressed the fears and concerns of parents about the possibility of their children contracting the disease.  Pending a safe, effective vaccine against this form of meningitis, information is of critical importance.  I have taken note of the concerns expressed by Senator McGennis and others in relation to the key role of information.  My Department will review the method of distributing information about the disease to ensure that it reaches as wide an audience as possible.</P>
    <P>Senator McGennis asked about the possible cause of the disease in north Dublin.  By its nature this disease is sporadic and occurs occasionally in clusters in localised areas, particularly in areas of high population density, such as north Dublin or Cork city two years ago.  There is no obvious link between these cases.  Different strains of the bacterium are involved so the reasons for this particular cluster are difficult to identify.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="1870" /> Senator Maloney spoke about the possibility of the spread of meningitis among groups such as students.  He asked that that be taken into account by my Department in its review of the circulation of information about the disease and I am happy to assure him in this regard.</P>
    <P>Senator Honan's remarks about the need for balance and a proper perspective to be taken in relation to bacterial meningitis are welcome and reflect the tenor of the debate.  I am happy to take on board suggestions made by Senator Norris and I thank Senators who contributed to the debate.  As I said, their contributions were constructive and responsible and they complement the efforts of the Minister, the Department and the health boards to deal with the disease.  This debate will lessen anxiety and will contribute to our knowledge about the disease.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MauriceManning" hpid="Mr. Manning Mr. Manning">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Manning</NameTxt>
      <P>While this debate was taking place, in an act of great political courage and integrity, the Minister of State at the Department of Finance, Deputy Hogan, announced his resignation in the other House.  I applaud him for his integrity and I would like to say that he has paid a high price for what was a genuine mistake.  I am sure Members on all sides would hope that Deputy Hogan will soon find his way back into the front ranks of Government again.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFallon" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>When is it proposed to sit again?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MauriceManning" hpid="Mr. Manning Mr. Manning">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Manning</NameTxt>
      <P>At 2.30 p.m. on Wednesday, 15 February 1995.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Adjournment Matters. - Printing" RHead="of Examination Papers">
    <Title>Adjournment Matters. - Printing of Examination Papers.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="ShaneRoss" hpid="Mr. Ross Mr. Ross">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Ross</NameTxt>
      <P>It is nice to welcome the Minister to the House.  It is a change for the appropriate Minister to take the Ajournment matter on an issue on which he has knowledge and the authority to speak.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="1871" /> I am raising the subject of the printing of the junior certificate examination papers overseas because I wish to know the Government policy on this issue.  It seems there is no Government policy on the printing of leaving certificate, junior certificate or any examination papers.  I am not saying that there should be necessarily a policy to print them willy nilly in Ireland; I want him to tell me why they were not printed in Ireland but that the contract went to an overseas printing firm.  I understand &mdash; it has not yet been confirmed &mdash; that the contract has gone to a printing firm in Hertfordshire. I hope the Minister does not give me the reply, which I have received from other sources, that he is compelled, by European Union rules, to put this out to tender.</P>
    <P>I thoroughly approve of competitive forces.  Putting the contract out to tender is a laudable objective.  However, I draw the Minister's attention &mdash; it is one of the rules of the Adjournment that we do not see the Minister's reply before we ask the question but anticipate it &mdash; to the EC Directive of 1976 which is specific in saying that supply contracts of less than 200,000 European units of account can be exempted in as much as their impact on competition is limited &mdash; at today's ECU levels, that is approximately £160,000.  This contract would be exempt because it is far below the £160,000 threshold.  It is far below that threshold &mdash; it is worth between £80,000-£90,000. EU competition rules only apply when the amount is large enough to be material in EU terms.  EU rules regard a contract of this size as immaterial.  It is at the discretion of the individual State to award it to one of its national companies.  There is discontent among some of our publishing companies that this contract was awarded abroad.  The Government is not compelled to do this because of the exemption rules, of which I am sure the Minister is aware.</P>
    <P>How much money will be saved by the State in awarding this contract to Stephen Austin's printers in Hertfordshire? <Col N="1872" /> How far is this measured against employment?  How many jobs does the Minister feel have been lost as a result of this?  What will be the future policy on contracts of this sort?  The Minister can tell me if I am incorrect, if the EU directive is immaterial and this is not exempt.  The EU is specific in saying that the Government is at liberty to award this contract to an Irish company and need not put it out to competitive tender.  However, in the interest of open Government and freedom of information, of which this Government is a great champion, we might hear what the tenders were, how much is being saved by awarding this contract abroad and, indeed, what Government policy will be on contracts of this size &mdash; not above the 200,000 ECU limit &mdash; in future?</P>
    <Speaker pid="AustinCurrie" hpid="Minister of State at the Department of Education (Mr. Currie) Minister of State at the Department of Education (Mr. Currie)">
      <NameTxt>Minister of State at the Department of Education (Mr. Currie)</NameTxt>
      <P>The majority of examination question papers for my Department's 1995 certificate examinations are being printed in Ireland. The work is done within my Department and by a commercial printing firm.  The balance of the work is being undertaken under contract by a firm outside Ireland.</P>
      <P>In dealing with public contracts for the printing of examination question papers, my Department is aware of the need to obtain the services of reputable and reliable firms in the context of fair commercial competition with the objective of securing full value for public funds.  The tender for the printing of the examination question papers each year is competitive and my Department has received tenders from firms outside Ireland in the past, but this is the first occasion on which such a tender has been accepted.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The performance of firms contracted to work on the examination question papers is closely monitored each year and rigorously assessed for future reference. The performance of the firms contracted to work on the 1995 papers will be appraised in this manner prior to a decision on the printing of the papers <Col N="1873" /> for future examinations.  The opening of EU markets to Irish companies has brought considerable benefits to this country in recent years and it must be remembered that our EU partners also have access to our markets in the reciprocal arrangements that apply.</P>
    <P>That is my official reply, but since the Senator has raised other matters, I will endeavour to reply to some of them.  I have not quoted the 1976 EC regulation to which the Senator referred and we are not relying on it.  This contract was awarded to the company that made the lowest tender.  From my knowledge of the Senator, his commitment to free market principles&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFallon" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>And we know it too.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="AustinCurrie" hpid="Mr. Currie Mr. Currie">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Currie</NameTxt>
      <P>&mdash;&mdash;and value for money, I would be extremely surprised if he were to suggest that we do anything else but get value for money in this instance.</P>
      <P>The Senator asked for some information about the size of the other tenders. I am not sure that he would entirely agree with me giving out all the information he requested.  He may think that some information of a commercial nature ought to remain private and confidential; it would again be contrary to his often expressed views if I were to do anything different.  The tender was £10,000 lower than the lowest of the other five tenders received and very substantially lower than most of them.</P>
      <P>No jobs have been lost.  This Government is particularly concerned with the preservation of jobs and the creation of new ones.  We would be concerned if we felt there was any threat to jobs in this or any other area.  In this instance, we have been insistent in getting value for money and I hope the Senator will approve of that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ShaneRoss" hpid="Mr. Ross Mr. Ross">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Ross</NameTxt>
      <P>I have a supplementary question.  I fully understand the Minister's sentiments.  From my knowledge of his political career.  I am delighted that he is abandoning his commitment to isolated nationalism and is now taking <Col N="1874" /> a wider view of the world.  He is prepared to put contracts out to competitive tender and not only to award them to Irish firms.  In calculating the cost of these contracts and of awarding them to overseas companies &mdash; this decision was made by the Minister's predecessor but he must defend it &mdash; does the Department take into account the costs of transporting those exam papers backwards and forwards across the Irish Sea, the number of journeys which have to be made and the number of civil servants who have to accompany the papers and who, I gather, are necessary for security reasons in every case?  I also gather that these exam papers are transported not in one but in several loads and several journeys have to be made.  It is far more expensive to transport them from Hertfordshire than from somewhere in Ireland.  I would be grateful if the Minister could say what the comparative costs are.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="AustinCurrie" hpid="Mr. Currie Mr. Currie">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Currie</NameTxt>
      <P>There is no rule which states one should not enjoy one's politics and the Senator is obviously enjoying himself.  I had not considered that there would be any enormous expense in transporting examination papers across the Irish Sea.  The Senator referred to isolated nationalism.  He was the one who raised this matter and voiced his concern about junior certificate examination papers being printed outside the country.  British firms were allowed to submit tenders in 1992, but because of a number of circumstances which applied that year it was decided to award the contract to Irish based firms.  Having established the competitiveness of British firms, it was decided that, as in the case of all new firms, they should be invited to tender for the least sensitive examination only, that is the junior certificate.  This is not a new issue.  In 1993 and 1994 the lowest tenders were submitted by an Irish firm and the contract was awarded accordingly. This year the contract was awarded to a British firm, purely on the grounds that it submitted the lowest tender. If next year an Irish firm submits <Col N="1875" /> the lowest tender it will be awarded the contract.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Adjournment Matters. - Rathkeale" RHead="(Limerick) Circuit Court Sittings">
    <Title>Adjournment Matters. - Rathkeale (Limerick) Circuit Court Sittings.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFallon" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I welcome the Minister for Justice on her first occasion in the House.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RoryKiely" hpid="Mr. R. Kiely Mr. R. Kiely">
      <NameTxt>Mr. R. Kiely</NameTxt>
      <P>I join with you in welcoming the Minister.  I congratulate her on her appointment and wish her well, however long her appointment will last after the events of today, which I will leave aside.  I sincerely wish her well.</P>
      <P>May I share my time with Senator Neville?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFallon" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Is that agreed? Agreed.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RoryKiely" hpid="Mr. R. Kiely Mr. R. Kiely">
      <NameTxt>Mr. R. Kiely</NameTxt>
      <P>We are both concerned about the impending decision of the Department of Justice to transfer the entire Rathkeale list of Circuit Court cases to Limerick city.  The Rathkeale Circuit Court was set up by the British Government in the 1880s.  Rathkeale was one of the main towns in County Limerick at the time.  It would be a pity to see an Irish Government deciding to abandon these sittings or transferring them to Limerick.  I, accompanied by Senator Neville, was with a deputation from Rathkeale last week on other matters. Rathkeale needs assistance and not persecution.  We need to ensure that it keeps what it has.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The list of Circuit Court cases in Rathkeale over the past five or six years has been steadily increasing.  Despite the enormous efforts of Judge Kevin O' Higgins to deal with the inexorable increases in the list, he is definitely losing the battle.  A typical Circuit Court sitting in Rathkeale would consist of dealing with licensing applications, notices of motion, appeals, both civil and criminal, from the District Court and normal Circuit Court civil litigation. The court is expected to deal with all of <Col N="1876" /> this in one sitting.  Despite the fact that, in an effort to stem the tide it sits from 10.30 a.m. to 6 p.m. and sometimes later, the list is fast becoming unmanageable due to the number of cases coming in for hearing.</P>
    <P>I understand that approximately 1,600 to 1,700 civil bills are set down for trial for Limerick city and county each year. Approximately 40 of them reach trial stage.  The average delay between the date one sets a case down for hearing and the actual hearing is approximately a year and a half.  However, in some cases the delay could be as long as two and a half or three years.  This applies to Rathkeale and Limerick city and I am sure Senator Neville would agree with me.</P>
    <P>Limerick city has an average of 30 jury trials coming before the Circuit Court per year.  One must bear in mind that this is on top of other criminal cases dealt with by the Circuit Court in Limerick city.  With regard to family law, my information is that approximately 60 to 70 family law cases are added to the city court list every year.  If one looks at the Circuit Court in Limerick city alone, it is clearly evident that it has too much work coming on stream for one Circuit Court judge.</P>
    <P>In Rathkeale the civil and criminal list has been increasing inexorably over the past six to seven years and there is an average delay of eight months to three years in dealing with civil cases.  Furthermore, one should bear in mind that the Circuit Court sits in Rathkeale for four days each calender year.  The arranged sittings for 1995 are as follows: 18 January, 29 March, 21 June and 22 November.  Is it any wonder that there is a delay of 18 months and, in some cases, three years in having cases heard in Rathkeale Circuit Court, given the service I have outlined?  The people and community council of Rathkeale are aware of the facilities needed.  I am sure the council would provide the new community centre, which was the old courthouse, for sitting and I am sure Senator Neville would agree with this.  Instead of transferring sitting from the Rathkeale <Col N="1877" /> Circuit Court to the Circuit Court in Limerick, there should be an increase in the number of sittings in Rathkeale from four to at least six to deal with these cases.  The judge and the members of the legal profession servicing that area are very much in favour of retaining Circuit Court sittings in Rathkeale. The decision of the Department of justice to transfer Circuit Court cases from Rathkeale to Limerick city should be reversed and I appeal to the Minister not to interfere with Rathkeale Circuit Court but leave it as it is, or maybe have more sittings there.</P>
    <Speaker pid="DanNeville" hpid="Mr. Neville Mr. Neville">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Neville</NameTxt>
      <P>I welcome the Minister on her first visit to the Seanad and wish her well in her very responsible brief.  I thank Senator Kiely for raising this issue, which is important to the town of Rathkeale.  The word went out earlier that there was a proposal from the Department.  We now know differently. The committee under the chairmanship of Mr. Justice Spain, the President of the Circuit Court, which was established by the Minister's predecessor, Deputy Máire Geoghegan-Quinn, has not yet made its recommendations, but there is no smoke without fire.  We feel in Rathkeale that if these proposals are appearing in the press, they are coming from somewhere.  We are extremely concerned about the situation.</P>
      <P>There are four sittings a year, sometimes more.  It is very important to Rathkeale that it holds this number. Over a period of time we feel that many of the services we had in the town have been removed or downgraded.  We feel this is the start of downgrading the whole courts system and that the District Court will be next.  If the court sittings are transferred to Limerick, they will enter a system in which delays for both civil and criminal cases extend to two and half years.  The waiting period in Rathkeale is about 12 months so if you remove those sittings to Limerick you will further clog up a system which already is not operating.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>A 40-mile round trip is involved for many people in getting to Limerick and <Col N="1878" /> they are unlikely to have their cases heard on the day they travel.  This means they might have to make the journey two or three times.  In Rathkeale, however, there is an arrangement for a one day sitting when all cases are heard.</P>
    <P>In her statement of 17 January, the Minister stated, &ldquo;My Government is committed to ensuring that the courts system is organised in such a way as to give the best possible service to the public&rdquo;. I welcome that statement because decisions like this are based too often on commerciality &mdash; what is cheapest and more efficient from a monetary point of view.</P>
    <P>The Minister has said she will look at proposals to give the best possible service to the public, and that is one reason we are asking her to do so.  It is in the best interests of the public that the sittings in Rathkeale continue.  It is also in the best interests of the legal profession whose members have made submissions to the committee and have written to public representatives.  Judge Kevin O'Higgins expressed his concern about this to legal representatives and said he would be disappointed if such proposals were made.</P>
    <P>It is in the best interests of the people involved in the courts, including court staff, to have sittings in Rathkeale.  The facilities may need to be upgraded and improved but the conditions are not bad and members of the legal profession have said they are satisfied with them.</P>
    <P>We have not had a discussion about the situation in Rathkeale for some time.  Rathkeale is unique in that we have two communities; a travelling community consisting of 45 per cent of the people and a settled community consisting of 55 per cent.  We are dealing with the unique problems in a tolerant way with understanding from both communities. Even though there are extreme difficulties at times, people are dealing with them.  They want to build up their town and keep what is there. While people are often not attracted to a town like Rathkeale, it is becoming more attractive.  We want more services <Col N="1879" /> there and feel that the loss of any service &mdash; even the Circuit Court sitting four days a year &mdash; is not acceptable. The community council and chamber of commerce feel strongly that the town should not lose its Circuit Court.  I hope that the committee looking at this will see the sense of the case that Senator Kiely and I are making, but if they do not I hope the Minister will when she makes a final decision.</P>
    <Speaker pid="NoraOwen" hpid="Minister for Justice (Mrs. Owen) Nora Owen">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Justice (Mrs. Owen)</NameTxt>
      <P>I thank you, a Chathaoirligh, and Senator for welcoming me to the House.  Some of you will know that I tried to get in here through the normal, democratic process.  As I travelled the 5,000 miles around the country little did I think that my first formal visit to the Seanad would be as Minister for Justice. I am glad to be here to take this important matter on the Adjournment.</P>
      <P>I have no proposals to dispense with the sittings of the Circuit Court in Rathkeale, County Limerick.  The position is, as Senator Kiely said, that a committee was established by my predecessor, Deputy Geoghegan-Quinn, in March 1994 under the chairmanship of the President of the Circuit Court, to determine the optimum size, number of circuits and number of venues with a view to ensuring the efficient working of the Circuit Court in all areas.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Recent articles in the national press have indicated that a report on the reorganisation of the Circuit Court circuits and a review of the number of Circuit Court venues has, in fact, been finalised. I wish to point out that these articles are inaccurate and, in fact, the committee is still in the process of formulating its proposals. <Col N="1880" /> The committee has not yet submitted its proposals to me.  As soon as they are submitted they will receive my immediate consideration.  This Government is committed to ensuring that the courts system is organised in such a way as to give the best possible service to the public.  I want to reiterate that, as I said in my statement earlier this year.</P>
    <P>I should add that under the terms of section 10 of the Courts of Justice Act, 1947, the fixing of Circuit Court venues is a matter for the President of the Circuit Court in consultation with the Circuit Court judge assigned to the respective circuits.</P>
    <P>I want to thank the Senators for raising this issue and for giving me a chance, publicly in the Seanad, to clarify what have been rumours in the newspapers. Since no report has been issued I have made no decisions, although I know that a number of Senators and members of the Lower House have read of these reports in the papers.  When the report comes before me, and any recommendations it might contain &mdash; it will receive the most serious consideration.  I will not make any precipitate decisions.</P>
    <Speaker pid="RoryKiely" hpid="Mr. R. Kiely Mr. R. Kiely">
      <NameTxt>Mr. R. Kiely</NameTxt>
      <P>I thank the Minister for her reply.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DanNeville" hpid="Mr. Neville Mr. Neville">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Neville</NameTxt>
      <P>I also thank the Minister. I note that there is a slight conflict between the terms of reference, &ldquo;efficient working of the Circuit Courts&rdquo;, and the Minister's approach to it, &ldquo;the best possible service for the public&rdquo;.</P>
      <P>The Seanad adjourned at 3.30 p.m. until 2.30 p.m. on Wednesday, 15 February 1995.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
</Debate>