<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE Debate SYSTEM "../Debate.dtd"[]>
<Debate DocTitle="Seanad Debate" Day="Thu" Date="23" Month="Mar" Year="1995" Vol="142" No="10" DateIrish="Déardaoin, 23 Márta 1995" DateEnglish="Thursday, 23 March 1995" House="S" CommitteeEng="" CommitteeIr="" SubNameEng="" cnum="0">
  <MainHeading Type="Prelude" LHead="" RHead="">
    <Title>
    </Title>
    <P>
      <Col N="1225" /> Chuaigh an Cathaoirleach i gceannas ar 10.30 a.m.</P>
    <P Just="Center">
      <i>Paidir.</i>
    </P>
    <P Just="Center">
      <i>Prayer.</i>
    </P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Business" RHead="of Seanad">
    <Title>Business of Seanad.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I have notice from Senator Kelly that, on the motion for the adjournment of the House today, she proposes to raise the following matter:</P>
      <P>The need for the Minister for Education to give consideration to the proposal to establish a senior training centre for travellers in Rathkeale, County Limerick.</P>
      <P>I have also received notice from Senator Fahey of the following matter:</P>
      <P>To ask the Minister for Foreign Affairs if he will request the British Home Office to initiate a public inquiry into the circumstances surrounding the death of a person (details supplied) in London in December 1985 and the subsequent investigation, until the body was returned to his family in Galway in early February 1986.</P>
      <P>I regard the matters raised as suitable for discussion on the Adjournment and they will be taken at the conclusion of business.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Order of" RHead="Business">
    <Title>Order of Business.</Title>
    <Col N="1226" />
    <Speaker pid="MauriceManning" hpid="Mr. Manning Mr. Manning">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Manning</NameTxt>
      <P>The Order of Business today is item 1 until 1 p.m. and the format is 25 minutes for the first speaker on behalf of each group and 15 minutes for each speaker thereafter.  It is proposed, in reply to requests, especially from Senator O'Toole, that the Minister or Minister of State, whoever is replying, will take questions in the concluding period.  The Minster will therefore address the House to conclude the debate not later than 12.30 p.m. and he will then take questions.  There will be a sos and item 2 will conclude the Order of Business.  For the information of Members, the House will sit earlier than usual next Wednesday, 29 March 1995, at 11.30 a.m.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GVWright" hpid="Mr. Wright Mr. Wright">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Wright</NameTxt>
      <P>I thank the Leader of the House, the Minister and Minister of State in arranging for the format of item 1 by allowing a debate to be followed by questions.  It is a positive way of dealing with issues such as this and I welcome it.</P>
      <P>Will the Leader of the House let the House know the legislative programme between now and Easter at the sitting next Wednesday, 29 March 1995?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeOToole" hpid="Mr. O'Toole Mr. O'Toole">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Toole</NameTxt>
      <P>I agree with the Order of Business as proposed.  With regard to item 1, I thank the Leader of the House for arranging the matter in this way and also the Minister and Minister of State for co-operating with the Leader in this regard.  It should be a useful way of acquiring an understanding of the problems with the marine and I look forward to the debate.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TomFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Fitzgerald Mr. Fitzgerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Fitzgerald</NameTxt>
      <P>Last week I raised the issue of European Nature Conservation Year.  This morning we received notification in the post that the Minister for Arts, Culture and the Gaeltacht, Deputy M. Higgins, is launching the year today in Kilmainham.  It is a pity he <Col N="1227" /> did not give us more warning about the matter.  Does the Leader of the House intend to have statements or a debate on the Nature Conservation Year in the next month to six weeks?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GordonWilson" hpid="Mr. Wilson Mr. Wilson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Wilson</NameTxt>
      <P>The Framework Document has been published for two or three weeks and we have discussed it in the Seanad.  Could the Leader advise us if there is anything further that we in the Seanad, rather than the Department of Foreign Affairs or the Dáil, could do to encourage Unionist politicians to come to the table and talk?  I believe that if the Seanad sent out a statement or message, it would carry a different sort of nuance and, hopefully, a little weight to these men.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryHenry" hpid="Dr. Henry Dr. Henry">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Henry</NameTxt>
      <P>In view of the fact that there have been further problems at the blood bank, would the Leader again ask the Minister for Health when we will be able to see the special report on the Hepatitis C and anti-D globulin problem? This is causing great worry to the women involved in this issue.  The emergence of further problems there has naturally increased their anxiety.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeSherlock" hpid="Mr. Sherlock Mr. Sherlock">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Sherlock</NameTxt>
      <P>In view of the many issues which were raised during Private Members' Business last night, I ask the Leader if it is intended to have the promised plan on waste management introduced shortly.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MauriceManning" hpid="Mr. Manning Mr. Manning">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Manning</NameTxt>
      <P>I will have the legislative programme for next week later, but at the moment I can tell the House that the following Bills will be taken between now and Easter: the Civil Legal Aid Bill, which is a Seanad Bill; the Criminal Law (Incest Proceedings) (No. 2) Bill, which passed Second Stage yesterday, will be completed by Easter; the Family Law Bill is on Committee Stage here and should also be completed by Easter; the Heritage Bill is <Col N="1228" /> coming back to the House in quite an amended form from the Dáil next week; and we also take the Social Welfare Bill. These Bills are on the legislative programme and if there are any additions to that I will inform the Leader of Fianna Fáil in the Seanad.</P>
      <P>Senator Fitzgerald spoke about the Nature Conservation Year.  There will be a debate to mark this.  The Minister is in foreign fields at present. accompanying the President, so I have not been able to get a definite date from him, but this debate will take place.</P>
      <P>Senator Wilson raised an interesting question to which I do not have the answer.  Perhaps he might use his good offices with some of his Unionist friends and some of the leaders of Unionism.  If any of them wanted to address the House about their concerns, I am sure that under the provisions of Standing Orders the House would be willing to welcome them.  The Senator might be able to help us in that regard.  It would be useful for us to hear at first hand their concerns about the Framework Document.</P>
      <P>I have been a little remiss on the question raised by Senator Henry about the blood bank.  I should have come back to her with information on this. The Minister for Health has admitted very openly that there are serious problems in the blood bank and that they are being addressed.  I will contact the Senator later on the question of hepatitis C.</P>
      <P>I will contact Senator Sherlock later on the issue of waste management, which he raised.</P>
      <P>Order of Business agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Marine Policy:" RHead="Statements">
    <Title>Marine Policy: Statements</Title>
    <Speaker pid="MauriceManning" hpid="Mr. Manning Mr. Manning">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Manning</NameTxt>
      <P>This is the first occasion on which the Minister for the Marine, Deputy Coveney, has visited the Seanad.  I welcome him and thank him for the speed with which he agreed <Col N="1229" /> to have this particular debate, which is of great interest and concern to quite a number of Members.  We had a similar debate during his predecessor's term of office, which was very successful and I know that today's debate will be very useful.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="HughCoveney" hpid="Minister for the Marine (Mr. Coveney) Minister for the Marine (Mr. Coveney)">
      <NameTxt>Minister for the Marine (Mr. Coveney)</NameTxt>
      <P>It is in fact my second time in the House.  I was here for an Adjournment debate recently.  I wish to begin with an apology.  When I spoke to Senator Manning about this, I was not aware that a Government meeting was going to be called for this morning. There are at least three items on the agenda of this meeting for which I must be there.  I must, therefore, leave the House after a half an hour and I am sorry about this because I wanted to be here for the statements.  The Minister of State at my Department, Deputy Gilmore, will be here for them.</P>
      <P>I am very pleased to be here to contribute to the debate on marine policy, which is taking place at an opportune time, coinciding as it does with my announcement and that of my Minister of State, Deputy Gilmore, earlier this month of a fundamental overhaul of marine policy.  I would like to start by outlining our approach to the policy review.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The time for a fundamental overhaul of marine policy was due.  The Government's programme commits us to pursue an integrated approach to the protection and development of our marine resources.  It has been a consistent theme of debate in both Houses of the Oireachtas that we have not begun to realise the full potential of the marine sector.  The purpose of the review is to address this acknowledged deficiency.  I would like to see that potential unlocked in the interests of regional development, job creation and in the interests of national economic and social prosperity.  To do so we need to reassess policies and strategies and to <Col N="1230" /> develop a coherent vision of the future. The review will be undertaken in full consultation with the many sectoral interests in the marine area and those inputs will critically inform the process.</P>
    <P>We are taking three specific initiatives which will advance the review process in a practical way.  First, we will have a public debate on the principal issues.  The Marine Institute has been invited to arrange a series of high level public seminars focusing on the separate dimensions of marine policy.  This process will commence in June.  Secondly, we are going to bring together a high level advisory group to be known as the Marine Advisory Council.  The council will include independent experts of national and international standing to advise on longer term strategic options in marine policy.</P>
    <P>Thirdly, a major review of the organisational and management structure of the fishery service is to be undertaken by independent consultants.  This review will look at the institutional framework for the sea fisheries, aquaculture and inland fisheries sectors.  It will advise on any changes necessary to improve the coherence and efficiency of the delivery of public policies and services to those sectors.  That examination will spread right across the various agencies under the aegis of the Department of the Marine and will also include the Department itself.</P>
    <P>Since coming into office I have been listening to the views of many individuals and organisations on the present structure of the fishery service.  While there has been praise for the commitment and professionalism of the staff of the fishery service agencies, there are strong and conflicting views on its overall efficiency and coherence.  This points to the need for a review of the kind now proposed.  It also ties in with the strategic management process at the wider public sector level which is also taking place in my Department.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="1231" /> Our only agenda in this exercise is how best to harness the human and financial resources of the State's fishery services in the best interests of the sectors. The challenges arising due to pressures on fish stocks and the marine and freshwater environment and from the development opportunities presented by increased EU funding make it imperative to get the best value for money.  I am looking forward, together with the Minister of State, to taking these initiatives forward rapidly in the months ahead.</P>
    <P>Marine safety and the protection of the marine environment have an overriding priority.  There are two main dimensions to this.  First we must have in place and apply strict safety codes for various vessels.  Second, we must operate effective and efficient marine emergency services to cope when things occasionally go wrong.</P>
    <P>There is a large international dimension to marine safety legislation which is governed by the International Maritime Organisation.  The IMO Conventions are the cornerstone of maritime safety regulation throughout the world.  We will continue to give every priority to introducing into Irish law the IMO's constantly evolving standards for safety and pollution prevention.</P>
    <P>The European Union is playing an increasing role in the area of maritime safety and pollution prevention.  This role was given increased impetus as a result of the <i>Braer</i> disaster and more recently following the <i>Estonia</i> passenger ferry casualty.  The EU's Common Policy on Safe Seas provides the framework for a range of important regulatory measures covering maritime safety, and notably port state control, the international safe management code and reporting arrangements for ships carrying dangerous or polluting goods.  We will continue to participate actively at EU level to ensure that practical and enforceable standards prevail.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="1232" /> In addition to regulation, I would like to emphasise the need for education and public awareness in the marine safety area.  Our annual maritime safety awareness campaign will once again this year urge people to &ldquo;take time to think safety&rdquo; before taking to the water.  Far too many maritime accidents which lead to loss of life could be prevented if basic safety practices were observed.  While most watersports enthusiasts are responsible in matters of safety, there are many more who have yet to realise that simple safety precautions can save their lives.  We will continue to reinforce our efforts to get the message across.</P>
    <P>I am particularly mindful of some of the leisure sports which, in many cases, are self regulating in a real and tangible way.  In other cases, however, they are not self regulating.  I am particularly worried about sail boards, for example, because often in the winter months of October and November you see a person almost out of sight of land on a sailboard in quite adverse, windy weather which suits their sport.  I plan to meet some of the organisations associated with that sport because I am concerned about that.  It is just one example.</P>
    <P>On the subject of maritime transport, ports policy is focused on improving competitiveness and expanding the capacity of the international traded sectors of the Irish economy.  The policy is directed at supply side factors which will reduce costs to industry, agriculture and the tourism sectors and will improve access and competitiveness in international markets.</P>
    <P>This policy is geared to the improvement of commercial harbour infrastructure, so as to facilitate the provision of fast, reliable, direct and cost effective sea passenger and freight services.  We are looking also to achieve major changes in the management structures of the main ports and improvement in labour relations and cargo handling practices.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="1233" /> Work is well advanced on the Harbours Bill.  This will provide for the introduction of commercial semi-State structures at the bigger commercial seaports. The main thrust of this new legislation is to facilitate commercialisation and a more customer-responsive service, while ensuring accountability for operational and financial performance.</P>
    <P>The development of Irish ports will be achieved by means of an EU supported investment programme of some £140 million up to 1999 in a number of strategic ports.  Priority will be given to investment in the principal strategic ports of Cork, Dublin, Dún Laoghaire, Rosslare, Waterford and the Shannon Estuary.  A programme of investment in the main regional ports to support regional development is also planned. The reorganisation of the commercial seaports together with continued EU support for development will give the ports the flexibility they need to operate as truly commercial enterprises and will gear them up to meet the transport challenges of the future.</P>
    <P>Shipping policy must also be framed in light of our dependence on external trade, our peripheral location and the fact that we are the only EU member state without a landlink to the Continent. The key objective is to ensure that efficient, competitive and safe shipping services are available to meet the needs of Irish trade and tourism.</P>
    <P>A related objective within these parameters is to ensure that Irish-flagged vessels can compete effectively, expand and maximise jobs for Irish seafarers.</P>
    <P>The international context is very tough.  EU flagged vessels in general have come under severe pressure during the past decade or so from flags of convenience. The EU share of the world fleet has declined from 30 per cent in 1980 to 15 per cent today.  Employment opportunities for EU seafarers have been severely curtailed by the availability of third world crews at one-third or less of the cost of EU seafarers.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="1234" /> Against this difficult background we are undertaking a review of Irish shipping policy in consultation with the social partners.  This will be concluded later this year.  The strategic objective under the review is to enable Irish shipping companies to meet international competition under comparable cost conditions without compromising on safety. That is, I must admit, a difficult objective.</P>
    <P>The Operational Programme for Fisheries 1994-1999, under the second Community Support Framework, was launched on 21 February.  The programme is intended to deliver integrated development in the fleet, aquaculture, processing, marine research, fishery harbours and training.  The total investment package for the period is £140 million.</P>
    <P>The primary objectives of the programme are to maintain and strengthen the contribution of the fisheries sector to the national economy and to support economic development and long term job creation in coastal communities. Though it is not enough, it will, I hope, create and sustain investment confidence and provide a sound basis for expansion and growth.</P>
    <P>The agreement reached at the Fisheries Council in last December on the integration of Spain and Portugal into the Common Fisheries Policy was a satisfactory outcome for Ireland in all the circumstances.  I believe it will provide continuing protection for the Irish fishing industry.  Since December much work and tough negotiations have gone into translating this broad political agreement into hard and binding arrangements.  We have maintained a determined approach in these negotiations to ensure that the arrangements will provide for a stringent and effective management of fishing effort, and in particular for real control and enforcement.</P>
    <P>In the negotiations we secured a number of key concessions.  There will be no <Col N="1235" /> increase in the quotas available in Irish waters to Spanish vessels.  Spanish fishing effort is to be maintained at its present level with a maximum of 93 vessels at any one time, and, significantly, will continue to be distributed on the basis of existing geographic spread.  We have nonetheless managed to secure continuing recognition of and protection for the Irish Box.  Spanish vessels will be totally excluded from the Irish Sea and only 40 named Spanish vessels of the total of 93 will be allowed to fish in other parts of the Irish Box.  These 40 vessels will continue to be distributed in accordance with the existing geographic spread, which is a favourable arrangement from Ireland's point of view.</P>
    <P>One of our major objectives was to ensure that the control and enforcement provisions would be stringent and effective. I am happy to say that a number of our proposals, notably the proposals on catch reporting and a greatly enhanced role for the coastal state, were included in the final agreement.  From January 1998 Spanish vessels will be required to report their catch to this country, not to their own as has been the case.  We all know the results of that.</P>
    <P>I am determined that we are going to have a more effective enforcement system. We also have two new Casa spotter aircraft, ironically built in Spain, which will greatly enhance the effectiveness of the naval effort to target Spanish vessels that we want to inspect.  We also managed to secure recognition of the heavy financial burden faced by Ireland in respect of fishing surveillance by getting a firm commitment at Council giving us additional financial resources not just for the capital costs but also, for the first time, for running costs.</P>
    <P>I wish to brief the House on Ireland's position on the contentious fishing dispute between the European Union and Canada and to explain the rationale for our position.  Throughout this dispute, which had been simmering for some <Col N="1236" /> time, we have constantly urged restraint on both sides and have encouraged efforts to reach a negotiated solution. That settlement must be mutually acceptable and lasting, one which will allow for fair distribution, proper controls and protection of stocks and which will safeguard Canada's rightful interests.  I am hopeful, now that the situation has been defused somewhat, that substantive talks along these lines can get underway.</P>
    <P>I wish to set the record straight on the background to this dispute since there are any number of misconceptions floating around.  The North Atlantic Fisheries Organisation &mdash; NAFO &mdash; regulates fisheries in the international waters of the north-west Atlantic, outside Canada's 200-mile limit.  Its members include Canada, the EU, Iceland, Cuba, Russia, Norway, Japan and Poland. Ireland has no fishing rights in the area so we are essentially a disinterested party in the matter.</P>
    <P>Last October, NAFO set a 1995 total allowable catch for turbot of 27,000 tonnes.  This was a steep reduction by reference to previous years' catches. Canada argued successfully that the cut was necessary to protect the viability of the stock.  Following a majority decision in the EU &mdash; opposed by Spain and Portugal &mdash; the EU's single vote in NAFO was cast in favour of the lower TAC. Last month, however, NAFO voted by 6 votes to 5 &mdash; EU against &mdash; to allocate 60 per cent of the TAC to Canada and a mere 12.5 per cent to the EU, that is, 16,000 tonnes and 3,400 tonnes respectively. The remainder of the TAC was distributed to other NAFO states.</P>
    <P>The EU could not accept this share out which does not reflect historic catching patterns and accordingly lodged an objection procedure under NAFO rules. Canada reacted strongly.  Instead of negotiating through the procedures available, Canada used domestic law to take the right to stop Spanish boats in international waters.  The arrest of the <i>Estai</i> followed.  I wish to emphasise that this was not an argument about the total catch; it was an argument about how it <Col N="1237" /> should be distributed.  It is not right to say that this is an argument about the Spaniards wanting to increase the quantity and the Canadians opposing that.  It is about the distribution among the nations within NAFO.</P>
    <P>We fully understand Canada's concerns. We support their call for conservation and we appreciate their frustration given that their own fisheries have been virtually fished out, largely by themselves.  That being said, it is wholly unacceptable that any State should give itself powers to stop or arrest vessels of another State in international waters.  It must also be said that the quota allocated by NAFO to the EU was seriously unsatisfactory and inequitable.</P>
    <P>Ireland has not, and will not, break ranks with the EU on this issue.  In principle and in practice that position is in our own best interests.  We agree that illegal or irresponsible fishing must be dealt with resolutely and we will do that in our waters.  We are at the forefront in pressing for tighter controls and enforcement within the EU on fleets that do not toe the line.  However, the problems should not be tackled by unilateral and illegal actions.  The EU, Canada and all NAFO members must face up to their joint responsibilities for management, control and conservation of stocks in the Grand Banks area.  They must do it around the table, not by brinkmanship.  The latter, in my view, is a recipe for chaos and we are working hard with the Canadians and the European Union to bring about a reasonable compromise.  We met with the Canadian Minister, Brian Tobin, about a month ago in this regard.</P>
    <P>There will be further development of infrastructure and facilities at priority fishing harbours to cater for the needs of the fishing sector and to meet EU safety and hygiene requirements.  We will also support, as far as resources permit, upgrading of local harbour infrastructures to cope with the rapid expansion of the aquaculture sector and local economic activity generally.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="1238" /> The level of investment in recent years falls far short of actual needs.  In the trips I have made to various fishery harbours, large and small, I have seen a great need for such investment.  That investment would trigger local effort and the creation of local employment.  I will, therefore, make every effort to secure additional funding to address the gap as far as possible.  The lack of facilities and general underdevelopment of our fishing harbours is difficult to justify given their importance for coastal regions and communities.</P>
    <P>Aquaculture offers important development opportunities for coastal regions with few, if any, alternative prospects for employment.  It is still a relatively young industry in Irish terms but has grown quickly in the last 15 years to a point where it now accounts for 25 per cent of the value of our total fish production.  Over 1,000 people are employed full time in aquaculture with a further 3,000 in part time jobs.  Total output is now valued at over £50 million and could double to over £100 million by 1999.  Investment under the operational programme will sustain existing jobs and production and generate new employment in the sector and in processing where aquaculture is increasingly a key supplier of raw material.</P>
    <P>There is a clear consensus right across the spectrum of interests on the need to put in place a new framework which will ensure that aquaculture development is securely underpinned by a streamlined transparent licensing process in the interests of the industry and all other concerns.  The legislation governing aquaculture is almost 15 years old.  It pre-dates significant aquaculture development in Ireland.  An overhaul is long overdue to reflect changed conditions, new thinking and the needs of all concerned.  It will also contribute to sustainable and balanced management of the coastal zone.</P>
    <P>We hope to bring forward proposals fairly soon which will address the issues comprehensively and which duly reflect the needs and concerns of all parties. The Minister of State at the Department <Col N="1239" /> of the Marine is deeply involved in that matter.</P>
    <P>I wish to take this opportunity to comment on the compatibility of salmon farming and sea trout angling or, perhaps, the lack of compatibility.  I am firmly of the view that there is room for both.  The sea trout task force report has given us a practical and sensible blueprint for the way forward.  The programme of action, based on the task force report and informed by ongoing scientific research, is being implemented as a high priority.</P>
    <P>The national objective must be to combine the sustainable development of salmon farming with the preservation of sea trout as an important contribution to local economies and jobs.  The action taken to date appears to be paying dividends in that sea trout stocks have shown encouraging signs of recovery.  It will be a long haul, however, and will take wholehearted commitment and cooperation and some compromise on all sides for the foreseeable future.</P>
    <P>Our inland fisheries are a valuable resource.  Concentrated mainly in the more disadvantaged areas of the country, they offer significant opportunities for jobs and economic activity.  The full potential of our inland fisheries will be realised through strategies for the management, protection, development, conservation and also the marketing of this valuable natural resource.</P>
    <P>The Exchequer grant to support the work of the fisheries boards in 1995 is in excess of £10 million.  In addition, significant EU Structural Funding will support investment of some £19 million up to 1999 in the conservation, development and protection of our rivers, lakes and fish stocks.  This will contribute directly to an enhanced angling tourism product with consequent generation of jobs and revenue.</P>
    <P>The development of our marine resources will be underpinned by the national marine research effort.  I am sure Senators will welcome the enhanced funding provided for the research component in the fisheries <Col N="1240" /> operational programme.  This investment of £8 million will be directed towards project based research to underpin the development of the marine sectors, upgrade infrastructure and to provide an enhanced research vessel capability.</P>
    <P>That programme is being implemented and administered by the Marine Institute in conjunction with the Department.  An enhanced grant allocation of £850,000 has also been provided to the Marine Institute for 1995. This is a significant increase compared with its 1994 allocation and will enable the institute to position itself well to oversee the national marine research effort and deliver on its statutory remit. The Marine Institute is really in its infancy, but I have great hopes for the contribution which it will make to the overall development of the marine sector as it has a first class chief executive with many ideas, initiative and energy.</P>
    <P>I have highlighted some of the main themes which will occupy me during my time as Minister for the Marine.  The Marine has a valuable contribution to make to national development and I am fully committed to realising that potential.</P>
    <P>We face big challenges; a growing economy and ever increasing use of the marine resource brings increased risks to the marine environment and to safety.  The pressures for development of the public marine resource lead to competition over the use and increase of the resource, which is very evident in many coastal areas where conflicts arise between the needs of leisure for marinas and the crowding of harbours with commercial use by fisheries and so on. These conflicts have to be resolved at local rather than national level, which I am anxious to develop a means of doing.  We must strike the balance between development and conservation in the interests of all beneficiaries of our marine resource.</P>
    <P>I look forward to hearing the contributions from the floor.  I apologise again that I have to leave, but the Minister of State, Deputy Gilmore, will be here.</P>
    <Col N="1241" />
    <Speaker pid="DenisDinoCregan" hpid="Mr. Cregan Mr. Cregan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cregan</NameTxt>
      <P>Before the Minister leaves, I wish to take the opportunity to welcome him to the House.  It is a great honour for me, as a Senator who has represented the Cork South Central area for the last ten years, to see, at long last, Deputy Coveney sitting in this House as Minister for Defence and the Marine.  I congratulate him on his appointment.  He made a great contribution here this morning and has put a great deal of work into the Departments of the Marine and Defence since the first week he took over.</P>
      <P>We have opposed each other at times but at other times, we have knocked on doors together.  I am delighted that, at long last, Deputy Coveney is a Minister, not alone for his contribution to the Departments of the Marine and Defence, but for his contribution to the country generally.  He will be a very fine Minister and for a very long time to come we will have the opportunity of using his ability, concern, interest and, most importantly, his motivation.  He is a highly motivated person&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="HughCoveney" hpid="Mr. Coveney Mr. Coveney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Coveney</NameTxt>
      <P>I did not expect this.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Neither did I.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DenisDinoCregan" hpid="Mr. Cregan Mr. Cregan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cregan</NameTxt>
      <P>I take pride in the fact that I always said that Deputy Coveney had the ability to be a Minister.  It is long overdue and I wish him well on behalf of the people of Cork, in particular. I am also delighted to see that he has recognised that Cork should come first.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="HughCoveney" hpid="Mr. Coveney Mr. Coveney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Coveney</NameTxt>
      <P>This is a much nicer House than the other one.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TomFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Fitzgerald Mr. Fitzgerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Fitzgerald</NameTxt>
      <P>I also welcome the Minister to the House and congratulate him on his appointment.  I understand why he has to leave; it is not always easy to arrange to be everywhere one wants to be.  However, he should come to Dingle in the next couple of weeks and we can have a chat.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1242" />
    <Speaker pid="HughCoveney" hpid="Mr. Coveney Mr. Coveney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Coveney</NameTxt>
      <P>I am going there at the end of April.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TomFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Fitzgerald Mr. Fitzgerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Fitzgerald</NameTxt>
      <P>I wish him well and thank him for coming to the House.  I am sure that the Minister of State, Deputy Gilmore, will be an able replacement; he also spends a great deal of his time in Kerry.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="HughCoveney" hpid="Mr. Coveney Mr. Coveney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Coveney</NameTxt>
      <P>Thank you.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TomFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Fitzgerald Mr. Fitzgerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Fitzgerald</NameTxt>
      <P>I am delighted to have this opportunity to respond to the programme for fishing development for 1994-96.  I welcome the Minister of State, Deputy Gilmore, to the House. We will have a question and answer session later, but we will not be too hard on him.  Any criticisms which I make today are not personal criticisms of the Minister or the Minister of State but of errors which were made in the whole fisheries programme over the years regardless of who the Minister was, as he is only the office holder.</P>
      <P>I am very critical of this document.  It covers everything, but I do not know how anybody could stand over a document which can only give us information up to 1992.  In any small business in the country the manager can press a button and say how much he owes and is owed up to the previous day, but the information in this document only goes up to 1992.  We do not know the figures for the landings of fish after 1992.  In this day and age the Department of the Marine must know how much was landed in the last week, month and year. How can the Department plan for the future when it has no idea what happened in 1993 or 1994?  The figures should be up to date.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The document refers only briefly to the fishing fleet and says that there are currently 1,460 vessels on the Irish fishing register, which is about 56,000 gross tonnage.  According to my calculations, that is an average of 40 tonnes per boat. If the Minister is to plan ahead, he needs to know how many half deckers, 30 foot, 40 foot, 50 foot and 60 foot boats and how many long distance <Col N="1243" /> boats, from 80 foot upwards, are in the fleet; what their capacity is and what kind of equipment they have on board.</P>
    <P>We need to know the up to date landing figures and the size of the fleet. Senator Daly and I have the opportunity to give our views on this today, but we do not have these figures.  I am very critical of those in the Department of the Marine who compile these figures.</P>
    <P>I know that it will never happen, but if I was the Minister for the Marine I would not have launched a document such as this in Kilmainham, as it is old hat and I have seen it all before.  There is a new document every couple of years with great ideas for the next three or four years, but nothing happens unless somebody puts in the boot.  Dingle would never have been developed but for Senator Daly and the former Taoiseach, Mr. Haughey.  Pressure was put on to develop Dingle, but the Department was totally against it.  I will not make an issue of this, but we can see it is a success story today.  The Minister of State knows Dingle and he can see the figures up to 1992; the face of the town and the peninsula has been changed and there has been much job creation.</P>
    <P>I also stand over the Minister's decision at that time to issue 20 licences for boats to go to the continental shelf to fish for uncaught quotas.  Up to 12 of those licences went to Dingle and good use was made of them; the landings of fish there have increased.  There were many complaints from other ports around the coast that Dingle was getting everything but I believe eight of those licences have still not been issued by the Department.  If they have not been issued, there is room for them in Dingle and they should go there as quickly as possible.</P>
    <Speaker pid="DenisDinoCregan" hpid="Mr. Cregan Mr. Cregan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cregan</NameTxt>
      <P>There is room in Kerry for everything.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TomFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Fitzgerald Mr. Fitzgerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Fitzgerald</NameTxt>
      <P>The document mentions the fleet.  After all the years spent developing the fishing industry, it is <Col N="1244" /> strange that the Department or whoever is responsible for this report would stand over what is said about our fleet. The different segments of fishing are outlined and on segment II it reads:</P>
      <P>Much of the fleet is old and lacks the facilities and equipment available to modern vessels.  Working conditions for crew on deck can be extremely dangerous.</P>
      <P>It goes on to say that vessels in segment II fish for whitefish, etc.  The report says we must cut down on the stocks and the authors almost praise themselves for reducing the amount of fish we catch:</P>
      <P>In recent years, given the poor state of stocks in Area VIIA, a considerable reduction has been achieved[.]</P>
      <P>What is wrong with the Department? What we should want to do is catch fish and make this a better place to live, yet here the Department is putting itself on a pedestal for reducing the amount of fish caught.  I hope Senator Daly is listening.  Not only that, but the Department is proud to state that in this document. I ask the Minister to speak to those responsible for the report.</P>
      <P>On segment III, the report states:</P>
      <P>Vessels in Segment III fish for generally high value ... species[.]  The boats in this segment are in general over 20 years of age.</P>
      <P>The boats in segment IV are also over 20 years old and of poor quality; they need to be replaced.  Basically we have no fleet.  No one would want to drive a 20 year old car in which the speedometer, the fuel gauge and the hand-brake did not work, and where the driver needed three hands &mdash; one to turn the key, one to pull the choke and one to pull the starter.  Is that the kind of boats we have and if so, why?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Money must be invested in the fleet, but the sums mentioned in the report are not enough.  If the money cannot be put into the fleet we must turn to people in the private sector who have the money and ask them to invest, buy boats and hire crews &mdash; it does not matter <Col N="1245" /> if we have to go to Spain and France for them.  We in Ireland do not have deckhands or crews because we are not training them properly for fishing. There is a little school in Greencastle, but it is useless.  I visited it when I was a director of BIM and it made me sad.</P>
    <P>To organise training, fisherman and the training sector must come together. If I had a boat, I would take on an apprentice who would fish with me for six months or some other period until we see if he is able to fish.  I was sent one trainee from Greencastle.  I took him salmon fishing with me &mdash; that trip was semi-legal.  The trainee lasted one week, although he was being well paid after coming from Greencastle.  Everyday he had terrible seasickness and was not fit for fishing.  He disappeared.</P>
    <P>The trainees should be given three to six months on the boat and then returned to the school to learn a deckhand's skills &mdash; splicing ropes and wires, mending nets, cleaning decks &mdash; or the skills for the engine room or those of a navigator.  A young man can to learn about fishing in Greencastle and get a certificate, but it is useless to him because he has not yet set foot on a boat.  The first day he goes to sea he will be extremely sick.  Before the Minister concludes, I ask him to give the figures for people trained in Greencastle over the last five years and to say whether they are fishing today or if all the training has been wasted.</P>
    <P>The fishing industry and the way it is seen by the Department both need major re-organisation.  We are quickly going down the drain, so it is great to see an occasional success story.  I want to mention a Donegal man, Mr. Kevin McHugh, and his new boat.  An Leas-Chathaoirleach will tell me I should not use names but I will say good things about him.  An Leas-Chathaoirleach probably knows the man well.  I was on the board of BIM in 1989 which did not want to give Mr. McHugh a grant for his boat.  He bought the boat, forced the board into helping him and we can see today what he has done for the fishing industry.  These are strange times.  I support <Col N="1246" /> many of the activities pursued by BIM; but in that case it was being held back by the Department of the Marine and the Department of Finance, instead of giving BIM its head and allowing it to develop the fishing industry.</P>
    <P>I have spent too long on this topic, so I will deal with other matters.  I have spoken for years about conservation. particularly of lobsters.  I have written letters to the Department to allow lobster pots with escape holes, as are used in other countries.  These have an entrance for lobsters but there is also a small hole near the bottom of the pot so small lobsters can escape.  Lobster fishers will not catch as many small lobsters. There is a disadvantage in using these pots because other small predators can come in the hole and eat the bait, so perhaps it may not be as good as it should be.</P>
    <P>However, there are problems all over the coast at present.  I fished lobster between 1978 and 1984.  On average, I caught about 50 dozen lobsters a week each summer.  I am told that a person doing the same amount of fishing with the same boat and the same number of pots would be lucky to catch two to three dozen a week now.  I have to check if those figures are accurate.</P>
    <P>Our training is not good enough.  We have no fleet and it is necessary to invest money in a fleet.  We have to think of conservation.  To be honest, I do not think of aquaculture as fishing.  I am against it but it is not in the same category as boats, fishing and nets.  It is different.  Aquaculture is an investment for rich people who can get money back from it but, in my book, it does not constitute fishing in any form.</P>
    <P>If we have a fleet, we need landing facilities.  I would be less than honest if I did not say that we have landing places.  In fairness, we have reasonably good landing places but they need to be upgraded.  Many things are essential in these ports.  The five main ports are Donegal, Rossaveel, Castletownbere, Dunmore East and Howth.  Dingle follows close behind them.  The on-shore facilities for upgrading the quality of <Col N="1247" /> fish are not there.  It is ludicrous to see a man standing on a fish box on the pier in the Dingle auctioning fish.  It is not right in this modern day that such a thing is happening.</P>
    <P>The former Minister said that there is not much point in having a good fishing fleet and harbours if one does not have a road from the port.  A proper road is essential.  If one is trying to get out of Castletownbere at 4 a.m. and heading off for Spain or France with an articulated truck loaded with 25 or 30 tonnes of fish, one finds that the first 25 or 30 miles of road out of Castletownbere are brutal.  It is the same in Dingle.  Dunmore East and Donegal are just as bad. If a person is going from Killybegs to Spain with an articulated lorry, by the time they get to Dublin or another Irish port, they feel as if they are halfway to Spain because the heavy work is over. The Minister should have talks with the Department of the Environment about improving the road network to the main ports.  I am not looking for dual carriageways or a major road.  I just ask that they be upgraded and improved because of the nature of the traffic using them.</P>
    <P>What happened to the £6 or £7 billion we were to get?  Why is such a small amount of it going into fishing?  Let us be fair and honest.  It is my belief that, over the years, fishing was the ransom paid to free agriculture and other businesses. That is my gut feeling.  Surely at this late stage there should be some compensation from the other sectors.  I would fight very hard and support the Minister of State and the Minister, Deputy Coveney, in their efforts to get some extra money.</P>
    <P>One has only to observe the advantage fishing has above anything else. One could get a 100 acre farm for nothing but one would have to buy cows and set a crop.  There is labour and expense involved.  However, if one was given a boat, all one would have to do is go out in it because everything one takes out of the water is free.  It does not have to be set and it does not have to <Col N="1248" /> grow.  All one has to do is take care of the fish stocks.</P>
    <P>I ask the Minister, why, considering all the money we will get, we could not have fixed up another two or three ports.  I think of ports such as Union Hall in Cork, Helvick in the Gaeltacht or our own place in Dingle.  Ballydavid is wide open.  I could never understand why Ballydavid, in the Dingle Gaeltacht, was never developed.  It is within five minutes on a boat of the richest fishing grounds in Europe and there was never any development there.</P>
    <P>Both the Minister of State and the Minister must have been very disappointed at the money allocated for the development of fishing over the years.  I believe the Minister of State's portfolio has been downgraded.  Initially there was a Minister for Fisheries who looked after nothing but fisheries.  I think Tom Fitzpatrick was the first Minister for Fisheries.  It subsequently was tied in with Defence and the Marine, which covers everything.  The Department has been downgraded.  Ministers with other portfolios in all Governments could not care less about fishing.  They think it is like the hind teat of the cow and they do not care.  They believe it is useless and they said: &ldquo;Give it to Eamon Gilmore and Hugh Coveney.  Let them look after it and take it out of our way&rdquo;. I have some advice for the Minister of State.  He should be like Senator Daly when he was Minister: stand his ground and dig in.  He should not be like the Minister.  He should not take &ldquo;no&rdquo; for an answer.  He should just tell the civil servants how he wants to do things and what he is going to do.  They have been proved wrong over the years and all the advisers have been wrong.  If they had not been wrong, we would not be in the mess we are in today.  Their greatest boast is that they have succeeded in reducing the catch of fish.  I could be here all day if we were to sit down and have a nice quiet chat about all the aspects.</P>
    <P>I will be asking the Minister of State a few questions later.  I am very disappointed about the overall amount of <Col N="1249" /> money allowed to keep fishing going over the next three or four years.  I am also disappointed that the Department has not learnt over the years to be up to date with their facts and figures.  I am disappointed that there is not a proper plan for the modernisation of the fleet. To be truthful, it is only a Mickey Mouse plan giving a couple of pounds here and there.  That will not do.  Considering the age of the boats, there is a need for major investment.</P>
    <P>There is also a need for on shore port facilities.  We do not have a good ice plant in Dingle.  If the Minister of State visits Dingle, I will show him the situation. If one puts ice on fish and allows it to rest for two or three hours until the ice starts to melt, the fish changes colour because the ice is not clean.  It is unhygienic. There was an application for planning permission to build an ice plant on the pier in Dingle.  I went to a senior official of Kerry County Council to inquire as to whether the planning permission would be granted.  He said it would be granted over his dead body.  If this is the attitude of county councils to the development of fishery harbours we will never have ice plants.</P>
    <P>I extend an invitation to the Minister to come to Dingle at any time.  People will be happy to point out the facts to him.  The Minister and the Minister of State would be as welcome as the flowers in May.  We will try to show them the problems which exist and for which we are seeking money.</P>
    <P>I look forward, as I am sure the Minister does, to the introduction of the Harbours Bill, which will include the designation of Dingle as a major fishery harbour centre.  This is covered by three lines in the Bill.  I wrote to the former Minister and asked him to deal with Dingle in a separate Bill, before he introduced the main Bill.  This matter could be dealt with in five minutes in the Seanad.</P>
    <P>I am very disappointed with the plans. However, I am most disappointed with the overall allocation of money.  If we had the required money we would have everything.</P>
    <Col N="1250" />
    <Speaker pid="LouisBelton" hpid="Mr. Belton Mr. Belton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Belton</NameTxt>
      <P>I wish to share my time with some of my colleagues.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaloney" hpid="Acting Chairman (Mr. Maloney) Acting Chairman (Mr. Maloney)">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman (Mr. Maloney)</NameTxt>
      <P>Is that agreed?  Agreed.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LouisBelton" hpid="Mr. Belton Mr. Belton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Belton</NameTxt>
      <P>I welcome the Minister to the House.  I wish to concentrate on the inland fisheries element of marine policy and I was interested to hear the Minister's comments this morning when he stated:</P>
      <P>Concentrated mainly in the more disadvantaged areas of the country they offer significant opportunities for jobs and economic activity.  The full potential of our inland fisheries will be realised through strategies for the management, protection, development, conservation and also the marketing of this valuable natural resource.</P>
      <P>I have a copy of a policy document produced by the South Inny Anglers' Club. This is a small club on the Inny River, a tributary of the River Shannon in counties Longford, Westmeath and Cavan. The document covers a general approach to the development of inland fishing and the tourism potential of coarse and trout fishing.  I mention this document because its broad policy would be suitable for all areas in the midlands and east midlands tourism area, where there are numerous fresh water lakes and rivers.  There is huge potential for this industry, which is growing steadily.</P>
      <P>Inland fishing by tourists has a great spin off for the community because these people tend to stay in small hotels or pub accommodation.  They spend their day on the lake or river and in the evenings they are prepared to have their meals and a few pints and go to whatever local entertainment is available. They tend to fit into the natural environment and entertainment which already exists.  The general input in terms of the national economy is quite small and this is all the more reason why resources should be concentrated on restocking rivers and lakes and so on.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="1251" /> There is a huge need to develop off-the-bank fishing.  For example, on the River Shannon at Lanesboro, there is an inflow of warm water at the power station.  The area has huge fishing potential and there is a great concentration of anglers there.  For some time, the local tourism committee has been calling for better facilities on the river banks.  This applies to most fishing areas in the midlands.</P>
    <P>Traditionally, this part of the country has not been tourism oriented, but in latter years the people are fighting back. They are coming together and there is a great realisation that this natural asset can be developed.  It can be shared and it can add to the national economy.  An increasing number of people are becoming interested in providing accommodation and entertainment facilities for tourists who come to fish.</P>
    <P>This natural asset should be developed, but it is important that it is also looked after in terms of pollution control.  There must be a co-ordinated approach in order to maintain the huge potential of this asset.  It is also important that the Minister and his Department, through the various regional fishery boards, concentrate on this matter.  I am glad the Minister is bringing forward a policy in that regard, given that extra EU funding for fishing has been approved.</P>
    <P>I have experience of dealing with the excellent staff of the regional fishery boards.  I am sure Senator Daly agrees that they are excellent.  I also have experience of local angling clubs and if they want any help or advice the officers of the regional boards are willing to oblige.  They will turn up at night, after office hours, to meet these people.  They have great enthusiasm and interest, which encourages other people to realise that this area has developmental potential for the future.</P>
    <P>We are capable of presenting fishing in this country as being as good as, if not better than, in any other country.  There is a huge market on our doorstep.  An enormous number of people from <Col N="1252" /> Britain could be attracted to come here to fish.  All they want is good clean water and good facilities at a reasonable price.  This is also important.  I wish the Minister well in his role.</P>
    <Speaker pid="DenisDinoCregan" hpid="Mr. Cregan Mr. Cregan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cregan</NameTxt>
      <P>I wish to share my time with Senator Cotter.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Acting Chairman Acting Chairman">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman</NameTxt>
      <P>Is that agreed? Agreed.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DenisDinoCregan" hpid="Mr. Cregan Mr. Cregan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cregan</NameTxt>
      <P>I welcome the Minister to the House.  I listened to Senator Fitzgerald talking about the problems associated with fishing.  However, I wonder if he is correct in saying there is an unfortunate impression that the Departments of the Marine and Defence are considered to be in a lower class to other ministries.  If so, it would be most unfair.</P>
      <P>The Senator mentioned the potential of fishing.  I come from a city but I live quite near the sea in Cork and we are aware of the value and potential of fishing.</P>
      <P>It is a sad that we have to argue &mdash; and a good argument was made before Christmas &mdash; about other countries, Spain in particular, being allowed into the Irish Box.  Having listened to Senator Fitzgerald I wonder if we have a policy of continuing the way we are going.  I understand the financial aspect. There is a view that County Donegal, in particular Killybegs, is doing exceptionally well from fishing.  It has the biggest boat ever bought for Irish fishing.  Why should we not have a policy where we give an incentive by buying a big boat for each of the big fishing ports?  I do not deny it would be costly, but if it can be done in Donegal there is no reason why it cannot be done in other areas.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I wish to refer to the harbours legislation as I am involved with the Cork Harbour Commissioners and I am particularly conscious of the work of the harbours.  With regard to competition between harbours, will we be taking the right approach in the Harbours Bills that will be introduced?  Are we taking enough account of what is happening in <Col N="1253" /> harbour areas?  Cork port is doing exceptionally well, but there is no reason why it could not do better.  There is a danger that we are creating competition between ports, particularly on the east and west coasts.</P>
    <P>I know how much the Minister of State is involved in the Harbours Bills, and I know he and the Minister are aware that we are the only EU member not linked directly to Europe.  We should be making a strong case at EU level for finance to develop proper shipping, safety precautions and the harbour areas, particularly the development of the industrial areas within the harbours.</P>
    <P>I was involved in the setting up of Cork Freeport.  In theory the legislation relating to it was excellent, but it is not working satisfactorily in practice with regard to the opportunities our harbour facilities afford that other countries do not have &mdash; the opportunity to get a fast turnaround for heavy shipping, for example.  I am conscious of the moneys that have been spent over the last ten to 12 years on deep water berths in Cork and Dublin and the development of Dublin and Rosslare, but we should be looking at opportunities we are not presently availing of.  We should be taking advantage of the fast turn around for heavy shipping, for example.  We should be giving the facilities; we have the workforce and the experience.</P>
    <P>We must look at the type of shipping coming to Ireland and the comparative cost of the Irish worker.  The loss of 30 per cent of the total shipping in the world down to 15 per cent over a ten year period is discouraging and worrying. Before we have any further consideration of the Harbours Bills it is important to have discussions with local groups, as is stated in the policy review. As Senator Fitzgerald and others said, it is important to listen to those who know best.  I know the Minister of State will do that.  It is important we do not have a situation where there is competition between each port, particularly on the east coast.  There is already great competition for business between Rosslare. Dublin and Cork.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="1254" /> Why is it that at EU level there are objections by other nations to have extra passenger shipping leaving Cork and Rosslare?  Why do the French authorities object to these extra shipping routes?  They would not give the opportunity to Irish Ferries to use other ports in France.  There a lot of traffic between Cork and Rosslare and Roscoff, and it is good business for Ireland and France. France does well from Irish tourists and French people like to come to Ireland. I object to a situation where the chamber of commerce of Brest was prepared to give docking facilities for ferries coming from Cork and Rosslare but it was objected to by the French authorities. I would like to know why they got away with that.  We could not get away with it as we could not make objections as easily as the French.  If they are objecting and are prepared to say that they do not need to use other ports, that Roscoff can take all the business, why is there not the opportunity to build another extension in Roscoff so that extra shipping can come into Ireland at peak times?  We must make that argument.  If they can object there is no reason why we cannot argue that we are entitled to something else in its place.</P>
    <P>I congratulate the Minister and the Minister of State on the items outlined this morning with regard to marine policy. Senator Fitzgerald is right in that fishing is big business for Ireland.  I sell a lot of fish and at certain times of the year one cannot get fresh fish.  That is a sad reflection on us and is due to the type of fishing vessels we have.  We should create a policy where each port, such as Dingle or Castletownbere, should have one big boat and that would be an incentive to others to work out of the port.</P>
    <Speaker pid="BillCotter" hpid="Mr. Cotter Mr. Cotter">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cotter</NameTxt>
      <P>This is an important opportunity for us to discuss an area which does not get as much attention as those of us who are interested in it would like.  I live in a Border county where fisheries and tourism are interrelated. County Monaghan is the lowest <Col N="1255" /> earner from tourism in the country, which is not surprising given its inland and Border location.  County Monaghan has the longest boundary on the Border of any county.  It has suffered greatly due to the troubles and the existence of the Border.</P>
      <P>A great opportunity for growth is available to us to develop tourism, given the movement towards peace, and the waterways are an important element of that.  We have important waterways like the Rivers Erne, Foyle, Blackwater and Finn and a huge number of isolated lakes.  It is a great resource, but our difficulty is how to handle it.</P>
      <P>We have a number of concerns, including, for example, the proper development of the water and its marketing thereafter and how to balance intensive agriculture, which we have in abundance, with the proper development of our waterways.  Pollution control and such factors are uppermost in our minds.  County Monaghan is a leader in the production of poultry, producing approximately 70 per cent of all Irish poultry.  One can imagine the difficulties we have in controlling waste from that scale of production.  We also have a huge mushroom business and there is also a huge waste problem arising from that.  Indeed, I was disappointed when a project which would have singlehandedly controlled most of that waste by using it to produce electricity was recently turned down. Another look will have to be taken at that.  There needs to be co-ordination between all the various interests when one is considering a project like that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Monaghan has always had very intensive agriculture and small holdings and one can imagine the level of pollution that tends to arise from that.  How do we get a balance between the various elements involved?  Most people would approach this positively.  There is an impressive take up level for pollution control grants in my region.  One will find that this will be the same for the new round of grants.  The effort is being <Col N="1256" /> made and we need co-ordinated support from all the areas involved to give us a break.  There needs to be some sort of peace dividend on the ground and this is one area where it could be seen.</P>
    <P>Our waters have not been developed properly.  We need proper access to waterways and good shore development. We also want the fisheries board to look after our stocks and ensure the fish are healthy and abundant.  There is little point in bringing fishermen to the area if they cannot catch fish from the waterways, because they certainly will not return.</P>
    <P>I welcome the tone of the Minister's speech.  He proposes to carry out a complete overhaul of marine policy, which I have no doubt will include those policies in regard to the inland waterways.  I ask the Minister of State to note the level of co-operation that exists between the regional tourism organisations and the Inland Fisheries Board.  I have always felt that it was lacking.  While they are working well on their own, they should be co-ordinated.</P>
    <P>I have beside me a wonderful new production &mdash; the Minister of State may have been involved with it &mdash; entitled <i>Angling over the Border.</i>  It shows the value of our waterways very well pictorially. However, when one looks at the acknowledgments in it &mdash; it was produced by the fisheries board &mdash; there is no mention of the regional tourism organisations.  That underlines the concerns I have.  The development, marketing and use of the waters for fishing must be combined.  I feel that this is currently not the case.  While the fisheries board is working hard on its own to develop the waterways and the regional tourism organisations are doing the same, there is a large slice of middle ground which has not been filled.  I ask the Minster to tell the Department, when it carries out its review, to look closely at ways and means of getting better co-ordination at that level. because we need it.  It does not make any sense at all to have one group spending a lot of money on development and another group working separately <Col N="1257" /> on promotion when they should he almost synonymous.  The two boards should overlap heavily and that is currently not the case.  It would be far more beneficial to us if there was a well co-ordinated effort by everybody involved. Obviously, co-ordination means co-operation.</P>
    <P>The other area with which I have difficulty is that a lot of our lakes are at the end of small roads.  What is the point of having good waterways if one does not have proper road access to them? We need &mdash; I am confident we will get it over the next few years &mdash; a co-ordinated approach involving the Department of the Environment.  There are all sorts of stories about tourists arriving in certain parts of the country having their cars damaged by potholes.  They spend a few extra days trying to fix them and go away with this bad feeling.  They will certainly not return.  The difficulty is that they will tell everybody about their bad experience, although they also tend to talk about the good ones.  A positive effort must be made to give these people good experiences.  Co-ordination across the board from all those relevant people should be the centrepiece of all our work and I leave it for the Minister to tackle.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JoeOToole" hpid="Mr. O'Toole Mr. O'Toole">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Toole</NameTxt>
      <P>I have agreed to reduce my contribution to ten minutes in order to accommodate the Labour Party and the former Minister; I think they might have something to say.  I welcome the Minister and wish him well in his new portfolio.  I know the Minister will bring to it the energy and enthusiasm he has for everything else he tackles.</P>
      <P>I come from a town where fishing was its life blood and main industry until tourism caught on.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TomFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Fitzgerald Mr. Fitzgerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Fitzgerald</NameTxt>
      <P>He is going to try to cash in on Dingle.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeOToole" hpid="Mr. O'Toole Mr. O'Toole">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Toole</NameTxt>
      <P>To pick up on one of Senator Fitzgerald's points, I believe that we have sold out to Europe to some extent in this area.  Our fishing industry has lost out in the European context. <Col N="1258" /> Perhaps it has been used as a bargaining chip to make gains in other areas.  There are fewer boats in Dingle now then there were when I was growing up 30 years ago.  Why is this the case?</P>
      <P>I want to refer briefly to the Canadian business.  When the Minister responds, I would not like to hear him regurgitate the legal response in his speech, which was clear enough.  I note the Minister's objection to the fact that Canadian domestic law gives it the right to arrest transgressing fishermen on the high seas &mdash; I do not want to get into that either. I want to hear what we have to say about the fact that, whatever about the means, when the Canadians did finally look inside the Spanish boat, they found that the vast majority of its catch was undersized.  Who will take responsibility for that and who will take it up with our European partners?</P>
      <P>When Spanish boats have been taken in by Irish fisheries vessels over the last number of years we have frequently found secret holds.  What has been done to deal with that kind of practice?  I am not raising these issues in a carping way, but Irish fishermen and those involved in this industry do not understand why we are keeping to the rules all the time while others are not.</P>
      <P>I also want to raise the question of ferries.  I thought that the Treaty of Rome was clear about the movement of people, capital etc.  The idea that an Irish company would not be able to land its passengers in a French port of its choosing seems to go completely against what was intended by this treaty, whatever the Maastricht Treaty might have done to it &mdash; as far as I know, it did not affect in any way the free movement of people between one state and another. The deregulation of entry and exit through air and sea ports should have allowed the Irish company to make that decision.  I would like to hear how we stand on that issue.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The Minister said in his speech that we have no traditional fishing rights off the coast of Canada.  There is a different opinion on that in Dingle, because we sent a man there approximately 1600 <Col N="1259" /> years ago and we made a saint of him afterwards.  St. Brendan left Dingle and established traditional fishing rights off the North American coast &mdash; off Canada and the US &mdash; and we are not going to give them up so we would like to be represented there.</P>
    <P>In a book published in 1947, called <i>It All Happened</i>, a Kerryman living in Dublin wrote about the fishermen from Loughshinny in north Dublin who spent most summers in the 1920s and 1930s fishing off the coast of Newfoundland.  I disagree with the statement in the Minister's speech that we do not have traditional fishing rights.  We have been fishing there since before Canada was established &mdash; for 1600 years &mdash; and we should be allowed to continue to do so. I ask the Minister to take that up with the Canadians.  I would also like to know about the future of halibut and cod stocks in that area &mdash; I am not talking about the figures in the Minister's speech.  What are the rules about fishing off the Great Banks?  What jurisdiction does the North Atlantic Fishing Organisation have and what is our connection with it?</P>
    <P>As Senator Cregan said, we are the only island state left in the European Union.  Some years ago we even discussed a rail link under the Irish Sea. Early proposals for European rail systems showed a dotted line under the Irish Sea, but that has since gone by the board.  In order to recognise our difficulties in terms of communications, everybody in Europe dealing with fisheries policy and exports should be made drive a heavy truck from Castletownbere to Dingle to Killybegs and back to Rosslare.  Roads to ports are substandard, particularly those to Castletownbere, Dingle and Killybegs. That is something which we should deal with quickly.</P>
    <Speaker pid="DenisDinoCregan" hpid="Mr. Cregan Mr. Cregan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cregan</NameTxt>
      <P>Except those on the east coast.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeOToole" hpid="Mr. O'Toole Mr. O'Toole">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Toole</NameTxt>
      <P>I would like to hear the Minister's views on training for skippers <Col N="1260" /> of boats.  Senator Fitzgerald and I grew up at a time when it was not unusual for someone with little training to be given control of a boat which would be valued at £0.75 million today.  They were often expected to look after them with little training.  I would like to hear how that is being developed.</P>
      <P>Fewer than 2 per cent of those employed, or 16,000 to 20,000 people, work in the fishing industry.  I would like to hear more about added value in terms of exports.  I understand we land about 100 million tonnes of fish each year at a cost of approximately £100 million.  Our exports are worth approximately £200 million which is an added value on whatever proportion we export.  It is worrying that so many frozen whole fish are being exported, particularly when they could be used for processing so as create employment here.</P>
      <P>I recall looking at figures less than seven or eight years ago which showed that one person was employed on land for every eight at sea.  I understand that has improved substantially in the meantime. What is the situation at present in terms of added value in the processing industry?  How many jobs are being created on shore?  We should double the value of the fish catch being exported. Our total exports are twice the value of the landed value of the fish.  We do not export all of the fish and there is a clear opening for much development.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I would like to draw the Minister's attention to the state of the fishing fleet, which was raised Senator Cregan.  The fish processing industry and those dependent on fish sales need a constant supply, which can be determined by the weather as much as anything else.  Fishing activity in certain weather conditions can be determined by the size and type of boat.  The most recent figures which I saw showed that almost 50 per cent of boats were 20 years old and the majority of the fleet was less than 40 feet or 12 metres long, which means we cannot always fish.  There are years when we do not reach our quota in <Col N="1261" /> terms of what we are entitled to in certain fish stocks.</P>
    <P>Every two months we read about problems of disease in aquaculture in the newspapers.  What progress have we made in that area?  Surely there is a need for research and development?  I do not know where it is being done or about the status of boats like the <i>Lough Beltray</i> or of the Sherkin Island station. What research is being done on disease? On the question of marketing, what restaurant in Dublin would serve me a reasonably priced fresh lobster?  How can I be sure that the salmon I get is not a pale version of fresh salmon?  We should do more processing in the aquaculture area rather than with sea catches.</P>
    <P>Will the Minister respond to the question of environmental problems, that is, conservation, which was mentioned by a number of Members, and pollution? The Department of the Environment demands sludge tanks or an area for dealing with it in every port.  As far as I know, there is none in any port and it is being dumped.  Earlier we heard about the inland problems of mushrooms and poultry, but there is also a problem at sea.  The more intensive it becomes and the more technology that is introduced into the industry, the greater the need for dealing with sludge from boats. There is nowhere to deal with it at present.  As far as I know, it cannot be dealt with in Dingle, Killlybegs or Castletownbere &mdash; I am sure the Minister will correct me if I am wrong. Research and development is required in these areas.  We need a constant supply of fish to make this industry more workable and useful and this requires a new and large fleet and more technology. We must look at conservation, catches and infrastructure in terms of roads and auction halls.  Dingle, for example, does not have an auction hall.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelCalnan" hpid="Mr. Calnan Mr. Calnan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Calnan</NameTxt>
      <P>I am glad to have the opportunity to speak, but I would have liked to have had more time.  I thank the Minister for coming to the House today to announce this fundamental overhaul of marine policy and I congratulate the <Col N="1262" /> Minister and the Minister of State on their appointment.  I compliment the Minister, Deputy Coveney, for visiting ports in west Cork to get first hand information on the position in the ports and on landing areas along the coast. His visit to Roaring Water Bay was deeply appreciated by the fishermen there, who encounter dangers in bringing mussels ashore, dragging in boats in the dark of winter time.  There is a need for proper facilities for the marvellous fishing industry that is developing along the south west coast &mdash; the development of mussels in our sheltered coves and harbours &mdash; and the tremendous potential that is there for future development.</P>
      <P>I welcome the Minister's statement on the fundamental overhaul of marine policy because fishing has been for too long the cinderella of the Irish economy. I also welcome the Minister's indication of having public debates, because this is where we will discover what is wanted and required.  The full potential of fishing has never been highlighted properly in this country.  We talk about regional and rural development and job creation. Fishing can play a major part in these areas.  At the moment there is a tremendous number of people employed directly in fishing on the south west coast of Cork, those who are involved in aquaculture and the spin-off from that.  The work on land is excellent and can be further developed if a proper overhaul takes place.</P>
      <P>I am glad to see that the Minister is taking full account of the problem with fish stocks.  I am not worried about what is going on between the Spaniards and the Canadians.  I am not taking sides. However, I am seriously concerned about the protection of Irish fishermen, because their smaller boats are being rammed by bigger Spanish ones when they meet at sea.  Ireland will have to be strong on this issue and raise it at EU level.  I do not want to see any boat or fishing tackle damaged or the lives of Irish fishermen endangered by people who are pirating our waters.  The Canadians can handle their own affairs; we have to handle ours.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="1263" /> In the short amount of time I have I would also like to speak about the Harbours Bill.  I am very glad to see money being pumped into Cork and Waterford and other places.  There are hundreds of other smaller ports along our coast, however, where very valuable economic work is being done in fishing, tourism and other areas related to the sea, which may be lost if EU money is only given to the big ports.  There are many jetties and piers along our coast that need financial aid and these will have to be developed also.</P>
    <P>The whole field of aquaculture needs research and proper policy.  I am pushing for proper development in this area as well as that of our lakes.  There is tremendous potential for fishing and tourism to be developed on Irish lakes. There is a lake near my own home where local people have formed an organisation, stocked the lakes, put in a little pier and brought in boats.  It is a tremendous tourist attraction already.</P>
    <P>I have continuously spoken about the inhabited islands off the south west coast of Cork and the need for their proper development.  I spoke to the Minister of State, Deputy Carey, recently.  He has been given responsibility for islands, but he is in the awful position that he has responsibility for the islands but has no budget.  How can he do anything for the islands unless he has a budget?  If he has to send people to the Department of the Marine, local authorities or Government agencies to get money for the islands, we are back to square one again.  Deputy Carey should be given money to ensure that fundamentals like a proper landing place on the mainland and a proper landing place on the island are in place on all of the inhabited islands.  There is potential for enormous prosperity on these islands if it is developed properly. Aquaculture, fishing, agriculture and other areas will have to be dealt with. There should be proper links between the Department of the Marine, other Departments, Government agencies and local authorities to have a comprehensive <Col N="1264" /> policy to deal with the island position.</P>
    <Speaker pid="BrendanDaly" hpid="Mr. Daly Mr. Daly">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Daly</NameTxt>
      <P>I thank Senator O'Toole for giving me the opportunity to make some remarks on this very important issue.  I wish both Ministers well and assure them of our co-operation in their task.</P>
      <P>Senator Fitzgerald mentioned the headline that I set in the Department of the Marine.  If Deputy Gilmore really wishes to be successful, I suggest that he might try to introduce the trout fishing licence and he will soon test his popularity.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonGilmore" hpid="Minister of State at the Department of the Marine (Mr. Gilmore) Minister of State at the Department of the Marine (Mr. Gilmore)">
      <NameTxt>Minister of State at the Department of the Marine (Mr. Gilmore)</NameTxt>
      <P>Was that not tried before?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Acting Chairman Acting Chairman">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman</NameTxt>
      <P>Trying to lose your job.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BrendanDaly" hpid="Mr. Daly Mr. Daly">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Daly</NameTxt>
      <P>This is an opportune time to underline the necessity for legislation. My main purpose in intervening here is to impress upon the Minister the desirability of pressing ahead with the introduction of legislation in key areas that are of immense importance and need to be urgently dealt with.  There is a special necessity to undertake a review of harbours legislation and to put commercial semi-State bodies in place to operate the harbours.  I strongly suggest that he look at the Shannon Estuary Bill &mdash; which was prepared but never brought forward or completed &mdash; that dealt with putting a modern efficient structure in place to deal with developments in the Shannon Estuary.  Each time the Shannon Estuary Bill has come before the Houses, the Dáil has collapsed.  I strongly suggest that he think carefully before he brings that particular piece of legislation forward.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>In relation to aquaculture, there is an urgent necessity to come to grips with the uncertainty in regard to the licensing of aquaculture projects.  I fully support the development of aquaculture.  Not only has it been recognised here as being vital to the development of <Col N="1265" /> employment and fish products, but it is recognised internationally also.  A huge output in international aquaculture is now evident and the pace of development is going to accelerate, in view of the fact that fish stocks are declining. The collapse of the cod fishery industry in the north west Atlantic has brought about the incidents between the Spanish and Canadians.  In Canada, 40,000 jobs were lost when the cod fishery industry collapsed.  This underlines the urgency of having a very strong conservation policy in Ireland.  I would be seriously worried about the changes from the 1 January next which allow Spanish boats access to the Irish Box.  The Irish Box was a conservation measure, and a successful one, which needs to be protected. If the activities we have seen from Spanish boats up to now are continued in the Irish Box, then Irish fish stocks, jobs and fishing are at serious risk.  We are appalled at the fact that, despite surveillance within the Community, a member state still has a fishing fleet with illegal holds, which takes undersized fish, is damaging the prospects for the livelihoods of many thousands of people in the Community and continues to flout the laws in this regard.  I strongly urge the Minister of State to have the Irish naval and protection services carry out a thorough check of every Spanish boat operating anywhere within the Irish economic zone, as a matter of extreme urgency, because they are operating illegal holds and mechanisms which are taking undersized fish.  This is damaging the prospect for recovery of international and local fisheries.</P>
    <P>The Minister has a very wide remit in his Department.  It would be impossible in the short time at our disposal to go into all the areas that are affected.  I feel that there is a necessity on the part of the Minister and the Minister of State to look very carefully at the potential of our marine environment for leisure and recreation.  The Minister did not mention this in his speech.  I know he has a very wide brief and it would be impossible for him to cover everything.  It is <Col N="1266" /> time that the Department of the Marine took positive action to undertake investment in the provision of marine leisure activities.  Even though some new marinas have been built, the provision of marinas and recreational related amenities in the area of the marine is of vital importance.  It has immense importance from the point of view of promoting tourism.  It has many opportunities for the provision employment and many openings for people to develop facilities which would enhance tourism.  It is an opportunity we have not exploited or developed up to now in some areas in west Clare where there is a pressing need for development.  The Minister of State recently visited Dun-beg to see applications for leisure and marine related activities which would enhance some of the coastal communities and provide opportunities for employment.</P>
    <P>Finally, I want to pay tribute to the Marine Search and Rescue Service, which is based in Shannon, and to congratulate all those who have been involved in that magnificent service which has saved hundreds of lives and has made an immense contribution to safety along the west coast.  I would like to get confirmation from the Minister of the future of the Marine Search and Rescue Service in Shannon, if it will be continued along the same lines and what the prospects are for having the service put on a firm footing.</P>
    <P>There has been much comment on the necessity for research and other activities.  I congratulate the Marine Institute on its establishment and wish it well in its work.  It is working in a vacuum because it does not have either the resources or the capability to effectively undertake the research that needs to be done.  This is identified in the Government plan.  The Government plan states stated that we would still have the <i>Lough Beltray</i>, which has done tremendous work within its limitations; but the <i>Lough Beltray</i> cannot undertake the work that needs to be done.  I strongly suggest to the Minister of State that he take a personal interest in undertaking <Col N="1267" /> joint ventures with some of the other member states of the European Community in matters of research.  I know that some research was done on the Shannon between the German and Irish research authorities.  He could involve the universities, young graduates and people who have a general interest in marine research, with co-operation from institutions like the University of Limerick, institutions in the United Kingdom and the French Maritime Institute, which has a huge marine research programme and would be very willing to co-operate with us in joint ventures in this country.  It is necessary to proceed with the legislation which is so urgently needed to deal with pollution of harbours and aquaculture.  There is need to take stock immediately of the activities of Spanish boats, which take undersize fish and operate illegal holds.  They damage the livelihoods of everybody in the Community with their activities.  The Minister might take a careful look at how he can assist the marine leisure industry, which could develop job opportunities for thousands of people if it were developed to a satisfactory level.</P>
    <Speaker pid="GVWright" hpid="Mr. Wright Mr. Wright">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Wright</NameTxt>
      <P>May I ask how we will be proceeding in the next half an hour?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryKelly" hpid="Acting Chairman (Ms Kelly) Acting Chairman (Ms Kelly)">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman (Ms Kelly)</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister will make a statement and then, in order to avoid repetition, we would suggest that when one Senator asks a question, other Senators wishing to ask related questions should indicate so at that time.  The Minister will then respond.  Questions will be taken alternatively from each side of the House.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonGilmore" hpid="Minister of State at the Department of the Marine (Mr. Gilmore) Minister of State at the Department of the Marine (Mr. Gilmore)">
      <NameTxt>Minister of State at the Department of the Marine (Mr. Gilmore)</NameTxt>
      <P>I welcome the opportunity to be here.  I welcome this debate and the range of issues which were covered during the course of the discussion this morning.  In deference to Members who wish to ask questions, I will keep my remarks brief. There were a number of points raised which were of a general nature and on <Col N="1268" /> which I wish to comment, and I will try to anticipate some of the questions which may arise.  A number Senators referred to the marine, and to fisheries in particular, as being something of a cinderella in our economic and political life.  There is some truth in that, historically. It is very regrettable that, as an island people, we have not given the marine and the fishing industries the kind of attention and priority they require.  Senator Fitzgerald very eloquently described our fleet as being like a 20 year old crock of a car which is barely able to manage on the road.  Of course, one of the things you do when you come across a crock is to have a look at the log book to find out the previous owners, to establish how they maintained the vehicle and why the did not trade it in at an earlier stage.  I do not share the conclusion that Senator Fitzgerald drew: that the problem rests with either officials of the Department of the Marine, of Bord Iascaigh Mhara or the various agencies and the staffs of those agencies, who in my opinion are very highly motivated and hard-working officials.  Perhaps the problem has to do with historic lack of policy and lack of political direction.  That is one of the reasons the Minister for the Marine, Deputy Coveney, and I, when we took up office and inherited the Department of the Marine with all of its problems and opportunities, decided that we could not continue on as we were.  We decided there was a necessity to carry out a fundamental overhaul of marine policy, to take stock of where we are as an island people and decide what we need to do with our marine resources and our fishing industry.  As the Minister explained this morning, there are a number of dimensions to that overhaul: the seminars to be organised by the Marine Institute, the advisory council that we plan to put in place and the work of the consultants who will examine the work of the Department and of the various agencies.  Many of the issues which arose here this morning are general issues of policy.  Issues such as training <Col N="1269" /> are issues that I envisage will come under that remit.</P>
      <P>Senator Fitzgerald also referred to the operational programme.  He was critical of the fact that the figures are 1992 figures.  The reason for that is that the programme, when it was agreed in 1994, was based on the figures then available.  The up to date figures which Senator Fitzgerald is seeking are available and I will be happy to make those available to him.  He also raised the question of conservation, particularly in reference to lobster.  There is a very encouraging development, which has been initiated by lobster fishermen themselves and which is based on an experiment which worked very successfully in Maine in the United States.  It involves notching, putting lobsters back in the water and is now operating very successfully around our coast.  I attended a conference of the Lobster Association in Ballyshannon two weeks ago which dealt with that issue.</P>
      <P>Inland fisheries were mentioned by a number of Senators, Senators Belton and Cotter in particular.  I agree with what they had to say: there is enormous tourism potential in our inland fisheries. The booklet Senator Cotter drew attention to, <i>Angling over the Border</i>, is a publication I was very privileged to launch last week in Ballyconnell, with an attendance of 300 people, representing fishing and tourist interests from both sides of the Border who are promoting the enormous potential for angling on the five waterways that straddle the Border.  There is an investment programme of about £19 million in the operational programme for tourism, which is aimed at encouraging angling-related tourism.  Our intention is that those resources will be used primarily for the development of the water and its fish.  There is not a great deal of merit in having very attractive driveways, little piers and so on, which may look very nice, if the angler cannot find fish in the river.  The priority will be the development of the resource itself and the development of hatcheries to ensure the re-stocking of the rivers.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="1270" /> The Harbours Bill was mentioned by Senators Cregan and Daly.  Again, we hope that legislation will be published very shortly.  Senators will understand that, following the change of Government, there was a necessity for the new administration to consider the work that had been done by the previous Government in drafting that legislation.  We have now completed this and the legislation will be published shortly.</P>
    <P>Senator Cregan and Senator O'Toole mentioned the problem encountered by Irish Ferries in operating its service form Rosslare and Cork to Roscoff.  Our position is that Irish Ferries has a right to operate a service from Rosslare and Cork to Brest or Roscoff.  It was originally intended to use the port of Brest. but the company now plans to have a service to Roscoff this summer.  The complaint regarding Roscoff is under consideration by the European Commission and I had a meeting last week with the French Transport Minister.  I am confident that the European Commission investigation will be completed reasonably quickly and that, arising from these discussions and our contacts with the European Commission, the result of the investigation will be in favour of Irish Ferries and that there will be no further obstacles placed in the way of Irish Ferries operating a valuable service between Rosslare and Cork into Roscoff this summer.</P>
    <P>Much has been said &mdash; thankfully, not in the House this morning, although it was inevitable that it would be referred to &mdash; regarding the Canadian dispute. The contradiction involved here was probably highlighted in the contribution made by Senator O'Toole, where on the one hand he questions the position we took with regard to this issue, but on the other hand he suggested that we may like to follow Saint Brendan and establish our traditional fishing rights off Newfoundland.</P>
    <P>Were we to follow Saint Brendan and attempt to do this, the difficulty we would have is that we would have to share a 3,500 ton share of the total allowable catch, which is the disputed <Col N="1271" /> share, and we may well find ourselves in the unfortunate position in which others have found themselves.  What we therefore must establish in this instance is that the issue in dispute is not one about conservation itself, because the reduction in the total allowable catch was established and we supported and continue to support this.  The issue at stake here was the share of the catch and how the dispute over the share was to be resolved.  We take the view that this dispute should be resolved by negotiation and we are now happy that the process of negotiation has got underway.</P>
    <P>With regard to the question of overfishing, there can be no doubt about our position.  We are absolutely opposed to overfishing.  We believe strongly that any State, including Spain, whose fleets are engaged in overfishing, must be stopped, that the EU must use its resources to stop those practices from taking place and must take whatever action is necessary in order to achieve that.</P>
    <P>I have already gone over time and I am anxious that there should be opportunity for questions, so if there are aspects which I have not covered I will be happy to deal with them by way of reply.</P>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Acting Chairman Acting Chairman">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman</NameTxt>
      <P>I call on Senator Wright to put a question to the Minister.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GVWright" hpid="Mr. Wright Mr. Wright">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Wright</NameTxt>
      <P>What role does the Minister see his Department having with regard to the protection of the asset our coastline and his plans for coastal zone management?  The Minister will be aware that the same problems pertained in regard to County Fingal, County Meath and County Wicklow but the different ideas put forward should be pooled together in a form of coastal zone management.  How does the Minister see this proceeding?  I note that for the first time funding this year includes a provision for coastal erosion protection. It is a small amount, but at least it is a start and it is an issue requiring bigger <Col N="1272" /> debate, perhaps on Private Members' Business.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Acting Chairman Acting Chairman">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman</NameTxt>
      <P>I call on any other Senator with a related question.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DenisDinoCregan" hpid="Mr. Cregan Mr. Cregan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cregan</NameTxt>
      <P>With regard to the matter raised by Senator Fitzgerald and myself on the policy of allowing one group of fishermen to buy a bigger ship&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Acting Chairman Acting Chairman">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator, I require a question which is related to coastal protection and I will call on you later with regard to your question.  I call on Senator Daly.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BrendanDaly" hpid="Mr. Daly Mr. Daly">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Daly</NameTxt>
      <P>Does the Minister have any funding at his disposal to deal with coastal erosion problems?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonGilmore" hpid="Mr. Gilmore Mr. Gilmore">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Gilmore</NameTxt>
      <P>The Department of the Marine, the Department of the Environment and the Office of Public Works have co-operated and put together a working group on coastal zone management. This group is engaging a firm of consultants, the appointment of which will be announced shortly, to draw up a coastal zone management plan for our entire coastline and to take into account the up to date thinking with regard to coastal zone management, with all of its different aspects.  We expect that the consultants will take approximately six months to complete their work in drawing up a coastal zone management plan for our coastline on which the three Departments involved in this matter can base their plans.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>There is a sum of just over £5 million in the operational programme for coastal protection.  It is quite small, but it is the first time that a provision has been made for the operational programme for coastal protection.  The various local authorities, which in the first instance are the bodies which have the front line responsibility in this area, have been asked for their priorities for coastal protection within their local authority area. Those proposals are being assessed by the Department, but I must qualify this <Col N="1273" /> by saying that the amount of money available for coastal protection, having regard to the need for coastal protection works, is extremely small.  We will therefore have to approach the allocation of those moneys in a targeted way.</P>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Acting Chairman Acting Chairman">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator Cregan, Senator Maloney had indicated before you, and, as he has not spoken already, I will call on him first, followed by Senator Fitzgerald.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaloney" hpid="Mr. Maloney Mr. Maloney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Maloney</NameTxt>
      <P>On page six of the speech by the Minister, Deputy Coveney, he refers to the development of Irish ports.  However, the sum of £140 million which he indicated will be spent, with priority given to investment in the strategic ports &mdash; Cork, Dublin, Dún Laoghaire, Rosslare, Waterford and the Shannon estuary &mdash; does not include any allocation for County Donegal. Almost 60 per cent of the national catch comes through ports such as Rathmullan, Greencastle and Killybegs. Rathmullan contains one of the deepest water ports in Europe and is crying out for development, but there is no mention of this.  It is first on the list of priorities of Donegal County Council for development.</P>
      <P>With regard to ferry services, these are being provided from Buncrana to Rathmullan and from Moville to Magilligan Point, which is in Northern Ireland and which is hopefully a spin-off from the peace process.  However, in the programme outlined by the Minister, no provision is made for County Donegal and I am disappointed with this.  The Minister should give it priority and I ask him to do so.  Will he also explain why no such provision has been provided?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Acting Chairman Acting Chairman">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman</NameTxt>
      <P>Are there any related questions?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TomFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Fitzgerald Mr. Fitzgerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Fitzgerald</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not wish to preempt the Minister's reply, but perhaps it is because there is over development in County Donegal.  With regard to the port of Dingle, there is unfinished work to be undertaken.  It has probably been <Col N="1274" /> delayed until it comes under the new major fishery harbours Bill.  What are the plans for finishing the pier in Dingle, putting in place an ice plant there and so on?  When will the Bill to designate Dingle be brought before the Oireachtas?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BrendanDaly" hpid="Mr. Daly Mr. Daly">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Daly</NameTxt>
      <P>Can the Minister of State hold out any hope that money will be provided for small fishing ports and landing places to undertake essential works in them?  The livelihoods of many small fishermen in them have been threatened.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GVWright" hpid="Mr. Wright Mr. Wright">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Wright</NameTxt>
      <P>Will these sort of ports be included in the Harbours Bill?  Will a decision be made on the Fingal area of Skerries and Balbriggan?  The legislation relating to these two harbours is absolutely antiquated.  Nobody claims to have any authority over them.  They are of great importance to the towns and I ask the Minister to make a decision as to who is in charge so that some finance can be provided for the area.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonGilmore" hpid="Mr. Gilmore Mr. Gilmore">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Gilmore</NameTxt>
      <P>We are talking about two categories of ports, commercial and fishing.  The reference in the Minister's speech to the development of, and investment in, ports relates to commercial ports.  These are essentially the ports which come under the 1946 Harbours Act.  The purpose of the legislation is primarily to establish 12 of those ports as commercial semi-State bodies and to provide for a number of options for the other ports which were listed under the 1946 Act.  This legislation will be published shortly.</P>
      <P>The operational programme provides for an investment of £140 million in the commercial ports.  The primary purpose of this is to improve and benefit trade and tourism between this island and the rest of Europe.  Many people and bodies have drawn attention to the competitive disadvantages suffered by Irish industry because of our transport distance from the rest of the European market.  The investment in ports and shipping is primarily aimed at this.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="1275" /> The development of fishery ports comes under another heading.  Provision has been made in the operational programme for these ports.  Senators will understand that I would be reluctant to refer to the problems of individual ports with regard to funding and so on.</P>
    <Speaker pid="GVWright" hpid="Mr. Wright Mr. Wright">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Wright</NameTxt>
      <P>But you have noted it?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonGilmore" hpid="Mr. Gilmore Mr. Gilmore">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Gilmore</NameTxt>
      <P>I have noted it and would be happy to respond to Senators on an individual basis if they wish to raise problems of individual ports with me.  The intention is that Dingle will be a fisheries harbour centre under the provisions of the new harbour legislation.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DenisDinoCregan" hpid="Mr. Cregan Mr. Cregan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cregan</NameTxt>
      <P>May I ask the Minister about the problems regarding the fishing fleet?  In Castletownbere at the moment we have Russian factory ships which are doing exceptionally well.  The one heavy ship we have in our fishing fleet is berthed in Donegal.  In what way can initiatives be given to people so that this type of fishing can be done from other harbours?  Would the Department be prepared to decide that there should be ships of this calibre in other fishing harbours?  Could money be made available from EU funding or grants from the Department of the Marine to help fishermen in this regard?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BrendanDaly" hpid="Mr. Daly Mr. Daly">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Daly</NameTxt>
      <P>With regard to the exploitation of new species and the taking of our full quota, there is evidence we are not taking our full quota in some species. What is the Minister's policy in that regard?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonGilmore" hpid="Mr. Gilmore Mr. Gilmore">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Gilmore</NameTxt>
      <P>It has to be acknowledged that our fishing fleet is very small.  Much of it is ageing.  We also have the additional constraint that we are now governed by the EU Common Fisheries Policy in relation to the size of our fleet and what we can do.  There is provision in the operational programme for a de-commissioning policy and the Minister for the Marine intends to make <Col N="1276" /> some announcements on this in the near future.  There was a sense of national pride at the launch of the <i>Veronica</i> and great encouragement for Mr. McHugh for bringing that vessel into operation and we all wish him well.</P>
      <P>There is, however, a general policy issue involved.  Part of the policy review we are undertaking must involve whether or not the best direction for our fishing industry is in a small number of large vessels or whether it is better to encourage the development of our fishing industry based on the development of fishing communities in ports where fishing has been a traditional way of life. There is a conflict between the two approaches.  This is one of the issues we will have to address in the policy review.</P>
      <P>With regard to the exploitation of new species, I acknowledge we are not taking up our quota in some areas and there is some potential there.  We are keeping this issue under review.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TomFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Fitzgerald Mr. Fitzgerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Fitzgerald</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator O'Toole asked me to apologise for the fact that he cannot be here while the Minister is answering his questions.  He had to go to a meeting.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonGilmore" hpid="Mr. Gilmore Mr. Gilmore">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Gilmore</NameTxt>
      <P>It just as well because we would be here all night if I tried to answer them.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TomFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Fitzgerald Mr. Fitzgerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Fitzgerald</NameTxt>
      <P>I think the Minister and all of us would agree that on-shore facilities are very slow in being provided. Would the Minister and his Department agree that the private sector should build auction halls, chill rooms and so on and lease them to harbour authorities and fishing co-operatives for a period of 20 to 25 years?  The money does not have to come from the Department's funds.</P>
      <P>I feel that from 1996 foreign fishing fleets will be enticed into landing their fish in Ireland because of different policies. What preparations can we make or are making for this?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GVWright" hpid="Mr. Wright Mr. Wright">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Wright</NameTxt>
      <P>What plans, if any, does the Minister have to approve the budget <Col N="1277" /> for the development and promotion of fish on the home market?  Senator Daly raised an issue which is very important for Malahide at present.  Will there be a co-ordinated role between the Departments of Tourism and Trade, the Environment and the Marine in the development of marine leisure facilities?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BrendanDaly" hpid="Mr. Daly Mr. Daly">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Daly</NameTxt>
      <P>Could the Minister communicate with me later about the long term prospects for the Search and Rescue Service at Shannon?  I raised it in my speech.  It is a very important issue and has a bearing on all the activities we are talking about.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Acting Chairman Acting Chairman">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman</NameTxt>
      <P>We can extend the time for any related questions if the Minister wants to give a comprehensive reply.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonGilmore" hpid="Mr. Gilmore Mr. Gilmore">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Gilmore</NameTxt>
      <P>On the question of processing and the involvement of private sector investment, Senator Fitzgerald can take it that the Government would welcome private sector investment in the&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TomFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Fitzgerald Mr. Fitzgerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Fitzgerald</NameTxt>
      <P>Sorry, Minister.  I think you misunderstood my question.  I am talking about putting in place onshore facilities which would normally be put in place by the Department of the Marine, such as auction halls and chill rooms, not processing plants but buildings that are essential to the fishing fleet.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonGilmore" hpid="Mr. Gilmore Mr. Gilmore">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Gilmore</NameTxt>
      <P>We will look at any proposals that come forward.  I do not know if Senator Fitzgerald has specific proposals in mind but the Department will look at any proposals that are put forward.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I apologise to Senator Daly for not having mentioned the question of the Air Sea Rescue service earlier.  The Department's present contract with Irish Helicopters for the medium range Sikorsky helicopter expires at the end of 1996.  The operational performance has been excellent, as reflected in the <Col N="1278" /> response rate, which was well in excess of 90 per cent.  As you know, the helicopter is based at Shannon, providing coverage for the south west and west and throughout our waters.  No decisions have yet been taken on the post-1996 arrangements but I can assure the Senator that the views he has expressed on the matter will be taken into account.</P>
    <P>In relation to the development and promotion of fish on the home market, as Senator Wright will know, An Bord Bia is now being established and the Minister will be making appointments to the board, with which we intend to work closely.  The future relationship between An Bord Bia's role and BIM's valuable work in promoting fish and other seafood will be part of the review that we are now undertaking and for which consultants are being appointed.</P>
    <P>Marine leisure and recreational facilities represent a dimension of marine activity to which we are giving a lot of attention.  We will be working closely on this with local authorities to advance proposals for the development of marine leisure facilities around our coastline. Proposals of that kind have to be looked at expeditiously and on an individual basis by the Department.</P>
    <Speaker pid="BrendanDaly" hpid="Mr. Daly Mr. Daly">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Daly</NameTxt>
      <P>Could we encourage you to set a specific subhead for expenditure in these areas, because one of the problems has been the lack of seed capital to get them started?  Could you put a subhead in place that would give grant aid towards the development of marine leisure facilities like small marinas and tourism projects?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonGilmore" hpid="Mr. Gilmore Mr. Gilmore">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Gilmore</NameTxt>
      <P>As Senator Daly will know, the policy up to now has been that these activities are not directly funded by the State.  I understand what he is saying and we can have a look at that suggestion.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Acting Chairman Acting Chairman">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman</NameTxt>
      <P>That concludes the questions.  I thank the Minister for his handling of the questions and the Senators for asking them.  Senator Fitzgerald <Col N="1279" /> wants to make a few concluding remarks.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TomFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Fitzgerald Mr. Fitzgerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Fitzgerald</NameTxt>
      <P>I thank the Minister and Minister of State for answering all the questions.  I also want to thank the Leader of the House, Senator Manning, for initiating this type of question and answer session.  I am sure that the leader of our own party in the House will have something to say on it.  It is a new approach and one that Ministers and Ministers of State need not be afraid of, because if they cannot find ready answers no one is going to embarrass them.  It is a healthy exercise and I hope that we will see more of it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MauriceManning" hpid="Mr. Manning Mr. Manning">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Manning</NameTxt>
      <P>I thank Senator Fitzgerald for his generous comments.  It has been a useful debate and I thank the Minister, and the Minister of State especially, for his open and frank replies to questions.  I also wish to thank those who took part in the debate.  It is something that we will see more of in this House.  The Minister knows that the questions were asked in good faith and that they all add to the ongoing debate.</P>
      <P>
        <i>Sitting suspended at 1.5 p.m. and resumed at 2 p.m.</i>
      </P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="NESC Report on Rural Development:" RHead="Statements (Resumed)">
    <Title>NESC Report on Rural Development: Statements (Resumed).</Title>
    <Speaker pid="JohnDardis" hpid="Mr. Dardis Mr. Dardis">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dardis</NameTxt>
      <P>I thank the Minister for returning to hear the debate on this important issue.  He is spending a lot of time in the House.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I wish to stress the importance of the Leader programme in rural development. I studied Leader 1 closely.  It was very successful, although there were some big exceptions which were well publicised.  Overall, however, it was successful. About £36 million was spent on the programme and it had the effect of boosting job creation in rural communities. More importantly, it gave rural communities great confidence in their ability to do things for themselves.  It has <Col N="1280" /> overcome much of the old inter-agency rivalries which were manifest.  Different Government agencies, non-Government agencies, voluntary bodies and farming organisations have co-operated well on Leader boards.</P>
    <P>The Minister will be aware of the Carney report, which was quite complimentary of the Leader programme. However, it suggested &mdash; although it is not within the Minister's remit &mdash; the establishment of a special unit within the Department of Agriculture to look after the programme.  I am aware that a Civil Service unit is already involved in that but the report envisaged a broader body of a consultancy nature.  The great strength of Leader is that it has cut out bureaucracy.  Decisions are made at local level by the boards and by the people who are involved and who know best what is required at local level.</P>
    <P>Can we do something about the way the county enterprise partnership boards and other bodies are run? If an application is made to a county enterprise partnership board it must go all the way up the line to the Department and back down again before sanction is given.  Leader has shown that one can invest authority in the local community to make the right decisions.  The successful ones, in which one of the major co-ops is almost always involved, along with the local authority and local people, have been quite competent to make decisions.  Let us give them the money and let them get on with the job.</P>
    <P>I appeal to the Minister to use whatever influence he can to get Leader II up and running.  We were told that it would commence at the start of 1995. Continuity is important for people in local organisations who are trying to make plans.  Some of them have been confronted with the problem of trying to fund an operation while they wait for Leader II to be up and running.  The delay is totally unnecessary and too long.  It sends out the wrong signal.  The amount of money made available has had a big and positive effect.  Please bring continuity to bear on this.  Let the successful groups know that they have <Col N="1281" /> been selected and let them get on with the job.  They have the capacity to improve rural communities.</P>
    <P>My final point relates to planning law and local authorities.  It does not appear to be sensible that we have a plethora of schemes designed to keep people in rural Ireland &mdash; they are good schemes which I hope will be successful &mdash; yet if somebody wishes to live and build a house in rural Ireland the local authority will not let them do so.  That is contradictory. I accept that good planning dictates that there should not be ribbon development or houses built in the wrong place in scenic areas.  However, there are plenty of areas in the country where houses could be built to replace derelict houses and help maintain the fabric of rural society.  Let us have consistency in the policy which says that people should be encouraged to live and work in their local communities but which also says that when they do want to live and work there they will not be allowed to build a house.  That problem must be addressed at both local authority and national level.</P>
    <P>The Minister referred to the fact that there would be centres to co-ordinate the schemes.  People are terribly confused by the plethora of agencies such as the county enterprise partnership boards, Leader and others.  We now have an additional one, the operational programme for tourism.  Money will be made available to people to renovate farmyards and old cottages.  That is welcome, but we should have a central place to which people could go for advice so that they would not have to go through a circle of agencies, Government Departments and so forth.  That would be a huge help.  I ask the Minister to do what he can &mdash; I realise that rural and western development are his responsibilities &mdash; to address these problems and to introduce policies which will make it easier for people to gain access to both the money and advice.</P>
    <Speaker pid="DanNeville" hpid="Mr. Neville Mr. Neville">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Neville</NameTxt>
      <P>I welcome the Minister of State to the House.  I also welcome <Col N="1282" /> his initiative in establishing pilot projects in rural Ireland.  We will be interested to see how these projects develop.  I hope they will be successful and I will discuss them further in the course of my contribution.</P>
      <P>To treat the problems currently facing rural communities as separate and divorced from the rest of Irish life would be a fundamental error.  Formulating a policy on that premise would be like laying foundations on a bed of quicksand. First, we must change our views of some basic aspects of Irish society.  We must, for example, finish forever with the urban/rural divide and begin to accept each other as one people.  We also must broaden our view on what constitutes wealth when we talk about sharing the wealth of the country among the people.  The real wealth of Ireland must surely include space, environment, peace, access to Irish culture and natural beauty &mdash; in short, all aspects of Ireland that attract tourists to our country. These aspects have always been available to Irish people with money. However, they should also be available to the many who face a future of unemployment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>We must also change our views about country living and the type of people who live in the country.  After some minor adjustments in lifestyle, and perhaps, a change in values, I believe virtually anybody can live a better life in the country.  History and experience have taught us, however, that only farmers and people involved in the agriculture sector want to live in the country. We must change that.  The tragic reason is the fact that the small farmer is being eliminated.  In a few decades there will be no small farmers in this country. Unfortunately, this development is probably EU driven.  The economics of the EU and of small farming dictate that in a period of years the small farmer will disappear.  Each small farm that disappears means one family less in an area. The result is inevitable: population decline and its attendant ills, such as loss of other services, derelict houses and <Col N="1283" /> general decay.  We can see this already in many parts of the west of Ireland.</P>
    <P>The policy of driving small farmers out of farming is now in top gear and probably cannot be stopped.  Although it is dictated by EU economic policies, it is also a worldwide phenomenon.  No apparent heed had been taken of the social destruction that follows in its wake and no counter-balancing policies are evident to deal with the destruction. In many European countries, such as France, thousands of rural communities will disappear and many villages are already deserted or reduced to one or two families.  In Ireland we are rushing along with the same policies and seemingly cannot wait to catch up with our European partners.</P>
    <P>This policy is unstoppable and probably irreversible.  I do not think that we will ever see the day when large farms will be broken up into smaller units.  We must accept that the new situation exists and formulate policies to deal with it. The new situation will mean fewer farms and, consequently, fewer farm families.  A reduction in population leads speedily to the inevitable break up of rural society and the loss of services, which the Minister is looking at seriously.  We cannot criticise the farming community for this or tell them how to run their business; they have to make a living, which is increasingly difficult to do on a small farm.</P>
    <P>With regard to the global farming situation, we can only lament that while on the one hand we have apparent massive overproduction and storage of mountains of beef, on the other hand people in the Third World are suffering from starvation and famine.  This sorry mess also results from policies which are purely economic driven.  Clearly, as humans, we have a long way to go before we sort out our priorities.</P>
    <P>Small farmers must leave the land and we must adjust our thinking about other categories of people who could live in rural areas and link this to a concept of sharing the natural wealth of Ireland with our fellow citizens.  The fundamental <Col N="1284" /> error which we are making is to consider the rural depopulation problem in isolation from the total Irish population.</P>
    <P>I wish to make some points about a rural renewal policy which would encompass broader Irish society.  We must accept that the problem exists and needs to be tackled.  People often talk about reversing or stopping the situation, but we are in an inevitable decline and must accept that a problem exists. We should focus our attention on the problem and open lines of communication in search of solutions for the developing situation.  This could act as a catalyst to bring together many diverse groups which have a vital interest in rural life but may never meet to discuss the crisis under normal circumstances.</P>
    <P>If a rural renewal policy was established and guidelines laid down, things could begin to happen.  At present development takes place on an <i>ad hoc</i> basis with all the attendant difficulties which such an approach implies.  For example, <i>ad hoc</i> developments may have extreme difficulty in getting official support and their full potential may never be realised because no mechanism exists to correlate specific developments to needs in other areas or to assess their improvement as part of an overall plan.  The development of the whole Leader programme concept is the key to an overall co-ordinated approach to the development of an area which encompasses all the activities in that area.</P>
    <P>Renewal policies in urban areas have resulted in massive investment in these areas over the past few years.  Investment in rural areas would be quite different, but until an official policy is in place little investment of any kind can take place.  The tax incentives which are part of the urban renewal programme have transformed Limerick city.  Such incentives would attract investment to rural areas.</P>
    <P>A comprehensive renewal policy could plan for developments in areas such as housing, industry, farming and tourism.  Development agencies could be co-ordinated to formulate a renewal <Col N="1285" /> policy for part of a county and so on, such as the development of the Leader programme to introduce incentives into the area.  Most importantly, decisions about rural development could be made and carried through with Government backing.  Local authorities and county councils would have a key role to play in that.</P>
    <P>A rural renewal policy should be people oriented.  The fundamental motivation should be to open up opportunities for as many families as possible to live in rural areas, including opportunities for displaced small farmers and the children of small farm families to live in their own areas, as well as resettling families from urban areas. The Minister of State has some experience of that in Clare.  Under such policies huge areas of rural Ireland could become virtually residential areas.  A precedent for this has been established in the Gweedore Gaeltacht area of Donegal, which is considered to be the most densely populated non-urban area in Europe.  If it can be done in Gweedore, why can the concept not be developed elsewhere?  It is not a new concept because in the early 19th century we had a population of eight million, most of whom lived in rural areas.</P>
    <P>In order to develop this residential concept many rural areas would need to be upgraded with the provision of better facilities.  An immediate stay would have to be put on the closure of small schools, post offices, police stations and so on.  It would be impossible to attract new families to live in rural areas if the essential services were allowed to close down.  Housing grants should be geared to upgrade existing rural houses for new families.  With regard to social housing schemes, the share ownership scheme should be developed to encourage people to live in rural areas.</P>
    <P>I referred four or five times in the last three weeks to the fact that there is no point in talking about rural renewal if we do not have roads in rural Ireland.  It is a prerequisite to any discussion on rural renewal that people have access to rural areas, which in many areas at <Col N="1286" /> present they do not have.  Public transport is non existent in many areas.  Provision must be made for mini bus services to local towns or the introduction of special licences for car owners to operate cheap taxi rates in rural areas. Most rural areas do not have a taxi service. Surely it is nut beyond the ingenuity of our policy makers to give consideration to a special type of taxi licence in rural areas &mdash; to be used on a part time basis, for example &mdash; so that people who come to live there will have the services which are available in urban areas.</P>
    <P>Rural villages should receive special grants and encouragement to upgrade their environment.  In that context I welcome the recently announced village and town renewal grants.  This is an important EU development and we should build upon it; last year there was a tentative approach and this year there is a further development.  It is important to develop this approach to giving grants to upgrading small towns and villages.</P>
    <P>Special medical services should be retained in all areas.  If there is an increase in the numbers living in rural Ireland, naturally the dentists and doctors will remain there because they will have a population to service.  Leisure activities must be part of any renewal policy.  Any renewal policy should provide finance and encouragement for the development of such activities, which will make it more attractive to live in rural areas, especially for young people.  Facilities involved would include swimming baths, sports centres and more mobile libraries in areas in which they do not currently exist.</P>
    <P>A rural renewal policy must tackle unemployment.  There has been a trend towards moving unemployed families into rural areas; but with the rebuilding of the population, the introduction of new skills and trade and an expanding labour force, new opportunities for the development of small industries would present themselves.  Special grants, grant packages and tax incentives should be made available to make rural <Col N="1287" /> renewal comparable to the urban renewal scheme.</P>
    <P>Financial packages should be included for the development of one person enterprises of all kinds.  These should be free of the matching finance requirements of the Leader scheme when unemployed people are involved because there would be a payback in the reduction in social welfare costs.  A special programme of research into viable enterprises for community and private enterprises should be set up. The results of this research should be available on an ongoing basis.</P>
    <P>The local authorities would be the appropriate bodies to implement and co-ordinate a rural renewal policy.  This is not a new concept, because in urban areas urban councils are responsible for urban renewal.  County councils should form subcommittees with responsibility to combat rural decay.  Given the current draws on county council funding, the Government should recognise the need to appoint special local authority officers, designated to follow through and co-ordinate different aspects of renewal in each county.  This should be appropriately funded by central Government.</P>
    <P>All local authorities already deal with all the areas which need development, such as housing, water and sewerage schemes, roads, planning, etc.  In the case of planning, local authorities should adopt a &ldquo;people-friendly&rdquo; approach to new buildings.  The bias should be strongly in favour of encouragement to populate areas rather than refusing permission based on other possibly subjective factors.  We do not want to destroy the landscape, but there is a balance to be struck between returning people to the country and aesthetic planning to suit tourism.  We must find that balance to encourage people to return and live in the countryside.</P>
    <P>Providers of essential services such as electricity, post, telephone, public health and the Garda are for all intents and purposes part of the institutions of the State.  They were established with <Col N="1288" /> taxpayers' money and as part of the State have an obligation under the Constitution to cherish all the citizens equally.  It is necessary to make that point in the context of a rural renewal policy, because the modern tendency for some essential services is to consider the provision of these services purely on economic grounds.</P>
    <P>However, certain basic constitutional rights must be recognised.  Essential services are by definition essential for all citizens; people in densely populated areas have no greater right to them than people from sparsely populated areas. Providers of these services must manage their affairs in a manner which enables them to service all the people, irrespective of where they live.  There will always be extreme cases where exceptions apply, but in general there should be a policy of servicing all rural areas.</P>
    <P>Providers of essential services have no right under the Constitution to make judgments based on purely economic criteria to withdraw services from rural areas.  Economic criteria and social and constitutional obligations are compatible and where decisions to withdraw are based fundamentally on the former, social deprivation and a reduction in population is inevitable.  It is impossible to contemplate the revitalising of rural communities once essential services such as post offices and schools have been withdrawn.  Closures are more than a mere symptom of decay; they represent a major contributory factor towards the death of small communities.</P>
    <P>On the positive side, because the providers of essential services are huge organisations with massive resources, they are surely in a strong position to lend a hand to communities in trouble. The State, which represents the people of Ireland in a single community, has an obligation to come to the assistance of any threatened part of the community. whether in the city or the country.  The institutions of the State share the responsibility to save communities. Instead of threatening rural areas with the closure of 600 sub-post offices.  An Post could introduce a cheap rate for <Col N="1289" /> small parcels to enable vegetable growers to post directly to customers in the city.  This could be based on a specially designed and uniform box which could be reusable.  This is only one idea; the ESB and other institutions could look at other ways of providing extra services, which could bring more revenue.</P>
    <P>The Minister's proposal to bring various services under one root in rural areas is one innovative idea and other such approaches are needed.  Bus Éireann and Iarnród Éireann should be involved.  Iarnród Éireann once cut off vast areas of rural Ireland from the railways. Even 30 years later people believe that was wrong.  If these services were still available, they could enhance rural areas, and even although they might not all break even some could provide a small profit.</P>
    <P>All the services should be part of an integrated rural renewal policy, with the objective of the retention and development of country areas.  Some of the ideas these people bring forward will work, others will not; but if we do not try we will have nothing.  Closures, on the other hand, have a 100 per cent guaranteed negative impact, with a deadly knock on effect on the future of rural Ireland.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JoeLee" hpid="Professor Lee Professor Lee">
      <NameTxt>Professor Lee</NameTxt>
      <P>This report is potentially important &mdash; the topic certainly is. We debate matters such as rural development fairly frequently in this Chamber.  I recall the long discussion we had on <i>A Crusade for Survival,</i> the bishops' report on saving the west.  One sometimes wonders if it makes a blind bit of difference because little cognisance seems to be taken of points made. One wonders if we are just talking to ourselves.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I listened with great interest to what both Senators Dardis and Neville said. It is on precisely this sort of topic that Members of the Oireachtas have insights based on personal knowledge of a type that I and many of the experts who compile and pronounce on these reports do not have and which is potentially illuminating for policy purposes.  I <Col N="1290" /> have learnt a good deal this afternoon from listening to them.  I hope cognisance will be taken by policy makers of a number of the points made.</P>
    <P>I welcome the NESC report partly because one could have said that the western bishops' document was a vested interest document compiled by people living in the west who were simply proposing measures which would benefit themselves and would say what they said anyway.  If one examines the composition of NESC, one finds that it is an almost totally Dublin-based body.  It is therefore particularly encouraging that it has come out so strongly in favour of sustaining and developing rural Ireland. Particular cognisance should be taken of that.  This cannot be said to represent the vested interest of the majority of its members.  It must derive from a degree of intellectual conviction which is independent of individual or institutional interest.  Particular attention should be paid to it.</P>
    <P>I agree with Senator Neville that this is not a problem of rural Ireland but a national problem.  The basic problem is that we have shown we cannot cope with a population of 3.5 million people. For a long time after independence our population hovered around 3 million while the population of the rest of Europe was rising on a steady upwards trajectory.  We persuaded ourselves that if our population would rise, it would reflect some sort of injection of national virility and create a larger market which would be self-sustaining.</P>
    <P>Between 1970 and 1990 when the population began to rise by that staggering figure of 0.5 million &mdash; the size of a self-respecting London suburb &mdash; we found that rather than being an opportunity, it was a problem.  We began to blame unemployment and other problems on our population growth which was, most unsportingly, out of synch with the rest of Europe which was levelling off.  We still have one of the sparsest populations in Europe.  Quite frankly the record of the last 20 years is that we do not have the managerial capacity in this country to cope with a population <Col N="1291" /> of 3.5 million people.  It does not matter what growth rates we have or what we say about being the leading light of the European economy, we simply cannot cope with that population.</P>
    <P>Structural population decline is the essence of the definition of the rural problem.  Population decline becomes self-sustaining because the core of the community is broken.  Outer migration of people in the productive age groups leaves one with the young and the old and there is no viability left in the community. Even though it has elements of the urban problem and parts of the solutions are similar, the rural problem is not essentially one of unemployment. According to the official statistics, there is higher unemployment in many of the worst hit suburban areas in Ireland than there is in rural Ireland.</P>
    <P>The problems of Coolock, Darndale, Gurranebraher or Southill in unemployment terms are statistically worse than the problems even of Leitrim which we take as the paradigm of everything that can go wrong in rural Ireland.  Places such as Coolock and Darndale are not suffering structural population decline. Those communities are not going to wither away because of the problems they have.  Structural population decline is in progress over most of rural Ireland outside of a few counties towards the east and is the essential difference between rural and urban problems.</P>
    <P>I have one question for the Minister. It struck me on looking at the albeit illuminating maps in the NESC report that they stop at the Border.  What is the situation in Northern Ireland?  Is rural Northern Ireland suffering similar problems? The population density of Northern Ireland is about double that of the South.  If we had the same population density as the North, we would have a population of about 7 million.  We can imagine how we would cope with that if we cannot cope with 3.5 million.  I regret that the lines in the Northern Ireland statistics office were down this morning in this age of information technology <Col N="1292" /> which some see as the solution to all our problems.</P>
    <P>I had a quick glance at such data as I was able to get my hands on relating to Fermanagh and Tyrone, just across the Border.  The information in the statistics publication which came to hand is presented in a singularly unhelpful manner. In Fermanagh and Tyrone, four of the five district council areas of Cookstown, Dungannon, Fermanagh, Omagh and Strabane, with a population of over 210,000, experienced an increase in population between 1981 and 1991. There may be variations within it that are not captured here.  Only the district council area of Strabane fell from over 36,000 to 35,500 which is less than a 2 per cent decline.</P>
    <P>The other areas in Fermanagh and Tyrone, rural counties on the far side of the Border which may be presumed to be suffering to some extent from the types of problems we are only too familiar with on this side of the Border, all showed an increase.  They were not big increases &mdash; 2 or 3 per cent over that decade.  I deduce from that rightly or wrongly &mdash; those with more detailed information can correct me &mdash; that these counties are not suffering the type of structural population decline which we have identified as the essence of the rural problem in the South.  It would be useful if some research was done by people down here on what is happening there and if the deduction is correct.  If they are not suffering the identical problem, what are they doing that we might be able to learn?</P>
    <P>While our statistical abstract gives data on Northern Ireland, very often it is not in a form which is easily comparable for deducing policy implications.  I am grateful the information is there but it would be nice if we had a more policy oriented presentation of relevant data. It would be interesting to keep that dimension in mind.</P>
    <P>The report reinforces Senator Neville's point that we have no settlement policy in this State.  We have a rural development policy where rural development is isolated from national <Col N="1293" /> policy.  Many of the reasons for our failure to cope with the problems of rural Ireland are similar to the reasons for our failure to cope with many of the problems in urban Ireland.  There are recommendations in the report about institutional developments and the difficulty in co-ordinating numerous bodies whether they be State, non-State, community, local.  EU supported and so on. Those self same problems arise in most urban areas.  The same problem of coordination arises whether it is in rural or urban Ireland.</P>
    <P>The report contains a devastating vote of no confidence in our local authorities. It basically says that our local authorities are not competent to be entrusted with responsibility for discharging, as the central co-ordinating agencies, the types of policy recommended in the report.  I do not know whether that is justified.  I listened to Senator Neville saying that the local authorities ought to be more central to development.  If the vote of no confidence in our local authorities as possible engines of local development is justified then it is a frightening indictment not only of local government but of central Government because local government in this country is largely what central Government has made it.  Local government is the product of the powers that central Government has taken away from it and of the way central Government has chosen to organise and repress it.</P>
    <P>I do not doubt that there may be many things wrong with local government but if one is serious about energising local communities and if one wants to take this fashionable word &ldquo;empowerment&rdquo; seriously then one has to ask how one restores confidence in local government.  How does one give it the powers which allow it to act effectively and responsibly?  How can one expect people to act responsibly if they are not given real responsibility to exercise? This is a lacuna in the report, which seems to take the inadequacies of our local government system as given <Col N="1294" /> and virtually beyond human redemption.</P>
    <P>Although there is talk year in, year out about reform of local government, with reports on various aspects, it must be a central part of an overall strategy for the long term rejuvenation of all Ireland, not just rural Ireland.  Strategy is a much misused word, but it must not be regarded as a problem.  How does one turn a problem into an opportunity? It is a very large programme and it will not be done by one or several Governments. However, if there is not a long term objective and determination to do this, it will not happen at all.  A great deal of recommendations about rural or urban development, including Dublin itself, will be about how we circumvent the existing official structure of Government, rather than how we utilise it effectively. This is a sad commentary on the way we choose to manage our affairs.</P>
    <P>I agree with Senator Neville that a stop should be put on closures of small institutions in rural Ireland.  The report stresses emphatically what many of us have repeatedly said and which is self evident, that most of our Government planning is done in sectors.  Government is organised in sectors and Departments are organised around sectors.  However, nobody lives in a sector; we all live in places.</P>
    <P>There are very few mechanisms for co-ordinating the parallel activities of sectors.  An Post will close the small post office, the Department of Education will close the small school and the Department of Justice will close the small Garda station.  Within their own terms of reference and the tunnel vision with which they operate, they are perfectly justified in doing so on accounting grounds, not even on economic grounds, which are often myopic or short term.</P>
    <P>As long as Cabinet allows these to be the terms of reference of those Departments, they will continue to proceed along those lines.  There must be a policy decision that Cabinet is not prepared to accept that criterion if one is concerned with revitalising rural and urban communities.  The question of the <Col N="1295" /> viability of communities must be a central concern and criterion and all these proposals should be subject to proofing. There is now gender proofing of many committees and correctly so.  We should have community viability proofing of recommendations which taken in isolation may seem justifiable, but when added up simply subvert the viability and squeeze the life from them, even though nobody actually intends it.  I urge the Minister to try to have as a central plank of Government policy that the overall implications for the viability of the communities affected, whether they are villages, parishes or small towns, should be a central criterion in the evaluation of any such decisions.</P>
    <P>I strongly support the emphasis placed on settlement policy by this report.  There is no national settlement policy and there is a very skewed distribution of population between the capital city and the rest of the country.  I am not speaking against the capital city because there is as much powerlessness in large areas of Dublin, within a couple of miles of this building, as there is in the most remote parts of Ireland.</P>
    <P>The only other country in the EU which has such a top heavy capital city in demographic and power terms is Greece.  To the best of my knowledge, Athens and its greater area is the only other city in the EU whose proportion of total national population comes anywhere near the proportion of national population accounted for by the greater Dublin area.  This is not an anti-Dublin statement, but it means that we face a specific type of problem in this country in terms of settlement policy.</P>
    <P>There has been one settlement policy. By locating the headquarters of virtually every State body in Dublin, we automatically suck in all the resources attached to that type of location in terms of finance, support agencies, consultancies and power decisions, which are taken from a Dublin-centric perspective, however inadvertently.  I may be wrong in the precise figures but there are approximately 86 State or semi-State <Col N="1296" /> agencies, of which 81 have their headquarters in Dublin.  I was looking at the figures for Stockholm the other day and there are approximately 83 Swedish bodies, of which 41 have their headquarters in Stockholm.</P>
    <P>If 40 Irish semi-State or State agencies had headquarters properly located in areas to which they are most relevant around the country, one can imagine the difference it would make to a number of local areas.  An Bord Bia and a Marine Institute were recently established in Dublin when there were strong claims for them to go elsewhere in terms of the part of the State which is most actively concerned with them.</P>
    <P>There is an interesting section in the report on information technology and one should not exaggerate its potential for rejuvenating rural Ireland or the way in which it can reduce distance.  In terms of decision making centres, there is no reason why agency after agency must cluster beside one another in order to arrive at coherent decisions, even if they were co-ordinating their policies, which most of them do not.  I argue strongly that we need a settlement policy, devised at national level.</P>
    <P>What role can the education system in general and locally play in energising people to think about local development, whether rural or urban?  What role can the universities in particular play in inducing potential policy makers to think in area terms rather than sectoral terms?  One reason why we operate sectoral policies is that almost all the people working in those departments, in so far as there are an increasing number of graduates, come from departments and universities which are also organised on a sectoral basis.  For example, there are departments of economics, sociology, politics and public administration, all of which deal with some aspect of national problems.  However, none sees Ireland whole or from the point of view of integrated policy making.</P>
    <P>If one looks at any reports which are published, &ldquo;integrated&rdquo; is now one of the most fashionable words in our <Col N="1297" /> vocabulary.  It is nearly as fashionable as &ldquo;strategic&rdquo;.  When one cannot think of something to say, one shoves in &ldquo;strategic&rdquo;. There are no plans, just strategic plans.  On one page of the National Development Plan, the word &ldquo;strategic&rdquo; occurred six times and it meant precisely nothing every single time.  One is in trouble it one has a strategic plan, but one is in real trouble if one has an integrated strategic plan because it means that one doubly does not know what one is talking about or how to do it.</P>
    <P>Integration is, of course, necessary when there is so much fragmentation in policy making, but how to integrate is another matter.  It is left to individuals who have no personal experience, rather than being educated in concepts of integration or working in institutions which foster integration.  There ought to be encouragements and inducements available to some of our institutions of higher education to set up courses which try to teach potential policy makers how to think in integrated terms, without them simply having to pick this up as they go along, if they ever pick it up.</P>
    <P>This will not solve everything.  One cannot teach many things, which have to be picked up in real life outside. However, much of this is a question of mind set and a silent assumption that one does not interrogate oneself about. Rural and any other type of development should be asking what is the potential within the education system for inducing the type of approach which will be more conducive to what we are all trying to achieve.  I am loathe to say it, but I fear the initiative for this must come from the State because within the university sector we too think in sectoral terms.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MaryKelly" hpid="Ms Kelly Ms Kelly">
      <NameTxt>Ms Kelly</NameTxt>
      <P>In the Labour Party a fate worse than death is to be asked to speak after the Minister for Arts, Culture and the Gaeltacht, Deputy Michael Higgins. In the Seanad a similar fate is to speak after Senator Lee.  How can one compare with his eloquence?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I welcome this report as the most comprehensive to date on rural <Col N="1298" /> development.  The report is matter enough for ten days debate so any discussion on it will be rather hit and miss. I agree with Senator Neville and Senator Lee that the problems of rural Ireland are ones of population and settlement.  We have a decline in population in rural Ireland and, as Senator Lee pointed out, the decline is structural. We are losing rapidly the people who will make the difference in the future between a viable and a dead rural Ireland.</P>
    <P>The report mentions the possibility that we may have to accept and plan for rural decline.  It is the first time I have seen anybody face up to the reality that we may not be able to stop rural decline. To date we have been happy to promote strategies to reverse rural decline, yet this is the first report I have seen which suggests that rural decline may be here to stay.</P>
    <P>When one considers it the answer to rural decline is simple &mdash; one must get more people back into rural Ireland. That in turn means plans will have to be made as to what to do with the people one gets back into rural areas.  People must have jobs.  Trends in farming mean that as a sector it can no longer be expected to support the numbers it supported in pre-famine Ireland.  It is pointless to consider farming as the only sector which will keep young people in rural Ireland.  One must look to other farm-based activities or industries based loosely on rural life to keep people at work in rural areas.</P>
    <P>As has been said time and again, people will not stay in rural areas without the basic social fabric.  There needs to be schools, post offices, churches. community centres and leisure facilities. If they are not in place it is more tempting for somebody to build or buy in the nearest large town.  Local and national authorities have a role to play.  We must look at settlement policy in its entirety. Local authorities can examine their housing allocations.  Local councillors can make a conscious decision to build houses in the smaller villages for people who have gone to the larger towns to <Col N="1299" /> encourage them to return with skills they may have acquired.  Many skills are needed in rural areas which people have to seek in larger towns.  It is increasingly difficult to get a local carpenter, electrician or plumber; one may have to go some distance to the nearest town and there is the added problem of transport for the tradesman.</P>
    <P>We should encourage local service providers.  If there is not enough work in a local area to fully support a carpenter or plumber, the Government should look at ways in which these services can be supplemented.  A list of what is needed in a rural area could be drawn up and if an electrician, for example, is needed we could find one who grew up in a rural area and who would like to return, pay him basic income and let him top it up with what work he can get.  People with skills are the first to leave if they do not find a job in their own area.  They will not remain idle but will move to find jobs. The starting point is to keep the skills in the countryside.  Skilled people are the leaders of their communities and without them community development will die.</P>
    <P>A problem with the Leader groups and the area based development groups as currently constituted is that the areas which make the best use of the Leader programme are those areas where there is already leadership potential, where the people are already organised and there is some element of vitality left in the community.  Where that is missing and communities are dying, they are the last to be organised; they are the last in the queue for whatever help is being given out.  They often find themselves left out and one finds the money that should have been going to them being taken up by other, better organised communities.  Even within a disadvantaged area or an area where the Leader Programme is operating it is the better areas that seem to get the cream of the crop, so to speak.</P>
    <P>I am worried about the analysis of local government in the report.  Looking <Col N="1300" /> through the list of those who compiled the report, I could not identify one county councillor.  The Acting Chairman, Senator Farrell, the Minister of State and I, as local councillors, could simply outline what has been missing in local government for the past 20 years &mdash; money.  When rates were abolished local authorities were starved of money and they could not do anything.</P>
    <P>There is plenty of potential among local councillors.  They have come from the community.  One could not get elected to a local council unless one had already shown a willingness to take part in community development.  To say that local councillors are not in tune with what is happening locally is to miss the central point &mdash; they would not be local councillors had they not been involved locally.  When county councils attempt to draw up estimates it is evident that they are starved of money.  Successive Governments of all parties have starved them of money.  All Senators who have been on a local authority will agree that if local authorities were given the money the development would take place.  When councils have had access to that extra few pounds they have shown what they can do in developing local communities.  Without that money many councillors became apathetic and disillusioned, although these were not the first factors to arise.</P>
    <P>This brings me to one matter that worries me enormously about these initiatives.  Every year county councillors have to produce a book of estimates and every penny spent is subject to scrutiny.  However, I do not see this same scrutiny being imposed on many of the Leader groups and area partnerships and I fear this is a potential weakness. Many people say that if these groups were put under the control of local authorities, they would become politicised and councillors would get political credit for any work that was done.  There are as many people in the Leader groups who are as well attuned politically and are members of political parties, as one would find in any local <Col N="1301" /> council, but they are not shackled by having to report back to the public once a year by way of a book of estimates.</P>
    <P>This report is slightly lacking in a few areas.  While it is the best report that has been issued to date, it does look very much on the economic aspects of rural development.  Little attention has been given to its social aspects.  After all, it was the National Economic and Social Council that devised the report.  From that point of view I would consider it to be slightly defective.  One's social life and leisure facilities can be as important to one's feeling of wellbeing as one's economic situation.  There should be some kind of planned social development. For example, there is little in the report about education.  Senator Lee asked some interesting questions about the role of education and in changing the mind set of our people, particularly those young people who grow up in rural areas.  They want to kick the dust of the countryside off their heels as quickly as possible and go to the nearest big city, which could be Boston or New York, out of a yearning for excitement which they feel they are not getting at home.  Looking at that aspect of rural life may be as important as organising jobs.</P>
    <P>Another failing of the report is that it makes little reference to the role of women in rural Ireland.  The contribution that those women make to the economy is totally undercounted and undervalued.  Little reference seems to be made in it to the need to support women living in this region and to support the provision of services for them, particularly those of health and child care.  Child care services are usually aimed at working women, but that facility should be there for all women. Many women, particularly those with small children, may need this facility if, for example, they need to go to hospital for a checkup.  Unless a neighbour is willing to mind the children, there is no way they can go without bringing them. Small things like that can make a big difference to a woman living in a rural area.  The feeling of isolation is enormous, <Col N="1302" /> although we are not looking at that aspect of rural life today.</P>
    <P>I welcome the report; it is a good one. I also welcome the emphasis it places on the need for special planning and coordination, not only between the agencies working on the ground but between local, regional and central Government. I wish the Minister well in his portfolio; he has an arduous task ahead of him. Hopefully, before the Minister's term in office ends we will see measures put in train that will reverse the level of depopulation and structural decline and also see a little more life being brought back to rural Ireland.</P>
    <Speaker pid="DonnieCassidyFF" hpid="Mr. Cassidy Mr. Cassidy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cassidy</NameTxt>
      <P>Whatever the procedures of this House are under the Committee on Procedure and Privileges &mdash; and both you and I are members of that distinguished body, a Leas-Chathaoirleach &mdash; a member of the largest political party should not have to wait for four speakers to contribute before that party's turn comes around again.  If a group that is supposed to be speaking are not here to take their place&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>This is a resumed debate, Senator.  The point you have raised, as you have rightly said, is a matter for the Committee on Procedure and Privileges and not a matter for me at this point in time.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DonnieCassidyFF" hpid="Mr. Cassidy Mr. Cassidy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cassidy</NameTxt>
      <P>Perhaps you might raise this point at the next meeting of the committee, a Leas-Chathaoirleach.  We could have a discussion on it so as to help all Members.  I have waited a long time to contribute and I have stayed on, out of frustration and a lack of understanding of the rules of the House.  If a Member of a group is not here to speak, we should not be penalised.  However, the Chair is usually very fair and this seldom happens.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I understand there was no other Independent contribution before that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1303" />
    <Speaker pid="DonnieCassidyFF" hpid="Mr. Cassidy Mr. Cassidy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cassidy</NameTxt>
      <P>I welcome this debate on rural development.  The Minister with responsibility for that area has come to the House again &mdash; he is a hard working man.  Indeed, this is the second day in a row he has graced this Chamber with his presence.  I am delighted to see in this Ministry someone with such vast political experience of rural Ireland, coming from a dynamic part of the country, a man who has the expertise, experience and success of major companies like Aer Rianta in his constituency.  These companies have become world market leaders, have shown great incentive and created great wealth that many of our people enjoy.  I wish the Minister well in his new portfolio.</P>
      <P>For too long we have witnessed the decline of rural areas and the migration of people to far off countries like Australia, America and Canada in search of work.  One of our greatest problems is the total geographical imbalance of our population.  One third of our population lives in the greater Dublin area.  Furthermore, if one considers the whole of the east coast from Antrim to Wexford, it is clear that a disproportionate number of people are living there.  This is an unfair imbalance that has built up around the capital city.  It must be urgently addressed if the Minister is to succeed and if the problems that face our rural communities are to be dealt with.  However, it can only be done if there is a radical review of rural development and if we get away from some of the old ideas to which I referred.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Coming from a rural area, I know the potential values and strengths of rural areas if they were properly developed. There is a sense of community in rural areas, where everybody has an important part to play.  I particularly welcome the NESC report on rural development, which contains much useful information.  I am sure it will provide a framework for discussion on how rural Ireland might be developed.  I hope the report will stimulate a detailed look at the requirements of rural areas and that <Col N="1304" /> the Government will develop the necessary policies to ensure development.</P>
    <P>The Taoiseach and the Government must be congratulated for appointing Deputy Carey as Minister with responsibility for rural development.  Like the Leas-Chathaoirleach and myself, he comes from a rural area and would know about the imbalance with must be addressed.  We look forward to Minister Carey's proposals and to their implementation, which will benefit people in rural Ireland.</P>
    <P>It is important that the Government should remember that time is running out for many communities and that unless drastic action is taken, there will be no younger generation coming up. Due to dramatic demographic changes many areas face the prospect of schools being reduced to two or one teacher schools and the closing of essential services like post offices and Garda stations.  We are all aware of the benefit to rural communities which personnel from the Garda Síochána, post offices, creameries and other services provided and the benefit of their incomes.</P>
    <P>From the point of view of security, it is essential that Garda stations in villages with populations of 500 or more are reopened and fully manned.  Now that security has been reduced in Border areas &mdash; Members from those areas will know the financial constraint that had on expenditure &mdash; additional resources should be redirected to rural villages and towns.</P>
    <P>It is appalling that the Garda station in a town the size of Castlepollard, with population of 900-1,000 people, is open only for two hours.  If one requires a garda one must press a button on what is called &ldquo;the green man&rdquo;.  I am not complaining about the service provided by gardaí in Mullingar and Granard; it is excellent.  Two weeks ago I had to call on that service because of something suspicious in the area.  Gardaí arrived within ten minutes, having travelled ten miles.  However, local gardaí provided better security because they were a deterrent.  People in rural area are entitled to the same security as those in <Col N="1305" /> towns and cities.  This problem has not been created by the Garda but by the policies pursued by Government and the Minister for Justice.</P>
    <P>Rural life was richer because the gardaí were the backbone of musical societies, the GAA and other organisations. They set a good example and often trained teams because they were fit.  From that point of view, many of the proposals which have come before both Houses demean and take from small towns and villages.  There is no point putting resources into concrete jungles where unemployment is on the increase. Although I have spent a lot of time in Dublin since 1976, we have a better chance of getting things working in rural areas and future investment must cater for those who want to work in such areas.</P>
    <P>Our road infrastructure has improved considerably.  As someone who travelled 60,000 miles around Ireland each year for 18 years and also as a Seanad candidate, the improvements on primary roads are mind-boggling.  Like the late Donagh O'Malley, who gave us free education, and other Ministers who came up with novel ideas at a low cost, Minister Carey should be able to look back on his career as a Minister in a number of years and say that he got £200 million for county and secondary roads.  If County Westmeath, with a population of 73,000, got an additional allocation of £2 million, every road in the county, from <i>cul-de-sacs</i> to national primary roads, would not need to be repaired for ten years.</P>
    <P>At present good money is being thrown after bad on surface dressing, etc.  I am not talking about roads like those in Counties Cavan or Monaghan, which are in a worse condition than those in County Westmeath, but about a once off allocation of £200 million which would solve the problem of our roads. I am sure a case could be made to the European Parliament for 50 per cent funding in this regard.  It is a waste to allocate only one-third of that amount over ten years when a once-off allocation would do a better job at half the <Col N="1306" /> cost.  I suggest that that could be a legacy which Minister Carey could enjoy in years to come and which would improve the environment for those in rural communities.</P>
    <P>Although many reports have been produced, I welcome this one, which, I hope, will stimulate debate and action and will not be thrown on the shelf.  I hope this debate will not concentrate on the agricultural community only.  Why are rural development policies normally under the aegis of the Department of Agriculture, Food and Forestry?  One of the great myths of modern Ireland is that most people living in rural areas are involved in agriculture.  This is no longer true.  While agriculture plays a vital and important role, there are now more people working in industry than agriculture in rural Ireland.  This fact is analysed in the report.  I quote from chapter 12, page 201:</P>
    <P>There is a growing inter-dependence between rural areas and urban centres, with the demographic vitality of many rural areas becoming tied to the development of a diversified rural economy rather than to agriculture.</P>
    <P>We know this is true.  It is only when rural development is viewed in its wider context that we realise the importance of developing a broad rural infrastructure that would include a full service sector.</P>
    <P>We must continue to try to preserve our post offices.  We must insist on the localisation of as many services as possible. To this end it is very important that a whole range of services would be available locally.  There is no reason that this would not be possible with computer technology.  Computer technology has made the world a village in relation to business and information.  It is a great gift we are not using to the fullest, particularly in rural Ireland.  People should no longer have to go to a town to tax their cars, apply for social welfare, get information on tax returns or 101 other things.  With computer technology, services should be brought to the people and not the other way round. <Col N="1307" /> Every Wednesday and Saturday, due to modern technology, thousands of people play the national lottery.  At the press of a button they can have their coupons registered and returned.  There is no reason why post offices cannot be used for the registration of cars and the various services that could be supplied in local communities.</P>
    <P>I listened attentively to previous contributions to this debate.  I was very interested when Senator Neville said that a great example of rural life and community is in Gweedore, County Donegal.  He stated &mdash; I have no reason to disbelieve him, in fact I was delighted to hear it &mdash; that Gweedore is one of the most densely populated rural areas in Europe.  Whatever their secret of success and given the great community spirit which has developed in the Gweedore area, perhaps the Minister of State, when he next visits the Sligo/Donegal area, might go to Gweedore to meet community leaders and find out how they are keeping the community together.</P>
    <P>However, I return to my point of making the best services available through technology.  Many technological services could be administered by post offices.  It would surely be one way of subsiding the income of the postmaster or mistress in rural towns and villages if they administered these services.  I worked in a post office for nearly five years and I know the great community information centre a post office can be. Postmen going out and delivering letters to all the houses is a terrific social service. People living in rural areas quite often never meet or speak to anyone all day.  Perhaps 5 or 10 per cent of people in rural areas meet only the person who delivers their post.  From that point of view, rural life will have to be protected. The people in charge of post offices are not paid very much.  In fact, when we debated the issue of post offices in this House it was discovered that for the small amount of money they were paid, they would nearly be better off to claim social welfare.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="1308" /> A similar attitude must be adopted in relation to service jobs, particularly within the State sector.  There is no reason for a huge, centralised bureaucracy to be based in Dublin.  We must set ourselves a target that no person in the country should be living more than 30 miles from the opportunity of gaining employment in a Government office. There should be further decentralisation so that rural people would not have to move to bigger cities if they wanted to gain employment in a Government office.  The major semi-State bodies should also decentralise their headquarters.  I have never understood the logic of having the headquarters of Bord na Móna, Coillte Teoranta or Teagasc based in Dublin.  Why should the office employment in these organisations be based in the capital city when the reason for their existence is based on rural life and when they draw their resources and strength from rural Ireland?</P>
    <P>We must also ensure that rural Ireland is provided with a proper infrastructure in terms of railways, roads, electricity supplies, telephones, fibreoptic, cables etc..  We must also have the necessary infrastructure of water and sewage, which is vital in rural Ireland. In this modern age only about 50 per cent of smaller towns and villages in rural Ireland have sewage facilities. There is no reason why we cannot achieve as high a material standard of living in a rural area as exists in the cities. With the advent of television, the need to travel to the bright lights of the city no longer exists.  The situation 30 years ago was that people went to live in the cities because of the facilities available there.  People should now be given a free choice and work opportunities. The urban renewal programme has been an outstanding success.  I would be delighted to see the Government consider at some time in the future a rural renewal programme.  It would be a magnificent opportunity for people from the country to invest in their own areas and create their own employment and wealth.</P>
    <Col N="1309" />
    <Speaker pid="FergalQuinn" hpid="Mr. Quinn Mr. Quinn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Quinn</NameTxt>
      <P>I am glad of the opportunity to speak in this debate.  I welcome the Minister of State.  He has responsibility for the west, but that cannot help but be a responsibility for rural development also.  I am sure he will find the report of immense benefit.</P>
      <P>We cannot separate the challenge of rural development from that of regional development.  That is why I am delighted the Minister of State is here. We have to tackle both together, as two sides of the one coin, if we are to put right the imbalances that have crept up on us.  The centre of gravity of this country has shifted very definitely and decisively in two ways.  First, there has been a shift away from the rural areas towards the urban areas.  On top of this, and multiplying its effect, has been a further shift away from the western side of the country to the eastern side.  This has been happening for generations but has accelerated in recent years.  The result of this is that we now have a top-heavy country that has been tilted against rural areas, tilted against the western side of the country.  While the rural areas are clearly disadvantaged, rural areas in the west are doubly so.</P>
      <P>I want to make one simple point. These two shifts are not inevitable. They are not unchangeable.  On the contrary, I believe that they can and should be changed.  The question is how we do this.  I am sure the Minister will agree that it must be done with determination. It will not happen by accident.  I welcome the emphasis in the NESC report on the importance of local initiatives and I support its proposals for strengthening institutions to foster and facilitate those many local efforts, which are often going to be small, local, individual efforts but which will culminate in a giant effort when they come together.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I also emphasise that a great deal can be done at the level of national policy &mdash; Senator Lee spoke about this earlier in this debate.  The first stage is simply realising that change is possible.  There are two reasons.  We need a mindset to talk ourselves out of the danger of saying there is nothing we can do about it. <Col N="1310" /> I want to emphasise that change is possible and that something can be done about it.  The first reason is that touched on by Senator Cassidy &mdash; the whole area of the telecommunications revolution, the first waves of which are already with us.  The critical factor about that revolution, which has not been fully appreciated yet, is that for the first time in the history of the world, it can make where you are completely irrelevant to what you want to achieve.  The key cause of these two drifts I refer to, the drift from the west and the drift from rural areas, has now been largely removed.  The centre of gravity shifted from rural to urban because of the locational needs of the economy at the time.  We have to realise that those needs are changing.  We can and must take advantage of that change.</P>
    <P>For some industries, of course, the locational imperative remains.  The drift to the east of the country has come about largely because, as an exporting country, it makes sense for manufacturers to be close to the markets and the ports.  That will not change and there is nothing we can do about it.  What will change is that we now have the opportunity to create service industries that do not have to be in the east.  Telecommunications make it possible for them to be located anywhere they like but, unless we do something about it, these new industries will end up in the east side of the country, along with everything else.  We have to discriminate positively and work to bring about a situation where the west becomes the focus of services and the east, if necessary. becomes the focus of manufacturing. That will not happen unless we, as a State, adopt an aggressive national policy to that effect.  The State can lead it by shifting a far greater proportion of its service activity to the west of the country than has ever been envisaged before.</P>
    <P>The telecommunications revolution is one reason change is possible.  The other is the changing pattern of consumer needs and the increasing emphasis on customer needs in business today.  I have said on many occasions that the future for Irish agriculture is not as Irish <Col N="1311" /> agriculture but as Irish food &mdash; in other words, we must take a customer-driven approach to high value-added products, rather than a producer-driven approach to low-value commodity products.  This change of emphasis in agriculture can apply, and should apply, at the level of the individual farmer.  I have a fear that individual farmers believe it is someone else's job and, particularly, someone else up in Dublin.  Adding value to food need not be only be a matter of huge food processing plants, though they obviously play a large part in this.  It can also be done at the individual farm.  For instance, farmers can decide to go into organic food &mdash; and some have done that very successfully &mdash; for which there is a premium market all across Europe. The key value from the point of view of rural development is that it is also more labour-intensive.  We can reverse the drift away from employment on the farm by using such methods.</P>
    <P>Another way this can be done is by the farmer getting into production of certain foods, right down to the packaging and labelling of them, on the farm itself.  I was recently on a farm in north County Armagh in a townland called Derrylard on the banks of Lough Neagh.  I was there to look at the farm belonging to Séamus and Jennifer Donnelly. It is a small farm and Séamus Donnelly employs 28 to 32 people there. It was interesting to see such a small farm employing this number of people. He listened to the markets, to the customers. He looked at what they wanted and realised that one quality they wanted was freshness.  What he had been producing as a grower of vegetables, he then began to process to the extent that those people are employed not only in growing but in sorting, packing, or labelling.  On his farm one can see the products already packed for the stores &mdash; Marks and Spencers, Wellworths, Stewarts and the Co-op. What he is producing are products that are available in those supermarkets that day, already processed on his farm.  He is cutting out the middleman and getting <Col N="1312" /> close to the customer.  That is one further example of what is possible to achieve.  Individual farmers can develop niche markets in their local areas or beyond for value-added food products. This is the direction we should be encouraging people to explore.</P>
    <P>What we have seen over the past century is a vicious spiral, with the life and vitality drained out of rural areas as they become less and less viable in the new marketplaces.  That decline feeds on itself as time goes on.  What we have built up to is a pessimistic assumption that the whole process is inevitable and irreversible.  As long as we believe that, we condemn ourselves to just tinkering with the problem rather than getting to the solution.  If we can for once convince ourselves that it is possible to reverse these shifts, then we can take a much more aggressive approach.  That needs a mindset change, not just by us in Dublin but by those who are in rural areas, saying that this can be done.  It means that mindset has to change at national level as well as at local level.  We need to be much more aggressive because if we do not tackle rural development aggressively now, time will run out on us and there will be nothing left to build on. Let us make sure this does not happen.</P>
    <P>This NESC report has given us a great deal of food for thought.  Let us make sure that it is not just food for thought but fuel for action so that we do not stand by and let nothing happen.  I am delighted the Minister has given us the opportunity to voice some thoughts on the direction we can take.  I believe he will act on some of the ideas in this report and I am sure he is the person to make things happen.</P>
    <Speaker pid="FrancisOBrien" hpid="Mr. O'Brien Mr. O'Brien">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Brien</NameTxt>
      <P>I would like to wish a very warm welcome to the Minister, Deputy Carey, to this House.  I welcome the opportunity to discuss the National Economic and Social Council report on rural development.  This is an excellent report in many respects and will, if used properly, be of great assistance to all involved in the area of rural development.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="1313" /> Rural development is in need of urgent attention and action must be taken to halt the decline in our rural communities.  The potential of rural Ireland is enormous, and, fully developed, could greatly help rectify many social problems.</P>
    <P>We are all familiar with the decline of rural Ireland over the past 30 years. Houses have closed as people have left in the hope of finding a better way of life abroad or in the major cities.  As people leave, essential services are reduced or closed, such as post offices, schools, Garda barracks and so on. Closures such as these, which remove essential services, have further destroyed areas.  Coming from a rural area, I am well aware of these problems, but I see a new resolve to fight the decline and people are determined to help themselves in their own communities, being aware of the enormous potential for development in their areas.</P>
    <P>Strong communities are vital for the future of our rural areas and this report contains a large amount of useful information for discussion on how rural Ireland can be helped develop.  I hope the work put into its preparation will not be wasted by its suggestions and conclusions not being acted upon by the Government and the agencies involved in forming a strategy which will create the necessary policies to ensure development of rural Ireland to its full potential.</P>
    <P>In my own counties of Monaghan and Cavan big efforts are being made by communities to enable people to help themselves, with community groups now operating in virtually every area, examining ways of identifying the potential of their areas and working for its development.  I urge the Government to ensure that the State agencies have the proper strategies to help this process, and not kill off development ideas, as many believe happened in the past, through red tape or whatever.</P>
    <P>County Monaghan and County Cavan have traditional local and small business developments, and the mushroom, poultry and furniture industries are <Col N="1314" /> examples of the work ethic in the region.  In addition, the region is to the forefront with plans and ideas. However, our closeness to the troubles in Northern Ireland has had a damaging effect on the development of the area and the Border has been a great barrier to progress.  Co-operation has not always been what it should with regard to helping neighbours to develop, but thankfully this has now improved and many excellent development ideas operate as cross-Border partnerships.</P>
    <P>As a Border region, we have seen the benefit from a number of funding agencies, for example, Leader, IFI and INTERREG.  These programmes, together with the NESC report, identify that very modest expenditure has had a great impact on the development of the region, and they must be continued and enhanced, as they are an effective way of helping rural development.  For example, they have helped the development of tourism projects such as small businesses and new alternative farm enterprise ideas.</P>
    <P>The report rightly states that agriculture is still the major industry in rural areas, despite the fact that there has been a huge decline in those employed in the sector over the past 20 years.  I therefore support most developments in this area as diversification of the rural economy requires new ideas and an imaginative approach from all involved. Farming is no longer a way of life, but a competitive business with many farmers now seeking work outside the farm to provide a good standard of living for their families.  The provision of a high quality advisory service to farmers is therefore essential and I urge the Government to ensure that Teagasc is properly funded to provide the services necessary to farmers in these challenging times.</P>
    <P>Farmers must have an open mind to change and develop new enterprises such as agri-tourism.  As the report points out, this is an area which has been neglected to a large extent.  It is a sector which has an enormous potential for development.  Forestry can also be <Col N="1315" /> enhanced and must be further developed as its future development is enormous.</P>
    <P>To maintain people in rural areas, the State must ensure that the essential services are located in these areas.  While many services have been removed on economic grounds, the social effect of this must be considerable.  The relevant bodies, be they An Post or the banks, must consider the effects which decisions to close services will have on an area and the quality of life therein. The Government must play a major role in ensuring that these services are maintained in local areas and I urge it to immediately commence a programme of decentralisation of its offices, and those of commercial State-sponsored bodies, to the regions, especially to my own areas, which have very few Government Departments.</P>
    <P>Infrastructure is vital to an area, but the roads situation is terrible.  As I highlighted during the Adjournment debate yesterday, the Government must immediately give extra allocations to Monaghan County Council, particularly for county roads, which serve nearly all rural areas in the county.  The council estimates that £5.8 million will be required to bring the surface of our roads to an acceptable standard.  It is very disappointing that the Government should cut Monaghan's allocation for county roads by £400,000 this year.  I hope this is not an indication of the Government's commitment to rural Ireland.  Infrastructure is vital to an area to encourage investment and development.</P>
    <P>I thank the Leader for the opportunity to discuss this very comprehensive NESC report.  I hope many of its recommendations are taken on board to help rural Ireland.  We must all think positively for the future.  We have a well educated workforce and can rely on determination and true community spirit from everyone.  On behalf of the Fianna Fáil Members I compliment the NESC on yet another excellent report.</P>
    <Col N="1316" />
    <Speaker pid="DonalCarey" hpid="Minister of State at the Department of the Taoiseach (Mr. Carey) Minister of State at the Department of the Taoiseach (Mr. Carey)">
      <NameTxt>Minister of State at the Department of the Taoiseach (Mr. Carey)</NameTxt>
      <P>I thank the 14 Senators who contributed to the debate on this very important report.  As each of the speakers said, this report is very extensive, wide ranging and challenging. It is not very readable and perhaps the authors might reconsider how they put these matters together. However, there are challenges in each section.</P>
      <P>Senators adverted to many of the problems which exist because of the lack of a rural development policy and to the prospects for rural renewal in the future.  Among the responsibilities given to me is to update policy on rural renewal.  I have chosen one area highlighted by the report, that is the provision of public services.  My Department has already set in train systems to evolve the pilot studies recommended by the report.  These one stop shops will be set up following conferences in four areas, which we hope to hold in the west and north-west.</P>
      <P>We have to recognise, as Senator O'Brien has said, that there has been a great upsurge in activity by local committees, who are very anxious about the renewal of their own areas.  Perhaps it was the insensitive closures of post offices and Garda stations and the horrific problems which arose and were well highlighted in the press which activated further interest in maintaining rural communities.  I am confident that the partnership which is required between the public and private sectors will be forthcoming in the west.</P>
      <P>I am optimistic that the task which has been given to me by the Government will be bear fruit in the 120 weeks or so until the next general election.  I am not overly ambitious.  The report is so wide ranging that one could not hope even to start on some of its basic recommendations.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>It is sad that in this country we are somewhat behind in rural development policy.  Senator Lee asked about Northern Ireland.  It has a rural development policy.  He spoke about Strabane, where there are instances of this policy being <Col N="1317" /> implemented.  We are not aware of this here.  For some reason there has not been proper co-ordination and I hope we will correct this gap in our information. In France and all over Europe rural renewal has been tackled.  The one stop shop policy has been attempted in other jurisdictions.</P>
    <P>I hope all the Senators who spoke, and other Members who want to avail of the opportunity, will go to one of the four conferences which will be held in the west to make contributions and to see how people might examine, in the context of rural renewal, how flexibility can be provided in the public and private sectors and how we can create the unity which is needed between rural and urban areas to advance an increasing population in rural areas.</P>
    <P>Various initiatives have been spoken about.  I wish to acknowledge that Mr. Jim Connolly, through Rural Resettlement Ireland, has started a resettlement policy of his own.  Local government reform has unfortunately not been tackled.  This is one of the blights which exist and it is a challenge for the Government to take major initiatives in this area.</P>
    <P>Senators spoke about many areas with which I do not have time to deal. I value the contributions made and my Department will examine each of them. I invite Senators to take an active role in trying to assist the State to halt the terrible blight of rural decline, which is continuing.  Population is being continually attracted to Dublin, which is seen as the only centre for existence.</P>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>When is it proposed to sit again?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MauriceManning" hpid="Mr. Manning Mr. Manning">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Manning</NameTxt>
      <P>At 11.30 a.m. next Wednesday.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Adjournment Matters - Rathkeale (County" RHead="Limerick) Travellers Training Centre">
    <Title>Adjournment Matters - Rathkeale (County Limerick) Travellers Training Centre.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="MaryKelly" hpid="Ms Kelly Ms Kelly">
      <NameTxt>Ms Kelly</NameTxt>
      <P>I thank the Minister of State, Deputy Currie, for coming to the <Col N="1318" /> House to listen to the request I am about to make.  Rathkeale is the second largest town in County Limerick, the largest being Newcastle West.  It is perhaps unique in that it has proportionately more travellers living there than any other town in Ireland.  Some 35 per cent of the voting population of Rathkeale is of traveller stock.  This poses enormous problems for the town.  Travellers in Rathkeale are a trading group.  They are extremely mobile and some of them are very wealthy.  They have purchased a large proportion of the town's property. In one street formerly comprising 24 county council houses, 20 are now owned by the travelling community. Because there are so many and because they are so strong in their traditions there is a great gap between them and the settled community.  Yet, considering the numbers of travellers, there is a great deal of harmony between them and the townspeople.  Nevertheless, a huge gap exists between the two communities.</P>
      <P>There are two senior training centres in County Limerick, one in Abbeyfeale and one in Newcastle West.  Comprising 12 to 13 places, both are smaller than normal centres.  The centre at Newcastle West is populated primarily by students from Rathkeale.  The number of travellers living in Newcastle West and attending the senior training centre there has been declining over the years as many travellers choose to take up the educational opportunities offered by the town's two post primary schools.  The need for the training centre in Newcastle West is, therefore, not as great now as it was when first established.  But the need in Rathkeale is great because there is a high population of young travellers there.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Education needs to be promoted among these young travellers because the vast bulk of them do not continue on their education beyond primary school.  There is a junior training centre with anything up to 16 pupils, predominantly girls.  After completing the junior training centre, some of them go on to Newcastle West, where there is a good <Col N="1319" /> record of placing them in employment in local factories.  But the number of those who go from the junior training centre in Rathkeale to the senior training centre in Newcastle West is quite small, and this take up is worrying.</P>
    <P>A senior training centre in Rathkeale could be used outside normal hours as a community base for older travellers among whom there is a high degree of illiteracy.  Literacy programmes are required, in addition to assisting women by providing a great knowledge of health care.  In calling for a senior training centre for Rathkeale I am not thinking strictly of a training centre as such, but a resource centre for the travelling population.  Such a centre would enable travellers to become more attuned to taking up employment within the town.</P>
    <P>Those who do not trade and are not as well off are largely dependent on social welfare, but a training centre would help to break the gap that exists between those who are trading and those on social welfare.  For the good of the travellers themselves, as well as the community, a senior training centre is urgently required in Rathkeale, County Limerick.</P>
    <Speaker pid="AustinCurrie" hpid="Minister of State at the Department of Education (Mr. Currie) Minister of State at the Department of Education (Mr. Currie)">
      <NameTxt>Minister of State at the Department of Education (Mr. Currie)</NameTxt>
      <P>I thank Senator Kelly for her description of the circumstances in Rathkeale, which I found interesting and valuable.  It will certainly add to my knowledge of the area.  Throughout the country as a whole travellers are a relatively small but significant minority group.  Their participation rates at all levels of the educational system are low for a democratic society.  Significant progress has been made with regard to the education of traveller children over the past 20 years or so.  The main aim for the children of the travelling community is the promotion of fully integrated participation at all levels of the educational system while retaining respect and value for their own distinctive culture.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Sizeable numbers of traveller children now attend pre-schools or primary <Col N="1320" /> schools.  Achieving this level of attendance has been greatly helped by the visiting teacher service.  The success of these teachers is reflected in improved school attendance in their particular areas.  It is also evident in the goodwill that they enjoy in the traveller community and among teachers of traveller children.  It is generally accepted that a very small number of travellers attend post primary schools.  Many travellers appear to be reluctant to transfer their children to any form of post primary education.  In this regard the Department of Education intends to appoint additional visiting teachers to encourage traveller children to continue in school at second level.  Some traveller children attend junior training centres, which were established with the aim of providing a form of second level education for travellers which would be sufficiently attractive and relevant to make them want to continue attending school between the ages of 12 and 15.</P>
    <P>The curriculum attempts to maintain a balance between academic and craftwork education, together with an emphasis on social and sporting activities. These centres continue to provide an essential service at second level. There is a junior training centre in Rathkeale.  The Department approved an allocation of 1,500 teaching hours in County Limerick Vocational Education Committee for the 1994-95 school year which enabled the vocational education committee to employ teachers for that centre.</P>
    <P>Second level education for travellers up to now has been largely the responsibility of the vocational sector.  County Limerick Vocational Education Committee has made a significant contribution towards developing an education cum training programme for the travelling community.  In addition to providing teachers for the junior school in Rathkeale, the committee is providing teachers for senior centres in Newcastle West and Abbeyfeale.  The Department has approved a total of 7,500 teaching hours for the 1994-95 school year to <Col N="1321" /> enable the committee to employ teachers for these two centres.</P>
    <P>The network of senior traveller training centres is jointly funded by FÁS and the vocational education committees. The existing centres cater for approximately 550 trainees.  The annual cost is in excess of £5 million, of which my Department's contribution is approximately £2.9 million.  The vocational education committees provide tuition for a 48 week programme and some overheads, with FÁS providing the training allowances for participants.  These centres offer integrated education, vocational training and work experience for travellers, mainly in the 16 to 25 year old age group.  In addition, they are centres where travellers can express and celebrate their rich culture.</P>
    <P>With regard to the establishment of a senior travellers' training centre in Rathkeale, the Department has not to date received an application from County Limerick Vocational Education Committee for such a centre.  However, it is understood that a formal application is being prepared and as soon as the application is received the matter will be given due consideration in consultation with FÁS, and the vocational education committee will be advised of the decision in due course.  I am quite sure that the comments made here today by the Senator will be of great use in enabling a decision to be made.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Adjournment Matters - Death" RHead="of a Person in London">
    <Title>Adjournment Matters - Death of a Person in London.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="FrankFahey" hpid="Mr. Fahey Mr. Fahey">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Fahey</NameTxt>
      <P>I thank the Minister for coming to the House to deal with this issue on the Adjournment.  It is an issue which has caused grave concern to the Walsh family in Galway.  They have been trying to get answers to questions for the last nine years.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Edward Walsh was murdered sometime in December 1985.  He was a native of Galway and since 1985 the family has been trying to get answers from the Home Office in London through the Department of Foreign Affairs. However, to date they have not <Col N="1322" /> received satisfactory answers to questions regarding the events surrounding the investigation into his death.  I will briefly outline some of the matters which concern the family.</P>
    <P>The body was retained for two months before being released by the London authorities.  A post mortem was carried out on the body of Edward Walsh on 8 February 1986.  However, the body which was returned to the Walsh family was collected from the coroner on the day before, 7 February, 1986.  The Westminster coroner refused to hold an inquest.  The doctor who signed the casualty notes in St. Charles' hospital now says that he never worked there.  The Westminster coroner said in 1987 that the doctor who certified Edward Walsh dead was Dr. Anthony Jones.  The Westminster coroner says in 1994 that he did not know and does not know who certified Edward Walsh dead.</P>
    <P>The family now believes that Edward Walsh did not die on the night he was attacked.  The family believes that Edward was alive for at least three days after he was attacked.  The family was never told this.  In fact, they were told that he died on the same date on which he was injured.  The family wrote to the Tánaiste and Minister for Foreign Affairs, Deputy Spring, on 22 November 1994 asking him to meet the family. Three months later they got a response saying that a meeting would not be productive.  The officials in the Department of Foreign Affairs have been most helpful in trying to assist the family in uncovering answers in this sad case.  However, a number of issues are still a puzzle to the family.  They are anxious that the Department of Foreign Affairs would put further pressure on the British Home Office to carry out a full public inquiry into the events surrounding the investigation into the death of Edward Walsh.</P>
    <P>The investigation began shortly after his death in London when he was stabbed in a Notting Hill flat.  Former neighbours of the truck driver were charged and acquitted.  The incident <Col N="1323" /> occurred five days before Christmas 1985 and Walsh had already informed his father that he was planning to return home on holiday.  The family has unearthed evidence which suggests that the doctor alleged to have signed a death certificate in St. Charles' hospital never worked there at any stage.  Cornelius Walsh, his father, and his brother Raymond have also extracted statements of a mysterious and contradictory nature which convince them that they have not been told the full truth about the death of Edward.</P>
    <P>The key to the confusion surrounds statements by John Nodes and Co. Ltd., funeral directors.  When Raymond Walsh went to London three days after the murder to collect his brother's body, which was then in the Westminster mortuary, he was first informed by Mr. Michael Nodes that his company had done no business on the night of Edward's death.</P>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I remind the Senator that he cannot name people in the House.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrankFahey" hpid="Mr. Fahey Mr. Fahey">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Fahey</NameTxt>
      <P>My apologies.  The matter was pursued and the Walsh family was told by the undertaker that his company had collected a body from St. Charles' hospital that night.  The family was told that it had been certified as BID &mdash; brought in dead &mdash; yet hospital records clearly reveal that the young man was not dead when he was brought to hospital.  Instead, after attempts were made to resuscitate him, he died at 2.35 a.m. according to the certificate. Although the medical certificates outlining the treatment in the fruitless attempt to save his life are on file, the doctor, whose signature is clearly legible, has claimed that he never worked at St. Charles' hospital.  In a letter written in October last year he admits that he did work at the nearby St. Mary's hospital, Page Street.  &ldquo;If he was only treated at St. Charles' hospital then I think it is very unlikely that I was involved&rdquo;, he writes.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="1324" /> Raymond Walsh &mdash; I regret having to mention family names &mdash; signed a document stating that he had identified the body of his brother in Westminster mortuary but the fact is that he never saw the body.  He claims that when he asked to take a proper look he was told by an attendant that he could not.  This was three days after his brother's death. Raymond returned home, while the body continued to be held by the Westminster coroner, as is normal in a murder case.  It was seven weeks before the body was returned for burial.  The family was told not to look inside the casket by the undertakers who brought it from London, so it was buried without being viewed by any of the Walsh family.</P>
    <P>Contradictory statements from the undertakers, the coroner's office and the police all convince the family that something went terribly wrong after Edward's death.  They suspect that his body may have been used for other purposes, that perhaps organs could have been removed without their permission and that the entire confusion is nothing more than a massive cover-up.  The coroner has written to the family informing them that the body was labelled as being that of Edward Walsh when it was collected by the undertaker.</P>
    <P>Hospital notes also reveal that he was identified by a police officer who found him wounded and dying in the street. On his person, according to the police, was an Underground rail pass with his photograph, a driving licence and a security card.  The undertakers claim that the coroner was mistaken and that one of his staff denied that he had told Raymond Walsh that the firm had taken two bodies from St. Charles' hospital on the night in question.  &ldquo;Only one was taken to Westminster mortuary&rdquo;, he says.  For his part, the coroner says that the delay in returning the body was due to the fact that two post mortems had to be carried out, one on behalf of the defence in a murder trial.</P>
    <P>Even here huge confusion arises.  The records show that one post mortem was held on 8 February 1986.  The body was <Col N="1325" /> supposed to have been that of Edward Walsh.  However, that officially had been returned to Ireland the day before. Some problems in the management of the mortuary in Westminster have come to light.  The family is also angry at the fact that the coroner notified the registrar of deaths that Edward Walsh was of no fixed abode while the police were fully aware of his permanent address.</P>
    <P>It has cost the family a great deal of money trying to find answers to their questions.  They are concerned at this stage that the body that was returned from England is not that of Edward.  I ask the Minister that, nine years later, the Department of Foreign Affairs should insist on a proper public inquiry being held in London into the events surrounding the death of Edward Walsh.  His mother has died since then and his father is an old man who has had a great deal of trauma in trying to find answers to those questions.  The family is determined not to let this issue die without getting adequate answers.  I appeal to the Minister of State to have the matter investigated and to request the Tánaiste, as a matter of courtesy, to meet this family, acknowledge their plight and make a commitment to have a full inquiry carried out.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JoanBurtonLAB" hpid="Minister of State at the Department of Foreign Affairs (Ms Burton) Minister of State at the Department of Foreign Affairs (Ms Burton)">
      <NameTxt>Minister of State at the Department of Foreign Affairs (Ms Burton)</NameTxt>
      <P>I have great sympathy for the Walsh family. Their grief has been complicated and prolonged by the initial delay in having the remains of their son and brother returned to them and by the difficulties and delays they have encountered in trying to clarify some of the circumstances of his tragic death and its aftermath. It is a situation which cannot but arouse all of our sympathy.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The Department of Foreign Affairs and the Irish Embassy in London assisted the family in its efforts to secure the release of the remains by the coroner with the minimum of delay, but the coroner had to respect the legal right of the person accused of Edward Walsh's murder to carry out a second autopsy, and that was the main cause of the <Col N="1326" /> seven week delay which occurred. While fully understanding the distress this caused to the family, the Department had no reason to think that there was anything improper about the way the post mortem examination was carried out.</P>
    <P>Since 1989, as requested by the family, the Department and the Embassy have supplemented the efforts of their solicitors to elucidate details of what happened.  The points at issue are, essentially, matters of law for clarification by solicitors and, if necessary, by the courts in Britain.</P>
    <P>At a recent meeting the family told officials of the Department of Foreign Affairs that many of their concerns are still not resolved.  Among those, as the Senator mentioned, are the date when the injuries occurred; the date of the second autopsy; who carried it out and whether organs were removed; where the remains were kept in the hospital and whether there was proper supervision; the situation with regard to an inquest and, most distressful of all, the possibility that the body which was buried may not be that of Edward Walsh.</P>
    <P>I understand their frustration that, after over nine years, there are still unanswered questions.  It is well to bear in mind, however, that the Home Office in 1986 gave the family a full explanation of the delay in releasing the body and that the coroner's office, the police, the doctors, the hospital staff and the pathologists have rejected the serious allegations of impropriety which have been made against them.</P>
    <P>At the request of the family, the Embassy in London wrote to the Home Office last November outlining the family's outstanding questions and asking that they be investigated.  Contact with the Home Office is being maintained. The Embassy wrote on 6 February to the solicitors now dealing with the case and offered to assist and co-operate with them.</P>
    <P>It would not be appropriate at this stage for the Tánaiste and Minister for Foreign Affairs to seek a public inquiry <Col N="1327" /> into this case.  He would need to have much more information and advice about the legal position on each of the issues outstanding before he could decide whether that was a reasonable or appropriate option in British law and practice.</P>
    <P>It is, in the first instance, for the family's solicitors to advise them on the options open to them.  I understand that a request for a judicial review of the coroner's actions was made in 1993 and rejected by a British court.  If a convincing legal case for a formal inquiry of another kind is made, it may be possible for us to support it.</P>
    <P>The family has been assured that we will continue to supplement the efforts of their solicitors.  For the Senator's information, I offered to meet with the Walsh family recently on behalf of the Tánaiste.  That offer was not taken up, as I think the Senator is aware, but it still remains open.  Everybody sympathises very deeply with the family.  The staff in the Department of Foreign Affairs have made every effort over the nine year period to meet with the family's wishes.  This family has endured a horrific situation over a very long period. I assure the Senator that the Department of Foreign Affairs will continue to supplement the efforts of the family and to give them whatever assistance we can in what is a very difficult case.</P>
    <Speaker pid="FrankFahey" hpid="Mr. Fahey Mr. Fahey">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Fahey</NameTxt>
      <P>I appreciate the Minister of State's answer but the fact remains <Col N="1328" /> that although the coroner's office, police and doctors have rejected any allegations of impropriety, no investigation was carried out.  The Minister of State said in her reply that &ldquo;if a convincing legal case for a formal inquiry... is made it may be possible for us to support it&rdquo;.  Surely, the case which I have just outlined on behalf of the family is sufficient for a formal inquiry.  The fact that the Irish Embassy wrote to the Home Office last November, which is five months ago, and has still not received a reply means that this case is not being treated with the proper urgency and respect.  I ask the Minister of State to ask that a &ldquo;formal inquiry of another kind&rdquo;, as she described it, be made immediately.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoanBurtonLAB" hpid="Ms Burton Ms Burton">
      <NameTxt>Ms Burton</NameTxt>
      <P>We are dealing with another judicial system, the British judicial system, and whatever happens has to take place within the context of that system.  We are, obviously, acting on the advice and understanding of the Irish Embassy in London in relation to the British judicial system.  As I said, if there is further evidence which would open the way to a further inquiry, we would be happy to see that happening. As I pointed out, when a request for a judicial review was made by the family in 1993 it was turned down by the British courts.</P>
      <P>The Seanad adjourned at 4.30 p.m. until 11.30 a.m. on Wednesday, 29 March 1995.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
</Debate>