<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE Debate SYSTEM "../Debate.dtd"[]>
<Debate DocTitle="Seanad Debate" Day="Wed" Date="13" Month="Nov" Year="1985" Vol="109" No="12" DateIrish="Dé Céadaoin, 13 Samhain 1985" DateEnglish="Wednesday, 13 November 1985" House="S" CommitteeEng="" CommitteeIr="" SubNameEng="" cnum="1169">
  <MainHeading Type="Prelude" LHead="" RHead="">
    <Title>
    </Title>
    <P>
      <Col N="1169" /> Chuaigh an Cathaoirleach i gceannas ar 2.30 p.m.</P>
    <P Just="Center">
      <i>Paidir.</i>
    </P>
    <P Just="Center">
      <i>Prayer.</i>
    </P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Message" RHead="from Dáil">
    <Title>Message from Dáil.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickJReynolds" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Dáil Éireann has agreed to the amendments made by Seanad Éireann to the Nurses Bill, 1984.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Business" RHead="of Seanad">
    <Title>Business of Seanad.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickJReynolds" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I have notice from Senator Jim Higgins that, on the motion for the Adjournment of the House today, he proposes to raise the following matter:</P>
      <P>The administration of the Prescribed Relatives Allowance Scheme with particular reference to the failure to make payment to applicants whose prescribed relatives are living with them on small farms.</P>
      <P>I regard the matter as suitable for discussion on the Adjournment and it will be taken from 8 p.m. to 8.30 p.m. or earlier if the business ordered is concluded . .</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Order of" RHead="Business">
    <Title>Order of Business.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelFerris" hpid="Mr. Ferris Mr. Ferris">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Ferris</NameTxt>
      <P>It is proposed to take Nos. 1, 2, 3, 4 and 5 in that order.  It is proposed to adjourn for tea from 5.30 p.m. to 6.30 <Col N="1170" /> p.m. No. 5 will be taken at 6.30 p.m. to 8 p.m.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHoward" hpid="Mr. Howard Mr. Howard">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Howard</NameTxt>
      <P>I would like to refer to what I raised on the Order of Business last week and to inquire from the Leader of the House if there is a report on progress or the lack of progress upstairs.  I noticed that the same dust that was there last week is still on the stairs; the same footprint is on the stairs that was there last week, which leads me to believe that nothing happened, and that nobody was upstairs.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickJReynolds" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>The Board of Works assure us that they are going ahead as quickly as possible.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHoward" hpid="Mr. Howard Mr. Howard">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Howard</NameTxt>
      <P>I suggested to you the last day that a committee of the House should be appointed to examine progress and report on it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickJReynolds" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>The Committee on procedure and Privileges deal with it and you can rest assured that they will be taking up the matter with the Board of Works.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHoward" hpid="Mr. Howard Mr. Howard">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Howard</NameTxt>
      <P>Could you assure me that we will have a report from the Committee on Procedure and Privileges next week on the matter?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickJReynolds" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I cannot, but possibly before we adjourn for the Christmas.  I cannot give any guarantee when the work will be completed.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnBrowne1" hpid="Mr. Browne Mr. Browne">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Browne</NameTxt>
      <P>Would you think it would be appropriate for us here today to congratulate John Hume on the wonderful, statesmanlike performance he gave last night?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickJReynolds" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>No, it is not.  It is not appropriate on the Order of Business</P>
      <P>Order of Business agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Joint Committee on Commercial" RHead="State-Sponsored Bodies: Motion (Resumed)">
    <Title>Joint Committee on Commercial State-Sponsored Bodies: Motion (Resumed).</Title>
    <P>
      <Col N="1171" /> Debate resumed on the following motion:</P>
    <P>That paragraph 1 of the Orders of Reference of the Joint Committee on Commercial State-Sponsored Bodies, constituted pursuant to the Order of Dáil Éireann of 21st June, 1983, and the Order of Seanad Éireann of the 29th June, 1983, be amended by the deletion of all words after &ldquo;Bodies)&rdquo; where it first occurs and the substitution therefor of the following:&mdash;</P>
    <P>&ldquo;to examine&mdash;</P>
    <P>(a)  the Reports and Accounts and overall operational results, and</P>
    <P>(b)  in the light of the reports published pursuant to sub-paragraph (a), the common issues relating to Board responsibility, structure and organisation, accountability and financing, together with the relationship with central Government and the Houses of the Oireachtas</P>
    <P>of State-Sponsored Bodies engaged in trading or commercial activities referred to in the Schedule hereto and to report thereon to both Houses of the Oireachtas and to make recommendations where appropriate.&rdquo;</P>
    <P Just="Right">&mdash;(Senator Dooge.)</P>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHoward" hpid="Mr. Howard Mr. Howard">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Howard</NameTxt>
      <P>I welcome the opportunity to resume the debate on this motion which we last discussed here early in May.  I welcome the motion itself.  The purpose of the motion, as I understand it, is to extend the power and the mandate of the Joint Committee on Commercial State-Sponsored Bodies in relation to their examination of the performance of the commercial State-sponsored bodies concerned.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I would like very much to compliment the joint committee on their work to date and indeed on the many reports that they <Col N="1172" /> have issued.  Their work and the reports proved beyond any question the need to examine and report on the performance of commercial State-sponsored bodies. Furthermore, the work of the joint committee has heightened public awareness and interest in this matter.  I regret to say that, coupled with some unhappy results from some of the bodies in question, public interest in this area is at a level which had not been reached previously.</P>
    <P>I also welcome the motion as it is an indication of the commitment of the Minister and the Government to respond to the request from the Joint Committee on Commercial State-Sponsored Bodies to extend their powers of examination.  It is also evidence of the Minister's commitment to ensure that there is more control and accountability on the part of these bodies.</P>
    <P>The Minister indicated that the Government in their White Paper on Industrial Policy had decided to ensure that there would be better control and that overall examination would be exercised by them of the operation of these bodies.  The White Paper on Industrial Policy indicated a number of steps being taken by the Government to ensure that there would be more effective control in this area.</P>
    <P>Briefly, I refer to a number of points which emerge from the White Paper. First, the decision of the Government in relation to corporate planning by commercial State-sponsored bodies includes the five year rolling corporate plan in respect of the activities, the achievements and the work of these bodies.</P>
    <P>Secondly, it includes the commitment to improve monitoring of State boards by the Government.  Enshrined in the second commitment is the decision that the performance of each particular body will be subject to regular review by the Minister concerned.</P>
    <P>There is another welcome improvement contained in the White Paper which refers to the improved procedure for the appointment of people to State boards. There is a very clear indication there of the Government's commitment to obtain among the appointees to these bodies <Col N="1173" /> people possessing the proper skills and expertise for the job required of them.  I welcome this.  This is the measure that should have always been applied to appointments to State boards and bodies, particularly in the commercial field.  Too often in the past we have had the unfortunate experience where some of the appointees were selected as a reward for their efforts in other fields far removed from the duties they were expected to fulfil in their new role.  Therefore, I compliment the Minister on taking that decision because in the future it will be people with the proper skills, experience and expertise in related fields who will be selected and nominated for appointment to State boards.</P>
    <P>There is another point in the White Paper which I also welcome.  That is the creation of machinery for better monitoring and control of investments by State boards.  All these represent determination on the part of the Minister to ensure that we get better performance and better results.  Commercial State-sponsored bodies are owned by the State and they are responsible to the taxpayers. Their contribution, if they are successful in achieving their appointed objectives, can indeed be enormous.  Their need to be successful is crucial, particularly for the economic wellbeing of the country and for the benefit of so many people who are dependent on, or are involved in, or have a certain interest at stake in the fields in which these bodies operate.</P>
    <P>Equally, the risk of failure can be devastating. I regret that we have had some unhappy examples in this area in the past. I will refer to one or two of these events, but first of all I feel that I should recognise and acknowledge the success and excellent performances of some commercial State bodies.  I had the experience a number of years ago of being on the board of an Bord Bainne representing milk suppliers in its early days.  There can be no doubt that that organisation inherited a very difficult situation and within a relatively short period succeeded magnificently in bringing about progress and success in that field.</P>
    <P>It would be right to acknowledge also <Col N="1174" /> that, as a board member, I could easily see that the success Bord Bainne achieved then was largely related to the calibre of the people they had at management level there.  When we look at State boards, that is one of the factors which make for success or failure&mdash;the capacity and the ability of the boards in question to attract to top management people with the capacity and the enterprise to achieve the results that are necessary.  I had firsthand knowledge of success in that board. There are others who have done a magnificent job for this country, a magnificent job for many people who depend on the success of these boards.  Many of them filled a void that would not otherwise have been filled but for their creation and successful operation.  Unfortunately, some have been less than successful and it is these less than successful ones which often attract most attention&mdash;and I suppose rightly so.</P>
    <P>In relation to some of these bodies there appeared to be a certain reluctance to co-operate fully with the joint committee in its examination.  That, of course, is a cause of major concern.  It is recognised here and it is recognised by the Minister that so long as commercial State-sponsored bodies are in the ownership of the State and are responsible to the taxpayers there can be no question about their obligation and their duty to co-operate fully and in every way with a joint committee appointed by the Oireachtas to oversee and examine their operations.  Where commercial State-sponsored bodies have been in difficulty it has, as far as can be established, almost always been as a result of a bad decision at board level or at management level.  I want to emphasise that where that is the case responsibility must clearly rest where it belongs and the standards of the commercial world must apply within the commercial activities of State-sponsored bodies.  We cannot under any circumstances tolerate the avoidance of responsibility by those who are responsible for bad decision making, which in some cases has resulted in the imposition of substantial financial burdens on the State and, through the State, on the taxpayer.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="1175" /> Many of these bad commercial decisions taken by these bodies have been inspired by a desire to engage in empire building.  That is apparently done in the knowledge and the belief that if things go wrong the taxpayer is always there as a fallback, and the Government are always there and available to bail them out in these situations.  We must have reached the end of the day as far as that attitude and that mentality is concerned. Responsibility for bad decision making must in future rest where it belongs, particularly if such decisions, as would appear to have been the case in the past, have been taken without full consultation with either the Department, the Minister or the Government.</P>
    <P>I want to emphasise precisely what I mean.  Where bad decision making has resulted in substantial losses being incurred by the board in question and where the State and the taxpayer have been called upon to bail out that particular organisation, then the board of that company should be fired and, if necessary, top management with it.  It is only when we indicate that we are prepared to take that kind of attitude that we can insist and ensure that the standards of the commercial world will prevail within the realm of commercial State-sponsored activities.</P>
    <P>I know it is easy to be misunderstood on this point and it is easy to go overboard on it also.  Therefore, I want to say that I am not advocating day-to-day interference by any Minister of any Department in the activities of these boards.  If you start out on the basis, where these bodies are concerned, that their objectives and their obligations are clearly defined and that the frontiers of their decision-making are equally clearly defined, then if the bodies live within these objectives interference should and can be held to a minimum.  I draw the line in relation to substantial policy changes being made by boards within the semi-State field and substantial investment decisions being made without consultation, without reference or advice from <Col N="1176" /> the Minister responsible or the Government.</P>
    <P>I hope we have reached the stage where we can look forward with confidence to a situation within the State commercial field or the semi-State commercial field where we will not have to contend with any further disastrous investment decisions.</P>
    <P>I conclude by saying that I welcome the motion.  I welcome the attitude and the response of the Minister and the Government to the request of the Joint Committee on Commercial State-Sponsored bodies and I commend that committee for the excellent work they have done to date.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelSmith" hpid="Mr. Smith Mr. Smith">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Smith</NameTxt>
      <P>I believe that the Minister has the unanimous support of this House in making any changes that will help towards better answerability, better accounting and better commercial approaches being operated by all the State commercial companies.  In the past few years the Government have spent as much as $10 million on the planning, design and quantity surveying of projects which never went ahead.  I am not going to enter into the question of whether certain projects should or should not have gone ahead but I merely want to make the point that in the planning of Government activities there has to be something fundamentally wrong when that kind of figure can be spent on planning and designs where the projects are subsequently abandoned.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnBruton" hpid="Minister for Industry, Trade, Commerce and Tourism (Mr. J. Bruton) John Bruton">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Industry, Trade, Commerce and Tourism (Mr. J. Bruton)</NameTxt>
      <P>What is the project?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelSmith" hpid="Mr. Smith Mr. Smith">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Smith</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not want to enter into a question and answer session but it is clear that the Minister will know very well that I am talking about a number of projects involving some decentralisation and the building of Government offices in regions&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnBruton" hpid="Mr. J. Bruton Mr. J. Bruton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J. Bruton</NameTxt>
      <P>They are not semi-State bodies.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1177" />
    <Speaker pid="MichaelSmith" hpid="Mr. Smith Mr. Smith">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Smith</NameTxt>
      <P>I am developing the point, if I may &mdash; in regions throughout the country where this would have benefitted the economy of these regions.  When that happens as far as Governmental control itself is concerned, I am not so sure that it augurs well for the future.  Senator Howard referred to the composition of the boards and the fact that some State organisations have made&mdash;and we all agree &mdash; fairly serious mistakes in terms of investment; but I think it has to be spelt out that there is a social factor in a number of the activities being engaged in by State organisations.  I mention Córas Iompair Éireann as one; one could mention others.  I think we have clearly to define what is the social factor and what help the Government give towards these facilities.</P>
      <P>For instance, here in Dublin city the latest loss figure I have is something like £20 million in respect of the provision of the bus services in the most densely populated part of the country.  That is subsidised by the community as a whole, and obviously these services cannot be provided all around the country, but at the same time people who do not have any access to these services would like to know to what extent the State is prepared to support commercial State enterprises which have a social content and which need to be maintained because private enterprise would not become involved.  It is necessary that that would be quantified.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The second issue is that there has been down through the years a certain amount of political interference in the management and the running of these companies. Some of the interference has been very necessary but obviously at times it has not been too healthy.  I would like to compliment the chairman and the members of Bord na Móna on their recent intervention which enabled the board to continue without the lob losses which were about to become a reality in parts of the midlands and other regions in the country.  Bord na Móna have been an excellent example of how the State can become involved in this area.  They provide employment where there is little prospect of alternative employment.  In <Col N="1178" /> this context I would like to ask the Minister if there are any plans for diversification or involvement of Bord na Móna in the waste bogs that are now available and which would enable the board to maintain employment particularly in the regions that I have already referred to.</P>
    <P>With these few comments I would like broadly to welcome this report.  It is important that we have an opportunity here from time to time to monitor the development of State or semi-State commercial enterprises.  They have over the years provided excellent services and very useful employment.  At the same time, when there are tight Exchequer constraints it is very necessary that the taxpayer is assured that the maximum benefit is gained from the finance which is being provided by the Government for this purpose.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JohnBruton" hpid="Minister for Industry, Trade, Commerce and Tourism (Mr. J. Bruton) John Bruton">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Industry, Trade, Commerce and Tourism (Mr. J. Bruton)</NameTxt>
      <P>I would like to thank the Senators for the debate on this motion which is a relatively simple one.  It is concerned with amplifying the powers and responsibilities of the Committee on semi-State bodies.  At the moment that committee has a listed number of bodies to investigate individually. My proposal before both Houses of the Oireachtas at the moment is that in addition to investigating individual bodies they should in the light of their experience with such bodies, which is now quite considerable, be empowered to make general recommendations about State bodies in general &mdash; not in addition to the specific ones about specific bodies &mdash;as to their board structure, the organisation and accountability of the bodies, their relationship with central Government and the Houses of the Oireachtas.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I would like to acknowledge a number of points that have been made in this debate.  First, it is common cause that people selected for board membership should be of the highest quality.  Senator Howard made a valid point that if these people make serious mistakes they should be fired just as is done in the private sector when the same thing happens. But there is a problem with this. <Col N="1179" /> When many of these boards were founded the scale of fees was on a par with those set for people accepting similar responsibilities in the private sector. While the fees in the private sector have increased in line with inflation and incomes generally, the fee maxima set in respect of the State boards have been kept virtually at the same cash level as they were set at 20 or more years ago when many of these boards were established. That means that in real terms over the last 20 years we have quite dramatically cut the level of financial recognition given to people who take on the responsibility of being part time directors of State companies and many of them have heavy responsibilities elsewhere in their own business or other careers.</P>
    <P>I know that it will be argued that many people will take on such responsibilities in a spirit of public service in much the same way as people sit on a voluntary basis, say, on committees of inquiry.  On the other hand, that is not the basis on which people accept board responsibility in the private sector.  They do not accept it out of a spirit of public service or because of the good lunch they get every first Monday of every month.  They accept it partly for the financial benefits that accrue to them from being members of boards.  If we want to treat State boards and State directors on an equivalent basis with those in the private sector obviously the present scale of fees has got to be examined.  However, it is a moot point. Some will say that intrinsically public sector companies are different from private sector companies and that people are prepared to work for the public weal on a different financial basis than they would be prepared to work as directors for a private company for the private profit of the shareholders.</P>
    <P>There are two views about it.  One view is that we should update the fees in line with others in the private sector; and the other is that if people were to seek positions on State boards for the financial rewards we might not necessarily get the best people on State boards.  On the other <Col N="1180" /> hand, if one is to take the view that if you go on a State board and by so doing you are taking the risk of being fired, and if you are in business and you are a director who is fired, that does affect adversely the willingness of other companies to seek your services as a director in other private companies.  Likewise, if you are a director of a public sector company and are, as Senator Howard suggests, fired, that is a financial loss.  At least, that risk is a risk of a potential financial loss for which you should be remunerated while you serve, as a form of reinsurance against the opprobrium that may be applied if perchance one made the wrong decision.</P>
    <P>There are a number issues to be considered here.  In responding to Senator Howard, I do not think it is simply enough to look one side of the question without analysing both the reward of the remuneration of directors and the amount of time they are able to devote to voluntary work.  People have got only so much time for voluntary work in the course of their business lives, if serving on a State board is to be considered volunatry work.  If you are going to adopt the more muscular approach to State companies and their directors, as Senator Howard advocates, you have got to look at the other side as well, I am glad to be able to tell the Seanad that that is being done.  As a result of the initiative announced in the White Paper on Industry Policy, a review has been undertaken of the remuneration of part time directors of State companies.  I have not seen the results of this review yet.  It has been undertaken on an expert basis in the Department of the Public Service.  It will be coming before the Government in the relatively near future.  I cannot foresee what the decision will be, but I am sure the review will take account of all the factors I have mentioned and also the factors mentioned by the Senators in this debate.</P>
    <P>Senator Conway suggested that State body accounts instead of being handled by private auditors should be dealt with by the Comptroller and Auditor General in the same way as the accounts of <Col N="1181" /> Government Departments.  My advice is that this would impose an impossible wor-load on the Auditor General's office. While this is something that could be argued about, at least there is something to be said, if these are commercial concerns, for having their accounts audited in the same way as other commercial concerns have their accounts audited rather than having a separate body with a more public service ethos than a commercial ethos doing the job.  My tendency would be to disagree with what Senator Conway had suggested.  Nonetheless, he has a point.  Having one auditor audit all the bodies would ensure a greater degree of uniformity of treatment then having each of them with their own separate private auditor who may have some differences between the approach adopted.</P>
    <P>Senator Conway also suggested that the chairman of the joint committee should be given the status of a junior Minister.  I presume that means all the other accoutrements that go with that position.  I am sorry to be disagreeing with Senator Conway in his absence.  His contribution was a very thoughtful one that warrants a response.  The difficulty in that is that to single out one member of the committee, namely, the chairman, for very special status with a large salary, while all the other members were virtual amateurs who had to spend all their time in their constituencies with no similar aid, would be to personalise the work of committees in one person whereas committees operate on a collegiate basis.  I do not think that suggestion would be a good one either.</P>
    <P>The Senator also argued that the committee should have the power to subpoena people to come before them to give evidence.  That comment was also reflected in Senator Howard's remarks. The position is that some committees have been given the power in their terms of reference to send for persons, papers and records.  The sad fact is that, as of now, that power is legally unenforceable. There is no bailiff available to this House to go out and drag people screaming before committees.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="1182" /> There is an argument in certain circumstances for giving the committee power, not just in name but in practice, to get people before it.  As of now there is doubt as to what privilege in terms of immunity from action for defamation or slander would be available to witnesses appearing before committees if they did come on foot of such a binding summons.  Until we sort out the immunities of witnesses before committees it is not going to be possible to deal with the enforcement of orders to appear.  Both matters are being dealt with, therefore, in single piece of legislation on which discussion is currently taking place with the parliamentary draftsman, the heads of the Bill having been approved by the Cabinet.  I hope that it will be possible to introduce this legislation either before Christmas or shortly afterwards in order to settle the powers of the committees more definitively.</P>
    <P>I agree with Senator Smith on the need to define the social factors in State bodies, It has to be spelled out that there is a social factor in the activities of any State companies.  I emphasise the words &ldquo;spelled out&rdquo;.  There is no point in saying they have a social responsibility unless that responsibility is clearly financially differentiated from their commercial responsibilities. In the case to which the Senator referred, namely, CIE, my understanding is that the Minister for Communications, who happens to be in the precincts of the House at the moment, has done just that.  That is a major step forward in what is the biggest and most important of all State bodies in terms of its ramifications.  The advice Senator Smith was giving has, perhaps it is fair to say, been taken before he gave it.  That does not invalidate the advice in any way. May I thank the Seanad for its customary courteous reception for this motion, and also you, Sir.</P>
    <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Mergers, Take-overs and Monopolies" RHead="(Control) Act, Order, 1985: Motion">
    <Title>Mergers, Take-overs and Monopolies (Control) Act, Order, 1985: Motion.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHoward" hpid="Mr. Howard Mr. Howard">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Howard</NameTxt>
      <P>I move:</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>That Seanad Éireann, pursuant to <Col N="1183" /> the provisions of section 2 (6) of the Mergers, Take-overs and Monopolies (Control) Act, 1978 (No. 17 of 1978), hereby confirms the Mergers, Take-overs and Monopolies (Control) Act, 1978 (Section 2) Order, 1985 (S. I. No. 230 of 1985), made under section 2 (4) of that Act.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JohnBruton" hpid="Minister for Industry, Trade, Commerce and Tourism (Mr. J. Bruton) John Bruton">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Industry, Trade, Commerce and Tourism (Mr. J. Bruton)</NameTxt>
      <P>The purpose of the resolution is to confirm an order which I have made under the Mergers, Take-overs and Monopolies (Control) Act, 1978 relating to the financial criteria which apply to mergers, take-overs and monopolies for the purposes of that Act.</P>
      <P>Under the 1978 Act, any proposed merger or take-over which meets certain financial criteria must be notified to me. These criteria, which are specified in section 2 (1) (a) of the Act, are, where the value of the gross assets of each of the two or more enterprises to be involved in the proposal is not less than £1,250,000, or where the turnover of each of those two or more enterprises is not less than £2,500,000.  In addition to requiring notification, a proposed merger or take-over must be the subject of a reference to the Examiner of Restrictive Practices and, ultimately, may become subject to an order prohibiting it absolutely or conditionally. Different provisions apply to monopolies under the Act.  These do not require notification but may be the subject of an inquiry by the Restrictive Practices Commission and, subsequently, may be prohibited or broken up by order. The provisions of the Act relating to monopolies apply where a single criterion is met, that is, where the annual sales or purchases of the monopoly of the goods or services concerned exceed £1,500,000.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The 1978 Act made special provision, in section 2 (4) for increasing, by order, the amounts specified in the financial criteria relating to mergers, take-overs and monopolies.  Any such orders also require confirmation by both Houses within 21 <Col N="1184" /> sitting days after presentation.  The present order, which is the first order providing for any increase in these amounts, was made by me on 8 July 1985 and was laid before each House on 11 July 1985.</P>
    <P>When the limits were fixed by statute in 1978, the intention was to exclude from the scope of mergers and monopolies control small to medium sized enterprises. These limits reflected that approach.  With the passage of time, however, those limits were affecting a considerable number of enterprises in the small to medium sized sector by virtue of inflation.  One indication of the position may be obtained from the number of firms to which, by virtue of the limits, the provisions of the Mergers Act applied. At the time of enactment, in 1978, it was estimated that the Act would have applied to about 200 firms.  At present, it is certain that at least the 500 top firms in the country&mdash;and probably more&mdash; would, by virtue of these limits, be subject to the Act.  Another effect of the lower limits was to cause an increase in the volume of administrative work involved in dealing with merger/take-over notifications.  The number of formal proposals notified under the Act each year increased from 45 in 1978-79 to almost 80 in 1984.</P>
    <P>In these circumstance,s it was, in my view, necessary and desirable that the limits fixed in the 1978 Act should be increased and I made the order accordingly. The new limits, as set out in the order, are £5 million and £10 million for gross assets and turnover, respectively in merger/take-over cases and £6 million in the case of the sales or purchases of a monopoly.  It is estimated that the new merger/take-over limits would apply to about 300 enterprises at present.  The figure of £6 million in relation to monopolies is also a reasonable one.  In fact, no inquiry or order relating to any monopoly has taken place under the Act since it was enacted.  The new limits proposed in the order generally should ensure that the provisions of the 1978 Act apply only to the types of enterprises for which it was intended and therefore I commend the motion to the House accordingly.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="1185" /> Really, what this is all about is taking account of inflation.  Many companies that were not intended to be subject to the administrative costs of having to submit an application to me to merge with another enterprise are, as a result of inflation that occurred in the late seventies and in the early part of this decade, now in the net.  Mercifully, inflation has come down to a very low level.  It is unlikely that we will have to raise these limits again for quite some time.</P>
    <P>We now have a situation where one of the big demands is for lifting the burdens imposed on business by administrative requirements of all kinds.  Obviously, where two companies want to merge there is no real threat by their merger to competition, because once we are in the EC if any company is getting too dominant a position, a foreign company from another part of the EC can move into the market anyway and ensure that it does not overcharge except in certain services where the structure of the market is one that imposes a protection of its own.  In such circumstances it is rather a waste of resources in the firms themselves and in my Department to have to go through the rigmarole of applying for approval. For me in 90 per cent of the cases, it would be granted without any great qualms at all.  Nonetheless, to comply with the Act, a lot of paper work has to be gone through to reach a decision.  The final analysis would probably to taken in about 60 seconds flat.  That is not the best use of anyone's time.  By raising these limits we are really lifting the burden not just off business but also off the people sitting behind me here, which is no bad thing either.  I hope that it will command the support of the House.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelLynch" hpid="Mr. Lynch Mr. Lynch">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lynch</NameTxt>
      <P>I thank the Minister for his explanatory speech on this matter because I was not quite sure of what it was all about.  It is a non-contentious issue and it deserves the support of the House.  Anything any Minister can do to remove the red tape which, as all of us who are in public life knows, is tying the hands of the administrative process, would certainly be welcome.  There is one <Col N="1186" /> question on which the Minister might comment before the motion is approved. No inquiry or order relating to any monopoly has taken place under the Act since it was enacted.  Does that surprise the Minister, or was that just to be expected?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHoward" hpid="Mr. Howard Mr. Howard">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Howard</NameTxt>
      <P>Very briefly, I welcome the motion and, indeed, support it.  As Senator Lynch has said, it is a non-contentious issue.  I welcome the decision of the Minister to take this very necessary and desirable step.  He has, indeed, very clearly pointed out to us that inflation over the years took very many small companies into the net, which it was never intended, I would imagine, to include when this order came in 1978.  The raising of the new limits to the figures that have been outlined by the Minister are, indeed, substantial enough and high enough to take it into some period that we cannot as yet identify in the future when a repeat of this exercise would be necessary.  Indeed, I concur with what the Minister and Senator Lynch have said in welcoming anything that relieves the burden, whether it is an administrative burden within the Department, or the burden imposed by this order on small companies who found themselves in this situation.  Much time and resources were involved in meeting the obligations that the original order had imposed on them. I welcome the motion and support it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelSmith" hpid="Mr. Smith Mr. Smith">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Smith</NameTxt>
      <P>With the growth of mergers and the fact that so many commercial enterprises are dominated by major companies, and sometimes international companies, it is very important that the widest possible scope is given as quickly as possible to companies who want to merge for the purposes of being able to compete and stay in business.  Obviously, it is possible to give, in a merger, the power and scope to small companies which they would not have in operation on their own.  I agree with my colleagues and I welcome this measure.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I would like to ask the Minister, in relation to the statistics we have on mergers that have taken place up to now and the likely trend of events in the future, <Col N="1187" /> what percentage of those would be wholly Irish-owned?</P>
    <Speaker pid="JohnBruton" hpid="Minister for Industry, Trade, Commerce and Tourism (Mr. J. Bruton) John Bruton">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Industry, Trade, Commerce and Tourism (Mr. J. Bruton)</NameTxt>
      <P>We do not have the information which the Senator is looking for.  I will send the Senator a note on that point.  This legislation is about lifting the burden of administrative responsibility from business. A large part of the inspiration for mergers' control is to prevent the development of monopolies.  Membership of the EC is the biggest single guarantee we have against monopolies. Monopolies only exist when firms are in a position, by virtue of dominance, to charge prices that otherwise the market would not bare.  The EC gives freedom of establishment to business from outside Ireland from any one of the 11 member states.  That, in itself, is the best guarantee of all that companies will not be in a position to take unfair advantage of the consumer.</P>
      <P>Senator Smith made the interesting point that we should, in fact, be promoting mergers in Irish industry.  It is a point I strongly agree with, and one that was made very forcibly in the Telesis report and subsequently endorsed by the National Economic and Social Council and in the White Paper on Industrial Policy.  We need to build up strong Irish firms.  One way of doing that is by mergers between existing firms.  Rather than placing obstacles in the way of such firms, we should be encouraging restructuring of industry.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Provision already exists in section 2 of the Industrial Development Act, 1977, and in section 6 of the Industrial Development Act, 1981, for the IDA to guarantee loans and interest subsidy for the restructuring of industry.  It is a power that is being continued in the Industrial Development Bill which is circulated to Members of the Dáil and Seanad today. I have asked the Industrial Development Authority for a report on the use of this power.  The IDA should be making more active use of their powers in order to <Col N="1188" /> assist Irish firms in merging to become stronger and hence have the critical &ldquo;mass&rdquo; necessary to compete with foreign firms.  I hope there will be active use of that power in the future because it is entirely consistent with the objectives of industrial policy which we have set for ourselves in the White Paper.</P>
    <P>Senator Lynch asked a question as to my surprise or otherwise of the lack of any inquiry into monopoly under the Act. The situation is that any inquiry would normally be initiated by the Examiner of Restrictive Practices rather than by the Minister.  He has not done so and, therefore, it has not occurred.  The main reason is the one I have given at the outset of my speech.  Monopolies do not exist in this country to any appreciable degree except in the public sector.  Of course, the public sector is exempt from the restrictive practices and mergers control legislation.  Some would argue that it should not be exempt and that its activities should also be subject to control of this kind.  This matter was addressed in the Government's White Paper <i>Building on Reality.</i> Legislation to reform restrictive practices legislation generally is under consideration by the Government and we will be dealing with that matter.</P>
    <P>I should like to thank the Seanad for the non-partisan welcome extended to this measure</P>
    <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="State Guarantee Act, 1954 (Amendment" RHead="of Schedule) Order, 1985: Motion">
    <Title>State Guarantee Act, 1954 (Amendment of Schedule) Order, 1985: Motion.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="AlexisJGFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. FitzGerald Mr. FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>I move:</P>
      <P>That Seanad Éireann approves the following Order in draft:</P>
      <P>State Guarantee Act, 1954 (Amendment of Schedule) Order, 1985,</P>
      <P>a copy of which Order in draft has been laid before the House.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JimMitchell" hpid="Minister for Communications (Mr. J. Mitchell) Jim Mitchell">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Communications (Mr. J. Mitchell)</NameTxt>
      <P>This resolution arises as a part of a series of measures needed for the financial restructuring of the Dublin Port and Docks Board which is now virtually <Col N="1189" /> complete and which is part of the rescue package for the board decided on by the Government earlier this year.  In presenting this proposal to the House I feel it would be useful to look briefly at some of the events which gave rise to the need for the action by the Government in relation to the port of Dublin.</P>
      <P>Dublin port has been adversely affected by a number of factors over the past few years such as the common plague of the recession and the drop in the demand for oil due largely to increased usage of natural gas.  These factors alone would have led to significant deterioration in the financial performance of the Port and Docks Board.  On top of that, as we all know the board has had to contend with the fruits of the board's decision to become directly involved in stevedoring through the establishment of Dublin Cargo Handling Limited.  The result of this decision so fundamentally affected the financial wellbeing of the Port and Docks Board as to call into question the board's future viability.  The disputes which followed the establishment of Dublin Cargo Handling Limited, including the blockading of the port by one section of the work force, represented a sad chapter indeed in the long and distinguished history of Dublin port. Happily, that chapter is now coming to an end, thanks to the persistent efforts of those truly concerned with the welfare of the port.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>As I have said on a number of occasions in the past, a viable successful Dublin port can only be achieved if everybody plays a part.  The Government have consistently shown willingness to play their part and continue to do so.  In order to assist the Port and Docks Board the Government approved a package of measures designed to restore the port to financial viability last March.  The board later informed us of difficulties they had encountered in implementing the measures. Following a review of the position the Government agreed in May on a revised financial package for the board. The package comprised: (1) Exchequer grant assistance of £3 million in each of the years 1985, 1986 and 1987; (2) a State <Col N="1190" /> guarantee of borrowing by the Port and Docks Board of up to £7 million; (3) a requirement that the board would take necessary steps to solve its financial problems by cutting costs, increasing revenue and disposal of assets.  In addition, there were some local loans fund provisions which I will refer to later.  The State assistance was contingent on the conclusion of negotiations between Dublin Cargo Handling Limited and the dock labour force.</P>
    <P>I am pleased to report that the major elements of the rescue package are now falling into place.  Negotiations have been successfully concluded with the dock labour force and the 1985 State grant of £3 million has been paid in full.  The board are taking steps to rectify their financial situation by disposing of assets and increasing revenue.  These are all essential components to the restoration of viability at Dublin port.  The onus is on those who oppose increased charges to show how their approach would improve the prospects of viability.</P>
    <P>In the context of the Government rescue package I recently withheld my consent to a proposal from the board for the sale and lease-back of the port centre building because I did not regard the terms as being satisfactory from the board's point of view.  Non-implementation of the board's proposal has had implications for the board insofar as the level of bank borrowings is concerned.  In view of this I have, following consultation with the Minister for Finance, agreed to make available to the board a Local Loans Fund loan of £3 million.  This is in addition to another Local Loans Fund loan of £2.5 million which was given earlier this year.  Taking into account direct grants, loan guarantees and direct loans the Government have either provided or committed financial assistance in the amount of £21.5 million to the board over the past 12 months.  I am glad to note that the banks have also carried out their role in a responsible manner by making funds available and continuing to support the board.  Now that normal activity at the port has resumed it is up to those directly involved, both management and <Col N="1191" /> workers, to show that they have the skill and determination to make it work.</P>
    <P>The resolution which is now before the House, if approved, will provide a State guarantee of up to £7 million of the board's borrowings and will complete the Government rescue package for the board.  The guarantee necessitates an appropriate amendment to the Schedule of the State Guarantees Act, 1954, and it is specifically in this context that the resolution arises.  Approval of this amendment by the House and by the Dáil is necessary in order to complete legal formalities in respect of the guarantee.</P>
    <P>I should point out that a revised borrowing package has recently been agreed between the Port and Docks Board and their bankers.  The new borrowing arrangements are conditional on the State guarantee being in place no later than the end of this year.  There is, therefore, an obvious urgency about the matter.  Therefore, I recommend the resolution to the House.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelLynch" hpid="Mr. Lynch Mr. Lynch">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lynch</NameTxt>
      <P>I regret we did not get a copy of the Minister's speech.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JimMitchell" hpid="Mr. J. Mitchell Mr. J. Mitchell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J. Mitchell</NameTxt>
      <P>There are copies available.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelLynch" hpid="Mr. Lynch Mr. Lynch">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lynch</NameTxt>
      <P>Having listened to what the Minister has stated I feel it is a measure we should adopt in this House.  We are concerend about the future of Dublin port and we will support any efforts to make it viable and successful.  The Minister stated that the Government have prepared a package which will help to restore the port as a viable enterprise and we hope it is successful.  A total package of £21.5 million in the past 12 months seems to be a fairly large sum, but when we take into consideration the problems that Dublin port faced over the last number of years I feel that the sum is not large enough.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The Minister said that there is a responsibility on the board to ensure that they operate as successfully as possible, and all of us agree with that.  We discussed Irish Shipping here last week and it <Col N="1192" /> caused some concern.  Perhaps the Minister could clarify something in relation to that.  He said that Members of the House had not done their sums properly and were possibly ill-informed.  In an article in the <i>Evening Press</i> on 8 November we read that a former PRO with the company said that any primary cert students who look at the figures would clarify that the Minister supplied the wrong figures.</P>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I have to bring it to the Senator's notice that he cannot debate Irish Shipping now because that was debated last Thursday.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelLynch" hpid="Mr. Lynch Mr. Lynch">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lynch</NameTxt>
      <P>I know but the Minister might clarify the position if it would be £30 million more than he stated at that time.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JimMitchell" hpid="Mr. J. Mitchell Mr. J. Mitchell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J. Mitchell</NameTxt>
      <P>That was stated by me last week.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="AlexisJGFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. FitzGerald Mr. FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>I would like to welcome this motion.  The order is being brought to this House and the other House in very exceptional circumstances. As Members of the House are aware, Dublin port has been in extreme financial difficulty over the last few years and this order, along with the other aspects of the financial package that have been negotiated with the Port and Docks Board, are all in an effort to restore viability to the port, recognising the important economic role that the port of Dublin plays in this country.  The package, which includes this £7 million guaranteed arrangement to the Port and Docks by way of loan, is short lived and should, of course, be short lived.  We are aware that the intention is to provide assistance to the board with reducing commitment from 1 January 1987 and that this arrangement will be eliminated within two years following that.  The proposal is included with the grant assistance of £3 million each year until 1987 and it is very good news to hear from the Minister that that particular provision this year has already been discharged.  All of this, together with the rationalisation of the <Col N="1193" /> work force in the port and a more determined effort all round by those involved in running the port, whether by way of management or the work force itself, should bring the port into a viable and commercially successful state again.  That should be achieved as urgently as possible.</P>
      <P>In relation to the recent announcement of the establishment of a statutory authority to deal with the development of the Port and Docks Board site, I presume that the benefits of that, combined with the value of the redevelopment of a large 27 acre site in the centre of Dublin along the Liffey side, will also be a measure&mdash; one not mentioned by the Minister&mdash;to bring back normality to the finances of the Port and Docks Board.  I have great pleasure in welcoming this order and hope that the Minister, when replying, will make some comment on that area.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JimMitchell" hpid="Minister for Communications (Mr. J. Mitchell) Jim Mitchell">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Communications (Mr. J. Mitchell)</NameTxt>
      <P>I would like to thank the House for facilitating the speedy passage of this order.  I would like to comment on points made by Senators Lynch and FitzGerald. May I say in passing that the figures I gave to the House in relation to Irish Shipping are the correct figures.  I am surprised that Senator Lynch would in any way question the veracity of the figures I gave the House.  He can rest assured that all those other figures that have been bandied about are inaccurate, distortion, double counting or not comparing like with like.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelLynch" hpid="Mr. Lynch Mr. Lynch">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lynch</NameTxt>
      <P>I am glad to hear that.  It was a newspaper report.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JimMitchell" hpid="Mr. J. Mitchell Mr. J. Mitchell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J. Mitchell</NameTxt>
      <P>The point I made in last week's debate was that so many figures have been bandied about in newspapers that I had better put on the record accurate figures.  The actual cost of the liquidation will be, as I said last week, of the order of just under £50 million compared to a revised estimate for keeping going of £220 million.  I think the gentlemen of the press in the last few days were also adding in the cost to the <Col N="1194" /> Exchequer anyway, whether Irish Shipping had closed down or not, of the subsidy on the <i>Irish Spruce.</i> That did not fall on Irish Shipping. That was £30 million. That would have fallen to be paid whether or not Irish Shipping went into liquidation, so that should not be included.</P>
      <P>In relation to the points made by Senator FitzGerald, there has been a long saga about the Custom House dock site. As I said in the other House last night during a motion on Dublin port, there has been a lot of comment, controversy and indeed criticism of the then Government for deciding to intervene on the 27 acre dock site.  I do not dispute the wisdom of the decision of the then Government in saying &ldquo;This is a very important site for the city of Dublin.  This cannot be allowed to go out of public ownership without considering how its development can be maximised to the advantage of the city of Dublin, especially the heart of Dublin.&rdquo;  I am not at all critical of the decision of the then Government under Deputy Haughey to intervene politically in that case.  I want to put that on record.  There has been a lot of criticism of the so-called Gregory deal.  People took exception to the idea that one Deputy in the House could extract this sort of commitment from the Government.  I know that the then Government did not make that commitment with a glad heart or would not do it in normal circumstances.  The site in question is very important for Dublin city centre.  I hope the decisions taken by this Government and announced by the Taoiseach in the Dáil on 23 October, after very detailed consideration by an inter-departmental working committee under the chairmanship of the Minister of State at the Department of the Environment, will permit and encourage the best development of that site to the advantage of Dublin city.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The rescue package which I announced to the Seanad in my opening speech includes grants of £9 million, £3 million already paid, a further £3 million next year and £3 million in 1987.  The Government in giving those grants&mdash;it is the <Col N="1195" /> first time grants have been paid to Dublin port&mdash;decided that they would be taken into account in the final reconciliation between the State and the Dublin Port and Docks Board when that site comes to be valued.  Those questions will be addressed in the Bill which the Minister for the Environment will bring before both Houses of the Oireachtas in the next few months to give effect to the new authority to develop the Port and Docks site.</P>
    <P>The port of Dublin has suffered a very severe decline since 1979.  Yes, recession has played its part; yes, the changing consumption patterns of petroleum products have played a big part, because of natural gas in particular.  These were two aspects outside the control of the Port and Docks Board and their work force. But there was a third and probably most serious cause &mdash; the whole area of industrial relations, which in the deep sea section have been extremely bad for too long and have really strangled the port.</P>
    <P>We have been through the hoops on this in the past 18 months.  We have had visits to the Labour Court, agreements signed by both sides, dock review groups and then failure by one side to implement that agreement.  At the eleventh hour agreement was finally reached and, I am glad to say, is now being implemented since the past month or so.  First reports about the implementation of that agreement are encouraging.  I say to those people who work in the port, management and workforce alike, and also to the board, that it is vital to the future viability of the port, to the survival of the port and to the prosperity of the port that there be a continuation of this full, comprehensive and glad co-operation between all in the port.  I believe that the port because of its natural assets can prosper and win back the trade it has lost. Its location and its facilities are major advantages for it.  It has to keep its charges competitive and, above all, it has to keep its service to the customer competitive and good.  After very painful months I believe we have now reached the stage where there is room for hope <Col N="1196" /> and encouragement.  I hope that persists in the future.</P>
    <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="European Communities (Amendment)" RHead="Bill, 1985: Second Stage">
    <Title>European Communities (Amendment) Bill, 1985: Second Stage.</Title>
    <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That the Bill be now read a Second Time.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="PeterBarry" hpid="Minister for Foreign Affairs (Mr. P. Barry) Peter Barry">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Foreign Affairs (Mr. P. Barry)</NameTxt>
      <P>The objective of this Bill is to complete our ratification procedures so as to allow Spain and Portugal to become full members of the European Community. For this purpose it is necessary to amend the European Communities Act, 1972, by adding to it the Treaty of Accession of Spain and Portugal to the European Economic Community and to the European Atomic Energy Community. While Spain and Portugal may accede to the European Coal and Steel Community through a decision of the Council, the Irish Constitution requires that both the Treaty and this decision must be made part of the law of the State.</P>
      <P>The negotiations were completed in May of this year and the Treaty of Accession was signed in Lisbon and Madrid on 12 June.  Since it has been agreed that the date of accession should be 1 January 1986, both the present member states and the adherents must complete their national ratification procedures in time to meet this deadline.  To date, Belgium and Luxembourg are the only members of the existing Community to have complete their ratification procedures, though the process is under way in a number of other member states. Once the Bill before the House becomes law, the way will be clear for Ireland to ratify the Treaty of Accession.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>It is, I think, reflective of the interest, and indeed the concern, that Spanish and Portuguese accession evokes that this Bill was debated for a total period of about ten hours in the other House.  That debate not only ranged over the various implications of enlargement but also touched upon a panoply of other Community <Col N="1197" /> issues.  Today I would like to concentrate on a number of areas where the prospect of enlargement is, rightly or wrongly, causing concern in come quarters and also, and perhaps more importantly, to try to identify a few areas where the accession of Spain and Portugal to the Community will create opportunities which must be exploited.</P>
    <P>Before this process of analysis, however, it may be useful to provide the context by mentioning the origins of Spain and Portugal's applications for membership and the subsequent history of the accession negotiations.  In both of these countries the decision to apply for membership of the Community was the external manifestation of their return to democracy in the seventies.  In Portugal this return to democracy was achieved very quickly when the old authoritarian regime collapsed practically overnight in 1974.  The achievement of the fathers of the revolution in the subsequent few years was to ensure that Portugal's authoritarian system of Government was not replaced by a totalitarian one.  The attainment of democracy in Spain was, on the other hand, a more gradual process.  After the death of General Franco in 1975 King Juan Carlos bravely and skilfully presided over a process which culminated in the establishment of democratic institutions in Spain.</P>
    <P>By the latter half of the 1970s it was clear that democracy in both of these countries was well established.  As part of the process of its consolidation the Governments of Portugal and Spain applied for membership of the Community in the first half of 1977.  The Community required a certain amount of time to consider and formally accept the applications of the candidates.  It was recognised that it was desirable in political terms for Spain and Portugal to accede to the Community.  On the other hand, however, it was also recognised that, as the applicants were relatively underdeveloped countries whose main agricultural products were already in surplus in the existing Community, there would be an economic price to pay.</P>
    <P>It is a tribute to the Community spirit <Col N="1198" /> of the then Mediterranean member states, namely France and Italy, that they supported politically the applications of Spain and Portugal in the knowledge that competition from the Iberian peninsula after enlargement would pose a substantial challenge to their own fruit and vegetable, wine and olive oil producers. After the Council formally accepted the applications of the candidates, negotiations were opened with Portugal in October 1978 and with Spain in February 1979.</P>
    <P>The fact that these negotiations lasted over six years is a reflection of the intrinsic complexity and difficulty of the issues that had to be tackled.  As well as the question of integrating the agricultural economies of the applicant states into the system of Community agriculture, there were also the problems of the dismantlement of Spain's highly protectionist industrial tariffs, the restructuring of its large steel capacity in accordance with Community rules, and, of course, the integration of the huge Spanish fishing fleet within the Common Fisheries Policy.  It must be said, however, that there were also factors extraneous to the negotiations themselves which retarded progress.  In 1980 the negotiation were effectively frozen while the Community set about a major reform of its regime for Mediterranean agricultural products. A couple of years later the momentum was again lost as the Community became increasingly preoccupied with its internal, that is to say, budgetary difficulties.</P>
    <P>The French Presidency was successful in regaining the political momentum for the advancement of the negotiations. Nevertheless when Ireland took over the Presidency in June 1984 a great deal of the substance of the negotiations remained to be dealt with.  Indeed, in a number of vital areas such as agriculture, fisheries, industrial tariff dismantlement, steel restructuring, and the question of the free movement of workers, the key issues remained to be resolved.</P>
    <P>As we set about tackling these individual issues our greatest task, as Presidency, was in securing the agreement of <Col N="1199" /> member states to common positions to present to the applicants.  This was because member states were inclined to link agreement on one issue to a satisfactory outcome for them on another. Consequently, many of the sensitive chapters in the negotiations became the captives of a complex system of negotiating linkages.</P>
    <P>The key issue, and a solution to which allowed this impasse to be unblocked, was the question of wine and, in particular, the control of its production in an enlarged Community.  Agreement on this issue at the Dublin European Council in December 1984 allowed the Community to adopt positions on a whole range of other areas.  Those who voiced criticisms that the Dublin Summit concentrated too much on the wine issue were obviously unaware of the central importance of the wine dossier in the overall scheme of the enlargement negotiations.  If the wine question had not been resolved and the Community was not, in turn, able to present negotiating positions to the applicants, there was a real danger that the Spanish and Portuguese delegation would have left the negotiating table for good.  The agreement at Dublin allowed the Italian Presidency to pursue the final stages of the negotiations and to negotiate directly, on behalf of the Community, with the applicants on the major outstanding issues.</P>
    <P>One of these concerns, and perhaps our primary one, was the fisheries chapter which was resolved in the final stage of the negotiations under the Italian Presidency. It has, incidentally, been claimed that we made a tactical error in not insisting on the settlement of the fisheries chapter during our own Presidency.  As any experienced Community commentator knows, the role of Presidency requires a member state to behave in a disinterested and accommodating manner in the search for a compromise acceptable to all partners.  The ability of a member state to vigorously protect its interests can be inhibited by the responsibility which accompanies the role of <Col N="1200" /> Presidency.  During the Italian Presidency on the other hand, we were able to negotiate in a hard-headed and determined manner, unencumbered by the responsibility which the custodial role of Presidency involves.</P>
    <P>I wish to restate my conviction that the arrangements we secured on the fisheries chapter represent the optimum that could be achieved without, in effect, denying Spain its right of inclusion in the Common Fisheries Policy.  That policy, which had been worked out for the Ten in 1982 after very lengthy and difficult negotiations, provided the necessary scope for the further development of our fishing industry. Our primary negotiating objective during the accession negotiations was to ensure that the inclusion of Spain in the Common Fisheries Policy was achieved in such a phased manner as not to jeopardise the benefits we had secured from the policy.  The centre piece of this negotiating strategy was the achievement of a long period during which Spanish fishing vessels would be excluded from the 50 mile fishing zone around our coast, the co-called Irish box.</P>
    <P>Spain, on the other hand, was pressing for a substantial measure of integration of its fishing fleet into the Common Fisheries Policy from the date of entry, including some immediate level of access to the Irish box from accession.  This was totally unacceptable to us.  Near the conclusion of the negotiations the Commission and Presidency tabled a compromise package which would have given Spanish fishing vessels full access to the Irish box after seven years.  While we were aware that our resolute stand in the protection of a vital national asset might seriously affect the entire negotiations, we, nonetheless, again rejected this compromise proposal.</P>
    <P>I am glad to say, however, that our negotiating partners ultimately recognised the primary importance we attached to this issue and, at the Foreign Affairs Council at the end of March, we were successful in securing a derogation whereby Spanish and Portuguese fishing vessels will be excluded from the Irish <Col N="1201" /> box for a ten-year period up to the beginning of 1996.  Moreover, the Spanish Minister made a unilateral declaration committing his authorities to talks with the Irish Government, before the ten-year period expires, to secure the orderly integration of Spanish boats into the Irish box after 1995.</P>
    <P>The fisheries chapter did, of course, contain other elements such as agreement on the number of Spanish vessels that can fish in Community waters other than the Irish box during the transitional period, the re-allocation of catch quotas of particular species to include the acceding States&mdash;where, incidentally, Ireland was successful in securing improved quotas for our own fishermen&mdash;and the extension of the strict supervisory regulations of the Common Fisheries Policy to the Spanish fishing fleet, including regular inspections by Community fisheries inspectors.</P>
    <P>Notwithstanding the merits of the deal we negotiated, concern has been expressed about the willingness of Spanish fishermen to respect the arrangements and of our capacity to fully implement them.  Given the past record of Spanish vessels fishing illegally in our waters, these reservations are understandable and I fully appreciate the fishing industry's concern in this regard.  Since 1980, a total of 233 Spanish, and Spanish vessels registered in Britain and Ireland, have been arrested for illegal fishing in Irish waters and practically all have been fined heavily.  If such incidents continue after accession the supervisory regime of the Common Fisheries Policy to be applied to Spanish fishing vessels will assist us in ensuring that a greater number of transgressors are caught and subject to the full rigour of the law.</P>
    <P>However, we must not presume in advance that things will continue as before.  Spain will be taking its place at the Council table as a full partner on 1 January 1986 and I am confident that the Spanish Government will, in good faith, actively enforce the agreed fisheries arrangements set out in the Treaty of Accession.  As regards our ability to <Col N="1202" /> ensure compliance with these arrangements, I might mention that the Council on 29 March, 1985, at our insistence, declared its willingness to assist member states to improve their fishing surveillance capacity.  This declaration stated that the Council was prepared to consider, on a proposal from the Commission, financial aid for member states for the provision of adequate surveillance and control measures necessitated by the enlargement of the Community.  On foot of this understanding the Government are currently considering the adequacy of our fishing surveillance capacity for an enlarged Community.</P>
    <P>Any assessment of the implications for Ireland of an enlarged Community should not, of course, be restricted only to the area of fisheries.  There is also the question of the general impact of enlargement on the already straitened budgetary capacity of the Community and, in particular, the effect on Ireland's transfers from the Community's structural funds, that is the Regional Fund, Social Fund and the FEOGA guidance section.</P>
    <P>On the general question of the adequacy of the Community's budget to absorb the costs of enlargement, Senators will be aware that, in parallel to the accession of Spain and Portugal, the VAT element in the Community's own resources will be increased from the existing ceiling of 1 per cent to 1.4 per cent of member states VAT bases on 1 January 1986.  Provision has also been made for a possible further increase of 1.6 per cent on 1 January 1988.  This increase in own resources and the enlargement of the Community are inextricably linked. Indeed, the agreement of a number of the larger member states to an increase in own resources was conditional on the accession of Spain and Portugal to the Community.</P>
    <P>Doubts have been expressed about the adequacy of a 1.4 or, indeed, 1.6 per cent VAT base for the functioning of an enlarged Community.  I fully share those doubts.  In fact the Government have for a long time been using every opportunity to make the point that the Community <Col N="1203" /> needs to be provided with a long-term stable revenue base.</P>
    <P>This revenue base should be sufficient to enable the Community, first, to strengthen and develop its existing policies; secondly, to allow it to meet the new demands which the impending enlargement will place on its resources; and thirdly, enable it to develop the new policies which are necessary if the Community is to be revitalised.  The increase to 1.4 per cent is a start, but we believe that a further early increase in own resources is necessary if the Community is to be able to meet the three challenges I have mentioned.  The Government will continue to press in Brussels for such a further increase.</P>
    <P>The adequacy of a stable revenue base in the Community determines, to a great extent, the Community's ability to transfer resources from its prosperous centre to the less developed periphery.  The Preamble to the Treaty of Rome speaks of the desire to reduce the differences existing between the various regions and the backwardness of the less favoured regions.  The operation of the three structural funds has gone some way to achieving this goal.  Since our own accession to the Community we have received in aggregate over 1.1 billion pounds from these three funds.  Spain and Portugal, as relatively underdeveloped countries, will have access to all of the structural funds from accession.  At the moment the precise manner in which the acceding states will be integrated into the Regional and Social Funds is being discussed in Brussels. In the case of the Regional Fund, the provision of shares for Spain and Portugal means that the share of the present member states must be proportionately reduced in percentage terms.  However, we firmly believe that the less prosperous member states should not have to accept a real fall in their receipts because of enlargement.  We shall continue to insist that there should be no erosion in our current level of transfers from the Regional Fund.  As regards the Social Fund, the present 40 per cent allocation <Col N="1204" /> reserved for the existing regions of absolute priority, including the whole of Ireland, is being revised upwards to take account of the inclusion of Portugal and certain regions of Spain.  We are pressing for an increase in the allocation that is sufficient to meet the needs of all the regions of absolute priority in an enlarged Community.</P>
    <P>When this Bill was being discussed in the other House, it was said by many participants in the debate that the Community had failed to develop an effective regional policy and that this situation would be exacerbated in an enlarged Community.  It was stated that economic indicators showed that, since the establishment of the Regional Fund in 1975, the disparities in living standards between the centre and the periphery have widened not narrowed.  While the Regional Fund has made a useful contribution towards the development of our national infrastructure, it has to be admitted that it has not met the expectations of those who saw its establishment as the beginning of a process aimed at the elimination of economic disparities between regions.</P>
    <P>The Government certainly feel that the fund could be made a much more effective instrument of economic convergence. This can only be achieved, however, by a more realistic endowment of its resources.  At the moment the Regional Fund's resources only represent between 4 and 6 per cent of the national expenditure by all member states on regional development.  The question of endowing the Regional Fund with sufficient resources to begin to achieve a degree of economic convergence between regions is, of course, related to the more general question of equipping the Community with a realistic revenue base.  As Senators will know, there is at the moment an Intergovernmental Conference of the member and acceding states whose purpose is to decide on further steps towards European integration. In the Government's approach to the conference we are seeking, together with others who share our concerns, to focus attention on the need to increase the economic cohesion of the <Col N="1205" /> Community and to provide for the necessary financial capacity to achieve this.</P>
    <P>These then are the main concerns and challenges which I believe are created by enlargement.  I have dealt with them at some length to give Senators an idea of the complexity of the issues we confronted and to show that, while the accession negotiations are over, the challenge of enlargement in many respects remains to be dealt with.  The enlarged Community, of course, also brings opportunities. In the other House last Thursday one speaker spoke of enlargement in terms of its positive challenge for the Community in general and for Ireland in particular.  He stated that the Community was not only about guarantees and financial transfers but also about the creation of an open market that could be exploited.  For too long we had passively enjoyed the guaranteed benefits of membership without actively seeking to utilise the potential which free access to a huge market offered us.</P>
    <P>The accession of Spain and Portugal represents such an opportunity which our exporters and industrialists must not miss.  These two countries will add a further 48 million consumers to the Community's common market.  Industrial tariffs on trade between the acceding states and the Community will be gradually abolished over seven years.  The greater part of this dismantlement will occur over the first three years.  In addition, apart from a very few exceptions, Spain and Portugal must abolish their non-tariff barriers &mdash; such as quotas or import licences&mdash;from the date of accession.  In the agricultural area, it has been agreed that the Community will have immediate access to the Iberian market for specified levels of its &ldquo;northern products&rdquo; such as dairy products, beef and pigmeat.  These levels will be gradually increased over the transitional period.</P>
    <P>At the moment Ireland's exports to Spain and Portugal represent about 1.25 per cent of our total exports.  While our trade with Portugal is relatively modest, Spain is our fifteenth largest export market.  We exported over £94 million <Col N="1206" /> worth of goods to Spain in 1984 and the figures for the first nine months of this year indicate that the export figure for 1985 will be significantly higher.  Our principal categories of exports to Spain are chemicals, office machinery, metals, beverages, pharmaceuticals and fish.</P>
    <P>Until now Spain has operated a very protectionist trade regime and has shielded its industry behind high tariff walls and a complex system of non-tariff barriers.  Notwithstanding this, Irish exporters and manufacturers have in recent years been successful in making even deeper inroads into the Spanish market.  After Spain begins the gradual dismantlement of its tariffs and the immediate abolition of its non-tariff barriers in 1986, Irish exporters will be in a much better position to penetrate the Spanish market.  An area where there clearly is potential is fish.  Spain has one of the highest <i>per capita</i> consumption rates of fish products in the world.  Our fishermen catch species, such as hake, which are very popular on the Spanish market.  In 1984 we exported over £4 million worth of fish to Spain.  If our fishermen and fish processors orientate themselves towards the Spanish market, I am sure that we can considerably increase this export figure after enlargement.</P>
    <P>It has been said that the economic benefits of enlargement will exclusively favour the large member states whose developed trade economies will allow them to exploit the opening of the market in Spain and Portugal.  However, there are a number of small and medium sized member states, such as Denmark and the Netherlands, who are preparing to avail of the trade opportunity which the opening of the Iberian market represents. These countries in the past have shown themselves adept, especially in the agricultural foodstuff sector, in gaining access to various world markets.  We are now beginning at last to develop a substantial food processing industry.  If this industry studies the needs of the market in Spain and Portugal, develops or refines its products to suit that market and used the right marketing techniques to sell them, I am convinced that we too can <Col N="1207" /> benefit significantly from the extension of the Community market.</P>
    <P>So far I have been addressing the question of the economic challenges and opportunities posed by the accession of Spain and Portugal to the Community. There are, however, other political and cultural implications which are, nonetheless, considerable.  One of the achievements of the Community has been that it has managed to give concrete expression to the notion of a European identity while, at the same time, safeguarding the cultural diversity of its constituent member states.  This cultural diversity will now be enriched by the addition of two new states who, while being European in every sense of the word, have their own distinct heritage.</P>
    <P>On account of their histories, the political and economic orientation of the two acceding states has in the past often been outside rather than inside the European mainland.  A large part of southern Spain was occupied and settled by the Moors of North Africa in the medieval period. While the native Spaniards were by the fifteenth century successful in reasserting their political dominance, the Moorish legacy can be seen to this day in the architecture of many Spanish cities, such as Granada and Seville.  The rise of Spain as a military and political power in the sixteenth century was, in large part, based on the wealth of its possessions in Latin America.  Today Spain still enjoys extensive political and cultural links with North African and South American states.  On the other hand, Portugal's focus of interest during its history was Africa and the Far East.  Portuguese navigators pioneered the voyages of discovery that began in the fifteenth century and Portugal succeeded in establishing an extensive trade network with its southern African and Asian territories.  The cultures of the acceding states have been enriched by their historical relationship with countries in Africa and Latin America. The cultural diversity of the existing Community will now, in turn, be <Col N="1208" /> enhanced by the accession of two European countries who enjoy such a rich heritage.</P>
    <P>The process of European political co-operation has meant that the Ten have been able to speak with one voice on important global issues.  The inclusion of Spain and Portugal in the system of European Political Co-operation will mean that the voice of the Ten now becomes of voice of Twelve and, consequently, all the more authoritative.  In addition, the Community has in recent years concluded co-operation agreements with individual third countries and with other regional multilateral groupings such as the Association of South-East Asian Nations.  The accession of Spain and Portugal to the Community will facilitate it in the development of its external policy in those regions where the acceding states have long standing cultural and political interests.  For instance, in regard to the co-operation agreement signed this week between the Community and the Central American states, Spain's <i>corpus</i> of knowledge and influence in this troubled region will greatly assist the Community in developing this new relationship with Central America.</P>
    <P>Finally, I would like to say again that the Government welcomes the accession of Spain and Portugal to the Community. After a period in their recent histories during which dictatorial regimes imposed an inward looking isolationism upon both countries, Spain and Portugal are now resuming their rightful place in Europe. While the integration of Spain and Portugal within the Community will present challenges, it should be remembered that the acceding states have also a great deal to contribute.  I look forward to a new and fruitful relationship with Spain and Portugal in the Community and am confident that the challenges which lie ahead can be effectively tackled in a spirit of co-operation between all member states, both old and new.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MickLanigan" hpid="Mr. Lanigan Mr. Lanigan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lanigan</NameTxt>
      <P>The introduction of this Bill to the House has come about after very delicate and protracted negotiations, which have gone on in the case <Col N="1209" /> of Portugal since 1978 and in the case of Spain since 1979.  There are a number of positive aspects in the accession of both these countries, but equally there are a number of aspects of accession which give rise to worry for this country in particular and for the rest of the Community in general.</P>
      <P>In every debate on the European Economic Community in this House doubts have been expressed about the efficiency of the present Community, about the great failures to maximise the benefits of the Community for the good of all members and the major failure even to confront the unemployment crisis which has beset all member states in the past six or seven years.  We have seen that the major lack of a coherent regional policy within the Community has resulted in an ever-growing gap between the wealthier nations of the Community and the poorer nations.  The amount of money being put into the regional development fund is a derisory 5 per cent of the overall Community budget.  The accession of Spain and Portugal will put further pressure on the Community to provide adequate financing for the purpose of extending regional schemes which would be of benefit to the poorer countries.  It would appear that the increase from 1 per cent to 1.4 per cent VAT from national sources will not be enough to confront the additional burden which will be imposed when Spain and Portugal come into the Community.</P>
      <P>If one were to assess the performance of the EC in the past ten years in relation to one of its most important objectives, that of providing work in a reasonable environment for people in the member states, one would have to say that the Community had failed and failed utterly. When we joined the Community 12 years ago the number of unemployed was 2.5 million people and today there are 14 million people unemployed in the Community. In an Irish context we had 65,000 people unemployed; now the figure is around the 240,000 mark and this figure hides a large number of people who have left Ireland on the emigration boat, plane or train in the past couple of years.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="1210" /> We wonder when we look at the unemployment figures why the Spanish and the Portugese should be so anxious to join. There are approximately three million people unemployed in Spain and approximately 500,000 unemployed in Portugal. If we were to progress forward the unemployment rate in these two countries, the accession of Spain and Portugal will have catastrophic consequences not alone for these countries but equally for the Community as a whole.  I hope it will become a fact that with the accession a new impetus will be given to the solution of unemployment in the Community.</P>
    <P>Agriculture plays a major part in the Irish economy.  It is of vital importance that Ireland's agricultural industry should be protected when one considers that last year gross output in the industry amounted to over £2½ billion and agricultural exports exceeded £1.6 billion.  We must protect this industry at all costs, even though it may bring about conflict with our European neighbours.  In the past we have too often been seen as good Europeans and seem to have neglected our own people in the attempt to continue as good Europeans.  The agricultural sector occupies a central role in the economy of Ireland and therefore agricultural development must be an essential priority of economic policy.</P>
    <P>The recent Green Paper issued by the European Commission strikes at the very basic principle of the policy which offered the greatest attraction to Ireland's entering into the Community.  It proposes that the current support systems be replaced by what are called market-orientated approaches.  This would mean the replacement of price support by income aids that are largely national and would return us to an era of low and unstable prices for our agrictural products, a situation which plagued our economy prior to our joining the Community.  This change, if effected, would have profound effects not alone on Ireland but equally on the newer members, whether Greece, Spain or Portugal.</P>
    <P>Last year from the guarantee section of FEOGA nearly £650 million came into Ireland.  This represented one half of the <Col N="1211" /> total farm income in that year.  Even with that injection, income per head in farms in Ireland is little more than 50 per cent of the European average.  Urban dwellers may see the Community's problems stemming from the support given to farmers, but the fact is that the food and drink industry is the largest industry in Europe.  It employs more than three million people and absorbs 85 per cent of the sales of agricultural products.  The meat and dairying industries look to agriculture for four-fifths of their purchases. The CAP has given a strong impetus to Europe's agricultural co-ops, which employ more than half a million staff</P>
    <P>The <i>per capita</i> support of the United States farmer is considerably greater than that of his European counterpart.  We have recently seen the phenomenal support in the United States for the farmers' plight, as expressed in the support that was given to the Farmers' Aid concert. There was magnificent support from all over the States.  These farmers are supported to a much greater extent than the European farmer.</P>
    <P>The entry of Spain and Portugal to the Community will see a worsening of the position of Irish farmers as we see a continuing major shift in the attitude of the Community, leading to stifling budgetary retrenchment and reduction in financial support for traditional Community policies. On the entry of Spain and Portugal there will be a diversion of resources from the northern to the southern agricultural regions, while at the same time the agricultural and regional funds are unlikely to be increased significantly enough to cope with the new demands which will be made upon them.</P>
    <P>The special position of Ireland as one of the least developed countries in the Community in which agriculture plays so large a role will have to be recognised more effectively in the future than it has been in the past.  It is particularly important that the EC schemes such as the western package scheme with 50 per cent reimbursement should be taken up so that we can take full advantage of what <Col N="1212" /> is available from Europe.  We were willing to sacrifice a great deal when we joined the Community but it was always our expectation that the benefits from economic developments under the CAP would more than compensate for losses in other sectors.</P>
    <P>In the light of the major upheavals which are taking place in Community policies, I believe we should now draw up a detailed, quantified balance sheet of advantage and disadvantage arising from membership.  Such a balance sheet would not be prepared as a test of continued membership but rather as a firm foundation on which we could base our negotiating stances in future on all relevant Community issues.  This information would then supply the basic data for econometric model which would be updated at regular intervals for developments and changes.</P>
    <P>In an enlarged Community we must with our new partners confront the problems of the internal market, the dismantling of frontiers, non-tariff barriers and State subsidies.  Whereas it must be said that each individual country will probably confront these problems from different perspectives, nevertheless they must be confronted and overcome.</P>
    <P>One of the main problems that will confront us in Ireland on the accession of Spain and Portugal is undoubtedly that associated with our fishing industry. Viewed from either an economic or a social perspective, Irish sea fisheries development is now in decline with fishing boats being repossessed and stocks endangered due to overfishing and the lack of a coherent fishery policy either in Ireland or in Europe.</P>
    <P>Protection of our exclusive fishing limits against illegal fishing by foreign vessels will be increasingly problematic. We have a coastline of some 1,737 miles. The 200-mile exclusive fishing limit gives us a sea area of approximately 132,000 square miles to patrol and this brings into context the huge problem confronting our fishery protection service.  Legislation for the control of illegal activities within our jurisdiction needs to be reviewed so as to ensure that it is adequate for the <Col N="1213" /> protection of our fishing stocks.  The joint committee have identified the major problem associated with Spain's accession, from the point of view of the Irish fishing industry, as the size of the Spanish fishing fleet and the dominant role that fish plays in the Spanish economy.</P>
    <P>Spain is a major producer and consumer of fish, with a fishing fleet of 17,500 vessels representing 750,000 gross registered tonnes.  The equivalent Irish figures are 1,600 vessels and 36,000 tonnes respectively.  The Spanish fleet represents 70 per cent of the Community fleet at present.  Spain also has the largest <i>per capita</i> consumption of fish in Europe, 40 pounds annually as against 12 pounds in Ireland.  In 1983 total fish landings in Spain amounted to 1.1 million tonnes, as against Irish landings of 200,000 tonnes. Spain imports about 270,000 tonnes of fish a year and exports 200,000 tonnes. The Spanish home consumption of fish is in the region of 1.2 million tonnes a year. Spain has a number of third country agreements and because of their need for fishing opportunities they have about 20 international agreements along the west coast of Africa, Canada and the United States.  They have about 106 joint ventures whereby they import up to 200,000 tonnes of white fish through these joint ventures alone, the equivalent of our total fish catch.  That is an aspect of entry that has to be very carefully gone into.</P>
    <P>In the Minister's speech he mentioned that the main element of the agreement with Spain and Portugal is that no Spanish vessel will be allowed inside the Irish box in the period from 1985 to 1995.  In the past 12 months, even though no Spanish fishing boat is allowed in, over 50 Spanish skippers have come before the courts and have been convicted of illegally fishing off Ireland.  I do not presume that this figure will lessen when the accession of Spain and Portugal is actually signed.  A basic list of 300 Spanish vessels will be authorised to fish in Community waters, excluding the Irish box, of which only 150 vessles of standard 700 horse power size on the periodic list will be allowed fish simultaneously in Community waters.  Of <Col N="1214" /> the 150 vessels on the periodic list, 93 will be allowed fish in the Irish 50 to 200-mile zone until December 1995.  Only 93 vessels of 700 horse power will be allowed to fish.  I would ask the Minister how many boats or ships we have in Ireland of 700 horse power in the total fleet.  I would not say there are any more than ten, yet we have 93 more coming in from Spain.</P>
    <P>The Spanish authorities, it is said, are committed to negotiations to secure an ordinary and phased access by Spanish boats to the Irish box after 1995.  They have made absolutely no attempt to supervise the boats that are fishing in Irish waters.  It must be said that many of the fishermen who come from Spain know the Irish fishing grounds as well as I know the road from Kilkenny to Dublin or the Leas-Chathaoirleach knows the road from here to Ennis.  They know every fishing ground in Ireland better than many of the Irish fishermen do.  They have been fishing here for the last 800 or 900 years and they head for their traditional fishing grounds.  Unless we are very careful in providing adequate servicing in terms of protection for our fishing industry we will be overrun in the next few years.</P>
    <P>The main problems we will have on the accession of Spain and Portugal are basically in the areas of agriculture and fishing.  Because of the different type of farming that goes on in Spain and Portugal, there will be an attempt to divert moneys from the northern countries, which are supported by CAP at present, into the southern countries, which are poor and which will need aid.  There will be a spreading out of the benefits of the CAP and the benefits to us will be diminished as a result.  The effect on our fishing industry could be catastrophic unless every attempt is made by the Community itself, by the Irish Government in particular and by the Spanish Government to ensure that our fish stocks are not decimated as feared by the fishermen and anybody who looks at the situation around our coast.</P>
    <P>We must be positive in our attitude.  It is without a doubt an opportunity for <Col N="1215" /> Irish industry to develop trade with Spain and Portugal.  There are trading arrangements that can be made.  Any extension of the Community must be of benefit to Irish manufacturers and exporters.</P>
    <P>We hope that the Spanish economy will be able effectively to survive its entry into the Community.  One of the very significant things that one notices when one travels in Spain and Portugal is the large number of people who are involved in service industries.  With the accession of these two countries to the EC, we can see that the cost of living will rise and there is no way they will be able to support the large numbers of people who are currently engaged in service industries.  I would fear that the same thing will happen in their traditional industries as happened here in the past ten years, that we will see an enormous number of new unemployed coming into the European scheme of things, who will have to be paid for by the European Community in general.</P>
    <P>We have had very long and very good relationships with Spain and Portugal.  It is significant that both countries have in the past few years become much more democratic in outlook.  They have moved away from the regressive regimes that they had and they are taking their place as full members of the world community. We welcome both countries into the European Community, but nevertheless have reservations about the benefits that will accrue to the Community and to the countries themselves by their accession.</P>
    <Speaker pid="CharlesBMcDonald" hpid="Mr. McDonald Mr. McDonald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McDonald</NameTxt>
      <P>I welcome this Bill to the House.  It is another significant step in the evolution of the European Community and a significant expansion in the family of European states that share the idealism of the people who founded the Community 25 or 30 years ago.  I listened with great interest to the speech of the Minister who, not only reminded the House of the plus factors but also mentioned the areas where more caution was needed.</P>
      <P>Senator Lanigan in his speech also touched on many of those problem areas.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="1216" /> I would like to welcome this further expansion of our European Community to embrace the ancient people of Spain and Portugal.  Their ancient and colourful cultures will certainly enhance a more united Europe.  It is eminently true that by laying down one brick after another we can together succeed in building something of lasting importance.  It must be equally true, however, that without a grand plan nothing of lasting greatness can be constructed.  It was Paul Henri Spaak who once said:</P>
    <P>He who never dreams can never construct anything of genuine importance. If yesterday's Europeans had been nothing more than realistic, nothing of that which today constitutes tomorrow's Europe would exist.</P>
    <P>We can expect a very positive, political, social and economic contribution from both Spain and Portugal to the EC, after 1 January 1986 when they will become full members.  I welcome our new partners and I wish them both well in their great task of adapting to what is for them a new situation and a difficult task, which the whole process of integration is.</P>
    <P>However, our Community has almost 30 years of experience of integration and co-operation which was started with the Six soon after the last European war. Despite many critics it has proved very successful and, in our own experience, very beneficial to ourselves and the other nine member states.  I look forward with great enthusiasm to the greater integration and harmonisation within the Community of our laws, our transport and of our taxation systems, especially in relation to direct tax bands so as to guarantee a greater degree of equality and fairer competition for our producers in the market place.</P>
    <P>I read recently where Spain had introduced the VAT system to bring their collecting system in line with that of the Community.  They have introduced three rates: 6 per cent, a standard rate of 12 per cent and another rate of 33 per cent. These rates replace 24 different taxes which were in use up to recently.  I expect <Col N="1217" /> that the new rates out there, while we can welcome them, may not be so readily welcomed by the Spaniards.  Their premier, Senor Gonzalez, is to be complimented on moving into the European system so promptly.  If we look, for example, at the Greeks &mdash; the latest to join the Community and now a member for the last five years &mdash; we find that they are asking for a further derogation from these VAT directives.</P>
    <P>It might be appropriate to stress that European Union must imply joint exercising of national sovereignty and all must work to eradicate the false concept of contradiction between common and national interests.  The hearts of the people of Europe must unite as well as the policies.  Our policies must continue to evolve in such a way as to reduce the imbalance between the poorer and the wealthier regions.</P>
    <P>Senator Lanigan touched on this topic. For my own part, as one who has studied, watched and was very much involved with the funding of the Regional Fund in 1974 and 1975, it is a disappointment that the regional policy, which in theory is a marvellous system and one which surely must hold out tremendous hope to people especially in the peripheral, disadvantaged or poorer regions, even though a considerable amount of money has been expended on it, has not altogether succeeded. For some extraordinary reason the imbalance between the richer and the poorer areas &mdash; the central wealthy triangle of Europe and the peripheral regions &mdash; is not getting smaller.  For that reason, in any reform of policies there must be greater examination of why despite the expenditure of considerable amounts of money via the Regional Fund, this does not reflect in the various national and regional statistics.</P>
    <P>In keeping an eye on the ordinary policies and day-to-day administration in Europe I am quite surprised that the Council of Ministers at one of their recent meetings proposed a reduction in the budget for the coming year of something like £31 billion.  This is some £4 billion or £5 billion less than what was originally <Col N="1218" /> suggested by the Commission.  At a meeting last week the European Parliament, in an effort at conciliation or mediation, have suggested 33 billion ECUs.</P>
    <P>I welcome the expansion of the Community not just because I see the possibility for us as producers, manufacturers or sales people to avail of the opportunities presented but also because I see two states coming in who just less than a decade ago did not enjoy living under democratic rule.  I am glad that people should come along when they got the opportunity of changing.  I am glad that the very few short years it has taken them to change to bi-cameral, democratic systems they have been able to reorganise not just their economies but their administration systems as to be able, with the aid of some derogation for teething purposes, to join the European Community as equal partners.  As Europeans we should be there to extend to them a helping hand and give them the benefits &mdash; economic, moral and social &mdash; that companionship in a Community such as ours must surely mean to them.  From that point of view we can, through closer working relationship in the Council of Ministers, in the Parliament and in the Commission, ensure henceforth, with the involvement of Europe, problems that may arise between member states will be argued out and will find solutions agreeable to all sides.  Therefore, we are indeed ensuring that, for the foreseeable future, Europe is going to be bathed in an atmosphere of significant peace.  It would be nice to think it was going to be all sunshine and all peace but nevertheless, by and large, as we move closer we are cementing and guaranteeing a peaceful existence within our Communities.</P>
    <P>I should like to see the European Parliament and the Turkish Assembly Joint Committee being reactivated and I should hope to see solid and continuing contacts being made with both the Republic of Cyprus and the Turkish Republic of Northern Cyprus, as it is my belief that only through political and diplomatic dialogue advancement towards peace and harmony can evolve.  Hopefully, the decision of the Parliament taken on 11 <Col N="1219" /> October last year to discontinue the joint committee will be reviewed early in 1986 because if we had that country included in our Community we would have a great European land mass where Governments would be working closely together in the interests of all the people in the entire region.</P>
    <P>I should like to ask the Minister if it has been decided what competences the new commissioners are going to be allocated. I read where Senor Manuel Marin has been nominated as one of the Spanish commissioners in the Community and I should like to ask the Minister if the name of the Portuguese commissioner designate has been announced yet.  From our point of view it is interesting to know the competences or portfolios that these people will be allocated.</P>
    <P>Over a number of weeks the House has allocated a considerable amount of time to debating European issues and Community issues and our Order Paper still has a great number of reports of the workings of our joint committee.  From that point of view, the House is devoting a considerable amount of time to the European Community.  That is as it should be because of the importance that the Community has in the lives of the ordinary citizen at present.</P>
    <P>The reforming of the Common Agricultural Policy is going at present and I see that the Commission have been working on reforming the cereal sector. This is a very important sector for a number of reasons.  I am quite surprised that the Commission should start on this particular sector and the implication is that there will be the introduction of quotas which would fall in line with the views of a new organisation in Ireland which is dedicated to removing the food mountains.  Since the cereal sector is the one source of food that can readily be transported and stock piled in the famine-stricken areas of Africa, I hope that the reforms will not go as far as eliminating that stockpile completely because that is the area where the Community can respond faster and more tellingly on behalf of people in the Africian regions <Col N="1220" /> especially those are experiencing famine situations.</P>
    <P>Expansion of the European Community has advantages both for the Community as a whole and for the individual member states and the various populations but we must also recognise that there will be disadvantages also.  It is good that we should be prepared for them. There will be some changes in the ordinary trading situation but, nevertheless, we have an obligation to maintain a balance and hopefully that will be in favour of our own people.  As far as Spain is concerned we can expect &mdash; at least in the long term &mdash; changes in the fisheries situation.  We have had long debates in this House on the fisheries sector.  The apprehensions of our fishermen and the people close to the fishing industry have been mentioned and debated in the House on many occassions.</P>
    <P>One thing that I should like to say to the Minister is that while I accept that the fishery negotiations have been very thorough and, from our point of view I think we can say, successful, nevertheless the experience would appear to be over the last year or two that the Spanish fishermen are either absolutely illiterate or have never had the opportunity of reading the agreements.  The last straw was when a Spanish boat attempted to attack or hole one of our fishery protection vessels.  I know that one swallow does not make a summer.  We are not all so law-abiding in this country as not to attempt to get away with whatever is possible but our hope is that our Government, heeding the interests of the national fishing resources and the fishing stocks, would be able to make available whatever national resources are necessary. We know from the fishery agreement that aid from the EC is available to us to provide fishery protection vessels and we hope our facilities will be increased to a level sufficient to give adequate protection for the proper and long term development of our fishing resources.</P>
    <P>I should like very briefly to impress on the Minister of State at the Department of Foreign Affairs the importance of the Community increasing the budget for the <Col N="1221" /> proper implementation of European policies in the enlarged member states. Greater resources will have to be made available through the Regional Fund to the social action programme.  It is important to recognise the Mediterranean problem and that the special funds that have been allocated to the Mediterranean basin region will now require significant inputs.  It is important that the Community should have a significant increase in its own resources.  The 1.4 per cent mentioned by the Minister must surely be inadequate now.  It is ten years since the target of 1 per cent of own resources was set.  In the last two years it has gone over the 1 per cent VAT.  I believe the suggested figure of 1.4 per cent is quite inadequate.  I accept that inflation is down right across the Community, which perhaps would mean some relief.  It is important that the Community should continue to go forward; it should not be allowed to stagnate for the want of finance.  The only way the community can be independent and can see the implementation of the the policies they want to try out is by having their own resources in order to pay for that exercise.</P>
    <P>The areas deserving of greater input would be the funds for the Mediterranean basin problem, the Regional Fund and some close examination or updating of transport policies.  The infuriating point about transport policies &mdash; I did spend a few years as President of the Transport Commission &mdash; is that the only movements which have been made in 27 or 28 years regarding transport policies have been in regulations governing drivers, such as the tachograph, some regulations on loading and perhaps a tightening up of some cross-border form-filling procedures. That in itself is absolutely useless. I understood that transport policies in Europe were going to assist in levelling out the difficulties, the expenses and the economics of producers, whether they are producing agricultural products or whether they are manufacturing consumer products.  I understood that all producers would be assisted, by means of a transport policy, to be able to put their <Col N="1222" /> produce on the central, lucrative and better markets of Europe without disadvantage on account of distance from the market place.  That has not happened. Now we are talking about a Community stretching from Greece to Spain and from Northern Ireland way down to the toe of Greece.  Ireland is one of the more difficult peripheral regions; we have two very expensive sea crossings if we want ready and prompt access to the Central European markets.  I do not know the Minister's view on the transport policy, but nevertheless the groundwork has been done more than 20 years ago and it has been stagnating ever since.  I do not know why it has never been introduced.</P>
    <P>The social action programme which President Hillery laid down so carefully, so thoughtfully and so well when he was commissioner in charge of it, has been of tremendous benefit especially to the younger population here and in all the underdeveloped areas throughout the Community.  In the poorer areas of Spain and Portugal there is, as everywhere else, a high percentage of unemployed, including unemployed young people.  Therefore, there will be a heavier demand on the Social Fund.  It is setting off on the wrong foot to expand the Community without providing adequate funding for the programmes which the Community has developed and which are ready for implementation.</P>
    <P>Also, we have the problem of industrial expansion and renewal, especially in Portugal. Here again, I would hope that the Community would be generous with those countries.  It is important that they should see as early as possible significant benefits to the ordinary citizen in the street by virtue of their countries having joined the European Community which has to be perceived by the various electors and voters as a great and lasting and inspiring institution for all of us to enjoy.</P>
    <P>I give this Bill a very sincere welcome. I am not looking at the problem with rosetinted glasses.  I know that if we work at it hard enough our efforts in this direction can only lead to an improvement in the regimes and in the living and working <Col N="1223" /> conditions of all of our people.  It is something that we cannot just accept and laud today: it is an area we must continue to work at.  We must be prepared to give and take.  The Government have an obligation to ensure that we as a country&mdash; listed by European standards in the various graphs and scales produced there about three quarter way down from the top &mdash; have aspirations to rise to at least middle level.  Our young people should be given hope.  Through the expansion of the Community and the building of a stronger European Economic Community there will be work and contentment for our whole population in the years ahead.</P>
    <Speaker pid="RoryKiely" hpid="Mr. Kiely Mr. Kiely">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Kiely</NameTxt>
      <P>I welcome the opportunity to speak on this legislation, the purpose of which is to seek approval from the Houses of the Oireachtas for the enlargement of the European Community in order to accommodate Portugal and Spain.  They have concluded their negotiations on the question of entry and they will become members of the EC on 1 January, 1986.</P>
      <P>This debate will provide us with an excellent opportunity to analyse the success or the lack of success of various European Community policies, how they affect us, how they fare today and how Ireland and the European Community will be affected by the addition of Spain and Portugal.  Spain and Portugal have as much right as any country to membership of the EC.  But we must ask ourselves the question; are we going to be better or worse off as a result of their inclusion in the Community?  Has there been sufficient homework done by our own Government and by the Community to date to provide for the welfare of member states even at present, let alone what is likely to happen when membership is increased?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>We must cast a critical eye at European Community policies.  There are several policies we could refer to but the European Regional Policy, I think, has failed. It has failed to prevent an increase in disparities between rich and poor regions <Col N="1224" /> and nations.  It is good to go out into the country and see certain projects funded by the European Regional Fund and to see that there is progress in our infrastructures. However, many of our roads are still in a poor state, especially our main roads.  The county roads and byroads are a lot worse.  Comparing the conditions of our roads, even since our entry into the EC, with that of roads and infrastructure of other countries we are very far behind the times.  This is a trend that will have to be rectified.  The EC should ensure that disparities between rich and poor regions are checked.</P>
    <P>The Regional Policy, with the Common Agricultural Policy, is one of the most important policies.  The Common Agricultural Policy accounts for approximately 42 per cent of the total European Community budget and the proportion for Ireland must be very relevant to the Community.  We must look at Spain and Portugal, especially Spain, with their growing populations as further outlets for our agricultural products.  We must look at the accession of these two countries from the point of view of third country agreements which will affect the Common Agricultural Policy.  The Common Agricultural Policy has been a success and is the cornerstone of agriculture of the Community.  It has given us a security of supply.  It has given Europe valuable international trade.  It has given us price stability and spectacular gains in agricultural products.  It has raised the standard of living of our farmers.  It is of definite benefit to the Community as a whole.  If agriculture is thriving, the whole economy benefits.</P>
    <P>The secrecy which surrounded the enlargement negotiations led to serious anxiety in many sectors of the economy. Have the implications of enlargement been put properly before us?  Have the Government done everything to see what the implications will be and how the enlargement will affect the Community and our own country?  The Government did very little by way of research.  I am sure there will be damage done to existing industries.  There may be opportunities for some other industries.  The tourist <Col N="1225" /> industry could benefit from the enlargement of the Community.  The development potential of the tourist industry must be considered in terms of closer liaison with Spain and Portugal.</P>
    <P>Enlargement of the Community will have a most detrimental effect on the fishing industry which is at present in a hopeless state.  I know that restrictions have been limited.  Restrictions have been negotiated, but are they sufficient to ensure the expansion of our industry? Prospects for expansion are, indeed, very limited.  That is the one fear this country has concerning the accession of Spain and Portugal to the European Community.  It will have a severe and damaging effect on the fishing industry.  I have a cutting from <i>The Irish Press</i> of Tuesday, 30 January. The heading is &ldquo;Barry says &lsquo;no&rsquo; to Spain's fish demands&rdquo;.  It says:</P>
    <P>Mr. Peter Barry, Minister for Foreign Affairs rejected Spanish demands for fishing rights in Irish coastal waters as soon as Spain joins the Common Market.</P>
    <P>On Monday, 11 February there was a heading: &ldquo;Spanish entry proposals &mdash; a sell out IFO&rdquo;.  It reads:</P>
    <P>The Irish Fishermen's Organisation yesterday strongly condemned the latest EEC fishery proposals for Spanish entry as a sell out to political convenience. The organisation in a statement, said the proposals do not contain a single safeguard to prevent a massive and uncontrolled invasion by Spanish vessels within the 200 mile limit.  The statement emphasised that Spanish vessels have no permanent rights within the 200 mile zone and that this position must be maintained, especially as these vessels have a total disregard for regulations of any kind. The IFO pointed out that the EEC was negotiating from a position of strength and called on the Irish Government to ensure that the fishing industry is not sacrificed in the negotiations.</P>
    <P>I would appeal to whoever is involved in negotiations to ensure that our fishing industry is safeguarded.  The people in <Col N="1226" /> that industry are very concerned.  Anybody who is familiar with the Spanish fleet will know what damage can be done as regards fishing illegally.  They resist arrest and they cause trouble to the Navy and whoever else is responsible for ensuring that illegal fishing is not taking place. They will definitely overfish our waters and, given an opportunity, will fish in other waters.  The Spanish fleet represents 75 per cent of the entire fleet in the European Community.  They have 17,500 vessels with a 750,000 tonne capacity, compared with 1,600 vessels in Ireland with a capacity of 3,600 tonnes. While I do not visualise the entire Spanish fleet working off our shores, if 500 vessels worked off them they could do immense damage to our fishing industry.  They have engines of 700 horse power compared with our vessels which have only engines of 20 horse power at the maximum or usually between 15 and 16 horsepower.</P>
    <P>I do not know whether the Minister for Foreign Affairs or the Minister for Fisheries whose participation in the Spanish accession negotiations is occasional, have full knowledge of the damage that the accession of Spain and Portugal will do to our fishing industry.  I would appeal to them to ensure that our fishing industry will be safeguarded.  I hope, by the enlargement of the Community through the accession of Spain and Portugal, that we will prosper in areas such as tourism and agriculture.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JimHiggins" hpid="Mr. J. Higgins Mr. J. Higgins">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J. Higgins</NameTxt>
      <P>I will not detain the House very long.  I would just like to add a few comments to what has been said already.  The first thing I would like to say is that when the business of negotiation for Spanish and Portuguese entry to the Community started the most popular thesis bandied around among Community member states, and within this country, was that it would be far better for the Community to put its own house in order, to consolidate and develop its own resources and then to take on board the idea of further development, particularly taking in two countries such as Spain <Col N="1227" /> and Portugal, both expecting to draw substantial funds from the EEC, from which we are large scale beneficiaries.</P>
      <P>Like other Senators, I welcome the Bill.  I welcome the accession of Spain and Portugal to the EEC.  Like Senator McDonald, not looking through rosetinted glasses, as good Europeans &mdash; and sometimes we are classed as being too good Europeans &mdash; we have to welcome two additional members despite the fact that in taking them on board we are taking the risks, hazards and challenges that this addition brings.  We can record our satisfaction and <i>cause célèbre</i> that it was during the six-month Irish Presidency that the most difficult area of negotiation in relation to accession was overcome. We owe a vote of congratulations to all the Ministers involved who as Presidents of their respective portfolios did a magnificent job: I mention in particular the Taoiseach, the Minister for Foreign Affairs and the Minister of State at the Department of Foreign Affairs for the manner in which they applied themselves to the task.</P>
      <P>Spain and Portugal are two countries which are valuable components in the new European Community; they are two countries which have a proud history; we will have two additional languages, which will pose a considerable threat for Irish members who have not been noted for their mastery of linguistic gymnastics. This is something which must be developed, because enlargement and consolidation at the same time, are a cause for jubilation and celebration.  We can justifiably celebrate that the land mass of the European Community has expanded to such a degree that it encompasses virtually all Western Europe with the exception of the Scandinavian countries.  These are exicting times and there are opportunities there for us.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>As a State which has a large fishing resource that is under-developed and where we have sat on our hands in relation to its development, it is not easy to take the membership of Spain without <Col N="1228" /> the consequent apprehensions and worries. Despite Senator Kiely's allegations that there was seen to have been a capitulation after a period of 12 days, the deal that was worked out ultimately was a good one.  It is a deal that protects our national interest and it strikes a balance between national and Community interests. The box deal adequately protects our coastline for 50 miles out.  The limited access afforded to Spain of 300 vessels, with a limited number of 150 which have a horse power of 700 or over, safeguards us adequately in terms of our national interest.</P>
    <P>At the end of the day the question that had to be answered in relation to Spain's accession was whether we could put our own national fishing industry at risk, with the minimal threats &mdash; in view of the fact that we were given a 50-mile limit, exclusively &mdash; or hold up accession of Spain and Portugal.  We have the best of both worlds: we have Spain and Portugal and we have the benefit of their membership. At the same time we have protected our national fishing interests.</P>
    <P>One of the factors which will become obvious when Spain and Portugal gain accession to the Community is the fact that Commissioner Sutherland will have to shed one of his areas of responsibility. We recall with some pride that he managed to wrest from the Commission the very valuable portfolio of Competition. This is an area in which he has gained an adequate mastery.  He was also given the added embellishment of the Social Affairs portfolio; this is one into which he has also thrust himself with the necessary dynamism and imagination.  Because of the accession of Spain and Portugal there will have to be a redeployment and redistribution of areas of responsibility.  We retain the confidence that Commissioner Sutherland will have the main area of responsibility, which is Competition.</P>
    <P>The emphasis has been on the dangers of accession from our national viewpoint. The fishing industry has been discussed exhaustively here and in the other House. This is also an era of opportunity.  We are opening up a vast new reservoir of markets &mdash; a market into which we can <Col N="1229" /> gain entry in time if we apply ourselves with the necessary confidence and determination. We are also in the process of seeing new development within the Regional Fund, which is the concept of integrated planning.  Heretofore, it was the practice within the Regional Fund to allocate funds to specific isolated projects. The new development of the promotion of integrated plans, balancing all the various components within particular regions and areas, rather than isolated projects, is a far more sensible approach. It can be recorded with satisfaction that in County Mayo there is, as a result of a visit some time ago of the Director General of the EC Regional Fund, Dr. Pierre Matheisson, and an ongoing high-powered study group, an undertaking regarding the formulation of an integrated plan. We are hopeful, when such a plan is presented to the Department of Finance, that it will receive the necessary encouragement and <i>imprimatur</i> in order to have it brought further afield for adoption by the EC Regional Fund.</P>
    <P>The Dooge and Spinelli reports have been debated at length at Committee level in this House.  They have been debated in the other House also.  The broad thrust of both documents is that we are moving towards the creation of a United States of Europe.  We welcome anything which breaks down barriers &mdash; tariff barriers, prohibitions or misunderstandings. The more fusion there is, the better it is from the point of view of the long term prospects for the survival of the Community.  We hope that the broad thrust of the Treaty of Rome in relation to achieving an equilibrium and an equality of resources within the Community and an equal distribution of resources, will diminish the glaring disparities within the Community.  Various bodies have done great work but we have got to address ourselves to these problems. Just as the United States of America, which have a far longer existence than the United States of Europe, have their disparities, and just as there is poverty on the slopes of the Appalachian Mountains while a few thousand miles away there is the staggering wealth of California, so <Col N="1230" /> also within this Community we have similar problems which have to be addressed.</P>
    <P>The word &ldquo;impetus&rdquo; was used by Senator Lanigan, despite his reservations in relation to Spanish and Portuguese entry.  The word &ldquo;impetus&rdquo;is the word we should be looking at.  Hopefully, the old idea, which for a while seemed to be very much in vogue, and reflected disillusionment by the stronger, longer-established European States, that we should move towards a two-tier Europe, will now be scotched.  Hopefully the entire Community will move in tandem and in unison towards a greater sense of convergence, unity and coherence.</P>
    <P>Senator Lanigan and Senator Kiely mentioned that the Common Agricultural Policy would be under severe threat. Senator Kiely reiterated something which the leader of his party stated some time ago when addressing an IFA conference, that this Government should set down a balance sheet of the advantages and disadvantages that we expected as being part and parcel of our commitment to Europe.  We have done this already. The record of the Government in relation to defending national interests at European level is of paramount importance. It stands unparalleled and unrivalled.</P>
    <P>We consider with pride the stand taken by the Ministers for Agriculture, the Minister for Foreign Affairs and the Taoiseach, when it came to threatening a vital national interest in relation to the superlevy negotiations.  When the negotiations were at a critical stage, reluctantly as the three Ministers in question took that stand, they were forced to withdraw until such time as there were adequate concessions in relation to the derogation. The derogation of 4.6 per cent which was subsequently granted made it the envy of the rest of Europe and, in particular, the envy of our peers north of the Border who did not get this derogation because of their participation within the United Kingdom.  There is no need for anyone on any side of the House to have apprehensions or worries in relation to the Common Agricultural Policy.  There are certain minimum price options and lines <Col N="1231" /> to be adopted when one enters a particular arrangement.  I am sure that it is the policy of the Government that the minimum price for participation of our country in Europe in retention of the Common Agricultural Policy and, hopefully, the retention also of price supports.</P>
    <P>The West is an area which is very often described as a disadvantaged area.  Just as we have disadvantaged and severely handicapped areas in Ireland such as our mountainous perimeter, so also areas of Spain will have similar problems.  We note in relation to the West that one area in France was granted a concession over and above the rest of the Community. That is the Cantal region on the slopes of the Auvergne Central Plateau.  This area was granted the concession.  It is one that Spanish membership will bring very much into vogue and focus, with the consequent aspirations on the part of Spain and Portugal that some of their mountainous regions might also be classified.  The point at issue is that the Cantal region of France is granted special concessions in relation to grants, infrastructural and otherwise, by virtue of the fact that it is on a very high plateau, and that because of its high altitude, it suffers consequent handicaps in relation to a shorter growing period.</P>
    <P>I validly make the point that the West of Ireland suffers similar handicaps, admittedly not through excessive altitude but because of rock formation, low permeability of soil, rapid transpiration, <i>et cetera.</i> It has been proven, and proven conclusively, by a well-established survey and study undertaken by north Connacht farmers that, in fact, the growing season &mdash; the number of daylight hours and the hours of sunshine <i>et cetera</i> in the West of Ireland &mdash; are shorter than those which pertain and operate within the Cantal. We hope that the submission which is made by the Government to the European Commission regarding reclassification will be followed up.  A document went forward with a view to having certain areas reclassified as disadvantaged areas.  That was successful and we hope that the other document, which is the one in relation to reclassification of regions in <Col N="1232" /> the West of Ireland will be followed up and pursued to its logical conclusion.  I think we can do so without apologies to anybody.  We are the most insular and the most handicapped and disadvantaged country in terms of distance within the Community.  Might I say, because of our more than spirited advocacy of the European Community, the Community can justifiably, without fear of assault from other areas for similar concessions, grant this concession to the West of Ireland.</P>
    <P>We have handicaps in the west.  For example, anybody could have noted this year that despite the fact that we had a boom year, tourism-wise, and that we seem largely to have overcome the apprehensions and worries of people in relation to safety from the point of view of the Northern troubles, the West of Ireland did not have the boom year that other areas had.  The ferries do not come to the West of Ireland.  We have, at this point in time, the embryo of an airport, but it has been noted that the buses come to Bunratty, they do the Ring of Kerry and go back down to the Minister's constituency, and the tourists take off from Cork to Roscoff or Le Haver.</P>
    <P>I again make a plea that the submission that has been made by our Government and by the Minister for Agriculture for reclassification for Western portions of Ireland should again be followed up with vigour.</P>
    <P>Again, I conclude where I started by saying that as good Europeans we should be more than grateful for the fact that we have taken in two countries which I am sure will prove an embellishment to the already decorated crown of Europe.</P>
    <P>Debate adjourned.</P>
    <P>
      <i>Sitting suspended at 5.30 p.m. and resumed at 6.30 p.m.</i>
    </P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Charter of Travellers' Rights:" RHead="Motion (Resumed)">
    <Title>Charter of Travellers' Rights: Motion (Resumed).</Title>
    <P>Debate resumed on the following motion:</P>
    <P>That Seanad Éireann welcomes the Charter of Travellers' Rights adopted by the National Council for Travelling <Col N="1233" /> People on November 11, 1984 and calls on the Government, to introduce as a matter of urgency, the administrative and legislative reforms demanded by the Charter.</P>
    <P Just="Right">&mdash; (Senator B. Ryan.)</P>
    <Speaker pid="JohnFDonnellan" hpid="Minister of State at the Department of Health (Mr. Donnellan) Minister of State at the Department of Health (Mr. Donnellan)">
      <NameTxt>Minister of State at the Department of Health (Mr. Donnellan)</NameTxt>
      <P>When I spoke last Wednesday evening I joined with Senators Ryan and McGuinness in welcoming the charter as a useful yardstick to measure progress towards travellers' full participation in society.  I made the point, however, that many of the principles enunciated in the charter have become part of Government policy, particularly the recognition of the distinct identity of travellers and their right to pursue a nomadic lifestyle if they so wish. Important steps have also been taken to ensure that travellers are consulted about policies which affect them and to encourage them to speak out about their situation.</P>
      <P>The Department of Health are particularly concerned about the health of travellers. Travellers are entitled to, and do receive, medical services; but evidence suggests that they do not make full use of the preventive health services.  It is not so much a question of providing special services for travellers as of positive action to ensure that they receive the services to which everyone is entitled.  To this end my Department made funds available to the Eastern Health Board for a mobile clinic, which visits traveller encampments to encourage mothers to attend antenatal examinations in the maternity hospitals and to offer vaccinations and developmental screening of young children.</P>
      <P>The clinic is staffed by two public health nurses and public health doctors attend as required.  The Clinic began work in July of this year and I am glad to say that already the clinic has proved its worth.  In one three day period alone, 164 children were vaccinated.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>There is, however, one note of caution which I must sound.  There is, unfortunately, an inherent conflict between the traditional travelling way of life and the <Col N="1234" /> attainment of the highest standard of health.  Travellers who wish to maintain a nomadic way of life have no option but to live in caravans.  The Review Body on Travelling People pointed out in 1983 that even the best appointed caravan is not suitable as permanent accommodation for a large family, particularly in the Irish climate.  Even when parked on a site with proper amenities, a caravan has many drawbacks.</P>
    <P>The overcrowding, lack of proper sleeping accommodation and poor ventilation associated with a large number of people living permanently in a caravan constituted, in the review body's opinion, a continuing hazard to the health of the occupants.  The price of continuing the traditional traveller way of life may be a lower level of health among the families concerned.</P>
    <P>Although I am not a lawyer, it seems to me that the principles listed under article 6 of the charter concerning the family are too broad and do not sufficiently take into account the rights of others in the society.  Article 6.3, for example, would declare illegal any measures aimed at forcing travellers to move on against their will.</P>
    <P>I would suggest that this should be qualified to the extent that traveller families should not be moved unless they are provided with suitable, alternative accommodation.  A blanket prohibition on any movement of travellers from any place they choose to park could interfere with the rights of other citizens and be against the best interest of the community.</P>
    <P>No discussion of rights, we are told is complete without reference to the accompanying duties.  If society is to recognise travellers' rights, travellers will be expected to accept certain duties in return.  The duties of citizenship are not always easy, particularly for those who up to now have only acknowledged the discipline of the road.  The best way of tackling fear and prejudice against travellers is to show that there is no grounds for such attitudes.  Integration, as the review body commented is a two-way process, involving give and take on both sides.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="1235" /> The charter draws attention to a number of issues where travellers rights may need to be protected by law.  In particular there is a need for legislation to outlaw discrimination by private individuals against travellers for no other reason than that they are travellers.  Such discrimination takes place in the work place, in public houses, hotels, dance halls, and cinemas.  At present travellers have no legal redress against such practices nor have travellers any remedy against public attacks on them as a group or propaganda designed to stir up hatred against them.</P>
    <P>My Department and the monitoring committee are concerned about the absence of statutory protection for travellers as a group and have made representations to the Departments of Justice and Foreign Affairs about measures necessary to remedy the situation.  Those Departments are involved in examining the implications for Ireland of ratifying the United Nations Covenant on Economic, Social and Cultural Rights and the Covenant on Civil and Political Rights. As far as travellers are concerned, what is required is that any anti-discrimination legislation necessary to ratify the above covenants and the Covenant on the Elimination of all forms of Racial Discrimination should be broad enough to cover attacks on, or discrimination against, travellers.  Senators can be assured that my Department will continue to pursue the interest of travellers in this matter. Senator Ryan, when he was speaking last week, claimed that discrimination against travellers takes place at unemployment exchanges.  If discrimination exists against travellers solely on the grounds that they are travellers, then it should be eliminated.  This is a matter which the monitoring committee should examine with the assistance of the Department of Social Welfare.  I will ensure that it is brought to their attention.</P>
    <P>It is time to say a bit more about the monitoring committee, which was established under the aegis of the Minister for Health to review progress towards the implementation of the Government <Col N="1236" /> policy statement on travellers of July 1984.  Travellers and persons who speak on their behalf make up the majority on the committee.  The committee have just completed their first year's work, a period during which much has happened of benefit to travellers.  In education and training, for example, progress has been particularly marked, although much remains to be done.  The impetus to increase educational opportunities for travellers children, based on principles such as those listed under article 7 of the charter, has resulted in more pre-schools, better attendance at primary schools and a growth in the number attending secondary schools.</P>
    <P>Most encouraging has been the success of the training centres for travellers which now provide 571 places, an increase of 43 per cent on the number provided in 1984. The centres help to compensate young travellers with inadequate primary education and to give them the skills to earn a living and participate fully in society. Senators may have heard about the recent celebration in Galway when over 500 travellers from the training centres throughout the country came together to share their experiences.  It was by all accounts a most successful day.  Thanks to the monitoring committee, pressure is being maintained on those bodies with responsibility for different aspects of travellers welfare, and the progress made in accommodation, education, training and health is in no small measure due to their persistence.  I hope they will continue the good work and be able to report further progress this time next year.</P>
    <P>There are many worthwhile aspects of this charter that I have not mentioned, not because I do not consider them important but because they have in general my wholehearted agreement.  I am thinking particularly of the articles dealing with economic needs and political rights.  I would ask Senators to recognise the many positive developments which have taken place in policies and services for travellers in recent years, without minimising the scale of what remains to be done.  I see this charter as both the <Col N="1237" /> indicator of the best thinking about travellers' rights and a signpost for the way forward.  I ask Senators to accept the Government's good faith as far as policies and services for travellers are concerned.</P>
    <Speaker pid="RoryKiely" hpid="Mr. Kiely Mr. Kiely">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Kiely</NameTxt>
      <P>I would like to say a few words on this motion.  We are all concerned with travellers and would like to see them treated equally.  Fianna Fáil, in their local government manifesto, are committed to bettering the lives of the travelling people.  It is their belief that supervised halting sites should be provided for travelling people with no more than five families per site.  These sites should be properly maintained, supervised and financed from central funds. Local authorities will be encouraged to provide special housing and give special attention to the health and educational needs for children.  It also calls for a renewed effort to address the problems of the travelling people and the areas in which they have settled.  Therefore it must involve local communities as well as central agencies in the solution of what Fianna Fáil see as a national problem.</P>
      <P>The settled community activists who wish to solve this problem claim that there is an inadequate standard of health among travellers.  This includes food, clothing, accommodation and medical care.  These services are not always available to the travelling people.  They say their physical, social and environmental conditions are not acceptable.  They seem to forget that every person in the State has an equal right and access to all the services made available by the State. Those who wish to solve this problem feel all travellers are left short-changed when it comes to State services.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>There are some travellers who say they have never asked for help and that they do not need help.  These are middle class travellers some whom are very well off. They have their own way of life.  They may deal in scrap, furniture, carpets, fuel and so on.  I see these people doing very well in my own area.  They provide their own houses from their own resources from dealing profitably in these trades. They also have an itinerant way of life <Col N="1238" /> but that is because it suits their mentality. They are not short of material wealth but because of their way of life they have not had the need to be literate and find it very difficult to locate services when they need them.  These include the poor, the sick and the young travellers.  That is a barrier that needs to be sorted out.</P>
    <P>Every citizen of the State should have access to the services of the State.  This weakness applies not only to travellers but also to many of the settled community. Because of red tape, people have difficulty in finding out their rights and then obtaining them.  This problem applies to a certain group of travellers. The travelling community get sick, grow old also and are no longer able to care for themselves.  It should be taken into account that they are itinerants and ought to be made more conversant with what is available to them then perhaps the settled community who have come across the rules and regulations during their settled existence.</P>
    <P>The notion that the fixed community have all the advantages because of their fixed, non-itinerant style of life and that the travelling style of life creates a disadvantage for these people when they need to avail of different services is wrong. There is an ostrich-type approach to this problem because the fixed community is riddled with insecurity, lawlessness, with serious breakdown in mental and physical care, where drug abuse is rampant, where moral principles that used to apply no longer apply and where marital fidelity is not as widespread as it used to be.  Those are the kind of conditions we offer as an alternative way of life to the travelling community.  Are they the type of conditions we would like to offer to them?</P>
    <P>The morals of the travelling community are very high.  There are very few pregnancies outside of marriage.  There is very little infidelity between husband and wife.  I am sure that Senator B. Ryan had no request from the travelling community that a referendum on divorce would be held in the lifetime of this Government.</P>
    <P>
      <i>(Interruptions.)</i>
    </P>
    <Col N="1239" />
    <Speaker pid="RoryKiely" hpid="Mr. Kiely Mr. Kiely">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Kiely</NameTxt>
      <P>Limerick County Council are doing what they can for the travelling community.  They find it difficult because of objections from farmers and so on. Any reasonable people who find travelling people reasonable will accept them. There is a halting site in Rathkeale where many rich members of the travelling community can afford to build their own houses.  There are 60 families housed in the settled community.  They were housed at the same time and are acceptable to one another.  There are 48 families parked illegally on the roadside.  They park on hard shoulders and grass margins and will not be asked to leave unless they cause trouble to neighbours and farmers. If suitable housing is provided they might like to be housed locally.  Many travelling families established in the community are acceptable.  They do not cause any litter problems in County Limerick.  I was told that there are two families living on a main road from Limerick to Killarney, the main road to Kerry near Croagh, who keep the place very tidy, and there are never any litter problems there.  They are very much accepted by the local community.</P>
      <P>The big problem is that travellers would like to have more halting sites. Land was offered, but because of objections the council had to decline buying it. I would like to mention one man, a former inter-county footballer.  I do not know whether Senator Deenihan would know him or not.  He is Basil Fitzgibbons of Askeaton, who some years ago offered three sites to the council for tigeens for these travelling people.  They built them, despite local objection.  Recently they demolished the tigeens and built more permanent housing for those itinerants. We need more people like that man who would accept these people.  They are all human beings and that should be the approach.  If the settled community could live with them and not have serious objection to them, they would find them acceptable.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>State involvement is needed, and needed urgently.  I would propose a simple modest programme.  Carry out a simple head count county by county all <Col N="1240" /> in one day, categorise the social positions within the travelling community, use existing structures to provide assistance where it is needed, have attached to each local authority extra social workers whose sole duty would be to identify areas of need within the travelling community and provide the assistance available now.  I would like to pay tribute to the social workers in Limerick.  I do not think there are enough of them.  There are only two to cater for the needs of the travellers and I would like to compliment them on the great work they are doing. This is an area where there should be more social workers employed to inform the travelling people of their rights, especially as regards social welfare, education and health.  I would say the most important thing would be not to condone any form of anti-social behaviour which comes from travelling communities. However, I think we have more anti-social behaviour from the settled community at present.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MaryRobinson" hpid="Mrs. Robinson Mrs. Robinson">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Robinson</NameTxt>
      <P>I, too, welcome this motion and in particular the fact that it gives the Seanad an opportunity to discuss the charter of travellers rights.  Indeed, it has already performed an important function in ensuring that a copy of this charter is available to and read by Members of the House, in particular by Members who are taking part in this debate.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I participated in part of the process that led to the adoption of this charter. It was, as is clear from the back of it, adopted by the National Council for Travelling People in November last, on 11 November 1984.  Prior to that, in June 1984, I took part in a meeting in Galway which centered on the draft charter as it was at that stage.  It was a very useful meeting, a very valuable day long discussion which brought together lawyers and academics as well as members of the National Council, who, of course, included a number of travellers.  It was a very healthy discussion.  There was some difference of view as to how the rights should be represented in the charter.  I would like to take the opportunity to say <Col N="1241" /> that the final version of the charter, as adopted, is a simpler, more direct and a better balanced and reasoned document than was the draft charter.  Therefore, it did benefit from a wide discussion process and from a very significant input from travellers through the consultation which occurred and through the National Council for Travelling People.</P>
    <P>I am going to come to the charter in such detail as I can in the time available to me.  First of all, it might be useful to stand back a bit from this charter and to ask ourselves the question why we need a charter for a section of our population. After all, we have the Constitution of 1937, so why should we need a charter? Before turning to answer that question, when we look at the position of the travellers in our community we are immediately confronted by one of the most telling indictments of our society.  We call ourselves a Christian people.  We call ourselves a family centred people.  We pride ourselves on subscribing to basic values in our society.</P>
    <P>We cannot deny now that we do not know about the problem because it has been examined, studies and reported on. The latest full report was the report in February 1983 and there is now a monitoring committee, as the Minister has said.  We know in detail the appalling deprivation that is suffered by the travelling people in our community &mdash; the most basic deprivation.  Hundreds of children have no form of schooling and are growing up illiterate in our society.  Mothers have inadequate child care to the point where the mortality rate is much higher than for the settled community, to the point where children suffer far more from early childhood diseases, where the birth weight of children is significantly below the average birth weight for the settled community and so on.  The most basic indicators, the most appalling deprivations of access on any sort of terms of equal opportunity, equal access to the basic rights in our society, are denied at the moment to the travelling community.</P>
    <P>Anybody who tries to say that this is not the case has not looked at the reports, the official reports which have been <Col N="1242" /> accepted by the Government and which have still not been adequately acted upon, nor have they listened to social workers and those who work in the educational sphere with the travelling community who have documented over and over again the extent of the deprivation. We should be &mdash; I do not want to be emotional about this &mdash; ashamed of ourselves, because the evidence is there.  We know it, but we somehow have a blindness about it.  We are not willing to see the necessity for a concerted programme to redress the injustice, the unfairness, the discrimination, the deprivation which has endured through the years of our independence and of our sovereignty as a people.  It is about time that we decided to do something about it.  For that reason I believe that this charter will be helpful at a number of different levels that I want to come to.</P>
    <P>Let me first say that it is a very interesting charter, even from a legal point of view.  It is an interesting charter because it serves two purposes.  First of all, it reminds us &mdash; and we need reminding &mdash; that travellers are entitled to be treated as individuals with the same fundamental rights as every other citizen in our society.  The children and the adults have the same fundamental rights and are entitled to the same access to the benefits of our society as any other citizens.  That is the first point.  As I said earlier, it seems strange that we actually have to produce a charter to affirm this because, of course, the Constitution of 1937 affirms it in its language; but we do not affirm it, as I say, in reality.</P>
    <P>A second purpose of this chapter is to affirm that travellers are a distinct minority group in the country.  They share, in addition to being citizens, a different way of life.  They share a common historical background which has been researched in recent years and shows the distinctiveness of this historical background and the culture associated with that background.  It has given the travelling people a distinct social and cultural ethos.  Therefore, we have a minority which on any normal scale at international level, when talking about <Col N="1243" /> international human rights, would claim the right to respect for that minority as a community and for their way of life, which should not be impeded, obstructed, denied or denigrated either openly or by insinuation.  Moreover, it is not just a passive approach.  A country should not simply passively tolerate a distinctive minority within it.  It is enriched by the fact that there is a minority with a distinctive culture and social ethos. Therefore the response should be one of an affirmative protection for that way of life.</P>
    <P>It may be that special measures are necessary &mdash; for example, measures of support which would ensure equal access to education, housing, training and health care.  I hope that the Minister was not implying that there has to be some radical change before there can be adequate access to these basic rights in our society.  It is not that the travelling community have totally to change their whole approach.  It is that we as a population have to ensure that we are providing, in a way that is sensitive to the community of the travelling people as a minority deserving our respect, adequate access to the kind of rights we are talking about.</P>
    <P>What is the purpose to be served by the charter in so far as it not only sets out the individual rights of the travelling people as citizens of the State but also their rights as a minority, their collective rights of a cultural and social nature? The charter serves a number of purposes. Firstly, it raise consciousness about these rights.  It is a new way of looking at the travelling community, a very different from the normal denigrating or ignoring, whether openly or covertly, the position of travellers, who are by no means always called &ldquo;travellers&rdquo;.  We have a whole Richter scale of terminology in relation to the travelling people, depending on the context and nature of the conversation. It very often happens, if travellers, for example, wish to buy a drink in a public house or use a bus or do any of the normal things we take for granted as a settled community, that they find they are not <Col N="1244" /> even referred to as &ldquo;travellers&rdquo; but referred to in a very different way.  They are denied basic rights again and again.</P>
    <P>It is necessary to change attitudes.  One way of changing attitudes is to have this consciousness, a very positive awareness, not just of the individal rights but of the position of a cultural minority in our country.  By discussing this charter today I hope we will play our part in raising consciousness of the nature of those rights and what we must do about it.</P>
    <P>Secondly, this charter performs an educational function.  It is a way of stimulating a better debate abut the broader aspects &mdash; educational and health care &mdash; in all kinds of different sectors and levels in our society.  For example, it would be very valuable if this chapter were discussed in schools.  It should be something which is discussed by childern both at national and secondary levels so that they have a greater awareness and appreciate not just the individual rights but also the culture associated with the travelling people.  By gaining that understanding and recognising it they learn a tolerance which is the best way of breaking down the blindness and prejudice which is so widely diffused in our society and which children learn from their parents and their community.  There is no sense in our denying it or saying that it does not happen.</P>
    <P>The charter should be discussed widely in the trade union movement.  I am very pleased to see that there is active support for the rights of travellers.  It is appreciated that this is a proper area of involvement for the trade union movement and that it will grow and strengthen.  The trade union movement has a great contribution to make in this area.  It is only through very substantial, collective weight being brought to bear by the settled community through, for example, the trade union movement that we are going to get the necessary change both in attitudes and decisions based on them.</P>
    <P>There will have to be very tough decisions made in regard to housing, accommodation generally and other areas.  It is important that residents' <Col N="1245" /> associations and tenants' associations discuss this charter and look at the position of travellers from that perspective.  It is not the only perspective but one which until now we have very sadly neglected. It will increase the respect and open the eyes of people to what should be the position and the reality which runs contrary to that position.</P>
    <P>A third function the charter serves is as a framework for action.  Hopefully, it will be used by the travellers themselves to seek recognition of their rights.  They will have this as a basis for pursuing those rights, as they are entitled to do as citizens by the normal means open to citizens and as a last resort pursuing them if necessary by legal action where appropriate. The law has served a very limited purpose but it has at least served as a form of shield against the worst oppression, by officialdom very often.  There is a more positive dimension to law and hopefully that also can be used.</P>
    <P>Finally and most importantly, the charter is also addressed to the Houses of the Oireachtas, to Government and to each local authority as a basis for implementing policy.  I will make a number of comments on that as I am running short of time.  I would hope that every local authority in the country would debate this charter.  I hope that this debate will be reflected on each local authority by putting this charter on the agenda and having a debate on it.  That is where the issue needs to be discussed and debated on the ground.  If that happens we will have less of the kind of lip service paid and a more genuine approach to recognising the individual and community rights of this minority who are deprived in our society.</P>
    <P>I should like to discuss the substance behind this charter.  This is a charter of rights, but the rights in question are the basic needs of men, women and children. I urge Senators to accept, since we can only make progress from there, that we deny to a minority within our people equal access and equal treatment in relation to basic health care, educational opportunity, housing and other needs in our society and that this demands redress.</P>
    <P>We champion the human rights of <Col N="1246" /> people in other countries, in South Africa and Central America, and that is quite right.  We champion the basic needs, the right to life, the right to food and shelter of deprived populations in parts of Africa.  We have all of this on our own doorstep.  We deny all these rights in some measure or other and in some instances to a quite flagrant degree within our own jurisdiction and it is about time we acted upon it.</P>
    <P>I hope the debate on this chapter at national and at local level will ensure that the Government meet the commitments which they have assured us they will be addressing in this regard.  The National Council for Travelling People have looked for a statutory body.  Is that going to be established and, if so, when?  When are we going to see the precise addressing of the particular problems and genuine progress on them?  When are we going to get away from politicking?  We should not be under any illusion on this.  A very bad step was taken by the Dublin County Council, in the name of apparent progress, by going back to the drawingboard. It is very interesting to see who dissented from that vote in Dublin County Council. That reveals a lot of the merits of that measure but it does mean for the travelling families in the greater Dublin area potentially a longer wait for the settled community to face up to their responsibilities.</P>
    <P>It is difficult to say anything in the brief time allotted but I welcome the debate. I commend the Senators who tabled it and I hope it will be reflected in other arenas around the country over the next year.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JimmyDeenihan" hpid="Mr. Deenihan Mr. Deenihan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Deenihan</NameTxt>
      <P>I join other Senators in welcoming the motion.  Although considerable progress has been made as regards the housing of itinerants, there is a long way to go with regard to proper health standards for itinerants and proper educational facilities.  The Minister referred to the health of travellers.  Over the years the travellers have not been looked after sufficiently and in most cases have been neglected.  As he and Senator Robinson pointed out, there is a very high <Col N="1247" /> mortality rate among young travellers. Hepatitis, gastroenteritis, pulmonary diseases and kindney problems are very prevalent.  Travellers age very quickly and it is rare to see old itinerants along the side of the road.  I am glad the recent initiative by the Eastern Health Board in providing a mobile unit has proved to be so successful.  The Minister should urge other health boards around the country to set up similar units if possible.</P>
      <P>Itinerants also suffer from a lack of education, as has been mentioned here by previous speakers.  Only 50 per cent of young travellers attend school regularly. Seemingly there is no apparent push by the Garda to enforce the School Attendance Act and young itinerants are left to wander around the streets without any attention.  However, it should not be the responsibility of the Garda to ensure that these young itinerants go to school.  The Department of Education should be allowed to appoint school attendance officers in all counties.  Very few travellers attend secondary and vocational schools, but this is improving and there have been exceptions.  I am glad that the training centres set up specially for itinerants have been so successful.  In a sense it is defeating the purpose because it is a form of segregated education.  In order to educate itinerants totally and to get them integrated with the community, it is important that they are educated with the community as much as possible. Segregated education only exaggerates the differences between the general population and the travellers.  The idea must be to integrate the itinerants as much as possible in our educational system without having to set up any special forms of education for them.</P>
      <P>The political involvement of itinerants was also mentioned.  Very few itinerants are actually registered to vote.  Those who are registered are sometimes exploited by politicians who pay them to vote for them, in some cases by voting illiterately.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnFDonnellan" hpid="Mr. Donnellan Mr. Donnellan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Donnellan</NameTxt>
      <P>I hope the Senator is not in that category.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1248" />
    <Speaker pid="JimmyDeenihan" hpid="Mr. Deenihan Mr. Deenihan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Deenihan</NameTxt>
      <P>I am not long enough in politics yet to get dirty about it.  Considerable progress has been made in the housing of itinerants.  In 1960 only 43 families were housed out of 1,198.  In 1980 this had increased to 957 out of 2,490 families.  This was a substantial increase and no doubt it has increased since.  Halting sites in general have also proved very successful.  Halting sites provide a necessary transitional period for itinerants to adapt eventually to living in houses.  Itinerants who have been taken from the roadside and put directly into houses have not adapted successfully in many cases.  It is important to have a transitional period.  Itinerants taken from the roadside should undergo some form of domestic education in order to ensure that when they are eventually living in houses they will be able to perform the normal duties.  In some cases itinerants find it very hard to adapt to doing the ordinary everyday jobs within a house.  It is important that before they are given the key to the house the various domestic duties are pointed out to them and it is made clear to them that they have a responsibility to keep the house tidy. When they get a house it does not mean they have a licence to destroy it, which happens a lot.  I do not blame the itinerants. I blame the people who put them into the houses without adequately preparing them.</P>
      <P>I agree with Senator Robinsom when she says that itinerants have been treated as second-class citizens and discriminated against for the past 60 years since the foundation of the State.  Indeed they have been a much denigrated and maligned group of people and they have been as exploited as the coloured people in America and in other countries.  All of us must share the same sense of guilt in this regard.  I mentioned to Senator Ryan this evening that we need a race relations Bill here to ensure that all discrimination is ended against minority groupings.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I would like to refer to the United Nations Sub-Committee on Prevention of Discrimination and Protection of Minorities who stated that the protection <Col N="1249" /> of minorities is the protection of non-dominant groups which, while wishing in general for equality of treatment with the majority, wish for a measure of differential treatment in order to preserve basic characteristics which they possess.  This amply applies to the itinerant people. We must allow them to some extent to continue with the customs they have come to live with and accept over the years.</P>
    <P>Senator Robinson referred to the ethos of the travelling people.  It is important that, as part of the overall culture of our country, this should be preserved.  They are a unique group of people and they have unique types of customs which we must not destroy by housing them.</P>
    <P>I feel very strongly that the travelling people must realise that they have responsibilities to the settled community. They must behave in a manner which is expected of everybody else and they cannot use the excuse that because they are travellers in some cases they break the law.  This must be spelled out to itinerants when they are being housed.  In some cases it is neglected.  It is not the fault of the travelling people but of the administrators, whether they are in the local authorities or the health boards.  We have an obligation to ensure that the travelling people are properly prepared and that they get the same chance as everybody else to become educated enough to form part of the settled community.</P>
    <P>I welcome the charter.  I sincerely hope &mdash; I am sure all the Senators share the same concern &mdash; that now at last we are getting somewhere regarding the settlement of itinerants.</P>
    <Speaker pid="BrendanRyan" hpid="Mr. B. Ryan Mr. B. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. B. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>I have to say initially that there are the best part of 20,000 travellers living in this country and most of them &mdash; whether they are settled or not &mdash; have been the victims of the most appalling discrimination and injustice.  There are, we are told on the other hand, about 70,000 victims of marital breakdown in Irish society.  When we debated the problem of marital breakdown we had an endless queue of speakers from both sides <Col N="1250" /> of the House who felt extremely concerned about this.  We got massive media coverage &mdash; myself included, which is why I feel free to make this statement. On the other hand we could not find sufficient speakers to fill the entire time of a three-hour debate, with limited contributions from Members, on a simple document which attempts to enunciate for the first time the rights of our travellers. The relative unimportance with which the rights of travellers have been treated by this House in comparison with the issue of marital breakdown underlines the depth of the need for a charter of rights for a minority who, notwithstanding their considerable numbers, are so insignificant in terms of political clout as to be almost dismissed, which is borne out by the fact that we will not even finish the time allowed for our debate.</P>
      <P>I quote a statement from <i>The Irish Times,</i> Friday, 21 December 1984, made by a representative of Minceir Misli:</P>
      <P>We are Irish people.  We share the same history, the same names.  We suffer the same as settled people do from the cold, the hunger.  We suffer illness and the struggle to make a living.  We differ from you only in terms of life style.  We are travelling people. We carry no shame for being such.  We make no apologies for our birth.  But we are treated in a most unjust manner in our own country.</P>
      <P>That is a statement by the people we are talking about.  I want to say again and again that we are not talking about a problem; we are not talking about a thing that is somehow abstracted into a problem which is going to be eliminated by services of a greater or lesser kind.  We are talking about people who see themselves as a community.  This charter contains a long list of rights.  It contains a list of 12 rights claimed by the travelling community.  As Senator Robinson has pointed out, all of those rights should not need to be written down because they should be taken for granted.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>In terms of the discussion in this House one would think the only right at issue was the right to accommodation.  We <Col N="1251" /> have had from a number of speakers a lot of information about the number of houses which have been built or the number of sites which have been constructed. If we constructed sites and houses for every single member of the travelling community and allowed the legal discriminations that exist against them in other areas &mdash; the double standards, the way the forces of the law treat them, the way local residents treat them, the way many politicians treat them, the way many of us in this House would treat them &mdash; then the provision of accommodation of itself would be of no great significance or assistance to the travellers. It is a much bigger issue than the provision of sites and houses.  I regret very much the emphasis on accommodation. Accommodation is tangible, measurable and, in a manner of speaking, easy to achieve because it is concerned with numbers and buildings.  There are many other rights.</P>
    <P>Secondly, I would like to mention the use of a large number of quite offensive expressions.  I believe in most cases this is done by omission rather than by commission. If we are talking about discrimination against the Jewish community in this country, if we are talking about discrimination against the residents of the Gaeltacht, nobody would presume to get up and give them lectures about rights, responsibilities, duties and the need to do this and that.  It appears that unique among minorities the travellers must always be treated to a lecture on their responsibilities whenever anybody dares to talk about their rights.  I regret it profoundly. I regret it in particular in a number of the speeches where quite extraordinary language was used about travellers, such as that some of them seem to prefer the side of a ditch and expressions like that.  Even if that were true &mdash; and I reject it &mdash; anybody with a sensitivity to the need to take care of and vindicate the rights of minorities would refrain from using that sort of language.</P>
    <P>It is because people will not refrain from using that sort of language, because <Col N="1252" /> the term &ldquo;itinerant&rdquo;&mdash; which the travelling community do not use to describe themselves &mdash; is still used, that we need not just goodwill but specific enforceable rights in all the areas we have talked about.  Those areas are the recognition of the minority, the recognition of the right to move and the right to stop, the recognition of the right to accommodation, of the right to have economic needs met, of the right to health, of the right to have their family rights protected, of the right to education, of the right to equality before the law, of the right to have political rights, of the right to have free expression, of the right to privacy and the right to non-discrimination.  They are the rights we are talking about, not just houses and sites but a whole range of rights.  It is in that context that some of the remarks made here during the debate need to be dealt with effectively.</P>
    <P>In particular, Senator Howard &mdash; a friend of mine I must say and a man I admire &mdash; used extraordinarily colourful language.  He said I made a generalised attack on the settled community and on local residents.  I have checked the record: I did not do any such thing.  I do not know why he thought I said it or whether he expected me to say something and when I did not say it he went ahead and said it anyway.  But Senator Howard asserted that in his own urban area they had housed 44 travelling families.  The most recent census of travellers in County Clare indicated that only 34 families had been settled in the entire county so, where these 40 families came from, I do not know.</P>
    <P>Travellers' rights need to be and must be vindicated, two travellers from Ennis have just spent some days in jail for refusing to pay a fine imposed as a result of a prosecution for illegally parking caravans. One of those travellers is aged 62 years an elderly gentleman who walked to members of this family for meals.  The urban council in Ennis proposed to relocate his caravan on a site two miles outside the town &mdash; this for a man who had not transport.  He refused to move; he was prosecuted for illegal parking and <Col N="1253" /> the expenses incurred by the local authority came to £60.  He could not pay it and he ended up in jail until members of the travelling community clubbed together to get the money to get him out. This is a traveller of 62 years of age in jail because he refused to move his caravan to a site two miles outside Ennis.  I say that simply to emphasise that even in areas where people perhaps believe a great deal is being done we really are a long way from treating people as equals.</P>
    <P>Talking about travelling people reminds me of the white minority in South Africa saying; &ldquo;Look what we have done for these people.  Look at how much more we have done and how much better off are the blacks in South Africa than anywhere else&rdquo;.  Many of our public representatives talk about how much better off the travellers are than they were 10 years ago.  They are still almost without rights and almost without any sort of position of equality in our society.  It is ironic that people talk a lot about the dirt created by travellers.  In <i>The Irish Times</i> of 25 February 1985 it was reported that travellers at Kissogue halting site in west County Dublin began a clean-up of the area on the previous Saturday in the hope that it would discourage members of the settled community from the prolific illegal dumping that is turning their area into a rural slum.  Here are travellers cleaning up their own site to try to get the settled community to stop dumping their rubbish there.  How many members of the Dublin County Council, T.D.s and Senators from Dublin city and county adverted to that fact, that the travellers are having rubbish dumped on them by members of the settled community?</P>
    <P>There is so much that needs to be said. The Minister's speech was full of interesting things though I have to say the fact that, unlike with many other issues, he had no script available to circulate to us and I have to work from notes, perhaps suggests that the issue was not given the priority that many others are given.  Normally we are assiduously supplied with Ministerial scripts but there were many good things in what he had to say.</P>
    <Col N="1254" />
    <Speaker pid="SeamusPattison" hpid="Minister of State at the Department of Social Welfare (Mr. Pattison) Séamus Pattison">
      <NameTxt>Minister of State at the Department of Social Welfare (Mr. Pattison)</NameTxt>
      <P>The Senator can be assured that the script of what I said will be given to him.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BrendanRyan" hpid="Mr. B. Ryan Mr. B. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. B. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>I thank the Minister.  It would have been much handier if I had it when he was speaking.  There are a number of things that need to be commented on.  I am very glad the Minister is working on anti-discrimination legislation but in referring to the monitoring committee, the Minister should be a little bit careful because that committee was in fact set up by the Government and those who are appointed to the monitoring committee were picked by the Government and do not represent anybody except themselves.  The National Council for Travelling People did not appoint nominees to the monitoring committee; the Government chose its own representatives and I would just like to draw attention to resolution passed at the Conference of the National Council of Travelling People in Cork last Sunday which called on the Government to enter into immediate negotiations with the national committee of the National Council and for the setting up of an effective body with statutory power to promote the welfare of travellers, to coordinate relevant programmes and to monitor implementation.</P>
      <P>That is a dramatic step forward by the National Council and I hope it is one that the Government will respond to, and let not the Minister simply tell me about the Housing Bill, because the Housing Bill empowers the managers to do things and I can quote now some documents about the behaviour of managers which suggest they are not going to do much.  The manager in my own County of Cork &mdash; I am not talking about the city, I am talking about the county &mdash; has spent the last three weeks wringing his hands about the fact that he cannot move travellers on because they are upsetting people.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>In the light of the fact that the Minister for Justice is allegedly going to do something about travellers' rights and anti-discrimination. I want to quote from the <i>Limerick Leader</i> of 12 October which <Col N="1255" /> talks about parents setting up a protest against travellers' caravans in their area, including withholding their children from school:</P>
    <P>Angry residents halted Limerick Corporation's refuse collection today and warned that this is only the start of a series of public disturbances over itinerants who are parked near St. Brigid's School, Dublin Road . . . gardaí were called in over the weekend to defuse the situation.</P>
    <P>Up to 100 men living in the vicinity of Childer's Road marched on the itinerants on Friday night, that was Friday 11 October and told them to move.</P>
    <P>The travellers themselves assert that the men were armed with pickaxes, shovels and things like that.  A member of the local action committee who organised this march is quoted as saying: &ldquo;We phoned the gardaí on both occasions to tell them what we were doing.&rdquo;  Nobody from that 100 people has been charged with any offence notwithstanding the intimidating nature of the protect march, and all this in the constituency of the Minister for Justice.</P>
    <P>Just to continue on this most recent form of anti-traveller prejudice &mdash; at 9.20 a.m. on 14 October about 15 residents marched into the corporation office at Sarsfield House demanding action to move on the travellers.  The next paragraph of the report says, and I quote:</P>
    <P>They were led by Canon James Sadlier, P.P., Mrs. Anne McCaffrey, treasurer of the parents council, and other committee members.</P>
    <P>It appears to me that the Bishop of Limerick would be better off controlling some of his own parish priests than giving lectures to the Minister for Agriculture about the nature of the responsibility of Catholic politicians.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickJReynolds" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>The Senator has two minutes left.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BrendanRyan" hpid="Mr. B. Ryan Mr. B. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. B. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>The Senator will be finished in two minutes.  What appals me <Col N="1256" /> is that we can have that sort of naked, brutal intimidation and use of force against travellers in the constituency of the Minister for Justice and we are still apparently going to have to wait for the Minister for Justice to bring in the necessary legislation to eliminate discrimination and incitement to hatred.  We have had it twice: we have had it in Tallaght and in Limerick.  When local residents choose to take the law into their own hands the travellers' have no rights.  When local residents choose to intimidate the travellers have no rights.  When local residents choose to be offensive and threatening and incite to hatred, travellers apparently have no rights.  It is because we have had a succession of these manifestations of the fact that travellers have no rights that they are effectively a voiceless, voteless and powerless minority.  No solution, no provision of services, no amount of articulation of goodwill, will substitute for what travellers need and demand, which is a charter of rights which enables them to say: &ldquo;We do not have to do this thing, because we are entitled to be here. We have rights just as you have and we are going to have those rights vindicated, not just through the courts but by those who are obliged to defend the law, that is the Garda Síochána.&rdquo;  This did not happen in Tallaght last year nor in Limerick in October.  Hence the need for a charter of rights; hence the need for moving the motion.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickJReynolds" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>When is it proposed to sit again?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDooge" hpid="Professor Dooge Professor Dooge">
      <NameTxt>Professor Dooge</NameTxt>
      <P>It is proposed to sit again at 10.30 a.m. tomorrow, and for the benefit of Senators I might indicate that, as is customary on Thursday, we will be discussing reports of joint committees. Tomorrow we will take up the Report of the Joint Committee on EC affairs dealing with forestry and forest-based products and if that is concluded before 4 p.m. we will then take up the report of the same committee on the Multi-Fibre Arrangement.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Adjournment Matter. - Prescribed" RHead="Relative Allowance Scheme">
    <Title>Adjournment Matter. - Prescribed Relative Allowance Scheme.</Title>
    <Col N="1257" />
    <Speaker pid="JimHiggins" hpid="Mr. J. Higgins Mr. J. Higgins">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J. Higgins</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator Ryan began his concluding statement by pointing out that the numerical insignificance of travellers meant that they had very little political clout and consequently that very few people thought it worth their while to come into the House tonight to defend travellers' rights.  In other words, the time allocated to this debate and this motion, three hours, was not fully utilised.  The group of people I represent in my contribution tonight is numerically far less significant than the travellers referred to by Senator Ryan.  The reason I have sought permission to raise this issue in the house has been the operation and administration of the prescribed relative allowance scheme which, in my opinion, particularly in view of recent developments, is a real cause for anxiety.</P>
      <P>If one looks at the figures one sees that in March 1983, 2,640 people were in receipt of the prescribed relative allowance; in March 1984, 2,500 people were in receipt of the benefit and presently 2,300 qualify.  Therefore, it can be concluded that in a two-year period over 340 people have been cut off from benefit. This is only the tip of the iceberg.  This number I believe should be far greater judging by the number of cases currently under appeal and the people who come to public representatives on an almost daily basis to make legitimate representations on their behalf.  I have sought permission to raise the issue because of the high incidence of people who are first-time applicants for the benefit and who are having their applications turned down.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Equally disturbing, as I have stated, is the fact that people who have been deemed eligible in the past for the allowance are being disallowed on an ever-increasing basis.  Form S.W. 41 is the form which one avails of in order to apply for the allowance.  It sets out clearly the particular conditions which pertain to the allowance.  The difficulties arise particularly in relation to condition no.2 which <Col N="1258" /> states that the incapacitated person must be so incapacitated as to need full time care and attention and be receiving this care and attention from a prescribed relative. This sounds a very reasonable clause and condition, but what happens when you have an incapacitated person whose son or daughter has land?  From the way the scheme is being operated in County Mayo, it would seem that any small farmer who is working on his land to even a limited degree is deemed as being outside the scope of the scheme.  Even carrying on a limited operation is taken as evidence that the prescribed relative is not devoting full time care and attention to looking after the pensioner in question.</P>
    <P>It is ridiculous to expect that a small farmer whose father or mother becomes incapacitated should dispose of his land, either by selling, letting or leasing it, in order to qualify for the allowance.  It is not reasonable to expect that somebody who has a small farm is quite capable of carrying on the two operations in tandem or indeed carrying on a limited farm function while at the same time devoting the most of his time to looking after his aged or incapacitated parent or parents as the case may be?  Surely it is nonsensical to suggest that on small farms &mdash; and people know from the structure of farms in rural areas that the house is within walking distance, and in some cases within shouting distance &mdash; it is not possible for a son or a daughter or a prescribed relative to carry on having a few dry stock grazing the land and at the same time adequately to cater for the needs of the parent in question?</P>
    <P>I am not aware of the reason for this clamp-down at this time.  It is a scheme that was operated with a fair degree of basic &ldquo;cop-on&rdquo; until now.  There was a fair element of commonsense used by the Department of Social Welfare officers in determining eligibility.  People have a grasp of the type of operation which exists on most small farms in the west.  There has been a clamp-down that seems not coincidental in that it comes hard on the heels of the campaign in relation to small farmers' dole.  I get the impression, in <Col N="1259" /> relation to the operation of some schemes in rural areas, that there is a hell-bent determination within the Department to bring small farmers in general in the west to their knees.  It happened in relation to the small farmers' dole in the early days; it is happening in relation to this scheme and again in relation to farmers who are cut off from disability benefit and while their cases are under appeal, apply for supplementary welfare benefit to health boards.  Technically, the implications of the term &ldquo;full-time care and attention&rdquo; is that the prescribed relative could not even go to Mass on Sunday, could not leave the home to go shopping, could not take time off from their duties in order to draw the pension on behalf of the applicant.  Thankfully, there has been enough &ldquo;cop-on&rdquo; there not to insist on such rigid interpretation and adherence. Why therefore is the small farmer who spends the bulk of the day looking after an incapacitated parent expected to forfeit the princely sum of £25?  This is wrong and I should like to get answers from the Minister of State in relation to this.</P>
    <P>In the majority of cases the farmers who stay at home to look after aged parents on farms do so at considerable personal sacrifice to themselves; there may be other members of the family away in secure employment elsewhere.  I have evidence of cases where farmers have had to pay people to do the chores for them in order that they themselves could look after parents and then they find that they have been turned down for the allowance. I have come across cases where farmers have ceased to sign the live register because they are no longer available for work outside the farm due to the increased pressure of the domestic requirements of looking after a parent or parents and they have been turned down. I ask the Minister of State to use whatever influence he has in his Department to go back to the previous understanding &mdash; a flexible and compassionate application of the guidelines.</P>
    <P>In view of the fact that my time has not been fully utilised, I request that Senator <Col N="1260" /> John Connor be granted the balance of it.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JohnConnor" hpid="Mr. Connor Mr. Connor">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Connor</NameTxt>
      <P>I thank Senator Higgins for granting me some of his time.  Much of what I would like to say on this subject has already been covered.  The Senator and I have discussed this problem together and it arises because of a number of incidents we have come across in our constituency work when people are suddenly, for some strange reason, deprived of their prescribed relative's allowance. Senator Higgins has outlined how it operates and the general guidelines which were adopted by the Department and its officials in administering the scheme. There are many people who for ten years and longer were in receipt of a prescribed relative allowance and suddenly this year, because of new guidelines emanating from the Department of Social Welfare, it was decided to re-examine their circumstances &mdash; for instance, the length of time that is spent in full time care and attention.  I cannot understand why a new interpretation is put on the circumstances of somebody who for ten years looked after an aged parent or parents, and was deemed to be within the regulations so that he or she is now suddenly found not to be devoting the prescribed amount of time to the parent and this even in view of the fact that in the last 12 years there has been major machanisation, even of small farms, which would have released many people from actual work on the smallholding itself.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Also there is the aspect that the payment of the prescribed relative allowance gave some form of recompense to a son, daughter or other prescribed relative who would look after elderly parents in their homes rather than have them looked after in institutions.  The amount of money offered to these people is £25 maximum &mdash; a pittance nowadays.  There are many hundreds of people looked after in their homes because this allowance was payable.  It was always very restricted in the range of people it was paid to, and the amount of money paid.  I would like the Minister to tell us what the new guidelines are and how they are arrived at. <Col N="1261" /> Would he set down for us the length of time the Department demands a prescribed relative must be in attendance in the home with the aged relative to quality for the scheme?  If the amount of time hitherto given was acceptable for ten years, or whatever length of time the scheme has been in operation, why the change now?  We did not hear of new guidelines being laid down in this House during the Social Welfare Bill or any other related legislation.  I believe that this is something else which may be wrong about the administration of social welfare; it may be somebody down the line who has decided, probably without proper ministerial permission, that the amount of time formerly given to the aged parent no longer is sufficient to qualify, according to the interpretation of a particular officer.  We have had this sort of thing also in the way certain officers interpretated regulations under the small farmers' assistance, as referred to by my colleague, Senator Higgins.  A major injustice has been done to hundreds and possibly more people throughout the country through the interpretation of those rules.  Many of those officers have no idea about assessing a small farmer's income.  In their interviews with people they do not allow them all their allowable expenses; they do not advice them etc.  It is from that school of thought I fear that this new campaign against this prescribed relative allowance has emerged.</P>
    <P>I want to thank Senator Higgins for allowing me some of his time and I would hope that the Minister, in his reply, have something of a positive and satisfactory answer for us.</P>
    <Speaker pid="SeamusPattison" hpid="Minister of State at the Department of Social Welfare (Mr. Pattison) Séamus Pattison">
      <NameTxt>Minister of State at the Department of Social Welfare (Mr. Pattison)</NameTxt>
      <P>The prescribed relative allowance is an increase in pension payable to incapacitated old age and invalidity pensioners in respect of a prescribed relative who is living with them and is providing full time care and attention to them.  Payment of the allowance depends on certain specific conditions being met.  These conditions are set out in regulations made under the Social Welfare Acts and deciding officers <Col N="1262" /> must satisfy themselves that these conditions are fulfilled before an allowance is awarded in any case.  As with social welfare payments generally, every person who is dissatisfied with the decision of a deciding officer has the right of appeal to an Appeals Officer.</P>
      <P>It would be helpful to give some history of the scheme at this stage.  The prescribed relative allowance was introduced in January 1969.  At that stage it was confined to cases where a qualified pensioner was being cared for on a full-time basis by a daughter or step-daughter who actually gave up long-standing insurable employment in order to provide that care.  The test applied for this purpose required the daughter or step-daughter to have at least 156 employment contributions in the five years preceding the claim.  This particular condition was however subsequently abolished and the scheme has been otherwise expanded by widening the categories of pensioners covered and by extending the definition of prescribed relative.  Nevertheless the conditions are still quite specific and I think it as well to set out briefly what these conditions are.</P>
      <P>There are, in effect, two sets of conditions to be fulfilled, one set applying to the pensioner and another set to the prescribed relative.</P>
      <P>In the case of the pensioner, he or she must be receiving an old age pension, a blind person's pension, an invalidity pension or be over 66 years and receiving a widow's pension, retirement pension, deserted wife's benefit, deserted wife's allowance or prisoner's wife's allowance from the Department of Social Welfare. He or she must be so incapacitated as to require full-time care and attention; and he or she must be receiving full-time care and attention from a prescribed relative who is residing with him or her for that purpose.  Apart from the prescribed relative, he or she must be living alone or only with children under 18 or persons aged 18 or over who are mentally or physically incapacitated.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>In the case of the prescribed relative, he or she must not be engaged in employment outside the home; he or she must <Col N="1263" /> not be entitled to any other benefit, pension or allowance from the Department of Social Welfare; and he or she must not be a married person who is maintained by his or her spouse.</P>
    <P>These conditions are, as I have said already, very specific.  Effectively, they restrict payment of the allowance to pensioners who require and are receiving full-time care and attention from a prescribed relative who, in turn and to all intents and purpose, has no other means of support.</P>
    <P>It is important to be clear about the actual conditions which apply in this scheme and to avoid any misapprehension on this score.</P>
    <P>The allowance does not apply, for example, where an incapacitated pensioner is being cared for by a relative who is maintained by his or her spouse; neither is it payable where the relative is employed outside the home or is unable for any reason, to provide the full-time care and attention required.  The important thing to note is that the allowance serves a very specific purpose, namely, to provide a measure of income maintenance to households where there is need to provide a pensioner with full-time care and attention and a relative is devoting his or her energies to that end to the exclusion of gainful activity.</P>
    <P>There are approximately 2,300 prescribed relative allowances currently in payment.  The majority of these are in payment to recipients of non-contributory pensions, a large proportion of whom would be self-employed persons, including farmers.  The proportion of non-contributory pensioners who qualify for this allowance is much greater than for contributory pensioners with non-contributory pensioners accounting for some 75 per cent of the total.</P>
    <P>Non-contributory pensioners are composed to a large extent, as I have said, of the self-employed, including farmers, and a large proportion of farmers will have relatives living with them.  In many cases these relatives will be engaged in running the farm, particularly where the farmer himself is an old person and not <Col N="1264" /> in a position to do so.  When an application for a prescribed relative allowance is made the deciding officer must establish whether the relative is in actual fact providing full-time care and attention to an incapacitated pensioner or whether he or she is not.  I know from my own experience and fully appreciate that any family who has a pensioner residing with them will feel that they should be entitled to an allowance for doing so, but as matters stand the scheme is a limited one which applies only in the circumstances which I have outlined.</P>
    <P>The relative of a non-contributory pensioner may be gainfully occupied in or around the home without necessarily being disqualified for payment of the prescribed relative allowance.  The allowance is being, and will continue to be, paid in cases where the prescribed relative is running a smallholding provided this does not conflict with the objective of providing full-time care and attention for the pensioner.  Where the level of activity is such, however, that the relative could not reasonably be in a position to provide the required care and attention on a full-time basis, a prescribed relative allowance cannot be paid.  The fact that, in real terms, four times as many non-contributory pensioners qualify for the allowance than contributory pensioners is a measure of the extent to which the allowance is paid to pensioners whose prescribed relatives are living with them on small farms.</P>
    <P>Routine reviews of continuing entitlement to the allowance is an ongoing feature of the administration of the scheme. These are conducted by social welfare officers who report on all the relevant circumstances of the case.  Where the relative is gainfully occupied around the house, information on the extent of this activity is furnished in order that the deciding officer will be in a position to decide whether the relative is providing full-time care and attention.  These reviews are not confined to any category of recipient.  They include all pensioners who are in receipt of the allowance.  The same criteria apply in all cases and each <Col N="1265" /> case is decided on its merits having regard to all relevant circumstances.</P>
    <P>It is clear, therefore, that smallholders are not ruled out for the purposes of the scheme.  The prescribed relative allowance is in payment in many instances where a pensioner is being cared for by a relative who is a smallholder.  The crucial factor is whether the farming commitments are consistent with the ability of the relative to provide full-time care and attention.</P>
    <P>The prescribed relative allowance scheme is a limited one.  We could have <Col N="1266" /> a long debate on whether the scheme could be expanded and so on, but this question is dealing with the scheme as it stands.  It is a limited one.  The role of the allowance is being reviewed as part of the general review of services which is being conducted by the Commission on Social Welfare.  Any proposals which the commission puts forward in this area will be fully and carefully examined.</P>
    <P>The Seanad adjourned at 8.05 p.m. until 10.30 a.m. on Thursday, 14 November 1985.</P>
  </MainHeading>
</Debate>