<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE Debate SYSTEM "../Debate.dtd"[]>
<Debate DocTitle="Seanad Debate" Day="Wed" Date="15" Month="Nov" Year="1972" Vol="73" No="10" DateIrish="Dé Céadaoin, 15 Samhain 1972" DateEnglish="Wednesday, 15 November 1972" House="S" CommitteeEng="" CommitteeIr="" SubNameEng="" cnum="815">
  <MainHeading Type="Prelude" LHead="" RHead="">
    <Title>
    </Title>
    <P>
      <Col N="815" /> Chuaigh an Cathaoirleach i gceannas ar 3 p.m.</P>
    <P Just="Center">
      <i>Paidir.</i>
    </P>
    <P Just="Center">
      <i>Prayer.</i>
    </P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Private Business. - Institute of Chartered Accountants in Ireland (Charter" RHead="Second Amendment) Bill, 1972: Appointment of Chairman of Joint Committee">
    <Title>Private Business. - Institute of Chartered Accountants in Ireland (Charter Second Amendment) Bill, 1972: Appointment of Chairman of Joint Committee.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelYeats" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>De bhun BhuanOrdú 71 de Bhuan-Orduithe na Dála agus an tSeanaid i dtaobh Gnó Phríobháidigh, déanaimidne, Ceann Comhairle na Dála agus Cathaoirleach an tSeanaid, i gcomhar</P>
      <P Just="Center">An Teachta Vivion de Valéra</P>
      <P>a ceapadh chun bheith ina Chathaoirleach ar an gComhchoiste ar an mBille um Institiúid na gCuntasóirí Cairte in Éirinn (an Dara Leasú Cairte), 1972.</P>
      <P>Pursuant to Standing Order 71 of the Standing Orders of the Dáil and the Seanad relative to Private Business, we, the Ceann Comhairle of the Dáil and the Cathaoirleach of the Seanad, jointly appoint</P>
      <P Just="Center">Deputy Vivion de Valera</P>
      <P>to be Chairman of the Joint Committee on the Institute of Chartered Accountants in Ireland (Charter Second Amendment) Bill, 1972.</P>
      <P Just="Right">(Sgd.) Cormac Ua Breisleáin,</P>
      <P Just="Right">Ceann Comhairle.</P>
      <P Just="Right">(Sgd.) Mícheál Yeats,</P>
      <P Just="Right">Cathaoirleach an tSeanaid.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Private Business. -" RHead="Order of Business">
    <Title>Private Business. - Order of Business.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>It is proposed to take No. 1 only.  As Senators are aware, we had hoped to take No. 14 on the agenda also but owing to unexpected circumstances the Minister is not available.  The proposer of the motion was not free at this time either.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="816" />
    <Speaker pid="PatrickQuinlan" hpid="Professor Quinlan Professor Quinlan">
      <NameTxt>Professor Quinlan</NameTxt>
      <P>I want to inquire what has happened to the motion concerning the Devlin Report which has been on the Order Paper for at least two years.  This is most important now when we are preparing for entry to the EEC.  Poor Buchanan having got a bad rattling around the country seems to have departed.  He has been paid his fees but we have taken no notice of the recommendations and we have profited nothing from the work done. I suggest that we should discuss those two items first.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TimothyWest" hpid="Dr. West Dr. West">
      <NameTxt>Dr. West</NameTxt>
      <P>I understand the difficulties of the Leader of the House in arranging the Order of Business for today and I hope he will be able to take No. 14 next week.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>I hope to do so.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Private Business. - Electricity (Supply)" RHead="(Amendment) Bill, 1972: Second Stage">
    <Title>Private Business. - Electricity (Supply) (Amendment) Bill, 1972: Second Stage.</Title>
    <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That the Bill be now read a Second Time.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelOKennedy" hpid="Parliamentary Secretary to the Minister for Education (Mr. O'Kennedy) Michael O'Kennedy">
      <NameTxt>Parliamentary Secretary to the Minister for Education (Mr. O'Kennedy)</NameTxt>
      <P>The purposes of this Bill are:</P>
      <P>(i)  to extend to the ESB general staff an improvement in superannuation benefits already enjoyed by the board's manual staff.</P>
      <P>(ii)  to eliminate any doubt which might arise as to the powers of the ESB to accord equal rank to all their borrowings.</P>
      <P>Before proceeding to the individual sections of the Bill I should like to mention that the proposed amendments in sections 2 and 3 of the Bill are identical to those contained in sections 3 and 4 of the Electricity (Supply) (Amendment) Act, 1970, except that the two sections in the 1970 Act are in respect of manual employees while the two sections in the present Bill concern the general employees.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Section 2 of the Bill provides for the addition of a further subsection&mdash;subsection 9&mdash;to section 7 of the 1942 Act.  The General Employees' Superannuation Scheme came into operation on 1st April, 1943.  Where a general employee entered the board's service <Col N="817" /> after 1st April, 1943, his service up to the date he was admitted to the scheme was not reckonable for superannuation purposes.  Section 2 of the Bill defines this service as &ldquo;previous service&rdquo; and enables the board to reckon half of it for superannuation purposes.</P>
    <P>Section 3 of the Bill enables the board to pay a supplementary allowance equal to the full pension value of the other half of a general employees previous service provided that the employees involved make a nominal contribution towards the cost of such an allowance.</P>
    <P>Section 4 of the Bill refers to the borrowing powers of the ESB.  Up to the time of the passing of the Electricity (Supply) (Amendment) Act, 1954, the board's capital requirements were borrowed from the Central Fund. All such borrowings under the Electricity (Supply) Act, 1927, and subsequent Acts carried with them either specific or floating charges on ESB property.  Under section 4 of the Electricity (Supply) (Amendment) Act, 1954, the board were empowered to make their own arrangements for getting, direct from the public or otherwise, the capital required to finance their development and since then no money has been borrowed by the board from the Central Fund.</P>
    <P>Section 4 (3) of the 1954 Act provided that the terms upon which capital is borrowed by the ESB may include provisions charging the moneys borrowed on the property of the board and also permitted the inclusion of provisions under which any charge in respect of money borrowed under the 1954 Act may rank before or equal with charges on the board's assets in respect of borrowings from the Central Fund.  In fact, however, the ESB did not give any charges on their property in respect of borrowings under the 1954 Act and they do not envisage the giving of such charges in respect of future borrowings.  As a consequence, the board are now advised that technically these borrowings under the 1954 Act cannot be ranked equally with the loans from the Central Fund in respect of which, as I have stated, a specific or floating charge on the board's assets <Col N="818" /> was created under the Electricity Supply Acts.  It was, however, the intention of the board that moneys borrowed under the 1954 Act would rank equally with loans from the Central Fund and the purpose of section 4 is to establish this position in law.</P>
    <Speaker pid="CharlesBMcDonald" hpid="Mr. McDonald Mr. McDonald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McDonald</NameTxt>
      <P>The amendments incorporated in this Bill cannot in any way be regarded as contentious.  We should like to compliment the Minister and the ESB for coming back so quickly to remedy the difficulty that arose subsequent to the passing of the legislation in 1970.  This speaks well for the Minister and the ESB.  The board must be complimented on the excellent service they are continuing to provide.  I hope that, with this additional piece of legislation, their service will improve and that it will lead to more harmonious relations between the board and their employees. It is most important that we should never again have to face the undesirable thought of having a strike in this very&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelYeats" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>The Senator appreciates, I am sure, that matters of administration do not arise under this Bill.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="CharlesBMcDonald" hpid="Mr. McDonald Mr. McDonald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McDonald</NameTxt>
      <P>I quite agree and bow to the Chair's ruling, but it is an opportunity of stating that we appreciate the difficulties that can arise in semi-State organisations.  I just wished to compliment the board and their employees on their progress to date.  I do not know if I am permitted to comment on the way the board expend some of the loan capital&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelYeats" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>This is purely a narrow technical Bill relating to superannuation and borrowing matters. Questions of administration do not arise under it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="CharlesBMcDonald" hpid="Mr. McDonald Mr. McDonald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McDonald</NameTxt>
      <P>We cannot comment on where the borrowings go to or on the annual report?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelYeats" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I am afraid not.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="CharlesBMcDonald" hpid="Mr. McDonald Mr. McDonald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McDonald</NameTxt>
      <P>Seeing that we have ordered so little business today, that is a pity.  It would have been an opportunity <Col N="819" /> to have a closer look at the workings of the board.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelYeats" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>The difficulty is that the opportunities must be orderly ones.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="CharlesBMcDonald" hpid="Mr. McDonald Mr. McDonald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McDonald</NameTxt>
      <P>I bow to your ruling.  We are particularly glad that this amendment has been introduced in section 2.  It will help to remove a bone of contention in the industry. Finally, again may I compliment the Minister for his very quick action in bringing in these amendments which we fully support?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FintanKennedy" hpid="Mr. Kennedy Mr. Kennedy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Kennedy</NameTxt>
      <P>The only criticism I have of the Bill is that it does not go far enough.  The principal cause of discontent among manual and other workers in the ESB and other public service is that the superannuation schemes do not provide for increases in pensions in accordance with increases in the cost of living.  Bearing in mind that the average rate of increase in the cost of living is about 12½ per cent, it will be seen that this complaint is justified.  Perhaps it is not in order to speak on matters which are not covered by the Bill but I should like an assurance from the Parliamentary Secretary, if he is in a position to give one, that the Government have under consideration other improvements in the ESB superannuation scheme and those of other semi-State bodies.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelJosephOHiggin" hpid="Mr. O'Higgins Mr. O'Higgins">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Higgins</NameTxt>
      <P>There is just one small point I wish to put to the Parliamentary Secretary.  I fully share Senator McDonald's satisfaction in relation to the Bill.  Section 3 of the Bill, to which the Parliamentary Secretary referred, is the section which provides for admission to the benefit under the Bill on payment of a contribution by the employee.  The Parliamentary Secretary referred to that as making a nominal contribution.  Section 3 of the Bill refers to:</P>
      <P>... a contribution equal to 1 per cent of the remuneration paid to him by the board during the three years immediately before his retirement.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I should like clarification as to what <Col N="820" /> that means.  Does it mean 1 per cent of the gross total over three years or 1 per cent of the remuneration paid in a single year?  I hope the Parliamentary Secretary gets the point I am making.  Do you gross the three years together and take 1 per cent of that figure or is it 1 per cent of an annual sum?</P>
    <Speaker pid="NevilleKeery" hpid="Mr. Keery Mr. Keery">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Keery</NameTxt>
      <P>I wish simply to welcome the extension of the superannuation benefits in the Bill and also the technicality that the board's view of their borrowings should be recognised in law.  Having said that, and appreciating that this is a technical Bill and that the debate must be brief, I should like to say that I think the whole financial structure and base of the ESB is a matter well worth deep discussion and serious consideration.  I hope that this House will have the opportunity of considering these aspects more thoroughly in the near future.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelOKennedy" hpid="Parliamentary Secretary to the Minister for Education (Mr. O'Kennedy) Michael O'Kennedy">
      <NameTxt>Parliamentary Secretary to the Minister for Education (Mr. O'Kennedy)</NameTxt>
      <P>I wish to thank Senators for the welcome they have given to this Bill.  In reply to Senator O'Higgins, may I say that the provisions of the Bill in respect of the 1 per cent apply to the salary over the three years.  I should like to draw his attention to the fact that it repeats the provisions of the Act of 1970 which introduced similar enabling powers in respect of manual employees.  The Senator will be aware that the board's scheme is a contributory one.  This particular provision preserves the principle of mutual financing of the superannuation scheme, requiring only the minimum contribution from the worker.  In view of the benefits it confers, which I understand have been welcomed by the staff concerned, the amount payable is very modest; to that extent it is nominal.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>It must be acknowledged that any scheme of this kind suffers from the disability mentioned by Senator Kennedy. It is a matter which the board must take into account when drawing up and implementing their schemes.  It is also a matter to which the Minister for Finance must have regard, not alone in relation to the ESB but in any semilar scheme.  The point is a relevant one <Col N="821" /> and I will convey it to the Minister and to the Minister for Finance.</P>
    <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
    <P>Agreed to take the remaining Stages today.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Private Business. - Electricity (Supply)" RHead="(Amendment) Bill, 1972: Committee and Final Stages">
    <Title>Private Business. - Electricity (Supply) (Amendment) Bill, 1972: Committee and Final Stages.</Title>
    <P>Sections 1 and 2 agreed to.</P>
    <P Just="Center">SECTION 3.</P>
    <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That section 3 stand part of the Bill.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelJosephOHiggin" hpid="Mr. O'Higgins Mr. O'Higgins">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Higgins</NameTxt>
      <P>Has the Parliamentary Secretary any figures as to how much, in terms of pounds and pence, the contribution will be on average?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelOKennedy" hpid="Mr. O'Kennedy Mr. O'Kennedy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Kennedy</NameTxt>
      <P>I have not, frankly, because it would relate over a wide range of employment.  I cannot give the Senator that information but on a rough calculation on the basis of a salary of £20 it would be about £30 for the three years.  Something in excess of that figure would be a reasonable average in the circumstances.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P Just="Center">SECTION 4.</P>
      <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That section 4 stand part of the Bill.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="CharlesBMcDonald" hpid="Mr. McDonald Mr. McDonald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McDonald</NameTxt>
      <P>Could the Parliamentary Secretary say what security the board have offered to foreign investors, for example, the 1975-84 and later loans from the German banks.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelOKennedy" hpid="Mr. O'Kennedy Mr. O'Kennedy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Kennedy</NameTxt>
      <P>Under previous legislation they are guaranteed by the Minister for Finance.  That is regarded as being fairly acceptable security.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="CharlesBMcDonald" hpid="Mr. McDonald Mr. McDonald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McDonald</NameTxt>
      <P>What is the reason for the amendment?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelOKennedy" hpid="Mr. O'Kennedy Mr. O'Kennedy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Kennedy</NameTxt>
      <P>As I indicated in my opening remarks it is to place these borrowings on an equal footing with the borrowings from the Central Fund. In the event of any further security being required, it seemed only reasonable that the same charge would apply to these borrowings as would apply to borrowings from the Central Fund.  It <Col N="822" /> is to amend a legal technicality when this legislation was introduced that that particular provision was added.  It is not expected to have any effective significance.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="CharlesBMcDonald" hpid="Mr. McDonald Mr. McDonald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McDonald</NameTxt>
      <P>At the present stage of the rural electrification post development scheme there seems to be a 100 per cent acceptance of the scheme. Those people who refused to have electricity in the past are now most anxious to get it.  For this reason, I should like to know if there are sufficient funds in the board's resources to meet the increased demand.  Would it be possible for the board to lay underground cables&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelYeats" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Under section 4?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="CharlesBMcDonald" hpid="Mr. McDonald Mr. McDonald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McDonald</NameTxt>
      <P>I am speaking about loans.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelOKennedy" hpid="Mr. O'Kennedy Mr. O'Kennedy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Kennedy</NameTxt>
      <P>I understand that the board are quite satisfied they have sufficient funds at their disposal under these borrowing powers to finance the continued programme for rural electrification.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="CharlesBMcDonald" hpid="Mr. McDonald Mr. McDonald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McDonald</NameTxt>
      <P>This is the final programme?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelOKennedy" hpid="Mr. O'Kennedy Mr. O'Kennedy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Kennedy</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes, the present programme is the final one.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelJosephOHiggin" hpid="Mr. O'Higgins Mr. O'Higgins">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Higgins</NameTxt>
      <P>I am sure it is quite simple if one knows enough about the ESB and the borrowings raised under the various Acts.  What we are doing in section 4 is cancelling or removing any charges which have been made by the board on their property under any of the Acts from 1927 to 1954.  We are going further than that by not giving to the Electricity Supply Board in future the authority to create or authorise the creation of charges on the property of the board.  Any power they have in that connection will be repealed when this Act is passed.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The Parliamentary Secretary, in the course of his introductory statement, pointed out that, in so far as the 1954 Act was concerned, the board had not created any charges on its property for moneys borrowed but that under the 1927 Act, where the borrowing was from the Central Fund, there was a general floating charge on all the property <Col N="823" /> and assets of the board.  Is it envisaged that the floating charge, or charges which arose as a result of borrowings under the 1927 Act, will be cancelled out by section 4?  If this is the case, is it because they have been repaid and therefore there is nothing outstanding on foot of them?  If that is the position then it is perfectly understandable; but if there is a residue of loan interest still due under 1927 Act borrowings from the Central Fund, there should be an explanation as to why it is being cancelled.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelOKennedy" hpid="Mr. O'Kennedy Mr. O'Kennedy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Kennedy</NameTxt>
      <P>The Senator put his finger on it when he said the effect of section 4 would be to cancel out these charges and to give them the benefit of the guarantee from the Minister.  There is a very practical reason for this, in so far as the charges would have related to assets then in existence which, in the course of time would not be as effective security now as they were previously.  For example, the old generating station.  Effectively, it ensures that charges raised prior to that would also have the guarantee from the Minister.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="CharlesBMcDonald" hpid="Mr. McDonald Mr. McDonald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McDonald</NameTxt>
      <P>I should like to inquire about the sources of some of the loans on the list&mdash;for example, the International Bank for Reconstruction and Development.  In what particular country is that organisation based?  Is it one of the European banking institutions which have provided the £6,200,000 loan?  I am referring to Table 8 in the latest annual report of the ESB, which covers the period up to 31st March last.  It would make things easier for people like myself if they gave a little more information in their annual report such as the exact countries from which those moneys were made available.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="824" />
    <Speaker pid="MichaelOKennedy" hpid="Mr. O'Kennedy Mr. O'Kennedy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Kennedy</NameTxt>
      <P>I presume Senators will have received a copy of the annual report of the board although I can understand that they, like myself, may not have had an opportunity of looking into it in detail.  The funds to which the Senator has referred are referred to on page 3.  I quote from page 3:</P>
      <P>The board had two very successful stock issues during the year. These were a £15 million European unity of account issue in May, 1971, and a £12 million issue on the home market in March, 1972.  The unit of account issue was the first public offering on the board's behalf on the international market and was very well received.</P>
      <P>It was, in fact, a public offering on the international market and it was very well received.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BernardMcGlinchey" hpid="Mr. McGlinchey Mr. McGlinchey">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGlinchey</NameTxt>
      <P>I wonder if I would be in order, under this section, in asking the Parliamentary Secretary to use his influence with the Minister to allow the ESB to borrow a little more in order to eliminate the special charge?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelYeats" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>That would not arise under this section nor, indeed, under this Bill.  Methods of borrowing do arise but the matters on which the money needs to be spent do not arise.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BernardMcGlinchey" hpid="Mr. McGlinchey Mr. McGlinchey">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGlinchey</NameTxt>
      <P>I have made my point.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>Section 5 agreed to.</P>
      <P>Title agreed to.</P>
      <P>Bill reported without amendment, received for final consideration and passed.</P>
      <P>The Seanad adjourned at 3.35 p.m. until 3 p.m. on Wednesday, 22nd November, 1972.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
</Debate>